<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298960-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298960</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10144087</doc-number>
<date>20020510</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>1140</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>76</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386 46</main-classification>
<further-classification>386 83</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Playback diagnostics</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6311011</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kuroda</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>386 46</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6650824</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Horlander et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>386 46</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6738559</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Yoo et al.</name>
<date>20040500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>386 46</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6925567</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hirata</name>
<date>20050800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>713189</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>58</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386  1</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386 46</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386 83</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386 94</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386125</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386126</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 58</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Taylor</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas H.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Redmond</city>
<state>WA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Potrebic</last-name>
<first-name>Peter J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Calistoga</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Horowitz</last-name>
<first-name>Steven</first-name>
<address>
<city>Los Altos</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Microsoft Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Redmond</city>
<state>WA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Tran</last-name>
<first-name>Thai Q.</first-name>
<department>2621</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Chowdhury</last-name>
<first-name>Nigar</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A request is received to create a program event to record a program from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel. The program event is created to record the program in a recording for a playback of the program from the recording. Upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the play back, a diagnostic descriptive of the incident is output.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="270.68mm" wi="219.71mm" file="US07298960-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="271.27mm" wi="219.96mm" file="US07298960-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="277.88mm" wi="216.49mm" file="US07298960-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="267.63mm" wi="202.52mm" file="US07298960-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="265.35mm" wi="215.14mm" file="US07298960-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="256.29mm" wi="202.86mm" file="US07298960-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="262.21mm" wi="201.76mm" file="US07298960-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to playing back a recording of a television program broadcast on a channel. More particularly, the present invention relates to providing diagnostics as to incidents likely to prevent a play back of the television program.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Client devices in a television-based entertainment system include set top boxes such as cable boxes, satellite receivers, video cassette recorders (VCRs), and digital video recorders (DVRs). Some client devices have recording capabilities and can be set-up to record a television (TV) program currently being broadcast. Typically, a client device is set-up to record a TV program ahead of time on a particular date at a certain starting time, on a particular broadcast channel, and for a particular duration. On the particular date, the client device tunes a tuner to the particular channel at the particular starting time and records the TV program being broadcast on the particular channel for the particular duration. After the recording of the TV program has been made, the recording can be played back for the enjoyment of a viewer. In the case of DVRs, the TV program doesn't have to finish recording before a viewer can start playing it back to watch it.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The general object of making a recording of a TV program is to be able to play back and thus enjoy the TV program at other than the broadcast time thereof. Various incidents can occur any one of which are likely to prevent such a play back, such as an incident that prevents the client device from recording the TV program. A viewer has an unpleasant experience with the client device when the desired recording is not made or when a recording that was made can not be played back. Moreover, the unpleasant nature of the experience is exacerbated for a viewer when the client device fails to provide an adequate explanation as to why the TV program could be neither recorded nor played back. It would be desirable to enhance viewer experience with a client device by informing the viewer of incidents likely to prevent the desired play back of the TV program. Consequently, there is a need for improved methods, client devices, digital video recorders, computer programs, and systems that can provide such a capability.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Methods, client devices, digital video recorders, computer programs, and systems receive a request to create a program event to record a program from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel. The program event is created to record the program in a recording for a playback of the program from the recording. Upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the play back, a diagnostic descriptive of the incident is output.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In an implementation, a client device has a processor in communication with a video recorder and a receiver. The processor executes an application to receive a request to create a program event to record a program with the video recorder from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel carrying a video signal. Execution of the application creates the program event. The program event coordinates the recording of the program in a recording. The video recorder, which has a component that is a video playback device, plays back the recorded broadcast of the program. When an incident occurs that is likely to prevent the program from being recorded or from playing back from a recording of the program, a diagnostic is output that describes the incident.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an exemplary environment in which the methods, client devices, digital video recorders, computer programs, and systems described herein may be implemented.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates of an example client device, a television, and various input devices that interact with the client device.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram that illustrates components of the example client device(s) shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow diagram that illustrates a procedure for outputting a diagnostic descriptive of an incident that is likely to prevent a recording of a TV program or a play back of the recording.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates, in a front elevation view, an exemplary environment in which a client device outputs a section of an electronic program guide (EPG) resulting in a display of same upon a television.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows the client device outputting diagnostics resulting in a display of same upon the television of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An entertainment architecture has a television broadcasting system that includes a television broadcast network, a network resource, and a client device. In addition to the television broadcast network, the entertainment architecture can have a two-way interconnected network placing the network resource in communication with the client device. The television broadcast network broadcasts video signals on a plurality of channels. The network resource includes a content database storing content of a plurality of video broadcast events and a content serving module to serve the video broadcast events by broadcasting on the television broadcast network. Also included in the network resource is a guide database that stores event schedules each including one of the channels, a start time, and a duration corresponding to one of the video broadcast events on the broadcast network. A guide serving module is also included in the network resource to serve the event schedules by broadcasting on the television broadcast network.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The client device includes a receiver to receive a video signal and a video recorder to create a recording of video data received in the video signal into a storage area of a memory device. A video play is included in the client device to play back the recording of video data in the storage area of the memory device. A processor in the client device executes an application to perform various functions. These functions include receiving a request to create a program event for making a recording in the memory of one of the video broadcast events that is being broadcast on one of the channels, where the recording includes the content and the corresponding event schedule. Another function is the creation of the program event in response to the request.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Once the program event has been created, various incidents can occur that might prevent the video recorder from either making a recording of the video broadcast event or playing back the recording once the recording has been made. If the recording is not made, the video recorder will not be capable of playing back the recording. Thus, an incident that prevents the recording from being made is also an incident that prevents the video recorder from playing back the recording. A corrective event can be initiated following such an incident which, if timely performed, will allow the recording to be made or will allow a recording that has been made to be played back. Nevertheless, without the needed corrective event, the incident would likely prevent the recording from being made, and thus would likely prevent a play back of the recording.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Upon an occurrence of an incident that will likely prevent a play back by the video recorder of the recording in the memory corresponding to the program event, be it either a failure to make a recording or a failure to play back the recording once it has been made, execution of the application causes an output of a diagnostic that is descriptive of the incident that occurred. The incident can be one that is likely to prevent making the recording from being made, or one that is likely to prevent the recording, once made, from being played back. The requested program event is created in conjunction with a guide database which can be an electronic program guide (EPG). The EPG can be received into the memory of the client device by various techniques, including but not limited to directly tuning to a guide data stream on demand, a once-per-day dial up to receive EPG data, and trickle streaming the EPG data from a satellite signal or from another program guide data provider. The EPG typically includes information that relates to the programming content that will be broadcast in the future. More specifically, the guide data contains information that indicates, in advance, the starting time and ending time of the programs that are described by the guide data. The EPG also includes the channel, and the program title. A viewer selects a TV program listed in the EPG for recording by the client device. The client device is then able to create a program event that coordinates the client device to record the program that is linked in the EPG at its corresponding broadcast time.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The discussion herein is directed to television-based entertainment systems, such as interactive TV networks, cable networks and satellite systems that utilize electronic program guides, and Web-enabled TV networks. Client devices in such systems range from full-resource clients with substantial memory and processing resources, such as TV-enabled personal computers and TV recorders equipped with hard-disks, to low-resource clients with limited memory and/or processing resources, such as traditional set-top boxes. While aspects of the described methods and computer programs can be used in any of these systems and for any types of client devices, they are described in the context of the following exemplary environment.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">Exemplary Environment</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an exemplary environment <b>100</b> in which the methods, client devices, digital video recorders, computer programs, and systems described herein may be implemented. Exemplary environment <b>100</b> is a television entertainment system that facilitates distribution of content and program data to multiple viewers. The environment <b>100</b> includes one or more content providers <b>102</b>, one or more program data providers <b>104</b>, a content distribution system <b>106</b>, and multiple client devices <b>108</b>(<b>1</b>), <b>108</b>(<b>2</b>), . . . , <b>108</b>(N) coupled to the content distribution system <b>106</b> via a broadcast network <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Content provider <b>102</b> includes a content server <b>112</b> and stored content <b>114</b>, such as movies, television programs, commercials, music, and similar audio and/or video content. Content server <b>112</b> controls distribution of the stored content <b>114</b> from content provider <b>102</b> to the content distribution system <b>106</b>. Additionally, content server <b>102</b> controls distribution of live content (e.g., content that was not previously stored, such as live feeds) and/or content stored at other locations to the content distribution system <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Program data provider <b>104</b> includes an electronic program guide (EPG) database <b>116</b> and an EPG server <b>118</b>. The EPG database <b>116</b> stores electronic files of program data <b>120</b> which is used to generate an electronic program guide (or, “program guide”). Program data includes program titles, ratings, characters, descriptions, actor names, station identifiers, channel identifiers, schedule information, and so on. The terms “program data” and “EPG data” are used interchangeably throughout this discussion. For discussion purposes, an electronic file maintains program data <b>120</b> that may include a program title <b>122</b>, a program day or days <b>124</b> to identify which days of the week the program will be shown, and a start time or times <b>126</b> to identify the time that the program will be shown on the particular day or days of the week.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The EPG server <b>118</b> processes the EPG data prior to distribution to generate a published version of the program data which contains programming information for all channels for one or more days. The processing may involve any number of techniques to reduce, modify, or enhance the EPG data. Such processes might include selection of content, content compression, format modification, and the like. The EPG server <b>118</b> controls distribution of the published version of the program data from program data provider <b>104</b> to the content distribution system <b>106</b> using, for example, a file transfer protocol (FTP) over a TCP/IP network (e.g., Internet, UNIX, etc.). Further, the published version of the program data can be transmitted from program data provider <b>102</b> via a satellite <b>134</b> directly to a client device <b>108</b> by use of a satellite dish <b>134</b>. The EPG data need not be received via a video signal. Rather, the EPG data can be received by the client device by tuning to a low bandwidth carrier signal that piggybacks with other signals and is generally transmitted at a lower data rate than video signals that are transmitted by satellite.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Content distribution system <b>106</b> includes a broadcast transmitter <b>128</b>, one or more content processors <b>130</b>, and one or more program data processors <b>132</b>. Broadcast transmitter <b>128</b> broadcasts signals, such as cable television signals, across broadcast network <b>110</b>. Broadcast network <b>110</b> can include a cable television network, RF, microwave, satellite, and/or data network, such as the Internet, and may also include wired or wireless media using any broadcast format or broadcast protocol. Additionally, broadcast network <b>110</b> can be any type of network, using any type of network topology and any network communication protocol, and can be represented or otherwise implemented as a combination of two or more networks.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Content processor <b>130</b> processes the content received from content provider <b>102</b> prior to transmitting the content across broadcast network <b>108</b>. Similarly, program data processor <b>132</b> processes the program data received from program data provider <b>104</b> prior to transmitting the program data across broadcast network <b>110</b>. A particular content processor <b>130</b> may encode, or otherwise process, the received content into a format that is understood by the multiple client devices <b>108</b>(<b>1</b>), <b>108</b>(<b>2</b>), . . . , <b>108</b>(N) coupled to broadcast network <b>110</b>. Although <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a single content provider <b>102</b>, a single program data provider <b>104</b>, and a single content distribution system <b>106</b>, exemplary environment <b>100</b> can include any number of content providers and/or program data providers coupled to any number of content distribution systems.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Content distribution system <b>106</b> is representative of a headend service that provides EPG data, as well as content, to multiple subscribers. Each content distribution system <b>104</b> may receive a slightly different version of the program data that takes into account different programming preferences and lineups. The EPG server <b>118</b> creates different versions of EPG data (e.g., different versions of a program guide) that include those channels of relevance to respective headend services, and the content distribution system <b>106</b> transmits the EPG data to the multiple client devices <b>108</b>(<b>1</b>), <b>108</b>(<b>2</b>), . . . , <b>108</b>(N). In one implementation, for example, content distribution system <b>106</b> utilizes a carousel file system to repeatedly broadcast the EPG data over an out-of-band (OOB) channel to the client devices <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Client devices <b>108</b> can be implemented in a number of ways. For example, a client device <b>108</b>(<b>1</b>) receives broadcast content from a satellite-based transmitter via satellite dish <b>134</b>. Client device <b>108</b>(<b>1</b>) is also referred to as a set-top box or a satellite receiving device. Client device <b>108</b>(<b>1</b>) is coupled to a television <b>136</b>(<b>1</b>) for presenting the content received by the client device (e.g., audio data and video data), as well as a graphical user interface. A particular client device <b>108</b> can be coupled to any number of televisions <b>136</b> and/or similar devices that can be implemented to display or otherwise render content. Similarly, any number of client devices <b>108</b> can be coupled to a single television <b>136</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Client device <b>108</b>(<b>2</b>) is also coupled to receive broadcast content from broadcast network <b>110</b> and provide the received content to associated television <b>136</b>(<b>2</b>). Client device <b>108</b>(N) is an example of a combination television <b>138</b> and integrated set-top box <b>140</b>. In this example, the various components and functionality of the set-top box are incorporated into the television, rather than using two separate devices. The set-top box incorporated into the television may receive broadcast signals via a satellite dish (similar to satellite dish <b>134</b>) and/or via broadcast network <b>110</b>. In alternate implementations, client devices <b>108</b> may receive broadcast signals via a two-way network, such as the Internet, or any other broadcast medium.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Each client device <b>108</b> runs an EPG application that utilizes the program data. The EPG application enables a television viewer to navigate through an onscreen program guide and locate television shows of interest to the viewer. With the EPG application, the television viewer can look at schedules of current and future programming, set reminders for upcoming programs, and/or enter instructions to record one or more television shows. The client device <b>108</b>, in turn, creates one or more corresponding program events for the recordings.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Also included in environment <b>100</b> are one or more network devices, such as a messaging server <b>150</b>, that communicate with content distribution system <b>106</b> and with client devices (<b>1</b>-N) through an interconnected network <b>109</b>, such as the Internet. Interconnected network <b>109</b> allows two-way communication between client devices <b>108</b> (<b>1</b>-N) to messaging server <b>150</b>. This communication allows client devices <b>108</b> (<b>1</b>-N) and/or messaging server <b>105</b> to transmit addressed messages over interconnected network <b>109</b>. The addressed messages can be used to carry information that describes to a reader thereof the particular status of the functioning and/or operation of client devices <b>108</b> (<b>1</b>-N). Once such status of state, among others, might be a description of an incident that is likely to prevent a client device from recording TV programs and/or playing back recorded TV programs. A viewer can use the client device <b>108</b>, or a personal computer or other network device to log on to network <b>109</b>, such as the Internet, and to communicate with messaging server <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The messaging server <b>150</b> can be a network service, such as a Web hosting service, that stores data about any client device <b>108</b> or its respective viewer. The viewer can keep data at messaging server <b>150</b> that can in turn be accessed by other Web hosting services on the Internet where the viewer has permitted such access, which may be of a limited nature. An example of such a data provider is the Microsoft Network (MSN) of the Microsoft Corporation of Redmond, Wash. MSN provides a .NET™ PASSPORT® service that, among other services, stores data that can be retrieved by other Web services on the Internet that are compatible with the .NET™ PASSPORT® service. In this example, the viewer can submit various contact information to messaging server <b>150</b>. These contact information can be one or more addresses to which diagnostics and/or descriptions of the diagnostics are to be sent with respect to recording and/or playing back a recording with a particular client device <b>108</b>. When an incident occurs at a particular client device <b>108</b> with respect to making a recording of a TV program, or playing back a recording of a TV program, client device <b>108</b> can send a cryptic diagnostic to messaging server <b>150</b>. Messaging server <b>150</b> can identify the particular client device by the content of the diagnostic, translate the cryptic diagnostic into a description of the incident and/or a solution thereof, and then transmit the description of the incident and/or solution to the one or more addresses that the viewer has stored at messaging server <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The process and circumstances under which messaging server <b>150</b> transmits descriptive diagnostics to the one or more addresses can be variously configured. For instance, messaging server <b>150</b> can be configured to transmit textual messages during daylight hours to a cellular telephone number and to transmit the same to a facsimile machine during evening hours. The configuration of a Web hosting service, such as messaging server <b>150</b>, can be operated by the viewer from a two-way network resource having access to interconnected network <b>109</b>, such as a personal computer or a local set top box client device. Of course, alternative configurations are contemplated as are conventional with message delivery modalities.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Optionally, one or more of the program data providers <b>104</b> can include stored on-demand content, such as Video On-Demand (VOD) movie content. The stored on-demand content can be viewed with a client device <b>108</b> through an onscreen movie guide, for example, and a viewer can enter instructions to stream a particular movie, or other stored content, down to a corresponding client device <b>108</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Exemplary Client Device</heading>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates an exemplary implementation <b>200</b> of a client device <b>108</b> shown as a standalone unit that connects to a television <b>136</b>. Client device <b>108</b> can be implemented in any number of embodiments, including as a set-top box, a satellite receiver, a TV recorder with a hard disk, personal computer, a game console, an information appliance, and so forth. Client device <b>108</b> includes a wireless receiving port <b>202</b>, such as an infrared (IR) or Bluetooth wireless port, for receiving wireless communications from a remote control device <b>204</b>, a handheld input device <b>206</b>, or any other wireless device, such as a wireless keyboard. Handheld input device <b>206</b> can be a personal digital assistant (PDA), handheld computer, wireless phone, or the like. Additionally, a wired keyboard <b>208</b> is coupled to communicate with the client device <b>108</b>. In alternate embodiments, remote control device <b>204</b>, handheld device <b>206</b>, and/or keyboard <b>208</b> may use an RF communication link or other mode of transmission to communicate with client device <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Client device <b>108</b> receives one or more broadcast signals <b>210</b> through from one or more broadcast sources, such as from a satellite or from a broadcast network. Client device <b>108</b> includes hardware and/or software for receiving and decoding broadcast signal <b>210</b>, such as an NTSC, PAL, SECAM or other TV system video signal. Client device <b>108</b> also includes hardware and/or software for providing the viewer with a graphical user interface by which the viewer can, for example, access various network services, configure the client device <b>108</b>, and perform other functions.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Client device <b>108</b> is capable of communicating through interconnected network <b>109</b> seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with other devices via one or more connections including a conventional telephone link <b>212</b>, an ISDN link <b>214</b>, a cable link <b>216</b>, an Ethernet link <b>218</b>, an ADSL and/or DSL link <b>220</b>, and the like. Client device <b>108</b> may use any one or more of the various communication links <b>212</b>-<b>220</b> at a particular instant to communicate with any number of other devices and/or to establish a two-way communication with one or more network resources.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Client device <b>108</b> generates video signal(s) <b>220</b> and audio signal(s) <b>222</b>, both of which are communicated to television <b>136</b>. The video signals and audio signals can be communicated from client device <b>108</b> to television <b>136</b> via an RF (radio frequency) link, S-video link, composite video link, component video link, or other communication link. At reference numeral <b>203</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, client device <b>108</b> includes one or more lights or other indicators identifying the current status of the device or for diagnostic reports to a viewer. Additionally, the client device may include one or more control buttons, switches, or other selectable controls for controlling operation of the device.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, television <b>136</b> shows a display line <b>224</b> which informs the viewer that client device <b>108</b> has output a diagnostic. By way of example, a diagnostic can be output by client device <b>108</b> that describes an incident in communications with a two-way network, where client device <b>108</b> can not send descriptive diagnostics to a predetermined network address. Such a failure can be due to excessive network traffic or a failure in logging onto the network. Other diagnostics and descriptions thereof that are output by client device <b>108</b> for display on television <b>136</b> are discussed below with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The diagnostics can be issued to the viewer for their own edification and/or so that the viewer may take any action that may be warranted. Additionally, a diagnostic visual and/or audible alarm device or mechanism at reference numeral <b>203</b> can emit a diagnostic representative of that which is displayed at display line <b>224</b>. In the alternative, both display line <b>224</b> and an alarm with the diagnostic visual and/or audible alarm device or mechanism at reference numeral <b>203</b> can be used so that the viewer may be warned visually and/or audibly.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates selected components of client device(s) <b>108</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-2</figref>. Client device <b>108</b> includes one or more tuners <b>300</b>(<i>i</i>). Tuners <b>300</b>(<i>i</i>) are representative of one or more in-band tuners that tune to various frequencies or channels to receive television signals, as well as an out-of-band tuner that tunes to the broadcast channel over which the EPG data is broadcast to client device <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Client device <b>108</b> also includes one or more processors <b>304</b> and one or more memory components. Examples of possible memory components include a random access memory (RAM) <b>306</b>, a disk drive <b>308</b>, a mass storage component <b>310</b>, and a non-volatile memory <b>312</b> (e.g., ROM, Flash, EPROM, EEPROM, etc.). Disk drive <b>308</b> can have one or a plurality of recordings (i) and one or a plurality of pause buffers (j) stored thereon. Recordings (i) and pause buffers (j) can also be stored in one or more other memory devices at client device <b>108</b>, such as in non-volatile memory <b>312</b>, RAM <b>306</b>, and/or storage media <b>310</b>. Alternatively, recordings (i) and pause buffers (j) can also be stored remote from client device <b>108</b> at a network resource in communication with client device <b>108</b> through interconnected network <b>109</b> seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Alternative implementations of client device <b>108</b> can include a range of processing and memory capabilities, and may include more or fewer types of memory components than those illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. For example, full-resource clients can be implemented with substantial memory and processing resources, including a disk drive <b>308</b> to store content for replay by the viewer. Low-resource clients, however, may have limited processing and memory capabilities, such as a limited amount of RAM <b>306</b>, no disk drive <b>308</b>, and limited processing capabilities. Nevertheless it is intended that client device <b>108</b> include a capability for video recording, either locally or remotely from client device <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Processor(s) <b>304</b> process various instructions to control the operation of client device <b>108</b> and to communicate with other electronic and computing devices. The memory components (e.g., RAM <b>306</b>, disk drive <b>308</b>, storage media <b>310</b>, and non-volatile memory <b>312</b>) can be used to store various information and/or data such as recordings of TV programs or other broadcast content, EPG data, configuration information for client device <b>108</b>, and/or graphical user interface information.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">An operating system <b>314</b> and one or more application programs <b>316</b> may be stored in non-volatile memory <b>312</b> and executed on processor <b>304</b> to provide a runtime environment. A runtime environment facilitates extensibility of client device <b>108</b> by allowing various interfaces to be defined that, in turn, allow application programs <b>316</b> to interact with client device <b>108</b>. In the illustrated example, an EPG application <b>318</b> is stored in memory <b>312</b> to operate on the EPG data and generate a program guide.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows non-volatile memory <b>312</b> having a diagnostics communication application <b>302</b> which, when executed by processor(s) <b>304</b>, causes client device <b>108</b> to output a diagnostic. The diagnostic is output when particular incidents are detected to have occurred. For instance, client device <b>108</b> may detect an incident that, if uncorrected, will prevent a recording of a broadcast TV show from being made. It follows, therefore, that if the recording is not made due to the incident, then the incident also prevents a play back of the TV show, unless corrective action is taken. Thus, the execution of diagnostic application <b>302</b> causes client device <b>108</b> to output a diagnostic upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent a play back of a recording that was made or that was sought to be made by client device <b>108</b>. A description of the particular diagnostic, and any remedy or correction thereto, can be stored in memory <b>312</b> and accessed in a variety of techniques, such as by a lookup table technique where a description corresponding to the particular diagnostic is found in the lookup table. The diagnostic output from client device <b>108</b>, as well as other communications, can be communicated in a one or two-way communication through interconnected network <b>109</b> see in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. These communications can be made with various network resources using network interface <b>324</b>, wireless interface <b>322</b>, serial/parallel interface <b>326</b>, modem <b>328</b>, or other well known communication hardware/software algorithms and protocol for computing devices. The application programs <b>316</b> that may be implemented at client device <b>108</b>, which can function with a diagnostics communication application <b>302</b>, include a browser to browse the Web so as to view diagnostics at a Web site, an electronic mail (email) program to facilitate email to transmit descriptive diagnostic emails to an email address, a facsimile transmission program to initiate a facsimile transmission to a facsimile machine through phone line <b>212</b> seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> so as to send a facsimile message describing diagnostics with respect to client device <b>108</b>, a Short Message Service (SMS) transmission program to initiate a transmission of a text message describing diagnostics with respect to client device <b>108</b> to a mobile pager on a page channel, and so on.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Client device <b>108</b> can also include other components pertaining to a television entertainment system which are not illustrated in this example for simplicity purposes. For instance, client device <b>108</b> can include a user interface application and user interface lights, buttons, controls, etc. to facilitate viewer interaction with the device.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Client device <b>108</b> also includes a decoder <b>320</b> to decode a broadcast video signal, such as an NTSC, PAL, SECAM or other TV system video signal. Alternatively, a decoder for client device <b>108</b> can be implemented, in whole or in part, as a software application executed by processor(s) <b>304</b>. Wireless interface <b>322</b> allows client device <b>108</b> to receive input commands and other information from a viewer-operated input device, such as from a remote control device or from another IR, Bluetooth, or similar RF input device.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Network interface <b>324</b> and serial and/or parallel interface <b>326</b> allows client device <b>108</b> to interact and communicate with other electronic and computing devices via various communication links. Although not shown, client device <b>108</b> may also include other types of data communication interfaces to communicate with other devices. Modem <b>328</b> facilitates client device <b>108</b> communications with other electronic and computing devices via a conventional telephone line. Components seen at reference numerals <b>316</b> and <b>322</b>-<b>328</b> facilitate applications where client device <b>108</b> has Internet access or communicates data on a two-way network.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Client device <b>108</b> also includes an audio output <b>330</b> and a video output <b>332</b> that provide signals to a television or other device that processes and/or presents or otherwise renders the audio and video data. Although shown separately, some of the components of client device <b>108</b> may be implemented in an application specific integrated circuit (ASIC). Additionally, a system bus (not shown) typically connects the various components within client device <b>108</b>. A system bus can be implemented as one or more of any of several types of bus structures, including a memory bus or memory controller, a peripheral bus, an accelerated graphics port, or a local bus using any of a variety of bus architectures. By way of example, such architectures can include an Industry Standard Architecture (ISA) bus, a Micro Channel Architecture (MCA) bus, an Enhanced ISA (EISA) bus, a Video Electronics Standards Association (VESA) local bus, and a Peripheral Component Interconnects (PCI) bus also known as a Mezzanine bus.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">General reference has been made herein to one or more client devices, such as client device <b>108</b>. As used herein, “client device” means any electronic device having data communications, data storage capabilities, and/or functions to process and record signals, such as broadcast signals, received from any of a number of different sources.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a method for programming a client device to create a program event so as to record a TV program that is to be broadcast at a broadcast time. The method in this implementation includes recording the TV program at the broadcast time, and playing back the recording TV program, where incidents are detected in the method so as to produce diagnostics therefrom. By way of example, and not by way of limitation, an incident can be an event that is likely to prevent a client device from making or playing back a recording. The order in which the method is described is not intended to be construed as a limitation, and any number of the described method blocks can be combined in any order to implement the method. Furthermore, the method can be implemented in any suitable hardware, software, firmware, or combination thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">A process <b>400</b> is seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> which can be used, for example, with respect to environments <b>100</b>, <b>200</b> depicted, respectively, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-2</figref>. Process <b>400</b> proceeds at block <b>402</b> where a client device has received a request to record a TV program according to EPG data that assigns to the TV program a broadcast channel at a future starting time on a particular date for a particular duration. Process <b>400</b> then moves to block <b>404</b> where the client device tests for an incident. If an incident is detected by the client device, process <b>400</b> moves to block <b>406</b> where the client device outputs a diagnostic descriptive of the detected incident. If no incident is detected by the client device, process <b>400</b> moves to block <b>408</b> where a clock, such as a system clock of the client device, tests whether the date and time of the TV program to be recorded has arrived. The time can be obtained from the broadcast received by the client device, by input from the viewer that is made to the client device, or by other knows means. If the date and starting time of the TV program has not yet arrived, the process <b>400</b> cycles through blocks <b>408</b> and <b>404</b> until the date and starting time have arrived.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In one implementation, process <b>400</b> continues to loop between blocks <b>406</b> and <b>404</b> to repeatedly test whether the previously detected incident no longer exists. If the incident no longer can be detected at block <b>404</b>, process <b>400</b> moves to block <b>406</b> where the client device outputs yet another diagnostic that describes that the previously detected incident can no longer be detected. Then, process <b>400</b> moves to block <b>408</b>. By way of example, and not by way of limitation, a viewer schedules a favored TV program for recording according to a first set of EPG data received by a client device. Later, the client device receives a second set of EPG data that shows the TV program to be have been preempted by an another TV program. A first diagnostic is output by the client device describing the preempting incident that will likely prevent the desired recording, and therefore play back, of the viewer favored TV program. The client device then receives a third set of EPG data that removes the preempting program and re-schedules the viewer favored TV program as per its original broadcast schedule. A second diagnostic is then output by the client device describing the removal of the incident and acknowledging that the original program will be recorded as originally scheduled.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">At the time of the broadcast of the TV program, in accordance with the corresponding EPG data, the client device begins recording the TV program on a corresponding broadcast channel at block <b>410</b>. During the recording through the duration of the broadcast, the client device tests for an incident at respective blocks <b>412</b> and <b>416</b>. A description of any detected incident is output at block <b>414</b> and process <b>400</b> can abort.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In one implementation, process <b>400</b> can continue loop from block <b>414</b> to block <b>412</b> to test whether the incident no longer exists, as was described above. When the incident can no longer be detected, process <b>400</b> proceeds to block <b>416</b> to complete the recording of the TV program in accordance with the corresponding EPG data.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">After the recording of the TV program in accordance with the corresponding EPG data, the recording process is completed at block <b>418</b>. Subsequently, at block <b>420</b>, a viewer inputs a command to the client device to request a play back of the TV program recorded by the client device. Before playing back the recorded TV program, the client device tests for an incident at block <b>422</b> and reports a diagnostic that is descriptive of any detected incidents at block <b>414</b>. Otherwise, the play back begins at block <b>424</b> and is completed at block <b>432</b>. Between the beginning and end of the play back of the recorded TV program, the client device tests for an incident at block <b>426</b> and outputs a description of the incident at block <b>428</b>. Process <b>400</b> shows that descriptive diagnostics of incidents can be output by a client device when there is an unsuccessful creation of a recording of a TV program or when there is an unsuccessful playback of the recording.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The techniques, methods, or algorithms in and by which the client device makes a descriptive report of a detected incident at blocks <b>406</b>, <b>414</b>, and <b>426</b> in process <b>400</b> are sufficient to communicate the context of the respective incident to a viewer or other interested party with respective to when the incident is likely to prevent a TV program from being recorded or when the incident is likely to prevent a TV program that was recorded from being played back. The incident detected by the client device can include, but is not limited to, a video signal failure on the broadcast channel, an equipment failure at the client device, and a receipt of notice at the client device that the broadcast of the TV program on the channel has in someway changed from the original data used to program the client device to perform the recording. By way of example of the later incident, a viewer first schedules a favored TV program for recording according to a first set of EPG data received by a client device. Later, the client device receives a second set of EPG data that shows the TV program to be have been preempted by an another TV program. A video signal failure on the broadcast channel incident can occur before a completion of making the recording of the TV program and before a completion of the playback of the same. Examples of a video signal failure include incidents where a cable that carries the video signal to the client device becomes unattached from the client device, or where the client device detects that the video signal is scrambled. The signal may become scrambled because the client device losses rights to view content on a particular channel to due a lapsed subscription to the channel to which access was conditioned upon a paid-up subscription. An equipment failure incident can occur before a completion of making the recording and before a completion of the playback thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The client device can be a standalone device that outputs diagnostics to a TV receiver. Alternatively, the client device can be in communication with other peripheral devices and/or with one or more network resources through an interconnected network. As such, the client device can output a diagnostic in various techniques, methods, or algorithms including, but not limited to, an audio output, a visual output, and by way of a transmission to an address on the interconnected network. In the case of the transmission, the transmission can include a message containing a diagnostic that describes the incident. The transmission of the message to the address can take several different actions including, but not limited to, transmitting the message for output at a printer having the address, transmitting the message for output on a television receiver having the address, transmitting the message for a facsimile transmission on a circuit switched network to a facsimile machine associated with a facsimile telephone number corresponding to the address, transmitting the message for a circuit switched network in a telephone transmission to a telephone number corresponding to the address, transmitting the message for a packet switched network to a network resource having the address as a publication to a Web site hosted by the network resource, transmitting the message in packets for a packet switched network to a network resource having the address, transmitting the message as email to an email address at an email server serving the address, and transmitting the message for an SMS transmission to a mobile pager on a page channel.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The message in the transmission can include not only a description of the incident, but also a description of one or more solutions or corrective actions that, if taken, will likely permit the intended TV program to be recorded and/or a recording thereof played back. The descriptive diagnostics can be output by the client device in a function that, for each incident, writes an entry to a history file for the TV program. The client device can then optionally output all or a portion of the history file. In addition to the incident, the client device can also be configured to output descriptions of each action taken with respect to recording and playing back a TV program, both the successful actions as well as the incidents. As such, a complete history log and/or file can be established for each TV program to be recorded and for each recorded TV program to be played back by the client device.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In general, an incident can occur within different time periods with respect to making a recording of a TV program and/or a play back of the recording of the TV program. An incident can occur before the recording in the time period prior to the broadcast start time of the TV program. During the recording, an incident can occur from about the broadcast start time to about the broadcast end time. An incident can also occur after the recording is made but prior to a completion of the play back of the recording of the TV program. Various incidents can occur prior to the broadcast start time of the TV program that will likely prevent a proper recording, and therefore a proper playback, of the TV program. One such incident is a change in the corresponding EPG data that invalidates the original EPG data used to program the client device. A revision to the EPG data that is received by the client device can detect such an incident when compared to prior viewer requests for recordings. Possible EPG data changes include the broadcast start time, the broadcast end time, and the broadcast channel. Other incidents are a video signal failure on the broadcast channel, failure in equipment for processing the video signal in the client device, unavailability of memory in the client device to record the TV program, and a reprogramming of the client device that changes the original instructions to record the TV program. Still another incident that can be output in a diagnostic by the client is where a viewer is notified when a TV program that is normally broadcast at a predetermined time is pre-empted by a different TV program. By way of example, and not by way of limitation, a circular four week recording history is associated with each series that a viewer wants to record. For the normal show time of each series, the viewer setups the client device with the appropriate recording event on. The client device is configured to maintain a history of the days the shows of each series were broadcast and the days the shows of the series were not broadcast. The client device can then use the statistical data of the history of broadcasts to output diagnostics that notify the user when a show in a series has been pre-empted. By way of a more particular example, a situation comedy show is normally scheduled to air every week for three consecutive Thursdays. On the fourth Thursday, the situation comedy is preempted by another show that is to be broadcast. The client can output a diagnostic, such as by writing a message entry to a history file, such as “The Situation Comedy on Channel 4 on Apr. 12, 2010 at 8:00 P.M. will not be recorded because it has been pre-empted by the Situation Drama.”</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">The client device can determine, prior to the program starting time, that it lacks available memory to record a requested TV program. The client device may be configured to determine that the recording request has a higher priority than that of a previous recording request, and that memory is not available to record both programs. As such, the client device can remove the first programming request in favor of the second programming request, and then output a diagnostic that reflects that the client device has perfected a removal of the first programming request in favor of the second programming event. Alternatively, the client device may simply output the diagnostic. The viewer, upon receipt of the descriptive diagnostic, can then take remedial action with the client device such as by deleting the first request in favor of the second recording request.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">While the client device is recording a TV program that is being broadcast on a channel of a broadcast network, various incidents can occur that will likely prevent a proper recording, and therefore a proper playback, of the TV program. This can include a change in at least one of the broadcast start time, the broadcast end time, and the broadcast channel, a video signal failure on the broadcast channel, a failure in equipment for processing the video signal or in the client device in general, unavailability of memory to record the TV program in the memory of the client device, a logical deletion of the recording that is being made or other memory failure, or a re-programming of the client device that changes the original instructions to record the TV program.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">An incident can occur during the recording of a TV program where the client device determines that is lacks sufficient memory capacity to record the TV program. This can occur when the client device receives input that requests that the client device record another program. The client device then processes the request and may be configured to determine that the new programming request has a higher priority than that of the TV program that is currently being recorded. The unavailability of memory for both TV programs is detected by the client device, which in turn can logically delete the recording corresponding to the first TV program so as to secure memory sufficient to record the second TV program. Also, the client device can then output a report descriptive of its actions and causes thereof. Alternatively, the client device may simply output the diagnostic. The viewer, upon receipt of the descriptive diagnostic, can then take remedial action with the client device.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">After a TV program has been recorded by a client device, incidents can occur that make a playback of the recorded TV program unlikely. Such incidents include failure in a playback component of the client device or other equipment required for same, or a logical deletion of the recorded TV program. Such a logical deletion can be made where the client device receives a request to create another TV program event from EPG data so as to record a corresponding TV program. The client device can be configured so as to detect both that the second TV program has a higher priority than that of the first TV program and that available memory in the client device that already holds a recording of the first TV program is insufficient to also record the second TV program. The client device can be configured to logically delete the recording corresponding to the first TV program so as to secure memory sufficient to recording the corresponding second TV program. Also, the client device can then output a report descriptive of its actions and causes thereof. Alternatively, the client device may simple output the diagnostic. The viewer, upon receipt of the descriptive diagnostic, can then take remedial action with the client device.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">In general, the client device can be configured to logically erase all or at least a portion of a memory of the client device that is required to record a TV program that corresponds to EPG data indicated by a viewer by input to the client device. The logical erasure of the memory of the client device, however, may still not be sufficient to allow the TV program to be recorded. In this case, the client device can be configured to output a diagnostic descriptive of this problem. The viewer, upon receipt of the descriptive diagnostic, can then take remedial action with the client device.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, an exemplary system <b>500</b> for implementing entertainment architecture includes client device <b>108</b> in communication with television <b>136</b>. Television <b>136</b> has display lines <b>12</b> through <b>26</b> where there is displayed an example of a program guide showing part of a channel programming lineup for Friday, Dec. 31, 2010. The program guide is generated with an EPG application in client device <b>108</b> with program data, where part of the program data is displayed on television <b>136</b>. The program guide provides a viewer with a program title, the associated local channel number and/or television broadcasting company that will broadcast the program, and a time of the day that the program will be broadcast.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The program guide assists a viewer to identify and select a program title that the viewer wishes to view or record if the program is currently being broadcast, access program data to learn more about the program, and/or enter a request to record the program if the program is to air in the future. A viewer can move within the program guide, using an input device such as a remote control device, to input control commands to client device <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">In display line <b>12</b>, an explanation for the display on television <b>136</b> is given that the display shows a portion of the EPG channel lineup for the date Friday, Dec. 31, 2010. Display line <b>14</b>, in the first column thereof, shows scrollable user interface icons. The first icon in the first column of display line <b>14</b> indicates that a viewer can scroll vertically to show various channels for the 6:00 P.M. to 9:00 P.M. time period. The second icon in the second column of display line <b>14</b> indicates that the viewer can scan chronologically forward and backwards for each of the displayed channels 2 through 9. The second, third and fourth columns indicate the timeslots 6 P.M., 7 P.M., and 8 P.M.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Display line <b>16</b> shows the lineup for channel 2, the “ABC” television broadcast network. As seen in the second column of display line <b>16</b> two programs are indicated, namely the Late News at 6 P.M. and the Late Show at 7 P.M. Display line <b>17</b> shows the lineup for channel 3, the “HBO” television broadcast network to be a TV program titled “Superman X” that starts at 6:00 PM and continues to 9:00 PM. Display line <b>24</b> for the display on television <b>136</b> shows the channel 7 line up for the CBN network. The line up includes several chronologically adjacent TV programs to be broadcast on Channel 7, including the Hunting News to begin at 6:00 P.M. and to continue until 7:00 P.M., the Sport Show B to begin at 7:00 P.M. and to continue until 8:00 P.M., and the Fishing News to begin at 8:00 P.M. Display line <b>26</b> shows that Sport Show A begins at 6 P.M. and continues until 7 P.M. on channel 9 on the ESPN television broadcast network. A viewer can use an input device, such as those seen at reference numerals <b>204</b>-<b>208</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, to select one or more of the TV program of the EPG seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> to be recorded.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the exemplary system <b>500</b> shows television <b>136</b> having a display in display lines <b>2</b> through <b>20</b> where various diagnostics have been output by client device <b>108</b> for display on television <b>136</b> to be observed by a viewer. As such, the method of communication of descriptive diagnostics to the viewer, with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, is by display on television <b>136</b>. Four (4) diagnostics are seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The first diagnostic is seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> at display lines <b>2</b> through <b>6</b> and is indicative of a circumstance where a viewer has requested that “This Week In Pictures” be recorded on Channel 6 on Friday, Dec. 31, 2010 at 7:00 PM. The client device has output the diagnostic that its second tuner has malfunctioned by which the TV program on Channel 6 was to have been recorded. This diagnostic might be output by the client device where there were multiple tuners each of was busy recording another program. The desired recording might have been made, however, if another tuner was available.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The client device, however, has initiated remedial action by sending an email to a customer service organization, the receipt of which has been acknowledged by the same. The client device has also displayed a Web site address at which more information as to the diagnosis can be found. In this case, a Web browser function of the client device can be actuated to view the diagnosis at the Web site, such as by using an input device to input a demand to link to the displayed Web site. In addition to Web site addresses, the client device can be configured to store telephone numbers, email addresses, and other addresses to which the client device can send diagnostics and/or descriptions of such diagnostics.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Display lines <b>8</b>-<b>9</b> confirm that that the client device has successfully recorded Sport Show B on Channel 7 on Friday, Dec. 31, 2010 at 7:00 PM. Display lines <b>12</b>-<b>15</b> indicates that Superman X was to be recorded, but that the viewer has cancelled a subscription to the HBO programming on Channel 3, effective Dec. 20, 2010. These display lines also give a telephone number to call in order to initiate a resumption of the HBO subscription.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">EPG data has been changed from the viewer's original programming instructions to the client device, as seen in display lines <b>16</b>-<b>20</b>. In particular, the Matinee Mystery, originally scheduled to broadcast on Channel 2 at 2:00 PM on Monday, Jan. 3, 2010, has been taken off the broadcast lineup. The client device has output a description to the viewer with respect to using an input device to find out when Matinee Mystery will be broadcast. Here, the input device has a key titled “ALTER” that the viewer can press to initial this function of the client device. Apparent from display lines <b>16</b>-<b>20</b> is that the original EPG data has been revised. The revised EPG may have received by the client device from the broadcast network, or from another source such as from a two-way network, from the viewer making an input to the client device, and/or from other sources.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Implementations extend to methods, client devices, digital video recorders, computer programs, and systems for outputting a diagnostic descriptive of an incident that is likely to prevent a recording of a TV program or a play back of the recording. The implementations may comprise a special purpose or general purpose computer including various computer hardware as discussed by way of example in greater detail above. Implementations also include computer-readable media for carrying or having computer-executable instructions or data structures stored thereon. Such computer-readable media can be any available media which can be accessed by a general purpose or special purpose computer. One example of a special purpose computer is a set top box. By way of example, and not limitation, such computer-readable media can comprise RAM, ROM, EEPROM, CD-ROM, DVD-R or other optical disk storage, magnetic disk storage or other magnetic storage devices, or any other medium which can be used to carry or store desired program code means in the form of computer-executable instructions or data structures and which can be accessed by a general purpose or special purpose computer. When information is transferred or provided over a network or another communications connection (either hardwired, wireless, or a combination of hardwired or wireless) to a computer, the computer properly views the connection as a computer-readable medium. Thus, any such a connection is properly termed a computer-readable medium. Combinations of the above should also be included within the scope of computer-readable media. Computer-executable instructions comprise, for example, instructions and data which cause a general purpose computer, special purpose computer, or special purpose processing device to perform a certain function or group of functions.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">The Figures and the foregoing discussion are intended to provide a brief, general description of a suitable computing environment in which the invention may be implemented. Although not required, the invention has been described in the general context of computer-executable instructions, such as program modules, being executed by computers in network environments. Generally, program modules include routines, programs, objects, components, data structures, etc. that perform particular tasks or implement particular abstract data types. Computer-executable instructions, associated data structures, and program modules represent examples of the program code means for executing steps of the methods disclosed herein. The particular sequence of such executable instructions or associated data structures represent examples of corresponding acts for implementing the functions described in such steps.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Those skilled in the art will appreciate that the invention may be practiced in network computing environments with many types of computer system configurations, including set top boxes, personal computers, hand-held devices, multi-processor systems, microprocessor-based or programmable consumer electronics, network PCs, minicomputers, mainframe computers, and the like. The invention may also be practiced in distributed computing environments where tasks are performed by local and remote processing devices that are linked (either by hardwired links, wireless links, or by a combination of hardwired or wireless links) through a communications network. In a distributed computing environment, program modules may be located in both local and remote memory storage devices.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">The present invention may be embodied in other specific forms without departing from its spirit or essential characteristics. The described embodiments are to be considered in all respects only as illustrative and not restrictive. The scope of the invention is, therefore, indicated by the appended claims rather than by the foregoing description. All changes which come within the meaning and range of equivalency of the claims are to be embraced within their scope.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method comprising:
<claim-text>receiving a request to create a program event to record a program from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>creating the program event to record the program in a recording for a playback of the program from the recording; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the playback, outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident, which includes communicating the diagnostic descriptive to a messaging service that transmits the diagnostic descriptive as a message to an address specified by a viewer, wherein the diagnostic descriptive describes one or more corrective actions for a recipient of the diagnostic descriptive to undertake to resolve the incident and permit the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising, upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent making the recording, outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the occurrence of the incident is within a time period selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>prior to the broadcast start time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>from about the broadcast start time to about the broadcast end time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>after the broadcast end time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>prior to a completion of making the recording;</claim-text>
<claim-text>before the playback;</claim-text>
<claim-text>during the playback; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>prior to a completion of the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein during the time period prior to the broadcast start time, the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>a change in at least one of the broadcast start time, the broadcast end time, and the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>video signal failure on the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>failure in equipment for processing the video signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>unavailability of memory to record the program in the recording corresponding to the program event; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a change to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the unavailability of memory to record the program in the recording corresponding to the program event comprises:
<claim-text>receiving a request to create a second program event to record a program from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>creating the second program event, wherein:</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second program event has a higher priority than that of the program event;</claim-text>
<claim-text>availability of memory is insufficient for the recording corresponding, respectively, to the both the program event and the second program event; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the diagnostic descriptive of the incident reflects a removal of the program event in favor the second program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein during the time period from about the broadcast start time to about the broadcast end time, the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>a change in at least one of the broadcast start time, the broadcast end time, and the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>video signal failure on the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>failure in equipment for processing the video signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>unavailability of memory to record the program in the recording;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a logical deletion of the recording; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a change to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the program event is a first program event and unavailability of memory to record the program in the recording corresponding to the first program event comprises:
<claim-text>receiving a request to create a second program event to record a program from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>creating the second program event, wherein:
<claim-text>the second program event has a higher priority than that of the first program event; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>availability of memory is insufficient for the recording corresponding, respectively, to the both the first program event and the second program event;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>logically deleting the recording corresponding to the first program event to secure availability of memory sufficient for the recording corresponding to the second program event, wherein the diagnostic descriptive of the incident reflects the unavailability of the recording corresponding to the first program event for play back in favor of the recording corresponding to the second program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein during the time period prior to the completion of the playback, the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>failure in equipment for the playback of the program from the recording; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a logical deletion of the recording corresponding to the first program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the logical deletion of the recording corresponding to the first program event comprises:
<claim-text>receiving a request to create a second program event to record a program from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>creating the second program event, wherein:
<claim-text>the second program event has a higher priority than that of the first program event; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>availability of memory is insufficient for the recording corresponding, respectively, to the both the first program event and the second program event;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>logically deleting the recording corresponding to the first program event to secure availability of memory sufficient for the recording corresponding to the second program event, wherein the diagnostic descriptive of the incident reflects the unavailability of the recording corresponding to the first program event for play back in favor of the recording corresponding to the second program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>video signal failure on the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>equipment failure; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>receipt of notice that broadcast of the program on the broadcast channel is not in accordance with the program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the video signal failure on the broadcast channel occurs at a time period selected from the group consisting of before a completion of making the recording and before a completion of the playback; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the equipment failure occurs at a time period selected from the group consisting of before a completion of making the recording and before a completion of the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>an audio output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a visual output; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transmission by the messaging service of a respective message including the diagnostic descriptive of the incident to each of a plurality of addresses specified by contact information provided to the messaging service by the viewer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the transmission of the message to the address is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a printer having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for output on a television receiver having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a facsimile transmission on a circuit switched network to a facsimile machine associated with a facsimile telephone number corresponding to the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a circuit switched network in a telephone transmission to a telephone number corresponding to the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a packet switched network to a network resource having the address as a publication to a Web site hosted by the network resource;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message in packets for a packet switched network to a network resource having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message as electronic mail (email) to an email address at an email server serving the address; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a Short Message Service (SMS) transmission to a mobile pager on a page channel.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the incident likely to prevent the playback is an unsuccessful making of the recording according to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the incident likely to prevent the playback is an unsuccessful playback of the recording.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident comprises, for each said incident, writing an entry to a history file for the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident further comprises outputting the history file.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. One or more computer-readable media comprising computer-executable instructions that, when executed, direct a computing system to perform the method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A digital video recorder comprising a processor in communication with a video recorder and a receiver and executing an application to:
<claim-text>receive a request to create a program event to record a program with the video recorder from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel carrying a video signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>create the program event to record the program in a recording for a playback of the program from the recording with the video recorder; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the playback, output a diagnostic descriptive of the incident, which includes the diagnostic descriptive being communicated to a messaging service configured to transmit the diagnostic descriptive as a message to an address specified by a viewer, wherein the diagnostic descriptive describes one or more corrective actions for a recipient of the diagnostic descriptive to undertake to resolve the incident and permit the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the processor executes the application further to, upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent making the recording of the program corresponding to the program event, output a diagnostic descriptive of the incident.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the occurrence of the incident is within a time period selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>prior to the broadcast start time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>from about the broadcast start time to about the broadcast end time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>after the broadcast end time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>prior to a completion of making the recording;</claim-text>
<claim-text>before the playback;</claim-text>
<claim-text>during the playback; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>prior to a completion of the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>insufficiency of the video signal carried on the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a failure of the video recorder; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>receipt at the receiver of notice that broadcast of the program on the broadcast channel is not in accordance with the program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the insufficiency of the video signal carried on the broadcast channel occurs at the time period selected from the group consisting of prior to the broadcast start time and from about the broadcast start time to about the broadcast end time; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the failure of the video recorder occurs at the time period selected from the group consisting of prior to a completion of making the recording and prior to a completion of the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the output of the diagnostic descriptive of the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>an audio output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a visual output; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transmission by the messaging service of a respective message including the diagnostic descriptive of the incident to each of a plurality of addresses specified by contact information provided to the messaging service by the viewer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the processor is in communication with an interconnected network that includes a network resource having the address; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the transmission to the address of the message is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a facsimile transmission on the interconnected network to a facsimile telephone number corresponding to the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a telephone transmission on the interconnected network to a telephone number corresponding to the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for the interconnected network as a publication to a Web site specified by the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message in packets for the interconnected network to the network resource corresponding to said address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message as an email to an email address corresponding to the address; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for an SMS transmission on the interconnected network to a mobile pager corresponding to the address on a page channel.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, wherein, prior to a completion of the playback, the message further includes a diagnostic descriptive of a correction action which, if undertaken, is likely to permit the playback.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the transmission of the message to the address is selected from a group consisting of:
<claim-text>transmitting the message for output at a printer having the address; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for output on a television receiver having the address.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the incident likely to prevent the playback is an unsuccessful making of the recording according to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the incident likely to prevent the playback is an unsuccessful playback of the recording.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the output of the diagnostic descriptive of the incident comprises, for each said incident, writing an entry to a history file for the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref>, wherein the output of the diagnostic descriptive of the incident further comprises outputting the history file.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. The digital video recorder as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, further comprising a memory including an entry in an electronic programming guide (EPG) corresponding to the program event, wherein:
<claim-text>the memory is in communication with the processor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the processor executes an application that, in response to an input thereto of a selection of the entry in the EPG, allocates a portion of the memory sufficient to record the program in the recording with the video recorder.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00033" num="00033">
<claim-text>33. A client device comprising:
<claim-text>means for receiving a request to create a program event to record a program from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for creating the program event to record the program in a recording;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for playing back the program from the recording in a play back; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means, upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the playback, for outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident, which includes communicating the diagnostic descriptive to a messaging service that transmits the diagnostic descriptive as a message to an address specified by a viewer, wherein:</claim-text>
<claim-text>the diagnostic descriptive describes one or more corrective actions for a recipient of the diagnostic descriptive to undertake to resolve the incident and permit the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00034" num="00034">
<claim-text>34. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, further comprising means, upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent making the recording, for outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00035" num="00035">
<claim-text>35. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>means for storing the recording corresponding to the program event;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for determining an amount of the means for storing the recording corresponding to the program event;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for logically erasing the means for storing the recording corresponding to the program event sufficient for the determined amount by the means for determining;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for receiving the program being broadcast on the broadcast channel corresponding to the program event; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for making the recording corresponding to the program event in the means for storing as received from the means for receiving the program.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00036" num="00036">
<claim-text>36. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, wherein the occurrence of the incident is within a time period selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>prior to the broadcast start time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>from about the broadcast start time to about the broadcast end time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>after the broadcast end time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>prior to a completion of making the recording;</claim-text>
<claim-text>before the playback;</claim-text>
<claim-text>during the playback; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>prior to a completion of the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00037" num="00037">
<claim-text>37. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00036">claim 36</claim-ref>, wherein during the time period prior to the broadcast start time, the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>a change in at least one of the broadcast start time, the broadcast end time, and the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>video signal failure on the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>failure in equipment for processing the video signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>unavailability of memory to record the program in the recording corresponding to the program event; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a change to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00038" num="00038">
<claim-text>38. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00036">claim 36</claim-ref>, wherein during the time period from about the broadcast start time to about the broadcast end time, the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>a change in at least one of the broadcast start time, the broadcast end time, and the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>video signal failure on the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>failure in equipment for processing the video signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>unavailability of memory to record the program in the recording;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a logical deletion of the recording; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a change to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00039" num="00039">
<claim-text>39. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00036">claim 36</claim-ref>, wherein during the time period selected from the group consisting of from after the completion of making the recording and prior to the completion of the playback, the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>failure in equipment for the playback of the program from the recording; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a logical deletion of the recording.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00040" num="00040">
<claim-text>40. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, wherein the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>video signal failure on the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>equipment failure; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>receipt of notice that broadcast of the program on the broadcast channel is not in accordance with the program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00041" num="00041">
<claim-text>41. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00040">claim 40</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the video signal failure on the broadcast channel occurs at the time period selected from the group consisting of before a completion of making the recording and before a completion of the playback; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the equipment failure occurs at the time period selected from the group consisting of before a completion of making the recording and before a completion of the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00042" num="00042">
<claim-text>42. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, wherein the means, upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the play back, for outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>means for an audio output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for a visual output; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for a transmission by the messaging service of a respective message including the diagnostic descriptive of the incident to each of a plurality of addresses specified by contact information provided to the messaging service by the viewer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00043" num="00043">
<claim-text>43. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, wherein the means for the transmission of the message to the address is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>means for transmitting the message to a printer having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transmitting the message for output on a television receiver having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transmitting the message in a facsimile transmission on a circuit switched network to a facsimile machine associated with a facsimile telephone number corresponding to the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transmitting the message on a circuit switched network in a telephone transmission to a telephone number corresponding to the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transmitting the message on a packet switched network to a network resource having the address as a publication to a Web site hosted by the network resource;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transmitting the message in packets on a packet switched network to a network resource having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transmitting the message as email to an email address at an email server serving the address; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transmitting the message in an SMS transmission to a mobile pager on a page channel.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00044" num="00044">
<claim-text>44. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, wherein the incident likely to prevent the playback is an unsuccessful making of the recording according to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00045" num="00045">
<claim-text>45. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, wherein the incident likely to prevent the playback is an unsuccessful playback of the recording.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00046" num="00046">
<claim-text>46. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, wherein the means, upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the playback, for outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident comprises, for each said incident, writing an entry to a history file for the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00047" num="00047">
<claim-text>47. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00046">claim 46</claim-ref>, wherein the means, upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the playback, for outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident further comprises outputting the history file.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00048" num="00048">
<claim-text>48. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref>, wherein the means for receiving a request to create a program event comprises means for selecting an entry in an EPG corresponding to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00049" num="00049">
<claim-text>49. The client device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00048">claim 48</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the EPG comprises a plurality of said entries each corresponding to respective said programs on the broadcast channel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the means for selecting the entry in the EPG further comprises means for selecting one said entry of said plurality of entries in the EPG.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00050" num="00050">
<claim-text>50. One or more computer-readable media comprising computer executable instructions that, when executed, direct a client device to:
<claim-text>receive a request to create a program event to record a program from a broadcast start time through a broadcast end time on a broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>create the program event to record the program in a recording for a playback of the program from the recording;</claim-text>
<claim-text>and</claim-text>
<claim-text>upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent the playback, output a diagnostic descriptive of the incident, which includes the diagnostic descriptive being communicated to a messaging service configured to transmit the diagnostic descriptive as a message to an address specified by a viewer, wherein:
<claim-text>the diagnostic descriptive describes one or more corrective actions for a recipient of the diagnostic descriptive to undertake to resolve the incident and permit the playback.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00051" num="00051">
<claim-text>51. One or more computer-readable media as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00050">claim 50</claim-ref>, further comprising computer executable instructions that, when executed, upon an occurrence of an incident likely to prevent making the recording of the program corresponding to the program event, direct the client device to output a diagnostic descriptive of the incident.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00052" num="00052">
<claim-text>52. One or more computer-readable media as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00050">claim 50</claim-ref>, wherein the incident is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>video signal failure on the broadcast channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>equipment failure; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>receipt of notice that broadcast of the program on the broadcast channel is not in accordance with the program event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00053" num="00053">
<claim-text>53. One or more computer-readable media as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00050">claim 50</claim-ref>, wherein the transmission of the message to the address is selected from the group consisting of:
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a printer having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for output on a television receiver having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a facsimile transmission for a circuit switched network for a facsimile machine associated with a facsimile telephone number corresponding to the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message in a telephone transmission for a circuit switched network to a telephone number corresponding to the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for a packet switched network to a network resource having the address as a publication to a Web site hosted by the network resource;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message in packets for a packet switched network to a network resource having the address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message as email for an email address at an email server serving the address; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the message for an SMS transmission to a mobile pager on a page channel.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00054" num="00054">
<claim-text>54. One or more computer-readable media as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00050">claim 50</claim-ref>, wherein the incident likely to prevent the playback is an unsuccessful making of the recording according to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00055" num="00055">
<claim-text>55. One or more computer-readable media as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00050">claim 50</claim-ref>, wherein the incident likely to prevent the playback is an unsuccessful playback of the recording.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00056" num="00056">
<claim-text>56. One or more computer-readable media as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00050">claim 50</claim-ref>, wherein the outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident comprises, for each said incident, writing an entry to a history file for the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00057" num="00057">
<claim-text>57. One or more computer-readable media as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00056">claim 56</claim-ref>, wherein the outputting a diagnostic descriptive of the incident further comprises outputting the history file.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00058" num="00058">
<claim-text>58. One or more computer-readable media as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00050">claim 50</claim-ref>, further comprises computer executable instructions that, when executed, direct the client device to logically erase at least a portion of a memory to record the recording of the program corresponding to the program event.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
