<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297853-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297853</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11144822</doc-number>
<date>20050606</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>221</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>10</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 844223</main-classification>
<further-classification> 844221</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Angle adjusting cymbal base assembly</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6570075</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lombardi</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 84421</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7102066</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chang</name>
<date>20060900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 844221</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 844223</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 844221</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 844222</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 84421</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060272477</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061207</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Liao</last-name>
<first-name>Tsun-Chi</first-name>
<address>
<street>1F, No.7, Lane 545, Sec. 2, Jyungong Rd.</street>
<city>Beitun District, Taichung City</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Birch, Stewart, Kolasch &amp; Birch, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Donovan</last-name>
<first-name>Lincoln</first-name>
<department>2837</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Qin</last-name>
<first-name>Jianchun</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An angle adjusting cymbal base assembly includes a base body provided with two sliding grooves. A sliding element is put in two sliding grooves and provided with a wedge-shaped pushing portion located at a side thereof. The sliding element is provided with a stopper located at the other side thereof. An adjusting screw bolt is locked to the base body and pushes the other side of the sliding element. The sliding element can be pushed by turning the adjusting screw bolt. The base body is provided with a central pillar connected to a passive element. The passive element is provided with an inclined portion pushed by the pushing portion, is at predetermined degree of inclination, and is pivotally connected to the base body, whereby a lower cymbal is stably supported, the inclined direction does not be change if the lower cymbal is struck, and the inclined direction is easily adjusted.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="218.86mm" wi="112.69mm" file="US07297853-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="207.86mm" wi="103.55mm" file="US07297853-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="152.99mm" wi="103.63mm" file="US07297853-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="238.08mm" wi="116.76mm" file="US07297853-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="168.66mm" wi="116.59mm" file="US07297853-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="170.35mm" wi="116.08mm" file="US07297853-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="140.72mm" wi="86.53mm" file="US07297853-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to an angle adjusting cymbal base assembly, and more particularly to an angle adjusting cymbal base assembly capable of adjusting the degree of inclination of a lower cymbal, whereby the lower cymbal is inclined, the lower cymbal is much stably supported, the inclined direction does not be change even if the lower cymbal is struck, the inclined direction is easily adjusted, and the appearance is beautiful.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Conventional cymbal base assembly is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> PRIOR ART and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> PRIOR ART, and includes a conical base body <b>1</b>. The base body <b>1</b> is provided with a protrudent edge <b>2</b> disposed at the bottom thereof. The protrudent edge <b>2</b> is put around and connected to the top of a hollow main rod of a cymbal stand (not shown). The base body <b>1</b> is provided with a tubal rod <b>3</b> disposed at the central top thereof. A metal covering plate <b>4</b> is put around and connected to the tubal rod <b>3</b> for sealing the top of the base body <b>1</b>. Also, a damping gasket <b>5</b> is put around the tubal rod <b>3</b> and connected to the metal covering plate <b>4</b>. A lower cymbal <b>6</b> is straddled on and connected to the damping gasket <b>5</b>. A screw bolt <b>7</b> is fastened upward in a side of the base body <b>1</b>, and an end of the screw bolt <b>7</b> pushes a side of the bottom surface of the covering plate <b>4</b>, whereby the covering plate <b>4</b> is at an angle, and the lower cymbal <b>6</b> which is straddled above the covering plate <b>4</b> is also straddled above the base body <b>1</b> at an angle. When an upper cymbal strikes the lower cymbal <b>6</b>, they can generate clearly sweet sound effect.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The bottom of the covering plate <b>4</b> is inclined because the screw bolt <b>7</b> pushes the bottom of the covering plate <b>4</b> upward. However, the side of the bottom of the covering plate <b>4</b> only pushed at a point by the screw bolt <b>7</b>. When the upper cymbal strikes the lower cymbal <b>6</b>, it is easy that the vibration changes the direction of the lower cymbal <b>6</b>. Thus, conventional cymbal base assembly is unstable, and the supporting force of the screw bolt <b>7</b> is not enough.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Accordingly, there exists a need for a cymbal base assembly to solve the above-mentioned disadvantages.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is an object of the present invention provides an angle adjusting cymbal base assembly to solve the above-mentioned disadvantages.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In order to achieve the foregoing objects, the present invention provides an angle adjusting cymbal base assembly including a base body provided with two sliding grooves. A sliding element is put in two sliding grooves and provided with a wedge-shaped pushing portion located at a side thereof. The sliding element is provided with a stopper located at the other side thereof and being vertical upward. An adjusting screw bolt is locked to the base body and pushes the other side of the sliding element. The sliding element can be pushed by turning the adjusting screw bolt. The base body is provided with a central pillar connected to a passive element. The passive element is provided with an inclined portion pushed by a pushing portion of the sliding element, is at predetermined degree of inclination, and is pivotally connected to the side of the base body, whereby a lower cymbal is inclined, the lower cymbal is much stably supported, the inclined direction does not be change even if the lower cymbal is struck, the inclined direction is easily adjusted, and the appearance is beautiful.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Further scope of the applicability of the present invention will become apparent from the detailed description given hereinafter. However, it should be understood that the detailed description and specific examples, while indicating preferred embodiments of the invention, are given by way of illustration only, since various changes and modifications within the spirit and scope of the invention will become apparent to those skilled in the art from this detailed description.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention will become more fully understood from the detailed description given hereinbelow and the accompanying drawings which are given by way of illustration only, and thus are not limitative of the present invention, and wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> PRIOR ART is an exploded perspective view of a conventional cymbal base assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> PRIOR ART is a cross sectional view showing the combination of a conventional cymbal base assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an exploded perspective view of an angle adjusting cymbal base assembly according to the first embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> is a cross sectional view showing the combination of an angle adjusting cymbal base assembly according to the first embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> is a cross sectional view showing the motion of the angle adjusting cymbal base assembly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a top plan view of an angle adjusting cymbal base assembly according to the first embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, it depicts an angle adjusting cymbal base assembly of the prevent invention. The cymbal base assembly includes a metal base body <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The base body <b>10</b> is provided with a protrudent tubal pillar <b>11</b> disposed at the bottom thereof. The tubal pillar <b>11</b> is put around and connected to the top of a hollow vertical rod <b>20</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>) of a cymbal stand (not shown). The base body <b>10</b> is provided with a central pillar <b>12</b> disposed at the top thereof. The base body <b>10</b> is provided with a through circular tube <b>13</b> located at the center thereof: The circular tube <b>13</b> is adapted for providing a pulling rod <b>21</b> to pass through the circular tube <b>13</b>, wherein the pulling rod <b>21</b> is disposed at the center of the cymbal stand. The top of the pulling rod <b>21</b> can be connected to an upper cymbal (not shown). When the pulling rod <b>21</b> is pulled downward, the upper cymbal is driven to strike a lower cymbal <b>22</b>. Also, the base body <b>10</b> is provided with two sliding grooves <b>14</b> disposed in the top surface thereof, and the base body <b>10</b> is provided with a pivoting portion <b>17</b> expanding from a side of the sliding groove <b>14</b>. The bottom of a U-shaped sliding element <b>15</b> can be put in two sliding grooves <b>14</b>, and the hollow portion of the sliding element <b>15</b> clips two sides of the central pillar <b>12</b>. Also, the sliding element <b>15</b> is provided with a pair of wedge-shaped pushing portion <b>151</b> located at a side thereof, wherein the inner surface of the pushing portion <b>151</b> is inclined downward. The sliding element <b>15</b> is provided with a stopper <b>152</b> located at the other side thereof, wherein the stopper <b>152</b> is vertical upward. The stopper <b>152</b> is provided with a through hole, the rear end of an adjusting screw bolt <b>16</b> passes through the through hole, and the rear end of the adjusting screw bolt <b>16</b> is locked by a screw nut. The outer diameter of the rear end of the adjusting screw bolt <b>16</b> is less than that of the main body of the adjusting screw bolt <b>16</b> so as to form a shoulder <b>161</b>. The shoulder <b>161</b> pushes the outer wall of the stopper <b>152</b> of the sliding element <b>15</b>. The adjusting screw bolt <b>16</b> is locked to a screw hole of the pivoting portion <b>17</b> of the base body <b>10</b>, and is parallel with the sliding grooves <b>14</b> of the base body <b>10</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">A passive element <b>30</b> is similar to a hollow and circular housing for covering and sealing the base body <b>10</b>. The passive element <b>30</b> is provided with an ear portion <b>31</b> located at a side thereof. A bolt <b>32</b> is passed through the ear portion <b>31</b>, whereby the passive element <b>30</b> is pivotally connected to the pivoting portion <b>17</b> of the base body <b>10</b> transversely. Also, the passive element <b>30</b> is provided with an inclined portion <b>33</b> located inside the top wall thereof. The inclined portion <b>33</b> cooperates with the pushing portion <b>151</b> of the sliding element <b>15</b>, whereby the inclined portion <b>33</b> is pushed by the pushing portion <b>151</b> of the wedge-shaped sliding element <b>15</b>, shown <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref>. The top surface of the passive element <b>30</b> is inclined, and further the lower cymbal <b>22</b> which is straddled above the top surface of the passive element <b>30</b> is inclined. Also, a damping pad <b>40</b> is disposed between the passive element <b>30</b> and the lower cymbal <b>22</b> for stopping the vibration transmitted from the lower cymbal <b>22</b>. More important, the passive element <b>30</b> which is located under the bottom of the lower cymbal <b>22</b> can be supported by the pair of pushing portions <b>151</b> of the sliding element <b>15</b> parallel to each other, thereby preventing the lower cymbal <b>22</b> from the vibration and change of direction when the lower cymbal <b>22</b> is struck, and solving the problem of supporting force. Specially, the passive element <b>30</b> is driven by the adjusting screw bolt <b>16</b>, and thus the passive element <b>30</b> is not shaken when the upper cymbal strikes the lower cymbal <b>22</b>. The passive element <b>30</b> which is supported by the pushing portions <b>151</b> of the sliding element <b>15</b> is kept at the predetermined degree of inclination. In other words, the lower cymbal <b>22</b> which is straddled above the passive element <b>30</b> can be adjusted at the predetermined degree of inclination, and the lower cymbal <b>22</b> is pushed by the pushing portion <b>151</b> of the sliding element <b>15</b>, thereby preventing the lower cymbal <b>22</b> from the vibration and change of inclined direction.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">It is noted that the passive element <b>30</b> of the prevent invention is a smooth circular housing for completely accommodating the base body <b>10</b> into an inner space thereof, and thus the appearance of the passive element <b>30</b> is simple and beautiful. Even if the degree of inclination of the passive element <b>30</b> is requested to change, the sliding element <b>15</b> disposed in the base body <b>10</b> can be pushed and moved by directly turning the adjusting screw bolt <b>16</b>, i.e. the supporting position of inclined surface of the pushing portions <b>151</b> depends on the degree of inclination of the passive element <b>30</b>. The operation is very convenient and quick.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Although the invention has been explained in relation to its preferred embodiment, it is not used to restrain the invention. It is to be understood that many other possible modifications and variations can be made by those skilled in the art without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as hereinafter claimed.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An angle adjusting cymbal base assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a base body having a bottom disposed at a top of a hollow vertical rod of a cymbal stand, wherein the base body is provided with two sliding grooves disposed in the top surface thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sliding element put in two sliding grooves, and provided with a wedge-shaped pushing portion located at a side thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjusting screw bolt pushing the other side of the sliding element, and locked to a pivoting portion of the base body; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a passive element pivotally connected to the pivoting portion, covering and sealing the base body, and provided with an inclined portion located inside a top wail thereof, wherein the inclined portion is pushed by the pushing pardon of the sliding element, and the base body is provided with a central pillar disposed at the top thereof, whereby the passive element passes through the central pillar,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the sliding element is provided with a stopper located at the other side thereof and being vertical upward, the stopper is provided with a through hole, a rear end of the adjusting screw bolt passes through the through hole, the rear end of the adjusting screw bolt is locked by a screw nut, the outer diameter of the rear end of the adjusting screw bolt is less than that of a main body of the adjusting screw bolt so as to form a shoulder, and the shoulder pushes an outer wall of the stopper of the sliding element.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The angle adjusting cymbal base assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the base body is provided with a through circular tube located at the center thereof, the circular tube is adapted for providing a pulling rod to pass through the circular tube, the pulling rod is disposed at the center of the cymbal stand, a top of the pulling rod is connected to an upper cymbal, the upper cymbal is driven to strike a lower cymbal when the pulling rod is pulled downward, and the angle adjusting cymbal base assembly further comprises a damping pad disposed between the passive element and the lower cymbal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The angle adjusting cymbal base assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the inner surface of the wedge-shaped pushing portion is inclined downward.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
