<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297006-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297006</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10578261</doc-number>
<date>20031113</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>12</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 77</main-classification>
<further-classification>439 67</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Flexible connector with printed circuit lines encircling two axes</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5205750</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Darrow et al.</name>
<date>19930400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439 77</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5330365</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Leeson</name>
<date>19940700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439 77</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5362243</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Huss et al.</name>
<date>19941100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439 761</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6484395</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Marcus et al.</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6811431</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hsieh</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439495</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2 322 504</doc-number>
<date>19980800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002 111138</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO 02 102224</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 64</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 65</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 67</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 77</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070082528</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070412</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Emme</last-name>
<first-name>Niels Peter</first-name>
<address>
<city>Copenhagen</city>
<country>DK</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>DK</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>DK</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Banner &amp; Witcoff, Ltd.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nokia Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Espoo</city>
<country>FI</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Khiem</first-name>
<department>2839</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/IB03/05124</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20031113</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20060504</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2005/041369</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20050526</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The invention relates to a flexible connector formed from a single layer flexible film with printed circuit lines. The flexible connector comprises a first connection means, a second connection means, a first part extending from the first connection means, wherein the first part is adapted to form a coiled part encircling a first axis, a second part extending from the second connection means, wherein the second part is adapted to form a coiled part encircling a second axis, and a third part interconnecting the first and second parts. The invention further relates to a method of manufacturing such a flexible connector, and a communication apparatus provided with such a flexible connector and comprising a first member and a second member, wherein the first and second members are mechanically connected by a two-axis hinge, and wherein circuitry of the first and second members are connected by said flexible connector.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="174.41mm" wi="157.48mm" file="US07297006-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="183.22mm" wi="157.65mm" file="US07297006-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="195.50mm" wi="84.07mm" file="US07297006-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="230.04mm" wi="179.07mm" file="US07297006-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="231.56mm" wi="161.21mm" file="US07297006-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="213.61mm" wi="166.79mm" file="US07297006-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a National Stage application of PCT application PCT/IB2003/005124 filed Nov. 13, 2003, which was published in English under PCT Article 21(2) on May 26, 2005. This application is incorporated herein by reference in its entirety.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a flexible connector, a method of manufacturing a flexible connector, and a communication apparatus comprising a flexible connector.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">UK patent application no. GB 2322504 A discloses a tri-fold cellular telephone including a top housing portion, a center housing portion, and a bottom housing portion, where the portions are rotably coupled to each other via hinges. One portion includes a display, another includes a keypad, and still another includes a speaker and a battery. FIG. 8 in GB 2322504 A illustrates wires, carried through one of the hinges between the portions, for electrical interconnection of the foldable members of the cellular telephone. GB 2322504 is an illustrative example of a need for flexible connection lines between members in a cellular telephone. Other examples of elecronic devices needing this kind of flexible interconnections are video and digital cameras, lap-top computers, PDA:s, and calculators.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Japanese patent application no. JP 2002-111138 A discloses a flexible printed board with a pair of terminals provided at the ends of the board, and wirings between the terminals. The wirings are formed into two parts having an empty space between them and are provided with bending pleats such that the flexible printed board can be folded up along the bending pleats.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The present invention is based on the understanding that a lead-through of a electrical connector through a two-axes hinge needs to be able to take up movements caused both when the members of the communication apparatus are pivoted around a first axis, and when the members of the communication apparatus are pivoted around a second axis. In this context, the first and second axes are essentially perpendicular to each other. The present invention is further based on the understanding that a plurality of electrical connection lines need to be provided between circuitry of the members of the communication apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The above objects, advantages and features together with numerous other objects, advantages and features, which will become evident from the detailed description below, are obtained according to a first aspect of the present invention by a flexible connector formed from a single layer flexible film with printed circuit lines, said flexible connector comprising a first connection means and a second connection means, wherein said flexible connector further comprises</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">a first part extending from the first connection means, wherein said first part is adapted to form a coiled part encircling a first axis;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">a second part extending from the second connection means, wherein said second part is adapted to form a coiled part encircling a second axis; and</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">a third part interconnecting said first and second parts.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The term “first”, “second”, and “third” should in this context be construed as terms for differentiating between elements and not be construed as a timing consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The first coiled part encircling the first axis will take up movements caused by pivoting around said first axis, and the second coiled part will take up movements caused by pivoting around said second axis. Thus, mechanical stress on the flexible connector is reduced. The flexible connector will enable lead-through through a two-axis hinge.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Said first, second and third parts of the flexible connector according to the first aspect of the present invention may comprise two or more strips having essentially the same shape, and intermediate parts, each having a first and a second dividing line, wherein said first and second dividing lines are parallel, said intermediate parts being arranged between each end of said strips to enable folding along the dividing lines such that said two or more strips form overlapping layers after folding. This feature will provide more connection lines as more connection lines are demanded, when an increase of the total width of the strip is unfeasable, and a decrease of the width of each connection line is inappropriate. Said intermediate parts may be provided with an adhesive. The adhesive will ensure that the single layer flexible film does not unfold while storing, transporting, handling or using the flexible connector. Said adhesive may be a pressure-sensitive adhesive. This is advantageous, while the folded parts are exposed to pressure during manufacturing anyway.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Said second part of the flexible connector according to the first aspect of the present invention may comprise a first elongated sub-part, a second curved sub-part, and a third elongated sub-part, which third elongated sub-part is adapted to form said coiled part.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Said third part of the flexible connector according to the first aspect of the present invention may comprise a first curved sub-part, a second elongated sub-part, and a third curved sub-part.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The above objects, advantages and features together with numerous other objects, advantages and features, which will become evident from the detailed description below, are obtained according to a second aspect of the present invention by a method for manufacturing a flexible connector, said flexible connector comprising a first connection means and a second connection means, wherein said flexible connector further comprises</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">a first part extending from the first connection means, wherein said first part is adapted to form a coiled part encircling a first axis;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">a second part extending from the second connection means, wherein said second part is adapted to form a coiled part encircling a second axis; and</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">a third part interconnecting said first and second parts, the method comprising the steps of:</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">printing said first and second connection means, and at least one strip between said first and second connection means provided with connection lines between the first and the second connection means, on a single layer flexible film, wherein said at least one strip forms said first, second and third parts; and</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">cutting out said printed flexible film.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The term “first”, “second”, and “third” should in this context be construed as terms for differentiating between elements and not be construed as a timing consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Said first, second and third parts of the flexible connector according to the second aspect of the present invention may comprise two or more strips having essentially the same shape, and intermediate parts, each having a first and a second dividing line, wherein said first and second dividing lines are parallel, said intermediate parts being arranged between each end of said strips, and said method may further comprise folding along the dividing lines such that said two or more strips form overlapping layers after folding. The method may further comprise providing said intermediate parts with an adhesive. Said adhesive may be a pressure sensitive adhesive, wherein said folding may further comprise applying a pressure on folded parts to activate said pressure sensitive adhesive.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The above objects, advantages and features together with numerous other objects, advantages and features, which will become evident from the detailed description below, are obtained according to a third aspect of the present invention by a communication apparatus comprising a first member and a second member, wherein said first and second members are mechanically connected by a two-axis hinge, said communication apparatus further comprising a flexible connector formed from a single layer flexible film with printed circuit lines, said flexible connector comprising a first connection means adapted to be connected to circuitry in the first member of said communication apparatus, and a second connection means adapted to be connected to circuitry in the second member of said communication apparatus,</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">wherein said flexible connector further comprises</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">a first part extending from the first connection means, wherein said first part form a coiled part encircling a first axis of said two-axes hinge;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">a second part extending from the second connection means, wherein said second part form a coiled part encircling a second axis of said two-axes hinge; and</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">a third part interconnecting said first and second parts.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The term “first”, “second”, and “third” should in this context be construed as terms for differentiating between elements and not be construed as a timing consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Said first, second and third parts of the flexible connector according to the third aspect of the present invention may comprise two or more strips having essentially the same shape, and intermediate parts, each having a first and a second dividing line, wherein said first and second dividing lines are parallel, said intermediate parts being arranged between each end of said strips to enable folding along the dividing lines such that said two or more strips form overlapping layers after folding. Said intermediate parts may be provided with an adhesive. Said adhesive may be a pressure sensitive adhesive.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Said second part of the flexible connector according to the third aspect of the present invention may comprise a first elongated sub-part, a second curved sub-part, and a third elongated sub-part, which third elongated sub-part is adapted to form said coiled part.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Said third part of the flexible connector according to the third aspect of the present invention may comprise a first curved sub-part, a second elongated sub-part, and a third curved sub-part.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b> and <b>3</b> show a communication apparatus comprising two members hinged to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a flexible connector.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a flexible connector comprising multiple strips.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a perspective view of the flexible connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 and 8</figref> show folding of the flexible connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows the flexible connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5-8</figref> folded from a single layer flexible film to a multi-layer structure.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows the flexible connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> as applied in a two-axis hinge.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF A PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In the following description of a preferred embodiment, reference is made to the accompanying drawings which form a part hereof, and in which is shown by way of illustration a preferred embodiment in which the invention may be practised. It is to be understood that other embodiments may be utilized and that structural and functional modifications may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b> and <b>3</b> show a communication apparatus <b>1</b> comprising two members <b>3</b>, <b>5</b> hinged to each other. The members can be pivoted around two axes by means of a two-axes hinge <b>7</b>. A flexible connector <b>9</b> is connected between first circuitry, e.g. a first printed circuit board (PCB), of the first member <b>3</b> of the communication apparatus <b>1</b> and second circuitry, e.g. a second PCB, of the second member <b>5</b> of the communication apparatus <b>1</b>. The flexible connector <b>9</b> is provided to connect electrical signals to or from the first circuitry of the first member <b>3</b> of the communication apparatus <b>1</b> to the second circuitry of the second member <b>5</b> of the communication apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a flexible connector <b>401</b>, provided with a first connection means <b>403</b> which is suited to be attached to first circuitry. The connector is further provided with a second connection means <b>405</b> which is suited to be attached to second circuitry. A strip <b>407</b> provided with one or more connection lines (not shown) is arranged between the first connection means <b>403</b> and the second connection means <b>405</b>. A first part of the strip <b>409</b> is extending from the first connection means <b>403</b> to a second curved part <b>411</b> forming a bend from which the strip <b>407</b> extends in a third part <b>413</b> essentially perpendicular to the first part <b>409</b>. The strip <b>407</b> is then provided with a fourth curved part <b>415</b> forming a bend from which the strip extends in a fifth part <b>417</b> essentially perpendicular to the third part <b>413</b>, and essentially parallel to the first part <b>409</b>. The strip <b>407</b> is further provided with a sixth curved part <b>419</b> forming a bend from which the strip <b>407</b> extends in a seventh part <b>421</b> essentially perpendicular to the fifth part <b>417</b>, and essentially parallel to the third part <b>413</b>. The seventh part <b>421</b> of the strip connects to the second connection means <b>405</b>. Note that the description above of the flexible connector <b>401</b> only applies when the flexible connector <b>401</b> is flattened out and is regarded in one plane.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The flexible connector <b>401</b> is preferably made of a flexible film material. Preferably, the first and second connection means <b>403</b>, <b>405</b> are made a bit stiffer than the rest of the flexible connector <b>401</b> to ease application at e.g. a PCB. The strip <b>407</b> is preferably provided with a multitude of connection lines, e.g. 20 connection lines each with a width of 100 μm, and a space with a width of 75 μm between each connection line, i.e. a distance of 175 μm from the center of one connection line to the center of next connection line.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">As more connection lines are demanded, when an increase of the total width of the strip is unfeasable, and a decrease of the width of each connection line is inappropriate, there is a need for a multi-layer structure.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a flexible connector <b>501</b> provided with a first connection means <b>503</b> which is suited to be attached to first circuitry. The connector is further provided with a second connection means <b>505</b> which is suited to be attached to second circuitry. A first strip <b>507</b> provided with one or more connection lines (not shown) is arranged between the first connection means <b>503</b> and the second connection means <b>505</b>. The first strip <b>507</b> is essentially of the same shape as the strip of the flexible connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The flexible connector <b>501</b> is further provided with a second strip <b>509</b> and a third strip <b>511</b>. The second and third strips <b>509</b>, <b>511</b> are essentially shaped like the first strip <b>507</b>. The strips <b>507</b>, <b>509</b>, <b>511</b> have preferably the same width, e.g. 8 mm. Alternatively, the strips <b>507</b>, <b>509</b>, <b>511</b> have different widths, e.g. 10 mm for the first strip <b>507</b>, 8 mm for the second strip <b>509</b>, and 6 mm for the third strip <b>511</b>. The flexible connector <b>501</b> is provided with intermediate parts <b>529</b>, <b>531</b>, <b>533</b>, <b>535</b> between each strip <b>507</b>, <b>509</b>, <b>511</b>. The intermediate parts <b>529</b>, <b>531</b>, <b>533</b>, <b>535</b> each have a first dividing line <b>513</b>, <b>515</b>, <b>521</b>, <b>523</b>, and a second dividing line <b>517</b>, <b>519</b>, <b>525</b>, <b>527</b> to the neighbouring strips <b>507</b>, <b>509</b>, <b>511</b>. The first and second dividing lines <b>513</b>, <b>515</b>, <b>517</b>, <b>519</b>, <b>521</b>, <b>523</b>, <b>525</b>, <b>527</b> are parallel. The flexible connector is adapted to be folded along the plurality of dividing lines <b>513</b>, <b>515</b>, <b>517</b>, <b>519</b>, <b>521</b>, <b>523</b>, <b>525</b>, <b>527</b>. It is preferrable to apply an adhesive on the intermediate parts <b>529</b>, <b>531</b>, <b>533</b>, <b>535</b> to keep the shape of the flexible connector after folding, which will be described in detail below. Note that the description above of the flexible connector <b>501</b> only applies when the flexible connector <b>501</b> is flattened out and is regarded in one plane.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a perspective view of the flexible connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The flexible connector <b>601</b> is provided with dividing lines <b>613</b>, <b>615</b>, <b>617</b>, <b>619</b>, <b>621</b>, <b>623</b>, <b>625</b>, <b>627</b>, which are parallel. This will enable a parallel displacement of the third strip <b>611</b> to a position above the second strip <b>609</b>, and then a parallel displacement of the second and third strips <b>609</b>, <b>611</b> to a position above the first strip <b>607</b>. Thus, said first, second and third strips <b>607</b>, <b>609</b>, <b>611</b> will overlap after folding.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 and 8</figref> show folding of the flexible connector <b>701</b>, <b>801</b>. Note that adhesive on the areas (not shown) on the intermediate parts <b>729</b>, <b>731</b>, <b>733</b>, <b>735</b> now will stick to connection means <b>703</b>, <b>705</b> and strip <b>709</b>, and will thus fix the folded parts. Pressure sensitive adhesive is preferably used, while the folded parts are exposed to pressure during manufacturing anyway. The adhesive will ensure that the single layer flexible film does not unfold while storing, transporting, handling or using the flexible connector.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows a flexible connector <b>901</b> folded from a single layer flexible film, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5-8</figref>, to a multi-layer structure, provided with a first connection means <b>903</b> which is suited to be attached to first circuitry. The flexible connector <b>901</b> is further provided with a second connection means <b>905</b> which is suited to be attached to second circuitry. First, second and third strips <b>906</b>, <b>907</b>, <b>908</b> are each provided with one or more connection lines (not shown), and are arranged between the first connection means <b>903</b> and the second connection means <b>905</b>. A first part <b>909</b> of each of the strips is extending from the first connection means <b>903</b>, wherein the second and third strips are connected via intermediate parts <b>931</b>, <b>935</b>, to a second curved part <b>911</b> forming a bend from which the strips <b>906</b>, <b>907</b>, <b>908</b> extend in a third part <b>913</b> essentially perpendicular to the first part <b>909</b>. The strips <b>906</b>, <b>907</b>, <b>908</b> are then provided with a fourth curved part <b>915</b> forming a bend from which the strips extend in a fifth part <b>917</b> essentially perpendicular to the third part <b>913</b>, and essentially parallel to the first part <b>909</b>. The strips <b>906</b>, <b>907</b>, <b>908</b> are further provided with a sixth curved part <b>919</b> forming a bend from which the strips <b>906</b>, <b>907</b>, <b>908</b> extend in a seventh part <b>921</b> essentially perpendicular to the fifth part <b>917</b>, and essentially parallel to the third part <b>913</b>. The seventh part <b>921</b> of the strips connects to the second connection means <b>905</b>, wherein the second and third strips are connected via the intermediate parts <b>929</b>, <b>933</b>. Said intermediate parts <b>929</b>, <b>931</b>, <b>933</b>, <b>935</b> each have a first dividing line and a second dividing line to the neighbouring strips <b>906</b>, <b>907</b>, <b>908</b>. The first and second dividing lines are parallel. Note that the description above of the flexible connector <b>901</b> only applies when the flexible connector <b>901</b> is flattened out and is regarded in one plane.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The flexible connector <b>901</b> is preferably made of a flexible film material. Preferably, the first and second connection means <b>903</b>, <b>905</b> are made a bit stiffer than the rest of the flexible connector <b>901</b> to ease application at circuitry. The strips <b>906</b>, <b>907</b>, <b>908</b> are preferably each provided with a multitude of connection lines, e.g. 20 connection lines, each with a width of 100 μm, and a space with a width of 75 μm between each connection line, i.e. a distance of 175 μm from the center of one connection line to the center of next connection line.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Alternatively, it is preferable to provide one strip with only one connection line, e.g. a full width copper layer to enhance performance related to electromagnetic compatibility and/or electrostatic discharges. Preferably, the first strip <b>906</b> is provided with one full copper layer, since it has the shortest path between the connectors <b>903</b>, <b>905</b>, and therefore normally, provides best performance related to electromagnetic compatibility and/or electrostatic discharges. This is true in many applications, but for some applications it may be more beneficiary to use another of the strips for this purpose.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows the flexible connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> as applied in a two-axes hinge (not shown) of e.g. a communication apparatus. The flexible connector <b>1001</b> provided with a first connection means <b>1003</b> which is suited to be attached to first circuitry. The flexible connector <b>1001</b> is further provided with a second connection means <b>1005</b> which is suited to be attached to second circuitry. First, second and third strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> are each provided with one or more connection lines (not shown), and are arranged between the first connection means <b>1003</b> and the second connection means <b>1005</b>. A first part <b>1009</b> of each of the strips is extending from the first connection means <b>1003</b>, wherein the second and third strips are connected via intermediate parts <b>1031</b>, <b>1035</b>, wherein the first part <b>1009</b> forms a coiled sub-part <b>1010</b> encircling a first axis A-A. Preferably, the lengths of the first part <b>1009</b> of the different strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> are slightly different to enable forming of the coiled sub-part <b>1010</b>, since the different strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> will have slightly different curvature at the coiled sub-part <b>1010</b>. A second curved part <b>1011</b> forms a bend from which each of the strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> extends in a third part <b>1013</b> in a direction of the first axis A-A towards a second axis B-B. The third part <b>1013</b> forms a curve, which is possible due to its flexible nature, such that it at the end, next to a fourth curved part <b>1015</b>, is essentially parallel to the second axis B-B. The fourth curved part <b>1015</b> forms a bend from which the strips extend in a fifth part <b>1017</b>, wherein the fifth part <b>1017</b> forms a coiled sub-part <b>1018</b> encircling the second axis B-B. Preferably, the lengths of the fifth part <b>1017</b> of the different strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> are slightly different to enable forming of the coiled sub-part <b>1018</b>, since the different strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> will have slightly different curvature at the coiled sub-part <b>1018</b>. The strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> are further provided with a sixth curved part <b>1019</b> forming a bend from which the strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> extend in a seventh part <b>1021</b> in a direction essentially parallel to the second axis B-B. The seventh part <b>1021</b> of the strips connects to the second connection means <b>1005</b>, wherein the second and third strips are connected via the intermediate parts (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The flexible connector <b>1001</b> is arranged to lead through the two-axis hinge, the first connection means <b>1003</b> is attached to the first circuitry, and the first part <b>1009</b> of the pack of strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> extends into the hinge and is coiled <b>1010</b> around the first axis A-A to be able to take up movements caused when the members of the communication apparatus are pivoted around the first axis A-A. Similarily, the fifth part <b>1017</b> is coiled <b>1018</b> around the second axis B-B to take up movements caused when the members of the communication apparatus are pivoted around the second axis B-B. The seventh part <b>1021</b> of the pack of strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b> extends from the coiled part <b>1018</b>, formed by the third part <b>1021</b> of the pack of strips <b>1006</b>, <b>1007</b>, <b>1008</b>, towards the second connection means <b>1005</b>, which is attached to the second circuitry.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Thus, mechanical stress of the flexible connector is minimized as the communication apparatus is folded, unfolded, and pivoted a great number of times around axes A-A and B-B. Therefore, a reliable connection is provided between the circuitry of the members of the communication apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The preferred embodiment has three strips, but it is also possible to provide a flexible connector with one strip, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Further, it is possible to provide a flexible connector with 2, 4, 5 or more strips.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">When the flexible connector is provided with two or more strips, wherein each strip has essentially the same shape, as described for the three strip embodiment above, the flexible connector is provided with intermediate parts between each strip, each intermediate part having a first and a second dividing line. The first and second dividing lines are parallel to enable parallel displacement of the strips, analogous to the preferred embodiment. Preferably, the lengths of the first part of the different strips are slightly different to enable forming of the coiled sub-part, since the different strips will have slightly different curvature at the coiled sub-part. Preferably, the lengths of the fifth part of the different strips are slightly different to enable forming of the coiled sub-part, since the different strips will have slightly different curvature at the coiled sub-part. The different strips have preferably the same width, e.g. 8 mm. Alternatively, the different strips have different widths.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A flexible connector formed from a single layer flexible film with printed circuit lines, said flexible connector comprising a first connection means, and a second connection means, wherein said flexible connector further comprises
<claim-text>a first part extending from the first connection means, wherein said first part is adapted to form a coiled part encircling a first axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second part extending from the second connection means, wherein said second part is adapted to form a coiled part encircling a second axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third part interconnecting said first and second parts.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The flexible connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said first, second and third parts comprise two or more strips having essentially the same shape, and intermediate parts, each having a first and a second dividing line, wherein said first and second dividing lines are parallel, said intermediate parts being arranged between each end of said strips to enable folding along the dividing lines such that said two or more strips form overlapping layers after folding.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The flexible connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said intermediate parts are provided with an adhesive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The flexible connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said adhesive is a pressure sensitive adhesive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The flexible connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said second part comprises a first elongated sub-part, a second curved sub-part, and a third elongated sub-part, which third elongated sub-part is adapted to form said coiled part, and said third part comprises a first curved sub-part, a second elongated sub-part, and a third curved sub-part.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A communication apparatus comprising a first member and a second member, wherein said first and second members are mechanically connected by a two-axis hinge, said communication apparatus further comprising a flexible connector formed from a single layer flexible film with printed circuit lines, said flexible connector comprising a first connection means adapted to be connected to circuitry in the first member of said communication apparatus, and a second connection means adapted to be connected to circuitry in the second member of said communication apparatus,
<claim-text>wherein said flexible connector further comprises</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first part extending from the first connection means, wherein said first part forms a coiled part encircling a first axis of said two-axes hinge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second part extending from the second connection means, wherein said second part forms a coiled part encircling a second axis of said two-axes hinge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third part interconnecting said first and second parts.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The communication apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said first, second and third parts comprise two or more strips having essentially the same shape, and intermediate parts, each having a first and a second dividing line, wherein said first and second dividing lines are parallel, said intermediate parts being arranged between each end of said strips to enable folding along the dividing lines such that said two or more strips form overlapping layers after folding.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The communication apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said intermediate parts are provided with an adhesive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The communication apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said adhesive is a pressure sensitive adhesive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The communication apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said second part comprises a first elongated sub-part, a second curved sub-part, and a third elongated sub-part, which third elongated sub-part is adapted to form said coiled part, and said third part comprises a first curved sub-part, a second elongated sub-part, and a third curved sub-part.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
