<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298405-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298405</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10360449</doc-number>
<date>20030207</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-030916</doc-number>
<date>20020207</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>911</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>14</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348304</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Image sensing apparatus having photoelectric conversion elements and a scanning circuit</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6559889</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Tanaka et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348299</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0067416</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Yoneda et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348304</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2-69081</doc-number>
<date>19900300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>4-277985</doc-number>
<date>19921000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>5-137071</doc-number>
<date>19930600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>7-46483</doc-number>
<date>19950200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348303</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348304</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040080647</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040429</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Inui</last-name>
<first-name>Fumihiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Itano</last-name>
<first-name>Tetsuya</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ogura</last-name>
<first-name>Masanori</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Morgan &amp; Finnegan LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Canon Kabushiki Kaisha</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ye</last-name>
<first-name>Lin</first-name>
<department>2622</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Durnford-Geszvain</last-name>
<first-name>Dillon</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An image sensing apparatus which reduces noise generated by shift operation and power consumption is disclosed. The shift register of a horizontal scanning circuit is divided into a plurality of partial shift registers. Shift clock control circuits control supply of a shift clock to the partial shift registers individually for each partial shift register.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="181.02mm" wi="151.21mm" file="US07298405-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="202.18mm" wi="134.28mm" file="US07298405-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="198.71mm" wi="154.94mm" file="US07298405-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="189.31mm" wi="162.14mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298405-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="233.68mm" wi="120.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298405-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="182.20mm" wi="162.81mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298405-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="231.73mm" wi="123.02mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298405-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="188.38mm" wi="171.28mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298405-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="145.88mm" wi="120.65mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298405-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to an image sensing apparatus, camera, and information processing apparatus and, more particularly, to an image sensing apparatus having a scanning circuit for sequentially selecting a plurality of lines of a sensor array in which a plurality of photoelectric conversion elements are arrayed, and a camera and information processing apparatus which incorporate the image sensing apparatus.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Solid-state image sensing apparatuses are roughly classified into CCD sensors and MOS sensors. The CCD sensor generally has a small-noise advantage but requires high power consumption. The MOS sensor is much lower in power consumption than the CCD sensor, but generally suffers large noise. However, the MOS sensor tends to reduce noise, and is expected to attain performance equal to or higher than that of the CCD sensor in the future.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram showing the schematic arrangement of a conventional MOS sensor. The MOS sensor comprises a sensor array <b>110</b> in which many photoelectric conversion elements <b>101</b> are two-dimensionally arrayed, a vertical shift register <b>120</b> for sequentially selecting (activating) the rows of the sensor array <b>110</b>, a horizontal shift register <b>130</b> for sequentially selecting (activating) vertical transfer switches <b>131</b> to sequentially connect the vertical signal lines of the sensor array <b>110</b> to a common output line <b>132</b>, and an amplifier <b>133</b> for amplifying a signal which appears on the common output line <b>132</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In the conventional MOS sensor shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the horizontal shift register <b>130</b> is constituted by series-connecting many registers. Shift data HD input to a register on the first stage is sequentially shifted to the final stage in accordance with a horizontal shift clock HCLK. The output of each register is connected to the gate of a corresponding vertical transfer switch <b>131</b>. A plurality of switches <b>131</b> are sequentially activated one by one in accordance with the shift of shift data. The vertical shift register <b>120</b> operates almost similarly to the horizontal shift register <b>130</b> though the cycle of a vertical shift clock VCLK is different from that of the horizontal shift clock.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the conventional MOS sensor shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, noise on the power supply line is large along with the operations of the shift registers <b>120</b> and <b>130</b>. This problem becomes serious particularly in the horizontal shift register <b>130</b> which performs shift operation at a high speed. The noise problem in the conventional MOS sensor will be explained by exemplifying the horizontal shift register <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In the conventional MOS sensor, the shift clock HCLK is supplied to all the registers which constitute the horizontal shift register <b>130</b> when signals of respective rows are to be successively read out via the common signal line <b>132</b>, i.e., when the horizontal shift register <b>130</b> is to be operated. In the arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the shift clock HCLK is supplied to all the registers which constitute the horizontal shift register <b>130</b>. Every time the potential level of the shift clock HCLK changes (i.e., at each HCLK edge), a large current flows through the shift clock line, inducing noise on the power supply line or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In the above shift clock supply method, all the registers which constitute the shift register <b>130</b> are simultaneously driven, and power consumption by these registers becomes very large.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">This problem also occurs not only in an area sensor in which photoelectric conversion elements are two-dimensionally arrayed, but also in a line sensor in which photoelectric conversion elements are arrayed in a line.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The present invention has been made in consideration of the above situation, and has as its object to reduce, e.g., noise in an image sensing apparatus and/or power consumption of the image sensing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According to one aspect of the present invention, there is provided an image sensing apparatus having a scanning circuit for scanning a sensor array in which a plurality of photoelectric conversion elements are arrayed, wherein the scanning circuit comprises a shift register constituted by series-connecting a plurality of partial shift registers which shift shift data in response to a shift clock, and a control circuit which controls supply of the shift clock to the plurality of partial shift registers individually for each partial shift register.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to a preferred aspect of the present invention, the control circuit preferably operates the shift register while changing, of the plurality of partial shift registers, a partial shift register to which the shift clock is supplied.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to another preferred aspect of the present invention, the control circuit preferably operates the shift register while changing, of the plurality of partial shift registers, a partial shift register to which the shift clock is supplied, so as to shift the shift data from a first stage to final stage of the shift register.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to still another preferred aspect of the present invention, it is preferable that each of the plurality of partial shift registers comprise a plurality of series-connected registers, and the control circuit start supply of the shift clock to a next partial shift register at an arbitrary timing before a timing at which the shift data is transferred from one partial shift register to the next partial shift register. The control circuit preferably stops supply of the shift clock to one partial shift register at an arbitrary timing after the shift data is transferred from one partial shift register to the next partial shift register.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to still another preferred aspect of the present invention, the control circuit preferably controls supply of the shift clock to the plurality of partial shift registers so as to suppress, to not more than two, the number of partial shift registers to which the shift clock is simultaneously supplied.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to still another preferred aspect of the present invention, the control circuit preferably controls supply of the shift clock to the plurality of partial shift registers so as to suppress, to one, the number of partial shift registers to which the shift clock is simultaneously supplied.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The shift register may include a horizontal shift register or vertical shift register.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">According to another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a camera or information processing apparatus, comprising the above-described image sensing apparatus, and a processor which processes an image sensed by the image sensing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Other features and advantages of the present invention will be apparent from the following description taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which like reference characters designate the same or similar parts throughout the figures thereof.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The accompanying drawings, which are incorporated in and constitute a part of the specification, illustrate embodiments of the invention and, together with the description, serve to explain the principles of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram showing the arrangement of a conventional image sensing apparatus;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram showing the arrangement of an image sensing apparatus according to a preferred embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a timing chart showing the operation of a horizontal scanning circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a circuit diagram showing an arrangement of a horizontal scanning circuit according to the second embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a timing chart showing the operation of the horizontal scanning circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a circuit diagram showing an arrangement of a horizontal scanning circuit according to the third embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a timing chart showing the operation of the horizontal scanning circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a block diagram showing an application of the image sensing apparatus according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Preferred embodiments of the present invention will be described below with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram showing the schematic arrangement of a MOS sensor as a solid-state image sensing apparatus according to the first embodiment of the present invention. A MOS sensor <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> comprises a sensor array <b>110</b> in which many photoelectric conversion elements <b>101</b> are two-dimensionally arrayed, a vertical scanning circuit <b>160</b> for sequentially selecting (activating) a plurality of rows of the sensor array <b>110</b> one by one, a horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> for sequentially selecting (activating) a plurality of vertical transfer switches <b>131</b> one by one to sequentially connect a plurality of vertical signal lines of the sensor array <b>110</b> to a common output line <b>132</b> one by one, and an amplifier <b>133</b> for amplifying a signal which appears on the common output line <b>132</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">According to the present invention, it is preferable to divide a shift register which constitutes the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> into a plurality of partial shift registers, and control supply of a horizontal shift clock HCLK to the plurality of partial shift registers individually every block register. This can decrease the number of simultaneously driven registers, compared to a conventional image sensing apparatus which supplies a horizontal shift clock to all the registers that constitute the horizontal shift register. That is, the shift register to which the shift clock is supplied is divided into a plurality of blocks, and the shift clock is simultaneously supplied to only some of these blocks. Noise generated on the power supply line or the like upon driving a register can be reduced. Also, power consumption can be reduced by reducing a load (the number of registers to be simultaneously driven) on the shift clock supply line.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The number of blocks to which the shift clock is simultaneously supplied is preferably two or less, and more preferably one in order to maintain noise generated on the power supply line or the like at a predetermined level and/or further reduce power consumption.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In the preferred embodiment of the present invention shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the shift register of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> is divided into three partial shift registers <b>151</b>, <b>152</b>, and <b>153</b>. Supply of the horizontal shift clock HCLK to the three partial shift registers <b>151</b>, <b>152</b>, and <b>153</b> is individually controlled by shift clock control circuits <b>154</b>, <b>155</b>, and <b>156</b>. The shift clock control circuits <b>154</b>, <b>155</b>, and <b>156</b> can be constituted by, e.g., multiplexers each of which receives the shift clock HCLK at one input and is set to the ground potential at the other input.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a timing chart showing typical signals concerning the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> of the MOS image sensor <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the total number of vertical signal lines of the MOS sensor <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is nine for illustrative convenience, and each of the partial shift registers <b>151</b>, <b>152</b>, and <b>153</b> is assigned to three vertical signal lines.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The first partial shift register <b>151</b> is formed from, e.g., three registers (e.g., D flip-flops), and sequentially activates column selection signals h<sub>11</sub>, h<sub>12</sub>, and h<sub>13 </sub>while shifting pulse-like shift data HD in accordance with a first shift clock hclk<b>1</b>. The output of the register on the final stage is cleared (i.e., raw data is received) in synchronism with the final leading edge of the first shift clock hclk<b>1</b>. The first shift clock hclk<b>1</b> is a signal generated by the shift clock control circuit <b>154</b> on the basis of the shift clock HCLK. For example, when the shift clock control circuit <b>154</b> is formed from a multiplexer, the switching signal of the multiplexer is so controlled as to output a signal identical to the shift clock HCLK during the generation period of hclk<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The second partial shift register <b>152</b> has the same arrangement as that of the first partial shift register <b>151</b>. The second partial shift register <b>152</b> receives an output pulse (shift data) from the first partial shift register <b>151</b>, and sequentially activates column selection signals h<sub>21</sub>, h<sub>22</sub>, and h<sub>23 </sub>while shifting the pulse in accordance with a second shift clock hclk<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The third partial shift register <b>153</b> has the same arrangement as that of the first partial shift register <b>151</b>. The third partial shift register <b>153</b> receives an output pulse (shift data) from the second partial shift register <b>152</b>, and sequentially activates column selection signals h<sub>31</sub>, h<sub>32</sub>, and h<sub>33 </sub>while shifting the pulse in accordance with a third shift clock hclk<b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In the example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the final pulse of the first shift clock hclk<b>1</b> and the first pulse of the second shift clock hclk<b>2</b> are respectively supplied to the first partial shift register <b>151</b> and second partial shift register <b>152</b> at the same timing. It is also possible to form the final-stage register of each partial shift register from a register with a reset terminal and after activating the final column selection signals h<sub>13</sub>, h<sub>23</sub>, and h<sub>33</sub>, supply a reset signal to the reset terminal, resetting the register on the final stage. In this case, shift clocks can be supplied to the partial shift registers <b>151</b> to <b>153</b> at exclusive timings (i.e., the shift clock is supplied to only one partial shift register at one timing). The number of registers to which the shift clock is supplied can always be kept constant in a series of shift registers constituted by the first to third partial shift registers <b>151</b> to <b>153</b>. As a result, the noise level which may be induced on the power supply line or the like due to the shift clock can be suppressed almost constant, realizing stabler signal read. This arrangement minimizes the number of registers to which the shift clock is supplied, further suppressing power consumption.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Only an arrangement of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> has been described, but the vertical scanning circuit <b>160</b> can also adopt the same arrangement. It is also possible that the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> takes the same arrangement as the conventional one, and only the vertical scanning circuit <b>160</b> is constituted in accordance with the above-described arrangement of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The second embodiment provides another arrangement of a horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> in a MOS sensor <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a circuit diagram showing the arrangement of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> according to the second embodiment of the present invention. In the arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> is divided into four partial shift registers <b>201</b>, <b>202</b>, <b>203</b>, and <b>204</b>. In the arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the total number of vertical signal lines of the MOS sensor <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is 16 for illustrative convenience, and each of the partial shift registers <b>201</b>, <b>202</b>, <b>203</b>, and <b>204</b> is assigned to four vertical signal lines.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a timing chart showing typical signals concerning the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The feature and operation of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> according to the second embodiment of the present invention, each of the partial shift registers <b>201</b>, <b>202</b>, <b>203</b>, and <b>204</b> is comprised of four registers (in this case, D flip-flops) <b>221</b>. Note that the number of partial shift registers (i.e., the division number of the scanning circuit <b>150</b>) and the number of stages of registers which constitute each partial shift register can be properly changed.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the second embodiment, supply of a shift clock (e.g., hclk<b>2</b>) to the next partial shift regiser starts earlier by a predetermined period than timings (shift timings of shift data between partial shift registers) T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, and T<b>3</b> at which shift data (HD: pulses h<sub>11 </sub>to h<sub>44</sub>) is transferred from one partial shift register (e.g., the first partial shift register <b>201</b>) to the next partial shift register (e.g., the second partial shift register <b>202</b>). Supply of the shift clock to each partial shift register stops at an arbitrary timing after shift data on the final stage of a partial shift register is transferred to the next partial shift register.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The start and stop of supplying the shift clocks hclk<b>1</b>, hclk<b>2</b>, hclk<b>3</b>, and hclk<b>4</b> to the partial shift registers <b>201</b>, <b>202</b>, <b>203</b>, and <b>204</b> are controlled by shift clock control circuits <b>211</b>, <b>212</b>, <b>213</b>, and <b>214</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">More specifically, in the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, supply of the shift clock starts earlier by two cycles of the shift clock HCLK than the timings T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, and T<b>3</b> for a partial shift register next to a partial shift register having shift data (high pulses h<sub>11 </sub>to h<sub>44</sub>). Supply of the shift clock to each partial shift register stops later by one cycle of the shift clock HCLK than the shift timings T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, and T<b>3</b> of shift data from the partial shift register to the next partial shift register (shift clock of one clock is supplied after T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, and T<b>3</b>). Note that the final-stage registers of the partial shift registers <b>201</b>, <b>202</b>, <b>203</b>, and <b>204</b> are reset by receiving a low-level signal.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">When an input set signal changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>211</b> is so set as to output the shift clock HCLK as the shift clock hclk<b>1</b>. When a column selection signal h<sub>14 </sub>changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>211</b> is so reset as to output a low-level signal by a reset signal which changes to high level upon the lapse of a predetermined period (e.g., ¾ the cycle of the shift clock HCLK) from the transition timing by a delay circuit <b>231</b>. The set signal can be, e.g., the shift data HD.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">When an input set signal (h<sub>12</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>212</b> is so set as to output the shift clock HCLK as the shift clock hclk<b>2</b>. When a selection signal h<sub>24 </sub>changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>212</b> is so reset as to output a low-level signal by a reset signal which changes to high level upon the lapse of a predetermined period (e.g., ¾ the cycle of the shift clock HCLK) from the transition timing by a delay circuit <b>232</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">When an input set signal (h<sub>22</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>213</b> is so set as to output the shift clock HCLK as the shift clock hclk<b>3</b>. When a selection signal h<sub>34 </sub>changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>213</b> is so reset as to output a low-level signal by a reset signal which changes to high level upon the lapse of a predetermined period (e.g., ¾ the cycle of the shift clock HCLK) from the transition timing by a delay circuit <b>233</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">When an input set signal (h<sub>32</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>214</b> is so set as to output the shift clock HCLK as the shift clock hclk<b>4</b>. When a selection signal h<sub>44 </sub>changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>214</b> is so reset as to output a low-level signal by a reset signal which changes to high level upon the lapse of a predetermined period (e.g., ¾ the cycle of the shift clock HCLK) from the transition timing by a delay circuit <b>234</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The shift clock control circuits <b>211</b>, <b>212</b>, <b>213</b>, and <b>214</b> can be formed from, e.g., flip-flops with set and reset terminals.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The arrangement of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> can also be applied to that of a vertical scanning circuit <b>160</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">Third Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The third embodiment provides still another arrangement of a horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> in a MOS sensor <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The third embodiment is different from the second embodiment in a method of generating a reset signal to be supplied to a shift clock control circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a circuit diagram showing the arrangement of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> according to the third embodiment of the present invention. In the arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> is divided into four partial shift registers <b>301</b>, <b>302</b>, <b>303</b>, and <b>304</b>. In the arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the total number of vertical signal lines of the MOS sensor <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is 16 for illustrative convenience, and each of the partial shift registers <b>301</b>, <b>302</b>, <b>303</b>, and <b>304</b> is assigned to four vertical signal lines.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a timing chart showing typical signals concerning the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The feature and operation of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> according to the third embodiment of the present invention, each of the partial shift registers <b>301</b>, <b>302</b>, <b>303</b>, and <b>304</b> is comprised of four registers (in this case, D flip-flops) <b>321</b>. Note that the number of partial shift registers (i.e., the division number of the scanning circuit <b>150</b>) and the number of stages of registers which constitute each partial shift register can be properly changed.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Also in the third embodiment, similar to the second embodiment, supply of a shift clock (e.g., hclk<b>2</b>) to the next partial shift regiser starts earlier by a predetermined period than timings (shift timings of shift data between partial shift registers) T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, and T<b>3</b> at which shift data (HD: pulses h<sub>11 </sub>to h<sub>44</sub>) is transferred from one partial shift register (e.g., the first partial shift register <b>301</b>) to the next partial shift register (e.g., the second partial shift register <b>302</b>). Supply of the shift clock to each partial shift register stops at an arbitrary timing after shift data on the final stage of a partial shift register is transferred to the next partial shift register.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The start and stop of supplying the shift clocks hclk<b>1</b>, hclk<b>2</b>, hclk<b>3</b>, and hclk<b>4</b> to the partial shift registers <b>301</b>, <b>302</b>, <b>303</b>, and <b>304</b> are controlled by shift clock control circuits <b>311</b>, <b>312</b>, <b>313</b>, and <b>314</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">More specifically, in the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, supply of the shift clock starts earlier by two cycles of the shift clock HCLK than the timings T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, and T<b>3</b> for a partial shift register next to a partial shift register having shift data (high pulses h<sub>11 </sub>to h<sub>44</sub>). Supply of the shift clock to each partial shift register stops later by one cycle of the shift clock HCLK than the shift timings T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, and T<b>3</b> of shift data from the partial shift register to the next partial shift register (shift clock of one clock is supplied after T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, and T<b>3</b>). Note that the final-stage registers of the partial shift registers <b>301</b>, <b>302</b>, <b>303</b>, and <b>304</b> are reset by receiving a low-level signal.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">When an input set signal changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>311</b> is so set as to output the shift clock HCLK as the shift clock hclk<b>1</b>. When an input reset signal (h<sub>22</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>311</b> is so reset as to output a low-level signal. The set signal can be, e.g., the shift data HD.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">When an input set signal (h<sub>12</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>312</b> is so set as to output the shift clock HCLK as the shift clock hclk<b>2</b>. When an input reset signal (h<sub>32</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>312</b> is so reset as to output a low-level signal.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">When an input set signal (h<sub>22</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>313</b> is so set as to output the shift clock HCLK as the shift clock hclk<b>3</b>. When an input reset signal (h<sub>42</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>313</b> is so reset as to output a low-level signal.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">When an input set signal (h<sub>32</sub>) changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>314</b> is so set as to output the shift clock HCLK as the shift clock hclk<b>4</b>. When a column selection signal h<sub>44 </sub>changes to high level, the shift clock control circuit <b>314</b> is so reset as to output a low-level signal upon the lapse of a predetermined period (e.g., ¾ the cycle of the shift clock HCLK) from the transition timing.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">The shift clock control circuits <b>311</b>, <b>312</b>, <b>313</b>, and <b>314</b> can be formed from, e.g., flip-flops with set and reset terminals.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The arrangement of the horizontal scanning circuit <b>150</b> can also be applied to that of a vertical scanning circuit <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="h-0009" num="0000">[Application]</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a block diagram showing the schematic arrangement of a camera which incorporates the image sensing apparatus <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. This camera is generally called an electronic camera as a concept coordinate with a silver halide camera, and includes a still camera, a movie camera, and a hybrid camera having these functions. This camera may be assembled as part of an information processing apparatus such as a personal computer or portable terminal.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">An image of an object to be sensed is formed on the image sensing apparatus <b>100</b> via a fixed or interchangeable lens unit <b>1110</b>. An output from the image sensing apparatus <b>100</b> is supplied to a processor (image processor) <b>1120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The processor <b>1120</b> performs image processing for a signal supplied from the image sensing apparatus <b>100</b>, supplies the resultant data to a display <b>1140</b>, and stores the data in a storage medium <b>1130</b>. The display <b>1140</b> can function as a viewfinder and an information providing unit which displays various pieces of information concerning image sensing and reproduction.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Note that this camera typically comprises an exposure adjusting function, focusing function, and the like. These functions can be designed based on known techniques, and a detailed description thereof will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The present invention can reduce, e.g., noise in the image sensing apparatus and/or power consumption of the image sensing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">As many apparently widely different embodiments of the present invention can be made without departing from the spirit and scope thereof, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited to the specific embodiments thereof except as defined in the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An image sensing apparatus having a plurality of photoelectric conversion elements and a scanning circuit for reading out signals from the plurality of photoelectric conversion elements, wherein the scanning circuit comprises:
<claim-text>a shift register constituted by series-connecting a plurality of partial shift registers, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control circuit configured to supply, on the basis of a shift clock, a individual shift clock to each of the plurality of partial shift registers,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said shift register is configured to shift one shift data is transferred from one partial shift register to a next partial shift register and said control circuit is configured to start supply of the individual shift clock to the next partial shift register at an arbitrary timing before a timing at which the shift data is transferred from the one partial shift register to the next partial shift register.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said control circuit operates said shift register while changing, of the plurality of partial shift registers, a partial shift register to which the individual shift clock is supplied.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said control circuit operates said shift register while changing, of the plurality of partial shift registers, a partial shift register to which the individual shift clock is supplied, so as to shift the shift data from a first stage to final stage of said shift register.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said control circuit stops supply of the individual shift clock to the one partial shift register at an arbitrary timing after the shift data is transferred from the one partial shift register to the next partial shift register.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said control circuit controls supply of the individual shift clock to the plurality of partial shift registers so as to suppress, to not more than two, the number of partial shift registers to which the individual shift clock is simultaneously supplied.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said shift register includes a horizontal shift register.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said shift register includes a vertical shift register.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A camera comprising:
<claim-text>an image sensing apparatus defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a processor which processes an image sensed by said image sensing apparatus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An information processing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>an image sensing apparatus defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a processor which processes an image sensed by said image sensing apparatus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
