<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299488-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299488</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10199598</doc-number>
<date>20020719</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>1237</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>173</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725119</main-classification>
<further-classification>725 98</further-classification>
<further-classification>725116</further-classification>
<further-classification>725118</further-classification>
<further-classification>725 93</further-classification>
<further-classification>709228</further-classification>
<further-classification>709229</further-classification>
<further-classification>709231</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">System and method for provisioning a single physical broadband drop to accommodate multiple specific devices</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5420923</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Beyers et al.</name>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5677905</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bigham et al.</name>
<date>19971000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>37039521</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5756280</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Soora et al.</name>
<date>19980500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6044076</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yamamoto</name>
<date>20000300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370392</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6055560</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mills et al.</name>
<date>20000400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6219355</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Brodigan</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6289381</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Brodigan</name>
<date>20010900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>U.S. Appl. No. 09/115,749, filed Jul. 15, 1998, Donald L. Brodigan.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>U.S. Appl. No. 09/115,752, filed Jul. 15, 1998, Donald L. Brodigan.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709228-232</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709238</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709245</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709249-250</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709223-225</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370401</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370486</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 25</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 34</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 98- 99</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725114-119</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 86</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 87</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 91</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 93- 94</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725144</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>09115752</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>19980715</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6526582</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10199598</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20020194615</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20021219</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Brodigan</last-name>
<first-name>Donald L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Westminster</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Baker</last-name>
<first-name>Gerald F.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Littleton</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Dodson</last-name>
<first-name>Patricia A.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lake Oswego</city>
<state>OR</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Townsend and Townsend and Crew LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Qwest Communications International Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Vu</last-name>
<first-name>Ngoc</first-name>
<department>2623</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method and system for provisioning a specific device to receive video and/or data services from a plurality of service providers at a physical drop in a digital broadband network serviced by a telecommunication services provider utilizes a broadcast manager for transmitting an electronic message in a modified format determined by the telecommunication services provider, wherein the electronic message contains information identifying the physical drop associated with the specific device. A broadband digital terminal, in communication with the broadcast manager and the physical-port, receives the electronic message, stores the information, and upon receiving a sign-on request from a requesting device that is requesting access to one of the video and/or data services, determines whether the requesting device is authorized to access the requested video and/or data service based on the stored information.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="183.30mm" wi="248.24mm" file="US07299488-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="249.94mm" wi="185.50mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299488-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="203.12mm" wi="143.26mm" file="US07299488-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="145.12mm" wi="146.98mm" file="US07299488-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of co-pending, commonly assigned U.S. patent application Ser. No. 09/115,752, entitled, “METHOD AND SYSTEM FOR PROVISIONING A SINGLE PHYSICAL BROADBAND DROP TO ACCOMMODATE MULTIPLE SPECIFIC DEVICES”, filed on Jul. 15, 1998 now is U.S. Pat. No 6,526,582 , by Donald L. Brodigan, et al., the entirety of which application is incorporated herein by reference for all purposes. This application is related to co-pending, commonly assigned U.S. patent application Ser. No. 09/115,749, entitled, “METHOD AND SYSTEM FOR PROVISIONING A SINGLE PHYSICAL BROADBAND DROP TO ACCOMMODATE MULTIPLE DEVICES”, filed on Jul. 15, 1998 now is U.S. Pat. No. 6,467,090, by Donald L. Brodigan, and to co-pending, commonly assigned U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10,199906, entitled, “METHOD AND SYSTEM FOR PROVISIONING A SINGLE PHYSICAL BROADBAND DROP TO ACCOMMODATE MULTIPLE DEVICES”, filed on Jul. 19, 2002, by Donald L. Brodigan, which is a continuation of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 09/115,749, the entirety of which applications are incorporated herein by reference for all purposes.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to methods and systems for provisioning single physical broadband drops to accommodate multiple specific devices.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Existing cable TV networks utilize Hybrid Fiber Coaxial (“HFC”) architecture that includes a fiber coaxial distribution network similar to a tree and branch architecture. All video channels are sent to this HFC network for distribution throughout the network. The cable TV service provider has a controller at the headend that is connected to the HFC network and another connection through a Business System Interface (“BSI”) to a company that provides the platform for the service provider for provisioning the video service for the cable TV's customers.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Provisioning commands are sent from the platform company to the controller including a media access control (“MAC”) address of the customer's set-top-box (“STB”), which is purchased or leased from the service provider, and the entitlements the customer has subscribed to. The controller then broadcasts this provisioning information over the HFC network to the STB having the MAC address specified in the provisioning command. The customer's STB must be attached to the network in order for it to receive the entitlements it has subscribed to. Thus, the STB can be anywhere on the network since it is not associated with a single physical drop corresponding to the customer's home/place of business. Furthermore, anyone capable of duplicating the MAC address of the customer's STB can receive free service.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Some cable TV operators have chosen to use interdiction devices on their HFC network which eliminates the need for the customer to have an STB. The interdiction devices, located at a pedestal serving several homes, are provisioned from a controller at the headend for entitlements based on a physical drop. Any cable-ready TV connected to the drop is capable of receiving and viewing the provisioned entitlements. All other channels are filtered or modified at the interdiction device so that they cannot be view on that physical drop.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Interdiction devices, however, have several drawbacks. First, they are designed for analog cable TV and do not support digital MPEG video. Second, interdiction devices are designed for a single cable TV network serving the customer. Thus, multiple video/data service providers are not supported. And third, all devices on the physical drop associated with the corresponding interdiction device receive all the filtered channels and entitlements. There is no ability to allow each device to have its own specific entitlements.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Today's digital broadband architecture allows for multiple service providers to serve a single customer belonging to a video/data network. However, as with the traditional cable TV network, video/data entitlements can be provisioned for a single device. That device can be located anywhere in the network, yet still be able to receive the provisioned entitlements thereby opening the door for theft of services, especially if the MAC address of the device can be duplicated by an unauthorized customer.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Thus, there exists a need for a method of provisioning a physical drop to allow a customer to obtain access to video/data services based on the customer's address in a digital broadband architecture that overcomes the disadvantages encountered by the known prior art.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">It is therefore a general object of the present invention to provide a method and system for provisioning a single physical drop in a digital broadband architecture that allows a customer to obtain access to video/data services based on the customer's address.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">It is another object of the present invention to provide a method and system for provisioning a single physical drop to be able to obtain access to various video and data suppliers based on the customer's address.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">It is yet another object of the present invention to provide a method and system for provisioning a single physical drop so as to allow each device on the physical drop to be provisioned with different or same type of entitlements for each device.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In carrying out the above objects and other objects, features, and advantages of the present invention, a method is provided for provisioning a first specific device to receive video and/or data services from a plurality of service providers at a customer's physical drop in a digital broadband network serviced by a telecommunication services provider wherein the plurality of service providers normally communicate with the telecommunication services provider utilizing electronic messages having predetermined formats as defined in a communications protocol. The method includes transmitting an electronic message in a modified format determined by the telecommunication services provider and containing information identifying the physical drop associated with the first specific device, storing the information at a location servicing the physical drop, and upon receiving a sign-on request from a requesting device that is requesting access to one of the video and data services, determining whether the requesting device is authorized to access the requested video or data service based on the stored information.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In further carrying out the above objects and other objects, features, and advantages of the present invention, a system is also provided for carrying out the steps of the above described method. The system includes a broadcast manager, in communication with the video/data service providers, for transmitting an electronic message in a modified format determined by the telecommunication services provider, the electronic message containing information identifying the physical drop associated with the first specific device. The system also includes a broadband digital terminal, in communication with the broadcast manager and the physical port, programmed to receive the electronic message, store the information, and upon receiving a sign-on request from a requesting device that is requesting access to one of the video and/or data services, determine whether the requesting device is authorized to access the requested video and/or data service based on the stored information.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The above objects and other objects, features and advantages of the present invention are readily apparent from the following detailed description of the best mode for carrying out the invention when taken in connection with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of the system of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a flow diagram illustrating the general sequence of steps associated with the provisioning process of the present invention; and</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BEST MODES FOR CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the system of the present invention, denoted generally by reference numeral <b>10</b>. The system <b>10</b> includes a headend portion <b>12</b> and a network portion <b>14</b>. The headend <b>12</b> includes a Business System Interface (“BSI”) <b>16</b> for interconnecting the network <b>14</b> with a platform company serving a service provider. The BSI <b>16</b> sends provisioning commands to the network <b>14</b> utilizing a predetermined format/protocol.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The headend <b>12</b> further includes video service providers <b>18</b> that provide motion video/audio data encoded according to MPEG 1 and 2 video encoding standards. Examples of video service providers <b>18</b> include satellite MPEG 2 video delivery (DSS Satellite and Primestar) as well as other cable companies moving towards digital cable TV technology.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Data service providers <b>20</b> are also included in the headend <b>12</b> for providing data services. Data service providers may include service providers such as America On-Line, Prodigy, Microsoft Network, MCI, and other internet and intranet data service providers as well as corporate data service providers.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The network <b>14</b> includes a View 2 Broadcast Manager <b>22</b> in communication with the BSI <b>16</b> for receiving the provisioning commands and managing video and high speed data access at a customer's physical drop. Upon receiving a provisioning command from the BSI <b>16</b>, the broadcast manager <b>22</b> creates a customer profile <b>24</b> that identifies the video channel entitlements that are associated with a specific physical drop serving a residence or business. In the case of data services, the profile <b>24</b> is used to identify the data service provider <b>20</b>. Asynchronous Transfer Mode (ATM) is used between the customer and the data service provider <b>20</b> so as to provide a private line-like connection.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Video/data entitlements are then provisioned through the broadcast manager <b>22</b> to a Broadband Digital Terminal (“BDT”) <b>26</b> serving the customer. The network <b>14</b> preferably includes a plurality of BDTs <b>26</b>, each of which serve a plurality of customers. The number of customers served is dependent upon the actual vendor's equipment. The BDT <b>26</b> is coupled to the video and data service providers <b>18</b> and <b>20</b> so that multiple video and data service providers can be served on a shared transport. Data is established from the customer's physical drop through the BDT <b>26</b> to a data network and then to the appropriate data service provider <b>20</b>. In the case of video, the video service provider <b>18</b> sends MPEG video through the data network to the BDT <b>26</b>. The customer selects a channel from their STB <b>27</b> to the BDT <b>26</b> to select the video channel they want to watch, but is restricted to the channel entitlements provisioned in their profile <b>24</b>. Thus, the BDT <b>26</b> is responsible for switching the video and data provided by the video and data service providers <b>18</b>, <b>20</b> to the appropriate physical drop based on the provisioned profile <b>24</b> transferred from the broadcast manager <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Each of the BDTs <b>26</b> includes a microprocessor <b>29</b> in communication with various computer readable storage media <b>31</b>. Computer-readable storage media <b>31</b> may include various types of media or memories and may be implemented utilizing any of a number of known hardware devices such as flash memory, PROMs, EEPROMS, and other electrical, electromagnetic, and optical storage devices capable of storing data representing instructions executable by a computer. As is known, computer-readable media <b>31</b> contain various program instructions, software, or control logic to affect access to the service providers <b>18</b>, <b>20</b>. Microprocessor <b>29</b> executes various instructions to generate output signals to each of the service providers <b>18</b>, <b>20</b> based on signals received from the devices <b>27</b> via a Broadband Network Unit (“BNU”) <b>28</b> or a Universal Service Access Multiplexer (“USAM”) <b>30</b>, as described below.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Each of the BDTs <b>26</b> are coupled to either a BNU <b>28</b> or a USAM <b>30</b>. The BNU <b>28</b> is a physical unit that is placed in the serving neighborhood and is connected to the BDT <b>26</b> via a single fiber link. Typically, the BNU <b>28</b> serves up to <b>16</b> homes or physical drops. A coaxial cable is run from a port (#1-16) on the BNU <b>28</b> to the home or business so that multiple devices on a single physical drop can have different entitlements. A twisted copper pair running between the BNU <b>28</b> and a home or business provides telephone service.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The USAM <b>30</b> performs the same function as the BNU <b>28</b>, but combines the video and data service on the same twisted copper pair as the voice, or telephone, service. By providing video/data and voice on a single pair of wires to the customer, the total customers served is increased from 16 to 32.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Turning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, there is shown a flow diagram illustrating the general sequence of steps associated with the provisioning process of the present invention. First, the customer orders video and/or data service from one of many video/data service providers servicing the customer's area, as shown at block <b>100</b>. At this time, the customer provides the video/data service provider(s) with one or more devices, or STBs, for which she would like provisioned. Each device has a specific MAC address so that each device can be separately identified.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The video or data service provider then enters the video/data entitlements in the BSI <b>16</b>, as shown at block <b>110</b>. At block <b>112</b>, the BSI <b>16</b> then transmits the entitlements to the broadcast manager <b>22</b> identifying the physical drop to be provisioned. This information is preferably transmitted utilizing the existing Jerrold communication protocol, specifically the Add New Settop <b>660</b> command. The Add New Settop <b>660</b> command is utilized to add a new digital settop box and authorize services for the settop box. This command contains the following fields in addition to the STX, the packet header, the Checksum field, and the ETX:</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="3">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="14pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="98pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="105pt" align="left"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Field</entry>
<entry>Format</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>BSI_Code</entry>
<entry>16-bit unsigned integer</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Headend_Number</entry>
<entry>16-bit unsigned integer</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Equip_Type</entry>
<entry>16-bit unsigned integer</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Equip_Sub_Type</entry>
<entry>16-bit unsigned integer</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Serial_Number</entry>
<entry>12-character alphanumeric</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Unit_Address</entry>
<entry>16-character alphanumeric</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Init_Flag</entry>
<entry>8-bit unsigned integer</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Num_Changed_Services</entry>
<entry>16-bit unsigned integer</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Service_Handle</entry>
<entry>32-bit unsigned integer</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The BSI_Code and Headend_Number identify the video or data service provider. The Equip_Type and Equip_Sub_Type codes identify the specific manufacturer, model number, and software release of the STB or data device being provisioned. The Serial_Number field identifies the MAC address of the STB/data device. The Service_Handle field is used to specify the video or data entitlements the customer has subscribed to. The Unit_Address field specifies the unit address assigned to the STB/data device by the manufacturer. Although these fields specify entitlements provisioned for a specific STB/data device, none of them, alone or together, provide information so as to insure that the STB/data device is at the authorized physical drop and, if applicable, one of many devices authorized on the physical drop.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Therefore, in the present invention, the Unit_Address field is modified to identify the customer's address, while the actual entitlements remain controlled by the code in the Service_Handle field. The Unit_Address is modified as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00002" num="00002">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="5">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="70pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="56pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="5" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>xx</entry>
<entry>xxxx</entry>
<entry>xxxxxx</entry>
<entry>xxx</entry>
<entry>xx</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="5" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
<br/>
where,
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0031">the first 2 Octet=State code identifying the state in which the service is being provided;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0032">the next 4 Octet=Common Language Circuit Identifier (“CLCI”) identifying the serving wire center;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0003" num="0033">the next 6 Octet=BDT/BNU/Port identifying the physical location of the customer's broadband drop;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0004" num="0034">the next 3 Octet=Service Wire Center identifying the central office that provides dialtone to the physical drop; and</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0005" num="0035">the next 2 Octet=a fixed value, e.g., U, due to limited field length, but could be used for other features in the future.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0036">Upon receiving the video/data entitlements, the broadcast manager creates a device profile for the customer's physical drop, as shown at block <b>114</b>. The device profile includes service provider information, entitlements, device type (or equipment type), MAC address of video/data device, and physical drop identification information, i.e., BDT, BNU/USAM and Port.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0037">A physical broadband drop can support multiple device profiles. Therefore, if the customer is provisioning more than one device, the BSI <b>16</b> transmits the additional entitlement information to the broadcast manager <b>22</b>. In this case, all the information transmitted in the Unit_Address field remains the same except for the Serial_Number field and the Service_Handle field. The Serial_Number field will contain the specific MAC address of the additional/different STB/data device, while the Service_Handle field will contain the entitlements subscribed to by the customer for that specific STB/data device.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0038">The device profiles are then transmitted by the broadcast manager <b>22</b> to the appropriate BDT <b>26</b> identified in the Unit_Address field, as shown at block <b>116</b>. The BDT <b>26</b> identified in the Unit_Address field corresponds to the BDT <b>26</b> serving the customer's home or place of business. Finally, access to the video/data service subscribed to by the customer is enabled, as shown at block <b>118</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0039">Thus, the BDT <b>26</b> stores the device profile(s) associated with a single physical drop for use in allowing the customer to gain access to the subscribed services. This process is further illustrated in the flow diagram of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The device <b>27</b> uses the DAVIC 1.2 Interface Initialization Protocol (DiiP) to register with the network <b>14</b>. Upon activating the device <b>27</b>, the device transmits a sign-on request, including the MAC address of the device <b>27</b>, to the BDT <b>26</b>, as shown at block <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0040">When the BDT <b>26</b> receives the sign-on request from the device <b>27</b>, the BDT <b>26</b> looks in a table for a device profile associated with the physical drop from which the sign-on request originated to determine if the MAC address sent by the requesting device matches a MAC address stored in the device profile, as shown at block <b>210</b>. If the MAC address does not match a preprovisioned MAC address profile, the BDT <b>26</b> denies access to the device <b>27</b>, as shown at block <b>212</b>. However, if there is a match, the device <b>27</b> is given access to the requested services, as shown at block <b>214</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0041">While the best modes for carrying out the invention have been described in detail, those familiar with the art to which this invention relates will recognize various alternative designs and embodiments for practicing the invention as defined by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of provisioning a plurality of devices at a single physical drop to receive telecommunications services, comprising:
<claim-text>receiving at a network an electronic message from a head end, wherein the electronic message comprises:
<claim-text>a first information field that specifies telecommunication services which the devices at the single physical drop are entitled to receive;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second information field that comprises, in modified format, information that identifies the single physical drop; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third information field that comprises, in modified format, a maximum number of simultaneously active devices at the single physical drop, wherein the third information field comprises a modified version of a Serial Number field of an Add New Settop command of the Jerrold communication protocol;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>creating a device profile associated with the single physical drop corresponding to the electronic message; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing the device profile;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving, from a device at the single physical drop, a request to access telecommunication services;</claim-text>
<claim-text>checking the device profile associated with the single physical drop to determine whether the maximum number of simultaneously active devices at the single physical drop has been exceeded; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>processing the request accordingly to thereby provision the device to access the telecommunication services.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A system for provisioning a plurality of devices at a single physical drop to receive telecommunications services, comprising:
<claim-text>a network, wherein the network comprises:
<claim-text>means for receiving from a head end, an electronic message, wherein the electronic message comprises:
<claim-text>a first information field that specifies telecommunication services which the devicesat the single physical drop are entitled to receive;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second information field that comprises, in modified format, information that identifies the single physical drop; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third information field that comprises, in modified format, a maximum number of simultaneously active devices at the single physical drop, wherein the third information field comprises a modified version of a Serial Number field of an Add New Settop command of the Jerrold communication protocol;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for creating a device profile associated with the single physical drop corresponding to the electronic message;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for storing the device profile;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for receiving, from a device at the single physical drop, a request to access telecommunication services; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for checking the device profile associated with the single physical drop to determine whether the maximum number of simultaneously active devices at the single physical drop has been exceeded.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A system for provisioning a plurality of devices at a single physical drop to receive telecommunication services, comprising:
<claim-text>a network, wherein the network comprises:
<claim-text>a broadcast manager that receives from a Business System Interface, an electronic message relating to an Add New Settop command of the Jerrold communication protocol, wherein the electronic message comprises:
<claim-text>a Service Handle field that specifies telecommunication services which the devices at the single physical drop are entitled to receive;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Unit Address field that comprises, in modified format, information that identifies the single physical drop; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Serial Number field that comprises, in modified format, a maximum number of simultaneously active devices at the single physical drop;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Broadband Digital Terminal operable to create a device profile associated with the single physical drop corresponding to the electronic message; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a storage arrangement that stores the device profile;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the Broadband Digital Terminal is further operable to receive, from a device at the single physical drop, a request to access telecommunication services, and wherein the Broadband Digital Terminal is further operable to check the device profile associated with the single physical drop to determine whether the maximum number of simultaneously active devices at the single physical drop has been exceeded.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
