<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298642-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298642</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11012114</doc-number>
<date>20041216</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-249051</doc-number>
<date>20040827</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>365158</main-classification>
<further-classification>365148</further-classification>
<further-classification>36518907</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Magnetic resistance memory and method of writing data</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3530441</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ovshinsky</name>
<date>19700900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6438665</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Norman</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>711159</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0235118</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Moriyama et al.</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>711154</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>7-65586</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-330790</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>03/079365</doc-number>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>K.F. Strauss and T. Daud, “Overview of Radiation Tolerant Unlimited Write Cycle Non-Volatile Memory,” <i>Proc. 2000 IEEE Aerospace Conf.</i>, vol. 5, pp. 399-408.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>S. Lai and T. Lowrey, “OUM—A 180 nm Nonvolatile Memory Cell Element Technology for Stand Alone and Embedded Applications,” <i>IEDM Dig</i>. (2001), pp. 803-806.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>365148</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>36518907</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>365158</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060044867</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060302</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ise</last-name>
<first-name>Masahiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kawasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Staas &amp; Halsey LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fujitsu Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kawasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ho</last-name>
<first-name>Hoai V.</first-name>
<department>2827</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A magnetic resistance memory includes an identity determining unit that compares, bit by bit, first data stored in an address specified by a write request with second data to be written to the address, and that determines whether bit-by-bit values of the first data and the second data are identical; and a writing control unit that halts, when a bit of the second data is identical with a corresponding bit of the first data, writing of the bit of the second data.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="233.68mm" wi="155.70mm" file="US07298642-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="246.63mm" wi="161.54mm" file="US07298642-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="160.27mm" wi="178.22mm" file="US07298642-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="123.19mm" wi="166.96mm" file="US07298642-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="189.82mm" wi="156.38mm" file="US07298642-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="124.46mm" wi="178.56mm" file="US07298642-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="91.95mm" wi="136.40mm" file="US07298642-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1) Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a magnetic resistance memory and a writing method of the magnetic resistance memory.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2) Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Magnetic resistance memory (MRAM: Magnetic Random Access Memory) is gaining ground in recent years as a next generation memory for its high speed and non-volatile properties. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic diagram of a basic principle of an MRAM. Each memory cell is formed of a non-magnetic layer <b>502</b> sandwiched between a first ferromagnetic layer <b>501</b> and a second ferromagnetic layer <b>503</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The first ferromagnetic layer <b>501</b> is a changeable ferromagnetic layer, of which the magnetization direction can be changed by passing an electric current, whereas the second ferromagnetic layer <b>503</b> is an unchangeable ferromagnetic layer, of which the magnetization direction remains constant. When the first ferromagnetic layer <b>501</b> and the second ferromagnetic layer <b>503</b> have a same magnetization direction, magnetic resistance between the first ferromagnetic layer <b>501</b> and the second ferromagnetic layer <b>503</b> decreases. When the first ferromagnetic layer <b>501</b> and the second ferromagnetic layer <b>503</b> have different magnetization directions, the magnetic resistance between the first ferromagnetic layer <b>501</b> and the second ferromagnetic layer <b>503</b> increases.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The MRAM memory cell stores information based on a degree of magnetic resistance, which is dependent on the magnetization direction of the first ferromagnetic layer <b>501</b>, between the first ferromagnetic layer <b>501</b> and the second ferromagnetic layer <b>503</b>. For instance, when the magnetic resistance is low, a one-bit data ‘0’ is stored, and when the magnetic resistance is high, a one-bit data ‘1’ is stored.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Data can be written to MRAM by passing an electric current in a destination memory cell to change the magnetization direction of the changeable ferromagnetic layer to a predetermined direction. A technology relating to the MRAM is disclosed in, for example, “MRAM”, URL: http://www.nanoelectronic.jp/kaitai/mram/, searched on Jul. 29, 2004.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, writing data to MRAM requires a constant application of electric current to the destination memory cell, resulting in large power consumption.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">It is an object of the present invention to solve at least the above problems in the conventional technology.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A magnetic resistance memory according to one aspect of the present invention includes an identity determining unit that compares, bit by bit, first data stored in an address specified by a write request with second data to be written to the address, and that determines whether bit-by-bit values of the first data and the second data are identical; and a writing control unit that halts, when a bit of the second data is identical with a corresponding bit of the first data, writing of the bit of the second data.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A method of writing data with a magnetic resistance memory according to another aspect of the present invention includes comparing, bit by bit, first data stored in an address specified by a write request with second data to be written to the address; determining whether bit-by-bit values of the first data and the second data are identical; and halting, when a bit of the second data is identical with a corresponding bit of the first data, writing of the bit of the second data.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The other objects, features, and advantages of the present invention are specifically set forth in or will become apparent from the following detailed description of the invention when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of an MRAM according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of the MRAM;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic diagram of an MRAM cell;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flowchart of a writing process of the MRAM; and</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic diagram of a basic principle of the MRAM.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates an embodiment of a comparing circuit <b>150</b> included in the MRAM structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Exemplary embodiments of a magnetic resistance memory and a writing method of the magnetic resistance memory according to the present invention will be explained with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of an MRAM according to an embodiment of the present invention. When data is being written to the MRAM, data to be written and existing data are compared and no electric current is applied to the memory cell having same data as the data to be written. Consequently, an electric current for writing is not constantly applied to all destination cells as in a conventional MRAM.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">For instance, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, if the black circles are taken as representing ‘1’ and the white circles as ‘0’, the 3-bit data stored in the MRAM is ‘101’ and the data to be written is ‘000’. Therefore, in the conventional MRAM, the electric current for writing has to be applied to all the three memory cells to write the data to the MRAM. However, in the MRAM according to the present embodiment, the electric current for writing is not applied to the memory cell of the second bit since the existing data in that memory cell is the same as the data to be written.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Thus, when writing data to the MRAM according to the present embodiment, the data existing in the memory cell and the data to be written are compared, and if found to be the same, the application of electric current for writing to the relevant memory cell is stopped. As a result, power consumption during writing to the MRAM can be curtailed.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of the MRAM according to the present embodiment. The MRAM includes a memory cell array <b>110</b>, an address decoder <b>120</b>, a control circuit <b>130</b>, an I/O buffer <b>140</b>, a comparing circuit <b>150</b>, and a current controller <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The memory cell array <b>110</b> includes a 3-dimensional array of MRAM cells, which are the memory cells of the MRAM, and a control unit that controls reading data from and writing data to each MRAM cell. The capacity of the memory cell array <b>110</b> is 256 K word, each word being 16-bit.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic diagram of an MRAM cell. A bit line is used for writing data and a sense line is used for reading data. A word line is composed of 16 MRAM cells. Data equivalent to one word is read from and written to 16 MRAM cells of the word line.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The address decoder <b>120</b> receives an address signal and specifies the word line corresponding to the received address. The memory cell array <b>110</b> reads data from or writes data to 16 MRAM cells of the word line specified by address decoder <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The control circuit <b>130</b> receives a control signal such as an instruction to writing data to or read data from the memory cell array <b>110</b>, etc. and carries out the instruction according to the control signal.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The I/O buffer <b>140</b> is a 10-bit buffer that stores the data read from or written to the memory cell array <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">When writing data to the memory cell array <b>110</b>, the comparing circuit <b>150</b> compares, bit by bit, the data existing in the word line where the data is to be written and the data to be written stored in the I/O buffer <b>140</b>, and creates a comparison result signal that indicates whether the compared bits are the same.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">For instance, the comparing circuit <b>150</b> creates the comparison result signal by carrying out exclusive OR logical operation (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) of the data existing in the word line where the data is to be written and the data to be written stored in the I/O buffer <b>140</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The current controller <b>160</b> outputs to the memory cell array <b>110</b> a current control signal that controls the electric current for writing applied to the MRAM cell based on the comparison result signal created by the comparing circuit <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In other words, the current controller <b>160</b> creates a current control signal that controls the electric current for writing in such a way that the application of electric current for writing is stopped for the bits whose values match, from among the bits of the data existing in the word line where the data is to be written and the data to be written stored in the I/O buffer <b>140</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Thus, when writing data to the memory cell array <b>110</b>, the comparing circuit <b>150</b> compares, bit by bit, the data existing in the word line where the data is to be written and the data to be written stored in the I/O buffer <b>140</b>, and creates a comparison result signal indicating whether the bits are the same. The current controller <b>160</b> creates, based on the comparison result signal, the current control signal that controls the electric current for writing, and stops the application of electric current for writing to the MRAM cells that have the same value.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In the present embodiment, the current controller <b>160</b> creates a single current control signal, which is a 16-bit data that indicates for each MRAM cell whether the application of electric current for writing is to be stopped. However, the 16-bit data may also be broken down into a plurality of current control signals which may be serially output to the memory cell array <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Upon receiving from the control circuit <b>130</b> an instruction to write data to the word line specified by the address decoder <b>120</b>, the memory cell array <b>110</b> stops the electric current for writing based on the current control signal received from the current controller <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In other words, when writing the data stored in the I/O buffer <b>140</b>, the memory cell array <b>110</b> stops the electric current for writing to the MRAM cell that has the same bit value as the bit value of the data to be written.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow chart of a writing process of the MRAM according to the present embodiment. The comparing circuit <b>150</b> of the MRAM detects a state of the memory cell where data is to be written, and compares, bit by bit, the state with the data to be written in the I/O buffer <b>140</b> (step S<b>101</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Based on the comparison result from the comparing circuit <b>150</b>, for the bits that do not match (“NO” at step S<b>102</b>), the current controller <b>160</b> creates the current control signal that instructs data writing (step S<b>103</b>) and for the bits that match (“YES” at step S<b>102</b>), the current controller <b>160</b> creates the current control signal that instructs stoppage of electric current for writing (step S<b>104</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The memory cell array <b>110</b> controls the electric current for writing based on the current control signal created by the current controller <b>160</b>, and writes the data stored in the I/O buffer <b>140</b> (step S<b>105</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Thus, the comparing circuit <b>150</b> detects the state of the memory cell to which data is to be written, and compares, bit by bit, with the data to be written stored in the I/O buffer <b>140</b>. The current controller <b>160</b> creates the current control signal that instructs to stop electric current for writing for the bits that match. Thus, the application of the electric current for writing to the MRAM cells that have the same value before and after data writing is stopped.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">To sum up, in the present embodiment, when writing data to the memory array <b>110</b>, the comparing circuit <b>150</b> compares, bit by bit, the data existing in the word line where the data is to be written and the data to be written stored in the I/O buffer <b>140</b>, and creates the comparison result signal. The current controller <b>160</b> creates, based on the comparison result signal, the current control signal that controls the electric current for writing. The memory cell array <b>110</b> controls the electric current for writing based on the current control signal. Consequently, the application of electric current for writing to the MRAM cells is stopped in the cases where the existing data and the data to be written are the same, and as a result, power consumption can be reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the present embodiment, the word length of the memory array is taken as 16 bits and the capacity of the memory array is 256 K word. The present invention is equally applicable for memory arrays having any word length or capacity.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">According to the present invention, power consumption is reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Furthermore, according to the present invention, overall power consumption is reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Moreover, according to the present invention, power consumption during writing is reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Although the invention has been described with respect to a specific embodiment for a complete and clear disclosure, the appended claims are not to be thus limited but are to be construed as embodying all modifications and alternative constructions that may occur to one skilled in the art which fairly fall within the basic teaching herein set forth.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A magnetic resistance memory comprising:
<claim-text>an identity determining unit that compares, bit by bit, first data stored in an address specified by a write request with second data to be written to the address, that determines whether bit-by-bit values of the first data and the second data are identical, and that creates a comparison result signal indicating whether the compared bits are the same or not, wherein the first data and the second data include a plurality of bits; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first current control unit that creates a current control signal based on the comparison result signal, wherein the current control signal instructs to halt writing of any bit of the second data when the bit of the second data is identical with a corresponding bit of the first data; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a memory cell array that halts writing of the bit of the second data upon receiving the current control signal instructing to halt writing of the bit of the second data.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The magnetic resistance memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the memory cell array halts the writing of the bit of the second data by cutting off an electric current flowing into a corresponding memory cell.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The magnetic resistance memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the current control signal corresponds to a bit width equal to a bit width of the second data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The magnetic resistance memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the identity determining unit determines whether the bit-by-bit values of the first data and the second data are identical by an exclusive OR operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A method of writing data into a magnetic resistance memory, the method comprising:
<claim-text>comparing, bit by bit, first data stored in an address specified by a write request with second data to be written to the address, wherein the first data and the second data include a plurality of bits;</claim-text>
<claim-text>determining whether bit-by-bit values of the first data and the second data are identical;</claim-text>
<claim-text>creating a comparison result signal indicating whether the compared bits are the same or not;</claim-text>
<claim-text>creating a current control signal based on the comparison result signal, wherein the current control signal instructs to halt writing of the bit of the second data, when the bit of the second data is identical with the corresponding bit of the first data; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>halting writing of the bit of the second data upon receiving the current control signal instructing to halt writing of the bit of the second data.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the halting includes halting the writing of the bit of the second data by cutting off an electric current flowing into a corresponding memory cell.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the current control signal corresponds to a bit width equal to a bit width of the second data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the determining includes determining whether the bit-by-bit values of the first data and the second data are identical by an exclusive OR operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A magnetic random access memory (MRAM) system, comprising:
<claim-text>a memory cell array to store data;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an I/O interface to receive new data to be stored in the memory cell array and to transmit the data stored in the memory cell array upon request; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control unit to compare bit-by-bit the new data to be stored in the memory cell array at an address with existing data at the address and to generate a current control signal corresponding to the bit-by-bit comparison that enables writing bits of the new data in memory cells of the memory cell array when corresponding bits of the existing data and the bits of the new data to be written in a memory cell are not identical.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The magnetic resistance memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the current control signal corresponds to 16-bit data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The magnetic resistance memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising an I/O buffer, wherein
<claim-text>the I/O buffer stores the first data or the second data and sends the second data to the identity determining unit, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the identity determining unit receives the second data from the I/O buffer, compares, bit by bit, first data stored in an address specified by a write request with second data to be written to the address, determines whether bit-by-bit values of the first data and the second data are identical, and creates a comparison result signal indicating whether the compared bits are the same or not.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The magnetic resistance memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the memory cell array includes a control unit which halts writing of a bit of the second data upon receiving the current signal instructing to halt writing of the bit of the second data.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
