<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297628-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297628</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10718320</doc-number>
<date>20031119</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>196</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>4763</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438635</main-classification>
<further-classification>438636</further-classification>
<further-classification>438637</further-classification>
<further-classification>438638</further-classification>
<further-classification>438639</further-classification>
<further-classification>438640</further-classification>
<further-classification>438714</further-classification>
<further-classification>438717</further-classification>
<further-classification>438723</further-classification>
<further-classification>438724</further-classification>
<further-classification>438725</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Dynamically controllable reduction of vertical contact diameter through adjustment of etch mask stack for dielectric etch</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5629237</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wang et al.</name>
<date>19970500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5753418</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tsai et al.</name>
<date>19980500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>430313</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6171951</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lee et al.</name>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438640</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6329109</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Figura et al.</name>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6383863</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Chiang et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6387798</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Loke et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438623</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6514868</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hui et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438713</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6613686</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Nishizawa</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438710</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0142610</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chien et al.</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438710</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0173162</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Liu et al.</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438732</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>33</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>11</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050106882</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050519</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chao</last-name>
<first-name>Chunyuan</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fremont</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tsai</last-name>
<first-name>Kuei-Chang</first-name>
<address>
<city>Cupertino</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kovall</last-name>
<first-name>George A.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Campbell</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>MacPherson Kwok Chen &amp; Heid LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Promos Technologies, Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Hsinchu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Deo</last-name>
<first-name>Duy-Vu N</first-name>
<department>1765</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Inwardly-tapered openings are created in an Anti-Reflection Coating layer (ARC layer) provided beneath a patterned photoresist layer. The smaller, bottom width dimensions of the inwardly-tapered openings are used for defining further openings in an interlayer dielectric region (ILD) provided beneath the ARC layer. In one embodiment, the ILD separates an active layers set of an integrated circuit from its first major interconnect layer. Further in one embodiment, a taper-inducing etch recipe is used to create the inwardly-tapered ARC openings, where the etch recipe uses a mixture of CF4 and CHF3 and where the CF4/CHF3 volumetric inflow ratio is substantially less than 5 to 1, and more preferably closer to 1 to 1.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="179.15mm" wi="234.95mm" file="US07297628-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="243.84mm" wi="194.39mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297628-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="224.71mm" wi="173.14mm" file="US07297628-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="205.82mm" wi="165.86mm" file="US07297628-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="206.59mm" wi="167.30mm" file="US07297628-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="206.67mm" wi="165.86mm" file="US07297628-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="207.86mm" wi="170.10mm" file="US07297628-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="212.09mm" wi="178.05mm" file="US07297628-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="247.23mm" wi="198.71mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297628-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="190.50mm" wi="205.99mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297628-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="181.19mm" wi="147.32mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297628-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="236.47mm" wi="181.53mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297628-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">1. FIELD OF DISCLOSURE</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present disclosure of invention relates generally to fabrication of multilayered semiconductor or other monolithically integrated devices.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The disclosure relates more specifically to lithography driven creation of through-holes (vias) through an interlayer dielectric (ILD) that separates a first major, signal conducting layer (e.g., Metal-1) from an active-components containing layer set of a monolithically integrated device so that signal communication may occur between the first layer and the active-components containing layer set.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">2. CROSS REFERENCE TO PATENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The disclosures of the following U.S. patents are incorporated herein by reference for purpose of background or otherwise:</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">(A) U.S. Pat. No. 5,629,237, issued May 13, 1997 to Wang et al. and entitled “Taper Etching Without Re-Entrance Profile”;</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">(B) U.S. Pat. No. 6,329,109 B1, issued Dec. 11, 2001 to Figura et al. and entitled “Mask Having Tapered Profile Used During the Formation of a Semiconductor Device”; and</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">(C) U.S. Pat. No. 6,383,863 B1, issued May 7, 2002 to Chiang al. and entitled “Approach to Integrate Salicide Gate for Embedded DRAM Devices”.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">3. DESCRIPTION OF RELATED ART</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Monolithically integrated devices such as semiconductor integrated circuits typically contain multiple layers of materials, successively disposed one above the other. By way of example, a typical integrated circuit (IC) device may include a monocrystalline silicon substrate on top of which are formed a gate oxide layer, a first polysilicon layer (poly-1), and a next oxide layer, this being followed by alternating further layers of metal or other electrical conductors and oxide or other electrical insulation.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Many of the integrally stacked layers of an IC are specially patterned to contain unique configurations of interconnect, insulation, and/or active components. Often, the so-called, active layers set or lowest set of the patterned layers has the greatest number of, and the most densely packed set of, active component terminals (e.g., transistor gates, drains and sources). (The active layers set or “ALS” typically includes the poly-1 and/or poly-2 layers, the gate oxide layer(s) and the semiconductor epitaxial layer. It may have fewer or more such, densely patterned layers.)</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Because there is often a high density of component terminals in the active layers set, and because component terminations in the ALS are often very close to one another (e.g., they are more closely spaced to one another than are comparable terminals in higher layers), device designers usually face more challenging interconnection problems at or near this active layers region than those found in higher and less densely populated layers.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Among the challenges that designers face when interconnecting to, or near the active layers set are those of: (a) how to make effective contact with the active layer set while preventing short circuits from developing between terminal nodes that are intended to be isolated from one another; (b) how to avoid open circuit breaks from occurring among interconnect lines just above the active layer set; (c) how to maintain desired conductivity values (e.g., low resistance) along various interconnect lines and at respective contact points; and (d) how to avoid excessive electrical capacitance from developing between adjacent conductors. When cutting edge technology is being deployed (e.g., where transistor sizes are at or close to leading edge capabilities and switching frequencies are very high), it is often desirable to engage in actual experimentation for determining whether the monolithically integrated device operates as intended rather then merely resorting to computer simulation in order to prove that desired results (e.g., signal switching speeds, interconnect delays) have been achieved. Cost and time limitations are problems however. Lithography masks for the active and near-active layers tend to be relatively expensive and it may take some time to have revised photomasks made and delivered. As a result, designers of the ALS (active) layers and of the first major interconnect layer (metal-1) often shy away from actually experimenting with too many permutations of critically dimensioned aspects such as contact size and inter-contact spacing. This may disadvantageously block them from finding optimal configurations for critically-dimensioned (CD'd) aspects of their designs.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Techniques are disclosed herein for giving designers of the so-called, Metal-1 interconnect layer, and of the insulation layer directly below it (ILD-0/1), more latitude in finding optimal configurations for critically-dimensioned (CD'd) aspects of those layers.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">INTRODUCTORY SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Structures and methods may be provided in accordance with the present disclosure of invention for improving over the above-described design problems.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">More specifically, in accordance with a first aspect of the present disclosure, during test and/or mass-production of integrated device wafers a lithographic photomask is used to project an image of ILD through-holes onto a photoresist (PR) layer disposed above an interlayer dielectric (ILD) of the in-process wafers. An ARC layer (Anti-Reflection Coating layer) is interposed between the PR and the ILD layers. Vertical through-holes are etched through the photoresist layer in accordance with the projected mask image. However, when it comes to continuing the through-holes through the ARC layer, an inwardly-tapering etch process is used. In the inwardly-tapering etch process, an etch recipe that excessively protects ARC sidewall material from being quickly eroded away is used. As a result of the sidewall etch inhibiting mechanism, a centrally-oriented vertical etch rate along a center line of an ARC layer opening (along a vertical line spaced away from sidewalls) substantially exceeds sidewall-adjacent vertical etch rate and a sloped sidewall results. This sloped-sidewall etch mechanism causes the opening dimensions at the bottom of the ARC layer through-holes to be substantially smaller than those at the top of the ARC layer through-holes.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The inwardly-tapered through-holes of the ARC layer are then used for masking, a vertical etch-formation of openings through the ILD layer. As a result, the vertically etched-through openings in the ILD have smaller width dimensions than corresponding dimensions of the lithographic image that had been projected onto the photoresist from the photomask. By adjusting the sidewall-sloping angle of the inwardly-tapering etch process used on the ARC layer, a same lithography mask and same optics settings may be used over and over while creating vertical etch-through openings through the ILD layer of different opening dimensions. Designers can conveniently experiment with different vertical opening dimensions so as to find better permutations of contact width and interconnect pitch.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A further aspect of the disclosure is that a mask-protecting etch recipe is also used for etching through the ILD (interlayer dielectric), where the etch recipe selectively protects the tapered openings in the ARC layer from excessive wearing away.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">An in-process wafer in accordance with the present disclosure may comprise: a photoresist layer (PR layer) disposed over an interlayer dielectric (ILD) with an ARC layer interposed between the PR layer and the ILD, where first openings of respective first widths are defined through the PR layer and where, inwardly tapering, second openings are defined through the ARC layer continuing from the first openings of the PR layer and tapering to substantially smaller and respective, second opening widths in the ARC layer. An in-process wafer in accordance with the present disclosure may further comprise: respective and vertical, third openings are defined through the ILD and continuing from the inwardly tapering, second openings of the ARC layer.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">A contact forming method in accordance with the present disclosure may comprise: (a) patterning an organic photoresist layer which is provided over an organic ARC layer, where the ARC layer is provided over a dielectric layer, the patterning of the photoresist layer causing through-holes to be defined in the photoresist layer; (b) using an inwardly-tapering etch process to continue the through-holes of the photoresist layer into the ARC layer as inwardly-tapered through-holes of the ARC layer; (c) using an anisotropic etch process to continue the inwardly-tapered through-holes of the ARC layer into the dielectric layer as substantially vertical contact holes through the dielectric layer; and (d) filling the substantially vertical contact holes with an electrical conductor.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Other aspects of the disclosure will become apparent from the below detailed description.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The below detailed description section makes reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a wireframe perspective diagram for introducing issues associated with making contact to the active layers set of an integrated circuit and with forming interconnect lines in the metal-1 layer;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a first schematic cross sectional view of an in-process wafer that is being fabricated in accordance with the disclosure and that has a developed photoresist layer at its top;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a second schematic cross sectional view continuing the process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> and showing a state where inwardly-tapering openings have been formed in the ARC layer;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> is a third schematic cross sectional view continuing the process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> and showing a state where vertical openings have been formed in the interlayer dielectric material to reach the active layers set (e.g., transistor gate, drain and source electrodes);</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref> is a fourth schematic cross sectional view continuing the process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> and showing a state where the ARC layer has been removed;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2E</figref> is a fifth schematic cross sectional view continuing the process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref> and showing a state where the vertical vias in the interlayer dielectric have been filled with metal;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref> is a sixth schematic cross sectional view continuing the process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2E</figref> and showing a state where the metal-1 interconnect layer has been patterned;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> includes a graph showing experimental results following use of different ARC tapering recipes;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> includes a graph showing different ARC tapering results for densely-packed and relatively isolated ARC openings;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref> includes a graph showing ARC tapering results as a function of etch time; and</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic diagram showing some of the mechanisms which may be responsible for creating and maintaining a tapered slope.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a wireframe perspective view (a see-through view) is provided in order to explain a fabrication environment <b>100</b> in which through-holes are made through a first interlayer dielectric (ILD-0/1) material layer to provide contact between a set of material layers referred to herein as the active layers set (ALS <b>119</b>), and a first major interconnect layer (Metal-1 layer <b>140</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">More specifically, in the illustrated fabrication environment <b>100</b>, a base substrate <b>110</b> is provided. The substrate <b>110</b> may be composed of monocrystalline silicon or another suitable material (e.g., SiGe) depending on application. A first gate-defining layer <b>120</b>, such as made of polysilicon or another suitable material is disposed above the substrate <b>110</b>. A first gate dielectric layer <b>115</b>, such as made of a thermally-grown silicon oxide or another suitable material is interposed between the substrate <b>110</b> and the first gate-defining layer <b>120</b>. There could be additional gate-defining layers (e.g., poly-2) and further gate dielectric layers. There could be no gate oxide or gate electrode layer if a gateless technology such as bipolar junction transistors is used. For sake of simplicity, a single-gate, horizontal MOS-FET transistor technology is assumed in the illustrated example. Each single gate, horizontal MOS-FET may be comprised of respective source and drain regions, <b>112</b> and <b>114</b>, with a channel provided between. The dimensions of modern transistors tend to be very small. By way of example, channel lengths in the deep submicron range or smaller are currently common. Source, drain, and gate contact areas tend to have proportionally small dimensions. For example, a source contact region may be circular in shape and may have a diameter of 500 nanometers (nm) or less.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">A rough definition for the active layers set (ALS <b>119</b>) has been introduced above. Within the context of the present disclosure, transistor forming layers such as the substrate <b>110</b> (or an epitaxially grown surface thereof), the gate dielectric <b>115</b> and the gate-electrode <b>120</b> defining layers (e.g., poly-1) can be considered part of the active layers set <b>119</b>. More generally, any set of layers where relatively closely spaced components (e.g., electrical and/or optical) are provided may be considered as part of the active layers set <b>119</b>. Thus, if <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> had alternatively shown the presence of a second polysilicon gate layer and a control gate dielectric layer, those too would typically have been considered as part of the active layers set <b>119</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Those skilled in the art will appreciate that the components of the active layers set <b>119</b> are typically the most closely spaced together parts of the monolithically integrated device. The problem is how to operatively couple to the components of the active layers set <b>119</b> so that interconnection between the components and/or communication with the components of the active layers set <b>119</b> may be made while fabricating in a mass-production environment. The problem is how to do so without running into problems such as undesired shorts or opens. The problem is how to do so while achieving circuit switching speeds and/or signal transmission times within pre-specified tolerance windows. These are significant problems.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The specific example <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> includes a first metal layer <b>140</b> (Metal-1) that is insulatively supported above the active layers set <b>119</b>. This Metal-1 layer <b>140</b> is to be used for interconnecting different parts (e.g., different transistors) of the active layers set <b>119</b> to one another and/or to elements in higher layers (e.g., in the Metal-2 layer, <b>160</b>). A first interlayer dielectric (ILD) film <b>130</b> is provided to separate the densely-populated active layers <b>119</b> from the first major interconnect layer (Metal-1, <b>140</b>). The first major interconnect layer (<b>140</b>) is usually one of the most densely populated and densely patterned of the interconnect layers (<b>140</b>, <b>160</b>, etc.) in terms of numbers of interconnect lines, in terms of interconnect line widths and in terms of spacing provided between interconnect lines. The need for such dense patterning is understandable given that the first major interconnect layer (<b>140</b>) makes primary contact with the active layers set <b>119</b> (the set that is usually most densely populated with active components, e.g., transistors, diodes, etc.). Often, if a connection to a component terminal in the ALS is to be made at all, it will be made by way of a contact extending vertically from the first major interconnect layer (<b>140</b>) to the ALS (<b>119</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Typically, there will be provided above the first major interconnect layer (<b>140</b>) additional layers of alternating insulation (e.g., ILD <b>150</b>) and conducting material (e.g., Metal-2 <b>160</b>). It is possible for contact holes to be made directly from the Metal-2 layer <b>160</b> to the active layers set <b>119</b> and for these long-reach holes (not shown) to be filled with metal. This is not typically done. However, to avoid possible confusion, short-reach contact holes; meaning the ones which are designed to extend upwardly from the active layers set <b>119</b> (hereafter, also conductive LAYER-0) to make connection with the first major interconnect layer <b>140</b> (hereafter, also conductive LAYER-1) will be referenced as “0/1 vias” and their respective, hole-filling and signal-conducting material (e.g., tungsten), if any, will be referenced as “0/1 plugs”. Similarly, short-reach contact holes which are designed to reach from conductive LAYER-1 (e.g., Metal-1 layer <b>140</b>) to make connection with conductive LAYER-2 (e.g., Metal-2 layer <b>160</b>) will be referenced as “1/2 vias” and their respective, hole-filling and signal-conducting material, if any, will be referenced as “1/2 plugs”. A cylindrically-shaped, 0/1 via is shown at <b>135</b> in wireframe format and it is understood to be conformably filled with a cylindrically-shaped, 0/1 plug (e.g., a tungsten plug). Similarly, a frusto-conically shaped, 1/2 via is shown at <b>155</b> in wireframe format and it is understood to be conformably filled with a frusto-conically shaped, 1/2 plug, where the smaller diameter end of the frusto-cone makes contact with an interconnect line <b>145</b> in conductive LAYER-1 (<b>140</b>) and the where the larger diameter end of the frusto-cone makes contact with an interconnect line <b>165</b> in conductive LAYER-2 (<b>160</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The insulating material which defines at least part of each major insulating layer (<b>130</b>, <b>150</b>, etc.) will be similarly referenced. Thus, “ILD 0/1” is the insulating layer material which separates conductive LAYER-0 (the active layers set <b>119</b>) from conductive LAYER-1 (e.g., the Metal-1 layer <b>140</b>). Similarly, “ILD 1/2” is the insulating layer material which separates conductive LAYER-1 from conductive LAYER-2, and so forth.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">After the active layers set <b>119</b> has been defined and the ILD-0/1 material (<b>130</b>, e.g., silicon dioxide) is deposited or otherwise layered on top of set <b>119</b>, the 0/1 through-holes or vias are formed through the ILD-0/1 film for providing passageways for the so-called, short-reach contact connections between the active layers set <b>119</b> and the first major interconnect layer (<b>140</b>, e.g., Metal-1). The locations and diameters (or other cross-sectional dimensions) of these 0/1 vias are usually defined lithographically by a dielectric-etch photomask such as shown at <b>190</b>. More specifically, the location and on-photomask diameter <b>195</b><i>c </i>of a given on-photomask feature <b>195</b> will be translated (<b>198</b>) by optical transfer means (e.g., 5:1 reduction optics), and photoresist chemistry effects (e.g., optical proximity effects), and etch chemistry effects, into a corresponding 0/1 via <b>135</b>′ having a first contact diameter <b>135</b><i>a </i>at its interface with conductive LAYER-0 and having a second contact diameter <b>135</b><i>b </i>at its interface with conductive LAYER-1 (Metal-1). For reasons that will be given shortly, it is desirable for diameters <b>135</b><i>a </i>and <b>135</b><i>b </i>to be fairly close in size to one another so that the corresponding 0/1 via <b>135</b>′ and its filling 0/1 plug (also denoted as <b>135</b>′) will have a sidewall profile that is essentially vertical (about 90 degrees).</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In addition to defining contact via widths (e.g., <b>135</b><i>a</i>), the 0/1 dielectric-etch photomask <b>190</b> will also define separation distances between such ILD-0/1 elements. One such separation-defining aspect of mask <b>190</b> is shown at <b>196</b> as the on-mask distance between adjacent ones of the on-photomask, via-defining features (e.g., <b>195</b>). The on-photomask locations and on-photomask dimensions of such separation distances (e.g., <b>196</b>) will also be translated by optical transfer means (e.g., 5:1 reduction optics), and photoresist chemistry effects (e.g., optical proximity effects), and etch chemistry effects into corresponding separation distances within the ILD-0/1 region, such as separation <b>136</b> shown between the rightmost 0/1 vias.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Certain ones of the on-photomask, and via-defining features (e.g., <b>195</b>) and certain ones of the on-photomask, and separation-defining distances (e.g., <b>196</b>) will be designated as having critical dimensions (CD's). The critically dimensioned via-defining features (<b>195</b>) and/or separation-defining distances (<b>196</b>) of the photomask <b>190</b> are often associated with counterpart, and in-wafer features which are also deemed as being critically dimensioned because they are most difficult to consistently form on a mass-production basis in the in-process wafers and their proper formation is critical to desired operation of the integrated device. (Substrate <b>110</b> is understood to be part of such a wafer. Dimension <b>135</b><i>a </i>may be an in-wafer CD and dimension <b>136</b> may also be an in-wafer CD.) Consistent mass-production of the in-wafer, CD elements (critically dimensioned features) will often depend on what is done during a subsequent one or more photoresist development processes associated with ILD-0/1 (see briefly, photoresist layer <b>280</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>). Consistent mass-production of the in-wafer, CD elements will also often depend on what is done during a subsequent one or more dielectric etch processes which etch through the 0/1 ILD, and also on what is done during a subsequent one or more via-filling processes that fill 0/1 vias. The critically dimensioned features of the photomask <b>190</b> may alternatively or additionally be defined by what formational challenges these on-photomask features (<b>195</b> and/or <b>196</b>) place on a more downstream processes, where the more downstream processes define conductive LAYER-1 (e.g., the Metal-1 layer <b>140</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Because the critically dimensioned features of the 0/1 etch photomask <b>190</b> usually push photomask-making technology close to its available limits, manufacturing and inspection of such a 0/1 etch photomask <b>190</b> can be both time-consuming and expensive. If designers of conductive LAYER-1 decide they want to change critically dimensioned line widths <b>145</b><i>b </i>and/or critically dimensioned line separations <b>145</b><i>c </i>within the patterned version of conductive LAYER-1 (metal-1 <b>140</b>), it may be very difficult for the designers of the 0/1-etch photomask <b>190</b> to provide an accommodatingly revised, 0/1-etch photomask <b>190</b>′ (revised version not shown) for doing so in acceptably short time. Typically there will be optical proximity effects to be considered and corrected (by way of OPC) before a workable substitute photomask can be provided. The present disclosure provides an alternate way in which vertically-profiled 0/1 vias (e.g., <b>135</b>) can be provided in the ILD-0/1 layer (<b>130</b>) where the widths (e.g., diameters <b>135</b><i>a</i>, <b>135</b><i>b</i>) of the 0/1 vias can be changed and/or the separations <b>136</b> between such substantially vertically-profiled 0/1 vias can be changed without having to change the 0/1-etch photomask <b>190</b> and/or the 0/1 photoresist exposure and photoresist development processes (part of process <b>198</b>) that rely on that 0/1-etch photomask <b>190</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The reason why it is desirable to maintain the 0/1 vias and 0/1 plugs <b>135</b> with substantially vertical sidewall profiles is fairly straight forward. Any substantial increase of width (e.g., diameter) <b>135</b><i>a </i>at the conductive LAYER-0 interface can increase alignment problems with underlying LAYER-0 component terminals (e.g., <b>112</b>, <b>114</b>, <b>120</b>). Any substantial increase of width (e.g., diameter) <b>135</b><i>b </i>at the conductive LAYER-1 interface can increase alignment problems with overlying LAYER-1 interconnect lines <b>145</b>. The design pressures are such as to keep each of the top contact dimension <b>135</b><i>b </i>and bottom contact dimension as small as possible without becoming so small that contact is lost or electrical resistance becomes excessive. A cylindrical profile satisfies all these design pressures. Often, the LAYER-1 interconnect lines <b>145</b> will have to be packed very tightly together because contact with each respective one of the many underlying component nodes (e.g., <b>112</b>, <b>114</b>, <b>120</b>) has to be made, if at all, by way of an overlying LAYER-1 interconnect line <b>145</b>. Similar design pressures often do not exist for higher ILD's (e.g., <b>150</b>) and as such, contact plugs (e.g., <b>155</b>) in those higher ILD's may be made with substantially tapered profiles as is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The interconnect lines (e.g., <b>165</b>) in the higher interconnect layers (e.g., Metal-2, <b>160</b>) tend to be wider than those (e.g., <b>145</b>) in the first major interconnect layer (Metal-1, <b>140</b>). A width expanding process may be used for increasing via width in the upward direction. Such width expansion may rely on an etch process that has lateral etch rate anisotropy. The lateral etch undercuts an etch mask and creates the wider contact size near the higher interconnect layer (e.g., Metal-2, <b>160</b>). Such lateral etching is not practical for the densely patterned, first major interconnect layer (Metal-1, <b>140</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, a first state <b>201</b> in accordance with the disclosure is illustrated by way of a cross sectional, schematic view. An active layers set (ALS) is shown at <b>210</b>. In one embodiment, the ALS <b>210</b> includes a monocrystalline semiconductor substrate composed, for example, of silicon. The substrate includes a plurality of doped regions such as N regions <b>212</b>, <b>214</b> and P region <b>215</b>. The doped regions (e.g., <b>212</b>, <b>214</b>, <b>215</b>) may define termination areas (e.g., ohmic contact regions) for various active components such as transistors, diodes, etc. By way of more specific example, the lateral dimensions of the illustrated termination areas (e.g., <b>212</b>, <b>214</b>, <b>215</b>) can be as small as about 500 nanometers or less. It is desirable in the more specific example to create substantially, vertically-profiled contact vias (0/1 vias) down to these termination areas where a bottom width dimension (<b>135</b><i>a</i>) of the 0/1 vias (not yet shown, see briefly <b>231</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>) may need to be as small as about 200 nanometers or less.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The illustrated ILD-0/1 layer <b>230</b> that is provided above ALS <b>210</b> may be composed of a plasma-deposited, inorganic dielectric such as HDP-deposited TEOS (Tetra-Ethyl-OrthoSilicate) or another such silicon-oxide based insulator. In one set of embodiments, the ILD-0/1 layer <b>230</b> has a thickness of about 0.1 μm or more and is composed essentially of CVD silicon dioxide or of spun-on silicon oxide. The inorganic dielectric material of ILD-0/1 layer <b>230</b> can be etched by reactive ion plasmas (REI plasmas) which include fluorine containing compounds such as CF<sub>4 </sub>or CHF<sub>3</sub>. The dielectric etching plasma may also contain one or more inert bombardment gases such as argon. Alternative or additional inert bombardment gases may be selected from the group including neon, xenon, krypton and nitrogen. (Note nitrogen is not a noble gas, but it may be used in various circumstances as a substantially non-reactive bombardment component, particularly where the layer being bombarded, i.e. the ARC layer, is not going to be retained in the final product, namely the manufactured and monolithically integrated circuit.)</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The ILD-0/1 layer is to be lithographically patterned. However, when a photoresist layer such as <b>280</b> is exposed to mask-patterned radiation (e.g., UV light), undesired reflections may be produced by reflective surfaces (e.g., silicon) below the photoresist layer. It is therefore common to provide an Anti-Reflection Coating (ARC) layer <b>270</b> immediately below the photoresist layer. The ARC layer may be composed of any one of a variety of organic compounds that absorb light at wavelengths such as those used for imaging the overlying photoresist layer <b>280</b>. In one embodiment, the organic ARC layer <b>270</b> typically has a thickness of about 100 Å to 1000 Å or more. In one embodiment, the ARC layer has a thickness of about 700 Å to 800 Å (about 750 Å as an average). The overlying photoresist layer <b>280</b> may be composed of a UV-sensitive photoresist material such as UV<b>6</b> and may have a thickness of about 0.61 μm or less. Both the PR layer <b>280</b> and the ARC layer may be stripped away by plasma volatilization after they are no longer useful.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In the illustrated example of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, the photomask <b>290</b> has a first feature <b>295</b> for photolithographically defining corresponding opening <b>281</b> in the PR layer <b>280</b>. The photomask <b>290</b> has a second feature <b>296</b> for photolithographically defining a corresponding solid region <b>282</b> in the PR layer <b>280</b>. Appropriate focusing and/or image reduction mechanisms in an optics system <b>288</b> are used for projecting a mask image <b>283</b> onto the PR layer <b>280</b> where the projected image <b>283</b> has a width dimension such as <b>285</b> for defining respective PR opening <b>281</b> and it has a width dimension such as <b>286</b> for defining respective solid part <b>282</b>. In one embodiment, the openings <b>281</b> of the post-development photoresist layer <b>280</b> have substantially vertical sidewalls with a slope angle in the range of about 87 to 90 degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">On first glance, it may appear that dimensions of the projected image <b>283</b>, such as opening width <b>285</b> or solid width <b>286</b> can be easily changed simply by changing the magnification power of the optics system <b>288</b>. This is not correct for several reasons. First, there is the problem of the optical proximity effects that occur during exposure of the photoresist <b>280</b>. Dimension specific, optical proximity corrections (OPC's) may have been worked into the design of the photomask <b>290</b>. Therefore, projected image dimensions such as <b>285</b> and <b>286</b> may not be practically varied merely by changing the magnification or reduction power of the optics system <b>288</b>. Secondly, the whole of the projected reticle image <b>283</b> must fit into a prescribed area and various portions (e.g., <b>281</b>, <b>282</b>) of the projected reticle image <b>283</b> must align with underlying parts (e.g., <b>212</b>-<b>215</b>) of the active layers set (ALS) <b>210</b>. This is yet another fundamental reason why the image reduction factor (e.g., 5:1) of the optics <b>288</b> cannot be practically varied after the photomask <b>290</b> is made. Nonetheless, a practical method will be disclosed whereby contact widths can be reduced and contact separation distances can be increased without altering the photomask <b>290</b> and/or the photoresist exposure and development processes.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, a second state <b>202</b> in accordance with the disclosure is illustrated by way of a cross sectional view. For each of the through-hole openings <b>281</b> made in the post-development PR layer <b>280</b>′, corresponding and inwardly-tapering through-holes <b>271</b> are made in the ARC layer <b>270</b>′. The holes <b>271</b> are bounded in the illustration by sloped sidewall surfaces such as <b>272</b><i>a </i>and a lateral bottom surface such as <b>271</b><i>a</i>. A variety of slope-inducing etch mechanisms may be used for creating the inward tapers of holes <b>271</b>. Generally these etch mechanisms may be characterized by a relatively low sidewall etch rate and a comparatively high deposition rate for sidewall-etch inhibitors. Examples of sidewall-etch inhibitors include polymeric compounds which tend to cling to organic sidewall material, and build up on the sidewalls, and protect the coated sidewalls against etching. More on this when <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is explained.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The slope-inducing etch mechanism(s) used for creating inwardly-tapered openings <b>271</b> cause(s) the opening width dimensions <b>275</b> at the bottoms <b>271</b><i>a </i>of the through-holes <b>271</b> to be substantially smaller than those (e.g., <b>285</b>′) at the tops of the respective ARC layer through-holes <b>271</b>. (The prime {′} in <b>285</b>′ indicates that this dimension may be slightly different from <b>285</b> <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> as a result of the etch used to create holes <b>271</b>.) One specific example of a sloped-holes creating mechanism is a Reactive Ion Etch (RIE) which uses a plasma containing a combination of CF<sub>4 </sub>and CHF<sub>3 </sub>together with an inert bombardment gas such as argon, where CHF<sub>3 </sub>content is increased above normal. More specifically, the amount of CHF<sub>3 </sub>is increased to encourage the generation within the RIE plasma (not shown) of sidewall-etch inhibiting, organic polymer material for attaching to the ARC sidewalls <b>272</b><i>a </i>of forming holes <b>271</b>. The etch-inhibiting polymer accumulates more on the earlier-exposed, higher-up sidewall surfaces and thus inhibits their further erosion. In one embodiment, the volumetric flow ratio of CF<sub>4 </sub>(in sccm) to CHF<sub>3 </sub>(also measured in sccm) is reduced to substantially less than 5:1 (5-to-one), and more preferably, to less than about 3:1, and yet more preferably, to being at or less than about 1:1.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">It is believed that the CF<sub>4 </sub>component of the plasma produces fluorine radicals which tend to isotropically etch away exposed parts of the organic, ARC material. The CHF<sub>3 </sub>content in the plasma is believed to produce polymeric organic compounds which attach to and protectively cover the ARC material. Argon ions are believed to be propelled by electric fields to move mostly in the vertical direction to bombard and erode-away etch inhibitors, mostly from the bottom surfaces <b>271</b><i>a</i>, thereby allowing fluorine radicals to eat away at those bottom surfaces <b>271</b><i>a</i>. An inwardly-growing ring (not shown) of accumulating polymer slowly reduces the surface area at the bottoms <b>271</b><i>a </i>which is available for attack by argon and fluorine. Increasing the ratio of CHF<sub>3 </sub>to CF<sub>4 </sub>increases the rate at which the protective bottom ring shrinks inwardly along bottom surface <b>271</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">For one specific etch tool (the Applied Materials eMax™ Centura™ dielectric etch tool) it was observed that a CF<sub>4</sub>/CHF<sub>3 </sub>flow ratio (in sccm/sccm) of about 5:1 should be used if a substantially vertical sidewall profile is desired for the through-holes of the ARC layer <b>270</b>. However, in accordance with the present disclosure, the CF<sub>4</sub>/CHF<sub>3 </sub>flow ratio is intentionally altered toward being less than about 3:1, and yet more preferably, toward being at or less than about 1:1 so that inhibitor deposition rate on the organic sidewalls <b>272</b><i>a </i>(and also on PR sidewalls <b>282</b><i>a</i>) is greater and inwardly tapering of the through-holes <b>271</b> results as a consequence.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In one embodiment, an ARC etching recipe of 60 sccm CF<sub>4</sub>, 60 sccm CHF<sub>3 </sub>and 100 sccm Ar was used in a magnetically-enhanced reactive ion plasma etch tool such as the Applied Materials eMax™ Centura™ dielectric etch tool with a pressure of 100 mT (milliTorr), a power setting of 300 W (Watts) and a magnetic field setting of 30 G (Gauss) to achieve the 1:1 CF<sub>4</sub>/CHF<sub>3 </sub>flow ratio. Observed via width reduction was about 13% (going down from a 0.205 μm average diameter to a 0.178 μm average diameter as further explicated below). In the given case, the thickness of the ARC layer was about 750 Angstroms and the inward slope angle was therefore about 10 degrees off the perpendicular. Greater slopes are achievable. Workable slopes off the perpendicular can be in the range of about 4 to about 40 degrees, or more particularly in the range of about 7 to about 22 degrees. The bottom width dimension <b>275</b> is a function of ARC layer thickness as well as inward-taper slope. Accordingly both should be considered in determining how to realize a desired reduction of hole size <b>275</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">It may be understood from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> that bottom hole size <b>275</b> is not the only dimension which changes as a result of tapered etching. At the same time that the bottom dimension <b>275</b> of each inwardly-tapered and respective, ARC opening (e.g., <b>271</b>) is made substantially smaller (e.g., 13% smaller than the top opening <b>285</b>′), the bottom dimension <b>276</b> of each corresponding and trapezoidally-shaped, solid section (e.g., <b>272</b>) in the ARC layer is made commensurately larger than the corresponding width dimension <b>286</b>′ of the overlying and respective, PR solid section <b>282</b>. It will be seen shortly that each such, increased, bottom dimension <b>276</b> of the corresponding solid part <b>272</b> of the ARC layer can be associated with a respective, plug separation distance. (See briefly <b>236</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>). It will be seen shortly that each bottom opening dimension <b>275</b> of each inwardly-tapered ARC opening <b>271</b> can be associated with a respective, plug width dimension. (See briefly, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2E</figref>.)</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>, a third state <b>203</b> in accordance with the disclosure is illustrated by way of a cross sectional view. A selective and primarily vertically directed, dielectric etch process <b>208</b> is used to etch substantially vertical through-holes <b>231</b> through the ILD <b>230</b>′ while using the inwardly-tapered openings <b>271</b> of the ARC layer <b>270</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>) as masking means for defining the width dimensions <b>235</b> of the dielectric through-holes <b>231</b>. During the etching of the material of ILD <b>230</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, e.g., SiO<sub>2</sub>), some erosion may take place in the overlying ARC material <b>270</b>′. Therefore the end state <b>271</b>′ of the ARC openings may be slightly wider than what was originally present when the dielectric etch process <b>208</b> began. Dashed lines <b>271</b><i>b </i>indicate a possible “before” profile of the ARC openings <b>271</b>. As can be seen, the bottom corners <b>272</b><i>b </i>of the ARC solid regions <b>272</b>′ may be slightly eroded away, more so than the top corners <b>272</b><i>t </i>of such solid regions <b>272</b>′. This is because the bottom ARC corners <b>272</b><i>b </i>are not protected by the overlying solid material <b>282</b> of the PR layer <b>280</b>′ as are the top corners <b>272</b><i>t. </i></p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In order to prevent excessive erosion of the exposed bottom corners <b>271</b><i>b </i>of the ARC solid regions <b>272</b>′, a substantially carbonaceous, etch recipe may be used for protectively covering the organic surface material of the bottom ARC corners <b>272</b><i>b</i>. Selective adhesion of such a carbonaceous coating to the exposed ARC surfaces <b>272</b>′ can help to minimize their erosion during the creation of vertical through-holes <b>231</b> in the ILD. More specifically, in one embodiment, the dielectric etch process <b>208</b> comprises the use of a 40 sccm flow of C<sub>4</sub>F<sub>6</sub>, 25 sccm of O<sub>2</sub>, 250 sccm of CO and 350 sccm of Ar in an Applied Materials eMax™ Centura™ dielectric etch tool with a pressure setting of 30 mT (milliTorr), a power setting of 1000 W (Watts) and a magnetic field setting of 50 G (Gauss) for 280 seconds to achieve the substantially vertical etch-through of vias <b>231</b> through an ILD <b>230</b>′ having a thickness of about 0.1 um or more. The inclusion of the significant carbon monoxide content (e.g., 250 standard cubic centimeters per minute of CO) into the plasma mix is believed to generate a carbonaceous coating material which preferentially adheres to the organic surface material of the ARC surfaces, including to corners <b>272</b><i>b</i>, but not so much to the inorganic material of the ILD material <b>230</b>′. This preferential adherence is believed to cause the carbonaceous dielectric etch process <b>208</b> to be selective for vertical removal of the ILD material <b>230</b>′ as opposed to removal of the ARC material at bottom ARC corners <b>272</b><i>b</i>. As a result, much of the bottom corner material <b>272</b><i>b </i>of the taper-etched ARC layer (<b>270</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>) is preserved and a substantial reduction in contact width size (<b>235</b> as opposed to <b>285</b>″) is therefore realized.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">A previous etch recipe for creating through-holes through the ILD layer <b>230</b> was constituted by a 15 sccm flow of C<sub>4</sub>F<sub>6</sub>, 10 sccm Of O<sub>2</sub>, 0 sccm of CO and 350 sccm of Ar in an Applied Materials eMax™ Centura™ dielectric etch tool with a pressure of 30 mT (milliTorr), a power setting of 1600 W (Watts) and a magnetic field setting of 50 G (Gauss) for 160 seconds to achieve the substantially vertical etch-through of vias through the same thickness of dielectric material. If this previous etch recipe is compared against the newer, carbon-monoxide containing recipe (above), it can be seen that the newer etch recipe is characterized by a longer etch time, a lower power setting, substantially increased flow rates for the C<sub>4</sub>F<sub>6 </sub>and O<sub>2 </sub>input gases, and of course, the addition of the carbon monoxide input gas. Other alternatives may be used for providing the ARC-protecting, carbonaceous coating material of the newer etch recipe. In place of, or in addition to the carbon monoxide (CO) input gas, CO<sub>2 </sub>for example, may be used as a carbon source.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>, a fourth state <b>204</b> in accordance with the disclosure is illustrated by way of a cross sectional view. The photoresist layer <b>280</b>′ and ARC layer <b>270</b>′ of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> have been stripped away by plasma ashing or other appropriate means. ILD layer <b>230</b>″ is left behind with substantially vertical, contact vias <b>231</b>′ (e.g., with sidewalls of about 0 to 2 degrees slant off the perfect perpendicular) extending through to respective active layers set, contact regions such as <b>212</b>′, <b>214</b>′ and <b>215</b>′. (For purpose of safety margin, the vias cut slightly into the ALS contact regions <b>212</b>′, <b>214</b>′, <b>215</b>′ etc.) The formed vias <b>231</b>′ have corresponding via widths <b>235</b> that have been derived from the inwardly-tapered openings <b>271</b>′ of the ARC layer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>. Spacings <b>236</b> between the formed vias <b>231</b>′ have corresponding dimensions that are also attributed to the bottom dimensions of the inwardly-tapered openings <b>271</b>′ of the ARC layer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2E</figref>, a fifth state <b>205</b> in accordance with the disclosure is illustrated by way of a cross sectional view. A filling metal material <b>240</b> such as tungsten (W) is sputter deposited or otherwise provided to fill the open vias <b>231</b>′ of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref> and to cover the tops of the solid ILD islands (e.g., of dimensions <b>236</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>). Element <b>242</b> is a metal plug that conformably fills via <b>231</b>′ (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>) and makes operative contact with active region <b>214</b>″ (e.g., an N+ doped, ohmic contact region). In one embodiment, additional barrier metal films may be pre-deposited on top of the ILD mesas, such as made of TiN.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref>, a sixth state <b>206</b> in accordance with the disclosure is illustrated by way of a cross sectional view. A new photomask <b>297</b> is used to project a further lithographic image through optics system <b>287</b> onto a photoresist layer (not shown) that was earlier deposited on metal layer <b>240</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2E</figref>. That PR layer (not shown) would have been developed and used for etching new openings such as <b>241</b><i>a</i>-<b>241</b><i>c </i>in the illustrated metal layer <b>240</b>′ of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref>. The metal layer openings <b>241</b> have respective opening dimensions such as <b>245</b><i>c </i>of opening <b>241</b><i>a</i>, where the latter opening dimensions correspond to features <b>298</b> of the new photomask <b>297</b>. Additionally, interconnect lines such as metal island <b>243</b><i>c </i>(shown in cross section) are defined to have respective line-width dimensions such as represented by <b>245</b><i>b</i>′. The line-width dimensions <b>245</b><i>b </i>correspond to features <b>299</b> of the new photomask <b>297</b>. Given that the widths of corresponding contact plugs <b>242</b><i>a</i>-<b>242</b><i>c </i>are defined by the tapered ARC openings <b>271</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> and by the separations <b>236</b> between the contact plugs, it may be seen that the interconnect combination of plugs <b>242</b> and lines <b>243</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref> has been partially defined by the tapered ARC openings <b>271</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">More specifically, for the illustrated example of interconnect lines <b>243</b><i>a</i>-<b>243</b><i>b </i>(associated with respective plugs <b>242</b><i>a </i>and <b>242</b><i>b</i>), a greater, lines-separation distance <b>245</b><i>c </i>has been realized due to the increased separation distance <b>236</b><i>a </i>between contact plugs <b>242</b><i>a </i>and <b>242</b><i>b</i>. Alternatively or additionally, in the ALS <b>210</b>′″, a greater, terminal-separation distance <b>216</b><i>a </i>has been realized between component contact regions <b>212</b>′″ and <b>214</b>′″ due to the increased separation distance <b>236</b><i>a </i>realized between contact plugs <b>242</b><i>a </i>and <b>242</b><i>b</i>. The ability to increase contact separation distance <b>236</b><i>a </i>(through the inwardly-tapering process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2B-2C</figref>) gives design engineers some degrees of flexibility in determining where to place metal interconnect lines such as <b>243</b><i>a</i>-<b>243</b><i>b </i>and/or in determining where to place ALS contact regions such as <b>212</b>′″ and <b>214</b>′″. Such flexibility would not have been otherwise present if the flexible, ARC-hole tapering process (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2B-2C</figref>) were not available.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Alternatively or additionally in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref>, a shrunken (<b>216</b><i>c</i>) and/or positionally shifted (<b>216</b><i>b</i>) contact region <b>217</b>″ may be included in the design of the active layers set (ALS) <b>210</b>′″ due to the ability to reduce contact plug width dimensions <b>235</b> (not explicitly shown, see instead <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>). Such small changes in critically dimensioned separation distances (e.g., <b>236</b><i>a</i>, <b>245</b><i>c</i>, <b>216</b><i>a</i>) and/or component contact widths (<b>216</b><i>c</i>) or placements can have significant impact on device performance. Those skilled in the art will appreciate that switching speeds in the active layers set <b>210</b>′ and/or signal propagating characteristics of the interconnect (e.g., the patterned metal layer <b>240</b>′) can be fine tuned by altering a number of parameters including separation distances such as <b>236</b><i>a</i>, <b>245</b><i>c</i>, and/or <b>216</b><i>c</i>. The other factors which may come into play in determining device performance include, but are not limited to, doping profiles in the ALS <b>210</b>′, the composition of the metal used for defining plugs <b>242</b> and the rest of layer <b>240</b>′, the composition of the dielectric used for defining layer <b>230</b>″ (e.g., low-K or high-K), and the line widths <b>245</b><i>b </i>of the interconnect lines <b>243</b> in layer <b>240</b>′. Signal propagation characteristics of the fabricated device may also depend on the respective widths of metal plugs <b>242</b> since the RC contributions of these can play a role in determining device performance. Plug widths (see briefly <b>235</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>) can affect more than just the RLC transmission line characteristics of the Metal-1 interconnect. They can also affect mass-production yield because they may determine how closely the Metal-1 photomask <b>297</b> has to be aligned with ALS features (e.g., <b>212</b>″, <b>214</b>″, <b>217</b>″, etc.) in order to provide for consistent and reliable mass production of monolithically integrated device such as that shown being produced in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">As already explained above, device performance cannot always be precisely predicted with computer analysis tools. Situations may arise where the designers of the Metal-1 photomask <b>297</b> or of the ALS photomasks (not shown) wish to slightly change the patterning of their respective layers <b>240</b>′ and <b>210</b>′″. They may want to do so without forcing designers of the ILD layer <b>230</b>′″ to order a new via photomask <b>290</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>). In accordance with the present disclosure, some of these changes may be realized using the chemically-tailorable process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2B-2C</figref> without having to order a new via photomask <b>290</b>. Accordingly, designers can more readily experiment, in the physically realized sense, with changing plug widths (e.g., <b>235</b>) and/or plug separations distances (e.g., <b>236</b><i>a</i>) and/or other parameters (e.g., line spacing <b>245</b><i>c</i>′) of critically dimensioned parts in order to see how such changes may affect device performance and/or mass-reproducibility and reliability. The present disclosure therefore contemplates the use of ARC tapering to different plug widths and/or plug-separation distances so that comparative wafer samples can be generated by use of variable tapering and the produced wafers can then be physically tested and the test results compared to see which of different contact plug widths (<b>235</b>) and/or separation distances (e.g., <b>216</b><i>a</i>) provides the best of desired wafer characteristics (e.g., high switching speed, low power consumption, high mass production yield, good reliability, etc.).</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> includes a first graph <b>301</b> which shows some experimental results that have been obtained from use of different ARC tapering recipes. The graph suggests that a good range of fine tunability is available for defining average opening size (bottom diameter <b>335</b><i>a</i>) of the ILD-0/1 vias (<b>335</b>′), and distinct min/max ranges for mass production of wafers with such ARC-controlled ILD-0/1 vias. The experimental results are given in more detail in below Table 1A. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> shows only average and min/max results for so-called star measurement points (MP's). Yet other details from the same experiments are given in Table 1B.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Three sample wafers were used for each given flow ratio of CF<sub>4 </sub>versus CHF<sub>3</sub>, namely, three for the 5:1 ratio, three for the 3:1 ratio, and three for the 1:1 ratio. The sample wafers were all made with a same photomask <b>390</b> and photoresist development process <b>398</b> The photomask <b>390</b> included feature areas defining relatively sparse via populations (relatively “isolated” vias) such as the one represented at <b>395</b>. The photomask <b>390</b> also included yet other feature areas with relatively dense populations of via features (for defining vias that are to be closely spaced apart e.g., about 2000 nm or less from each other on the corresponding wafer). such a “dense” population is schematically represented at <b>396</b>. Total gas flow rate and chamber pressures were kept crudely constant across the experiment. The experiment used approximately 100 sccm of Ar as the inert bombardment gas. Chamber pressure was set around 100 mT-150 mT, RF power was set at 300 W and magnetic filed was set at 30 G. Run time was about 20-60 seconds. Five sample measurement points were used in a star pattern on each of the nine wafers after via formation in the ILD and after ARC stripping (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>). A scanning electron microscope (SEM) was used to measure via diameters at the bottoms (<b>335</b><i>a</i>) of a respective 5 sample measurement points on each wafer. SEM observations were also made immediately after photoresist development (ADI is After Development Inspection) but before ARC and ILD etchings. “After Etch Inspection” (AIE) refers to the SEM measurements made after the ARC and ILD etchings but without metal plug fill. The “Bias” column of Table 1 B refers to AEI minus ADI. In other words, it looks for how much wider the post-etch vias were as compared to the substantially non-tapered PR openings (not shown, see briefly <b>281</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>). Besides the 5-star measurement points (MP's), additional measurements were taken separately for “Densely-packed” vias and for vias that were relatively Isolated (not Densely-packed). Average values and range between minimums and maximums were then calculated as shown in Tables 1A-1B.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">It may be seen from Tables 1A-1B and graph <b>301</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>) that the CH<sub>4 </sub>versus CHF<sub>3 </sub>flow ratio defines a tunable parameter which may be used to control the resultant via diameters. Table 1B indicates that the process tends to create the narrower vias where they are usually most needed, in the more densely-packed contact areas of the wafers. (In Table 1B, wafer recipe #8, some of the densely-packed vias did open fully to the slated width all the way down to the contact depth. Thus the 0.124 μm result is starred (**) as being a not wholly reliable number. The width was observed, but it was not always a complete opening all the way through to the bottom of the ILD through-hole.)</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0" pgwide="1">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="5">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="35pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="133pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" rowsep="1">TABLE 1A</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Process</entry>
<entry>Measurement Points</entry>
<entry>CD</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="10">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="6" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="7" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="8" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="9" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="10" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Condition</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry>CD</entry>
<entry>Average</entry>
<entry>Range</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Recipe #</entry>
<entry>CF4/CHF3</entry>
<entry>MP1</entry>
<entry>MP2</entry>
<entry>MP3</entry>
<entry>MP4</entry>
<entry>MP5</entry>
<entry>Average</entry>
<entry>(um)</entry>
<entry>(um)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="10" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry>5:1</entry>
<entry>0.203</entry>
<entry>0.212</entry>
<entry>0.215</entry>
<entry>0.205</entry>
<entry>0.207</entry>
<entry>0.208</entry>
<entry>0.205</entry>
<entry>0.026</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>0.213</entry>
<entry>0.189</entry>
<entry>0.210</entry>
<entry>0.189</entry>
<entry>0.195</entry>
<entry>0.199</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>0.211</entry>
<entry>0.202</entry>
<entry>0.203</entry>
<entry>0.215</entry>
<entry>0.207</entry>
<entry>0.208</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>4</entry>
<entry>3:1</entry>
<entry>0.205</entry>
<entry>0.192</entry>
<entry>0.198</entry>
<entry>0.197</entry>
<entry>0.189</entry>
<entry>0.196</entry>
<entry>0.197</entry>
<entry>0.022</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>5</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>0.199</entry>
<entry>0.210</entry>
<entry>0.193</entry>
<entry>0.202</entry>
<entry>0.201</entry>
<entry>0.201</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>6</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>0.192</entry>
<entry>0.204</entry>
<entry>0.188</entry>
<entry>0.199</entry>
<entry>0.190</entry>
<entry>0.194</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>7</entry>
<entry>1:1</entry>
<entry>0.182</entry>
<entry>0.183</entry>
<entry>0.179</entry>
<entry>0.182</entry>
<entry>0.175</entry>
<entry>0.180</entry>
<entry>0.178</entry>
<entry>0.016</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>8</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>0.182</entry>
<entry>0.171</entry>
<entry>0.176</entry>
<entry>0.175</entry>
<entry>0.167</entry>
<entry>0.174</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>9</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>0.180</entry>
<entry>0.182</entry>
<entry>0.177</entry>
<entry>0.183</entry>
<entry>0.182</entry>
<entry>0.181</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="10" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00002" num="00002">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0" pgwide="1">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="4">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="35pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="98pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="84pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="77pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="3" rowsep="1">TABLE 1B</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="3" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry>CD</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Process</entry>
<entry>Averages (μm)</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="9">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="6" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="7" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="8" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="9" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>Recipe #</entry>
<entry>
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mfrac>
  <mi>CF4</mi>
  <mi>CHF3</mi>
</mfrac>
</math>
</maths>
</entry>
<entry>
<maths id="MATH-US-00002" num="00002">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mfrac>
  <mi>CHF3</mi>
  <mi>Ar</mi>
</mfrac>
</math>
</maths>
</entry>
<entry>Press (mT)</entry>
<entry>MP's</entry>
<entry>Dense</entry>
<entry>Iso</entry>
<entry>CD Range</entry>
<entry>Bias Range</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="9" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="9">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="28pt" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colname="6" colwidth="35pt" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colname="7" colwidth="21pt" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colname="8" colwidth="35pt" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colname="9" colwidth="42pt" align="char" char="."/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry>5:1</entry>
<entry>2:1</entry>
<entry>100</entry>
<entry>0.208</entry>
<entry>0.199</entry>
<entry>0.176</entry>
<entry>0.047</entry>
<entry>0.100</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry>5:1</entry>
<entry>2:1</entry>
<entry>150</entry>
<entry>0.199</entry>
<entry>0.170</entry>
<entry>0.210</entry>
<entry>0.054</entry>
<entry>0.051</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry>5:1</entry>
<entry>4:1</entry>
<entry>100</entry>
<entry>0.208</entry>
<entry>0.170</entry>
<entry>0.213</entry>
<entry>0.050</entry>
<entry>0.028</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>4</entry>
<entry>3:1</entry>
<entry>2:1</entry>
<entry>100</entry>
<entry>0.196</entry>
<entry>0.171</entry>
<entry>0.187</entry>
<entry>0.043</entry>
<entry>0.060</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>5</entry>
<entry>3:1</entry>
<entry>2:1</entry>
<entry>150</entry>
<entry>0.201</entry>
<entry>0.165</entry>
<entry>0.190</entry>
<entry>0.046</entry>
<entry>0.034</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>6</entry>
<entry>3:1</entry>
<entry>4:1</entry>
<entry>100</entry>
<entry>0.194</entry>
<entry>0.137</entry>
<entry>0.182</entry>
<entry>0.069</entry>
<entry>0.014</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>7</entry>
<entry>1:1</entry>
<entry>2:1</entry>
<entry>100</entry>
<entry>0.180</entry>
<entry>0.130</entry>
<entry>0.167</entry>
<entry>0.070</entry>
<entry>0.052</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>8</entry>
<entry>1:1</entry>
<entry>2:1</entry>
<entry>150</entry>
<entry>0.174</entry>
<entry>0.124**</entry>
<entry>0.191</entry>
<entry>0.076</entry>
<entry>0.047</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>9</entry>
<entry>1:1</entry>
<entry>4:1</entry>
<entry>100</entry>
<entry>0.181</entry>
<entry>0.131</entry>
<entry>0.164</entry>
<entry>0.053</entry>
<entry>0.036</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>ADI</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry>0.209</entry>
<entry>0.147</entry>
<entry>0.192</entry>
<entry>0.077</entry>
<entry>0</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="9" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The common photomask <b>390</b> and photoresist development process <b>398</b> were originally designed for generating cylindrical vias in the ILD layer of diameters of about 0.200 μm each. Plot <b>301</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> shows that the 5:1 ARC opening recipe generated ILD vias in the diameter range of about 0.199 to 0.208 μm. There was mostly a positive bias (AEI-ADI) towards enlarging the width of the actual vias as compared to the widths of the ARC openings. As the CF4/CHF3 ratio was reduced from 5:1 to 1:1, the observed AEI opening sizes shrank accordingly. This demonstrates that via width can be reduced by process parameters, with some independence from features originally defined by the via photomask <b>390</b> and photoresist development process <b>398</b>. There appears to be a proximity effect for densely-packed vias. Via width appears to decrease with higher packing density as is indicated in Table 1B. This can be due to optical proximity effects during photolithographic patterning as well as to enhanced density of etch-inhibiting organic compounds during etching of the ARC layer.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> provides a second graph <b>302</b> which shows further aspects of the experimental results. The diamond-shaped plot points and flat line range limiters respectively indicate the average and min/max values for the star-pattern measurement points (MP's) across each of the wafers, both before ARC etching (ADI measurements) and then at the 5:1, 3:1 and 1:1 flow ratios. The triangle-shaped plot points and triangle-shaped range limiters respectively indicate the average and min/max values for the isolated vias. The square-shaped plot points and rectangle-shaped range limiters respectively indicate the average and min/max values for the densely packed vias. It can be readily seen that the densely packed vias responded most aggressively to reduction of the CF<sub>4</sub>/CHF<sub>3 </sub>ratio. The 5:1 CF<sub>4</sub>/CHF<sub>3 </sub>experiments did not incorporate as much ARC-preserving character in the ILD etching for generating the ILD through-holes <b>231</b> while the 3:1 and 1:1 experiments used more of the ARC-preserving, ILD etch (process <b>208</b>). This may explain the positive jump in aperture size from ADI results to the 5:1 AEI results. It may be seen that the 1:1 experiments all showed AEI widths smaller than the original ADI widths.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref> provides a third graph <b>303</b> which shows results of further experiments. Here, the time for the ARC opening etch (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>) was varied over the range 30 seconds to 50 seconds. The ILD etch-through process was the same for both the 5:1 results and the 1:1 results. In each case the ILD etch-through process used the ARC-preserving, ILD etching process <b>208</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> for generating the ILD through-holes <b>231</b>. The 1:1 results show good nonvariability to etch time in the range 40-50 seconds. In other words, etch time for ARC opening will not be a critical parameter for determining via width when the 1:1 CF<sub>4</sub>/CHF<sub>3 </sub>flow ratio (or thereabouts) is used.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> provides a schematic explanation for possible mechanisms which can help create and maintain the inwardly-tapered ARC openings. The illustrated openings <b>471</b>.<b>1</b>, <b>471</b>.<b>2</b>, <b>431</b>.<b>3</b> and <b>431</b>.<b>4</b> appear in time staggered order (left to right) rather than all being present in their illustrated states at the same time. In other words, when the first, partially-formed ARC opening <b>471</b>.<b>1</b> is present, the completed ARC opening <b>471</b>.<b>2</b> is not yet present in its completed state and neither are the partially-formed ILD opening <b>431</b>.<b>3</b> and completed ILD opening <b>431</b>.<b>4</b> present in their illustrated states. Each comes into being, as illustrated, in a respective one of successive time periods.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Referring first to the partially-formed ARC opening <b>471</b>.<b>1</b>, the corresponding, tapering plasma <b>407</b> is generated in the presence of a vertically-oriented and corresponding electric field <b>407</b><i>e</i>. The components of plasma <b>407</b> include an etch-inhibitor generating agent such as CHF<sub>3</sub>. This etch-inhibitor generating agent produces organic polymer components for sticking to organic surfaces such as sidewalls <b>472</b><i>a</i>.<b>1</b> and <b>482</b><i>a</i>.<b>1</b>. The vertically-oriented electric field <b>407</b><i>e </i>propels non-reactive ions such as argon (Ar) and chemically reactive ions such as fluorine radicals (F) towards lateral surface <b>471</b><i>a</i>. There, the organic polymer etch-inhibitors are removed at a rate faster than their deposition rate. The argon ions (Ar) and fluorine radicals (F, generated from CF<sub>4 </sub>and CHF<sub>3</sub>) easily penetrate to vertically remove material from most of lateral surface <b>471</b><i>a</i>. The exception is at the outer edges of lateral surface <b>471</b><i>a </i>where organic polymer etch-inhibitors are accumulating faster than their removal rate. The accumulating process may be understood to begin on vertical sidewall <b>482</b><i>a</i>.<b>1</b> of the photoresist layer. Ar ions are blocked from reaching the bottom-more of the etch-inhibitors <b>482</b><i>b</i>.<b>1</b> because they strike higher ones on the vertical sidewalls. The accumulating etch-inhibitors <b>482</b><i>b</i>.<b>1</b> define a protective shroud that further extends over the outer edges of lateral surface <b>471</b><i>a</i>. This starts the inwardly-tapering etch process going. The taper slope is often a function of electric field strength and mixture ration of CF<sub>4 </sub>to CHF<sub>3 </sub>and also of Ar to CHF<sub>3</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Referring next to the partially-formed ILD opening <b>431</b>.<b>3</b> below the essentially-fully-opened ARC opening <b>471</b>.<b>2</b>, it is to be understood that the corresponding, vertical plasma <b>408</b> is generated in the presence of a vertically-oriented and corresponding electric field <b>408</b><i>e</i>. The components of plasma <b>408</b> include an etch-inhibitor generating agent such as CO. This etch-inhibitor generating agent produces organic polymer components for sticking to organic surfaces such as sidewalls <b>482</b><i>a</i>.<b>3</b> of the photoresist and/or to sidewalls <b>472</b><i>a</i>.<b>3</b> of the inwardly-tapered through-holes of the ARC layer. The vertically-oriented electric field <b>408</b><i>e </i>propels non-reactive ions such as argon (Ar) and chemically reactive ions such as fluorine radicals (F) towards the essentially lateral surface at the bottom of growing well <b>431</b>.<b>3</b>. There are essentially no organic etch-inhibitors attaching at this bottom surface because it is made of non-organic ILD material. The ILD material is therefore removed independently of deposition rate for etch-inhibitors attaching to organic surfaces such as sidewalls <b>482</b><i>a</i>.<b>3</b> (providing sidewall <b>482</b><i>a</i>.<b>3</b> does not close in on itself). Deposition rate for the organic sidewalls (e.g., <b>482</b><i>a</i>.<b>3</b>) is preferably controlled to roughly equalize with removal rate so that the inwardly-tapered ARC sidewall, <b>472</b><i>a</i>.<b>3</b> does not close in on itself. Although the quantity of etch-inhibitor needed for causing the PR sidewall <b>482</b><i>a</i>.<b>3</b> to begin closing in on itself was not experimentally verified, it is reasonably surmised that addition of CHF<sub>3 </sub>to the second plasma <b>408</b> (shifting the carbon to fluorine mix ratio) could cause the developing ILD via <b>431</b>.<b>3</b> to begin tapering inwardly as PR sidewall <b>482</b><i>a</i>.<b>3</b> begins closing in on itself. However, as explained above, inward-tapering of the ILD-0/1 vias (<b>431</b>.<b>4</b>) is often undesirable. Nonetheless, it is within the contemplation of the present disclosure that in some cases such inward-tapering of the ILD-0/1 vias (<b>431</b>.<b>4</b>) may be realized through the use of additional carbon content during the ILD via etch where the generated organic material sticks to the sidewalls of the ARC and/or photoresist layers.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">Alternatively or additionally, isotropic etching of the ILD-0/1 material may be carried out after the inwardly-tapered ARC openings <b>471</b>.<b>2</b> are formed. Such isotropic formation of the ILD-0/1 vias is schematically represented by dashed lines <b>431</b>.<b>5</b>. The result is different from that of performing an isotropic ILD etch after formation of vertical ARC openings because the starting width for the inwardly-tapered ARC openings <b>471</b>.<b>2</b> is smaller. Therefore, the resulting top and bottom widths of the isotropically-etched ILD-0/1 vias (<b>431</b>.<b>5</b>) can be made smaller than what would have occurred had ARC openings with substantially vertical sidewalls been used. Alternatively or additionally, formation of the ILD-0/1 vias may be performed with a combination of the vertical profile plasma <b>408</b> being used for part of the formation of the vias and an isotropic etch recipe being used for another part of the formation of the ILD-0/1 vias.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">The present disclosure is to be taken as illustrative rather than as limiting the scope, nature, or spirit of the subject matter claimed below. Numerous modifications and variations will become apparent to those skilled in the art after studying the disclosure, including use of equivalent functional and/or structural substitutes for elements described herein, use of equivalent functional couplings for couplings described herein, and/or use of equivalent functional steps for steps described herein. Such insubstantial variations are to be considered within the scope of what is contemplated here. Moreover, if plural examples are given for specific means, or steps, and extrapolation between and/or beyond such given examples is obvious in view of the present disclosure, then the disclosure is to be deemed as effectively disclosing and thus covering at least such extrapolations.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">By way of an example, inward-tapering may be carried out within other kinds of layers besides an organic ARC layer. More specifically, so-called hardmaks composed of Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4 </sub>or SiON are sometimes provided below the patterned photoresist layer. An etching chemistry that uses etch inhibitors for maintaining vertical sidewall profile, such as a reactive ion plasma containing HBr and Cl<sub>2 </sub>may be used for forming inwardly-tapered openings in the hardmask by shifting the mixture of the hardmask etching recipe towards greater generation of etch inhibitors. The inwardly-tapered openings of such a hardmask may then be used for creation of smaller width vias in an underlying interlayer dielectric layer.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">By way of a further example, it may be understood that the via reduction results (AEI's) of experiments such as represented by the graphs of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-3C</figref> may be integrated into a computer program. Optimizing algorithms may be devised for finding the least error recipes for mass production of a desired amount of via width reduction. Then, when designers want to obtain a predetermined amount of via width reduction by using at least the ARC inward-tapering techniques disclosed herein; the designers can input the desired width reduction into the computer program and the program can automatically generate a computed recipe for achieving the desired amount of width reduction. The computer generated recipe may then be supplied to one or more programmable etch tools for realizing the computed inward-tapering of the ARC openings and the corresponding reduction of via width without altering the ILD-0/1 photomask. Therefore, a computer-readable medium or another form of a software product or machine-instructing means (including but not limited to, a hard disk, a compact disk, a flash memory stick, a downloading of manufactured instructing signals over a network and/or like software products) may be used in accordance with the present disclosure for instructing an instructable machine (e.g., a programmable etch tool) to carry out an etch recipe which includes the formation of substantial inward-tapering of ARC openings.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Reservation of Extra-Patent Rights, Resolution of Conflicts, and Interpretation of Terms</heading>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">After this disclosure is lawfully published, the owner of the present patent application has no objection to the reproduction by others of textual and graphic materials contained herein provided such reproduction is for the limited purpose of understanding the present disclosure of invention and of thereby promoting the useful arts and sciences. The owner does not however disclaim any other rights that may be lawfully associated with the disclosed materials, including but not limited to, copyrights in any computer program listings or art works or other works provided herein, and to trademark or trade dress rights that may be associated with coined terms or art works provided herein and to other otherwise-protectable subject matter included herein or otherwise derivable herefrom.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">If any disclosures are incorporated herein by reference and such incorporated disclosures conflict in part or whole with the present disclosure, then to the extent of conflict, and/or broader disclosure, and/or broader definition of terms, the present disclosure controls. If such incorporated disclosures conflict in part or whole with one another, then to the extent of conflict, the later-dated disclosure controls.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Unless expressly stated otherwise herein, ordinary terms have their corresponding ordinary meanings within the respective contexts of their presentations, and ordinary terms of art have their corresponding regular meanings within the relevant technical arts and within the respective contexts of their presentations herein.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">Given the above disclosure of general concepts and specific embodiments, the scope of protection sought is to be defined by the claims appended hereto. The issued claims are not to be taken as limiting Applicant's right to claim disclosed, but not yet literally claimed subject matter by way of one or more further applications including those filed pursuant to 35 U.S.C. §120 and/or 35 U.S.C. §251.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07297628-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="6.01mm" wi="8.13mm" file="US07297628-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="table" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00002" nb-file="US07297628-20071120-M00002.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00002" he="6.01mm" wi="8.13mm" file="US07297628-20071120-M00002.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="table" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for forming vias through an interlayer dielectric region of a monolithically integrated device where the interlayer dielectric region (ILD) is structured to separate a first conductive layer from a second conductive layer of the monolithically integrated device, the method comprising:
<claim-text>(a) providing an organic Anti-Reflection Coating layer (ARC layer) above the material of the ILD;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) providing a photoresist layer above the ARC layer, where the photoresist layer includes a plurality of first openings defined therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) creating from the first openings, a plurality of second openings extending through the organic ARC layer, where the second openings have inwardly-tapered sidewalls such that bottom width dimensions of the second openings are smaller than corresponding width dimensions of the first openings; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(d) creating from the second openings, a plurality of third openings extending through the ILD material;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first conductive layer is part of an active layers set and wherein said second conductive layer defines a first major interconnect layer above said active layers set.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(b.1) said photoresist layer is composed of an organic material; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c.1) said step of creating the second openings includes using an etch inhibitor which selectively adheres to organic surfaces.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1) said step of creating the third openings includes causing isolated ones of said third openings to have bottom width dimensions, on average, of no more than about 0.20 μm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1) said step of creating the third openings includes causing densely-packed ones of said third openings to have bottom width dimensions, on average, of no more than about 0.18 μm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.1) said step of creating the second openings includes causing the slopes of said inwardly-tapered sidewalls to be at least about four degrees or more away from a 90 degree vertical slope.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.1a) said step of creating the second openings includes causing the slopes of said inwardly-tapered sidewalls to be inwardly sloped in a range of about 7 degrees to about 40 degrees away from a 90 degree vertical slope.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.1b) said step of creating the second openings includes causing the slopes of said inwardly-tapered sidewalls to be inwardly sloped in a range of about 7 degrees to about 22 degrees away from a 90 degree vertical slope.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1) said step of creating the third openings includes causing said third openings to have sidewall profiles that are not sloped by more than about 3 degrees away from a 90 degree vertical slope.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1) said step of creating the third openings includes creating a reactive ion plasma having a carbon-providing component, having a fluorine-providing component, and having an inert bombardment component.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1a) the carbon-providing component includes carbon monoxide (CO).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1a) the fluorine-providing component includes C<sub>4</sub>F<sub>6</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1a) the inert bombardment component includes argon (Ar).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1) said third openings have bottom width dimensions, on average, that are at least 5 percent smaller than corresponding bottom width dimensions of corresponding first openings in the photoresist layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.2) said third openings have bottom width dimensions, on average, that are at least 10 percent smaller than the corresponding bottom width dimensions of the corresponding first openings in the photoresist layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> and further comprising:
<claim-text>(e) using a predefined photomask to define width dimensions of the first openings; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(f) using the same predefined photomask to manufacture additional monolithically integrated devices each having a respective version of said ILD region, of said photoresist layer and of said ARC layer with inwardly-tapered openings, but where at least two of the monolithically integrated devices that are manufactured by use of said same predefined photomask have substantially differently dimensioned widths for their corresponding, third openings extending through their corresponding ILD regions and have substantially differently dimensioned widths for their corresponding, second openings.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> and further comprising:
<claim-text>(g) providing respective conductive plugs extending through said third openings of the respective monolithically integrated devices.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> and further comprising:
<claim-text>(h) providing patterned conductive layers above the corresponding ILD regions of the respective monolithically integrated devices.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(h.1) at least two of said respective patterned conductive layers have substantially different plug spacings and/or substantially different spacings between corresponding conductive lines of their respective, patterned conductive layers.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1) said ILD includes a silicon-oxide based insulator having a thickness of about 0.1 μm or more.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(b.1) said photoresist layer has a thickness of about 0.61 μm or less.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(a.1) said organic ARC layer has a thickness of about 700 Å to 800 Å.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>at least two of said third openings are densely packed so as to have a spacing of no more than about 2000 nm between them.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. A method for forming vias through an interlayer dielectric region of a monolithically integrated device where the interlayer dielectric region (ILD) is structured to separate a first conductive layer from a second conductive layer of the monolithically integrated device, the method comprising:
<claim-text>(a) providing an organic Anti-Reflection Coating layer (ARC layer) above the material of the ILD;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) providing a photoresist layer above the ARC layer, where the photoresist layer includes a plurality of first openings defined therethrough, wherein said photoresist layer is composed of an organic material;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) creating from the first openings, a plurality of second openings extending through the organic ARC layer, where the second openings have inwardly-tapered sidewalls such that bottom width dimensions of the second openings are smaller than corresponding width dimensions of the first openings; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(d) creating from the second openings, a plurality of third openings extending through the ILD material; wherein
<claim-text>(c.1) said step of creating the second openings includes using an etch inhibitor which selectively adheres to organic surfaces, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c.2) said step of creating the second openings includes creating a reactive ion plasma having a hydrocarbon-providing component, having a fluorine-providing component, and having an inert bombardment component.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.2a) the hydrocarbon-providing component includes CHF<sub>3</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.2a) the fluorine-providing component includes CF<sub>4</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.2a) the inert bombardment component includes argon (Ar).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.2a) the hydrocarbon-providing component includes CHF<sub>3</sub>;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c.2b) the fluorine-providing component includes CF<sub>4</sub>; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c.2c) the ratio in the reactive ion plasma of said CF<sub>4 </sub>to said CHF<sub>3</sub>, as measured by volumetric input flow is substantially less than five to one (5:1).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.2c1) said CF<sub>4 </sub>to CHF<sub>3 </sub>ratio is about or less than three to one (3:1).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00028">claim 28</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.2c2) said CF<sub>4 </sub>to CHF<sub>3 </sub>ratio is about or less than one to one (1:1).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. A contact forming method comprising:
<claim-text>(a) patterning an organic photoresist layer which is provided over an organic ARC layer, where the ARC layer is provided over a dielectric layer, the patterning of the photoresist layer causing through-holes to be defined in the photoresist layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) using an inwardly-tapering etch process to continue the through-holes of the lithography mask into the ARC layer as inwardly-tapered through-holes of the ARC layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) using an anisotropic etch process to continue the inwardly-tapered through-holes of the ARC layer into the dielectric layer as substantially vertical contact holes through the dielectric layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(d) filling the substantially vertical contact holes with an electrical conductor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. The contact forming method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(b.1) said inwardly-tapering etch process causes etch inhibitors to adhere to sidewalls of the photoresist layer through-holes.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. The contact forming method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(c.1) said anisotropic etch process causes etch inhibitors to adhere to sidewalls of the inwardly-tapered through-holes of the ARC layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00033" num="00033">
<claim-text>33. The contact forming method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>(d.1) said electrical conductor includes a refractory metal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
