<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298712-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298712</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10802789</doc-number>
<date>20040318</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>632</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370310</main-classification>
<further-classification>712217</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Wireless network device with data storage</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0207363</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Yen et al.</name>
<date>20050900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370310</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0095732</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Tran et al.</name>
<date>20060500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>712217</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370310</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>712217</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050207363</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050922</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yen</last-name>
<first-name>An-Yu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Shiao</last-name>
<first-name>Kuang-Ju</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lin</last-name>
<first-name>Yu-Hsiang</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Yu-Hsiang</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Rosenberg, Klein &amp; Lee</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Microlink Communications Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Cumming</last-name>
<first-name>William D.</first-name>
<department>2617</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A wireless network device with data storage is provided that utilizes a wireless connection to communicate with a LAN. The wireless network device with data storage includes a control unit, a memory element and a wireless communication module. The control unit includes a base-band processor, an RF interface, an external memory interface and a host device interface, wherein the base-band processor is adapted to process all data input/output through each interfaces. The RF interface connects the wireless communication module with the control unit, the external memory interface connects the memory element with the control unit, and the host device interface makes the control unit connect with an electronic device. The wireless communication module is able to either transmit or receive wireless signals from other electronic devices. The memory element is divided into two storage areas, one used for storage of the driver program for the control unit, the other for storage of user data.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="109.73mm" wi="235.46mm" file="US07298712-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="225.04mm" wi="156.38mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298712-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="235.63mm" wi="141.05mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298712-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="156.38mm" wi="116.67mm" file="US07298712-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention relates to a wireless network device. More particularly, the invention relates to a wireless network device that can be used to store data for a user.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. The Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">With the development of the informatization society, communication is very important. At the same time, the means of communication tends to diversification. Communication through Internet has become an important part in the life and work of the people. But the traditional means of connecting with Internet needs a cable for transferring data that connects a host device with LAN (local area network), which constrains the movement of the host device. The user cannot transfer the host device freely. Besides, the common network device generally includes a memory element. However the memory element is only used to store program data that support the network communication, at the same time, the capacity of the memory element is so small that the memory element is not provided for storing data.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Furthermore, for the constraint of the cable, the use of the network device is limited, and it cannot suit to the development tendency of communication. Therefore, there is a need for a wireless network device that can be used to store data for a user.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">An objective of the present invention is to provide a wireless network device with data storage which makes a host device connect with LAN by means of wireless and is used to store data for a user.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">To achieve the above objective, the present invention provides a wireless network device with data storage that connects with LAN by means of wireless. The wireless network device with data storage includes a control unit, a wireless communication module and a memory element.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The control unit connects with a wireless communication module and a memory element. The control unit also connects with a host device such as a computer. Therefore, the host device communicates with the AP (access point) of the LAN.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The memory element is divided into two storage areas, one is used to store the driver program data that makes the control unit support the wireless communication such as the IEEE802.11 protocol data; and the other is used to store other data. Therefore, this memory element can be used to directly store data downloaded from the LAN.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The host device interface of the wireless network device with data storage may adopt the USB interface in order to make the wireless network device with data storage connect with different kinds of the host devices such as a note-book computer, a PDA (personal digital assistant) or a digital still camera.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Therefore, the wireless network device with data storage can make a host device connect with the LAN by means of wireless and is used to store data for a user.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present invention will be apparent to those skilled in the art by reading the following description of embodiments thereof, with reference to the attached drawing, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of the wireless network device with data storage according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of the control unit of the wireless network device with data storage according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram of the wireless module of the wireless network device with data storage according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> of the present invention is disclosed. The wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> connects with LAN <b>300</b> by means of wireless. The wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> includes a control unit <b>110</b>, a wireless communication module <b>120</b> and a memory element <b>130</b>. The control unit <b>110</b> connects with a wireless communication module <b>120</b> and a memory element <b>130</b>. The control unit <b>110</b> may connects with a host device <b>200</b> such as a computer. Therefore, the host device <b>200</b> can communicate with the AP (access point) <b>310</b> of the LAN <b>300</b>. Besides, the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> can also be used to extend the memory of the host device <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the block diagram of the control unit <b>110</b> of the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> is shown. The control unit <b>110</b> further composes a base-band processor <b>111</b>, a media access controller <b>112</b>, a RF interface <b>113</b>, a memory controller <b>114</b>, a RAM (Random Access Memory) <b>115</b>, an external memory interface <b>116</b> and a host device interface <b>117</b>. The base-band processor <b>111</b> connects with the media access controller <b>112</b> and the host device interface <b>117</b>. The base-band processor <b>111</b> controls the transferring of data of the host device interface <b>117</b>. The RF interface <b>113</b> connects with the media access controller <b>112</b> and the wireless communication module <b>120</b>. Through the RF interface <b>113</b>, the wireless signal is inputted the media access controller <b>112</b> or outputted the wireless communication module <b>120</b>. Besides, the base-band processor <b>111</b> further connects with the memory controller <b>114</b> and controls the RAM <b>115</b> and the external memory interface <b>116</b> through the memory controller <b>114</b>. The RAM <b>115</b> is used to store temporary data that the base-band processor <b>111</b> produces in the run. The external memory interface <b>116</b> connects with the memory element <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The memory element <b>130</b> adopts the non-volatile semiconductor memory such as Flash memory. The memory element <b>130</b> is divided into two storage areas, one is used to store the driver program data that can make the control unit support the wireless communication such as the IEEE802.11 protocol data, this area occupies the lower address part of the memory element <b>130</b>; and the other is used to store other data for a user, therefore, this area is not only used to extend the capacity of the host device <b>200</b>, but also can be used to directly store data downloaded from the LAN <b>300</b>, and this area occupies the upper address part of the memory element <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Additionally, the memory element <b>130</b> can include two pieces of independent memories, one of which is used to store the driver program data that makes the control unit support the wireless communication, and the other is used to store other data for a user. Both of the two memories adopt the non-volatile semiconductor memory, such as Flash memory.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the block diagram of the wireless communication module <b>120</b> of the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> is shown. The wireless communication module <b>120</b> is used to receive and/or transmit the wireless signal, therefore, the host device <b>200</b> can communicate with the LAN by means of wireless. IEEE 802.11b or IEEE 802.11a technology accepted communication protocol is used in the wireless communication module <b>120</b>, or other technology accepted communication protocol such Blue-tooth technology is also adopted. The wireless communication module <b>120</b> includes an antenna <b>125</b> and an RF Front-end <b>121</b>. The RF Front-end <b>121</b> connects with the RF interface <b>113</b> of the control unit <b>110</b> by an RS-232 interface or a USB interface. The RF Front-end <b>121</b> further comprises an RF oscillator <b>122</b>, an analog RF stage <b>123</b> and a digital base-band component <b>124</b>. When the wireless signal is transmitted, a digital base-band component <b>124</b> receives the signal from the control unit <b>110</b> and outputs the digital signal to the analog RF stage <b>123</b>. The analog RF stage <b>123</b> converts the digital signal to the analog signal under the control of waves that come from the RF oscillator <b>122</b>. The antenna <b>125</b> transmits the wireless signal according the analog signal under the control the analog RF stage <b>123</b>. If the wireless signal is received, the analog RF stage <b>123</b> converts the wireless signal received by the antenna <b>125</b> into the analog signal, then the a digital base-band component <b>124</b> receives the analog signal and converts the analog signal into the digital signal, at last the digital signal is inputted into the control unit <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The following will show how the host device <b>200</b> equipped with the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> communicates with the AP <b>310</b> of the LAN <b>300</b>. The host device <b>200</b> transmits the data signal to the base-band processor <b>111</b> of the control unit <b>110</b> through the host device interface <b>117</b>. The base-band processor <b>111</b> receives and processes the data signal according the wireless communication protocol and driver program, and the wireless communication protocol and driver program data are stored in the memory element <b>130</b> and transferred to the base-band processor <b>111</b> through the external memory interface <b>116</b>. The data signal being processed by the base-band processor <b>111</b> is inputted to the media access controller <b>112</b>, and then the data signal is transferred into the wireless communication module <b>120</b> through the RF interface <b>113</b>. Therefore, the host device <b>200</b> can transfer the data to the LAN <b>300</b>; on the contrary, the host device <b>200</b> can download the data from the LAN <b>300</b> through the AP <b>310</b> through the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Furthermore, when the user utilizes the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> to store data, the host device <b>200</b> transfers the data into the base-band processor <b>111</b> of the control unit <b>110</b>, then the data are inputted into the memory element through the memory controller <b>114</b> and the external memory interface <b>116</b>. The user also makes the data download from the LAN <b>300</b> stored in the memory element <b>130</b> under the control of the control unit <b>110</b>, or send the data in the memory element <b>130</b> to the LAN <b>300</b> under the control of the control unit <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In the present invention, the host device interface <b>117</b> of the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> may adopt the USB interface in order to make the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> connect with different kinds of the host devices such as a note-book computer, a PDA (personal digital assistant) or a digital still camera. Besides, because the USB interface has the power bus, the host device <b>200</b> supplies the power to the wireless network device <b>100</b>, as the result, the separate supply circuit is not needed in the wireless network device <b>100</b>, therefore, the structure of the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> is simple and the cost is also lower.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">According to the above-mentioned description about the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b>, it is possible to provide a wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> which not only overcomes the constraint of the cable to make the host device <b>200</b> communicate with LAN <b>300</b> by means of wireless, but also be used to store data for a user. Therefore, the wireless network device with data storage <b>100</b> makes the user communicate conveniently and satisfy the demand of the users.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Although the present invention has been filly described by way of the example with reference to the accompanying drawings, it is to be noted that various changes and modifications will be apparent to those skilled in the art. Therefore, unless otherwise such changes and modifications depart from the scope of the present invention, they should be construed as being included therein.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A wireless network device with data storage, comprising:
<claim-text>a control unit including a base-band processor, a media access controller, a RF interface, a memory controller, RAM (Random Access Memory), an external memory interface and a host device interface; the base-band processor connecting with the media access controller, the host device interface and the memory controller for processing all data input/output through each interfaces, the RF interface connecting with the media access controller, the RAM and the external memory interface connecting with the memory controller, the RAM storing temporary data that the base-band processor produces in the run; a wireless communication module connecting with the RF interface through which the wireless signals are transmitted/received; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a memory element connecting with the external memory interface being divided into two storage areas, one of which storing the driver program, and the other storing data.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The wireless network device with data storage as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the area that is used to store data occupies the upper address of the memory element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The wireless network device with data storage as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the memory element is Flash Memory.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The wireless network device with data storage as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the memory element includes two pieces of memories, one of which stores the driver program, and the other stores data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The wireless network device with storage as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein both two pieces of memories are Flash Memory.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
