<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296764-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296764</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11650504</doc-number>
<date>20070108</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>89</main-group>
<subgroup>01</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>242231</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Spinning reel</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5848757</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Amano et al.</name>
<date>19981200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6318654</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Amano et al.</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6405955</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Furomoto</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6572042</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Sugawara</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6595449</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Ikuta et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0066919</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ikuta et al.</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>2</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>242230</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>242231</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>242232</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>242234</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11065067</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20050225</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7159812</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11650504</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070108329</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070517</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chang</last-name>
<first-name>Liang-Jen</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taichung</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Browdy and Neimark, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Okuma Fishing Tackle Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taichung</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Crawford</last-name>
<first-name>Gene O.</first-name>
<department>3654</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Langdon</last-name>
<first-name>Evan</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A spinning reel has a reel body and a rotor. The rotor has a base pivoted to the base, a first arm pivoted to an end of the base, a second arm pivoted to the other end of the base, an arc connected between the first arm and the second arm, a guiding block disposed between the first arm and the arc, and a wheel disposed between the guiding block and the first arm. The guiding block has a cone portion connected to the arc and a base portion connected to the wheel. The cone portion has a hole into which the arc is inserted and two tip ends located at opposite sides of the hole.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="153.67mm" wi="383.46mm" file="US07296764-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="192.79mm" wi="162.05mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296764-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="178.05mm" wi="156.46mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296764-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="158.07mm" wi="151.55mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296764-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="191.85mm" wi="149.01mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296764-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="226.14mm" wi="155.87mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296764-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to a fishing tool, and more particularly to a spinning reel, which prevents the fishing line from jam.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> show a conventional spinning reel <b>1</b> mainly having a reel body <b>2</b>, a spool <b>3</b>, a rotor <b>4</b> and a handle <b>5</b>. The handle <b>5</b> is rotated to drive the spool <b>3</b> for reciprocation via a transmission device (not shown) and to drive the rotor <b>4</b> for rotation. As a result, a fishing line can be winded on the spool <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The rotor <b>4</b> has two arms <b>6</b> at opposite sides thereof, on one of which a wheel <b>8</b> is provided, and a curved arc <b>7</b> with opposite ends connected to the arms <b>6</b>. To wind the fishing line on the wheel <b>8</b>, there usually is a guiding block <b>9</b> between the arc <b>7</b> and the wheel <b>8</b>. The guiding block <b>9</b> has a hole <b>91</b> behind a tip end thereof to insert the arc <b>7</b> therein. To avoid the fishing line jamming in a gap between the arc <b>7</b> and the guiding block <b>9</b>, the hole <b>91</b> is kept away from a backside of the tip end of the guiding block <b>9</b>, such that a location labeled a (between the arc <b>7</b> and the tip end of the guiding block <b>9</b>) in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> indicating that the fishing line is jammed thereat is kept out of a path of the fishing line passing to reduce the risk of jamming of the fishing line.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">When the fishing line is released, the arc <b>7</b> and the arms <b>6</b> have to be rotated about 110 degrees, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. At this time, the fishing line is twisted randomly, and sometime the fishing line is jammed as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in which the fishing line <b>92</b> is jammed between the arc <b>7</b> and the tip end of the guiding block <b>9</b> (the location a).</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The primary objective of the present invention is to provide a spinning reel, which avoids the jamming of a fishing line.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">According to the objectives of the present invention, a spinning reel comprises a reel body and a rotor. The rotor has a base pivoted to the reel body, a first arm pivoted to an end of the base, a second arm pivoted to the other end of the base, an arc connected between the first arm and the second arm, a guiding block disposed between the first arm and the arc, and a wheel disposed between the guiding block and the first arm. The guiding block has a cone portion connected to the arc and a base portion connected to the wheel. The cone portion has a hole into which the arc is inserted and two tip ends located at opposite sides of the hole.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of the conventional spinning reel;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of the conventional spinning reel in action;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an enlarged view in parts of the conventional spinning reel;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective view of a preferred embodiment of the present invention, and</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an exploded view of the guiding block of the preferred embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a spinning reel <b>10</b> of the preferred embodiment of the present invention comprises a reel body <b>20</b>, a spool <b>30</b>, a rotor <b>40</b>, a handle <b>60</b> and a transmission device (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The reel body <b>20</b> has a T-shaped connection portion <b>22</b> to be connected to a fishing rod (not shown). The spool <b>30</b> is provided at a front end of the reel body <b>20</b> to wind a fishing line (not shown) thereon. The handle <b>60</b> is provided at a side of the reel body <b>20</b> to drive the spool <b>30</b> for reciprocation via the transmission device.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The rotor <b>40</b> has a base pivoted to the reel body <b>20</b>, a first arm <b>43</b> pivoted to an end of the base <b>42</b>, a second arm <b>44</b> pivoted to the other end of the base <b>42</b>, a curved arc <b>45</b> connected between the arms <b>43</b> and <b>44</b>, a guiding block <b>48</b> disposed between the. first arm <b>43</b> and the arc <b>45</b> and a wheel <b>46</b> disposed between the guiding block <b>48</b> and the first arm <b>43</b>. The guiding block <b>48</b>, and a base portion <b>55</b> connected to the wheel <b>46</b> has a cone portion <b>50</b> connected to the arc <b>45</b>. The cone portion <b>50</b> has a hole into which the arc <b>45</b> is inserted which creates two tip ends <b>52</b> located at opposite sides of the hole on the upper surface <b>54</b> of the guiding block <b>48</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the hole provided at the end of cone portion <b>50</b> to engage arc <b>45</b> creates an arc edge <b>60</b> on the upper surface <b>54</b> extending into the upper surface <b>54</b> and an arc edge <b>62</b> extending down from the side edges <b>53</b> of upper surface <b>50</b> into the bottom surface <b>54</b>. Arc edges <b>60</b> and <b>62</b> together forming the sides of the two tip ends <b>52</b> and side edges <b>53</b> extending down from the tip ends <b>52</b> between arc edges <b>60</b> and <b>62</b> into base portion <b>55</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In practice, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the guiding block <b>48</b> is made into a cone-shaped block, and then the guiding block <b>48</b> is drilled with a hole at a tip end of the cone portion <b>50</b>. Because the guiding block <b>48</b> has two side edges <b>53</b> at opposite sides of upper surface <b>54</b>, the two tip ends <b>52</b> are formed on the cone portion <b>50</b> of the guiding block <b>48</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">When the spinning reel <b>10</b> of the present invention is in a normal operation, the fishing line is located at a right side of the wheel <b>46</b> (according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) via the guiding block <b>48</b> so that the fishing line will not jam between the tip ends <b>52</b> of the guiding block <b>48</b> and the arc <b>45</b>. When the spinning reel <b>10</b> of the present invention releases the fishing line so that the arc <b>45</b> and the arms <b>43</b> and <b>44</b> are rotated to the position shown as <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the fishing line passes the guiding block <b>48</b> randomly via a left side thereof (according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) to avoid the fishing line from being jammed between the tip ends <b>52</b> of the guiding block <b>48</b> and the arc <b>45</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In conclusion, the spinning reel <b>10</b> of the present invention provides two tip ends <b>52</b> of the guiding block <b>48</b> to replace the single tip end of the conventional guiding block at the left side of the arc (according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) and keeps the tip ends <b>52</b> away from the right side of the arc <b>45</b> (according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) at the same time. The relative positions of the tip ends are not restricted in the drawings shown in the present invention. Any equivalent structure should be still within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A spinning reel, comprising:
<claim-text>a reel body, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotor having a base pivoted to the reel body, a first arm pivoted to an end of the base, a second arm pivoted to the other end of the base, an arc connected between the first arm and the second arm, a guiding block having an upper surface and a bottom surface disposed between the first arm and the arc, and a wheel disposed between the guiding block and the first arm;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the guiding block has a cone portion connected to the arc and a base portion connected to the wheel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the cone portion of the guiding block is provided with a hole within which the arc is engaged,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the hole forms a first arc edge extending into the upper surface of the guiding block and a second arc edge extending down from the upper surface into the bottom surface of the guiding block; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein two intersections of first arc edge and the second arc edge respectively produce two tip ends located at opposite sides of the hole at the upper surface of the guiding block.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The spinning reel as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the upper surface of the guiding block has side edges which respectively extend from the two tip ends toward the base portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
