<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296664-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296664</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10396819</doc-number>
<date>20030326</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-087537</doc-number>
<date>20020327</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>313</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>57</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>188294</main-classification>
<further-classification>188130</further-classification>
<further-classification>188 83</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Rotary damper</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4694530</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Foggini</name>
<date>19870900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4893522</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Arakawa</name>
<date>19900100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5001809</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kim et al.</name>
<date>19910300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>44 13 325</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>0 422 882</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19910400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2 288 450</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2544628</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Patent Abstracts of Japan, vol. 013, No. 189, May 8, 1989, JP 01-015547, Jan. 19, 1989.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>16</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>188290</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>188293</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>188294</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>188296</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>188130</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1883225</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>188 83</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 16 54</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 16 82</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 16 85</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 16197</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  42462</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  4236</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  4240</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20030183039</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20031002</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ohta</last-name>
<first-name>Naotoshi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Takahashi</last-name>
<first-name>Ryusuke</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Foley &amp; Lardner LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Calsonic Kansei Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Xuan Lan</first-name>
<department>3683</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A rotary damper includes: a damper body mounted on a rotary shaft; a cam mechanism provided in the damper body to set a rotation pattern of the rotary shaft; a restoring force-accumulating member that accumulates a restoring force in accordance with rotation of the rotary shaft; and a rotation control member for controlling the rotation of the rotary shaft. The damper body is formed by setting a bottomed, cylindrical outer case having an opening at one end thereof and a bottomed, cylindrical inner case having an opening at one end thereof, face-to-face with each other and fitting the two with each other rotatably. The rotation control member is interposed between an inner periphery surface of the outer case and an outer periphery surface of the inner case on an outer periphery side of the damper body.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="171.20mm" wi="144.10mm" file="US07296664-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="203.12mm" wi="195.66mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296664-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="190.84mm" wi="153.67mm" file="US07296664-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="256.20mm" wi="172.64mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296664-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="254.17mm" wi="166.45mm" file="US07296664-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="257.47mm" wi="150.88mm" file="US07296664-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a rotary damper used in a vehicle such as an automobile.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In a vehicle such as an automobile there are provided various receptacle portions within a passenger compartment. Some such receptacle portions are provided with a lid that closes when it is pushed once and opens when it is pushed once more. One such lid, which is supported through a rotary damper, is disclosed in Japanese Patent No. 2544628.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 and 8</figref>, this rotary damper includes: (a) a cylindrical rotor <b>1</b> that receives a rotational input, (b) a housing <b>2</b> that has a shaft <b>3</b> that is fitted in an inner periphery of the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b> and also has a cylindrical wall <b>4</b> that surrounds the shaft <b>3</b>. A viscous fluid <b>5</b> is interposed between the inner periphery of the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b> and the shaft <b>3</b> of the housing <b>2</b>. A coiled spring <b>6</b> is interposed between an inner periphery of the cylindrical wall <b>4</b> of the housing <b>2</b> and an outer periphery of the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b>. The coiled spring <b>6</b>, which is fixed at one end thereof to the housing <b>2</b> and at an opposite end thereof to the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b>, is tightened with rotation of the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b>, which rotation is performed upon receipt of a rotational input in the cylindrical rotor. A cover <b>7</b> is fixed to the housing <b>2</b> so as to close an open end face of the cylindrical wall <b>4</b> of the housing; an inner surface of the cover <b>7</b> is opposed to an end face of the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b>. A spiral groove <b>9</b>, which is formed in one of the inner surface of the cover <b>7</b> and the end face of the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b>, is provided at one end thereof with a heart cam groove <b>10</b>. An operating pin <b>8</b> is mounted to the other of the cover <b>7</b> and the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b> and is guided through the spiral groove <b>9</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">An input/output shaft <b>12</b>, which projects outward from the cover <b>7</b>, is integral with the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b>; a lid of a receptacle portion is attached to the input/output shaft <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The heart cam groove <b>10</b> is provided with: (a) heart island <b>10</b>′, (b) end portions <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>c </i>of two arcuate and straight paths, respectively, that are formed along both side portions of the heart island <b>10</b>′, and (c) a slit <b>10</b><i>b </i>that is formed in a rear end portion of the heart island <b>10</b>′ at an intermediate position of a path that interconnects the arcuate and straight paths at positions near the two end portions <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>c. </i></p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">When the lid is pushed into a closed state from an open state, the input/output shaft <b>12</b> connected to the lid is rotated. Thus, when the lid is pushed, a rotational force is imparted to the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b> through the input/output shaft <b>12</b>. As a result of the rotational force, the coiled spring <b>6</b> is tightened and a restoring force is accumulated in the spring. At this time, the operating pin <b>8</b> moves along the spiral groove <b>9</b> to a first end side from an opposite, second end 9′ side of the same groove, i.e., toward the heart cam groove <b>10</b> that is formed at the first end side of the spiral, groove <b>9</b>. The pin then reaches one end portion <b>10</b><i>a </i>of the heart cam groove <b>10</b> through the arcuate path of the same arcuate groove. Subsequently, the pin <b>8</b> returns slightly and is caught (i.e., stopped) in the slit <b>10</b><i>b </i>of the heart island <b>10</b>′, thereby maintaining the lid in a closed position.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">When the lid is pushed again, the operating pin <b>8</b> is disengaged from the slit <b>10</b><i>b </i>formed in the heart island <b>10</b>′. The pin <b>8</b> then moves to the other end portion <b>10</b><i>c </i>of the heart cam groove <b>10</b>. Subsequently, with the restoring force of the coiled spring <b>6</b>, the pin <b>8</b> linearly returns from the other end portion <b>10</b><i>c </i>of the heart cam groove <b>10</b> to the first side of the spiral groove <b>9</b>. Thereafter, the pin <b>8</b> moves to the opposite, second end <b>9</b>′ side of the spiral groove <b>9</b>, at which the lid opens.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In such a conventional rotary damper, however, as the operating pin <b>8</b> is provided on the cover <b>7</b> side of the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b>, a vertical size of the entire device becomes large, i.e., the device is not of a compact size. Moreover, as the device uses the cylindrical rotor <b>1</b>, the housing <b>2</b>, and and the cover <b>7</b>, the number of components, and hence the cost, is high.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">To solve the above-mentioned problems, it is an object of the present invention to provide a rotary damper that includes: a damper body mounted on a rotary shaft; a cam mechanism provided in the damper body to set a rotation pattern of the rotary shaft; a restoring force-accumulating member that accumulates a restoring force in accordance with rotation of the rotary shaft; and a rotation control member for controlling the rotation of the rotary shaft. The damper body is formed by setting a bottomed, cylindrical outer case having an opening at one end thereof and a bottomed, cylindrical inner case having an opening at one end thereof, face to face with each other and fitting the two with each other rotatably. The rotation control member is interposed between an inner periphery surface of the outer case and an outer periphery surface of the inner case on an outer periphery side of the damper body, thereby attaining a compact structure and reducing the number of components used and, therefore, consequently reducing cost.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates the whole of an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a partial enlarged diagram of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an exploded perspective view of a rotary damper shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an end view of an outer case as seen from an opening side thereof;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a partial enlarged sectional view of the outer case shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an end view of an inner case as seen from an opening side thereof;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a conventional rotary damper; and</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is an explanatory diagram of a heart cam groove shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF A PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">An embodiment of the present invention will hereafter be described with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">First, a description will be given about construction. Within a passenger compartment of a vehicle such as an automobile, a receptacle portion <b>26</b> such as a drink holder <b>25</b> is provided for example in such a portion as a center console or an instrument panel, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The drink holder <b>25</b> is constructed so as to be covered with an opening/closing lid <b>27</b>, which closes when pushed once and opens when pushed once more. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the reference numeral <b>28</b> denotes a drink container such as a drink can or a PET bottle.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The lid <b>27</b> is connected at one end thereof to a structural member <b>30</b>, such as a center console or an instrument panel, through a semi-shaft member <b>29</b> (e.g., a clip pin) and is supported at an opposite end of the structural member <b>30</b> through an input/output shaft <b>31</b> (rotary shaft) and a rotary damper <b>32</b> in this embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 to 6</figref>, the rotary damper <b>32</b> of this embodiment is provided with a bottomed, short cylindrical, outer case <b>35</b> and a bottomed, short cylindrical, inner case <b>37</b>. The bottomed, short cylindrical, outer case <b>35</b> has an opening at one end thereof. The bottomed, short cylindrical, inner case <b>37</b> is sized smaller than the outer case <b>35</b> and has an opening at one end thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The outer case <b>35</b> and the inner case <b>37</b> are brought face-to-face with each other such that the inner case <b>37</b> is rotatably fitted in the interior of the outer case <b>35</b>. As a result, a generally short cylindrical damper body <b>38</b> is formed of the inner and outer cases <b>35</b>, <b>37</b>. An outer surface of a bottom <b>35</b><i>a </i>of the outer case <b>35</b> in the damper body <b>38</b> is fixed to the structural member <b>30</b>. On an inner surface of the bottom <b>35</b><i>a </i>of the outer case <b>35</b> is formed a rib <b>39</b> that extends in the circumferential direction to effect positioning of a front-end inner periphery of a peripheral wall <b>37</b><i>b </i>of the inner case <b>37</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Between the outer case <b>35</b> and the inner case <b>37</b> is provided a retaining portion <b>40</b> for making both cases rotatable in the mutually fitted state and for retaining them in the axial direction. For example, the retaining portion <b>40</b> comprises plural (four in the figures) retaining pawls <b>41</b> arranged in the circumferential direction on a front end of a peripheral wall <b>35</b><i>b </i>of the outer case <b>35</b> to retain an outer surface of a bottom <b>37</b><i>a </i>of the inner case <b>37</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">On an outer periphery side of the damper body <b>38</b>, a viscous fluid <b>42</b>, e.g., silicone grease, is interposed between an inner periphery surface of the peripheral wall <b>35</b><i>b </i>of the outer case <b>35</b> and an outer periphery surface of the peripheral wall <b>37</b><i>b </i>of the inner case <b>37</b>. The viscous fluid <b>42</b> is used as a resistor acting as a rotation control member. To seal the viscous fluid <b>42</b>, a pair of O-rings <b>43</b> and <b>44</b> are interposed between the inner periphery surface of the outer case <b>35</b> and the outer periphery surface of the inner case <b>37</b> so as to be spaced a predetermined distance from each other. In this case, one O-ring <b>43</b> is fitted and compressed between a base portion of an inner periphery of the peripheral wall <b>35</b><i>b </i>of the outer case <b>35</b> and a circumferentially extending stepped portion formed at a front-end outer periphery surface of the peripheral wall <b>37</b><i>b </i>of the inner case <b>37</b>. Likewise, the other O-ring <b>44</b> is fitted and compressed between a flange <b>45</b> formed on a rear-end outer periphery surface of the peripheral wall <b>37</b><i>b </i>of the inner case <b>37</b> and a circumferentially extending stepped portion formed on a front-end inner periphery surface of the peripheral wall <b>35</b><i>a </i>of the outer case <b>35</b>. The flange <b>45</b> is flush with the bottom <b>37</b><i>a </i>of the inner case <b>37</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">On the other hand axial holes <b>46</b> and <b>47</b> for passing the external input/output shaft <b>31</b> therethrough are formed axially of the outer case <b>35</b> and the inner case <b>37</b>, respectively. In the interior of the inner case <b>37</b>, a cylindrical shaft holding portion <b>48</b> is projectingly provided to hold the input/output shaft <b>31</b>,<b>170</b> which is inserted in an axial position into the damper body <b>38</b>. Key lugs <b>50</b> are formed on a front-end inner periphery side of the shaft holding portion <b>48</b> to fit in axially extending key ways <b>49</b> that are formed in a front-end outer periphery of the input/output shaft <b>31</b>. A front-end outer periphery of the shaft holding portion <b>48</b> is formed with a stepped portion, which stepped portion is engaged with a stepped portion formed on an inner surface side of the axial hole <b>46</b> in the outer case <b>35</b> to effect positioning of the two. An intermediate portion of the input/output shaft <b>31</b> is supported by the structural member <b>30</b> through a bearing member <b>51</b> such as a bushing, and a rear end portion thereof is formed with a lid mounting portion <b>52</b> for mounting the lid <b>27</b> and a flange <b>53</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">A coiled spring <b>55</b>, which acts as a restoring force accumulating member, is fitted on the outer periphery of the shaft holding portion <b>48</b>. One end of the coiled spring <b>55</b> is anchored to a retaining hole <b>57</b> formed in the bottom <b>37</b><i>a </i>of the inner case <b>37</b>. An opposite end of the coiled spring <b>55</b> is anchored to a retaining portion <b>56</b> formed on the rib <b>39</b>, which is formed on the inner periphery of the bottom <b>35</b><i>a </i>of the outer case <b>35</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Further, a generally arcuate guide groove <b>61</b> having a heart cam groove <b>60</b> at one end is formed as part of a cam mechanism in either the inner case <b>37</b> or the outer case <b>35</b> (the inner case <b>37</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 6</figref>) located in the interior of the damper body <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The heart cam groove <b>60</b> includes: (a) a heart island <b>62</b>, (b) end portions <b>60</b><i>a </i>and <b>60</b><i>b </i>of two arcuate and straight paths, respectively, which are formed along both side portions of the heart island <b>62</b>, and (c) a slit <b>60</b><i>c </i>that is formed in a rear end portion of the heart island <b>62</b><i>a </i>an intermediate position of a path that interconnects the two end portions <b>60</b><i>a </i>and <b>60</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In the interior space of the damper body <b>38</b> and sideways of the coiled spring <b>55</b> there is disposed an operating pin <b>64</b> as part of the cam mechanism. The operating pin <b>64</b> is guided at one end thereof by both heart cam groove <b>60</b> and guide groove <b>61</b> and is retained at an opposite end thereof by a pin retaining portion <b>63</b> provided in the other (the outer case <b>35</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 4</figref>) of the inner and outer eases <b>37</b>, <b>35</b>. In the other (the outer case <b>35</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b> and <b>5</b>) of the inner and outer eases <b>37</b>, <b>35</b> there is provided a guide portion <b>65</b> that restricts a movement range of the operating pin <b>64</b> and that guides and holds an intermediate part of the operating pin <b>64</b>, to prevent the pin from coming off the heart cam groove <b>60</b>, the guide groove <b>61</b>, and the pin retaining portion <b>63</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The following description is now provided about the operation of this embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The rotary damper <b>32</b> functions so that the lid <b>27</b> of the drink holder <b>25</b> closes when pushed once and opens when pushed once more.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">More specifically, when the lid <b>27</b> is pushed into a closed state from an open state, the input/output shaft <b>31</b> connected to the lid <b>27</b> is rotated and the inner case <b>37</b>, which is rendered integral in the rotational direction with the input/output shaft <b>31</b> through the key ways <b>49</b> and the key lugs <b>50</b>, rotates relative to the outer case <b>35</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">At this time, the viscous fluid <b>42</b> (e.g., silicone oil), which is interposed between the inner periphery surface of the outer case <b>35</b> and the outer periphery surface of the inner case <b>37</b>, functions as fluid bearing. When the rotational force is thus imparted to the inner case through the lid <b>27</b>, the coiled spring <b>55</b> is tightened, thereby accumulating a restoring force.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">At this time, the operating pin <b>64</b> moves along the guide groove <b>61</b> from an opposite end side to one end side of the guide groove. Subsequently, the pin <b>64</b> shifts to the heart cam groove <b>60</b> located at one end side of the guide groove and reaches one end portion <b>60</b><i>a </i>of the heart cam groove <b>60</b> through the arcuate path of the same groove. Thereafter, the pin <b>64</b> returns a little and is caught (i.e., stopped) in the slit <b>60</b><i>c </i>of the heart island <b>62</b>, thereby maintaining the lid <b>27</b> in a closed position.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Next, when the lid <b>27</b> is pushed again, the operating pin <b>64</b> shifts from the slit <b>60</b><i>c </i>of the heart island <b>62</b> to the other end portion <b>60</b><i>b </i>of the heart cam groove <b>60</b>. Subsequently, the pin <b>64</b>, with the restoring force of the coiled spring <b>55</b>, returns from the other end portion <b>60</b><i>b </i>of the heart cam groove <b>60</b> to one end side of the guide groove <b>61</b> through the straight path. Thereafter the pin <b>64</b> moves to the opposite end side of the guide groove <b>61</b>, thereby opening the lid <b>27</b> automatically.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">At this time, the viscous fluid <b>42</b>, which is interposed between the inner periphery surface of the outer case <b>35</b> and the outer periphery surface of the inner case <b>37</b>, functions as a rotation control member, so that the lid <b>27</b> opens slowly with a high-class feeling.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">According to this embodiment, as the bottomed, short cylindrical outer and inner cases <b>35</b>, <b>37</b> (each of which has an opening at one end thereof) are brought face-to-face with each other and as the inner and outer cases <b>35</b>, <b>37</b> are fitted together to form the damper body <b>38</b>, it is possible to reduce the number of components used, thereby reducing the cost.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Further, as the operating pin <b>64</b> is disposed sideways of the coiled spring <b>55</b> in the internal space of the damper body <b>38</b>, it is possible to form the damper body <b>38</b> in a generally short cylindrical shape, thereby attaining a compact structure of the device.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Although an embodiment of the present invention has been described above in detail with reference to the accompanying drawings, no limitation is made thereto, but there may be made design changes and the like insofar as they are within the scope not departing from the gist of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">For example, it is not limited to the lid <b>27</b> of the drink holder that the rotary damper <b>32</b> of this embodiment is applied.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A rotary damper comprising:
<claim-text>a rotary shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a damper body mounted on the rotary shaft, the damper body comprising:
<claim-text>a bottomed, cylindrical outer case, which has an opening at one end thereof on an opposite side to which the rotary shaft extends and having a retaining portion on the opening at the one end; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bottomed, cylindrical inner case, which has an opening at one end thereof, wherein the inner case is rotatably arranged in the outer case and a bottom surface thereof is retained by the retaining portion of the outer case;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cam mechanism provided in the damper body to set a rotation pattern of the rotary shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a restoring force-accumulating member that accumulates a restoring force in accordance with rotation of the rotary shaft; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotation control member for controlling the rotation of the rotary shaft,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said rotation control member is interposed between an inner periphery surface of said outer case and an outer periphery surface of said inner case,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said restoring force-accumulating member is provided around the rotary shaft in the damper body,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said cam mechanism extends from said outer case to said inner case, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said cam mechanism is disposed radially and side-by-side relative to the rotary shaft and the restoring force-accumulating member in the damper body.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein said cam mechanism comprises a guide groove and an operating pin,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide groove is formed in one of said inner case and said outer case, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said operating pin is guided at one end thereof by said guide groove and retained at an opposite end thereof by the other of said inner case and said outer case.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein a shaft holding portion is formed in an interior of said inner case for coupling a rotational axis of said damper body and said rotary shaft,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said restoring force-accumulating member is a coiled spring that is fitted on an outer periphery side of said shaft holding portion,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein both ends of said coiled spring are anchored to said inner case and said outer case, respectively,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide groove of said cam mechanism has a heart cam groove in an end portion thereof, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said cam mechanism is disposed side-by-side with respect to said coiled spring in an interior space of said damper body.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said rotation control member is a viscous fluid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said rotation control member is a viscous fluid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said rotation control member is a viscous fluid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said viscous fluid comprises silicon grease.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said viscous fluid comprises silicon grease.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said viscous fluid comprises silicon grease.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A rotary damper comprising:
<claim-text>a rotary shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a damper body mounted on the rotary shaft, the damper body comprising:
<claim-text>a bottomed, cylindrical outer case, which has an opening at one end thereof on an opposite side to which the rotary shaft extends and having a retaining portion on the opening at the one end; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bottomed, cylindrical inner case, which has an opening at one end thereof, wherein the inner case is rotatably arranged in the outer case and a bottom surface thereof is retained by the retaining portion of the outer case;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cam mechanism provided in the damper body to set a rotation pattern of the rotary shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a restoring force-accumulating member that accumulates a restoring force in accordance with rotation of the rotary shaft; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotation control member for controlling the rotation of the rotary shaft,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said rotation control member is interposed between an inner periphery surface of said outer case and an outer periphery surface of said inner case,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said restoring force-accumulating member is provided around the rotary shaft in the damper body,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said cam mechanism comprises a guide groove and an operating pin,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said cam mechanism is disposed radially and side-by-side relative to the rotary shaft and the restoring force-accumulating member in the damper body,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide groove is formed in one of said inner case and said outer case, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said operating pin is guided at one end thereof by said guide groove and retained at an opposite end thereof by the other of said inner case and said outer case.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein a shaft holding portion is formed in an interior of said inner case for coupling a rotational axis of said damper body and said rotary shaft,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said restoring force-accumulating member is a coiled spring that is fitted on an outer periphery side of said shaft holding portion,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein both ends of said coiled spring are anchored to said inner case and said outer case, respectively,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide groove of said cam mechanism has a heart cam groove in an end portion thereof, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said cam mechanism is disposed side-by-side with respect to said coiled spring in an interior space of said damper body.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said rotation control member is a viscous fluid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein said rotation control member is a viscous fluid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said viscous fluid comprises silicon grease.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said viscous fluid comprises silicon grease.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A rotary damper, comprising:
<claim-text>a rotary shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a damper body mounted on the rotary shaft, the damper body comprising:
<claim-text>an outer case having an opening on one end on an opposite side to which the rotary shaft extends, a bottom surface on the other end thereof and a retaining portion on the opening on the one end; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inner case rotatably arranged in the outer case and having an opening on one end, and a bottom surface on the other thereof being retained by the retaining portion of the outer case;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cam mechanism provided in the damper body configured to set a rotation pattern of the rotary shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a restoring force-accumulating member configured to accumulate a restoring force in accordance with rotation of the rotary shaft; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotation control member interposed between an inner periphery surface of the outer case and an outer periphery surface of the inner case on an outer periphery side of the damper body and configured to control the rotation of the rotary shaft.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the retaining portion includes a plurality of retaining pawls provided on the opening on the one end of the outer case in a circumferential direction of the outer case.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the cam mechanism includes a guide groove provided in one of the inner case and the outer case, and an operating pin guided on one end thereof by the guide groove and retained on an opposite end thereof by the other of the inner case and the outer case.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The rotary damper according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the cam mechanism is disposed to extend from the outer case to the inner case and disposed sideways of the restoring force-accumulating member in the damper body.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
