<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296970-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296970</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11148040</doc-number>
<date>20050608</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>341</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>64</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>64</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 44</main-classification>
<further-classification>416 51</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Ram air turbine speed sensing ball detent over-speed prevention mechanism</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2685932</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hartel</name>
<date>19540800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>416 37</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4743163</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Markunas et al.</name>
<date>19880500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2072271</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19810900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>28</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415 30</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415 33</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415 34</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415 13</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 44</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 51</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 45</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 46</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>1</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060280603</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061214</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bannon</last-name>
<first-name>David G.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Rockford</city>
<state>IL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Seidel</last-name>
<first-name>William E.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Rockford</city>
<state>IL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mican</last-name>
<first-name>Stephen G.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hamilton Sundstrand Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Windsor Locks</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Look</last-name>
<first-name>Edward K.</first-name>
<department>3745</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>White</last-name>
<first-name>Dwayne J</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A ram air turbine (RAT) prevents release of its turbine blades due an over-speed condition by detecting an over-speed condition with a turbine hub-mounted centrifugally operated trigger mechanism and rotating the blades to a fixed coarse pitch position with a release mechanism that responds to the trigger mechanism.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="102.70mm" wi="223.60mm" file="US07296970-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="226.65mm" wi="137.41mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296970-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention relates to emergency supplemental power supplies for aeronautical applications, and more particularly to an improved ram air turbine for generating emergency supplemental power for aircraft in flight.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A ram air turbine (RAT) is a device for generating emergency supplemental power in a wide variety of aircraft. A RAT may generate hydraulic power, electric power or both. A RAT incorporates a turbine that extracts power from an air stream proximate the aircraft in flight. A typical RAT in current use is described in U.S. Pat. No. 4,743,163 to Markunas et al., owned by the assignee of this application, and incorporated herein by reference. The turbine is coupled to suitable power generating equipment, such as a hydraulic pump for hydraulic power and an electric generator for electric power, or both in the case of a hybrid RAT.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">As described in Markunas et al., the turbine includes a speed governor that changes the turbine blade position to maintain a relatively constant shaft speed to the power generating equipment. Failure of the turbine speed governor can cause an over-speed condition that may ultimately cause the release of a turbine blade at very high speed. Due to the high speed, the wayward blade has very high energy as well. The most common cause of governor failure is due to seizure of the bearing between the turbine shaft and the governor yoke plate that controls the pitch of the turbine blades.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The potential release of a high-energy blade proximate the aircraft is a concern for both commercial and military RAT applications. Should the wayward blade strike the aircraft fuselage, it may penetrate the skin and cause damage to electric or hydraulic power equipment or control systems. It may also injure passengers or crew. If one of the propulsion engines ingests the wayward blade, the engine may suffer severe damage that results in loss of thrust.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Current methods to minimise hazards caused by turbine over-speed-induced release of a turbine blade have involved strategic placement of key elements or shields to prevent penetration. These methods no longer satisfy increasingly stringent certification and safety requirements promoted by airworthiness authorities.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The invention comprises a RAT that prevents release of its turbine blades due an over-speed condition by detecting an over-speed condition with a turbine hub-mounted centrifugally operated trigger mechanism and rotating the blades to a fixed coarse pitch position with a release mechanism that responds to the trigger mechanism.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In a preferred embodiment, the invention comprises an improved ram air turbine (RAT) for generating emergency aeronautical supplemental power that has a governor for automatically adjusting the pitch of turbine blades rotatingly attached to a RAT turbine hub with an axis of rotation and coupled to a governor mechanism by way of cam plate and respective cam follower pins, comprising: a centrifugally operated trigger mechanism attached to the turbine hub responsive to an over-speed condition of the turbine hub; and a release mechanism responsive to the trigger mechanism that frees the turbine blades from the governor mechanism by separating the cam follower plate from the cam follower pins to let them assume a fixed coarse pitch condition.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a sectional cut-away side view of a RAT that incorporates the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">As described in Markunas et al., during normal operation RAT speed is controlled with a counterweight/spring governor balance system. As speed increases the centrifugal torque of a blade/counterweight assembly increases. This torque acts through a cam follower and yoke plate slidingly supported by a turbine shaft to compress a helical spring and thus change the position of the yoke plate. The blades move to a coarser angle with movement of the yoke plate and thus extract less power from the air stream. In this way, the turbine speed is controlled over a range of airspeeds, altitudes and loads.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Such a mechanical governor system requires a translation of rotary motion about the axis of the turbine blade due to the blade/counterweight assembly turning about the blade pitch change axis to axial motion along the turbine shaft such that the force balance with the helical spring can be affected. The translation occurs by means of a roller bearing on the counterweight assembly that engages a bearing surface on the yoke plate. The yoke plate in turn engages the turbine shaft with a linear bearing to slide along the turbine shaft, so that low-friction translation is obtained. Unfortunately, seizure of this linear bearing sometimes occurs and such seizure tends to lock the blades at or near the fine pitch position. In this position, the turbine is most susceptible to over-speed. The invention dramatically reduces the likelihood of over-speed-induced release of a turbine blade due to such a failure of the mechanical governor system.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a sectional cut-away side view of a portion of a turbine hub <b>2</b> for a RAT that incorporates this invention. The turbine hub <b>2</b> has turbine shaft <b>4</b> with a turbine shaft axis of rotation <b>6</b> that is supported by at least a bearing assembly <b>8</b>. Turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>10</b> rotatingly attached to the turbine hub <b>2</b> by bearing assemblies (not shown) are free to rotate about a turbine blade axis of rotation <b>12</b> that is generally perpendicular to the turbine shaft axis of rotation <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">At start-up, the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>10</b> maintain a fine pitch position. An air stream generally parallel to the turbine shaft axis <b>6</b> due to motion of the RAT causes the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>10</b> to revolve about the turbine shaft axis <b>6</b>. Resulting centrifugal twisting moments (CTMs) on the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>10</b> due to the air stream and centrifugal counterweight forces cause them to start to rotate toward a coarse pitch position. Relative to the turbine axis <b>6</b>, rotary motion of the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>10</b> rotatingly attached to the turbine hub <b>2</b> translates to axial motion through cam follower or op pins <b>14</b> riding on a cam plate <b>16</b>. The cam plate <b>16</b> normally attaches to a governor yoke plate <b>18</b>. Linear bearings <b>20</b> provide an axial freedom of movement of the yoke plate <b>18</b> along a governor shaft <b>22</b> that has a common axis of rotation with the turbine shaft axis <b>6</b>. As the yoke plate <b>18</b> moves axially in response to the change of position of the cam follower pins <b>14</b>, the yoke plate <b>18</b> compresses a governor spring assembly <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">As the yoke plate <b>18</b> compresses the governor spring assembly <b>24</b>, the governor spring assembly <b>24</b> exerts an increasing force that opposes the force applied to the yoke plate <b>18</b> by the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>10</b>. The yoke plate <b>18</b> changes the pitch of the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>10</b> to be more coarse as it moves axially toward the governor spring assembly <b>24</b>, thereby reducing the force of the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>10</b>, thereby bringing about a force equilibrium that ultimately controls turbine speed. Although the governor spring assembly <b>24</b> comprises two nested helical springs <b>26</b> held between the yolk plate <b>18</b> and a forward spring seat <b>28</b> attached to the governor shaft <b>22</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, any number of helical springs, or alternatively, other axial spring designs such as disc (Belleville) springs, may be used.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to a first embodiment of the invention, at least one centrifugal plunger assembly <b>30</b>, and preferably a pair or more of opposed centrifugal plunger assemblies <b>30</b> to provide dynamic balance, mount within or about the cam plate <b>16</b>. Each centrifugal plunger assembly <b>30</b> comprises at least a centrifugal plunger <b>32</b>, a plunger cylinder <b>34</b> and a compression plunger bias spring <b>36</b>. One end of the plunger <b>32</b> captivates the plunger bias spring <b>36</b> within the plunger cylinder <b>34</b>. The plunger cylinder <b>34</b> is aligned within or about the cam plate <b>16</b> so that the plunger <b>32</b> has a radial freedom of movement relative to the turbine axis <b>6</b>. The plunger cylinder <b>34</b> may be a cavity within the cam plate <b>16</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, or alternatively may be an independent unit mounted within or about the cam plate <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">When the turbine hub <b>2</b> operates no greater than its normal operating speed, for each plunger assembly <b>30</b> the plunger bias spring <b>36</b> holds a free end <b>38</b> of the plunger <b>32</b> against a ball <b>40</b> that sits in a detent <b>42</b> along the yoke plate <b>18</b>. In this embodiment of the invention, the cam plate <b>16</b> is rigidly coupled to the yoke plate <b>18</b> by way of this ball-detent interface. When the turbine hub <b>2</b> exceeds its normal operating speed, the centrifugal force of the plunger <b>32</b> radially away from the turbine shaft axis <b>6</b> starts to exceed the force of the plunger bias spring <b>36</b> against the plunger <b>32</b>. As a result, for each centrifugal plunger assembly <b>30</b> the plunger <b>32</b> starts to displace radially outwardly in the plunger cylinder <b>34</b> away from the turbine shaft axis <b>6</b>, thereby creating a gap between the plunger free end <b>38</b> and the adjacent ball <b>40</b>. The centrifugal plunger assemblies <b>30</b> thereby act as a centrifugal trigger mechanism.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Each ball <b>40</b> then moves out of its respective detent <b>42</b> due to centrifugal force on it combined with the axial force exerted by the cam follower pins <b>14</b> on the cam plate <b>16</b>, thus removing the ball-detent coupling of the cam plate <b>16</b> to the yoke plate <b>18</b>. The balls <b>40</b> and detents <b>42</b> thus act as a release mechanism that is activated by the centrifugal trigger mechanism that comprises the centrifugal plunger assemblies <b>30</b>. In this way, even if the linear bearings <b>20</b> are frozen such that the yoke plate <b>18</b> is not free to move along the governor shaft <b>22</b>, the cam plate <b>16</b> is now free to move axially along the yoke plate <b>18</b> until it makes contact with an inner seat <b>44</b> of the yoke plate <b>18</b>, thereby letting the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>12</b> assume a coarse position that slows down the turbine hub <b>2</b> to a safe operating speed.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In an alternative embodiment of the invention, the centrifugal plunger assemblies <b>30</b> may be mounted within or about the turbine shaft <b>4</b>, indicated in dashed line as <b>30</b>′. In this case, the balls <b>40</b>′ are held in detents <b>42</b>′ in the governor shaft <b>22</b>, so that the governor shaft <b>22</b> is rigidly coupled to the turbine shaft <b>4</b> by way of this ball-detent interface. When the turbine hub <b>2</b> exceeds its normal operating speed, for each centrifugal plunger assembly <b>30</b> the centrifugal force of the plunger <b>32</b> radially away from the turbine shaft axis <b>6</b> starts to exceed the force of the plunger bias spring <b>36</b> against the plunger <b>32</b>. As a result, the plunger <b>32</b> starts to displace radially outwardly in the plunger cylinder <b>34</b> away from the turbine shaft axis <b>6</b>, thereby creating a gap between the plunger free end <b>38</b> and the adjacent ball <b>40</b>′. The centrifugal plunger assemblies <b>30</b>′ thereby act as a centrifugal trigger mechanism.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Each ball <b>40</b>′ then moves out of its respective detent <b>42</b>′ due to centrifugal force on it combined with the axial force exerted by the cam follower pins <b>14</b> on the cam plate, thus removing the ball-detent coupling of the cam plate <b>16</b> to the yoke plate <b>18</b>. The balls <b>38</b>′ and detents <b>40</b>′ thus act as a release mechanism that is activated by the centrifugal trigger mechanism that comprises the centrifugal plunger assemblies <b>30</b>. In this way, even if the linear bearings <b>20</b> are frozen such that the yoke plate <b>18</b> is not free to move along the governor shaft <b>22</b>, the governor shaft <b>22</b> is now free to move axially with respect to the turbine shaft <b>4</b> until the forward spring seat <b>28</b> attached to the governor shaft <b>22</b> makes contact with a retaining ring <b>46</b> attached to the turbine shaft <b>4</b>, thereby letting the turbine blade/counterweight assemblies <b>12</b> assume a coarse position that slows down the turbine hub <b>2</b> to a safe operating speed.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The invention as described above comprises a RAT that prevents release of its turbine blades due an over-speed condition by detecting an over-speed condition with a turbine hub-mounted centrifugally operated trigger mechanism and rotating the blades to a fixed coarse pitch position with a release mechanism that responds to the trigger mechanism. It should be understood that this embodiment is only an illustrative implementation of the invention, that the various parts and arrangement thereof may be changed or substituted, and that the invention is only limited by the scope of the attached claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An improved ram air turbine (RAT) for generating emergency aeronautical supplemental power that has a governor for automatically adjusting the pitch of turbine blades rotatingly attached to a RAT turbine hub with an axis of rotation and coupled to a governor mechanism by way of cam plate and respective cam follower pins, comprising:
<claim-text>a centrifugally operated trigger mechanism attached to the turbine hub responsive to an over-speed condition of the turbine hub; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a release mechanism responsive to the trigger mechanism that frees the turbine blades from the governor mechanism by separating the cam follower plate from the cam follower pins to let them assume a fixed coarse pitch condition.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the centrifugally operated trigger mechanism comprises at least one centrifugal plunger assembly mounted within the turbine hub with a plunger that shifts position radially from the axis of the turbine hub when the RAT exceeds normal operating speed to activate the release mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the centrifugally operated trigger mechanism comprises a pair of opposed centrifugal plunger assemblies.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugally operated plunger assembly comprises a compression plunger spring coupled to a plunger that moves radially outwardly from the turbine hub axis when its centrifugal force exceeds a preload bias force of the plunger spring as the RAT exceeds its normal speed of operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the release mechanism comprises at least one ball detent mechanism that axially positions the cam plate within the turbine hub with a ball held in place by one end of a corresponding one of the centrifugal plunger assembly plungers, wherein the plunger releases the ball from its position in the ball detent mechanism to release the cam plate from its axial position when the RAT exceeds its normal speed of operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the ball for each ball detent mechanism sits in a detent along a yoke plate for the governor mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts within the cam plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts about the cam plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the ball for each ball detent mechanism sits in a detent along a governor shaft for the governor mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts within a turbine shaft for the turbine hub.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts about a turbine shaft for the turbine hub.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An improved ram air turbine (RAT) for generating emergency aeronautical supplemental power that has a governor for automatically adjusting the pitch of turbine blades rotatingly attached to a RAT turbine hub with an axis of rotation and coupled to a governor mechanism by way of cam plate and respective cam follower pins, comprising:
<claim-text>a centrifugally operated trigger mechanism comprising at least one centrifugal plunger assembly mounted within the turbine hub with a plunger that shifts position radially from the axis of the turbine hub when the RAT exceeds normal operating speed; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a release mechanism that frees the turbine blades from the governor mechanism by separating the cam follower plate from the cam follower pins to let them assume a fixed coarse pitch condition responsive to the trigger mechanism, comprising at least one ball detent mechanism that axially positions the cam plate within the turbine hub with a ball held in place by one end of a corresponding one of the centrifugal plunger assembly plungers, wherein the plunger for the centrifugal operated trigger mechanism releases the ball from its position in the ball detent mechanism to release the cam plate from its axial position when the RAT exceeds its normal speed of operation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the centrifugally operated trigger mechanism comprises a pair of opposed centrifugal plunger assemblies.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugally operated plunger assembly comprises a compression plunger spring coupled to a plunger that moves radially outwardly from the turbine hub axis when its centrifugal force exceeds a preload bias force of the plunger spring as the RAT exceeds its normal speed of operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the ball for each ball detent mechanism sits in a detent along a yoke plate for the governor mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts within the cam plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts about the cam plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the ball for each ball detent mechanism sits in a detent along a governor shaft for the governor mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts within a turbine shaft for the turbine hub.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts about a turbine shaft for the turbine hub.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. An improved ram air turbine (RAT) for generating emergency aeronautical supplemental power that has a governor for automatically adjusting the pitch of turbine blades rotatingly attached to a RAT turbine hub with an axis of rotation and coupled to a governor mechanism by way of cam plate and respective cam follower pins, comprising:
<claim-text>a centrifugally operated trigger mechanism comprising at least one centrifugal plunger assembly mounted within the turbine hub with a plunger that shifts position radially from the axis of the turbine hub when the RAT exceeds normal operating speed; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a release mechanism responsive to the trigger mechanism that frees the turbine blades from the governor mechanism by separating the cam follower plate from the cam follower pins to let them assume a fixed coarse pitch condition, comprising at least one ball detent mechanism that axially positions the cam plate within the turbine hub with a ball sitting in a detent along a yoke plate for the governor mechanism held in place by one end of a corresponding one of the centrifugal plunger assembly plungers, wherein the plunger for the centrifugal operated trigger mechanism releases the ball from its position in the ball detent mechanism to release the cam plate from its axial position when the RAT exceeds its normal speed of operation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref>, wherein the centrifugally operated trigger mechanism comprises a pair of opposed centrifugal plunger assemblies.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugally operated plunger assembly comprises a compression plunger spring coupled to a plunger that moves radially outwardly from the turbine hub axis when its centrifugal force exceeds a preload bias force of the plunger spring as the RAT exceeds its normal speed of operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts within the cam plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts about the cam plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. An improved ram air turbine (RAT) for generating emergency aeronautical supplemental power that has a governor for automatically adjusting the pitch of turbine blades rotatingly attached to a RAT turbine hub with an axis of rotation and coupled to a governor mechanism by way of cam plate and respective cam follower pins, comprising:
<claim-text>a centrifugally operated trigger mechanism comprising at least one centrifugal plunger assembly mounted within the turbine hub with a plunger that shifts position radially from the axis of the turbine hub when the RAT exceeds normal operating speed; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a release mechanism responsive to the trigger mechanism for freeing the turbine blades from the governor mechanism by separating the cam follower plate from the cam follower pins to let them assume a fixed coarse pitch condition comprising at least one ball detent mechanism that axially positions the cam plate within the turbine hub with a ball sitting in a detent along a governor shaft for the governor mechanism held in place by one end of a corresponding one of the centrifugal plunger assembly plungers, wherein the plunger for the centrifugal operated trigger mechanism releases the ball from its position in the ball detent mechanism to release the cam plate from its axial position when the RAT exceeds its normal speed of operation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00026">claim 26</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts within a turbine shaft for the turbine hub.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The RAT of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00026">claim 26</claim-ref>, wherein each centrifugal plunger assembly mounts about a turbine shaft for the turbine hub.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
