<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298185-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298185</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11054356</doc-number>
<date>20050209</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>10 2004 006 254</doc-number>
<date>20040209</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>179</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327143</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Circuit arrangement for production of a reset signal after a supply has fallen and risen again</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4594688</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Uno</name>
<date>19860600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>365 95</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4634904</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wong</name>
<date>19870100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5321317</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Pascucci et al.</name>
<date>19940600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5517144</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nakashima</name>
<date>19960500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327198</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5552725</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ray et al.</name>
<date>19960900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5812001</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Imamiya</name>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327198</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5847586</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Burstein et al.</name>
<date>19981200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327142</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6016068</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ding</name>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327142</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6060919</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wilson et al.</name>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6556058</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Ohbayashi et al.</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6600350</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Sekimoto et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0028263</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ohbayashi et al.</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0201807</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ohbayashi et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>0 482 661</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>19920400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>55047727</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19800400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>01192212</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19890800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00017">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>01212024</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19890800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327143</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327198</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>19</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050195001</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050908</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Motz</last-name>
<first-name>Mario</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wernberg</city>
<country>AT</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>AT</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>AT</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Maginot, Moore &amp; Beck</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Infineon Technologies AG</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Munich</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Tra</last-name>
<first-name>Quan</first-name>
<department>2816</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The invention relates to a circuit arrangement for production of a reset signal after a supply voltage (Vdd) has fallen and risen again, which circuit arrangement has two cross-coupled inverters (INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>) and an initialization circuit (S) which is connected to the input of one of the inverters (INV<b>2</b>), in which case the outputs of the inverters (INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>) are capacitively connected asymmetrically, andlor in which case the inverters (INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>) have different transfer voltages.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="93.39mm" wi="128.10mm" file="US07298185-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="158.07mm" wi="132.76mm" file="US07298185-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="186.27mm" wi="130.64mm" file="US07298185-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="194.56mm" wi="128.35mm" file="US07298185-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="111.76mm" wi="132.84mm" file="US07298185-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="212.60mm" wi="137.24mm" file="US07298185-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="208.45mm" wi="128.44mm" file="US07298185-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="187.71mm" wi="121.16mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298185-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="211.24mm" wi="126.49mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298185-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a circuit arrangement for production of a rest signal after a supply voltage has fallen and risen again, in particular for use in a circuit which has a static memory.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Static memories (SRAMs) permanently require a supply voltage for reliable maintenance of a predetermined memory state, and this supply voltage must not fall below a predetermined value which is dependent on the technology of the respective memory. If the supply voltage falls below this minimum value despite this, then this can lead to undesirable changes in the memory states of individual memory cells, or to undefined memory states.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">It is therefore necessary to identify such a fall in the supply voltage (which, for example, may be also be caused by EMC interference radiation) and to make a reset signal available once the supply voltage has risen again to a value which is required for reliable operation. A reset signal such as this may be used, for example, to carry out initialization of the memory via further circuit components. Various concepts are known for production of such reset signals.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Fundamentally, it is possible to compare the supply voltage with a reference voltage continuously and to produce a reset signal when the supply voltage falls below the reference voltage. A circuit arrangement such as this, which uses a reference voltage source, for producing a reset signal is described, for example, in U.S. Pat. No. 5,552,725.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">This concept has the disadvantage that the reference voltage source which, for example, may also be in the form of a band gap reference voltage source, permanently draws an operating current in the μA range. This concept is not suitable for battery-powered circuit applications in which a minimum power consumption must be ensured in order to achieve a long battery life.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">One example of applications such as these is so-called ultra low power sensors, whose voltage supply is intended to be ensured, by means of a small battery, for a time period of three to ten years. Sensors such as these operate intermittently with short operating phases during which the mean current that is drawn is in the μA range, and with rest phases which are long in comparison to the operating phases and in which the current that is drawn is intended to be less than 20 nA, in order to ensure a long battery life. Reset circuits which draw small currents such as these can be produced, for example, using very high-value resistors, but these occupy a very large amount of space. In the case of sensors such as these, comparison values relating to the measured values determined by the sensor are stored, for example, in an SRAM. Sensors such as these are used, for example, as tire pressure sensors in motor vehicles, which cannot be connected to the vehicle power supply system voltage and which must therefore be supplied via their own battery, which is isolated from the vehicle power supply system battery.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">U.S. Pat. No. 6,556,058 B2 describes a POR circuit (POR=Power On Reset) for production of a reset signal after a supply voltage has been switched on, in which a threshold voltage of an MOS transistor is used as a reference voltage for the production of a reset signal when the supply voltage rises.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">U.S. Pat. No. 6,600,350 B2 describes a POR circuit having a capacitor which is connected to the supply voltage via a resistor, and whose state of charge is evaluated in order to produce a reset signal. This circuit has the disadvantage that it does not operate reliably when the supply voltage rises slowly again.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The aim of the present invention is to provide a circuit arrangement for production of a reset signal after a supply voltage has fallen and risen again, which circuit arrangement draws a very low current, can be produced easily and operates reliably.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The circuit arrangement according to the invention for production of a reset signal after a supply voltage has fallen and risen again has a first and a second inverter, which each have one input and one output. The input of the first inverter is in this case coupled to the output of the second inverter, and the input of the second inverter is coupled to the output of the first inverter. The two inverters are connected between the first and the second supply voltage terminals, between which the supply voltage is present. The two cross-coupled inverters operate like a static memory cell, which can be initialized via an initialization circuit which is connected to the input of one of the inverters.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The circuit arrangement also has a first rectifier element which is connected between the output of one of the inverters and one of the supply voltage terminals, and a first capacitance which is connected between this output and the other of the supply voltage terminals and which is larger than a capacitance which is provided between the output of the other inverter and the respective supply voltage terminal. In the case of the circuit arrangement according to the invention, the larger capacitance on the output of one of the inverters means that the static memory cell formed by the first and second inverters is capacitively asymmetric. This first capacitance is discharged via the rectifier element when the supply voltage falls, in order to follow the falling supply voltage. When the supply voltage rises again, the first capacitance ensures that the output of the inverter follows the voltage rise of the supply voltage in a slowed-down form, in order to ensure that, when the supply voltage rises again, the memory cell assumes a memory state which is complementary to the memory state after initialization of the memory cell, that is to say before the supply voltage fell. In the case of this circuit arrangement, the output signal from either of the two inverters is evaluated as a reset signal, with a high level or a low level of this output signal being used as the reset level depending on the level that this signal assumes after initialization of the circuit arrangement.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The first and second inverters may each have a first transistor and a second transistor, which is complementary to this first transistor, in which case the load paths of those first and second transistors of the inverters are connected between the first and the second supply voltage terminal, and in which case the drive connections of the first and second transistors of an inverter are jointly connected to the input of the respective inverter.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The first and second transistors in the inverters may in this case be in the form of mutually complementary MOS transistors. MOS transistors such as these inherently all have a drive capacitance, the so-called gate/source capacitance, between their gate connection, which forms the drive connection, and their source connection, which forms one of the load path connections. If the inverters are produced in a manner such as this by means of MOS transistors, it is possible for the first capacitance which is connected to the output of one of the inverters, and thus to the input of the other inverter, to be provided by the gate/source capacitance of one of the transistors, and this gate/source capacitance can be varied by means of the surface area of the gate electrode of this transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">It is, of course, also possible for the first capacitance to be formed by a separate capacitor, which is connected between the output of one of the inverters and one of the supply voltage terminals.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The switching behavior of the circuit arrangement according to the invention after the supply voltage has fallen and risen again, from a first switching state after initialization of the circuit arrangement to a second, complementary switching state after the voltage supply has risen again can be improved by the first and second inverters having different transfer voltages. The transfer voltage of an inverter is in this case the value of an input voltage which is applied to the input for which an output voltage which is produced at the output reaches 50% of its level change resulting from the supply voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The transfer voltages of the inverters may in this case be varied by means of the width-to-length ratio of the first and second transistors in the inverters. It is also possible to vary the transfer voltages of the inverters by means of a diode, which is connected in series with the load paths of the first and second transistors in the inverters. Using modern technologies, this diode can advantageously be in the form of an MOS transistor with a low threshold voltage (low threshold voltage transistor), whose drain and gate are shorted together. This allows diode voltages of only about 0.4 V to be achieved. The provision of diodes such as these makes it possible for the inverter transistors to be discharged to below the threshold voltage when operating voltage dips occur.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The circuit arrangement as claimed in claim <b>11</b> likewise has a first and a second inverter, which each have one input and one output and which are likewise cross-coupled, with the output of the first inverter being connected to the input of the second inverter, and the output of the second inverter being connected to the input of the first inverter. The two inverters each have two supply connections, which are connected between a first and a second supply voltage terminal, between which the supply voltage is present. These two inverters form a memory cell which can be initialized via an initialization circuit which is connected to the input of one of the inverters. The two inverters also have different transfer voltages, which are matched to one another such that, after the supply voltage has fallen and risen again, the two inverters each assume complementary switching states in comparison to the respective switching states after initialization of the circuit arrangement.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">This circuit arrangement, in which the memory state is changed by the provision of different transfer voltages for the two inverters, is particularly suitable for detection of a slow rise in the supply voltage after it has fallen.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The two inverters preferably each have a first and a second transistor, whose load paths are connected in series between the supply connections of the inverters, and whose drive connections are each jointly connected to the input of the respective inverter.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The transfer voltages of the inverters can be varied by means of the width-to-length ratio of the first and second transistors, or by the provision of a resistance element or a diode in series with the load paths of the first and second transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The circuit arrangement according to the invention, which can be produced in particular using transistors based on CMOS technology, draws no significant current after it has been initialized and can therefore be used in particular for detection of a supply voltage falling and rising again in circuit arrangements in which the reset circuit has to have a low power consumption.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The present invention will be explained in more detail in the following text using exemplary embodiments and with reference to the Figures, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a first exemplary embodiment of a circuit arrangement according to the invention having two cross-coupled inverters, whose outputs are capacitively connected asymmetrically.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows, by way of example, time profiles of signals in the circuit illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, in order to explain the method of operation when the supply voltage falls.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows an example of a circuitry implementation of the arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> using CMOS inverters.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the electrical equivalent circuit of the circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> for low supply voltages.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows, by way of example, time profiles of signals in the circuit illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, in order to explain the method of operation when the supply voltage falls.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows one possible way to provide the capacitances which are illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> and result in the asymmetric capacitive circuitry.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows an alternative circuit arrangement to the circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows a further exemplary embodiment of a circuit arrangement according to the invention having two cross-coupled inverters which have different transfer points.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows examples of the time profiles of signals in the circuit illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, in order to explain the method of operation when the supply voltage falls and rises slowly again.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows various concepts for variation of the transfer point of a CMOS inverter.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows an exemplary embodiment of a circuit arrangement according to the invention which has two cross-coupled inverters which are connected capacitively asymmetrically and which have different transfer points.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows an arrangement having a number of reset cells, with different dimensions, in order to produce a reset signal.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Unless stated to the contrary, identical-reference symbols in the Figures denote identical circuit components and signals with the same meaning.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a first exemplary embodiment of a circuit arrangement for production of a reset signal after a supply voltage Vdd has fallen and risen again. The circuit arrangement has a first inverter INV<b>1</b> having an input IN<b>1</b> and an output OUT<b>1</b>, as well as a second inverter INV<b>2</b> having an input IN<b>2</b> and an output OUT<b>2</b>. The two inverters also each have first and second supply connections A<b>11</b>, A<b>12</b>, A<b>21</b>, A<b>22</b>, which are each connected between supply voltage terminals between which the supply voltage Vdd is present. This supply voltage Vdd in the exemplary embodiment is related to a reference ground potential GND to which the two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> are respectively connected via their second connecting terminal A<b>12</b>, A<b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> are cross-coupled by the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> being connected to the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, and by the output OUT<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> being connected to the input IN<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The first and second inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> operate in the form of a memory cell which can be initialized by means of an initialization circuit. In the exemplary embodiment, the initialization circuit has a switch S which is connected between the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> and the reference ground potential GND, and which can be driven by means of an initialization signal INIT. The two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> are connected capacitively asymmetrically by connecting a first capacitance C<b>2</b> between the output OUT<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> and the terminal for the reference ground potential GND, while no such additional capacitance is provided between the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> and the terminal for the reference ground potential GND. The capacitance between the output terminal OUT<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> and the terminal for the reference ground potential GND is greater than the capacitance between the first output terminal OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> and the terminal for the reference ground potential GND, on the assumption that the two inverters are internally designed to be identical.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The method of operation of the circuit arrangement illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> which, because of its similarity to a memory cell, is referred to in the following text as a reset cell, will be explained in the following text with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows, by way of example, the time profile of the supply voltage Vdd which, in the example, falls to a considerably low voltage level from a time t<b>1</b> starting from a first voltage level Vn which, for example, corresponds to the nominal voltage level for the supply voltage Vdd and which rises to the nominal voltage level Vn again from a time t<b>2</b>, starting from this low voltage level. Fluctuations in the supply voltage Vdd such as these may be caused, for example, by external influences, for example by radiated EMC interference.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The rest of the explanation is based on the assumption that the reset cell has been initialized before the time t<b>1</b>. For initialization of the reset cell, the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> and the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> are connected to the reference ground potential GND via the switch S, so that the output signal Vout<b>1</b> which is produced at the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> assumes a low level. This low level is also stored after the switch S has been opened, since the low level at the input of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> causes a high level at its output OUT<b>2</b>, and thus at the input IN<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b>. During the initialization process, the switch S remains closed until the low level at the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> results in the first capacitance C<b>1</b> at its output OUT<b>2</b> rising to the value of the supply voltage Vdd. The illustration in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is in this case based on the assumption that the inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> are ideal inverters, which produce at the output the level of the supply potential Vdd as a high level and the level of the reference ground potential GND as a low level.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">If the supply voltage Vdd falls starting from the time t<b>1</b>, then the output voltage Vout<b>2</b> from the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, which is produced across the capacitance C<b>2</b>, follows the supply voltage Vdd, with the output voltage Vout<b>2</b> being less than the supply voltage Vdd by the value of the forward voltage of the diode D<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> require a minimum supply voltage between their power supply connections A<b>11</b>, A<b>12</b>, A<b>21</b>, A<b>22</b> and, if the supply voltage falls below this level, are no longer able to convert an input signal to a complementary output signal. The following text is based on the assumption that the supply voltage Vdd falls below this minimum required supply voltage for the two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> after the time t<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">When the supply voltage Vdd reaches this minimum required supply voltage for the inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> after the time t<b>2</b> when it rises again, then the low signal from the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> is initially still present at the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, so that the capacitance C<b>2</b> is still initially connected to the rising supply potential Vdd via this inverter INV<b>2</b>. The signal Vout<b>2</b> at the output of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> can, however, follow the rise in the supply voltage Vdd only more slowly owing to the first capacitance C<b>2</b>, so that a low signal is initially still present at the input IN<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b>. The first inverter INV<b>1</b> therefore switches over, and its output signal Vout<b>1</b> is quickly drawn to the value of the rising supply potential Vdd, so that a high level is present at the input of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, which connects the output OUT<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> to the reference ground potential GND, in order to discharge the first capacitance C<b>2</b> and to set the output OUT<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> permanently to a low level.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The output signal Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> thus assumes a complementary switching state in comparison to the switching state after the initialization of the reset cell once the supply voltage Vdd has fallen and risen again. In the case of this reset cell, the output signal Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> can be used directly as the reset signal. In the exemplary embodiment which has been explained, a high level of this first output signal Vout<b>1</b>, that is to say a level which corresponds to the supply potential Vdd, indicates that there is a need to reset a circuit (which is not illustrated in more detail) which is connected to the supply voltage Vdd. This circuit may, for example, be a memory circuit with a large number of static memory cells.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">A conventional circuit arrangement can be used (in a manner which is not illustrated in any more detail) for evaluation of this output signal Vout<b>1</b> which is used as a reset signal, which circuit arrangement detects a rising flank of this output signal Vout<b>1</b> in order to initiate the resetting or initialization of further circuit components which are connected to the supply voltage Vdd.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">In addition to the output signal Vout<b>1</b>, the output signal Vout<b>2</b> from the second inverter INV<b>2</b> may, of course, also be used as a reset signal which, in the example, assumes a low level after the supply voltage Vdd has risen again, rather than the high level which existed after the initialization process.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Furthermore, it is also possible to evaluate the output signals Vout<b>1</b>, Vout<b>2</b> from the two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> using a logic circuit in order to produce a reset signal which then has only one level, which indicates the need to reset a circuit arrangement, when the output signal Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> assumes a high level and the output signal Vout<b>2</b> from the second inverter INV<b>2</b> assumes a low level. A logic circuit such as this is illustrated by dashed lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and has an AND gate with a non-inverting input and an inverting input, with the output signal Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> being supplied to the non-inverting input, and the output signal Vout<b>2</b> from the second inverter INV<b>2</b> being supplied to the inverting input. The reset signal RS is produced at the output of this gate <b>20</b> and assumes a high level in order to indicate the need to reset a circuit arrangement when the output signal Vout<b>1</b> assumes a high level and the output signal Vout<b>2</b> assumes a low level.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a circuitry implementation example of the circuit arrangement illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, in which the two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> are each in the form of a CMOS inverter, and which respectively have a first transistor T<b>10</b>, T<b>20</b> and a second transistor T<b>11</b>, T<b>21</b>. The drain/source paths through the first and second transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>20</b>, T<b>11</b>, T<b>21</b> in each inverter INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>, which form the load paths of the transistors, are connected in series between the supply connections A<b>11</b>, A<b>12</b>, A<b>21</b>, A<b>22</b> and thus between the terminal for the supply potential Vdd and the terminal for the reference ground potential GND. The first transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>20</b> are in the form of p-conductive MOS transistors, whose source connections are connected to the terminal for the supply potential Vdd, while the second transistors T<b>11</b>, T<b>21</b> are in the form of n-conductive MOS transistors, whose source connections are connected to the reference ground potential GND. The gate connections of the first and second transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>20</b>, T<b>11</b>, T<b>21</b> of each inverter INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>, which form the drive connections for the transistors, are jointly connected to the input IN<b>1</b>, IN<b>2</b> of the respective inverter INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>. The nodes which are common to the load paths of the first and second transistors form the outputs OUT<b>1</b>, OUT<b>2</b> of the inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">In order to assist understanding of the method of operation of the circuit arrangement, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> also shows the gate/source capacitances C<b>10</b>, C<b>11</b>, C<b>20</b>, C<b>21</b> of the transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>11</b>, T<b>20</b>, T<b>21</b> in the CMOS inverters. These capacitors C<b>10</b>-C<b>21</b> are an inherent component of the transistors T<b>10</b>-T<b>21</b> in the CMOS inverters.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">While the method of operation of the circuit arrangement has been described initially with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and taking into account only the basic method of operation of the inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>, the switching processes in the inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> will also be considered for the analysis of the method of operation of the exemplary embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">During the initialization phase, when the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> is connected to the reference ground potential GND via the switch S<b>1</b>, the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> is switched on, and its second transistor T<b>21</b> is switched off. The first capacitance C<b>2</b> is thus charged via the first transistor T<b>20</b> approximately to the supply potential Vdd, ignoring the voltage drop across the first transistor T<b>20</b>. When the voltage Vout<b>2</b> across this capacitance C<b>2</b> reaches the transfer voltage of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> during this process, the inverter INV<b>1</b> switches over, that is to say its second transistor T<b>11</b> is switched on, and its first transistor T<b>10</b> is switched off. The output OUT<b>1</b>, which is in consequence drawn to a low level, is also kept at a low level after completion of the initialization phase, with this low level corresponding approximately to the reference ground potential GND, ignoring the voltage drop across the switched-on second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The method of operation of this circuit arrangement will be explained in the following text with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, analyzing, in a corresponding manner to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a profile of the supply voltage Vdd in which the supply voltage starts from a nominal value Vn and falls to a level which is considerably lower than the nominal value Vn, before rising again to the nominal value Vn. The output voltage Vout<b>2</b>, which corresponds to the voltage across the first capacitance C<b>2</b>, after the initialization process is slightly below the supply voltage Vdd, with the difference corresponding to the voltage drop across the switched-on first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> during the initialization process. This voltage Vout<b>2</b> which is produced across the capacitance C<b>2</b> follows the falling supply voltage Vdd, with the voltage across the capacitance Vout<b>2</b> always being greater than the supply voltage Vdd by a voltage difference ΔV<b>1</b>. This voltage difference ΔV<b>1</b> corresponds to the forward voltage of the diode D<b>2</b>, which is used as the rectifier element. The output voltage Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> is slightly above the reference ground potential GND after completion of the initialization phase, with the voltage difference resulting from the voltage drop across the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b> during the initialization phase.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In order to assist understanding of the rest of the profile of the output voltage Vout<b>1</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the equivalent circuit of the circuit arrangement illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, for values of the supply voltage Vdd which are below the threshold voltage of the transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>11</b>, T<b>20</b>, T<b>21</b> in the CMOS inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>. Normal values for these threshold voltages are between 0.6 V and 0.8 V. The transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>11</b>, T<b>20</b>, T<b>21</b> no longer operate at supply voltages Vdd below this minimum value, and only the gate/source capacitances in the circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> are still effective. The gate/source capacitances C<b>20</b>, C<b>21</b> of the first and second transistors T<b>20</b>, T<b>21</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> in this case form a capacitive voltage divider between the supply potential connection A<b>21</b> and the reference ground potential connection A<b>22</b>. The gate/source capacitances C<b>10</b>, C<b>11</b> of the first and second transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b> form a further capacitive voltage divider between the supply potential connection A<b>11</b> and the reference ground potential connection A<b>12</b>, with the center tap of this capacitive voltage divider being connected via the diode D<b>2</b> to the supply potential connection Vdd, and with the first capacitance C<b>1</b> being connected in parallel with the gate/source capacitance C<b>11</b> of the transistor T<b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">When the output voltage Vdd falls in the illustrated circuit arrangement, the second capacitance C<b>2</b> is thus discharged via the diode D<b>2</b> and the transistor T<b>20</b>, which is initially still switched on. During this process, when the supply potential Vdd reaches values which are in the region of the threshold voltage of this transistor T<b>20</b>, the transistor T<b>20</b> is thus switched off, and further discharging of the capacitor C<b>2</b> takes place exclusively via the diode D<b>2</b>. Once the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> has been switched off, its gate/source capacitance C<b>20</b> still remains charged to a voltage which corresponds to the threshold voltage of this transistor T<b>20</b>. This charge in the gate/source capacitance C<b>20</b> of this transistor T<b>20</b> and the gate/source capacitance C<b>21</b> (which is connected in series with this gate/source capacitance C<b>20</b>) of the second transistor T<b>21</b> in the inverter INV<b>2</b> ensure that the output voltage Vout<b>1</b> is always lower than the supply voltage Vdd by the value of the threshold voltage as the supply voltage Vdd falls further, so that the output voltage Vout<b>1</b> can also assume negative values with respect to the reference ground potential GND. ΔV<b>2</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> denotes the voltage across the gate/source capacitance C<b>20</b> of the first transistor T<b>20</b> after this transistor has switched off.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">When the supply voltage Vdd rises again over the further course of time, it once again reaches values above the threshold voltage of the transistors which, by way of example is about 0.8 V, so that the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, whose gate connection is still at the reference ground potential, starts to conduct again, in order in consequence once again to charge the gate/source capacitance of the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b>, and the first capacitance C<b>2</b> which is connected in parallel with it. However, if the supply voltage Vdd rises more quickly than the charging of the parallel circuit comprising the gate/source capacitance C<b>11</b> of the transistor T<b>11</b> and the first capacitance C<b>2</b>, and the voltage difference between the supply voltage Vdd and the voltage Vout<b>2</b> across the parallel circuit formed by the capacitances C<b>11</b>, C<b>2</b> reaches the value of the threshold voltage of the first transistor T<b>10</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b>, then this transistor T<b>10</b> is switched on, and draws the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> in the direction of the supply potential Vdd, thus regulating the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> down in order to prevent further charging of the parallel circuit formed by the two capacitances C<b>11</b>, C<b>2</b>. At the same time, the second transistor T<b>21</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> is driven in the upward direction, in order to discharge the gate/source capacitance C<b>11</b> of the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b> and the first capacitance C<b>2</b>. This second transistor T<b>11</b> finally switches off, so that the output voltage Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> permanently assumes a high level, with the output voltage Vout<b>2</b> from the second inverter INV<b>2</b> also permanently assuming a low level whilst the first capacitance C<b>2</b> and the gate/source capacitance C<b>11</b> of the transistor T<b>11</b> have been discharged completely.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">A second capacitance C<b>1</b> is preferably connected in parallel with the load path of the first transistor T<b>10</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b>, and thus in parallel with the gate/source capacitance C<b>20</b> of the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, reduces the rate of rise of the gate/source voltage of the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, and thus ensures that this transistor starts to conduct only slowly as the supply voltage Vdd rises, so that the capacitance C<b>2</b> is charged more slowly after the supply voltage Vdd rises again, in order to ensure that the first inverter INV<b>1</b> switches over reliably.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">In order to produce the circuit arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the transistors T<b>10</b>-T<b>21</b> in the CMOS inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> may be designed to be identical, that is to say to have the same transistor surface areas (equal to W×L) and to each have the same width-to-length ratios (W/L ratios). In this embodiment, additional capacitances in the form of capacitors may be provided in order to produce the first capacitance C<b>1</b> and, if required, the further capacitance C<b>1</b>, with these capacitors being connected as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">As explained, the first capacitance C<b>2</b> is connected in parallel with the gate/source capacitance C<b>11</b> of the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b>, and the second capacitance C<b>1</b> is connected in parallel with the gate/source capacitance C<b>20</b> of the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b>. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, it is therefore also necessary to choose the first capacitance C<b>2</b> such that it is an inherent component of the gate/source capacitance of the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b>. The circuit arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> can thus also be produced by using as the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b> a transistor T<b>11</b>′ whose gate/source capacitance C<b>11</b>′ is greater than the gate/source capacitances C<b>10</b>, C<b>20</b>, C<b>21</b> of the other transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>20</b>, T<b>21</b>. This can be achieved by the transistor T<b>11</b>′ having a larger transistor surface area than the other transistors, in which case the W/L ratio of this transistor may correspond to the W/L ratio of the other transistors.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">In a corresponding manner, the further capacitance C<b>1</b>, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, may be an inherent component of a transistor T<b>20</b>′ which is used as the first transistor in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> and whose transistor surface area is larger than that of the transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>21</b>. The transistor surface area of this transistor T<b>20</b> corresponds, for example, to the transistor surface area of the transistor T<b>11</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The significant factor for the operation of the circuit arrangement illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is that the outputs OUT<b>1</b>, OUT<b>2</b> of the inverters are connected capacitively asymmetrically.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">This asymmetry may also be achieved, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, by providing a larger capacitance between the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> and the supply potential terminal A<b>11</b> than that between the output OUT<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> and the supply potential terminal A<b>12</b>. In the exemplary embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, only the capacitance C<b>1</b> between the output OUT<b>1</b> and the supply potential terminal Vdd is provided for this purpose, which ensures, as the supply voltage Vdd rises again, that the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> starts to conduct only slowly. This capacitance C<b>1</b> may, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, be an inherent component of a transistor T<b>21</b>′ which is used as the first transistor in the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, while the other transistors T<b>10</b>, T<b>11</b>, T<b>21</b> are preferably each designed to be identical.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The reset cells explained so far, with the two cross-coupled inverters whose outputs are connected capacitively asymmetrically, reliable produce a reset signal whenever the fluctuations in the supply voltage Vdd take place comparatively quickly, as is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 5</figref>. The principle of operation is based on the idea of connecting a larger capacitance between the output of one inverter and one of the supply voltage terminals than that between the output of the other inverter and this supply voltage terminal.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The reset cells explained so far with cross-coupled inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> which have asymmetric output capacitances may reach their limits, however, when very slow changes occur in the supply voltage Vdd, in particular when the supply voltage Vdd has fallen to a low voltage level for a long time and then rises only very slowly.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows an exemplary embodiment of a reset cell which is suitable for detection of even profiles of the supply voltage Vdd such as these, in order to produce a suitable reset signal.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">This reset cell has a first and a second inverter INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>, which are cross-coupled by connecting the output OUT<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> to the input IN<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b>, and by connecting the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> to the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>. This reset cell can be initialized by means of a switch S, on the basis of an initialization signal INIT. This switch S is connected between the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, and a reference ground potential GND. This switch S is closed for initialization, thus resulting in an output signal Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> assuming a low level, and the output signal Vout<b>2</b> from the second inverter INV<b>2</b> assuming a high level. These level states are also maintained after completion of the initialization process, owing to the cross-coupling of the two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> are in the form of CMOS inverters, and each have a first transistor T<b>10</b>, T<b>20</b> and a second transistor T<b>11</b>, T<b>21</b>, which are each connected between first and second connecting terminals A<b>11</b>, A<b>12</b>, A<b>21</b>, A<b>22</b> and are driven jointly. The capacitors C<b>10</b>-C<b>21</b>, which are in each case shown between the gate connections and the source connections of these transistors T<b>20</b>-T<b>21</b> that are in the form of MOSFETs, respectively represent the gate/source capacitances of these transistors.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> in this reset cell are designed to have different transfer voltages. The transfer voltage of an inverter in this case refers to the value of a voltage which is applied to its input which results in the output voltage reaching 50% of its level range, that is to say the input voltage at which the inverter switches over. In the example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the inverter INV<b>1</b> has a higher transfer voltage than the second inverter INV<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">The transfer voltage of the first inverter INV<b>1</b>, which is higher than that of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> is achieved by connecting a diode D<b>11</b> in series with the second transistor T<b>11</b> between the output terminal OUT<b>1</b> and the reference ground potential terminal A<b>12</b>. In particular, this diode D<b>11</b> may be in the form of a MOSFET which is connected as a diode, as is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref><i>b</i>. The transfer voltage of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> is greater than the transfer voltage of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, since the threshold voltage of the second transistor T<b>11</b> plus the forward voltage of the diode D<b>11</b> must be present at the input IN<b>1</b> of this inverter before the second transistor T<b>11</b> starts to conduct.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The method of operation of the reset cell illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> will be explained in the following text with reference to the time profile of the supply voltage Vdd in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. This is based on the assumption that the supply voltage Vdd has fallen to a value which is below the threshold voltage of the transistors in the reset cell, and that the supply voltage Vdd has already been at this potential for a long time, so that the potentials at the inputs IN<b>1</b>, IN<b>2</b> and the outputs OUT<b>1</b>, OUT<b>2</b> of the inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> have fallen to this low supply voltage value.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the supply voltage Vdd starts to rise slowly at a time t<b>0</b>. As soon as the supply voltage Vdd has risen to a value Vth<b>10</b> at which the voltage between the source connection of the first transistor T<b>10</b> in the inverter INV<b>1</b> and the input IN<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> corresponds to the threshold voltage of this first transistor T<b>10</b>, this transistor T<b>10</b> starts to conduct, and the output voltage Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> starts to follow the supply voltage Vdd, with the output voltage Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> always remaining below the supply voltage Vdd by the value of the threshold voltage of the first transistor T<b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">The first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> is switched on in a corresponding manner to the first transistor T<b>10</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b>. In this case, the voltage at the two outputs OUT<b>1</b>, OUT<b>2</b> rises, and the voltage at the inputs of the respective other inverter INV<b>2</b>, INV<b>1</b> thus in each case initially rises in the same way. The diode D<b>11</b> which is connected in series with the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b> results in this second transistor T<b>11</b> not starting to conduct until the voltages at its input IN<b>1</b> are higher than those of the second transistor T<b>21</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b>. The switched-on second transistor T<b>21</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> prevents the potential at the input IN<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> from rising, so that the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b> remains switched off, and the output voltage Vout<b>1</b> from this first inverter INV<b>1</b> follows the supply voltage Vdd in the manner explained above.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">At the end of the rise of the supply voltage Vdd, there is therefore a voltage level at the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> which corresponds to the supply voltage Vdd, and which is thus complementary to the voltage level after the initialization process, which corresponded to the reference ground potential GND. The output signal Vout<b>1</b> from the first inverter INV<b>1</b> in this reset cell can thus be used directly as a reset signal. This output signal Vout<b>1</b> assumes a low level after the initialization process and during normal operation, when no fluctuations occur in the supply voltage Vdd, and rises to a high level after a long-term drop in the supply voltage Vdd and a slow rise in the supply voltage Vdd.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">One significant factor for the operation of the reset cell illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is for the two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> to have different transfer voltages, particularly for the first inverter INV<b>1</b> to have a higher transfer voltage than the second inverter. As explained, this can be achieved by one of the two inverters, the second inverter INV<b>2</b> in the situation being explained, being a symmetrical CMOS inverter, while the transfer voltage of the other of the two inverters, in the illustrated case the first inverter INV<b>1</b>, is increased in comparison to the transfer voltage of a symmetrical CMOS inverter by the insertion of an additional diode D<b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">The reliability of the reset cell illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> for identification of a drop in the supply voltage Vdd can be improved by reducing the transfer voltage of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> in comparison to the transfer voltage of a symmetrical CMOS inverter. This can be achieved by connecting a further diode D<b>20</b> in series with the first transistor C<b>20</b> between the positive supply potential Vdd and the output OUT<b>2</b>, which, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref><i>c</i>, may, for example, be in the form of a p-conductor MOSFET with a low threshold voltage (low threshold MOSFET), which is connected as a diode. The threshold voltage of this transistor that is in the form of a diode is in this case lower than the threshold voltage of the CMOS transistors which are required to produce the inverters. Normal values for the threshold voltage of low threshold transistors such as these are in the region of about 0.4 V. The additional diode D<b>20</b> results in the first transistor T<b>20</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> not starting to conduct until the supply voltages are higher than those on the first transistor T<b>10</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b>, so that the potential at the input IN<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> is always lower than the potential at the input IN<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>, thus increasing the effect explained above, on the basis of which the second transistor T<b>21</b> in the second inverter INV<b>2</b> starts to conduct before the second transistor T<b>11</b> in the first inverter INV<b>1</b> when the supply voltage rises.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">As already explained, the transfer voltage of a CMOS inverter can be varied in comparison to the transfer voltage of a symmetrical CMOS inverter by the insertion of additional diodes. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>a </i>once again shows a CMOS inverter such as this having a first and a second transistor T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b>, which are driven jointly via an input voltage Vin, and which produces an output voltage Vout. The two transistors T<b>1</b>, T<b>2</b> are symmetrical, that is to say they have the same width-to-length ratios (W<b>1</b>/L<b>1</b>=W<b>2</b>/L<b>2</b>). The transfer voltage of this inverter as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>a </i>is increased above the transfer voltage of a symmetrical CMOS inverter by the insertion of an additional diode D<b>2</b> in series with the second transistor T<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">The dashed lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>c </i>show the transfer characteristic of a symmetrical CMOS inverter. The transfer characteristic of the inverter shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>a </i>is shifted towards higher input voltage values Vin in comparison to this transfer characteristic.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>b</i>, it is also possible to produce an inverter with a higher transfer voltage by varying the width-to-length ratio of the two CMOS inverters. A higher transfer voltage than that of a symmetrical CMOS inverter can be achieved by the width-to-length ratio of the p-conductive transistor T<b>1</b> being greater than the width-to-length ratio of the n-conductive transistor T<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">As already explained and as illustrated once again in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>d</i>, a CMOS inverter whose transfer voltage is lower than that of a symmetrical CMOS inverter can be produced by connecting a diode D<b>1</b> in series with the p-conductive transistor T<b>1</b> between the supply potential Vdd and the output OUT. The transfer characteristic of an inverter such as this is likewise illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>c</i>. In addition to the provision of an additional diode D<b>1</b>, a CMOS inverter with a lower transfer voltage can also be achieved, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>e</i>, by the width-to-length ratio of the p-conductive transistor T<b>1</b> being lower than the width-to-length ratio of the n-conductive transistor T<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">The width-to-length ratio of an MOS transistor governs, in a manner which has been known for a long time, the ratio between the input voltage of this transistor and its load current, with the load current rising, for the same input voltage, as the width-to-length ratio increases. This results in the transfer voltage shifts which have been explained when different width-to-length ratios are chosen for the transistors in a CMOS inverter.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">The already explained concepts for production of reset cells, specifically on the one hand the use of cross-coupled inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> with capacitively asymmetric output capacitances, and on the other hand the use of inverters with different transfer voltages, are advantageously combined with one another, as is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows a reset cell with a first and a second inverter INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> with a greater capacitance than that between the output OUT<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> and the reference ground potential GND being provided between the output OUT<b>2</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> and the reference ground potential GND by the addition of a capacitor C<b>2</b>. Furthermore, the two inverters INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> in the exemplary embodiments are chosen such that the first inverter INV<b>1</b> has a higher transfer voltage than the second inverter INV<b>2</b>. The first inverter INV<b>1</b> is in this case designed to correspond to the first inverter INV<b>1</b> in the reset cell shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, or in a corresponding manner to the inverter in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>a</i>. This inverter INV<b>1</b> may, of course, also be replaced by an inverter corresponding to that in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>b</i>. The second inverter INV<b>2</b> is a symmetrical CMOS inverter, which may optionally also be formed in a corresponding manner to the inverter shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>d</i>, or in a corresponding manner to the inverter shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>e</i>. Alternatively, it is possible for the second inverter INV<b>2</b> to be in the form of an inverter as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref><i>d </i>or <b>10</b><i>e</i>, and for the first inverter INV<b>1</b> to be a symmetrical CMOS inverter.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">This reset cell as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is reset in a corresponding manner to the reset cells which have been explained in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 8</figref>, by connecting the input IN<b>1</b> of the second inverter INV<b>2</b> to the reference ground potential by means of a switch S. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, the switch S is in the form of an n-conductive MOSFET, which is driven by the initialization signal INIT. For symmetry reasons, an MOS transistor D<b>3</b>, which is connected as a switched-off transistor, is connected between the input IN<b>1</b> of the first inverter INV<b>1</b> and the reference ground potential.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">This reset cell shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> operates in the same way as the reset cell shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> when rapid fluctuations occur, particularly when the supply voltage Vdd falls rapidly, and operates in a corresponding manner to the reset cell shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> when slow changes occur in the supply voltage Vdd.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">A number of reset cells with different dimensions are advantageously used for detection of a time profile of the supply voltage Vdd at whose end it is necessary to reset circuit components which are connected to this supply voltage Vdd.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows an arrangement with four reset cells RS<b>1</b>, RS<b>2</b>, RS<b>3</b>, RS<b>4</b> which each have different dimensions.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">In principle, the design of each of these reset cells corresponds to the design of the reset cell illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In order to assist understanding, the individual components of these reset cells RS<b>1</b>-RS<b>4</b> are provided with the same reference symbols and differ only by the letter “n”, with “n” indicating the order of one of the reset cells RS<b>1</b>-RS<b>4</b>, which are numbered successively from 1 to 4.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">Each reset cell RSn has a first inverter INV<b>1</b>_n and a second inverter INV<b>2</b>_n, which are cross-coupled. A first capacitance C<b>2</b>_n is connected between the output of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>_n and the reference ground potential, and is also connected to the supply potential Vdd via a diode D<b>2</b>_n. Additional capacitors C<b>1</b>_n can optionally be connected between the outputs of the first inverter INV<b>1</b>_n and the supply potential Vdd in order to increase the capacitive asymmetry of the outputs of the inverters INV<b>1</b>_n, INV<b>2</b>_n. Each reset cell RSn has a switching element S_n via which the reset cell RSn can be initialized on the basis of an initialization signal INIT. The switching element S_n is in each case connected between the output of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>_n and the reference ground potential GND, so that a lower voltage level is in each case produced at the output of the first inverter INV<b>1</b>_n after the initialization process, corresponding essentially to the reference ground potential GND, and a high voltage level is produced at the output of the second inverter INV<b>2</b>_n, corresponding essentially to the supply potential Vdd.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">The first and second reset cells RS<b>1</b>, RS<b>2</b> therefore have different dimensions such that, in the case of the reset cell RS<b>1</b>, the second inverter INV<b>2</b>_<b>1</b> has a higher transfer voltage than the first inverter INV<b>1</b>_<b>1</b>, while in the case of the second reset cell RS<b>1</b>, the second inverter INV<b>2</b>_<b>2</b> has a lower transfer voltage than the first inverter INV<b>1</b>_<b>2</b>. Reference should be made to the statements made above, in particular to the statements relating to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, for the production of inverters such as these with a different transfer voltage in a reset cell.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">The different dimensions of the two reset cells RS<b>1</b>, RS<b>2</b> take account of the fact that fluctuations in the supply voltage Vdd represent disturbance situations, whose occurrence and time profile cannot be predicted. Depending on the respective dimensions, individual reset cells may be differently well suited for the identification of individual disturbance situations.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">In the case of the arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, the output voltages Vout<b>1</b>_<b>1</b>, Vout<b>1</b>_<b>2</b> of the first inverters INV<b>1</b>_<b>1</b>, INV<b>1</b>_<b>2</b> are processed further in a logic circuit <b>41</b>, <b>42</b>, <b>43</b>. In the example, this logic circuit is an OR gate <b>41</b>, to which the output signals Vout<b>1</b>_<b>1</b>, Vout<b>1</b>_<b>2</b> from the two reset cells RS<b>1</b>, RS<b>2</b> are supplied. The output signal S<b>41</b> from this OR gate <b>41</b> is supplied to a further OR gate <b>43</b>, at whose output a reset signal RS is produced. In this case, in order to produce a high level for this reset signal S<b>43</b>, it is sufficient for only one of the two output signals Vout<b>1</b>_<b>1</b>, Vout<b>1</b>_<b>2</b> from the two reset cells RS<b>1</b>, RS<b>2</b> to assume a high level. After the initialization process, these output signals are initially at a low level and assume a high level only when the supply voltage Vdd has fallen.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">The design of the third reset cell RS<b>3</b> corresponds, by way of example, to the design of the first reset cell RS<b>1</b>, so that the first inverter INV<b>1</b>_<b>3</b> in this reset cell RS<b>3</b> likewise has a higher transfer voltage than the second inverter INV<b>2</b>_<b>3</b> in this reset cell RS<b>3</b>. Furthermore, the design of the fourth reset cell RS<b>4</b> corresponds to the design of the second reset cell RS<b>2</b>, whose first inverter INV<b>1</b>_<b>4</b> thus has a lower transfer voltage than its second inverter INV<b>2</b>_<b>4</b>. However, the output signal Vout<b>2</b>_<b>3</b>, Vout<b>2</b>_<b>4</b> from the second inverters INV<b>2</b>_<b>3</b>, INV<b>2</b>_<b>4</b>, which are at a high level after resetting, are evaluated by these third and fourth reset cells RS<b>3</b>, RS<b>4</b>. These output signals are supplied to an NAND gate <b>42</b>, whose output signal S<b>42</b> is supplied to the already explained OR gate <b>43</b>. A high level is produced at the output of this NAND gate <b>42</b> only in order to likewise set the reset signal S<b>43</b> to a high level when the output signal Vout<b>2</b>_<b>3</b>, Vout<b>2</b>_<b>4</b> from one of these reset cells RS<b>3</b>, RS<b>4</b> assumes a low level.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">LIST OF REFERENCE SYMBOLS</heading>
<p id="p-0094" num="0000">
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0093">Vdd Supply voltage, supply potential</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0002" num="0094">GND Reference ground potential</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0003" num="0095">INV<b>1</b>, INV<b>2</b> Inverter</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0004" num="0096">IN<b>1</b>, IN<b>2</b> Inputs</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0005" num="0097">OUT<b>1</b>, OUT<b>2</b> Outputs</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0006" num="0098">VOUT<b>1</b>, VOUT<b>2</b> output voltages, output signals</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0007" num="0099">D<b>2</b> Diode</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0008" num="0100">C<b>2</b> Capacitor</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0009" num="0101">RS Reset signal</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0010" num="0102">S Switch</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0011" num="0103">INIT Initialization signal</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0012" num="0104">T<b>10</b>, T<b>20</b> p-channel transistors</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0013" num="0105">T<b>11</b>, T<b>21</b> n-channel transistors</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0014" num="0106">C<b>10</b>, C<b>20</b> Gate/source capacitances</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0015" num="0107">C<b>11</b>, C<b>21</b> Gate/source capacitances</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0016" num="0108">C<b>1</b> Capacitor</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0017" num="0109">D<b>11</b>, D<b>20</b> Diodes</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0018" num="0110">T<b>1</b> p-conductive transistor</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0019" num="0111">T<b>2</b> n-conductive transistor</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0020" num="0112">D<b>1</b>, D<b>2</b> Diodes</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0021" num="0113">Vin Input voltage</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0022" num="0114">Vout Output voltage</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0023" num="0115">INV<b>1</b>_n, INV<b>2</b>_n Inverters</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0024" num="0116">D<b>2</b>_n Diodes</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0025" num="0117">C<b>2</b>_n Capacitors</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0026" num="0118">C<b>1</b>_n Capacitors</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0027" num="0119">S_<b>1</b> Switching elements</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0028" num="0120">D<b>3</b>_<b>1</b> Diodes</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0029" num="0121">Vout<b>1</b>_<b>1</b>, Vout<b>1</b>_<b>2</b> Output signals</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0030" num="0122">Vout<b>2</b>_<b>3</b>, Vout<b>2</b>_<b>4</b> Output signals</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0031" num="0123">RS<b>1</b>-RS<b>4</b> Reset cells</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0032" num="0124"><b>41</b>, <b>43</b> OR gates</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0033" num="0125"><b>42</b> NAND gates</li>
</ul>
</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A circuit arrangement configured to produce a reset signal after a supply voltage has fallen and risen again comprising:
<claim-text>a first inverter having a first inverter input, a first inverter output, and a first and a second supply voltage connection, the first inverter also having a first transfer voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second inverter having a second inverter input, a second inverter output, and a first and a second supply voltage connection, wherein the first inverter output is operably coupled to the second inverter input and the second inverter output is operably coupled to the first inverter input, the second inverter having a second transfer voltage, the first and the second transfer voltages having different values;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an initialization circuit operably connected to the first inverter input or the second inverter input; a first rectifier element operably connected between the second inverter output and the first supply voltage connection of the first or second inverter;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first capacitance provided between the second inverter output and the second supply voltage connection of the first or second inverter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second capacitance provided between the first inverter output and the second supply voltage connection of the first or second inverter, wherein the first capacitance is larger than the second capacitance.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first and second inverters each include a first and a second transistor, the second transistor being complementary to the first transistor;
<claim-text>wherein each of the first and second transistors of the first and second inverters comprises a load path and a drive connection;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each load path is connected between the first and second supply voltage connection of the first or second inverter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each drive connection is connected to the first inverter input or the second inverter input.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the first capacitance comprises a capacitor operably connected to the second inverter output.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the first capacitance is formed by a drive capacitance of one of the transistors in the first inverter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the first and second transistors in at least one of the inverters have different width-to-length ratios.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein at least one further rectifier element is operably connected in series with the load paths of the first and second transistors in at least one of the inverters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the initialization circuit comprises a switch operably connected between the second inverter input and the second supply voltage connection of the first or second inverter, the switch being controlled by an initialization signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the switch comprises a transistor, and wherein a further transistor is operably connected as a diode between the first inverter input and the second supply voltage connection of the first or second inverter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A circuit arrangement for production of a reset signal after a supply voltage has fallen and risen again, the circuit arrangement comprising:
<claim-text>a first inverter having a first inverter input, a first inverter output, a first transfer voltage, and first and second supply voltage connections;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second inverter having a second inverter input, a second inverter output, a second transfer voltage, and first and second supply voltage connections;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first inverter output is operably coupled to the second inverter input and the second inverter output is operably coupled to the first inverter input, and wherein the first and second transfer voltages have different values; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first capacitance provided between the second inverter output and the second supply voltage connection of the first or second inverter;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second capacitance provided between the first inverter output and the second supply voltage connection of the first or second inverter, the first capacitance being larger than the second capacitance;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first and second inverters each include a first and a second transistor, the second transistor being complementary to the first transistor, and each transistor comprising a load path and a drive connection, the load paths of the first and second transistors of each inverter are connected in series between the first and second supply voltage connections of each inverter; and the drive connections of the first and second transistors of each inverter are jointly connected to the input of the respective inverter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first and second transistors in at least one of the inverters have different width-to-length ratios to provide different transfer voltages for the first and the second inverters.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein at least one rectifier element is connected in series with the load paths of the first and second transistors in at least one inverter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one rectifier element comprises a transistor having a low threshold voltage, the transistor being connected as a diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The circuit arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the threshold voltage of the transistor is approximately 0.4 V.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method of producing a reset signal after a supply voltage has fallen and risen again, the method comprising:
<claim-text>providing the supply voltage between a first supply voltage terminal and a second supply voltage terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a first circuit operably connected to the supply voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a reset circuit comprising: a first inverter including an first inverter input and a first inverter output, the first inverter connected between the first supply voltage terminal and the second supply voltage terminal, wherein the first inverter has a first transfer voltage; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second inverter including a second inverter input and a second inverter output, the second inverter connected between the first supply voltage terminal and the second supply voltage terminal, wherein the second inverter has a second transfer voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first inverter output is operably coupled to the second inverter input and the second inverter output is operably coupled to the first inverter input, and wherein the first and second transfer voltages have different values;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a first capacitance between the second inverter output and the second supply voltage terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a second capacitance between the first inverter output and the second supply voltage terminal, wherein the first capacitance is larger than the second capacitance;</claim-text>
<claim-text>operably connecting the reset circuit to the first circuit; and using the reset circuit to generate a reset signal for the first circuit when the supply voltage has fallen and risen again.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>providing each inverter with a first and second transistor, the second transistor being complementary to the first transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each transistor comprises a load path and a drive connection;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the load paths of the first and second transistors of each inverter are connected in series between the first and second supply voltage terminals; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the drive connections of the first and second transistor of each inverter are jointly connected to the input of the respective inverter.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, further comprising: providing the first and second transistors in at least one of the inverters with different width-to-length ratios to provide different transfer voltages for the inverters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, further comprising: operably connecting at least one rectifier element in series with the load paths of the first and second transistors in at least one inverter.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
