<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296563-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296563</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11483537</doc-number>
<date>20060711</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-202163</doc-number>
<date>20050711</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>10</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>M</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>07</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>M</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>12356817</main-classification>
<further-classification>123572</further-classification>
<further-classification>12318424</further-classification>
<further-classification>12318426</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Internal combustion engine intake device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6272851</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Mori et al.</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 60278</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6805087</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Yakabe et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>12318425</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7089921</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Matsuoka et al.</name>
<date>20060800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>123572</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-140713</doc-number>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>12318424</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>12318426</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123572</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>12356817</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>12356811</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070006856</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070111</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yakabe</last-name>
<first-name>Yoshinori</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sasaki</last-name>
<first-name>Junya</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Global IP Counselors, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nissan Motor Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Cronin</last-name>
<first-name>Stephen K.</first-name>
<department>3747</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Castro</last-name>
<first-name>Arnold</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An internal combustion engine intake device is configured to suppress the occurrence of freezing in a portion thereof where blow-by gas or another gas is introduced into an intake passage. The intake device basically has a throttle chamber, an intake air collector, an air induction pipe, a partitioning part, a gas introducing pipe and a volume chamber. The air induction pipe is provided between the throttle valve and the intake air collector. The partitioning part divides the space inside the air induction pipe into first and second air induction spaces. The gas introducing pipe introduces the blow-by gas into the first and second air induction spaces directly. The blow-by gas contains moisture and has a higher temperature than the fresh air in the first and second air induction spaces. The volume chamber is arranged between the gas introducing pipe and the first and second air induction spaces.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="131.32mm" wi="156.21mm" file="US07296563-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="182.80mm" wi="159.94mm" file="US07296563-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="214.29mm" wi="188.04mm" file="US07296563-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="215.90mm" wi="122.34mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296563-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="196.17mm" wi="162.48mm" file="US07296563-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="156.89mm" wi="160.19mm" file="US07296563-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="171.28mm" wi="167.05mm" file="US07296563-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="159.85mm" wi="156.89mm" file="US07296563-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority under 35 U.S.C. § 119 to Japanese Patent Application No. 2005-202163. The entire disclosure of Japanese Patent Application No. 2005-202163 is hereby incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to an intake device for an internal combustion engine.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Background Information</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the past, there have been several proposals (e.g., Japanese Laid-Open Patent Publication No. 2001-140713 (pages 1 to 3, FIGS. 1 to 7)) for an intake device that introduces blow-by gas or another gas into an intake passage.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In view of the above, it will be apparent to those skilled in the art from this disclosure that there exists a need for an improved internal combustion engine intake device. This invention addresses this need in the art as well as other needs, which will become apparent to those skilled in the art from this disclosure.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It has been discovered that in some of these conventional intake devices, the portion of the intake passage between the throttle valve and the intake air collector is divided into a first air induction space and a second air induction space by a partitioning plate. In such intake devices, blow-by gas or another gas is sometimes introduced into the first air induction space and the second air induction space either from the side of the partitioning plate or from above and below the partitioning plate. Freezing may occur at the portion where the gas is introduced into the intake passage.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">One object of the present invention is to provide an intake device that can suppress the occurrence of freezing in the portion thereof where blow-by gas or another gas is introduced into the intake passage.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In order to achieve the above mentioned object and other objects of the present invention, an internal combustion engine intake device is provided that basically comprises a regulating chamber, an intake air collector, an air induction pipe, a partitioning part, a gas introducing pipe and a volume chamber. The regulating chamber has a regulating valve configured and arranged to regulate a quantity of fresh air flowing therethrough. The intake air collector fluidly communicates with the regulating chamber at a position downstream of the regulating valve. The air induction pipe is arranged between the regulating valve and the intake air collector to communicate the fresh air from the regulating chamber to the intake air collector. The air induction pipe includes a partitioning part arranged and configured to divide a space inside the air induction pipe into a first air induction space and a second air induction space. The gas introducing pipe is configured and arranged to introduce a first gas into the first and second air induction spaces. The first gas is different from the fresh air. The volume chamber is arranged between the gas introducing pipe and the first and second air induction spaces such that the first gas passes from the gas introducing pipe through the volume chamber and into the first and second air induction spaces.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">These and other objects, features, aspects and advantages of the present invention will become apparent to those skilled in the art from the following detailed description, which, taken in conjunction with the annexed drawings, discloses a preferred embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Referring now to the attached drawings which form a part of this original disclosure:</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic view of an internal combustion engine intake device in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top plan view of the internal combustion engine intake device illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevational view of the internal combustion engine intake device taken from the direction of arrows III of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross sectional view of the internal combustion engine intake device in accordance with the present invention as seen along a section line IV-IV of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross sectional view of the internal combustion engine intake device in accordance with the present invention as seen along a section line V-V of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross sectional view of the internal combustion engine intake device in accordance with the present invention as seen along a section line VI-VI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross sectional view of the internal combustion engine intake device in accordance with the present invention as seen along a section line VII-VII of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Selected embodiments of the present invention will now be explained with reference to the drawings. It will be apparent to those skilled in the art from this disclosure that the following descriptions of the embodiments of the present invention are provided for illustration only and not for the purpose of limiting the invention as defined by the appended claims and their equivalents.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">Overview of Structure of Internal Combustion Engine</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Referring initially to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an internal combustion engine <b>1</b> is schematically illustrated in accordance with a first embodiment of the present invention. The internal combustion engine <b>1</b> is, for example, a conventional V6 engine configured to execute air intake that utilizes resonance. The engine <b>1</b> is preferably mounted transversely inside an engine compartment at the front of a vehicle (i.e., a crankshaft (not shown) of the engine <b>1</b> is oriented to extend in a transverse direction of the vehicle). In the conventional V6 engine, the six cylinders are divided into a right-hand bank located on the right-hand side and a left-hand bank located on the left-hand side when the engine <b>1</b> is viewed from the lengthwise direction. Each cylinder bank has the same number of cylinders.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The engine <b>1</b> includes six combustion chambers <b>63</b> (only one combustion chamber <b>63</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), an intake device <b>70</b>, an exhaust device <b>30</b>, six fuel injection valves <b>27</b> (only one fuel injection valve <b>27</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), and six spark plugs <b>29</b> (only one spark plug <b>29</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The combustion chamber <b>63</b> of each cylinder is defined by a cylinder head <b>20</b>, a cylinder block <b>10</b>, and a piston <b>3</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The cylinder head <b>20</b> has a plurality of intake ports <b>23</b> (only one intake port <b>23</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) for supplying fresh air to the combustion chambers <b>63</b> and a plurality of exhaust ports <b>24</b> (only one exhaust port <b>24</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) for discharging burned gas from the combustion chambers <b>63</b> as exhaust gas.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The intake device <b>70</b> is configured and arranged to guide fresh air and fuel to each of the combustion chambers <b>63</b> through an intake passage <b>50</b>. A common intake device <b>70</b> serves all six of the cylinders. The intake device <b>70</b> includes a plurality of intake valves <b>21</b> (only one intake valve <b>21</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), the intake ports <b>23</b>, and a plurality of runners or intake branches <b>52</b> (only one intake branch <b>52</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). The intake branches <b>52</b> are positioned upstream of the intake ports <b>23</b>. The intake valves <b>21</b> are arranged at the downstream ends of the intake ports <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The exhaust device <b>30</b> is configured and arranged to discharge exhaust gas from the combustion chambers <b>63</b>. The exhaust device <b>30</b> is connected to all six cylinders. The exhaust device <b>30</b> includes a plurality of exhaust valves <b>22</b> (only one exhaust valve <b>22</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), the exhaust ports <b>24</b>, and a plurality of exhaust branches <b>31</b> (only one exhaust branch <b>31</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). The exhaust branches <b>31</b> are positioned downstream of the exhaust ports <b>24</b>. The exhaust valves <b>22</b> are arranged at the upstream ends of the exhaust ports <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">An intake camshaft <b>21</b><i>b </i>has a plurality of intake cams <b>21</b><i>a </i>(only one intake cam <b>21</b><i>a </i>is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) fixed thereto. The intake cams <b>21</b><i>a </i>are arranged such that the intake cams <b>21</b><i>a </i>are positioned above the intake valves <b>21</b>. The intake camshaft <b>21</b><i>b </i>is arranged such that it rotates when the crankshaft of the engine <b>1</b> rotates. When the intake camshaft <b>21</b><i>b </i>rotates, the intake cams <b>21</b><i>a </i>cause the intake valves <b>21</b> to open and close. Likewise, an exhaust camshaft <b>22</b><i>b </i>having a plurality of exhaust cams <b>22</b><i>a </i>(only one exhaust cam <b>22</b><i>a </i>is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) fixed thereto is arranged such that the exhaust cams <b>22</b><i>a </i>are positioned above the exhaust valves <b>22</b>. The exhaust camshaft <b>22</b><i>b </i>is arranged such that it rotates when the crankshaft of the engine <b>1</b> rotates. When the exhaust camshaft <b>22</b><i>b </i>rotates, the exhaust cams <b>22</b><i>a </i>cause the exhaust valves <b>22</b> to open and close.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">One fuel injection valve <b>27</b> is provided with respect to each cylinder and each fuel injection valve <b>27</b> serves to inject fuel (gasoline) into the respective intake port <b>23</b>. The tip end of the fuel injection valve <b>27</b> protrudes into the combustion chamber <b>63</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">One spark plug <b>29</b> is provided with respect to each cylinder. Each spark plug <b>29</b> is arranged to extend into the respective one of the combustion chambers <b>63</b> from a portion of the cylinder head <b>20</b> that is positioned above the approximate center of the combustion chamber <b>63</b>. The tip end portion <b>29</b><i>a </i>of the spark plug <b>29</b> protrudes into the combustion chamber <b>63</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Overview of Operation of Internal Combustion Engine</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In the internal combustion engine <b>1</b>, fresh air introduced into the intake branches <b>52</b> is guided to the intake ports <b>23</b> as a second air mixture (described later). Pressurized fuel supplied to the fuel injection valves <b>27</b> is injected into the fresh air guided into the intake ports <b>23</b>. As a result, a mixture of fresh air and fuel is formed in the intake ports <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In the intake stroke of any given cylinder, the intake valve <b>21</b> is opened by the intake cam <b>21</b><i>a </i>and the mixture of fresh air and fuel formed in the intake port <b>23</b> is introduced into the combustion chamber <b>63</b> from the intake port <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">During the compression stroke, the piston <b>3</b> rises and the mixture of fresh air and fuel inside the combustion chamber <b>63</b> is compressed. Then, at a prescribed timing, the tip end portion <b>29</b><i>a </i>of the spark plug <b>29</b> ignites the mixture of fresh air and fuel (air-fuel mixture) inside the combustion chamber <b>63</b>, thereby causing the air-fuel mixture to combust.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">During the power stroke, the combustion pressure generated by the combustion of the mixture of fresh air and fuel pushes the piston <b>3</b> downward.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">During the exhaust stroke, the exhaust cam <b>22</b><i>a </i>opens the exhaust valve <b>22</b> and burned gas remaining after combustion in the combustion chamber <b>63</b> is discharged as exhaust gas to the exhaust branch <b>31</b> through the exhaust port <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Accordingly, the engine <b>1</b> is configured to have the mixture of fresh air and fuel inducted into combustion chambers <b>63</b> from the intake device <b>70</b>. The mixture of fresh air and fuel is combusted inside the combustion chambers <b>63</b> and the combustion causes pistons <b>3</b> to move reciprocally inside cylinders. The reciprocal motion of the pistons <b>3</b> is converted into rotational motion of a crankshaft of the engine <b>1</b> by means of connecting rods (not shown).</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">Overview of Structure of Internal Combustion Engine Intake Device</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">A top plan view of the intake device <b>70</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevational view of the intake device <b>70</b> from the direction of the arrows III of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross sectional view of the intake device <b>70</b> taken along a section line IV-IV of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>4</b>, <b>5</b> and <b>6</b>, the intake device <b>70</b> basically includes an intake passage <b>50</b>, a throttle or regulating valve <b>91</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), the intake valves <b>21</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), a partitioning part <b>80</b>, a volume chamber <b>72</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>), a connector (connector part) <b>75</b>, and a gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>). The intake passage <b>50</b> is the passage through which fresh air flows until it is drawn into the combustion chamber <b>63</b>. The intake passage <b>50</b> basically includes a throttle or regulating chamber <b>54</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), an air induction pipe <b>53</b>, an intake air collector <b>51</b>, the intake branches <b>52</b>, and the intake ports <b>23</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). The partitioning part <b>80</b> comprises a first partitioning plate <b>81</b> and a second partitioning plate <b>82</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The throttle valve <b>91</b> is arranged in the throttle chamber <b>54</b>. The throttle valve <b>91</b> is configured and arranged such that the amount of fresh air flowing through the throttle chamber <b>54</b> can be changed by changing the opening degree of the throttle valve <b>91</b>. As a result, the throttle valve <b>91</b> is configured and arranged to adjust the quantity of fresh air taken into the combustion chambers <b>63</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The air induction pipe <b>53</b> is provided between the throttle chamber <b>54</b> and the intake air collector <b>51</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the air induction pipe <b>53</b> is curved in a substantially circular arc-like shape and serves as a communication passage between the throttle chamber <b>54</b> and the intake air collector <b>51</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the space inside the air induction pipe <b>53</b> is divided by the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> into a first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and a second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>such that the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>is disposed above the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> and the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>is disposed below the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> with respect to the vertical direction of the vehicle. The first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>is fluidly communicated with the right-hand cylinder bank and the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>is fluidly communicated with the left-hand cylinder bank. The first partitioning plate <b>81</b> is configured and arranged to extend from a position in a vicinity of the throttle valve <b>91</b> (i.e., a position near a flange <b>53</b><i>e </i>but slightly downstream from the flange <b>53</b><i>e</i>) to a position where the intake air collector <b>51</b> begins.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>, the volume chamber <b>72</b> is enclosed by a volume chamber wall and is arranged between the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) and the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b</i>. The volume chamber <b>72</b> is connected to the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> by the connector <b>75</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>). As a result, the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> can introduce blow-by gas (first gas) into the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>through the connector <b>75</b> and the volume chamber <b>72</b>. The blow-by gas is a gas that contains a higher moisture content and has a higher temperature than the fresh air in the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The volume chamber wall <b>71</b> is configured and arranged to project outward from the air induction pipe <b>53</b>. In this way, a volume chamber <b>72</b> enclosed by a volume chamber wall <b>71</b> can be obtained. By using the volume chamber wall <b>71</b> that projects outward from the air induction pipe <b>53</b>, a higher degree of freedom can be secured with respect to the layout of other members, e.g., a harness bracket mounting boss <b>79</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). Additionally, since the harness bracket mounting boss <b>79</b> is connected to the volume chamber wall <b>71</b>, the rigidity of the harness bracket mounting boss <b>79</b> can be increased with a comparatively simple structure that is relatively easy to fabricate.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the intake air collector <b>51</b> is enclosed by a collector wall <b>51</b><i>c</i>. The intake air collector <b>51</b> is arranged downstream of the throttle valve <b>91</b> and the air induction pipe <b>53</b>. The intake air collector <b>51</b> has the form of a generally rectangular box with the air induction pipe <b>53</b> being connected thereto in the vicinity of a central portion thereof. The space inside the intake air collector <b>51</b> is divided by the second partitioning plate <b>82</b> into a first collector space and a second collector space such that the first collector space is disposed above the second partitioning plate <b>82</b> and the second collector space is disposed below the second partitioning plate <b>82</b> with respect to the vertical direction of the vehicle. The first collector space is fluidly communicated with the right-hand cylinder bank and the second collector space is fluidly communicated with the left-hand cylinder bank.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The second partitioning plate <b>82</b> has an end portion <b>82</b><i>c </i>that is located close to the air induction pipe <b>53</b> and is joined to an end portion <b>81</b><i>c </i>of the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> that is located close to the intake air collector <b>51</b> in a smooth and uninterrupted manner as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Consequently, the first collector space communicates with the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>but does not communicate with the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b</i>. Similarly, the second collector space communicates with the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>but does not communicate with the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">As seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the intake branches <b>52</b> are enclosed by branch walls. The intake branches <b>52</b> are arranged between the intake air collector <b>51</b> and the cylinder head <b>20</b>. The intake branches <b>52</b> are connected to the opposite side of the intake air collector <b>51</b> as the air induction pipe <b>53</b>. There is one intake branch <b>52</b> provided with respect to the intake ports <b>23</b> of each of the left and right cylinder banks (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an example in which there are six cylinders). More specifically, the intake branches <b>52</b> include a first intake branch having a first branch pipe <b>52</b><i>a</i>, a second branch pipe <b>52</b><i>b</i>, a third branch pipe <b>52</b><i>c</i>, and a second intake branch includes a fourth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>d</i>, a fifth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>e</i>, and a sixth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>f</i>. The first branch pipe <b>52</b><i>a</i>, the second branch pipe <b>52</b><i>b</i>, and the third branch pipe <b>52</b><i>c </i>of the first intake branch serve the right-hand cylinder bank and are configured to extend from the first collector space to the respective intake ports <b>23</b> of the right-hand bank of cylinders. The fourth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>d</i>, the fifth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>e</i>, and the sixth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>f </i>of the second intake branch serve the left-hand cylinder bank and are configured to extend from the second collector space to the respective intake ports <b>23</b> of the left-hand bank of cylinders. One of the intake valves <b>21</b> is provided at the downstream end of each intake port <b>23</b> and serves to open and close communication between the intake port and the respective combustion chamber <b>63</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0009" level="1">Overview of Operation of Internal Combustion Engine Intake Device</heading>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The throttle valve <b>91</b> is opened to a prescribed opening degree based on a command from an ECU (not shown). The quantity of fresh air taken in is adjusted according to the opening degree of the throttle valve <b>91</b>. The fresh air passes through the throttle chamber <b>54</b> and into the air induction pipe <b>53</b>. The fresh air introduced into the air induction pipe <b>53</b> is divided into a portion that flows through the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>toward the intake air collector <b>51</b> and a portion that flows through the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>toward the intake air collector <b>51</b>. Consequently, the pulsations of the fresh air in the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>can be offset so as to be out of phase with the pulsations of the fresh air in the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b</i>, thereby enabling resonance to be utilized with respect to the intake of air.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Meanwhile, blow-by gas from the crankcase (not shown) is directed into the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b>. The blow-by gas passes from the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> through the connector <b>75</b> and into the volume chamber <b>72</b>. At the same time, fresh air is introduced into the volume chamber <b>72</b> from the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b</i>. Thus, a mixture of fresh air and blow-by gas (hereinafter called “first air mixture”) is formed in the volume chamber <b>72</b>. The first air mixture is introduced into the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>from the volume chamber <b>72</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a</i>, a mixture of fresh air and the first air mixture (hereinafter called “second air mixture”) is formed. The second air mixture in the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>is directly introduced into the first collector space, which in turn introduces the second air mixture into the intake ports <b>23</b> of the right-hand bank of cylinders via the first branch pipe <b>52</b><i>a</i>, the second branch pipe <b>52</b><i>b</i>, and the third branch pipe <b>52</b><i>c</i>. The second air mixture introduced into the intake ports <b>23</b> is directed into the combustion chambers <b>63</b> and combusted when the intake valves <b>21</b> open.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Similarly, in the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b</i>, the fresh air and the first air mixture mix together to form a second air mixture. The second air mixture in the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>is directly introduced into the second collector space, which in turn introduces the second air mixture into the intake ports <b>23</b> of the left-hand bank of cylinders via the fourth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>d</i>, the fifth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>e</i>, and the sixth branch pipe <b>52</b><i>f</i>. The second air mixture introduced into the intake ports <b>23</b> is directed into the combustion chambers <b>63</b> and combusted when the intake valves <b>21</b> open.</p>
<heading id="h-0010" level="1">Description of Volume Chamber</heading>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross sectional view of the intake device <b>70</b> taken along the section line V-V of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross sectional view of the intake device <b>70</b> taken along the section line VI-VI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross sectional view of the intake device <b>70</b> taken along the section line VII-VII of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The volume chamber <b>72</b> is generally shaped like a backwards letter L and is surrounded by the volume chamber wall <b>71</b>. The volume chamber <b>72</b> has a first space <b>72</b><i>a</i>, a second space <b>72</b><i>b</i>, and a third space <b>72</b><i>c</i>. The first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>extends away from the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> is arranged to be generally coplanar with respect to the first partitioning plate <b>81</b>. The second space <b>72</b><i>b </i>extends from a portion of the first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>that is far from the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> and follows along the direction of a side face of the first partitioning plate <b>81</b>. The third space <b>72</b><i>c </i>extends from a portion of the second space <b>72</b><i>b </i>that is far from the first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>and follows along a direction oriented diagonally away from the first partitioning plate <b>81</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">An opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>that enables communication between the first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b> and the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>of the air induction pipe <b>53</b> is provided in a portion of the volume chamber wall <b>71</b> that faces the first partitioning plate <b>81</b>. The opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>has a generally rectangular cross sectional shape and the cross sectional area thereof is larger than the cross sectional area of the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b>. More specifically, the cross sectional area of the first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b> and the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>have a width W<b>1</b> and a height H<b>1</b> with the width W<b>1</b> being at least 1.5 times larger (preferably at least 2 times larger) than the cross sectional area of the introducing pipe <b>78</b> which has a width W<b>4</b>. Also, the cross sectional area of the second space <b>72</b><i>b </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b> has a width W<b>2</b> and a height H<b>2</b> and the cross sectional area of the third space <b>72</b><i>c </i>having a width W<b>3</b> and a height H<b>3</b> with the widths W<b>2</b> and W<b>3</b> both being larger than the cross sectional area of the first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b> having the width W<b>1</b> and the height H<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Preferably, a notch <b>81</b><i>a </i>is provided in a portion of the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> near the opening <b>71</b><i>e</i>. The notch <b>81</b><i>a </i>ensures good communication of the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>with both the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b</i>. As seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> divides or bisects the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>so as to define a first communication surface area <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>1</b> and a second communication surface area <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>2</b> that are substantially equal. The first communication surface area <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>1</b> is the area of the portion <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>1</b> where the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>directly communicates with the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a</i>. The second communication surface area <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>2</b> is the area of the portion <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>2</b> where the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>directly communicates the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The first partitioning plate <b>81</b> is arranged such that it passes nearby the center CP of the area of the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>at an intermediate position along the length of the first partitioning plate <b>81</b>, which spans from the vicinity of the throttle valve <b>91</b> to the intake air collector <b>51</b>. As a result, the blow-by gas introduced into the volume chamber <b>72</b> is distributed substantially evenly to the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>through the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>at a middle region or area of the air induction pipe <b>53</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">A communication passage <b>71</b><i>d </i>is formed in a portion of the volume chamber wall <b>71</b> that is far from the opening <b>71</b><i>e</i>. The communication passage <b>71</b><i>d </i>communicates between the space <b>75</b><i>d </i>inside the connector <b>75</b> and the third space <b>72</b><i>c </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b>. The gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> is attached to the connector <b>75</b> such that the connector <b>75</b> is inserted into the space <b>78</b><i>d </i>inside the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b>. As a result, the space <b>78</b><i>d </i>inside the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> communicates with the space <b>75</b><i>d </i>inside the connector <b>75</b>. As a result, the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> can introduce blow-by gas into the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>through the connector <b>75</b> and the volume chamber <b>72</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">If the cross sectional area of the portion having the width W<b>1</b> and height H<b>1</b> is too large, the pulsations of the fresh air in the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and the pulsations of the fresh air in the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>will weaken. Therefore, it is preferable for the cross sectional area of the portion having the width W<b>1</b> and the height H<b>1</b> to be small enough that marked weakening of the pulsations of the fresh air does not occur (e.g., not larger than 2.5 times the cross sectional area of the portion having the width W<b>4</b>).</p>
<heading id="h-0011" level="1">Description of the Behavior of the Blow by Gas in the Volume Chamber</heading>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The blow-by gas introduced into the space <b>78</b><i>d </i>inside the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> passes through the space <b>75</b><i>d </i>inside the connector <b>75</b> and the communication passage <b>71</b><i>d </i>and flows into the third space <b>72</b><i>c </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b>. The blow-by gas introduced into the third space <b>72</b><i>c </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b> becomes distributed among the third space <b>72</b><i>c</i>, the second space <b>72</b><i>b</i>, and the first space <b>72</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Since the cross sectional area of the portion having the width W<b>1</b> is at least 1.5 times larger than the cross sectional area of the portion having the width W<b>4</b>, a portion of the fresh air in the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and a portion of the fresh air in the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>enter the first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b> through the notch <b>81</b><i>a </i>and the opening <b>71</b><i>e</i>. Since the fresh air from the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>enter the first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b> while pulsating out of phase with each other, the fresh air mixes rapidly with the blow-by gas in the first space <b>72</b><i>a</i>. Thus, a mixture (first air mixture) of fresh air and blow-by gas is formed in the first space <b>72</b><i>a</i>. Since the cross sectional area of the portion having the width W<b>2</b> and the cross sectional area of the portion having the width W<b>3</b> are larger than the cross sectional area of the portion having the width W<b>1</b>, the first air mixture readily diffuses from the first space <b>72</b><i>a </i>to the second space <b>72</b><i>b </i>and the third space <b>72</b><i>c</i>, further promoting the mixing of the fresh air and blow-by gas. As a result, a portion of the thermal energy of the blow-by gas is absorbed by the fresh air and the temperature of the blow-by gas decreases. In other words, the temperature difference between the blow-by gas and the fresh air in the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>decreases.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The first air mixture in the first space <b>72</b><i>a</i>, the second space <b>72</b><i>b</i>, and the third space <b>72</b><i>c </i>of the volume chamber <b>72</b> is introduced into the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>through the opening <b>71</b><i>e</i>. The first air mixture (which contains blow-by gas) is distributed substantially evenly to the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>because the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> is arranged such that it passes nearby the center CP of the area of the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>at an intermediate position along the length of the air induction pipe <b>53</b>, and because the first and second communication areas <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>1</b> and are substantially equal. Additionally, since a first air mixture comprising a mixture of fresh air and blow-by gas is distributed to the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>instead of blow-by gas alone, the ?blow-by gas is less likely to be distributed unevenly to the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">In the illustrated embodiment, the volume chamber <b>72</b> is arranged between the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> and the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b</i>. Since a portion of fresh air from the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and a portion of fresh air from the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>mix with the blow-by gas in the volume chamber <b>72</b>, the temperature difference between the blow-by gas and the fresh air in the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>is reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">As a result of reducing the temperature difference between the blow-by gas and the fresh air in the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b</i>, the occurrence of freezing at the portion of the intake device <b>70</b> where the blow-by gas is introduced into the intake passage <b>50</b> is suppressed.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">If the cross sectional area of the opening were small, high-temperature blow-by gas would be introduced into fresh air at the ambient temperature. Consequently, the freezing would tend to occur at the opening due to the temperature difference between the blow-by gas and the fresh air. Freezing at the opening would, in turn, tend to block the opening.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">In the present invention, the cross sectional area of the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>is larger than the cross sectional area of the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b>. More specifically, the cross sectional area of the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>is at least 1.5 times larger (preferably at least 2 times larger) than the cross sectional area of the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b>. Consequently, the portion of fresh air from the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and the portion of fresh air from the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>readily mix with the blow-by gas inside the volume chamber. As a result, the temperature difference between the blow-by gas and the fresh air in the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>is reduced and the occurrence of freezing at the portion of the intake device <b>70</b> where the blow-by gas is introduced into the intake passage <b>50</b> is suppressed.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Furthermore, even if freezing does occur at the opening <b>71</b><i>e</i>, the degree to which the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>is blocked will be reduced if the cross sectional area of the opening <b>71</b><i>e </i>is larger than the cross sectional area in which freezing occurs.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">In the illustrated embodiment, the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> is arranged and configured to extend from the vicinity of the throttle valve <b>91</b> to the intake air collector <b>51</b>. As a result, the fresh air in the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and the fresh air in the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>can be made to undergo an ample degree of pulsation. Furthermore, the pulsations of the fresh air in the first air induction space are out of phase with the pulsations of the second air induction space. Consequently, the portion of fresh air from the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and the portion of fresh air from the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>readily mix with the blow-by gas inside the volume chamber <b>72</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">In this illustrated embodiment, the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> is arranged to pass nearby the center CP of the area of the opening at an intermediate position along the length of the first partitioning plate <b>81</b>, which spans from the vicinity of the throttle valve <b>91</b> to the intake air collector <b>51</b>. Additionally, the first communication surface area <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>1</b> and the second communication surface area <b>71</b><i>e</i><b>2</b> are substantially equal. As a result, the blow-by gas is distributed substantially evenly to the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">In the embodiment, the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> introduces blow-by gas into the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>through the connector <b>75</b> and the volume chamber <b>72</b>. Thus, the manner in which the blow-by gas is distributed is determined by the relative positioning of the first partitioning plate <b>81</b> and the volume chamber <b>72</b>. As a result, the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> can be arranged as appropriate in consideration of the distribution of the blow-by gas without being completely dependent on the position of the first partitioning plate <b>81</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">In the illustrated embodiment, the volume chamber <b>71</b> is configured and arranged to project outward from the air induction pipe <b>53</b>. In this way, a volume chamber <b>72</b> enclosed by a volume chamber wall <b>71</b> can be obtained. By using a volume chamber wall <b>71</b> that projects outward from the air induction pipe <b>53</b>, a higher degree of freedom can be secured with respect to the layout of other members (e.g., harness bracket mounting boss <b>79</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>)). Additionally, since the harness bracket mounting boss <b>79</b> is connected to the volume chamber wall <b>71</b>, the rigidity of the harness bracket mounting boss can be increased with a comparatively simple structure that is relatively easy to fabricate.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">It is acceptable for the gas introduced from the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> to the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>to be EGR gas instead of blow-by gas. EGR gas, too, is a gas that contains moisture and has a higher temperature than the fresh air in the first air induction space and second air induction space. Consequently, freezing tends to occur at the opening <b>71</b><i>e. </i></p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">In this variation, too, the volume chamber <b>72</b> is arranged between the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> and the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b</i>. Since a portion of fresh air from the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and a portion of fresh air from the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b </i>mix with the blow-by gas in the volume chamber <b>72</b>, the temperature difference between the blow-by gas and the fresh air in the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>is reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">As a result of reducing the temperature difference between the blow-by gas and the fresh air in the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b</i>, the occurrence of freezing at the portion of the intake device <b>70</b> where the blow-by gas is introduced into the intake passage <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Furthermore, the gas introduced to the first and second air induction spaces <b>53</b><i>a </i>and <b>53</b><i>b </i>from the gas introducing pipe <b>78</b> can be any other gas besides blow-by gas or EGR gas so long it is a gas that contains moisture and has a different temperature than the fresh air in the first air induction space <b>53</b><i>a </i>and the fresh air in the second air induction space <b>53</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The number of cylinders of the internal combustion engine <b>1</b> is not limited to six and is not limited to an even number. It is also acceptable for the internal combustion engine <b>1</b> to be a flat engine instead of a V-type engine.</p>
<heading id="h-0012" level="1">General Interpretation of Terms</heading>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">In understanding the scope of the present invention, the term “comprising” and its derivatives, as used herein, are intended to be open ended terms that specify the presence of the stated features, elements, components, groups, integers, and/or steps, but do not exclude the presence of other unstated features, elements, components, groups, integers and/or steps. The foregoing also applies to words having similar meanings such as the terms, “including”, “having” and their derivatives. Also, the terms “part,” “section,” “portion,” “member” or “element” when used in the singular can have the dual meaning of a single part or a plurality of parts. Also as used herein to describe the above embodiment(s), the following directional terms “forward, rearward, above, downward, vertical, horizontal, below and transverse” as well as any other similar directional terms refer to those directions of a vehicle equipped with the present invention. Accordingly, these terms, as utilized to describe the present invention should be interpreted relative to a vehicle equipped with the present invention. Moreover, terms that are expressed as “means-plus function” in the claims should include any structure that can be utilized to carry out the function of that part of the present invention. The terms of degree such as “substantially”, “about” and “approximately” as used herein mean a reasonable amount of deviation of the modified term such that the end result is not significantly changed. For example, these terms can be construed as including a deviation of at least ±5% of the modified term if this deviation would not negate the meaning of the word it modifies.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">While only selected embodiments have been chosen to illustrate the present invention, it will be apparent to those skilled in the art from this disclosure that various changes and modifications can be made herein without departing from the scope of the invention as defined in the appended claims. For example, the size, shape, location or orientation of the various components can be changed as needed and/or desired. Components that are shown directly connected or contacting each other can have intermediate structures disposed between them. The functions of one element can be performed by two, and vice versa. The structures and functions of one embodiment can be adopted in another embodiment. It is not necessary for all advantages to be present in a particular embodiment at the same time. Every feature which is unique from the prior art, alone or in combination with other features, also should be considered a separate description of further inventions by the applicant, including the structural and/or functional concepts embodied by such feature(s). Thus, the foregoing descriptions of the embodiments according to the present invention are provided for illustration only, and not for the purpose of limiting the invention as defined by the appended claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An internal combustion engine intake device comprising:
<claim-text>a regulating chamber having a regulating valve configured and arranged to regulate a quantity of fresh air flowing therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an intake air collector fluidly communicating with the regulating chamber at a position downstream of the regulating valve;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an air induction pipe arranged between the regulating valve and the intake air collector to communicate the fresh air from the regulating chamber to the intake air collector, the air induction pipe including a partitioning part arranged and configured to divide a space inside the air induction pipe into a first air induction space and a second air induction space;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gas introducing pipe configured and arranged to introduce a first gas into the first and second air induction spaces, the first gas being different from the fresh air; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a volume chamber arranged between the gas introducing pipe and the first and second air induction spaces such that the first gas passes from the gas introducing pipe through the volume chamber and into the first and second air induction spaces.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the volume chamber has an opening that communicates with the first and second air induction spaces, and the cross sectional area of the opening is larger than the cross sectional area of the gas introducing pipe.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the cross sectional area of the opening is at least 1.5 times larger than the cross sectional area of the gas introducing pipe.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the gas introducing pipe is configured and arranged as one of a blow-by gas pipe that introduces blow-by gas as the first gas or an EGR gas pipe that introduces EGR gas as the first gas.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the partitioning part is configured and arranged to extend from a position in a vicinity of the regulating valve to a position substantially coplanar with a boundary plane between a space inside the air induction pipe and a space inside the intake air collector such that pulsations of the fresh air in the first air induction space are out of phase with pulsations of the fresh air in the second air induction space.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the partitioning part is arranged to divide an opening of the volume chamber such that the first gas exiting the opening communicates with both of the first and second air induction spaces, the opening of the volume chamber being disposed at an intermediate position along the air induction pipe.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the opening of the volume chamber has a first communication area defined by an area of communication between the opening and the first air induction space that is substantially equal to a second communication area defined by an area of communication between the opening and the second air induction space.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising
<claim-text>a connector part fluidly communicating the volume chamber to the gas introducing pipe such that the first gas from the gas introducing pipe is introduce the first gas into the first and second air introduction spaces through the connector part and the volume chamber.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the volume chamber includes a volume chamber wall with a harness bracket mounting boss that is connected to the volume chamber wall.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the gas introducing pipe is configured and arranged as one of a blow-by gas pipe that introduces blow-by gas as the first gas or an EGR gas pipe that introduces EGR gas as the first gas.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the partitioning part is configured and arranged to extend from a position in a vicinity of the regulating valve to a position substantially coplanar with a boundary plane between a space inside the air induction pipe and a space inside the intake air collector such that pulsations of the fresh air in the first air induction space are out of phase with pulsations of the fresh air in the second air induction space.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the partitioning part is arranged to divide the opening of the volume chamber such that the opening communicates with both of the first and second air induction spaces, the opening of the volume chamber being disposed at an intermediate position along the air induction pipe.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the opening of the volume chamber has a first communication area defined by an area of communication between the opening and the first air induction space that is substantially equal to a second communication area defined by an area of communication between the opening and the second air induction space.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising
<claim-text>a connector part fluidly communicating the volume chamber to the gas introducing pipe such that the first gas from the gas introducing pipe is introduce the first gas into the first and second air introduction spaces through the connector part and the volume chamber.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the volume chamber includes a volume chamber wall with a harness bracket mounting boss that is connected to the volume chamber wall.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the volume chamber includes a volume chamber wall that is a portion of a wall forming the air induction pipe.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the intake air collector is divided into a first collector space fluidly communicating with the first air induction space and isolated from the second air induction space, and a second collector space fluidly communicating with the second air induction space and isolated from the first air induction space.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The internal combustion engine intake device as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the partitioning part includes a notch arranged adjacent an opening of the volume chamber with an edge portion of the notch lying in plane that divides the opening of the volume chamber such that the first gas exiting the opening communicates with both of the first and second air induction spaces.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. An internal combustion engine intake device comprising:
<claim-text>regulating means for regulating a quantity of fresh air flowing therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>intake air collecting means for collecting intake air into a first collector space and a second collector space;</claim-text>
<claim-text>air induction means for introducing intake air from to an upstream side of the intake air collecting means;</claim-text>
<claim-text>partitioning means for dividing the intake air in the air induction means into first air and second air induction spaces that fluidly communicate with the first and second collector spaces;</claim-text>
<claim-text>gas introducing means for introducing a first gas other than fresh air into the first air and second air induction spaces of the air induction means; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>volume chamber means for communicating the first gas from the gas introducing means to the first and second air induction spaces.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
