<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297993-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297993</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11179404</doc-number>
<date>20050712</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-213591</doc-number>
<date>20040721</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>739</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257197</main-classification>
<further-classification>257198</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E29185</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E29188</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E29189</further-classification>
<further-classification>438235</further-classification>
<further-classification>438309</further-classification>
<further-classification>438312</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Bipolar transistor and fabrication method of the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6600179</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Quaglietta et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257197</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0015474</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Blayac et al.</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257565</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0238843</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Sawdai et al.</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257197</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>FR</country>
<doc-number>2726125</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19960400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257197</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257198</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E29091</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E29124</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E29185</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E29188</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257571</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257586</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257587</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257592</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E29189</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438235</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438309</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438312</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438E21371</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438317</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438350</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>12</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>22</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060017065</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060126</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kobayashi</last-name>
<first-name>Junichiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sonnenschein Nath &amp; Rosenthal LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sony Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Purvis</last-name>
<first-name>Sue A.</first-name>
<department>2826</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Liu</last-name>
<first-name>Benjamin Tzu-Hung</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A bipolar transistor having a base electrode of an air bridge structure is simplified in structure and enhanced in the degree of freedom of a contact position of a base wiring line with the base electrode. The bipolar transistor has a semiconductor mesa portion having a base layer formed on an upper face thereof, and a base electrode contacts with the base layer and has a floating extension which extends from the semiconductor mesa portion to a space on the outer side with respect to the semiconductor mesa portion. The floating extension is used as a contact portion for a base wiring line to the base electrode.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="67.39mm" wi="141.73mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="211.33mm" wi="153.16mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="230.63mm" wi="149.01mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="185.84mm" wi="147.83mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="197.78mm" wi="144.36mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="205.49mm" wi="148.59mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="215.22mm" wi="151.21mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="158.58mm" wi="87.55mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="132.42mm" wi="141.39mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="173.99mm" wi="142.07mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="204.81mm" wi="130.30mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297993-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="210.14mm" wi="143.93mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="92.03mm" wi="122.00mm" file="US07297993-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates to a bipolar transistor suitably applied to a hetero-junction bipolar transistor and a fabrication method of the same.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A conventional hetero-junction bipolar transistor (HBT) is generally configured in such a manner as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12A</figref> which is a schematic plan view and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12B</figref> which is a schematic sectional view taken along line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12A</figref>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12A and 12B</figref>, the hetero-junction bipolar transistor shown includes a sub collector layer <b>101</b>, a collector layer <b>102</b> and a base layer <b>103</b> laminated in order on a substrate <b>100</b> made of, for example, a semi-insulating semiconductor material to form a semiconductor mesa portion BM having an upper face to which the base layer <b>103</b> is exposed. Emitter layers <b>104</b> are formed limitatively on the semiconductor mesa portion BM.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In the HBT, provision of a contact portion, through which an external wiring line for a base electrode <b>105</b> which is in ohmic contact with the base layer <b>103</b> is connected to the base electrode <b>105</b>, on the semiconductor mesa portion BM increases the area of the base region and increases the capacitance between the base and the collector, and consequently deteriorates high-frequency characteristics of the transistor, that is, the characteristic frequency fT, gain and so forth of the transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In order to prevent this, the base electrode <b>105</b> is extended, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12A and 12B</figref>, to the outer side farther than the semiconductor mesa portion BM to a location on an insulating layer <b>106</b> made of, for example, SiN and formed in the form of an island on the semi-insulating semiconductor substrate. Thus, the fixed extension of the base electrode <b>105</b> on the insulating layer <b>106</b> is used as a contact portion <b>105</b>C for a base wiring line.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the configuration described, the emitter layers <b>104</b> are formed, for example, on the opposite sides of the location of the base electrode <b>105</b>, and an emitter electrode <b>107</b> is formed on each of the emitter layers <b>104</b>. Further, collector electrodes <b>108</b> are formed on the sub collector layer <b>101</b> on the opposite outer sides of the emitter electrodes <b>107</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">However, where the base electrode <b>105</b> is formed in such a manner as to extend to the insulating layer <b>106</b> on the semi-insulating semiconductor substrate <b>100</b> to form the contact portion <b>105</b>C as described above, there is a problem that the fabrication process therefor is much complicated and also it is difficult to control the shape the base electrode <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Another more simplified HBT structure has been proposed and is disclosed in Japanese Patent Laid-Open No. 2001-308312 and Technical Report of IEICE, the Institute of Electronics, Information and Communication Engineers, ED99-262. The HBT structure mentioned is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, an isolation groove <b>210</b> is formed in a laminated semiconductor layer formed on a semi-insulating semiconductor substrate <b>200</b> and formed from a sub collector layer <b>201</b>, a collector layer <b>202</b>, a base layer <b>203</b>, an emitter layer <b>204</b> and so forth. The isolation groove <b>210</b> defines a semiconductor mesa portion BM having an upper face to which the base layer <b>203</b> is exposed and an isolation portion <b>206</b> formed from part of the laminated semiconductor material separated from the semiconductor mesa portion BM. Further, a base electrode <b>205</b> is formed such that it has an extension which spans the semiconductor mesa portion BM and the isolation portion <b>206</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In this instance, a base wiring line contact portion <b>205</b>C is a fixed extension of the base electrode <b>205</b> which is fixed to the isolation portion <b>206</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A collector electrode <b>208</b> is disposed on the sub collector layer <b>201</b> outside the semiconductor mesa portion BM, and an emitter electrode <b>207</b> is disposed on the emitter layer <b>204</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In any of the HBT described hereinabove with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12A and 12B</figref> and the HBT described above with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, the base electrode <b>105</b> or <b>205</b> has an air bridge configuration wherein it is formed such that it extends to the outer side from the semiconductor mesa portion BM and is fixed at an outer end thereof to the insulating layer <b>106</b> or the isolation portion <b>206</b> of the laminated semiconductor layer while the semiconductor layer is hollowed out below an intermediate portion of the extension so as to form an air layer.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The air layer which defines the air bridge is formed by hollowing out, after the base electrode <b>105</b> or <b>205</b> is formed, the semiconductor layer below the base electrode <b>105</b> or <b>205</b> by wet etching by which side etching of the base electrode <b>105</b> or <b>205</b> occurs.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">However, in this instance, it is difficult to control the etching for the hollowing out. Further, by the etching, abnormal etching proceeds with an interface between an edge portion of the electrode and the semiconductor material, and this gives rise to such problems as deterioration of transistor characteristics, degradation of the reliability and a drop of the yield upon fabrication.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Particularly in an InP type HBT, InP is used for the substrate, and where a sub collector layer and a collector layer each formed from a semiconductor layer of an InP type which exhibits lattice matching with the InP, the side etching exhibits a high crystal selectivity. Therefore, a restriction occurs with the selection of the arrangement direction of the base electrode, and this gives rise to a restriction to the arrangement design of the base electrode. Consequently, there is a problem that the fabrication method is complicated and the yield is degraded.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Further, if the metal of the base electrode contacts at the air bridge portion with an end portion of a base mesa portion, then the stress distortion of the base metal or diffusion of the metal element reaches the semiconductor layer immediately below the same, and leak current between the base and the collector appears on a side face (end face) of the base-collector junction exposed to the side face of the mesa portion. This gives rise to a problem that there is the possibility that the reliability may be deteriorated.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Further, where a plurality of InP type HBT devices having, for example, an InGaAs layer are formed on a common substrate, since InGaAs has a small band gap, isolation of the devices cannot be achieved by application of an ordinary device isolation method by ion implantation of a neutral impurity, but it cannot be avoided to adopt the mesa structure.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">It is desirable to provide a bipolar transistor which, where a base wiring line contact for a base electrode as in an InP type HBT or the like which cannot be avoided to be formed in a mesa structure is provided on an extension of the base electrode outside a base mesa portion to form an air bridge structure, is simple in configuration and high in reliability and can be fabricated with a high yield and a fabrication method of the bipolar transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In order to attain the desire described above, according to an embodiment of the present invention, there is provided a bipolar transistor, having a semiconductor mesa portion having a base layer formed on an upper face thereof, and a base electrode contacting with the base layer and having a floating extension which extends from the semiconductor mesa portion to a location above a recess on the outer side with respect to the semiconductor mesa portion, the floating extension being used as a contact portion for a base wiring line to the base electrode.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The bipolar transistor may be configured such that two or more such semiconductor mesa portions are disposed in a spaced relationship by a required distance from each other, and the base electrode is provided in contact commonly with the base layers of mutually adjacent ones of the semiconductor mesa portions, the floating extension of the common base electrode extending above a recess formed between paired ones of the semiconductor mesa portions.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Preferably, the floating extension is provided on the base electrode through an upright portion which spatially rises uprightly on the inner side by a required distance with respect to a side edge of the semiconductor mesa portion on an upper face of the semiconductor mesa portion. In this instance, preferably the distance is selected to be equal to or greater than 0.5 μm from the side edge of the semiconductor mesa portion.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The bipolar transistor may be a hetero-junction bipolar transistor, an InP type hetero-junction bipolar transistor, or an InP type hetero-junction bipolar transistor having a base layer made of InGaAs or GaAsSb and a collector layer made of InGaAs or InP.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In the bipolar transistor, the base electrode which contacts with the base layer formed on the upper face of the semiconductor mesa portion has the floating extension which extends from the semiconductor mesa portion to a location above the recess on the outer side with respect to the semiconductor mesa portion, and the contact portion for a base wiring line to the base electrode is provided on the floating extension.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Where the contact portion for the wiring line to the base electrode is provided at a place other than the semiconductor mesa portion in this manner, the area of the mesa portion can be reduced when compared with that in an alternative case wherein the contact portion is provided on the mesa portion. Consequently, reduction of the junction capacitance between the base and the collector can be anticipated, and enhancement of high-frequency characteristics of the transistor, that is, the characteristic frequency f<sub>T</sub>, gain and so forth of the transistor, can be anticipated.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Further, since the contact of the base wiring line to the base electrode is established in the proximity of the semiconductor mesa portion, that is, in the proximity of the contact portion of the base electrode with the base layer, the current path provided by the electrode and the wiring line is reduced in length. Consequently, reduction in resistance and parasitic capacitance can be anticipated and enhance of a frequency characteristic of the transistor can be anticipated.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Further, since the contact of the base wiring line with the base electrode can be established in the proximity of the semiconductor mesa portion in this manner, mechanical stabilization of the floating extension of the base electrode at the location can be anticipated. Consequently, the contact of the base wiring line can be established favorably.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Further, after the contact of the base wiring line is established, the holding function of the floating extension of the base electrode can be provided by the electrode base wiring line.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Further, reduction of the occupied area and simplification of the structure can be anticipated when compared with an alternative case wherein a free end of the floating extension of the base electrode is secured to a semiconductor isolation portion or an insulating layer in the form of an isle for fixation is provide specifically on a substrate and the base electrode is secured to the insulating layer as in the prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Further, since the degree of freedom in arrangement position of the contact portion of the base wiring line increases, the degree of freedom in layout, for example, of the wiring line increases.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Further, where the bipolar transistor is applied, for example, as a bipolar transistor for high output power, the mechanical stabilization of the wiring line contact portion described above can be further enhanced by forming a plurality of semiconductor mesa portions each having a transistor configuration, forming a common base electrode across the semiconductor mesa portions and using an intermediate portion of the floating extension of the base electrode above a recess as the base wiring line contact portion.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Further, where the base electrode is so shaped that it rises uprightly on the inner side by a required distance with respect to an edge portion of the semiconductor mesa portion, and particularly where the distance is selected to be equal to or greater than 0.5 μm, leak current between the base and the collector on a side face (end face) of the base-collector junction exposed to the side face of the mesa portion, which is caused by stress distortion by the contact of the base electrode or diffusion of a metal element, can be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">According to another embodiment of the present invention, there is provided a fabrication method of a bipolar transistor, including a semiconductor mesa portion forming step of forming a semiconductor mesa portion formed from at least a collector layer, a base layer and an emitter layer laminated on a substrate such that part of the base layer is exposed to an upper face of the semiconductor mesa portion, and a base electrode forming step of forming a base electrode which contacts with the base layer and has a floating extension which extends from the semiconductor mesa portion to a location above a recess on the outer side with respect to the semiconductor mesa portion, the base electrode forming step including a step of forming a base electrode forming support member and a base electrode metal layer patterning step, the step of forming a base electrode forming support member forming, on the base electrode forming location, the base forming support member in such a manner as to extend by a predetermined distance from a mesa side edge portion on the semiconductor mesa portion and extend into the recess of the formation location for the floating extension of the base electrode, the base electrode metal layer patterning step including a step of forming liftoff resist except the base electrode formation location, a step of forming an electrode metal layer in a region at least including a region on the base electrode formation portion, and a step of removing the liftoff resist to pattern the electrode metal layer to form the base electrode.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In the fabrication method of a bipolar transistor, a base electrode forming support member is formed at a formation location for a floating extension, and a base electrode of a predetermined pattern is formed on the base electrode forming support member by a liftoff method, and thereafter, the support member of the electrode metal is removed. Consequently, if the support member is formed from a material different from that of the semiconductor mesa portion and besides, for example, a solvent for removing the support member is selected to a material which does not erode the composing material of the semiconductor mesa portion, then the influence of the fact that the semiconductor mesa portion is eroded by side etching performed for hollowing out a lower portion of the base electrode to obtain a floating configuration upon the characteristic of the bipolar transistor can be prevented. Consequently, enhancement of the productivity and enhancement of the yield can be anticipated, and a bipolar transistor having a characteristic conforming to a designed characteristic can be formed.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Further, with the fabrication method of a bipolar transistor, the formation of the semiconductor space below the base electrode, that is, the formation of the floating portion, does not rely upon the technique of hollowing out the semiconductor by side etching. Therefore, in a bipolar transistor which cannot be avoided to have a mesa type shape as in the case of an InP type HBT, moderation of a restriction in pattern designing such as a limitation to the taking out direction of the base electrode in a case wherein the direction of the crystal axis in which side etching is liable to occur in the case of an InP type HBT is specified can be anticipated.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a schematic plan view of a bipolar transistor to which the present invention is applied and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> is a schematic sectional view taken along line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a schematic plan view illustrating a step of a fabrication method of the transistor shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2B and 2C</figref> are schematic sectional views taken along line X-X and line X′-X′ of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, respectively;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a schematic plan view illustrating another step of the fabrication method and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is a sectional view taken along line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> is a schematic plan view illustrating a further step of the fabrication method and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> is a sectional view taken along line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a schematic plan view illustrating a still further step of the fabrication method and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is a sectional view taken along line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> is a schematic plan view illustrating a yet further step of the fabrication method and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> is a sectional view taken along line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A and 7B</figref> are schematic sectional views illustrating different liftoff steps of the fabrication method;</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a diagram illustrating measurement curves of the dependency between the collector-base leak current and the collector-base voltage where the width of a rise portion on a mesa portion of the bipolar transistor according to the present invention from an edge portion of the mesa portion is used as a parameter;</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9 and 10</figref> are schematic sectional views of different bipolar transistors to which the present invention is applied;</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a schematic plan view of another different bipolar transistor to which the present invention is applied;</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12A</figref> is a schematic plan view of an example of a conventional bipolar transistor and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12B</figref> is a sectional view taken along line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12A</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a schematic sectional view showing another example of a conventional bipolar transistor.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">A hetero-junction bipolar transistor (HBT) to which the present invention is applied is described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref>.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">Embodiment Regarding an HBT</heading>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In the present embodiment, the present invention is applied, for example, to an InP type HBT for power amplification. In particular, first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> are formed in a spaced relationship by a required distance from each other on a common semi-insulating substrate <b>10</b> made of, for example, InP. In the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b>, a common sub collector layer <b>11</b> is formed on the semi-insulating substrate <b>10</b>, and collector layers <b>12</b> and base layers <b>13</b> are successively laminated on the sub collector layer <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> have first and second semiconductor mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and EM<b>2</b> paired with each other and provided symmetrically with respect to an X-X line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>. Each of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and EM<b>2</b> has emitter electrodes <b>17</b> coated in an ohmic relationship on an upper face thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">A pair of collector electrodes <b>18</b> are provided in contact with the sub collector layer <b>11</b> on the opposite sides of each of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> symmetrically with respect to the X-X line.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">A common base electrode <b>15</b> is disposed on the base layers <b>13</b> exposed to the upper faces of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> such that it spans the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> along the X-X line.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The base electrode <b>15</b> is held in contact at the opposite ends thereof with the base layers <b>13</b> of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b>, and a common floating extension <b>15</b>F rises uprightly from the contact portions of the base electrode <b>15</b> in such a manner as to be spaced away from the upper faces of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> and extend above a recess <b>40</b> formed between the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The rising positions of the base electrode <b>15</b> from the upper faces of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> are selected such that they are displaced to the inner side, that is, to the center side, from the opposing edges of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> so as to have a required width W as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The width W is selected particularly to 0.5 μm or more.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Further, a contact portion <b>15</b>C for a base wiring line with the base electrode <b>15</b> is set to the above-described floating extension <b>15</b>F of the base electrode <b>15</b>, and the contact portion <b>15</b>C can have a required greater width as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">An insulating layer <b>41</b>, for example, an interlayer insulating layer, is formed in such a manner as to cover the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> with which the base electrode <b>15</b> contacts in this manner.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Further, a wiring line contact opening <b>41</b><i>a </i>is formed by photolithography or the like on the floating extension <b>15</b>F of the base electrode <b>15</b> such that a base wiring line <b>42</b> which is to contact with the base electrode <b>15</b> extends through the wiring line contact opening <b>41</b><i>a </i>and contacts with the contact portion <b>15</b>C of the floating extension <b>15</b>F of the base electrode <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The insulating layer <b>41</b> described above can be formed, for example, using SiN, SiO<sub>2 </sub>or BCB(benzocyclobutane)and so forth. In this instance, a space <b>30</b> may remain in the recess <b>40</b> below the floating extension <b>15</b>F of the base electrode <b>15</b>, or the space <b>30</b> may be embedded completely or incompletely, for example, upon formation of the insulating layer <b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Though not shown, the emitter electrodes <b>17</b> and the collector electrodes <b>18</b> contact individually with wiring lines.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Now, a fabrication method of the HBT according to the present invention is described.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">Embodiment Regarding the Fabrication Method of the HBT</heading>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The InP type HBT for power amplification described above with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is fabricated in the following manner.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Referring first to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A to 2C</figref>, a semi-insulating substrate <b>10</b>, for example, of InP is prepared first, and a sub collector layer <b>11</b> of InGaAs or InP of a high impurity concentration of the first conduction type such as, for example, the n type, n-type collector layers <b>12</b> of InP of approximately 500 nm thick, base layers <b>13</b> of, for example, 50 nm thick made of InGaAs of a high impurity concentration of the second conduction type, for example, the p type, emitter layers <b>14</b> of 50 nm thick made of n-type InP, and n-type emitter cap layers <b>20</b> of 150 nm thick made of, for example, InGaAs of a high concentration are successively formed once over an overall area of the substrate <b>10</b>, for example, by MOCVD (Metal Organic Chemical Vapor Deposition).</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Further, emitter electrodes <b>17</b> of, for example, a Ti/Pt/Au (thickness: 50/50/200 nm) structure are formed on the emitter cap layers <b>20</b> by vapor deposition, sputtering or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Thereafter, a step of forming semiconductor mesa portions is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">At the step, mesa etching of required patterns is performed for the emitter electrodes <b>17</b>, emitter cap layers <b>20</b> and emitter layers <b>14</b> successively by pattern etching by photolithography thereby to form a pair of first emitter mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and a pair of second emitter mesa portions EM<b>2</b>. The first emitter mesa portions EM<b>1</b> are disposed, for example, symmetrically with respect to the X-X line and opposed to each other, and the second emitter mesa portions EM<b>2</b> are disposed symmetrically with respect to the X-X line similarly in a spaced relationship by a required distance from the first emitter mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and are opposed to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Further, the base layers <b>13</b> and the collector layers <b>12</b> are successively mesa-etched such that portions having the paired first emitter mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and portions having the paired second emitter mesa portions EM<b>2</b> may be left on the upper faces to form first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> of a transistor structure in a spaced relationship by a required distance D from each other such that they are opposed to the paired first and second semiconductor mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and EM<b>2</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">The first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> wherein the collector layers <b>12</b> and the base layers <b>13</b> are provided in a spaced relationship by a required distance from each other on the common sub collector layer <b>11</b> and the paired first and second semiconductor mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and EM<b>2</b> are formed on the base layers <b>13</b> are formed in this manner.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Thus, the semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> having a collector-common transistor structure are formed on the substrate <b>10</b>, and a recess <b>40</b> of the width D is defined between the semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Then, a step of forming a base electrode is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">At the step, a first stage step is performed in order to form a base electrode <b>15</b> common to and extending between the two semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref> such that a space <b>30</b> is formed below the base electrode <b>15</b> between the paired first and second semiconductor mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and EM<b>2</b> and the base electrode <b>15</b> extends along the X-X line. Particularly, as the first stage step, a base electrode forming support member <b>32</b> is filled into a concave portion formed between both of the emitter mesa portions EM<b>1</b> and EM<b>2</b> at the formation location of the base electrode <b>15</b> as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">The base electrode forming support member <b>32</b> is formed such that it extends inwardly from edge portions of the semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> spaced by a width corresponding to 0.5 μm or more of the width W from the edge portions of the semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> to the rising positions of the base electrode <b>15</b> to be formed finally.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The base electrode forming support member <b>32</b> can be formed, for example, from a photoresist and has a surface having a rounded sectional shape as a result of a baking process applied thereto. Further, a hardening process by irradiation of ultraviolet rays, that is, UV cure, is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Then, a liftoff mask layer <b>33</b> having an opening <b>33</b><i>a </i>formed at the base electrode formation location finally is formed as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref>, and a base electrode metal layer <b>34</b> from which a base electrode is to be formed is formed over an overall area on the liftoff mask layer <b>33</b> by sputtering or the like. Upon development of the photolithography in the formation of the opening <b>33</b><i>a</i>, the base electrode forming support member <b>32</b> described above is prevented from being removed because of the UV cure applied thereto.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">However, if the base electrode forming support member <b>32</b> is made of a material which is less likely to mix with the liftoff mask, the cure process described above is not required.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">The liftoff mask layer <b>33</b> may have a double layer structure wherein a liftoff layer <b>33</b>B is formed as a lower layer and a photoresist layer <b>33</b>A is formed as an upper layer, for example, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">Thus, an opening <b>33</b><i>a </i>corresponding to the pattern of an object base electrode <b>15</b> is formed in the photoresist layer <b>33</b>A of the upper layer by photolithography, and in development of the photoresist layer <b>33</b>A, that is, in formation of the opening <b>33</b><i>a</i>, side etching occurs with the liftoff layer <b>33</b>B of the lower layer by the developer. Consequently, an opening <b>33</b><i>b </i>is formed in the liftoff layer <b>33</b>B of the lower layer such that it is retracted from the circumferential edge of the opening <b>33</b><i>a</i>, and a visor <b>35</b> is formed above on the circumferential edge of the opening <b>33</b><i>b </i>by the opening <b>33</b><i>a </i>in the upper layer.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Accordingly, if a base electrode metal layer <b>34</b> is vapor deposited from above the mask layer <b>33</b>, then a base electrode metal layer <b>34</b> is deposited directly in a pattern corresponding to the pattern of the opening <b>33</b><i>a </i>of the mask layer <b>33</b>A of the upper layer, that is, at the formation location of the object base electrode <b>15</b>, that is, at the formation locations of the base electrode <b>15</b> on the base electrode forming support member <b>32</b> and on the base layers of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">At this time, the base electrode metal layers <b>34</b> are formed also on the mask layer <b>33</b>A of the upper layer. However, the base electrode metal layer <b>34</b> on the formation location of the base electrode <b>15</b> and the base electrode metal layers <b>34</b> on the upper layer mask layer <b>33</b>A are formed separately from each other.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">In this state, the mask layer <b>33</b> is removed. As a result, the base electrode metal layer <b>34</b> on the liftoff mask layer <b>33</b> is removed together with the collector. In other words, the base electrode metal layer <b>34</b> is lifted off, and an object base electrode <b>15</b> is formed from the remaining base electrode metal layer <b>34</b> as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref>. At this time, also the base electrode forming support member <b>32</b> is removed, and a space <b>30</b> is formed here. Consequently, an air bridge structure is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">It is to be noted that such liftoff may not rely upon the double layer structure described above but may be performed using a single layer resist such as, for example, RD2000 (commodity name by Hitachi Chemical) with which a visor <b>35</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref>) is generated upon development.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The base electrode metal layer <b>34</b> may be formed in a Ti/Pt/Au structure (thickness: Ti/Pt/Au˜50/50/200 nm).</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">An air bridge structure, that is, the floating extension <b>15</b>F, is formed in this manner.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">Then, in the present embodiment, the floating extension <b>15</b>F is used as a contact portion <b>15</b>C for a wiring line to the base electrode <b>15</b>. To this end, the floating extension <b>15</b>F is formed with an increased width such that it has an area necessary for the contact, that is, an area of, for example, approximately 3 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">Further, the base electrode <b>15</b> is configured such that it rises from the positions of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> spaced by the width W to the inner side from the opposing edges of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b>. The width W is set to 0.5 μm or more.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">It is to be noted that the thickness of the base electrode <b>15</b>, the width of the air bridge portion, that is, the floating extension <b>15</b>F, the mesa distance D and so forth are determined taking a mechanical strength required for the air bridge into consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">Then, collector electrodes <b>18</b> are formed in ohmic contact on the sub collector layer <b>11</b> on the opposite sides of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref>. Then, the sub collector layer <b>11</b> is etched to perform device isolation.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">Thereafter, an insulating layer <b>41</b> of, for example, SiN, SiO<sub>2</sub>, BCB (benzocyclobutane) or the like is formed as indicated by a chain line in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> such that it covers over the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> with which the base electrode <b>15</b> contacts.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">Then, a wiring line contact opening <b>41</b><i>a </i>is formed on the floating extension <b>15</b>F of the base electrode <b>15</b> by photolithography or the like. Then, a base wiring line <b>42</b> to contact with the base electrode <b>15</b> extends through the wiring line contact opening <b>41</b><i>a </i>and contacts with the contact portion <b>15</b>C of the floating extension <b>15</b>F of the base electrode <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">The insulating layer <b>41</b> described above may be formed such that a space <b>30</b> remains in the recess <b>40</b> below the floating extension <b>15</b>F of the base electrode <b>15</b> or may otherwise be formed such that the space <b>30</b> is filled completely or not completely.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">Further, though not shown, a multilayer wiring line structure may be used wherein a wiring layer of an upper layer is formed on the wiring layer, on which the base wiring line <b>42</b> is formed, with an interlayer insulating film interposed therebetween and the two wiring line layers are connected to each other through a contact hole perforated in the interlayer insulating layer.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">As described above, in the structure of the present embodiment, where the base electrode <b>15</b> rises in a spaced relationship by the width W of 0.5 μm or more from the edge portions of the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b>, leak current between the collector and the base extending along side faces of the mesa portions can be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, curves <b>81</b>, <b>82</b> and <b>83</b> indicate results of measurement of the collector-base current Icbo with respect to the collector-base voltage Vcb when the width W is set to W=0.5 μm, 1.0 μm and 1.5 μm, respectively. As seen from the curves <b>81</b>, <b>82</b> and <b>83</b>, enhancement with regard to the leak current between the collector and the base can be observed where W≧0.5 μm, preferably W≧1.0 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">It is to be noted that the bipolar transistor and the fabrication method of the same according to the present invention are not limited to those described hereinabove but may be configured otherwise such that, for example, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, also the collector layers <b>12</b> in the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> having a transistor structure are formed as mesa portions CM<b>1</b> and CM<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">Further, while, in the embodiment described hereinabove, the base electrode <b>15</b> is formed so as to span a plurality of mesa portions, that is, the first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b>, the base electrode <b>15</b> may be structured otherwise such that, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, it contacts only at one end thereof with the base layer of a semiconductor mesa portion BM.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">Further, the number of air bridge portions is not limited to one but may be any number in various arrangement configurations which include three or more semiconductor mesa portions. An example is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, three semiconductor mesa portions including such first and second semiconductor mesa portions BM<b>1</b> and BM<b>2</b> having a transistor structure as described above and an additional third semiconductor mesa portion BM<b>3</b> having a transistor structure of a similar configuration are provided. Further, a plurality of floating extensions <b>15</b>F are formed between the individual semiconductor mesa portions, and a contact portion <b>15</b>C for a base wiring line <b>42</b> is formed on each of the floating extensions <b>15</b>F.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">Further, the composition of each element in the InP type bipolar transistor described hereinabove is not limited to that of the example described hereinabove.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">In particular, for example, the collector layers <b>12</b> may be formed not from InP but from InGaAs; the base layers <b>13</b> may be formed not from InGaAs but from GaAsSb; and the emitter layers <b>14</b> may be formed not from InP but from InAlAs. In this manner, various configurations are possible.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">Further, the present invention can be applied also to a bipolar transistor such as an HBT of the GaAs type or the like. In this instance, the collector layer and the base layer can be formed from GaAs while the emitter layer can be formed from AlGaAs or InGaP.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">Further, it is also possible to form an InP bipolar transistor of the non-lattice matching type by forming a metamorphic buffer layer of InAlAs or InP on a GaAs substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">As described above, according the bipolar transistor such as, for example, an HBT and the fabrication method of the same according to the present invention, the floating extension <b>15</b>F is formed such that it extends from a semiconductor mesa portion to the recess <b>40</b> on the outer side of the semiconductor mesa portion, and the contact portion <b>15</b>C for a base wiring line to the base electrode is provided on the floating extension <b>15</b>F. By the configuration just described, since an insulating layer for fixing the electrode extension or a mesa portion is not disposed specifically except a semiconductor mesa portion which is provided in a conventional bipolar transistor. Consequently, simplification in structure and reduction in area can be achieved. Further, since the degree of freedom in arrangement position of a contact portion for a base wiring line increases, the degree of freedom in layout, for example, of a wiring line increases.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">Further, since the contact for the base wiring line with the base electrode <b>15</b> is established in the proximity of a semiconductor mesa portion, that is, in the proximity of the contact portion of the base electrode with the base layer, reduction of the resistance and the parasitic capacitance incidental to the electrode and the wiring line can be anticipated, and enhancement of a frequency characteristic of the transistor can be anticipated.</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0100">Further, since the contact portion <b>15</b>C for the base wiring line with the base electrode <b>15</b> can be positioned in the proximity of a semiconductor mesa portion in this manner, the mechanical stability of the floating extension <b>15</b>F of the base electrode <b>15</b> at the location mentioned is high, and the contact of the base wiring line can be established favorably.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0101">Further, after the base wiring line contact is established, the function of holding the floating extension of the base electrode can be exhibited by the electrode base wiring line.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0102">Particularly, for example, in a bipolar transistor for high output power, the above-described mechanical stability of the wiring line contact portion can be further enhanced if a plurality of semiconductor mesa portions each having a transistor configuration are formed and a common base electrode is formed such that it spans the semiconductor mesa portions and the floating extension above each of recesses intermediately between the semiconductor mesa portions is used as a base wiring line contact portion.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0103">Further, in the fabrication method of the present embodiment, since a method of removing a semiconductor layer below the extension of the base electrode <b>15</b> by side etching is not used, the influence of erosion of a semiconductor mesa portion on a characteristic of the bipolar transistor can be prevented. Consequently, enhancement of the productivity and enhancement of the yield can be achieved and a bipolar transistor having a characteristic conforming to a designed characteristic can be formed.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0104">While preferred embodiments of the present invention have been described using specific terms, such description is for illustrative purposes only, and it is to be understood that changes and variations may be made without departing from the spirit or scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A bipolar transistor, including:
<claim-text>a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one pair of semiconductor mesa portions provided on said substrate with a space therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base layer on each semiconductor mesa portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base electrode contacting and bridging between each base layer of each pair of semiconductor mesa portions; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base wiring,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said base layers of a semiconductor mesa portion pair are spaced from each other by a first predetermined distance,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said base electrode extends over said first predetermined distance and forms a floating extension between said base layers,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said floating extension includes a contact portion between said base layers where said base electrode can be connected to said base wiring over said space below said base electrode and between said corresponding mesa portions,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said floating extension includes a portion which spatially rises uprightly above said space on an inner side by a second predetermined distance with respect to a side edge of each of said base layers, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said second predetermined distance is selected to be equal to or greater than 1.0 μm from said side edge of each of said base layers to decrease a leak current between a collector and said base layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The bipolar transistor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said bipolar transistor is a hetero-junction bipolar transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The bipolar transistor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said bipolar transistor is an InP type heterojunction bipolar transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The bipolar transistor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said bipolar transistor is an InP type heterojunction bipolar transistor having a base layer made of InGaAs or GaAsSb and a collector layer made of InGaAs or InP.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A fabrication method of a bipolar transistor, composing:
<claim-text>a semiconductor mesa portion forming step of forming a semiconductor mesa portion formed from at least a collector layer, a base layer and an emitter layer laminated on a substrate such that part of said base layer is exposed to an upper face of said semiconductor mesa portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base electrode forming step of forming a base electrode which contacts with the base layer and has a floating extension which extends from said semiconductor mesa portion to a location above a space on the outer side with respect to said semiconductor mesa portion, said floating extension being used as a contact portion for a base wiring line to said base electrode, and said base wiring positioned and contacting said floating extension spatially above the space;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the base electrode forming step including a step of forming a base electrode forming support member and a base electrode metal layer patterning step;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the step of forming a base electrode forming support member forming, on the base electrode forming location, the base forming support member in such a manner as to extend by a predetermined distance from a mesa side edge of the semiconductor mesa portion and extend into the space of the formation location for the floating extension of the base electrode, said predetermined distance is equal to or greater than 1.0 μm from the side edge of said semiconductor mesa portion for decreasing a leak current between a collector and the base layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the base electrode metal layer patterning step including a step of forming liftoff resist except the base electrode formation location, a step of forming an electrode metal layer in a region at least including a region on the base electrode formation portion, and a step of removing the liftoff resist to pattern the electrode metal layer to form the base electrode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
