<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298495-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298495</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11167006</doc-number>
<date>20050623</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356500</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">System and method for positioning an object through use of a rotating laser metrology system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4572021</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Guarracini et al.</name>
<date>19860200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4627009</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Holmes et al.</name>
<date>19861200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4655594</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wittekoek et al.</name>
<date>19870400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>356500</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5734164</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sanford</name>
<date>19980300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6403968</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hazaki et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6407373</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Dotan</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2502013</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6661009</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Groholski et al.</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6855940</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Mutou</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>25044011</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0093663</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Tsai</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>356498</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0180159</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Nakamura et al.</name>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>277500</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>1275577</doc-number>
<date>19720500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>1458778</doc-number>
<date>19761200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>25</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356486</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356487</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356493</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356498</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356500</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>17</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070023684</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070201</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lewis</last-name>
<first-name>George C.</first-name>
<address>
<street>103 Horse Pond Rd.</street>
<city>Sudbury</city>
<state>MA</state>
<postcode>01776</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Krokar</last-name>
<first-name>Zelimir</first-name>
<address>
<street>88 Brush Hill Rd.</street>
<city>Sherborn</city>
<state>MA</state>
<postcode>01770</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hamilton, Brook, Smith &amp; Reynolds, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Turner</last-name>
<first-name>Samuel A.</first-name>
<department>2877</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A motion system includes a first stage that is configured to rotate about a first axis and a second stage coupled to the first stage that includes an object carrier adapted to position an object in at least one other axis. The motion system has a novel arrangement of laser interferometer elements and axes of motion. The arrangement permits accurate and precise measurement of a position of the object carrier in up to three (or more) axes of motion even as the first stage of the motion system is tilted through relatively large angles. The novel arrangement of the axes of motion also enables very precise control of the position of the object carrier even at high tilt angles.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="127.59mm" wi="164.34mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="213.02mm" wi="143.68mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="205.32mm" wi="131.23mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="232.33mm" wi="154.60mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="223.52mm" wi="134.62mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="239.86mm" wi="167.64mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="212.34mm" wi="159.77mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="218.61mm" wi="140.63mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="220.30mm" wi="159.17mm" file="US07298495-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a typical electron beam or ion beam system. A vacuum chamber <b>1</b> contains a multi-axis motion system <b>2</b> which is used to position an object <b>3</b>, such as a semiconductor wafer, under a beam <b>4</b> so that one or more sites of interest on the object <b>3</b> may be examined or processed. A column <b>5</b> on top of the vacuum chamber <b>1</b> provides an electron beam or ion beam. Generally, an electron beam is used to scan, observe, and measure features at sites of interest on the object <b>3</b>. Focused ion beams (FIB) may be used to observe and repair features. Electron, laser, or ion beams can be used to control processes, such as removal or deposition of material(s), at sites of interest on the object <b>3</b>. In some designs, two or more columns are used on one vacuum chamber, such as an electron beam system for observing defects and a separate FIB column for repairing defects.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A common arrangement in such motion systems is to have a tilting stage <b>6</b> on top of a rotating stage <b>7</b>, on top of a Y-axis stage <b>8</b>, on top of an X-axis stage <b>9</b>. When a large variety of object thicknesses must be managed, a Z-axis of motion stage <b>10</b> is also included in the multi-axis motion system <b>2</b>. The stacked arrangement in such a multi-axis motion system <b>2</b> limits accuracy of measurement(s) that can be obtained.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Often stepper motor drives are used to move the stages in their respective axes. A count of steps taken is used to effect approximate navigation. Then, the user must search in X, Y, and Z for each site of interest. After these adjustments are made, the object <b>3</b> may be tilted by using the tilting stage <b>6</b> to gain better access to lower layers at each site of interest.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Tilting the object <b>3</b> without moving the site of interest is not a simple task. Electron beam and FIB systems have limited viewing space. Most motion systems that provide a tilting motion quickly move the site of interest outside the viewing space. This problem is generally due to mechanical tolerances. Sometimes it is due to an inferior arrangement of the axes of motion. It is also a challenge to properly align the axis of beam <b>4</b> with the axes of motion in the multi-axis motion system <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The system in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> often limits the size of object that can be moved, observed, or processed. Generally, a small object, broken from an original full-sized object, is all that can be placed on such a motion system <b>2</b>. This limits use of the system to analytical tasks, since the broken piece often cannot be returned to the manufacturing line.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Electron, laser, or ion beam columns may be used in conjunction with one or more fixed gas jets <b>11</b> to remove or deposit material at each site of interest on an object. While it is possible to refocus the beam <b>4</b> over short distances, it is impractical to move gas jets <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A more robust motion system is needed. Users need to handle complete objects, without breaking them, and to navigate quickly and accurately to each site of interest. They need to do this when the object <b>3</b> has been tilted through an arbitrary angle, to navigate accurately in tilted space without the need for constant adjustment of the electron beam, laser beam, ion beam, or gas jets.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The principles of the present invention address the aforementioned and other problems associated with the motion system described in reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In accordance with the principles of the present invention, a novel arrangement of laser interferometer elements and axes of motion permits accurate and precise measurement of position of an object carrier on a second stage in up to three (or more) axes of linear motion even as a first stage, to which the second stage is coupled, is tilted through relatively large angles. The novel arrangement also enables very precise control of the second stage even at high tilt angles.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Accordingly, a system or corresponding method employing the principles of the present invention may be used for positioning an object. The system includes a structural support member to which a first stage is coupled through at least one rotational element. The first stage also includes a frame coupled to the at least one rotational element operable to rotate about a first axis through use of the at least one rotational element. The system also includes at least one second stage coupled to the first stage. The at least one second stage includes an object carrier adapted to move an object in at least a second axis. The system also includes a laser metrology system configured (i) to direct a laser beam in a direction substantially on and parallel to the first axis and (ii) to measure a position of the object carrier.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The laser metrology system may be configured to direct the laser beam through the structural support member. The at least one second stage may include an X-stage and a Y-stage, in which case, the laser metrology system includes optical elements that direct the laser beam to measure a position of the object carrier in respective X- and Y-axes. The system may further include at least one Z-control mechanism that moves the first stage in a Z-axis direction, in which case the laser metrology system is adapted to direct the laser beam in a direction substantially on and parallel to the first axis for all first stage positions on the Z-axis.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The aggregate center of gravity of the first stage and the second stage is within 1 inch of the first axis. In a preferred embodiment, the aggregate center of gravity is substantially on the first axis. Positioning the aggregate center of gravity in such proximity to the first axis provides balance to the system, which allows for reduced control requirements, smaller motors than for unbalanced systems, and other advantages understood in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In one embodiment, the first stage includes a first rotational element and a second rotational element. The first rotational element may be fixedly coupled to the structural support member, and the second rotational element may be variably coupled to the structural support member. In both one and multiple rotational element embodiments, the first stage may be adapted to rotate greater than one degree. The system may further include an immobilization mechanism coupled to the first stage to restrict motion (e.g., rotation or vibration) of the first stage.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The system may also include an alignment sensor adapted to detect an orientation of the object on the object carrier.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In some embodiments, the system further includes at least one motion control processor coupled to the second stage that causes the second stage to move in a desired manner. In such embodiments, the at least one motion control processor receives feedback of the position of the object carrier from the laser metrology system. The system may further include at least one other metrology system to measure a position of the object carrier or object, in which case the at least one motion control processor receives feedback from the at least one other metrology system for use in controlling the position of the object carrier or object.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The system may be used in an electron scanning microscope, vacuum chamber, ion beam repair or diagnostic system, or automated manufacturing process. For example, the system can be used with high resolution electron beam or ion beam systems to improve viewing and measurement capabilities. It may also be used with electron, laser, or ion beam systems to manufacture or repair objects such as integrated circuits, masks, nano-imprint molds, nano-devices or MEMS devices.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The foregoing and other objects, features and advantages of the invention will be apparent from the following more particular description of preferred embodiments of the invention, as illustrated in the accompanying drawings in which like reference characters refer to the same parts throughout the different views. The drawings are not necessarily to scale, emphasis instead being placed upon illustrating the principles of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a vertical section diagram of a prior art multi-axis motion system used to position a wafer, for example, in an electron, ion, or laser column or in front of a fixed gas jet provided to deliver process chemicals;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of a multi-axis motion system, according to the principles of the present invention, with coordinate conventions as viewed from the rear, right side;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a horizontal section view at a plane of a first (tilt) axis showing the first stage, which rotates about the first axis, and an arrangement of a first laser interferometer and first laser beam used to add a second (X) axis of motion, which is a first axis of laser metered motion;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a horizontal section view, similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, that shows an arrangement of a second laser interferometer and a second laser beam used to add a third (Y) axis of motion, which is a second axis of laser metered motion;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a vertical view of the outside of a right structural support member, supporting the multi-axis motion system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, showing how the first laser beam is delivered to the first (tilt) axis of motion;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is an enlarged view of a beam bender used to direct the first laser beam on and parallel to the first axis of motion as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a vertical view of the inside of the right structural support member of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> showing how an original (i.e., source) laser beam is divided to provide the first laser beam shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b>, and <b>5</b>, showing a further division of the laser beam that provides a third laser beam and third laser interferometer arranged to measure a fourth (Z) axis in a vertical motion provided within the right structural support member, and showing how a fourth laser beam is provided to measure a fifth (second Z) axis in a vertical motion for a left side structural support member;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a vertical view of the inside of a left structural support member, supporting the multi-axis motion system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, showing how the fourth laser beam of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> arrives and how it is used to provide the fourth laser interferometer to measure vertical (second Z) motion provided within the left structural support member;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a perspective view from the right rear of the multi-axis motion system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> showing the arrangement of laser parts and beams in one embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a detailed perspective view of the motion system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> showing relationships among the various laser parts and beams and their related mechanical parts to provide one integrated view with the related laser parts;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a perspective view of an object carrier and a sixth (object rotation) axis of motion in the multi-axis motion system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a bottom view of the third (Y) axis of motion in the multi-axis motion system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> showing an arrangement of a moving counterbalance to keep an aggregate center of gravity of this motion system and the parts it carries on the first axis throughout full travel of the third axis of motion;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a vertical section view through the first (tilt) axis, viewed from the rear, indicating an arrangement of masses used to place an aggregate center of gravity on the first axis indicated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a diagram of an alignment sensor used in the multi-axis motion system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> to orient objects after loading and prior to observation and/or processing;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a vertical section view through a left rotational element, normal to the first axis, showing how the rotational elements on the first tilt stage of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> can be immobilized;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is a vertical section through the left rotational element of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> and on the first axis showing how the left rotational element is designed to be variably coupled to the left structural support member of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> is a system block diagram of example controls used to operate the multi-axis motion system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram of a motion system <b>29</b> according to the principles of the present invention. A right structural support member <b>12</b> and a left structural support member <b>13</b> have within them a right rotational element <b>14</b> and a left rotational element <b>15</b>, respectively. These two rotational elements <b>14</b> and <b>15</b> define one axis of rotation, the first (tilt) axis <b>16</b>. The first axis <b>16</b> carries a first stage <b>17</b>, which includes a first stage frame <b>18</b> attached to the rotational elements <b>14</b> and <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In a preferred embodiment, the first stage frame <b>18</b> is attached to inner races (not shown) of spindle ball bearings by means well known in the art. It should be understood that other designs, such as gas bearings, roller bearings, crossed flexures, or other low friction rotational elements, can be used. But, the use of spindle ball bearings has other advantages as explained below in reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Referring briefly to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, a first axis drive motor <b>45</b> is attached to the first stage <b>17</b> to drive the first stage in rotation about the first (tilt) axis <b>16</b>. While a design using two supports is described herein, it should be understood that, in some applications, a cantilevered design using just one support member <b>12</b> and just one rotational element <b>14</b> can work equally well.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a second (X) stage <b>19</b> is coupled to the first stage <b>17</b> using crossed roller bearings. A front roller bearing <b>27</b> is mounted to the first stage <b>17</b> at the front of the first stage frame <b>18</b>. A rear roller bearing <b>28</b> is mounted to the first stage <b>17</b> at the rear of the first stage frame <b>18</b>. These two roller bearings <b>27</b> and <b>28</b> are aligned by well known methods so that the second stage <b>19</b> moves parallel to the first axis <b>16</b> along a second (X) axis <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Referring briefly to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, a second axis drive motor <b>46</b> may be mounted to the first stage frame <b>18</b> of the first stage <b>17</b>. Acting through a conventional ball screw drive and first ball nut <b>44</b>, the second axis drive motor <b>46</b> moves the ball nut <b>44</b>. The ball nut <b>44</b> is attached to the second stage <b>19</b>. In this manner, the second drive motor <b>46</b> moves the second stage <b>19</b> in a controlled manner. Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, plane (i.e., flat) mirror <b>22</b> may be associated with the second stage <b>19</b> and used as part of a laser measurement system to control the motion of the second stage <b>19</b>, as described below in reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b>, and <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">It should be understood that other low friction bearing elements, such as ball bearings or gas bearings, can be used to couple the second stage <b>19</b> to the first stage <b>17</b> in a manner that permits motion of the second stage <b>19</b> in the second (X) axis <b>26</b>. The assignment of coordinate systems is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. It should be understood that this nomenclature is easily changed, so it is quite arbitrary.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">A unique feature of this invention is an arrangement of a laser interferometer in a manner that permits measurement of linear motion over long distances while the first axis <b>16</b> is rotated through large angles. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows this unique arrangement. A first laser beam <b>20</b> is aligned to be parallel to and on the first axis <b>16</b> by means which are explained below in reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The first laser beam <b>20</b> passes through a first laser interferometer <b>21</b> and then on to a plane mirror <b>22</b>, which is adjustably attached to the second stage <b>19</b> by well known means. The laser and interferometer may be commercial items supplied by Hewlett Packard or Zygo Corporation. The first laser interferometer <b>21</b> may be adjustably attached using well known means to an inside structure of the right rotational element <b>14</b>. The first laser interferometer <b>21</b> may adjusted by well known methods so that a first measurement beam <b>23</b> exits parallel to the first axis <b>16</b>. When the first laser interferometer <b>21</b> is properly aligned, the first measurement beam <b>23</b> exits the first laser interferometer <b>21</b> offset from the first axis <b>16</b> by about ⅛ inch, in one embodiment, but still parallel to the first axis <b>16</b>. The internal operation of this first laser interferometer <b>21</b> is well described by its commercial supplier.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The first measurement beam <b>23</b> is reflected off the plane mirror <b>22</b>. The plane mirror <b>22</b> may be adjusted using well known methods so that the reflected beam returns along the same axis, again parallel to first axis <b>16</b>. The first measurement beam <b>23</b> makes several reflections inside the first laser interferometer <b>21</b>, then exits again as a second measurement beam <b>24</b>, again parallel to and offset from the first axis <b>16</b>. The second measurement beam <b>24</b> is also reflected by the plane mirror <b>22</b> so that it returns along the same axis back to the first laser interferometer <b>21</b>. In this manner, the plane mirror <b>22</b> is set perpendicular to the first axis <b>16</b>. Finally, the first laser beam <b>20</b> exits the first laser interferometer <b>21</b> and passes into a first optical fiber receiver <b>25</b>. The well known operation of first laser interferometer <b>21</b> causes the first and second measurement beams <b>23</b> and <b>24</b> to generate a measurement signal that is captured by the first optical fiber receiver <b>25</b>. This measurement signal is converted to position and velocity data by control electronics (not shown), which may be supplied by Hewlett Packard or Zygo.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the arrangement just described, the first stage <b>17</b> can be rotated around the first axis <b>16</b> without causing any loss of signal and without introducing false detection of motion of the second stage <b>19</b> in the second axis <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">While a unique arrangement of the mechanical parts, laser parts, and laser beams has been shown passing through right structural support member <b>12</b> and right rotational element <b>14</b>, other similar arrangements are possible. For example, a mirror image arrangement of the parts and beams using the left structural support member <b>13</b> and left rotational element <b>15</b> can work equally well.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows how a third (Y) axis <b>30</b> is added to the first and second axes <b>16</b> and <b>26</b> described above. The third (Y) stage <b>31</b> may be coupled to the second stage <b>19</b> using crossed roller bearings <b>42</b> and <b>43</b> mounted at the right and left sides, respectively, of the second stage <b>19</b> and the third stage <b>31</b>. The crossed roller bearings <b>42</b> and <b>43</b> may be adjusted by well known methods so that the third stage <b>31</b> moves along the third axis <b>30</b> in a direction that is perpendicular to the second axis <b>26</b>. It should be understood that other low friction bearing elements, such as ball bearings or gas bearings, can be used to couple the third stage <b>31</b> to the second stage <b>19</b> in a manner that permits motion of the third stage <b>31</b> in the third axis <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">As is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a first 50:50 beam splitter <b>32</b> is placed on the first axis <b>16</b> so that half of the intensity of first laser beam <b>20</b> is diverted in a new direction parallel to the third axis <b>30</b> and referred to as a second laser beam <b>33</b>. The first 50:50 beam splitter <b>32</b> may be adjustably mounted on the right rotational element <b>14</b> by well known means. When the first 50:50 beam splitter <b>32</b> is adjusted properly, the second laser beam <b>33</b> exits perpendicular to the first axis <b>16</b>. Since the first laser beam <b>20</b> is already aligned to be on and parallel to the first axis <b>16</b>, the relationship between the first laser beam <b>20</b> and the second laser beam <b>33</b> does not change as the first stage <b>17</b> rotates through its full range of travel about the first (tilt) axis <b>16</b>. In fact, the first laser beam <b>20</b> and the second laser beam <b>33</b> define a plane <b>34</b> that includes the first axis <b>16</b> and is parallel to and above the third axis <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the second laser beam <b>33</b> is next turned by a first 90° beam bender <b>35</b>. The first 90° beam bender <b>35</b> is adjustably mounted to the first stage frame <b>18</b> by a beam bender support <b>36</b>. The first 90° beam bender <b>35</b> may be adjusted by well known methods to turn the second laser beam <b>33</b> through a 90° angle and keep it in the plane <b>34</b> defined above. The second laser beam <b>33</b> then passes on to a second laser interferometer <b>37</b>. The second laser interferometer <b>37</b> may be assembled using well known methods so that third and forth measurement beams <b>38</b> and <b>39</b>, respectively, exit at a 90° angle to the incoming second laser beam <b>33</b>. The second laser interferometer <b>37</b> may be adjustably mounted to the second (X) stage <b>19</b> by well known means. The second laser interferometer <b>37</b> may be adjusted by well known methods so that the third measurement beam <b>38</b> exits in the plane <b>34</b> and parallel to the third (Y) axis <b>30</b>. A plane mirror <b>40</b> may be adjustably mounted to the third (Y) stage <b>31</b> by well known means. The plane mirror <b>40</b> may be adjusted using well known methods so that both the third and fourth measurement beams <b>38</b> and <b>39</b> return along their respective axes and parallel to the third axis <b>30</b>. After the fourth measurement beam <b>39</b> returns to the second laser interferometer <b>37</b>, it is deflected through a 90° angle and returns to a second optical fiber receiver <b>41</b> as a measurement signal. This measurement signal may be converted to position and velocity data by control electronics (not shown), which may be supplied by Hewlett Packard or Zygo.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">This arrangement of first and second laser beams <b>20</b> and <b>33</b>, beam splitter <b>32</b>, beam bender <b>35</b>, interferometers <b>21</b> and <b>37</b>, and plane mirrors <b>22</b> and <b>40</b> with respect to the three axes <b>16</b>, <b>26</b>, and <b>30</b> enables accurate laser measurement of the linear motion of the second (X) axis <b>26</b> and third (Y) axis <b>30</b> through a full range of travel of the first (tilt) axis <b>16</b> without loss of signal or false motion detection.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A</figref>, <b>5</b>B, <b>6</b> and <b>7</b> show how a fourth (Z) axis of motion <b>50</b> is added to the above system. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, the fourth axis of motion <b>50</b> is provided by crossed roller bearings <b>51</b> and <b>52</b> mounted to the right structural support member <b>12</b> and a fourth (Z) stage <b>53</b>. The crossed roller bearings <b>51</b> and <b>52</b> may be adjusted by well known methods so that the fourth axis of motion <b>50</b> is perpendicular to the first axis <b>16</b> and perpendicular to the plane <b>34</b> when the plane <b>34</b> is in a horizontal position. The fourth stage <b>53</b> may carry a right rotational element <b>14</b>. In this manner, the fourth axis of motion <b>50</b> can move the right rotational element <b>14</b> in a vertical axis. It should be understood that other low friction bearing elements, such as ball bearings, flexures or gas bearings, can be used to couple the fourth stage <b>53</b> to the right structural support member <b>12</b> in a manner that permits motion of the fourth stage <b>53</b>, as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, the first laser beam <b>20</b> exits through the right structural support member <b>12</b> at the second 90° beam bender <b>54</b>, which may be adjustably attached to right structural support member <b>12</b> by well known means. The second 90° beam bender <b>54</b> may be adjusted by well known methods so that it directs the first laser beam <b>20</b> to a third 90° beam bender <b>55</b>. The third 90° beam bender <b>55</b> may be adjustably attached to the right structural support member <b>12</b> by well known means. The third 90° beam bender <b>55</b> may be adjusted by well known methods so that the first laser beam <b>20</b> exits the third 90° beam bender <b>55</b> both parallel to a fourth (Z) axis <b>50</b> and directly through the first (tilt) axis <b>16</b>. In this manner, the fourth (Z) axis of motion <b>50</b>, which carries the right rotational element <b>14</b>, may be moved vertically while keeping the first laser beam <b>20</b> on the first axis <b>16</b>. A fourth 90° beam bender <b>56</b> may be adjustably attached by well known means to the fourth stage <b>53</b>. The fourth 90° beam bender <b>56</b> may be adjusted by well known methods so that the first laser beam <b>20</b> exits the fourth <b>900</b> beam bender <b>56</b> on and parallel to the first axis <b>16</b>. In this manner, the arrangement of beams and components described earlier is maintained even when the fourth (Z) axis of motion <b>50</b> is added to the system.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is an enlarged view that shows the first laser beam <b>20</b> coming from below, parallel to the fourth (Z) axis <b>50</b>, entering the fourth 90° beam bender <b>56</b>, where it is bent through a 90° angle to emerge on and parallel to the first (tilt) axis <b>16</b>, as described above. The fourth 90° beam bender <b>56</b> may be adjustably attached to the fourth (Z) stage <b>53</b>, so that it moves in the fourth axis <b>50</b> but does not rotate when the first axis <b>16</b> is moved. Shown in dashed lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is also the first 50:50 beam splitter <b>32</b>, which is behind the fourth 90° beam bender <b>56</b> in this view. The first 50:50 beam splitter <b>32</b> is shown rotated around the first axis <b>16</b> by an arbitrary angle. The second laser beam <b>33</b> is also shown exiting from the first 50:50 beam bender parallel to the third (Y) axis <b>30</b>, as described above. In this manner, the needed beam relationships are set-up and maintained as each axis moves.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, laser metering for the fourth (Z) axis <b>50</b> is provided on the inside of the right structural support member <b>12</b>. An original (i.e., source) laser beam <b>57</b> (not shown here but discussed below in reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 9</figref>) enters the system from the right rear side. This beam <b>57</b> is turned 90° by a fifth 90° beam bender <b>58</b> so that the original laser beam <b>57</b> travels parallel to the inside surface of the right structural support member <b>12</b>. A second 50:50 beam splitter <b>59</b> divides the original laser beam <b>57</b> into two equal strength beams. One of these beams is deflected through 90° and passes through the right structural support member <b>12</b> to become the first laser beam <b>20</b>. The other beam passes through the second 50:50 beam splitter <b>59</b> and into a third 50:50 beam splitter <b>60</b>. The third 50:50 beam splitter <b>60</b> divides the beam into two equal strength beams. A third laser beam <b>61</b> exits parallel to the inside surface of right structural support member <b>12</b>. A fourth laser beam <b>62</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>) exits horizontally and at 90° to the third laser beam <b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The third laser beam <b>61</b> passes on to a third laser interferometer <b>63</b>. The third laser interferometer <b>63</b> may be assembled using well known methods so that the fifth and sixth measurement beams <b>64</b> and <b>65</b> exit at a 90° angle to the incoming third laser beam <b>61</b>. The third laser interferometer <b>63</b> may be adjustably attached to an inside base of the right structural support member <b>12</b> by well known means. The third laser interferometer <b>63</b> may be adjusted by well known methods so that the fifth measurement beam <b>64</b> exits parallel to the fourth (Z) axis <b>50</b>. A plane mirror <b>66</b> may be adjustably attached by well known means to the fourth stage <b>53</b>, which extends through the right structural support member <b>12</b>. The plane mirror <b>66</b> may be adjusted using well known methods so that both the fifth and sixth measurement beams <b>64</b> and <b>65</b> return along their respective axes and parallel to the fourth axis <b>50</b>. After the sixth measurement beam <b>65</b> returns to the third laser interferometer <b>63</b>, it is deflected through a 90° angle and returns to a third optical fiber receiver <b>67</b> as a measurement signal. This measurement signal may be converted to position and velocity data by control electronics (not shown), which may be supplied by Hewlett Packard or Zygo.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The left structural support member <b>13</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a mirror image copy of the right structural support member <b>12</b>. It has a fifth axis of motion <b>68</b>, also referred to herein as the second (or left) Z-axis <b>68</b>, and a fifth (second Z) stage <b>69</b>, which are constructed and assembled as described above for the fourth (Z) axis of motion <b>50</b>. Like the fourth axis of motion <b>50</b>, the fifth axis of motion <b>68</b> may be set-up by well known methods to be perpendicular to the first axis <b>16</b> and perpendicular to the plane <b>34</b> described above, when the plane <b>34</b> is in a horizontal position. In this manner, the fourth axis <b>50</b> and the fifth axis <b>68</b> are also set parallel to each other. A fifth stage <b>69</b> may carry a left rotational element <b>15</b>. In this manner, the left rotational element <b>15</b> may be moved in the fifth (second Z) axis of motion <b>68</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">A fourth laser beam <b>62</b> passes horizontally across the base of the motion system <b>29</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> to the left structural support member <b>13</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. A sixth 90° beam bender <b>71</b> turns the fourth laser beam <b>62</b> so that it passes parallel to the inside surface of the left structural support member <b>13</b> to a fourth laser interferometer <b>72</b>. The fourth laser interferometer <b>72</b> may be assembled using well known methods so that seventh and eighth measurement beams <b>73</b> and <b>74</b> exit at a 90° angle to the incoming fourth laser beam <b>62</b>. The fourth laser interferometer <b>72</b> may be adjustably attached to the inside base of the left structural support member <b>13</b> by well known means. The fourth laser interferometer <b>72</b> may be adjusted by well known methods so that the seventh measurement beam <b>73</b> exits parallel to the fifth (second Z) axis of motion <b>68</b>. A plane mirror <b>75</b> may be adjustably attached by well known means to the fifth stage <b>69</b>, which extends through the left structural support member <b>13</b>. The plane mirror <b>75</b> may be adjusted using well known methods so that both seventh and eighth measurement beams <b>73</b> and <b>74</b> return along their respective axes and parallel to the fifth axis of motion <b>68</b>. After the eighth measurement beam <b>74</b> returns to the fourth laser interferometer <b>72</b>, it is deflected through a 90° angle and returns to a fourth optical fiber receiver <b>76</b> as a measurement signal. This measurement signal may be converted to position and velocity data by control electronics (not shown), which may be supplied by Hewlett Packard or Zygo.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> provides a perspective view of the full laser system just described. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows most, but not all, of the laser system mounted on the multi-axis motion system <b>29</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. These drawings are provided to add clarity to the detailed description provided above. The incoming, original (i.e., source), laser beam <b>57</b>, which has been mentioned but not shown in reference to prior presented figures, is shown in both <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 9</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Measurement signals from the third laser interferometer <b>63</b> and the fourth laser interferometer <b>72</b> are used to provide feedback control to two independent drive motors, a fourth axis drive motor <b>81</b> and a fifth axis drive motor <b>82</b>, which drive the fourth stage <b>53</b> and the fifth stage <b>69</b>, respectively, using well known or custom servo-control methods. In this manner, the first axis <b>16</b> can be moved linearly in a vertical direction without disturbing the relationships established for the first laser beam <b>20</b>, the fourth 90° beam bender <b>56</b>, and the first axis <b>16</b>. As a result, three linear (X, Y, and Z) axes of laser metered motion are provided throughout a full rotation of the first axis <b>16</b> and throughout a full range of linear travel in the second (X) axis <b>26</b>, the third (Y) axis <b>30</b>, and the fourth (first Z) and fifth (second Z) axes <b>50</b> and <b>68</b>, which act together as one linear (Z) axis.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows a sixth axis of motion <b>84</b>, also referred to herein as the object rotation axis <b>84</b>, which may be mounted in the third (Y) stage <b>31</b>. The sixth (object rotation) axis of motion <b>84</b> is set perpendicular to the first axis <b>16</b> and perpendicular to the plane <b>34</b>. The sixth axis of motion <b>84</b> may carry an object carrier <b>85</b>. In this embodiment, the object carrier <b>85</b> is set perpendicular to the sixth axis <b>84</b> and is therefore parallel to the plane <b>34</b>. The sixth axis <b>84</b> can rotate through 360° of motion when driven by a sixth axis drive motor <b>89</b>. The sixth axis drive motor <b>89</b> may be a commercial stepper motor or another type of motor. This motor <b>89</b> may be coupled to the object carrier <b>85</b> using commercially available drives, such as a harmonic reduction gear, drive parts, and rotary bearings. In this manner, the object <b>3</b>, generally a silicon wafer, can be rotated into a desired orientation for observing, repairing, or otherwise processing sites of interest on the object <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the object carrier <b>85</b> is shown in a loading position. Well known robotic means may be used to move the object <b>3</b> to the object carrier <b>85</b>. A sliding edge gripper <b>86</b> may be spring loaded. The sliding edge gripper <b>86</b> may be pushed towards the rear of the motion system <b>29</b> by a loading robot. As the loading robot withdraws, the object <b>3</b> is pressed against two fixed edge grippers <b>87</b> by a spring (not shown) in the sliding edge gripper <b>86</b>. The edge grippers <b>86</b> and <b>87</b> can be designed using well known techniques to provide top, center, or bottom reference of the object <b>3</b> in the object carrier <b>85</b>. Generally, a top reference is preferred. The reference surfaces (e.g., top reference) are set so that the object <b>3</b> is parallel to the plane <b>34</b>. When top referencing is provided, the top surface is therefore in the plane <b>34</b> and on the first axis <b>16</b>. This arrangement provides navigation benefits, which are further explained below in reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Very accurate and fine control of the motion system <b>29</b> requires careful attention to an aggregate center of gravity of the full motion system <b>29</b>. The aggregate center of gravity preferably remains on the first axis <b>16</b> as all motions move through their full ranges of travel. This arrangement provides the best possible control and the minimum possible vibration at all sites of interest. In some embodiments, the aggregate center of gravity is within a given tolerance (e.g., ±1 inch) of the first axis <b>16</b>, but, as understood in the art, requires more power, more powerful motors, and more control than when the aggregate center of gravity is on the first axis <b>16</b>. How the aggregate center of gravity can be designed to be on the first axis <b>16</b> in the preferred embodiment is described immediately below.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The object carrier <b>85</b> incorporates a counterbalance mass <b>91</b>. The counterbalance mass <b>91</b> is designed to exactly offset the weight of the sliding edge gripper <b>86</b>, so that the center of gravity of the object carrier <b>85</b> is on the center of the sixth axis of motion <b>84</b>. This arrangement assures no motion of the center of gravity of this assembly as the sixth axis of motion <b>84</b> moves through its full range of travel.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows how a stationary center of gravity is maintained for the third (Y) axis of motion <b>30</b>. As the third axis drive motor <b>47</b> moves the third (Y) stage <b>31</b>, a cable <b>48</b> drives a counterweight <b>49</b> in the opposite direction of the third stage <b>31</b>. The weight of counterweight <b>49</b> matches that of third stage <b>31</b> and all of the parts mounted thereon, such as the sixth (object rotation) axis of motion <b>84</b>, object carrier <b>85</b>, and object <b>3</b>. In this manner, the aggregate center of gravity of the third axis of motion <b>30</b> remains stationary throughout its full range of travel.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows a relationship of all six axes of motion to the first axis <b>16</b> and shows that the aggregate center of gravity is in fact directly on the first axis <b>16</b>. By placing the first stage <b>17</b> above the first axis <b>16</b>, the center of gravity is first above the first axis <b>16</b>. Then, the second axis <b>26</b>, second stage <b>19</b>, third axis <b>30</b>, third stage <b>31</b>, and sixth axis <b>84</b>, including the sixth axis drive motor <b>89</b> and object carrier <b>85</b>, are placed below the first axis <b>16</b>. This arrangement lowers the aggregate center of gravity to be nearly on the first axis <b>16</b>. A set of trim weights <b>92</b>, which can be machined to the correct weight, are then added to the first stage <b>17</b> below the first axis <b>16</b> to achieve an exact coincidence of the aggregate center of gravity and the first axis <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">Since the second (X) axis of motion <b>26</b> moves exactly parallel to the first axis <b>16</b>, the aggregate center of gravity moves left or right with the second axis of motion <b>26</b>, but remains on the first axis <b>16</b>. This shift does not harm fine control of the motion system <b>29</b>. The fourth (first Z) axis of motion <b>50</b> and fifth (second Z) axis of motion <b>68</b> are individually driven, as has been explained above. This arrangement of the vertical motion control enables fine control of the vertical position as the aggregate center of gravity moves slightly left and right of center.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Note also in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> that the preferred embodiment places the top surface of the object <b>3</b> exactly on the first axis <b>16</b>. This arrangement provides a eucentric motion system <b>29</b>, namely one that holds the surface of the object <b>3</b> and all sites of interest on the surface of object <b>3</b> at a focal point of the column <b>5</b> as the first axis <b>16</b>, second axis <b>26</b>, third axis <b>30</b>, and sixth axis <b>84</b> move through their full ranges of motion.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, calibration artifacts <b>93</b> are mounted on the second stage <b>19</b> and on the third stage <b>31</b> exactly at the height of the first axis <b>16</b>. When the third axis <b>30</b> moves to a proper position, the calibration artifacts <b>93</b> can be directly on the first axis <b>16</b>. The calibration artifacts <b>93</b> can then be used to set-up the focus of the column <b>5</b> or to verify that the focus is still set-up properly during use of the system. In this manner, proper synchronization of the column setup and the motion setup is achieved. Calibration artifacts <b>93</b> may also have detectable marks on their surfaces that can be used to establish a navigation origin for the second (X) axis <b>26</b> and third (Y) axis <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Many applications include another metrology system <b>94</b>, such as an autofocus or height sensor. Initially, this can be synchronized to the setup height of the calibration artifacts <b>93</b>. Thereafter, this sensor can be used to return the fourth (first Z) axis <b>50</b> and the fifth (second Z) axis <b>68</b> to the original setup height.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The other metrology system <b>94</b> can also be used to track sag of the object <b>3</b> and to command the fourth axis <b>50</b> and the fifth axis <b>68</b> to keep the top surface of object <b>3</b> at the focus point of the column <b>5</b>. In this manner, very precise and accurate observation, repair, or other processing use can be performed even on unflat objects.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, an alignment sensor <b>95</b> is shown attached to a side of the first stage frame <b>18</b> of the first stage <b>17</b>. After loading a new object <b>3</b>, the second axis of motion <b>26</b> and third axis of motion <b>30</b> move the object <b>3</b> to the alignment sensor <b>95</b>. The alignment sensor <b>95</b> may be a notch finder, for example. In such cases, the sixth axis <b>84</b> rotates the object <b>3</b> slowly until the notch finder locates both edges of a notch that has been previously fabricated in the edge of the object <b>3</b> for use in orienting the object <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">To align the notch, stepper motor counts from the sixth axis drive motor <b>89</b> may be tracked and recorded by the controller <b>115</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>) each edge of the notch. A center count for the notch center may be calculated by the controller <b>115</b>. Using a priori data for the process being used, the object <b>3</b> can then be rotated to the proper orientation for observing, repairing, or otherwise processing sites of interest on the object <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">For the preferred embodiment, it is anticipated that most use will involve frequent motion of the second (X) axis <b>26</b>, the third (Y) axis <b>30</b>, the fourth (first Z) axis <b>50</b> and the fifth (second Z) axis <b>68</b> (acting together as a single Z-axis), and the sixth (object rotation) axis <b>84</b>. The first axis <b>16</b> will likely be moved infrequently and set. For example, during orientation and alignment of the object <b>3</b>, rotation around the first axis <b>16</b> can be set so that the object <b>3</b> is horizontal, normal to the axis of column <b>5</b>. Once the sites of interest (e.g., patterns) on the object <b>3</b> have been precisely located, the first stage <b>17</b> is moved to a predetermined (tilt) angle by the first axis drive motor <b>45</b>. Once first stage <b>17</b> reaches a desired angle about the first axis <b>16</b>, the first stage <b>17</b> may be gently clamped at this angle. Through use of this gentle clamping, navigation in the other axes is improved, and vibration is significantly reduced. For this purpose, referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>, immobilization mechanism(s) <b>100</b> are provided on both the right rotational element <b>14</b> and the left rotational element <b>15</b>. As can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>, the immobilization mechanism(s) <b>100</b> have a belt <b>101</b> that wraps around a smooth surface <b>104</b>. A spring <b>102</b> normally pulls the belt <b>101</b> tightly against the smooth surface <b>104</b> so that the rotation member <b>15</b> is gently immobilized. When the rotation member <b>15</b> is to be moved, a solenoid <b>103</b> is energized. The solenoid <b>103</b> is arranged so that its mechanical action compresses the spring <b>102</b> and releases the grip of the belt <b>101</b> on the smooth surface <b>104</b>. In this manner, the rotation member <b>15</b> is made free to move (i.e., rotate for tilt).</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">While a single structural support member <b>12</b> and a single rotational element <b>14</b> can be used to define the first axis <b>16</b>, the preferred embodiment incorporates both a right structural support member <b>12</b> and a left structural support member <b>13</b>, as can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. In this case, it is useful to allow for expansion and contraction of a distance between the two structural support members <b>12</b> and <b>13</b> due to temperature changes. As a practical matter, some allowance for assembly errors and parts errors is also needed for this distance. The right rotational element <b>14</b> may be mounted in the right structural support member <b>12</b> so that it is fixed according to conventional mechanical design practice. But, the left rotational element <b>15</b> may be variably coupled to the left structural support member <b>13</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> shows that two commercial ball bearings <b>105</b> separated by a spacer <b>106</b> may be allowed to move parallel to the first axis <b>16</b> a small distance inside a housing <b>107</b>. In this embodiment, a precision radial flexure <b>108</b> presses against an outer race of ball bearings <b>105</b> with a variable force. Three adjustment screws <b>109</b> may be used to adjust this force. Three corresponding access holes <b>110</b> may be provided to measure a compression distance caused by adjusting the three screws <b>109</b>. The relationship between compressed distance and force may be determined for the precision radial flexure <b>108</b> prior to assembly. By measuring the compression distance through the access holes <b>110</b> as the adjustment screws <b>109</b> are moved, the amount of force applied to the ball bearings <b>105</b> can be set to the desired amount. In this manner, the left rotational element <b>15</b> may be variably coupled to the left structural support member <b>13</b>, and slight errors or changes in the distance between the two structural support members <b>12</b> and <b>13</b> can be accommodated.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">It should be understood that, while ball bearings have been shown here, other forms of bearings, such as gas bearings, may also be used to provide a variable coupling of either rotational element to its respective structural support member. Similarly, other forms of the precision radial flexure <b>108</b> are possible, such as adjustable gas pressure or a set of properly arranged linear flexures.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">The arrangement of parts and laser beams described above incorporates a useful design tradeoff. Best practice in most stage interferometer designs is to place the first interferometer <b>21</b> on the lower (inside) side of the vacuum chamber top plate and to place the plane mirror <b>22</b> on the object holder <b>85</b>. In this manner, most errors in the mechanical structure and motions that are between the column <b>5</b> and the object <b>3</b> are measured directly. Similarly, the beam splitter <b>32</b> may be attached to the lower (inside) side of the vacuum chamber top plate to add an additional axis of stage interferometry. But, in this arrangement, the rotation of the first axis <b>16</b> quickly interrupts laser beams needed for stage interferometry. To make stage interferometry work with a large range of tilt motion, the novel arrangements of parts and laser beams described herein or their equivalents are employed.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">The arrangements of parts and beams described herein does not measure some small motion errors that may occur and may need to be discovered and corrected in order to obtain more accurate navigation with the multi-axis motion system <b>29</b>. For example, the first interferometer <b>21</b> measures motion of the second stage <b>19</b> in the second (X) axis <b>26</b>. But, very small motions in the direction of the second (X) axis <b>26</b>, due to axial runout in bearings in the right rotational element <b>14</b>, are not measured, since the first interferometer <b>21</b> is attached to the first stage frame <b>18</b>. Similarly, any very small motion(s) in the direction of the second (X) axis <b>26</b> due to small mechanical errors in the right crossed roller bearing <b>42</b> or in the left crossed roller bearing <b>43</b> are not detected because the plane mirror <b>22</b> is attached to the second stage <b>19</b>, not to the object carrier <b>85</b>. There are other similar tradeoffs which should be obvious to one skilled in metrology design.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">To obtain more accurate navigation with the multi-axis system <b>29</b>, two features of this invention are useful. First, bearings and drive trains are preferably preloaded so that random vibration or backlash motion is suppressed or not possible. Second, full counter-weighting of the motions, as has been described above, improves system control. As a result, motion of the multi axis motion system <b>29</b> is very repeatable and very stable. The repeatability and stability of the multi axis motion system <b>29</b> permits calibration and correction of the errors just described. The process used to carry out this calibration and correction is briefly described immediately below.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">Using a very accurate wafer scanning tool or e-beam direct writing tool, a very accurate test pattern, such as a grid of alignment marks, may be generated on the object <b>3</b>. When the patterned object <b>3</b> is placed on the object carrier <b>85</b>, it can be measured by the beam and electronics associated with the column <b>5</b>. A table of error corrections can be generated. Using well known methods, the table of error corrections may be used to improve the accuracy of the multi-axis motion system <b>29</b> to within the limit of its mechanical repeatability and short term stability. The methods of making such a calibration wafer or object <b>3</b>, the methods of measuring it on the object carrier <b>85</b>, and the methods of creating and using the table of error corrections are generally well known in the art. These three steps (making a calibration object, measuring a calibration object, and using the error data to correct navigation) used with the parts and laser beams described herein may be employed to obtain an improved navigation result.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> shows a motion system controller <b>115</b> used to control motion of the object carrier <b>85</b> through use of the stages. The first axis <b>16</b> may use a drive motor <b>45</b> that may be a commercial precision stepper motor. The sixth (object rotation) axis <b>84</b> may use a sixth axis drive motor <b>89</b>, which may also be a commercial precision stepper motor. For these two rotating axes, the controller <b>115</b> may use well known or custom methods to generate micro-stepping phased signals to move the first axis <b>16</b> and the sixth axis <b>84</b> in fine increments of angle. The number of steps moved is used to keep track of where each of these two axes is in its travel. In the preferred embodiment, directly coupled, commercial, harmonic drives are used to move these two axes of rotation. The controller <b>115</b> may include (i) the table of error corrections described above and (ii) the software to apply this table of error corrections to navigation of the multi-axis motion system <b>29</b>. Hardware or firmware (not shown) separate from the controller <b>115</b> optionally in communication with the controller <b>115</b> may also be employed to implement the table of error corrections.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The second axis <b>26</b>, third axis <b>30</b>, fourth axis <b>50</b>, and fifth axis <b>68</b> may all be driven by commercial precision stepper motors (motors <b>46</b>, <b>47</b>, <b>81</b>, <b>82</b>). For these four axes, the first laser interferometer <b>21</b>, second laser interferometer <b>37</b>, third laser interferometer <b>63</b>, and fourth laser interferometer <b>72</b>, respectively, are used to provide feedback to control motion of these axes. Motion control methods, such as single-input single-output (SISO) or multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) feedback control techniques, may be used for these four axes of linear motion and are generally known by those skilled in the art of machine control. In the preferred embodiment, directly coupled, commercial, ball screws and ball nuts may be used to move these four axes of linear motion.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">As was described above, the calibration artifact <b>93</b>, the other metrology system <b>94</b> (e.g., a focus sensor), and the alignment sensor <b>95</b> (e.g., a notch finder) are also connected to the controller <b>115</b> so they may operate with other elements of the control system. Finally, the controller <b>115</b> has connections <b>116</b>, such as internal Ethernet connections, to other control systems <b>117</b>, such as (i) a host computer and/or the column control <b>119</b>, which controls the vacuum system for the column <b>5</b>, (ii) the beam scanning control <b>118</b>, which controls the beam position within the column <b>5</b>, or (iii) the Communications module <b>121</b>, which provides links to a world of data outside this machine, for example in a factory or a remote service location.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">While this invention has been particularly shown and described with references to preferred embodiments thereof, it will be understood by those skilled in the art that various changes in form and details may be made therein without departing from the scope of the invention encompassed by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A system for positioning an object, comprising:
<claim-text>a structural support member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first stage including (i) at least one rotational element coupled to the structural support member and (ii) a frame coupled to the at least one rotational element operable to rotate about a first axis through use of the at least one rotational element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second stage coupled to the first stage, the second stage having an object carrier adapted to move an object in a second axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a laser metrology system including optical elements that are configured to direct a laser beam relative to the first and the second stages and configured (i) to direct the laser beam in a direction substantially on and parallel to the first axis and (ii) to measure a position of the object carrier.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the laser metrology system is further configured to direct the laser beam through the structural support member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the second stage includes an X-stage and a Y-stage and wherein the laser metrology system includes optical elements that direct the laser beam to measure a position of the object carrier in respective X- and Y-axes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including at least one Z-control mechanism that moves the first stage in a Z-axis direction and wherein the laser metrology system is adapted to direct the laser beam in a direction substantially on and parallel to the first axis for all first stage positions on the Z-axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A system for positioning an object, comprising:
<claim-text>a structural support member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first stage including (i) at least one rotational element coupled to the structural support member and (ii) a frame coupled to the at least one rotational element operable to rotate about a first axis through use of the at least one rotational element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second stage coupled to the first stage, the second stage having an object carrier adapted to move an object in a second axis, and an aggregate center of gravity of the first stage and the second stage is within 1 inch of the first axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a laser metrology system including optical elements that are configured to direct a laser beam relative to the first and the second stages and configured (i) to direct the laser beam in a direction substantially on and parallel to the first axis and (ii) to measure a position of the object carrier.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first stage includes a first rotational element and a second rotational element, and wherein the first rotational element is fixedly coupled to the structural support member and the second rotational element is variably coupled to the structural support member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first stage is adapted to rotate greater than one degree.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including an immobilization mechanism coupled to the first stage to restrict motion of the first stage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including an alignment sensor adapted to detect an orientation of the object on the object carrier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including at least one motion control processor coupled to the second stage that causes the second stage to move in a desired manner and wherein the at least one motion control processor receives feedback of the position of the object carrier from the laser metrology system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> further including at least one other metrology system to measure a position of the object carrier or object, and wherein the at least one motion control processor receives feedback from the at least one other metrology system for use in controlling the position of the object carrier or object.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising an interface to communicate position information with a system selected from the group consisting of: an electron beam system, vacuum chamber, ion beam system, laser beam system, automated manufacturing process, and any combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method of positioning an object, comprising:
<claim-text>directing a laser beam relative to first and second stages and in a direction substantially on and parallel to a first axis about which the first stage rotates;</claim-text>
<claim-text>measuring, through use of the laser beam, a position of an object carrier of the second stage, coupled to the first stage, adapted to move an object in a second axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing measurement information associated with the position of the object carrier.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein directing the laser beam includes directing the laser beam through a structural support member to which the first stage is coupled.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein measuring the position of the object carrier includes measuring the position of the object carrier in X- and Y-axes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further including moving the first stage in a Z-axis direction and wherein measuring the position of the object carrier includes directing the laser beam in a direction substantially on and parallel to the first axis for all first stage positions on the Z-axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method of positioning an object, comprising:
<claim-text>directing a laser beam relative to first and second stages and in a direction substantially on and parallel to a first axis about which the first stage rotates;</claim-text>
<claim-text>measuring, through use of the laser beam, a position of an object carrier of the second stage, coupled to the first stage, adapted to move an object in a second axis, and an aggregate center of gravity of the first stage and the second stage is within 1 inch of the first axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing measurement information associated with the position of the object carrier.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further including adjusting a coupling of the first stage to a structural support member at one of two locations at which the first stage is coupled to the structural support member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further including rotating the first stage greater than one degree.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further including immobilizing the first stage to restrict motion of the first stage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further including detecting an orientation of the object on the object carrier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further including feeding back a position of the object carrier and causing the second stage to move in a desired manner based on feedback of the position of the object carrier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> further including measuring a position of the object carrier or object separate from the feeding back of the position of the object carrier and controlling the position of the object carrier or object based on the measured position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising communicating position information with a system selected from the group consisting of: an electron beam system, vacuum chamber, ion beam system, laser beam system, automated manufacturing process, and any combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. A system for positioning an object, comprising:
<claim-text>means for directing a laser beam in a direction substantially on and parallel to a first axis about which a first stage rotates; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for measuring, through use of the laser beam, a position of an object carrier of a second stage, coupled to the first stage, adapted to move an object in a second axis.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
