<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296408-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296408</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10946228</doc-number>
<date>20040921</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>240</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>10</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60522</main-classification>
<further-classification> 60524</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Heat engine</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4230024</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Becker</name>
<date>19801000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 92 131</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4918937</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fineblum</name>
<date>19900400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 62175</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5061391</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Scaringe et al.</name>
<date>19911000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>252 67</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6062023</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kerwin et al.</name>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6694731</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kamen et al.</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>Ordonez, C.A.; Liquid nitrogen fueled, closed Brayton cycle cryogenic heat engine; Energy Conversion and Management; 2000; pp. 331-341, vol. 41 No. 4; Great Britain.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>Chen, N.C.J., &amp; West, C.D.(M); Single-cylinder valveless heat engine; Intersociety Energy Conversion Engineering conference report; Aug. 10-14, 1987; Report #Conf-87080451.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60517</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60518</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60522</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60524</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60526</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 91396</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060059906</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060323</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Pierce</last-name>
<first-name>Michael R.</first-name>
<address>
<street>3465 N. Princess Cir.</street>
<city>Broomfield</city>
<state>CO</state>
<postcode>80020</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Macheledt Bales &amp; Heidmiller, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bales</last-name>
<first-name>Jennifer L.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Hoang</first-name>
<department>3748</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The heart of a heat engine is a reciprocating expansion chamber, which converts heat from a hot fluid into mechanical work. The expansion chamber utilizes a refrigerant in a liquid state as an input, and heats and expands the refrigerant to move pistons and generate work. A high pressure injector injects the liquid refrigerant into the chamber under enough pressure to keep it in a liquid state until it is desirable to have it expand into a gas. A hot fluid is the heat source for the expansion chamber and cold fluid is an output. Another output is the refrigerant, now a hot, low pressure gas. A compressor pressurizes the refrigerant, forming a hot, high pressure gas, and a condenser generates liquid refrigerant and provides it to the pressure injector.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="240.45mm" wi="181.78mm" file="US07296408-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="153.75mm" wi="163.66mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296408-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="205.06mm" wi="162.48mm" file="US07296408-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="141.82mm" wi="127.17mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296408-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="242.57mm" wi="183.39mm" file="US07296408-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="235.54mm" wi="182.37mm" file="US07296408-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="211.92mm" wi="158.07mm" file="US07296408-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="252.73mm" wi="158.24mm" file="US07296408-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to apparatus and methods for converting heat energy into mechanical energy.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The law of conservation of energy states that energy may be transformed from one kind to another, but it cannot be created or destroyed. Further, energy is defined as the ability to do work. Mechanical energy is more convenient for doing work of most kinds, various apparatus for converting heat energy into mechanical energy have been developed. These are generally called “heat engines.”</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The steam engine is an engine in which water is superheated to create high pressure steam, that in turn pressurizes a cylinder containing a piston. The pressure causes the displacement of the piston. The axial motion of the piston translates its energy to a crankshaft that rotates as a result of the piston motion. This results in mechanical work.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The steam turbine also utilizes super heated water vapor to generate mechanical work. The high pressure steam in this system applies a force normal to the turbine fins attached to a rotating armature. Hence the applied force results in the armature rotating.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The Stirling engine is a well known heat engine operating in two general modes during a cycle. In the first mode, the expansion cycle heats the internal gas via an external heat source. The gas expands and moves a first piston. In the second mode, the gas is cooled, retracting a second piston. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (prior art) is a simplified block diagram of one type of Stirling engine <b>100</b>. Like any heat engine it requires a heater <b>102</b> and a cooler <b>104</b>. Engine <b>100</b> has two pistons, a hot piston <b>106</b> and a cold piston <b>108</b> within cylinders <b>110</b> and <b>112</b> respectively. Cylinders <b>110</b>, <b>112</b> contain a working gas which (like all gases) expands when heated and compresses when cooled. Cylinders <b>110</b>, <b>112</b> are connected a regeneration area <b>114</b> which is used to store heat energy during one part of the Stirling cycle and return it to the working gas <b>116</b> in another part of the cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">According to the ideal gas law, PV=nRT, where P is pressure, V is volume, n is the number of moles of gas, R is a gas constant and T is temperature. So temperature is proportional to pressure time volumes. Hence, when a gas is heated it expands if possible, and otherwise the pressure increases.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The Stirling cycle has four phases, Isothermal Compression, Constant Volume Heating, Isothermal Expansion, and Constant Volume Cooling (these phases are somewhat simplified for this explanation). Isothermal Compression occurs as heat is transferred from the hot gas <b>116</b> to a cold sink, and the gas compresses, drawing piston <b>108</b> up from its full capacity. In the present case, the heat is removed by cooler <b>104</b>, perhaps by simply conducting the heat away from the engine. Some heat is also stored in the regenerator <b>114</b> (which might be a network of wires or the like).</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Once cold piston <b>108</b> is in its intermediate position, the Constant Volume Heating phase begins. Cold piston <b>108</b> moves up to its minimum capacity position and then hot piston <b>106</b> moves down to an intermediate position. Gas <b>116</b> hence passes through regenerator <b>114</b> and is heated. Since volume remains the same and the temperature of the gas increases, pressure goes up.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In the third phase, Isothermal Expansion, heater <b>102</b> heats the gas. It expands and moves hot piston <b>106</b> down to its full capacity position. In the Constant Volume Heating phase, hot piston <b>106</b> moves up to its minimum capacity position and then cold piston <b>108</b> moves down to its minimum capacity position, again passing gas <b>116</b> through regenerator <b>114</b>. Heat is passed from the gas to the regenerator, so its pressure and volume both remain constant.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Practical Stirling engines have been built. For example, some submarines use Stirling engines. A recent example of a Stirling engine is described in U.S. patent application Ser. No. 6,062,023 to Kerwin et al. Known Stirling engines generally require an extremely hot heat source (600 to 800 degrees Celsius) and a temperature gradient of at least 400° C. The gases used in these engines, for example Nitrogen and Carbon Dioxide are in the gas phase at all times. Thus, current Stirling engines operate at impractically high temperatures and do not take advantage of the liquid phase of the working gas.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A need remains in the art for improved heat engines that operate at more practical temperatures, do not require extreme heat gradients, and utilize the liquid phase of the refrigerant.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">It is an object of the present invention to provide an improved heat engine.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The heat engine of the present invention operates at practical temperatures and utilizes the liquid phase of the refrigerant. It does not require extreme heat gradients. In addition, the structure of the present heat engine is an improvement.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">A heat engine according to the present invention utilizes a liquid refrigerant and a hot thermal fluid to convert heat into mechanical work. The heat engine comprises (1) an expansion chamber having a piston disposed to execute strokes within a cylinder and a thermal fluid jacket containing the hot thermal fluid and disposed around the cylinder, wherein the expansion chamber heats the liquid refrigerant via heat transfer from the hot thermal fluid in the thermal fluid jacket and allows the refrigerant to expand, the expansion causing the piston to execute strokes and thereby generate work, (2) a dynamic throttling valve for injecting liquid refrigerant into the cylinder adjacent to the piston, wherein the valve injects a minimal flow of liquid refrigerant at the beginning of the piston stroke and a maximal flow as the piston stroke continues, (3) a pressure injector for injecting the liquid refrigerant into dynamic throttling valve under pressure, (4) a compressor for compressing the expanded gas refrigerant from the expansion chamber, and (5) a condenser for returning the compressed gas refrigerant from the compressor to a liquid state for use by the pressure injector.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The thermal fluid might be hot water.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In one preferred embodiment, two expansion chambers are used, and the piston in the second expansion chamber reciprocates with respect to the first. As a feature, the pressure injector includes a magnetically assisted hydraulic element having two paths for the refrigerant with an input three way switch and an output three way switch to channel the refrigerant through paths and increase pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The dynamic throttling valve may comprise a tapered pin at the end of the piston fitting into a tapered opening in the injector and a concave area on the piston surrounding the pin for allowing the minimal flow of refrigerant at the beginning of the stroke.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The fluid jacket preferably includes heat transfer bars and heat transfer rings to increase turbulent flow and maximize heat transfer. The heat transfer bars also extend into the cylinder to transfer heat to the refrigerant. Heat transfer fins extend from the fluid jacket into the cylinder to transfer heat to the refrigerant.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Input hot fluid inlet tubes inject the hot fluid into the fluid jacket and cold fluid outlet tubes remove the cold fluid from the jacket after it has warmed the refrigerant.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Preferably the heat transfer rings are toothed and the fluid passes through the teeth in a turbulent manner. The teeth on a ring are offset from teeth on an adjacent ring. Heat transfer bars pass through teeth on one or more rings. Also, heat transfer bars pass between the heat transfer fins.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (prior art) is a schematic drawing showing a conventional Stirling engine.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the heat engine of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the pressure injector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cutaway schematic diagram illustrating a preferred embodiment of the cylinder portion of the heat engine of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a simplified schematic diagram of the cylinder portion of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> showing the path of working gas and warming liquid in the engine.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an exploded isometric view of the cylinder portion of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a top cutaway view along section line AA of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a top cutaway view along section BB of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">A listing of parts and reference numbers is helpful in understanding the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="2">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="63pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="154pt" align="left"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Ref. No</entry>
<entry>Part</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="2">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="63pt" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="154pt" align="left"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry>Ceramic holder</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry>Ceramic insert</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry>Injector body (jet)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>4</entry>
<entry>Pressure plate outer ring</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>5</entry>
<entry>Pressure plate inner ring</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>6</entry>
<entry>Slip seal</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>7</entry>
<entry>Outer ring cap</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>8</entry>
<entry>Ring seal support</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>9</entry>
<entry>Top ring seal</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>10</entry>
<entry>Slide ring</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>11</entry>
<entry>Inner ring cap</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>12</entry>
<entry>Inner ring O-ring seal</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>13</entry>
<entry>Ring six flat seal</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>14</entry>
<entry>Inner cylinder jet seal A</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>15</entry>
<entry>Inner cylinder jet seal B</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>16</entry>
<entry>Inner cylinder jet</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>17</entry>
<entry>Ring 5 seal</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>18</entry>
<entry>Ring 2 seal</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>19</entry>
<entry>Cylinder main body</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>20</entry>
<entry>Gas exhaust ports (exhaust valves)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>21</entry>
<entry>Heat transfer bars (thermal conducting rods)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>22</entry>
<entry>Heat transfer rings</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>23</entry>
<entry>Heat cylinder fins</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>24</entry>
<entry>Heat cylinder</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>25</entry>
<entry>Hot fluid inlet tubes</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>26</entry>
<entry>Cold fluid outlet tubes</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>27</entry>
<entry>Fluid jacket</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>28</entry>
<entry>Cylinder lower ring seal</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>29</entry>
<entry>Cylinder lower rings</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>30</entry>
<entry>Piston seal</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>31</entry>
<entry>Piston</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>32</entry>
<entry>Piston lower seal capture ring</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>33</entry>
<entry>Piston pin (needle valve pin)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>34</entry>
<entry>Piston connecting rod</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>35</entry>
<entry>Drive linkage</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>36</entry>
<entry>Concave area</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>100</entry>
<entry>Conventional Stirling engine</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>102</entry>
<entry>Heat source</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>104</entry>
<entry>Cold source</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>106</entry>
<entry>Hot piston</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>108</entry>
<entry>Cold piston</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>110</entry>
<entry>Cylinder</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>112</entry>
<entry>Cylinder</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>114</entry>
<entry>Regenerator</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>116</entry>
<entry>Working gas</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>200</entry>
<entry>Heat engine</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>202</entry>
<entry>Reciprocating expansion chamber</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>204</entry>
<entry>Compressor</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>206</entry>
<entry>Condenser</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>208</entry>
<entry>High pressure injector</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>210</entry>
<entry>Refrigerant</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>211</entry>
<entry>Liquid refrigerant</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>212</entry>
<entry>Hot fluid</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>214</entry>
<entry>Work output</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>216</entry>
<entry>Cold fluid</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>218</entry>
<entry>Low pressure hot gas refrigerant</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>220</entry>
<entry>High pressure hot gas refrigerant</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>302</entry>
<entry>Input switch</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>304</entry>
<entry>Output switch</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>306</entry>
<entry>Coil</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>308</entry>
<entry>Coil</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>310</entry>
<entry>Magnet</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>312</entry>
<entry>Control block</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>314</entry>
<entry>Magnetic sleeves</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>316</entry>
<entry>One-way flow restrictor</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Note that the term “refrigerant” is used herein to designate not only traditional refrigerants such as R410-A, freon and the like, but also any suitable substance that has a cooling effect when converted from a liquid state to a gas state.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram that illustrates the entire heat engine assembly <b>200</b>. It shows the cycling of refrigerant <b>210</b> and fluid <b>212</b>. <b>216</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> illustrate reciprocating expansion chamber <b>202</b> in detail. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 through 8</figref> show the details of one cylinder assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating one embodiment of heat engine <b>200</b> of the present invention. Refer also to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 through 8</figref> for more detailed views of reciprocating expansion chamber <b>202</b>. A controlled mass of condensed refrigerant <b>210</b> is injected rapidly by a magnetically assisted hydraulic high pressure dynamic valve piston and injector <b>208</b> into reciprocating expansion chamber <b>202</b>. As shown in the left hand cylinder diagram in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a small amount of liquid refrigerant <b>211</b> trickles out of jet <b>3</b> and up into heat cylinder fins <b>23</b> and heat cylinder bars <b>21</b>. These are warmed by hot fluid <b>212</b>, and so liquid refrigerant <b>211</b> quickly warms and becomes a gas. As refrigerant <b>210</b> expands, it pushes piston <b>31</b> down. See the right hand cylinder diagram in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. This allows more liquid refrigerant <b>211</b> to exit jet <b>3</b> and expand into a gas. As the refrigerant is heated and expanded, the piston in the cylinder fully extends. The exhaust valves then open, and as the second cylinder enters its power stroke, it pushes the vaporized refrigerant <b>218</b> into the suction line of compressor <b>204</b>. The compressor increases the pressure of the vaporized refrigerant and then sends it to condenser <b>206</b>, where the refrigerant is reconstituted into a liquid ready for another cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The heart of heat engine <b>200</b> is reciprocating expansion chamber <b>202</b>, which converts heat from hot fluid <b>212</b> into mechanical work <b>214</b>. Reciprocating expansion chamber <b>202</b> is shown in more detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 through 8</figref>. Chamber <b>202</b> utilizes a refrigerant <b>210</b> such as R410-A or R134 (freon or the like) in a liquid state <b>211</b>. High pressure injector <b>208</b> (shown in more detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) injects refrigerant <b>210</b> into chamber <b>202</b> under enough pressure to keep refrigerant <b>210</b> in a liquid state until it is desirable to have refrigerant <b>210</b> expand into a gas. The expansion of refrigerant <b>210</b> into a gas assists chamber <b>202</b> in generating mechanical work <b>214</b>. Hot fluid <b>212</b> is the heat source for chamber <b>202</b> and cold fluid <b>216</b> is an output. Another output is refrigerant <b>210</b>, now a hot, low pressure gas <b>218</b>. Compressor <b>204</b> pressurizes refrigerant <b>210</b>, forming a hot, high pressure gas <b>220</b>, and condenser <b>206</b> generates liquid refrigerant again.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">One very beneficial use of heat engine <b>200</b> is in the internal combustion engine of a car (not shown). Hot fluid (for example hot water) <b>212</b> can be generated by the car engine, and cold fluid <b>216</b> may in turn be used to cool the engine. Hence, the only extra element the engine needs to provide is the work to compress and condense refrigerant <b>210</b>. As refrigerant <b>210</b> is preferably R410-A or the like, this is easily achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram illustrating a preferred embodiment of pressure injector <b>208</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. A controlled mass of condensed refrigerant <b>210</b> is injected rapidly by magnetically assisted hydraulic high pressure injector <b>208</b> into a cylinder <b>31</b>. Refrigerant <b>210</b> enters 3-way switch <b>302</b>. It exits switch <b>304</b> via one-way flow restrictor <b>316</b>. Control block <b>312</b> controls switches <b>302</b>, <b>304</b> according to the following table.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00002" num="00002">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="5">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="14pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="35pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="63pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="63pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" rowsep="1">TABLE 1</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry>Switch 302</entry>
<entry>Switch 304</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Function</entry>
<entry>Flow Direction</entry>
<entry>Direction</entry>
<entry>Direction</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Pressure</entry>
<entry>A</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Assist</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Pressure</entry>
<entry>B</entry>
<entry>b</entry>
<entry>b</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Assist</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Bypass</entry>
<entry>B</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
<entry>b</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Bypass</entry>
<entry>A</entry>
<entry>b</entry>
<entry>a</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The purpose of the magnetic assist on the high pressure injector is to increase the fluid injection pressure and rate of injection of the fluid into the cylinder. Increasing the fluid pressure helps to ensure that the refrigerant remains a liquid as it is injected, and increasing the rate of injection increases the work done by the engine. Increasing or decreasing the power to the magnetic assist also provides a throttling function.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In use, core <b>310</b> is alternatively pulled toward coil <b>306</b> and coil <b>308</b>. When core <b>310</b> moves towards coil <b>306</b>, it increases the pressure in branch A of the injector. When core <b>310</b> moves towards coil <b>308</b>, it increases the pressure in branch B of the injector. Control block <b>312</b> energizes coil <b>306</b> to attract core <b>310</b> when switch a and b are open. Hence, control block <b>312</b> energizes coil <b>308</b> to attract core <b>310</b> when switch <b>302</b><i>a </i>and switch <b>304</b><i>b </i>are open. Control block <b>312</b> energizes coil <b>306</b> to attract core <b>310</b> when switch <b>302</b><i>b </i>and switch <b>304</b><i>a </i>are open.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cutaway schematic diagram illustrating a preferred embodiment of the reciprocating expansion chamber <b>214</b> of heat engine <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a simplified version of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> designed to show the flow of refrigerant and hot fluid within chamber <b>214</b>. In the specific embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, two pistons <b>31</b> are used, though other configurations using a different number of pistons are also possible. The two pistons <b>31</b> are connected via a drive linkage <b>35</b> such that as one piston goes up, the other goes down. Piston connecting rods <b>34</b> connect pistons <b>30</b> to the drive linkage. Pistons <b>31</b> operate within cylinder main bodies <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In the heat engine of the present invention, heat is transferred to a working gas, or refrigerant, via conduction through the cylinder head and walls. The present invention is structured to maximize the heat transfer. The preferred embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-8</figref> includes heat transfer fins <b>23</b>, bars <b>21</b> and rings <b>22</b> in contact with hot liquid <b>212</b> that is in turbulent flow across the heat transfer elements. Another feature of the present invention is a configuration designed to cause the refrigerant to expand rapidly while it is heated. The gas injection system incorporates an internal dynamic throttle valve composed of the cylinder's thermally insulated input jet <b>3</b> and a needle valve pin <b>33</b> on the piston <b>31</b>. A controlled mass of condensed refrigerant <b>210</b> is injected rapidly by a magnetically assisted hydraulic high pressure injector <b>208</b> into a cylinder <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="h-0005" num="0000">Equation for heat transfer due to conduction:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Q/t−kA(T<sub>hot</sub>−T<sub>cold</sub><sub><sub2>—</sub2></sub><sub>x</sub>)/d<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Where:</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Q=heat transferred in time=t</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">k=thermal conductivity of the conductor</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">A=area</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">T=temperature</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">d=thickness of conductor</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">T<sub>hot</sub>=temperature of the outer surface of tabbed heat ring internal to fluid transport jacket</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">T<sub>cold</sub><sub><sub2>—</sub2></sub><sub>x</sub>=temperature of the internal surface of expansion cylinder, finned heat ring, and outer surface of internal jet</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">Equations for heat transfer due to forced convection:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Q=hA(T<sub>S</sub>−T<sub>∞</sub>)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Where:</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Q=Loss of Thermal energy</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">h=Heat transfer coefficient</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">T<sub>S</sub>=Surface temperature</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">T<sub>∞</sub>=Fluid ambient temperature</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">A=Area of heat element</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The relationship for the forced convection heat transfer coefficient (h) for a cylinder in cross-flow follows a non-dimensional correlation.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>N<sub>NU</sub>=C*(Re)<sup>m</sup>*(Pr)<sup>n </sup><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Where:</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">N<sub>NU</sub>=Nusselt number=(hd)/κ</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">C=Constant</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Pr=Prandtl number=(ρVd)/μ</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">m=Coefficient</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">n=Coefficient</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">h=Heat transfer coefficient</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">d=Sensor diameter</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">κ=Thermal conductivity of fluid</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">μ=Fluid viscosity</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Cp=Specific heat of the fluid</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">ρ=Fluid density</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">V=Fluid velocity</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">ρV=Mass velocity</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">The Prandtl number for gases is approximately 0.7 and does not vary much with  temperature so it is generally dropped from the equations. The heat transfer coefficient (h) is:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>h</i>=(<i>Cκ/d</i>)*(ρ<i>Vd/</i>μ)<sup>m </sup><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">In order to initially keep the refrigerant in a liquid state as it is being injected, the refrigerant is injected into a high pressure and thermally isolated chamber <b>2</b>. Refer to the left hand cylinder diagram in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> as an illustration of the beginning of the cylinder stroke and the right hand diagram for the end of the cylinder stroke. As the refrigerant is injected into the cylinder's input jet chamber maximum back pressure is developed, creating a high pressure region. Incorporated into the cylinder's input jet is a ceramic or thermally isolating polymer insert thermally isolating the refrigerant from the high temperature of the expansion chamber. With the piston at the beginning of its stroke (left hand diagram in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) a limited amount of liquid refrigerant <b>211</b> flows out of jet <b>3</b> and comes in contact with the heat fins <b>23</b> and thermal conducting rods <b>21</b> that pass heat from the external hot fluid <b>212</b> in the fluid jacket <b>27</b> that has been designed for maximum turbulent flow to produce maximum heat conduction to the input jet. The refrigerant boils and high pressure develops. This developing pressure produces a directed force against piston <b>31</b>, causing the piston to move. As the piston moves, the throttle valve opens, causing an increase in volume at the input jet. As a result, the refrigerant expansion rate rapidly increases.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">As the refrigerant continues to be heated, the pressure reaches its maximum, and then decreases in proportion to the increasing volume caused by the piston extending. Thus, the pressure is reduced by the time the piston is fully extended. See the right hand cylinder diagram in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The exhaust valves <b>20</b> then open, and as the second cylinder enters its power stroke, it pushes the vaporizes refrigerant into the suction line of the compressor <b>214</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">In operation, refrigerant <b>210</b> enters injector <b>3</b> from high pressure injector <b>208</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Ceramic holder <b>1</b> and ceramic insert <b>2</b> act as thermal isolation. As piston <b>31</b> moves downward, Pin <b>33</b> retracts from inner cylinder jet <b>16</b> and refrigerant <b>210</b> is able to enter cylinder <b>19</b>. Hot fluid <b>212</b> heats up refrigerant <b>210</b> and converts it from a fluid into a gas. Refrigerant <b>210</b> continues to expand as piston <b>31</b> moves down, and hence converts into a gas more quickly. As refrigerant <b>210</b> expends, it forces piston <b>31</b> to move the rest of the way down, and this is the portion of the cycle that provides mechanical work. Hot fluid <b>212</b> warms refrigerant <b>210</b> as follows. Hot fluid <b>212</b> enters fluid jacket <b>27</b> via hot fluid inlet tubes <b>25</b>. Hot fluid <b>212</b> circulates through and around heat transfer bars <b>21</b> and heat transfer rings <b>22</b>. As heat from hot fluid <b>212</b> is conducted into the expansion chamber and warms refrigerant <b>210</b>, the heat loss from hot fluid <b>212</b> turns hot fluid <b>212</b> into cold fluid <b>216</b>, and exits via cold fluid outlet tubes <b>26</b>. In addition, cylinder <b>24</b> includes heat fins <b>23</b> which also assist in quickly heating up refrigerant <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">As piston <b>31</b> moves back upward, the vaporized compound gas refrigerant <b>210</b>, now in its low pressure, hot gas phase <b>218</b>, exits gas exhaust ports <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">Returning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the preferred embodiment of reciprocating expansion chamber <b>202</b> will now be described in more detail.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an exploded isometric view of the cylinder assembly portion of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. This view better shows fins <b>23</b> of cylinder <b>24</b>, as well as heat transfer bars <b>21</b> and heat transfer rings <b>22</b> on the exterior of cylinder <b>19</b> and inside of fluid jacket <b>27</b>. Note that rings <b>22</b> are preferably toothed or crenulated as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, in order to allow fluid <b>212</b> to circulate around and among the teeth in a turbulent manner. The teeth on each ring are preferably offset from the teeth on an adjacent ring.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">This figure also shows the locations and spacing of gas exhaust ports <b>20</b>, hot fluid inlet tubes <b>25</b>, and cold fluid outlet tubes <b>26</b>. Cylinder lower ring <b>29</b> and cylinder lower ring seal <b>28</b> are positions at the bottom of water jacket <b>27</b>. Piston <b>31</b> comprises piston pin <b>33</b>, piston seal <b>30</b>, piston lower seal capture ring <b>32</b>, and piston connecting rod <b>34</b>. When the cylinder assembly is put together, jet <b>16</b> is inside of cylinder <b>24</b>, which is inside the top portion of cylinder body <b>19</b>. Water jacket <b>27</b> is outside of cylinder body <b>19</b>. Piston <b>31</b> is inside cylinder body <b>19</b>, with pin <b>33</b> fitted to the inside of jet <b>16</b> when the piston is in the uppermost position.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a top cutaway view along section line <b>7</b>-<b>7</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. This view shows gas exhaust ports <b>20</b>, a section of jet <b>16</b>, with its ceramic insert <b>2</b>, jet seal <b>15</b> and inner ring cap <b>11</b>. Cylinder <b>24</b> and its fins <b>23</b> are below section <b>7</b>-<b>7</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a top cutaway view along section <b>8</b>-<b>8</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. At this level, water jacket <b>27</b> is intersected and a set of heat transfer bars <b>21</b> are seen along with a set of heat transfer rings <b>22</b>. Fins <b>24</b> are also seen, interspersed with bars <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">Those skilled in the art will appreciate that various modifications to the exemplary embodiments are within the scope of the patent.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A heat engine which utilizes a liquid refrigerant and a hot thermal fluid to convert heat into mechanical work, the heat engine comprising:
<claim-text>an expansion chamber having a piston disposed to execute strokes within a cylinder and a thermal fluid jacket containing the hot thermal fluid and disposed around the cylinder, wherein the expansion chamber heats the liquid refrigerant via heat transfer from the hot thermal fluid in the thermal fluid jacket and allows the refrigerant to expand, the expansion causing the piston to execute strokes and thereby generate work;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic throttling valve for injecting liquid refrigerant into the cylinder adjacent to the piston, wherein the valve injects a minimal flow of liquid refrigerant at the beginning of the piston stroke and a maximal flow as the piston stroke continues;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pressure injector for injecting the liquid refrigerant into dynamic throttling valve under pressure;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a compressor for compressing the expanded gas refrigerant from the expansion chamber; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a condenser for returning the compressed gas refrigerant from the compressor to a liquid state for use by the pressure injector.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The heat engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the thermal fluid is hot water.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The heat engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a second expansion chamber, the piston in the second expansion chamber constructed and arranged to reciprocate with respect to the first.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The heat engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the pressure injector comprises a magnetically assisted hydraulic element and includes two paths for the refrigerant with an input three way switch and an output three way switch to channel the refrigerant through paths and increase pressure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The heat engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the fluid jacket includes heat transfer bars and heat transfer rings to increase turbulent flow and maximize heat transfer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The heat engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the heat transfer bars also extend into the cylinder to transfer heat to the refrigerant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The heat engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further including heat transfer fins extending from the fluid jacket into the cylinder to transfer heat to the refrigerant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The heat engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the dynamic throttling valve comprises a tapered pin at the end of the piston fitting into a tapered opening in the injector and a concave area on the piston surrounding the pin for allowing the minimal flow of refrigerant at the beginning of the stroke.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The heat engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including input hot fluid inlet tubes for injecting the hot fluid into the fluid jacket and cold fluid outlet tubes for removing the cold fluid from the jacket after it has warmed the refrigerant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A dynamic throttling valve for use with a piston and cylinder comprising:
<claim-text>an injector for injecting liquid refrigerant into the cylinder adjacent to an end of the piston, the injector having a tapered opening;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tapered pin at the end of the piston fitting into the tapered opening in the injector; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a concave area formed on the piston surrounding the pin for allowing a minimal flow of refrigerant at the beginning of a piston stroke;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the valve injects a minimal flow of liquid refrigerant at the beginning of the piston stroke and a maximal flow as the piston stroke continues.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> joined to a high pressure injector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the refrigerant expands into a gas in the cylinder and further including a compressor and condenser to return the refrigerant to a liquid state for reuse.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further including a conduction and forced convection element for heating the refrigerant in the cylinder.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A heat transfer system for use with a piston and cylinder comprising:
<claim-text>a thermal fluid jacket containing a hot thermal fluid and disposed around the cylinder;</claim-text>
<claim-text>heat transfer bars and heat transfer rings within the fluid jacket to increase turbulent flow of the thermal liquid;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the heat transfer bars extending into the cylinder to conduct heat into the cylinder; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>heat transfer fins extending from the fluid jacket into the cylinder to convect heat into the cylinder.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The heat transfer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further including a working gas in the cylinder which is warmed by the transferred heat.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The heat transfer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the refrigerant is converted from a liquid form to a gas form by the transferred heat and expansion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The heat transfer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the heat transfer rings are toothed and the fluid passes through the teeth in a turbulent manner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The heat transfer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein the teeth on a ring are offset from teeth on an adjacent ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The heat transfer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein heat transfer bars pass through teeth on one or more rings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The heat transfer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein heat transfer bars pass between the heat transfer fins.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
