<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297009-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297009</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11483766</doc-number>
<date>20060711</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>4</main-group>
<subgroup>60</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439212</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Protective plate kit for cables and the like</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4249353</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Berry</name>
<date>19810200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4419535</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>O'Hara</name>
<date>19831200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>D275831</doc-number>
<kind>S</kind>
<name>Legerius et al.</name>
<date>19841000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4936064</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gibb</name>
<date>19900600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5122069</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Brownlie et al.</name>
<date>19920600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439131</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5184793</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Heidt</name>
<date>19930200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5350316</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Van Wagener et al.</name>
<date>19940900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439460</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5417019</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Marshall et al.</name>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6353180</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>DeBartolo et al.</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>174483</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6483028</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>DeBartolo et al.</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>174483</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7082729</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Cole et al.</name>
<date>20060800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 522208</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7128585</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Evilsizer</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439120</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0221646</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Evilsizer</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439120</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>15</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439212</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439120</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439131</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 94</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439535</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439637</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439536</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439537</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439538</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 52232</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174505</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248 56</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gormerley</last-name>
<first-name>Holmes J.</first-name>
<address>
<street>7 Affirmed La.</street>
<city>Howell</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<postcode>07731</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Prasad</last-name>
<first-name>Chandrika</first-name>
<department>2839</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A kit includes a trim plate that has rigid sections arranged end-to-end, defining a cavity within an inner perimeter thereof. Each section has a corresponding beveled edge outwardly sloping away from the inner perimeter. A core member has a unitary body formed from deformably resilient material and is registered between the rigid sections, beneath the floor surface. Mounting flanges are aligned along the inner perimeter of the trim plate and abuts the outer perimeter of the core member. Each mounting flange has ribs that inwardly protrude into the core member and extend along an entire length thereof. The ribs are coupled with the core member so that same is prohibited from downwardly traveling beneath the floor surface. Computer cables pass through the core member, causing same to expand against the mounting flanges and constrict air gaps created within the core member when the cables are passed below the floor surface.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="171.79mm" wi="422.40mm" file="US07297009-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="203.88mm" wi="172.04mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297009-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="231.65mm" wi="173.23mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297009-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Not Applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR DEVELOPMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Not Applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">REFERENCE TO A MICROFICHE APPENDIX</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Not Applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">1. Technical Field</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">This invention relates to a protective plate kit and, more particularly, to a protective plate kit for cables and the like for providing a barrier through which cables are channeled from one room to another room.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">2. Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">During construction of buildings, it is necessary to provide openings through the building floors and walls to permit the running of piping, conduits, and cable systems. Many different types of fitting and coupling devices have been used for this purpose. These devices have varied from simple removable forms to permanently installed boxes and housings of complex design.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It has become known heretofore to use devices for feeding or passing cables through walls which are formed with openings corresponding to the size of the cables and, if necessary or desirable, have sealing means in order to provide protection against dust and water. However, such devices provide no means for protection against fire, or for maintaining the integrity of a firewall already in place.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Generally, however, whether of simple or complex design, the currently available devices are often very labor intensive. Their labor intensive nature is particularly evident during the installation of code required fire-stop materials after the piping and conduit systems have been installed. Typically, it has been necessary to caulk or trowel intumescent materials about the pipes and conduits where they pass through the partition fitting and coupling devices.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Accordingly, a need remains for a protective plate kit for cables and the like in order to overcome the above noted shortcomings. The present invention satisfies such a need by providing a protective plate kit that is easy to install and use, light weight, optimally sized and reasonably priced. Such a protective plate kit for cables and the like will provide a quick seal for the open areas in a floor surface around computer cables and other conduits. The foam present in the kit will further provide protection against fire damage which is greatly appreciated by contractors and individuals responsible for the operation of high-level computer rooms.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In view of the foregoing background, it is therefore an object of the present invention to provide a protective plate kit for cables and the like. These and other objects, features, and advantages of the invention are provided by a kit for providing a barrier through which cables can be directed from one room to another room.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The kit includes a trim plate that has a plurality of rigid sections contiguously arranged end-to-end and spanning across a floor surface such that the rigid sections effectively defines a cavity within an inner perimeter of the rigid sections. Each of the rigid sections has corresponding beveled edges outwardly sloping away from associated ones of the inner perimeters.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A core member has a single and unitary body formed from deformably resilient material. Such a core member is centrally registered between the rigid sections and is disposed beneath the floor surface. The core member is preferably formed from foam rubber and occupies an entire surface area between the inner perimeters of the trim plate.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A plurality of mounting flanges are symmetrically aligned along the inner perimeters of the trim plate and directly abuts the outer perimeter of the core member. Each of the mounting flanges may be removably engageable with the core member and corresponding ones of the rigid sections of the trim plate. Each of the mounting flanges is provided with a plurality of monolithically formed ribs that inwardly protrude into the core member. Such ribs effectively penetrate the core member and extend along an entire vertical length of the core member.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The ribs are coextensively shaped and are directly coupled with the core member in such a manner that the core member is advantageously and effectively prohibited from downwardly traveling beneath the floor surface. A plurality of computer cables are removably passed through the core member, thereby causing the core member to laterally expand against the mounting flanges and constrict air gaps created within the core member when the computer cables are passed below the floor surface and into the core member.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Each of the mounting flanges preferably includes a top surface that is disposed above corresponding ones of the rigid plates. Such mounting flanges have respective longitudinal lengths extending downwardly to a bottom surface of the core member. Each of the mounting flanges may be vertically registered along a vertical plane defined subjacent to the floor surface.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">It is noted the purpose of the foregoing abstract is to enable the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office and the public generally, especially the scientists, engineers and practitioners in the art who are not familiar with patent or legal terms or phraseology, to determine quickly from a cursory inspection the nature and essence of the technical disclosure of the application. The abstract is neither intended to define the invention of the application, which is measured by the claims, nor is it intended to be limiting as to the scope of the invention in any way.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWING</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The novel features believed to be characteristic of this invention are set forth with particularity in the appended claims. The invention itself, however, both as to its organization and method of operation, together with further objects and advantages thereof, may best be understood by reference to the following description taken in connection with the accompanying drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view showing a protective plate kit for cables and the like, in accordance with the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the assembly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, taken along line <b>2</b>-<b>2</b>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The present invention will now be described more fully hereinafter with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which a preferred embodiment of the invention is shown. This invention may, however, be embodied in many different forms and should not be construed as limited to the embodiment set forth herein. Rather, this embodiment is provided so that this application will be thorough and complete, and will fully convey the true scope of the invention to those skilled in the art. Like numbers refer to like elements throughout the figures.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The kit of this invention is referred to generally in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-2</figref> by the reference numeral <b>10</b> and is intended to provide a protective plate for cables and the like. It should be understood that the kit <b>10</b> may be used to protect many different types of structures passing through a wall, such as water lines, and should not be limited to only electrical cables.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Referring initially to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the kit <b>10</b> includes a trim plate <b>20</b> that has a plurality of rigid sections <b>21</b> contiguously arranged end-to-end and spanning across a floor surface <b>11</b> such that the rigid sections <b>21</b> effectively defines a cavity <b>22</b> within an inner perimeter <b>23</b> of the rigid sections <b>21</b>. Each of the rigid sections <b>21</b> has a corresponding beveled edge <b>24</b> outwardly sloping away from associated ones of the inner perimeters <b>23</b>. Such beveled edges <b>24</b> are important for conveniently eliminating any raised surface against which a person may inadvertently strike their foot and trip, or against which other items in the vicinity of the kit <b>10</b> may become caught while being moved across the floor surface <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Again referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, a core member <b>30</b> has a single and unitary body <b>31</b> formed from a deformably resilient material. Of course, the core member <b>30</b> may be produced from a variety of suitable materials, as is obvious to a person of ordinary skill in the art. Such a core member <b>30</b> is centrally registered between the rigid sections and is disposed beneath the floor surface <b>11</b>. The core member <b>30</b> is formed from foam rubber and occupies an entire surface area between the inner perimeters <b>23</b> of the trim plate <b>20</b>. The core member <b>30</b> is vital for advantageously defining a fire-resistant barrier through which the cables <b>12</b> are directed. Such a fire resistant barrier advantageously protects adjacent rooms from a growing fire, thus minimizing the damage in the event that a fire does occur.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, a plurality of mounting flanges <b>40</b> are symmetrically aligned along the inner perimeters <b>23</b> of the trim plate <b>20</b> and directly abuts, without the use of intervening elements, the outer perimeter <b>32</b> of the core member <b>30</b>. Each of the mounting flanges <b>40</b> is removably engageable with the core member <b>30</b> and corresponding ones of the rigid sections <b>21</b> of the trim plate <b>20</b>. Each of the mounting flanges <b>40</b> is provided with a plurality of monolithically formed ribs <b>41</b> that inwardly protrude into the core member <b>30</b>. Such ribs <b>41</b> effectively penetrate the core member <b>30</b> and extend along an entire vertical length of the core member <b>30</b>. The ribs <b>41</b> are coextensively shaped and are directly coupled, without the use of intervening elements, with the core member <b>30</b>, which is essential such that the core member <b>30</b> is advantageously and effectively prohibited from downwardly traveling beneath the floor surface <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Yet again referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, each of the mounting flanges <b>40</b> further includes a top surface <b>42</b> that is disposed above corresponding ones of the rigid plates <b>21</b>. Such mounting flanges <b>40</b> have respective longitudinal lengths extending downwardly to a bottom surface <b>33</b> of the core member <b>30</b>, as us best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Each of the mounting flanges <b>40</b> is also vertically registered along a vertical plane defined subjacent to the floor surface <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, a plurality of computer cables <b>12</b> are removably passed through the core member <b>30</b>, thereby causing the core member <b>30</b> to laterally expand against the mounting flanges <b>40</b> and effectively constrict air gaps created within the core member <b>30</b> when the computer cables <b>12</b> are passed below the floor surface <b>11</b> and into the core member <b>30</b>. This is a crucial feature such that a secure and generally air-tight relationship is advantageously maintained with the core member <b>30</b> after the cables <b>12</b> have been positioned through the core member <b>30</b>. Such an air tight relationship advantageously prevents the shifting of the cables <b>12</b> between rigid sections <b>21</b>. Of course, various alternate conduits and cables may be passed through the core member <b>30</b>, as is obvious to a person of ordinary skill in the art. Furthermore, of course, the trim plate <b>20</b>, core member <b>30</b> and mounting flanges <b>40</b> may be produced in a variety of sizes depending on the amount of cables <b>12</b> that must passed through the kit <b>10</b>, as is obvious to a person of ordinary skill in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">While the invention has been described with respect to a certain specific embodiment, it will be appreciated that many modifications and changes may be made by those skilled in the art without departing from the spirit of the invention. It is intended, therefore, by the appended claims to cover all such modifications and changes as fall within the true spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In particular, with respect to the above description, it is to be realized that the optimum dimensional relationships for the parts of the present invention may include variations in size, materials, shape, form, function and manner of operation. The assembly and use of the present invention are deemed readily apparent and obvious to one skilled in the art.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed as new and what is desired to secure by Letters Patent of the United States is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An insulating kit for providing a barrier through which cables are channeled from one room to another room, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a trim plate including a plurality of rigid sections contiguously arranged end-to-end and spanning across a floor surface such that said rigid sections define a cavity within an inner perimeter of said rigid sections, each of said rigid sections having corresponding beveled edges outwardly sloping away from associated ones of said inner perimeters;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a core member having a single and unitary body formed from deformably resilient material, said core member being centrally registered between said rigid sections and disposed beneath the floor surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of mounting flanges symmetrically aligned along said inner perimeters of said trim plate and directly abutting said outer perimeter of said core member, each of said mounting flanges being provided with a plurality of monolithically formed ribs inwardly protruding into said core member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a plurality of computer cables are removably passed through said core member and thereby causing said core member to laterally expand against said mounting flanges and constrict air gaps created within said core member when the computer cables are passed below the floor surface and into said core member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges are removably engageable with said core member and corresponding ones of said rigid sections of said trim plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges includes a top surface disposed above corresponding ones of said rigid plates, said mounting flanges having respective longitudinal lengths extending downwardly to a bottom surface of said core member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges are vertically registered along a vertical plane defined subjacent the floor surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said core member is formed from foam rubber and occupies an entire surface area between said inner perimeters of said trim plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An insulating kit for providing a barrier through which cables are channeled from one room to another room, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a trim plate including a plurality of rigid sections contiguously arranged end-to-end and spanning across a floor surface such that said rigid sections define a cavity within an inner perimeter of said rigid sections, each of said rigid sections having corresponding beveled edges outwardly sloping away from associated ones of said inner perimeters;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a core member having a single and unitary body formed from deformably resilient material, said core member being centrally registered between said rigid sections and disposed beneath the floor surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of mounting flanges symmetrically aligned along said inner perimeters of said trim plate and directly abutting said outer perimeter of said core member, each of said mounting flanges being provided with a plurality of monolithically formed ribs inwardly protruding into said core member, wherein said ribs penetrate said core member and extend along an entire vertical length of said core member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a plurality of computer cables are removably passed through said core member and thereby causing said core member to laterally expand against said mounting flanges and constrict air gaps created within said core member when the computer cables are passed below the floor surface and into said core member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges are removably engageable with said core member and corresponding ones of said rigid sections of said trim plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges includes a top surface disposed above corresponding ones of said rigid plates, said mounting flanges having respective longitudinal lengths extending downwardly to a bottom surface of said core member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges are vertically registered along a vertical plane defined subjacent the floor surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said core member is formed from foam rubber and occupies an entire surface area between said inner perimeters of said trim plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An insulating kit for providing a barrier through which cables are channeled from one room to another room, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a trim plate including a plurality of rigid sections contiguously arranged end-to-end and spanning across a floor surface such that said rigid sections define a cavity within an inner perimeter of said rigid sections, each of said rigid sections having corresponding beveled edges outwardly sloping away from associated ones of said inner perimeters;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a core member having a single and unitary body formed from deformably resilient material, said core member being centrally registered between said rigid sections and disposed beneath the floor surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of mounting flanges symmetrically aligned along said inner perimeters of said trim plate and directly abutting said outer perimeter of said core member, each of said mounting flanges being provided with a plurality of monolithically formed ribs inwardly protruding into said core member, wherein said ribs penetrate said core member and extend along an entire vertical length of said core member, wherein said ribs are coextensively shaped and are directly coupled with said core member in such a manner that said core member is prohibited from downwardly traveling beneath the floor surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a plurality of computer cables are removably passed through said core member and thereby causing said core member to laterally expand against said mounting flanges and constrict air gaps created within said core member when the computer cables are passed below the floor surface and into said core member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges are removably engageable with said core member and corresponding ones of said rigid sections of said trim plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges includes a top surface disposed above corresponding ones of said rigid plates, said mounting flanges having respective longitudinal lengths extending downwardly to a bottom surface of said core member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein each of said mounting flanges are vertically registered along a vertical plane defined subjacent the floor surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said core member is formed from foam rubber and occupies an entire surface area between said inner perimeters of said trim plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
