<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298521-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298521</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10326069</doc-number>
<date>20021223</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-005141</doc-number>
<date>20020111</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>826</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  118</main-classification>
<further-classification>358  11</further-classification>
<further-classification>358  112</further-classification>
<further-classification>358  114</further-classification>
<further-classification>358  115</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Information processing apparatus, information processing method, recording medium, and program</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6549300</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Motamed et al.</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>358  118</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  112</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  118</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  11</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20030133157</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20030717</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hayashi</last-name>
<first-name>Eiji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fitzpatrick, Cella, Harper &amp; Scinto</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Canon Kabushiki Kaisha</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lamb</last-name>
<first-name>Twyler</first-name>
<department>2625</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Hang</last-name>
<first-name>Vu</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Providing an information processing apparatus or the like for reusing generally used index data that has been registered. In order to generate index data that is to be printed on the tabbed area of tabbed paper, data selected from a data group including the registered index data is read and data for performing printing is generated.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="217.76mm" wi="161.21mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="231.31mm" wi="161.97mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="199.05mm" wi="131.66mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="216.15mm" wi="159.26mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="120.40mm" wi="159.60mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="135.97mm" wi="156.46mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="137.08mm" wi="154.94mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="135.89mm" wi="159.17mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="197.61mm" wi="160.95mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="220.39mm" wi="157.99mm" file="US07298521-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an information processing apparatus, an information processing method, a recording medium, and a program for printing print index data that has been registered on a tabbed area of tabbed paper by using a printer having a tabbed-paper printing function.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Conventionally, the user of a printing system or the like has to generate index data that is to be printed on a tabbed area of tabbed paper each time he/she wants to make the printer having the tabbed-paper printing function print the index data. In such a case, the user uses an information processing apparatus that can generate print data for printing the index data on the tabbed paper. Such an information processing apparatus is formed as, for example, a personal computer and is connected to the printer. Accordingly, a printing system including the information processing apparatus and the printer is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Conventionally, for making a printer, which has a tabbed-paper printing function (an index-paper printing function), perform tabbed-paper printing, the user has to generate a document for tabbed paper by using an application operated on a host computer. The document for tabbed paper is printed by the printer driver of the printer. In such a case, the user has to make document into which the document for tabbed paper is to be inserted, separately. Further, after printing both the documents, the user has to insert the document for tabbed paper into the separately-made document at a predetermined position.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Thus, the user has to make both the tabbed-paper document and the document into which the tabbed-paper document is to be inserted. Further, the user has to print both the documents separately and insert the tabbed-paper document into the other document. Performing such procedures is an enormous load on the user.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Accordingly, it is an object of the present invention to provide a printing system that can set the details of tabbed-paper printing by using a print-settings screen displayed by a printer driver.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The object of the present invention is to provide a printing system that can register at least one tab data item that has been set by using the print-settings screen displayed by the printer driver and can select desired tab data from the registered tab data for printing. According to the present invention, generally used specific titles to be printed on tabbed paper, such as “Section 1” and “Section 2” can be registered by using the print-settings screen displayed by the printer driver. Further, generic titles corresponding to the specific titles can also be registered with the printer driver. Therefore, the user does not have to generate and register new index data by using the print-settings screen, that is, the GUI of the printer driver, each time he/she wants to have the generally used index data printed.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Another object of the present invention is to reuse the generally used index data that has been registered.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Therefore, an aspect of the present invention is directed to an information processing apparatus for generating print data that is used by a printer for printing. The information processing apparatus comprises a setting unit for setting at least one index data item to be printed on a tabbed area of tabbed paper by the printer. The information processing apparatus further comprises a print-data generation unit for reading the set index data item and generating print data corresponding to the set index data item so that the set data item is printed on the tabbed area of tabbed paper by the printer.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Further objects, features and advantages of the present invention will become apparent from the following description of the preferred embodiments with reference to the attached drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the configuration of a printing system according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the main functions of the printing system.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> illustrates 5 sheets of tabbed paper.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> illustrates the configuration of a first sheet and a second sheet of tabbed paper.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref> further illustrates the configuration of the first sheet of tabbed paper.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> illustrates the tabbed-paper printing functions of the printing system.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> further illustrates the tabbed-paper printing functions of the printing system.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates the procedures performed for tabbed-paper printing when index data is set each time the tabbed-paper printing is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a user interface used for reusing the index data according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a user interface used for registering the index data according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates the flow of the procedures performed for reusing the index data according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates the configuration of a registered index-data table according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> illustrates a typical graphical user-interface screen for determining positions at which pages with the index data printed thereon are to be inserted.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Preferred embodiments of the present invention will now be described with reference to the attached drawings. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram for illustrating the configuration of a printing system according to a first embodiment of the present invention. The system includes a host computer <b>3000</b> (a printing control apparatus and an information processing apparatus) and a printer <b>1500</b> (a printer) that is connected thereto.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In the following description, a printing system using a laser-beam printer is described as a typical printing system. However, the present invention is not limited to such a case, and can be used for an inkjet printer or a multifunction machine having the function of copying, when the inkjet printer and the multifunctional printer have a tabbed-paper printing function. The printing system may be formed as a discrete machine or a system including a plurality of machines as long as the system has the function of the present invention. Further, the printing system may be connected to the host computer via a network such as a LAN, a WAN, and so forth so as to be processed by the host computer.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the host computer <b>3000</b> includes a ROM <b>3</b> having a font ROM <b>3</b><i>a, </i>a program ROM <b>3</b><i>b, </i>and a font-data ROM <b>3</b><i>c. </i>The host computer <b>3000</b> includes a CPU <b>1</b> (printing control means and reverse-surface printing control means) for performing processing of a document containing a mixture of drawings, images, text, tables (including a spreadsheet), and so forth based on a document-processing program stored in the program ROM <b>3</b><i>a </i>of the ROM <b>3</b> or an external memory (HD and FD) <b>11</b> such as a hard disk, a floppy disk, and so forth. The CPU <b>1</b> has centralized control over each device connected to a system bus <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">An operating system program (hereinafter referred to as an OS) or the like, which is a control program of the CPU <b>1</b>, is stored in the program ROM <b>3</b><i>b </i>or the external memory <b>11</b>. Font data used for performing the above-described document processing is stored in the font ROM <b>3</b><i>a </i>or the external memory <b>11</b>. Various kinds of data used for performing the document processing or the like are stored in the font-data ROM <b>3</b><i>c </i>or the external memory <b>11</b>. The data may include, for example, various kinds of page-description language programs, font-rasterizing data, and so forth.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Reference numeral <b>2</b> indicates RAM, which can be expanded by adding optional RAM or the like. The RAM <b>2</b> functions as a main memory, a work area, and so forth of the CPU <b>1</b>. Reference numeral <b>5</b> indicates a keyboard controller (KBC). The keyboard controller <b>5</b> controls a keyboard (KB) <b>9</b> and key entry from a pointing device that is not shown.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Reference numeral <b>6</b> indicates a CRT controller (CRTC). The CRT controller <b>6</b> controls the display shown on a CRT display (CRT) <b>10</b>. Reference numeral <b>7</b> indicates a disk controller (DKC). The disk controller <b>7</b> controls access with the external memory <b>11</b>, which stores a boot program, various kinds of applications, font data, a user file, an edit file, a printer control command generation program (hereinafter referred to as a printer driver), and so forth. Reference numeral <b>8</b> indicates a printer controller (PRTC). The printer controller <b>8</b> is connected to the printer <b>1500</b> via a predetermined bidirectional interface <b>21</b>. The printer controller <b>8</b> controls communication between the host computer <b>3000</b> and the printer <b>1500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The CPU <b>1</b> performs processing for expanding (rasterizing) an outline font to a display-information RAM area defined in the RAM <b>2</b> in order to make the printer <b>1500</b> print what is on the CRT <b>10</b> in a WYSIWYG (What you see is what you get) manner. Further, the CPU <b>1</b> opens various kinds of registered windows based on a command issued via a mouse cursor (not shown) or the like on the CRT <b>10</b> and performs various kinds of data processing.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">For performing printing, a user opens a window relating to printing settings and makes printer settings and print processing method settings for the printer driver. The print-processing method settings include selecting a printing mode.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The printer <b>1500</b> is controlled by a printer CPU <b>12</b>. The printer CPU <b>12</b> has a ROM <b>13</b> including a font ROM <b>13</b><i>a, </i>a program ROM <b>13</b><i>b, </i>and a data ROM <b>13</b><i>c. </i>The printer CPU <b>12</b> performs centralized control over the access with each device connected to a system bus <b>15</b> based on a control program or the like stored in the program ROM <b>13</b><i>b </i>or a control program or the like stored in an external memory (HD or FD) <b>14</b> such as a hard disk, a floppy disk, an IC card, and so forth. Then, the printer CPU <b>12</b> outputs an image signal serving as output information to a printing unit (printer engine) <b>17</b> connected thereto via a printing-unit interface (I/F) <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">A control program or the like that can be executed by the printer CPU <b>12</b> is stored in the program RAM <b>13</b><i>b. </i>Font data (including outline-font data) or the like that is used for generating the above-described output information is stored in the font ROM <b>13</b><i>a. </i>When the printer <b>1500</b> has no external memory such as a hard disk or the like, information that is used by the host computer <b>3000</b> is stored in the data ROM <b>13</b><i>c. </i></p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">An operating unit <b>1501</b> is an operating panel provided with switches, an LED display, and so forth (not shown) that are used for performing operations. The printer CPU <b>12</b> can communicate with the host computer <b>3000</b> via an inputting unit <b>18</b>. Therefore, the printer CPU <b>12</b> can inform the host computer <b>3000</b> of the information or the like in the printer <b>1500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Reference numeral <b>19</b> indicates a RAM mainly serving as a main memory or a work area of the printer CPU <b>12</b>. The amount of memory of the RAM <b>19</b> can be expanded by adding an optional RAM, which is connected to an additional port that is not shown. The RAM <b>19</b> is used for an output-information expansion area, an environment-data storing area, a NVRAM, and so forth. The access with the external memory <b>14</b> is controlled by a disk controller (DKC) <b>20</b>. The external memory <b>14</b>, which stores font data, an emulation program, form data, and so forth, is connected to the printer <b>1500</b> as an optional unit.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">More than one external memory <b>14</b> may be provided. Further, it may be arranged that a plurality of external memories storing an optional font card in addition to the internal font thereof and a program for translating printer control languages of different language systems are connected to the printer <b>1500</b>. Further, the external memories may have the NVRAM (not shown) and may store printer-mode setting information that is transmitted from an operating unit <b>1501</b> for each user or group, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the main functions of the printing system. An application <b>201</b>, a graphic engine <b>202</b>, a printer driver <b>203</b>, and a system spooler <b>204</b> in the host computer <b>3000</b> are files that are stored in the external memory <b>11</b>. Further, the application <b>201</b>, the graphic engine <b>202</b>, the printer driver <b>203</b>, and the system spooler <b>204</b> are program modules that are loaded into the RAM <b>2</b> and executed by an OS or a module that uses the module of the OS.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The application <b>201</b> and the printer driver <b>203</b> can be added to the HD of the external memory <b>11</b> via the FD of the external memory <b>11</b>, a CD-ROM (not shown), or a network (not shown). The application <b>201</b>, which is stored in the external memory <b>11</b>, is loaded into the RAM <b>2</b> and is executed. For making the printer <b>1500</b> perform printing in a case where the application <b>201</b> is used, the graphic engine <b>202</b>, which is also loaded and executed by the RAM <b>2</b>, is used for outputting (drawing).</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The graphic engine <b>202</b> is the drawing means of the OS (operation system). The graphic engine <b>202</b> loads each printer driver <b>203</b> that is provided for each printer from the external memory <b>11</b> into the RAM <b>2</b>. Then, the graphic engine <b>202</b> converts a drawing function (a GDI function in this embodiment) that is an output from the application <b>201</b> to a drawing function that can be translated by the printer driver <b>203</b> (a DDI function in this embodiment) and transmits the converted drawing function to the printer driver <b>203</b>. The printer driver <b>203</b> converts the DDI function to a printer-control command that can be translated by the printer <b>1500</b>. The DDI function is the drawing function transmitted from the graphic engine (sometimes referred to as a GDI: a Graphic Device Interface) <b>202</b>. The printer-control command is transmitted through the system spooler <b>204</b>, which is loaded into the RAM <b>2</b> by the OS, and is output to the printer <b>1500</b> via the interface <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="h-0005" num="0000">[Tabbed-Paper Printing Function]</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A</figref>, <b>3</b>B, and <b>3</b>C illustrate typical tabbed papers. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> illustrates a set of 5 sheets of tabbed paper, for example, even though the number of sheets of commercially available tabbed paper is not always 5. Of course, the present invention is not limited to the above-described case. The tabbed paper in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is aligned to be inserted into a document that is to be opened towards the left, for example, even though commercially available sets of paper are not always used for documents that are opened towards the left and other variations are possible with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> illustrates the configuration of a first sheet and a second sheet of tabbed paper. As shown in the drawing, each sheet has a projection (an index area) for writing index information thereon, which is attached to one side thereof. The index areas are arranged so that they do not overlap one another. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref> illustrates a case where index information “No. 01” is printed on the index area of the first sheet. In this drawing, the index information “No. 01” is printed in the horizontal direction. However, the index information may be printed in the vertical direction.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> illustrates a case where the tabbed-paper printing function is not yet performed by the printer <b>1500</b>. On the other hand, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> illustrates a case where the tabbed-paper printing function has been performed by the printer <b>1500</b>. Therefore, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> illustrates a case where sheets of tabbed paper are overlaid on one another wherein no information is printed on the index areas of the tabbed papers. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> illustrates a case where other sheets of tabbed paper are overlaid on one another after the tabbed-paper printing function is added to the printer <b>1500</b>. The tabbed paper, excluding the index areas are a standard size. For example, the tabbed paper, excluding the index areas may be letter-sized, A4-sized, and so forth. Therefore, by inserting tabbed paper between pages of a document after the tabbed-paper printing function is added to the printer <b>1500</b>, it becomes possible to immediately see the categories of the document contents.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">When the tabbed-paper printing function is added to the printer <b>1500</b>, the user of the printer generates index information every time he/she makes a document. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates the details of the tabbed-paper printing function. A graphical user interface (hereinafter referred to as a GUI) in an index-information setting screen shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is called up from a print-setting property screen displayed by the printer driver <b>203</b>. This drawing illustrates a typical text-edit box for inputting text information that is printed on each index area of the 5 sheets of tabbed paper. The user inputs index information “Section 1”, which is printed on a first tabbed sheet, into the uppermost edit box, index information “Section 2”, which is printed on a second tabbed sheet, into the second edit box, index information “Section 3”, which is printed on a third tabbed sheet, into the third edit box, index information “Section 4”, which is printed on a fourth tabbed sheet, into the fourth edit box, and index information “Section 5”, which is printed on a fifth tabbed sheet, into the lowermost edit box.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">After inputting the above-described index information in the edit boxes, the user presses an “OK” button shown in the drawing. When the user wants to cancel generation of the index information, the user presses a “cancel” button shown in the drawing. When the “OK” button is pressed, an index-information registering module of the printer driver <b>203</b> writes the contents of the index information into a predetermined storage area (for example, DEVMODE) for use at printing time. Thus, according to a first embodiment of the present invention, index information for a plurality of tabs can be stored via a user interface displayed by a printer driver so that the index information can be printed on tabs of tabbed paper. Further, since the index information for the plurality of tabs is registered, the printer driver can generate print data including control commands from the registered index information at printing time. Therefore, tabbed-paper printing can be easily performed as desired by the user.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As has been described in the embodiment above, the index information, which is used when tabbed-paper printing is performed, is set by using the index-information setting screen displayed by the printer driver <b>203</b>. Further, the index information, that is, the above-mentioned “Section 1”, “Section 2”, “Section 3” “Section 4”, and “Section 5”, is maintained in the predetermined storage area. Therefore, the index information that was stored for the previous tabbed-paper printing can be used again when the next tabbed-paper printing is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">However, according to the contents of a document into which the tabbed paper is inserted, the user may determine that other index information including “Part 1”, “Part 2”, “Part 3”, “Part 4” and “Part 5” should be printed on the tabbed paper. That is to say, index information that was set for the previous tabbed-paper printing is not always used for the next tabbed-paper printing.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As has been described, the index information is stored by using the index-information setting screen, which is displayed by the printer driver <b>203</b>. However, when a tabbed-paper printing function is added wherein the user is required to input the index information, the user must generate the index information every time he/she uses the tabbed-paper printing function.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">According to a second embodiment of the present invention, typical index information and frequently used index information can be used repeatedly. Therefore, according to the second embodiment, the user does not need to generate the index information every time he/she uses the tabbed-paper printing function. An index-information reusing processing method according to the second embodiment will now be described.</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">[Print Control Procedures]</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref> illustrate typical user interfaces (GUIs) according to the index-data reusing processing method of the second embodiment. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows one user interface serving as the index-data setting screen. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows another user interface serving as an index-data registration screen. The two user interfaces are called up from the print-setting properties screen, which is displayed by the printer driver <b>203</b>. The user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a screen for selecting index data, to be used for performing tabbed-paper printing, from the previously stored index data. The user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a screen for registering index data that is likely to be used frequently.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">By using the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the user selects index data that should be printed on the index area of the tabbed paper from one or more index data items that have been stored (referred to as “specific-title index” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>). The details of the selection will be described later with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The text box “specific-title index” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates the registered specific titles. A text box “generic-title index” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows registered generic titles, which have been registered by using the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In the text box “specific-title index” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the details of “Section N” selected by the user are shown as “Section 1”, “Section 2”, and so forth. Since, in this way, the user can understand the details of the “generic title”, he/she can select the most appropriate generic title for a document into which the tabbed paper is to be inserted. When the user presses a “new registration” button positioned at the lower end of the interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is displayed. The details of an “OK” button and a “cancel” button that are placed at the lower end of the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> will be described later. However, it should be noted that the “OK” button is a control button that is used for selecting the generic title and the “cancel” button is another control button that is used for canceling the selected generic title.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">By using the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the user generates generic titles for registration (referred to as “registered generic title”) and the details of the generic title for registration (referred to as a text box “definition of specific titles” shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a new generic title “product catalog 001” is registered in the text box “registered generic title”. The specific titles of the “product catalog 001”, such as “A-series”, “C-series”, and so forth, are registered in the text box “definition of specific titles”. Both the text box “registered generic title” and the text box “definition of specific titles” enter a selection mode when the cursor, which is moved by the mouse, is positioned thereon and clicked. Then, the user can input text via the keyboard.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">An “OK” button that is provided at the lower end of the user interface, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, is a control button for registering the new generic title and the specific titles. A “cancel” button that is also provided at the lower end of the user interface, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, is another control button for canceling the registration of the new generic title and the specific titles. If the user presses the “OK” button or the “cancel” button, the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is displayed. When the user presses the “OK” button and the new generic title and the specific titles are registered, the new generic title and specific titles, which are registered via the GUI shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, are stored as an index-data settings file in a predetermined area (more specifically, the system folder in the case where the OS is Microsoft Windows(R)).</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Thus, according to the embodiment, the user can register a new generic title. However, by providing a “delete” button, for example, on the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the user can arbitrarily select one or more generic titles from the “generic-title index” and can delete one or more specific titles corresponding to the one or more selected generic titles. The user can edit the specific titles that have been registered. Here, text that is printed on a tab of the tabbed paper is referred to as a “specific title”, and a group of the specific titles, which are printed on the tabs, is referred to as a “specific-title group”. A generic title and one or more specific titles that are registered corresponding to the generic title are collectively referred to as “tab data”.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a flowchart illustrating the procedure performed for reusing the index data according to the embodiment. The first half of the flowchart illustrates the procedure that is performed, using a user interface screen that is not shown, for determining the orientation of writing (the horizontal direction, the vertical direction, 180° rotation of vertically oriented text, and so forth), the font name, the font size, etc. Such procedures are started by opening the print-setting property screen (not shown) displayed by the printer driver <b>203</b> and by pressing a “set tabbed-paper printing details” button (not shown) for opening the GUI shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">First, the user selects the tab data used for printing from the previously registered index data by using the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> or registers new index data by using the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> (Step S<b>801</b>). The descriptions of types of data or information that are selected or registered are omitted since they have been described above. When the user presses the “OK” button in the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> after he/she selects a generic name from the “generic-title index”, or when the user presses the “OK” button or the “cancel button” in the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> after he/she registers new index data by using the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> and selects the registered index data by using the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the step advances to step S<b>802</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">At step S<b>802</b>, the printer driver <b>203</b> determines whether or not reusing of the registered index data is selected at step S<b>801</b>. When the printer driver <b>203</b> determines that the reusing was selected, it advances to step S<b>803</b>. Otherwise, the printer driver <b>203</b> advances to step S<b>804</b>. The printer driver <b>203</b> determines that the reusing of the registered index data is selected when the user selects a desired generic title from the “generic-title index” and presses the “OK” button in the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">At step S<b>803</b>, the printer driver <b>203</b> reads a generic title and a specific-title group corresponding to the generic title from the index-data setting file (hereinafter referred to as a registered index-data table), which is included in the printer driver <b>203</b>, or which is an external file to be referred to. Then, the printer driver <b>203</b> advances to step S<b>806</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">In the case where the number of tabbed papers used for printing is smaller than the number of tabs, the printer driver <b>203</b> informs the user of the fact by using a message dialog (not shown). Then, the user determines whether to let the printer driver <b>203</b> perform printing or to go back to change the number of tabbed papers by using the message dialog. When the user determines to let the printer driver <b>203</b> perform printing, the printer driver <b>203</b> can print the registered index data from the first part thereof on the tabbed papers.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">In the case where the number of tabbed papers used for printing is larger than the number of tabs, the printer driver <b>203</b> informs the user of the fact by using a message dialog (not shown). Then, the user determines whether to let the printer driver <b>203</b> perform printing or to go back to change the number of tabbed papers by using the message dialog.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates the details of the registered index-data table. As shown in this drawing, the registered index-data table stores the generic titles, the number of tabs, and text data or the specific titles to be printed on the tabs. Since <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates the conceptual configuration of the registered index-data table, the format of the registered index-data table is not limited to that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> as long as the table is appropriate for controlling the index data. For example, the table may store the specific titles, numerical values, and so forth, using binary-format representations or XML-format representations. The XML-format representations are structured text-format representations.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">When the printer driver <b>203</b> determines that the reusing of the index data was not selected at step S<b>802</b>, the step advances to step S<b>804</b>. The printer driver <b>203</b> determines whether or not to generate the new index data at step S<b>804</b>. If the printer driver <b>203</b> determines to generate the new index data, the step advances to step S<b>805</b>. Otherwise, that is to say, when the user presses the “cancel” button in the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the printer driver <b>203</b> stops operating for reusing the index-data.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">If the printer driver <b>203</b> determines to generate the new index data at step S<b>804</b>, the step advances to step S<b>805</b>. At step S<b>805</b>, an index-data registration module (not shown) of the printer driver <b>203</b> stores the index data, that is, the tab data, that is newly registered by using the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> in the registered index-data table. The tab data includes the text, that is, the specific titles that are to be printed on the tabs of the sheets of tabbed paper, the tab number, and the generic title of the specific titles. Then, the step advances to step S<b>806</b>. The tab number is input in the text box “definition of specific titles” shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> by the user.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">In the case where the number of tabbed-paper sheets used for printing is smaller than the number of tabs, the printer driver <b>203</b> informs the user of the fact by using a message dialog (not shown). Then, the user determines whether to let the printer driver <b>203</b> perform printing or to go back to change the number of tabbed-paper sheets by using the message dialog. When the user determines to let the printer driver <b>203</b> perform printing, the printer driver <b>203</b> can print the registered index data from the first part thereof on the tabbed-paper sheets.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">In the case where the number of tabbed-paper sheets used for printing is larger than the number of tabs, the printer driver <b>203</b> informs the user of the fact by using a message dialog (not shown). Then, the user determines whether to let the printer driver <b>203</b> perform printing or to go back to change the number of tabbed-paper sheets by using the message dialog.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">At step S<b>806</b>, the printer drier <b>203</b> generates print-job data based on the index data that has been determined at step S<b>803</b>, or at step S<b>805</b>, for printing the determined index data onto the tabbed paper. Then, the step advances to step S<b>807</b>. At step S<b>807</b>, the printer driver <b>203</b> outputs the print-job data, which is generated at step S<b>806</b>, to the system spooler <b>204</b> of the OS, thereby terminating the process of reusing the index data. The system spooler <b>204</b> transmits the print-job data to the printer <b>1500</b>. Upon receiving the print-job data, the printer <b>1500</b> prints the index data on the sheets of tabbed paper.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">The details of a process of generating an index job (S<b>806</b>) shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> will be described. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> illustrates a typical graphical user interface for determining positions in the document where the sheets of tabbed paper are to be inserted. Each item of the index data (represented by the first to fifth tabs shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>) is printed on the corresponding sheet of tabbed paper. When tabbed-paper printing is selected by the user via the print-setting properties screen, which is displayed by the printer driver <b>203</b>, for printing a document that is made by using the application <b>201</b>, the user can determine the positions in the document where the sheets of tabbed paper are to be inserted.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">By using the graphical user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the user can determine the positions in the document, which is made by using the application <b>201</b>, where the sheets of tabbed paper are to be inserted.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Accordingly, the user can make the printer <b>1500</b> perform printing after he/she determines the positions in the document where the sheets of tabbed paper are to be inserted. Then, at step S<b>806</b> where an index job is generated, the printer driver <b>203</b> receives a plotting function (a DDI function). The DDI function is obtained by converting a plotting function (a GDI function) via the graphic engine <b>202</b>. The GDI function is generated by the application <b>201</b>. Then, the printer driver <b>203</b> converts the DDI function into a page-description language (a PDL) per page.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">The printer driver <b>203</b> compares the pages of the document, which is transmitted from the application <b>201</b>, and the pages shown in the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>. If the printer driver <b>203</b> determines that one of the pages corresponds to one of the set pages shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the printer driver <b>203</b> reads index data corresponding to the set page from the tab data in the registered index-data table. The printer driver <b>203</b> further reads items of index data corresponding to each tab number and generates a PDL. Here, the printer driver <b>203</b> generates and enters a tabbed-paper print command because the page on which the index data is printed is a tabbed-paper sheet. Because, even though the printer <b>1500</b> performs regular printing upon receiving the PDL, for the page for which the tabbed-paper print command is entered, the printer <b>1500</b> unarchives the PDL, generates and prints a bit-map image on the tabbed-sheet at a shifted position. The image is formed by, for example, charging in the case where an electrophotographic printer is used, or spraying ink in the case where an ink jet printer is used.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Thus, for the page that has been set by the user interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the printer driver <b>203</b> generates the print-job data by entering the tabbed-paper print command and generating the PDL.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">According to this embodiment, for generating the specific titles which are to be printed on the tabbed area of tabbed paper, the user can select desired specific titles from the registered specific-title group including generally used specific titles, such as “Section 1”, “Section 2”, and so forth. Otherwise, the user can register new index data and select desired index data therefrom. Subsequently, the user can reuse generally used or frequently used index data without generating new data each time the tabbed-paper printing is performed. That is to say, the reduction of the tabbed-paper printing procedures benefits offices where large-volume documents are printed and the near-print publication industry.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">OTHER EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">The present invention can be used for a system including a plurality of apparatuses, such as a host computer, an interface, a reader, and a printer. Further, the present invention can be used for an apparatus, such as a copier, a printer, or a facsimile machine.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">In the above-described embodiment, the specific titles are printed on the tabbed area of the tabbed paper. However, other index data, such as a bar code, or an image may be printed.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">Further, a recording medium storing the program code of software that achieves the above-described functions may be supplied to a print-control apparatus or a print-control system. Then, a computer (or a CPU or a MPU) included in the print-control apparatus may read the program code and may execute it for achieving the object of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">Thus, the program code that is read from the recording medium achieves the new functions of the present invention. Therefore, in such a case, the recording medium storing the program code serves as the component of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The recording medium for storing the program code may be a floppy disk, a hard disk, an optical disk, a magneto-optical disk, a CD-ROM, a CD-R, a magnetic tape, a nonvolatile memory, or a ROM.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">As discussed, the above-described functions can be achieved by executing the program code read by the computer. However, an OS operated on the computer based on the instructions of the program code may perform part of the procedures or all the procedures for achieving the functions of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">Further, when the program code read from the recording medium is stored in an expansion board provided in the computer or in a memory provided in an expansion unit connected to the computer, a CPU in the expansion board or the expansion unit may perform part of the procedures or all the procedures for achieving the functions of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">While the present invention has been described with reference to what are presently considered to be the preferred embodiments, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited to the disclosed embodiments. On the contrary, the invention is intended to cover various modifications and equivalent arrangements included within the spirit and scope of the appended claims. The scope of the following claims is to be accorded the broadest interpretation so as to encompass all such modifications and equivalent structures and functions.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">As has been described, according to the present invention, a desired information group can be selected from information groups that have been registered in storing means and the output data of the selected information group can be printed on paper at a predetermined position. Therefore, the output data of the registered information groups can be reused. Since the user does not have to reenter the output data of the registered information for printing, reduction of the printing procedures is achieved.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An information processing apparatus having a printer driver for generating print data that is used by a printer for printing, the information processing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>setting means for setting at least one index data to be printed on a tabbed area of tabbed paper by the printer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>registering means for registering the index data set by said setting means as a group;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storage means for storing a plurality of groups registered by said registering means;</claim-text>
<claim-text>display control means for displaying a user interface to select a group, which includes the index data to be printed on the tabbed area of the tabbed paper, from the plurality of groups stored by said storage means;</claim-text>
<claim-text>selection means for selecting the group, which includes the index data to be printed on the tabbed area of the tabbed paper, via the user interface displayed by said display control means; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>print-data generation means for generating print data based on the index data, which is included in the group selected by said selection means, so that the index data is printed on the tabbed area of the tabbed paper by the printer,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said display control means displays (a) identification information of each of the plurality of groups and (b) the index data, which is included in the group selected by said selection means, in the same user interface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. An information processing method for generating print data that is used by a printer for performing printing, the information processing method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>setting at least one index data to be printed on a tabbed area of tabbed paper by the printer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>registering the index data set by said setting step as a group;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing a plurality of groups registered by said registering step;</claim-text>
<claim-text>displaying a user interface to select a group, which includes the index data to be printed on the tabbed area of the tabbed paper, from the plurality of groups stored by said storage step;</claim-text>
<claim-text>selecting the group, which includes the index data to be printed on the tabbed area of the tabbed paper, via the user interface displayed by said displaying step; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating print data based on the index data, which is included in the group selected by said selecting step, so that the index data is printed on the tabbed area of tabbed paper by the printer,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said displaying step displays (a) identification information of each of the plurality of groups and (b) the index data, which is included in the group selected by said selecting step, in the same user interface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A print-control program embodied on computer-readable storage medium, to be executed by an information processing apparatus having a printer driver that generates print data used by a printer for printing, the print-control program comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>setting at least one index data to be printed on a tabbed area of tabbed paper by the printer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>registering the index data set by said setting step as a group;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing a plurality of groups registered by said registering step;</claim-text>
<claim-text>displaying a user interface to select a group, which includes the index data to be printed on the tabbed area of the tabbed paper, from the plurality of groups stored by said storage step;</claim-text>
<claim-text>selecting the group, which includes the index data to be printed on the tabbed area of the tabbed paper, via the user interface displayed by said displaying step; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating print data based on the index data, which is included in the group selected by said selecting step, so that the index data is printed on the tabbed area of tabbed paper by the printer,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said displaying step displays (a) identification information of each of the plurality of groups and (b) the index data, which is included in the group selected by said selecting step, in the same user interface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. An information processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>designation means for designating a page of which index data is to be printed,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said print-data generation means generates print data to which a tabbed-paper printing command is inserted, on the page designated by said designation means.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An information processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>comparing means for comparing the number of sheets of the tabbed paper with the number of index data which is included in the group selected by said selection means,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said display control means indicates the comparison result when the number of sheets and the number of index data are determined to be discrepant based on the comparison result of said comparing means.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>designating a page of which index data is to be printed,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said print-data generation step generates print data to which a tabbed-paper printing command is inserted, on the page designated by said designating step.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>comparing the number of sheets of the tabbed paper with the number of index data which is included in the group selected by said selecting step,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said displaying step indicates the comparison result when the number of sheets and the number of index data are determined to be discrepant based on the comparison result of said comparing step.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
