<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296462-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296462</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11121332</doc-number>
<date>20050503</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>102</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>E</section>
<class>21</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>43</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315251</main-classification>
<further-classification>166250</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Multi-purpose downhole tool</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3577781</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lebourg et al.</name>
<date>19710500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7315226</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4936139</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Zimmerman et al.</name>
<date>19900600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7315226</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5337821</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Peterson</name>
<date>19940800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>16625007</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5549159</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Shwe et al.</name>
<date>19960800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>16625002</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5991602</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sturm</name>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>455 40</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6305470</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Woie</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>16625002</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6427530</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Krueger et al.</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7315246</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>32</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315227</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315236</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315222</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315251</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315226</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315246</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315252</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315254</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73 5251</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7315201</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>16625001</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>166250</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>16625002</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060248949</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061109</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gregory</last-name>
<first-name>Gilbert N.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sugar Land</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ball</last-name>
<first-name>David E.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Meadows Place</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Somers</last-name>
<first-name>Russell Scott</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tomball</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Grable</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Houston</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Menezes</last-name>
<first-name>Clive D.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Conroe</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Conley Rose, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Halliburton Energy Services, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Houston</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Williams</last-name>
<first-name>Hezron</first-name>
<department>2856</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Frank</last-name>
<first-name>Rodney</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A multi-purpose downhole tool comprising packers for isolating an interval of a downhole formation traversed by a borehole to form a packed-off interval annulus. The tool further comprises a reversible pump and more than one interval access port located between the packers. The ports provide fluid communication with fluid in the packed-off interval annulus. The tool further comprises a fluid conduit system and valves for controlling fluid communication between the interval access ports and the reversible pump. The multi-purpose tool is capable of pumping from the packed-off interval annulus as well as pumping into or “through” the packed-off interval annulus for determining formation pressures as well as introducing well enhancement fluids downhole.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="242.15mm" wi="156.63mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="203.12mm" wi="175.68mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="218.44mm" wi="175.26mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="219.20mm" wi="180.42mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="212.51mm" wi="182.63mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="218.02mm" wi="176.36mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="207.52mm" wi="150.79mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="242.65mm" wi="157.73mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="185.59mm" wi="138.01mm" file="US07296462-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Not Applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR DEVELOPMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Not Applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">During the drilling and completion of oil and gas wells, it may be necessary to engage in ancillary operations, such as monitoring the operability of equipment used during the drilling process or evaluating the production capabilities of formations intersected by the wellbore. For example, after a well or well interval has been drilled, zones of interest are often tested to determine various formation properties such as permeability, fluid type, fluid quality, formation temperature, formation pressure, bubblepoint, formation pressure gradient, mobility, filtrate viscosity, spherical mobility, coupled compressibility porosity, skin damage (which is an indication of how the mud filtrate has changed the permeability near the wellbore), and anisotropy (which is the ratio of the vertical and horizontal permeabilities). These tests are performed in order to determine whether commercial exploitation of the intersected formations is viable and how to optimize production.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Drill stem testers (DST) and wireline formation testers (WFT) have been commonly used to perform these tests. The basic DST tool consists of a packer or packers, valves, or ports that may be opened and closed from the surface, and two or more pressure-recording devices. The tool is lowered on a work string to the zone to be tested. The packer or packers are set, and drilling fluid is evacuated to isolate the zone from the drilling fluid column. The valves or ports are then opened to allow flow from the formation to the tool for testing while the recorders chart static pressures. A sampling chamber traps formation fluid at the end of the test. WFTs generally employ the same testing techniques but use a wireline to lower the test tool into the borehole after the drill string has been retrieved from the borehole. WFTs typically use packers also, although the packers are typically placed closer together, compared to DSTs, for more efficient formation testing. In some cases, packers are not even used. In those instances, the testing tool is brought into contact with the formation and testing is done without zonal isolation.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">WFTs may also include a probe assembly for engaging the borehole wall and acquiring formation fluid samples. The probe assembly may include an isolation pad to engage the borehole wall. The isolation pad seals against the formation and around a hollow probe, which places an internal cavity in fluid communication with the formation. This creates a fluid pathway that allows formation fluid to flow between the formation and the formation tester while isolated from the borehole fluid.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">With the use of DSTs and WFTs, the drill string with the drill bit must first be retracted from the borehole. Then, a separate work string containing the testing equipment, or, with WFTs, the wireline tool string, must be lowered into the well to conduct secondary operations.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">DSTs and WFTs may also cause tool sticking or formation damage. There may also be difficulties of running WFTs in highly deviated and extended reach wells. WFTs also do not have flowbores for the flow of drilling mud, nor are they designed to withstand drilling loads such as torque and weight on bit.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Further, the formation pressure measurement accuracy of drill stem tests and, especially, of wireline formation tests may be affected by mud filtrate invasion and mudcake buildup because significant amounts of time may have passed before a DST or WFT engages the formation after the borehole has been drilled. Mud filtrate invasion occurs when the drilling mud fluids displace formation fluid. Because the mud filtrate ingress into the formation begins at the borehole surface, it is most prevalent there and generally decreases further into the formation. When filtrate invasion occurs, it may become impossible to obtain a representative sample of formation fluid or, at a minimum, the duration of the sampling period must be increased to first remove the drilling fluid and then obtain a representative sample of formation fluid. Mudcake buildup occurs when any solid particles in the drilling fluid are plastered to the side of the wellbore by the circulating drilling mud during drilling. The prevalence of the mudcake at the borehole surface creates a “skin” that can affect the measurement results. The mudcake also acts as a region of reduced permeability adjacent to the borehole. Thus, once the mudcake forms, the accuracy of reservoir pressure measurements decreases, affecting the calculations for permeability and producibility of the formation. The mudcake should be flushed out of the formation before a true, uncontaminated sample of the fluid can be collected. Thus, it may be desirable to pump formation fluid that is contaminated with filtrate from the formation until uncontaminated connate fluid can be identified and produced.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Another testing apparatus is the formation tester while drilling (FTWD) tool. Typical FTWD formation testing equipment is suitable for integration with a drill string during drilling operations. Various devices or systems are used for isolating a formation from the remainder of the borehole, drawing fluid from the formation, and measuring physical properties of the fluid and the formation. Fluid properties, among other items, may include fluid compressibility, flowline fluid compressibility, density, resistivity, composition, and bubblepoint. For example, the FTWD may use a probe similar to a WFT that extends to the formation and a small sample chamber to draw in formation fluid through the probe to test the formation pressure. To perform a test, the drill string is stopped from rotating and moving axially and the test procedure, similar to a WFT described above, is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">After the testing of a well, it may be desirable to leave the testing string in place in the well and stimulate or otherwise treat the various formations of the well by pumping acids and other fluids into the formations. Well stimulation refers to a variety of techniques used for increasing the rate at which fluids flow out of or into a well at a fixed pressure difference. As used herein, the terms “stimulate”, “stimulation”, etc. are used in relation to operations wherein it is desired to inject, or otherwise introduce, fluids into a formation or formations intersected by a wellbore of a subterranean well. Typically, the purpose of such stimulation operations is to increase a production rate and/or capacity of hydrocarbons from the formation or formations. For example, stimulation operations may include a procedure known as “fracturing” wherein fluid is injected into a formation under relatively high pressure in order to fracture the formation, thus making it easier for hydrocarbons within the formation to flow toward the wellbore. Other stimulation operations include acidizing, acid-fracing, etc. Well treatment may include injecting such fluids as anti-emulsion fluid, etc.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">For a more detailed description of the embodiments, reference will now be made to the following accompanying drawings:</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of an embodiment of a multipurpose downhole tool;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of the embodiment of a multipurpose downhole tool of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of the embodiment of a multipurpose downhole tool of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of the embodiment of a multipurpose downhole tool of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of the embodiment of a multipurpose downhole tool of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of a first alternative embodiment of a multipurpose downhole tool;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of a second alternative embodiment of a multipurpose downhole tool; and</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a schematic view of a well drilling system using any of the embodiments of the multipurpose downhole tool.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In the drawings and description that follows, like parts are marked throughout the specification and drawings with the same reference numerals, respectively. The drawing figures are not necessarily to scale. Certain features of the invention may be illustrated exaggerated in scale or in somewhat schematic form and some details of conventional elements may not be illustrated in the interest of clarity and conciseness. The present invention is susceptible to embodiments of different forms. Specific embodiments are described in detail and are illustrated in the drawings, with the understanding that the present disclosure is to be considered an exemplification of the principles of the invention, and is not intended to limit the invention to that illustrated and described herein. It is to be fully recognized that the different teachings of the embodiments discussed below may be employed separately or in any suitable combination to produce desired results. Any use of any form of the terms “connect”, “engage”, “couple”, “attach”, or any other term describing an interaction between elements is not meant to limit the interaction to direct interaction between the elements and may also include indirect interaction between the elements described. The various characteristics mentioned above, as well as other features and characteristics described in more detail below, will be readily apparent to those skilled in the art upon reading the following detailed description of the embodiments, and by referring to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-5</figref> illustrate a multi-purpose downhole tool <b>10</b> that may be conveyed downhole into a borehole <b>19</b> on either a wireline or a pipe string. The pipe string may comprise either a tubing string or a drill string where the tool <b>10</b> is conveyed downhole during drilling operations. Not illustrated in the figures is a control system for controlling the downhole tool <b>10</b> from the surface. The control system may comprise a processor located on the surface and capable of communicating with the tool <b>10</b> or located downhole in the tool <b>10</b>. The processor gives instructions to a controller located downhole for operating the tool <b>10</b>. The controller may be any suitable controller or controllers for operating the tool <b>10</b> as described below.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The tool <b>10</b> further comprises a pump <b>22</b>. The pump <b>22</b> may be a centrifugal pump, a piston pump, or any other suitable type of fluid/gas pump. The pump <b>22</b> may also be a reversible pump such that flow through the pump <b>22</b> may be reversed without moving or changing the pump <b>22</b> itself. The pump <b>22</b> may be powered by any suitable means such as at least one of a power conduit through a wireline connection, downhole batteries, or a downhole generator.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the tool <b>10</b> comprises packers <b>12</b> for isolating an interval <b>14</b> of a downhole formation <b>16</b> traversed by the borehole <b>19</b>. The packers <b>12</b> may comprise what are commonly referred to as “straddle packers” because they “straddle” and isolate the desired interval <b>14</b> of the formation <b>16</b>. The packers <b>12</b> may also be located any suitable distance apart from each other. As a non-limiting example, the packers <b>12</b> may be between one meter to thirty meters apart. However, the packers <b>12</b> may be other distances apart as well depending on the desired operating parameters of the tool <b>10</b>. The tool <b>10</b> may also comprise more than two packers <b>12</b> for isolating more than one formation interval at one time. The packers <b>12</b> may also be made of any suitable material for forming a seal between the tool <b>10</b> and the borehole wall <b>20</b>. As a non-limiting example, the packers <b>12</b> may be made of rubber. The packers <b>12</b> expand to form a seal against the borehole wall <b>20</b>. To expand the packers <b>12</b>, they may be “inflatable packers” that are expanded by filling the packers <b>12</b> using, e.g., borehole fluids, hydraulic fluids, or any other suitable type of inflation fluid. The packers <b>12</b> may alternatively be “compression-style” packers where the packers <b>12</b> are compressed along the longitudinal axis of the tool <b>10</b> to expand the packers <b>12</b> in the radial direction into sealing engagement with the borehole wall <b>20</b>. For purposes of this application, the packers <b>12</b> will be described as inflatable packers. However, compression-style packers or a combination of inflatable and compression-style packers may also be used.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The tool <b>10</b> further comprises at least two interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b>. The interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> are located between the inflatable packers <b>12</b> and provide fluid communication between the tool <b>10</b> and the fluid within the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. Although only two interval access ports are illustrated, the tool <b>10</b> may comprise as many interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> as appropriate for the operations of the tool <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Connecting the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> with the pump <b>22</b> is a fluid conduit system generally designated by numeral <b>28</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> may comprise interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> to each interval access port <b>24</b>,<b>26</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> may further comprise a packer flowline <b>34</b> providing fluid flow to each of the packers <b>12</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> may further comprise a main flowline <b>36</b> connecting the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> and the packer flowline <b>34</b> with the pump <b>22</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> may further comprise a discharge line <b>38</b> that discharges fluid from the tool <b>10</b> to outside the packed-off annulus <b>18</b>. Alternatively, the fluid in the discharge line <b>38</b> may be redirected with additional flowlines and valving to other tools or sections on the wireline or drillstring without being discharged to the borehole <b>19</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> need not be configured exactly as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-5</figref> but may be arranged in any suitable configuration depending on the space and operation requirements of a particular application. Although not illustrated, the fluid conduit system <b>28</b> may further comprise a collection chamber such as the fluid collection chamber <b>54</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> for collecting fluids pumped from the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. The fluid collection chamber may also be releasably connected to the downhole tool <b>10</b>. After fluid is collected into the chamber, the chamber may be closed and released from the tool <b>10</b> into the borehole <b>19</b> above the packed-off interval amiulus <b>18</b>. The fluid collection chamber may then be pumped by fluid in the borehole to the surface.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Also within the fluid conduit system <b>28</b> are valves for controlling fluid flow within the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-5</figref>, the fluid conduit system <b>28</b> comprises interval flowline valves <b>40</b>,<b>42</b> for controlling fluid communication between the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> and the pump <b>22</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> further comprises a packer flowline valve <b>44</b> for controlling fluid communication between the packers <b>12</b> and the pump <b>22</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> further comprises a main flowline valve <b>46</b> for controlling fluid communication between the pump <b>22</b> and the interval flowline <b>32</b>. The valves of the tool <b>10</b> may be any suitable type of valve for regulating flow through the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>. Although the valves are illustrated in certain locations within the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>, the valves may alternatively be located in any suitable location within the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The tool <b>10</b> also further comprises a sensor <b>48</b> for measuring the pressure of the fluid within the interval access flowline <b>30</b> and a sensor <b>50</b> for measuring the pressure of the fluid within the packer flowline <b>34</b>. The tool <b>10</b> may further comprise a sensor <b>52</b> for measuring additional properties of the fluid in the interval flowline <b>30</b>. For example, the sensor <b>52</b> may measure fluid resistivity or fluid temperature. The sensor <b>52</b> may measure other properties of the fluid in the interval flowline <b>30</b> as well. Alternatively, although not illustrated, the fluid conduit system <b>28</b> may comprise a cross-over flowline and a cross-over valve directing fluid from the interval flowline <b>32</b> to the interval flowline <b>30</b> to be measured by the sensors <b>48</b>,<b>52</b>. Also alternatively, the tool <b>10</b> may comprise additional sensors <b>48</b>,<b>52</b> on each of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-5</figref>, the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> are spaced apart in the axial direction of the tool <b>10</b> as designated by the direction arrow A. Alternatively, the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> may be spaced at the same level axially within the borehole <b>19</b>. Additionally, although not illustrated, the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> may be spaced apart azimuthally around the tool <b>10</b> within the borehole <b>19</b>. Alternatively, the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> may allow access azimuthally around the tool <b>10</b> for flowing fluid from azimuthally around the tool <b>10</b>. Also alternatively, although only two access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> are illustrated, alternative embodiments may have a plurality of access ports at a plurality of locations within the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the tool <b>10</b> is positioned at the interval <b>14</b> of the formation <b>16</b>. Both the interval flowline valves <b>40</b>,<b>42</b> are closed and the packer flowline valve <b>44</b> is opened providing fluid communication between the main flowline <b>36</b> and the inside of the packers <b>12</b>. Additionally, although not shown, a valve may close fluid flow through the main flowline <b>36</b> below the tool <b>10</b>. The outlet of the pump <b>22</b> is then directed into the main flowline <b>36</b> as shown by direction arrow B and the packers <b>12</b> are inflated with fluid, e.g., from the borehole <b>19</b> pumped through discharge flowline <b>38</b>. The packers <b>12</b> are inflated until they form a seal between the tool <b>10</b> and the borehole wall <b>20</b>. When the desired inflation pressure is achieved, which is monitored by the sensor <b>50</b>, the pump <b>22</b> is stopped and the packer flowline valve <b>44</b> is closed.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates fluid sampling through the interval access port <b>24</b>. As illustrated, by opening the interval flowline valve <b>40</b> and by closing the interval flowline valve <b>42</b> and the packer flowline valve <b>44</b>, only the interval access port <b>24</b> is connected to the inlet of the pump <b>22</b> through the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>. Additionally, although not shown, a valve may close fluid flow through the main flowline <b>36</b> below the tool <b>10</b>. Alternatively, the main flowline valve <b>46</b> may be closed instead of the interval flowline valve <b>42</b>. The pump <b>22</b> is then started and fluid is extracted from the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b> and eventually the formation interval <b>14</b> and through the interval access port <b>24</b>. The fluid flows through the fluid conduit system <b>28</b> as illustrated by direction arrow C. The outlet of the pump <b>22</b> may be discharged to the borehole <b>19</b> through the discharge flowline <b>38</b>. As fluid flows through the interval flowline <b>30</b>, the interval flowline sensor <b>48</b> monitors, e.g., the resulting fluid pressure within the interval flowline <b>30</b>. The sensor(s) <b>52</b> monitor other properties of the fluid flowing through the interval flowline <b>30</b>. By way of non-limiting example, the sensor(s) <b>52</b> may monitor temperature, resistivity, or other fluid properties. When desired, the pump <b>22</b> may be stopped and the resulting “build-up” pressure may be monitored with the sensor <b>48</b>. Also, if desired, the outlet of the pump <b>22</b> may be directed into a fluid sample chamber (not shown) for fluid collection and retrieval. The fluid collection chamber may also be releasably connected to the downhole tool <b>10</b>. After fluid is collected into the chamber, the chamber may be closed and released from the tool <b>10</b> into the borehole <b>19</b> above the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. The fluid collection chamber may then be pumped by fluid in the borehole to the surface.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As illustrated, the interval access port <b>24</b> may be positioned close to the top of the packed-off interval. As a result, the fluid pumped through interval access port <b>24</b> may be the “lighter”, or less dense, fluids from the interval annulus <b>18</b> such as gas or oil as opposed to water. However, the location of the interval access port <b>24</b> may vary depending on the configuration of the tool <b>10</b> and the density of the fluids pumped through the interval access port <b>24</b>. Additionally, the variance of the density and resulting stratification of the fluids in the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b> depends on the composition of the fluids in the particular packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b> at any given time.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates fluid sampling through the interval access port <b>26</b>. As illustrated, by opening the interval flowline valve <b>42</b> and the main flowline valve <b>46</b> and by closing the interval flowline valve <b>40</b> and the packer flowline valve <b>44</b>, only the interval access port <b>26</b> is connected to the inlet of the pump <b>22</b> through the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>. Additionally, although not shown, a valve may close fluid flow through the main flowline <b>36</b> below the tool <b>10</b>. The pump <b>22</b> is then started and fluid is extracted from the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b> and eventually the formation interval <b>14</b> and through the interval access port <b>26</b>. The fluid flows though the fluid conduit system <b>28</b> as shown by direction arrow C. The outlet of the pump <b>22</b> may be discharged to the borehole <b>19</b> through the discharge flowline <b>38</b>. The interval flowline <b>32</b> as illustrated may not include the sensor <b>48</b> or sensor(s) <b>52</b> for measuring the pressure and other properties of the fluid in the interval flowline <b>32</b>. However, as described above, the tool <b>10</b> may comprise additional sensors <b>48</b>,<b>52</b> in the interval flowline <b>32</b> for measuring the pressure and other properties of the fluid in the interval flowline <b>32</b>. Also alternatively, although not illustrated, the fluid conduit system <b>28</b> may comprise a cross-over flowline and a cross-over valve directing fluid from the interval flowline <b>32</b> to the interval flowline <b>30</b> to be measured by the sensors <b>48</b>,<b>52</b> in the interval flowline <b>30</b>. When desired, the pump <b>22</b> may be stopped and the resulting “build-up” pressure may be monitored by the sensor <b>48</b>. Also, if desired, the outlet of the pump <b>22</b> may be directed into a fluid sample chamber (not shown) for subsequent fluid collection and retrieval to the surface. The fluid collection chamber may also be releasably connected to the downhole tool <b>10</b>. After fluid is collected into the chamber, the chamber may be closed and released from the tool <b>10</b> into the borehole <b>19</b> above the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. The fluid collection chamber may then be pumped by fluid in the borehole to the surface.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As illustrated, the interval access port <b>26</b> may be positioned close to the bottom of the packed-off interval. As a result, the fluid pumped through interval access port <b>26</b> may be the “heavier”, or more dense, fluids from the interval annulus <b>18</b> such as oil or water as opposed to gas. However, the location of the interval access port <b>26</b> may vary depending on the configuration of the tool <b>10</b> and the density of the fluids pumped through the interval access port <b>26</b>. Additionally, the variance of the density and resulting stratification of the fluids in the interval annulus <b>18</b> depends on the composition of the fluids in the particular interval annulus <b>18</b> at any given time.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the tool <b>10</b> may also operate to pump fluid into the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. As illustrated, by opening at least one of the interval flowline valves <b>40</b>,<b>42</b> and by closing the packer flowline valve <b>44</b>, at least one of the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> is connected to the outlet of the pump <b>22</b> through the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>. Additionally, although not shown, a valve may close fluid flow through the main flowline <b>36</b> below the tool <b>10</b>. The pump <b>22</b> is then operated to extract fluid from the borehole <b>19</b> outside the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b> through the discharge flowline <b>38</b>, with the outlet of the pump <b>22</b> directed as shown with direction arrow B. The pump <b>22</b> pumps the fluid through at least one of the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> into the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. The pump <b>22</b> may then be stopped and the pressure of the fluid in at least one of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> may be monitored by sensor <b>48</b> or multiple sensors <b>48</b> in each interval flowline <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Alternatively, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the tool <b>10</b> may operate to pump fluid into the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b> from a fluid chamber <b>54</b>. The embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is capable of performing the operations of the embodiment described above. Additionally, by opening at least one of the interval flowline valves <b>40</b>,<b>42</b> and by closing the packer flowline valve <b>44</b>, at least one of the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> is connected to the outlet of the pump <b>22</b> through the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>. The fluid chamber <b>54</b> comprises a piston <b>58</b> dividing the fluid chamber <b>54</b> into a first section <b>62</b> and a second section <b>66</b>. The first section <b>62</b> may contain well enhancement fluid. As used herein, well enhancement fluid may comprise well stimulation or treatment fluid. The well enhancement fluid may be any suitable fluid such as a fracturing fluid, anti-emulsion fluid, or any other type of well enhancement fluid. The second section <b>66</b> may be open to the hydrostatic pressure of the borehole <b>19</b> through a port <b>70</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> connects the fluid chamber <b>54</b> with the main flowline <b>36</b> through a chamber flowline <b>74</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> further comprises a chamber valve <b>78</b> for controlling fluid flow into and out of the fluid chamber <b>54</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> may further comprise a discharge valve <b>82</b> for controlling fluid flow through the discharge flowline <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">With the outlet of the pump <b>22</b> set as shown by direction arrow B, the chamber valve <b>78</b> is opened and the discharge valve <b>82</b> is closed. Additionally, although not shown, a valve may close fluid flow through the main flowline <b>36</b> below the tool <b>10</b>. The pump <b>22</b> is then started to pump well enhancement fluid from the fluid chamber <b>54</b>, out of at least one of the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b>, and into the formation interval annulus <b>18</b>. The pump <b>22</b> may then be stopped and the pressure of the fluid in at least one of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> may be monitored by sensor <b>48</b> or multiple sensors <b>48</b> in one or each of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> as described above. The sensor(s) <b>52</b> may also monitor other fluid properties in one or each of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> as described above. Alternatively, there may be more than one fluid chamber <b>54</b> and more than one pump <b>22</b> for pumping fluid into the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. The fluid chamber <b>54</b> may also be releasably connected to the downhole tool <b>10</b> for the retrieval of collected fluids. After fluid is collected into the chamber <b>54</b>, the chamber <b>54</b> may be closed and released from the tool <b>10</b> into the borehole <b>19</b> above the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. The fluid chamber <b>54</b> may then be pumped by fluid in the borehole to the surface.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Alternatively, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the tool <b>10</b> may operate to pump fluid “through” the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. The embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is capable of performing the operations of the embodiments described above. Additionally, by opening the interval flowline valves <b>40</b>,<b>42</b> and by closing the packer flowline valve <b>44</b>, the interval access ports <b>24</b>,<b>26</b> are connected to the pump <b>22</b> through the fluid conduit system <b>28</b>. The tool <b>10</b> may further comprise at least two fluid chambers <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> each comprising corresponding pistons <b>58</b>,<b>60</b> dividing the fluid chambers <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> into first sections <b>62</b>,<b>64</b> and second sections <b>66</b>,<b>68</b>, respectively. The first sections <b>62</b>,<b>64</b> may contain well enhancement fluid. The well enhancement fluid may comprise well stimulation or treatment fluid. The well enhancement fluid may be any suitable fluid such as a fracturing fluid, anti-emulsion fluid, or any other type of well enhancement fluid. The second sections <b>66</b>,<b>68</b> may be open to the hydrostatic pressure of the borehole <b>19</b> through ports <b>70</b>,<b>72</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> connects the fluid chambers <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> with the main flowline <b>36</b> through chamber flowlines <b>74</b>,<b>76</b>. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> further comprises chamber valves <b>78</b>,<b>80</b> for controlling fluid flow into and out of the fluid chambers <b>54</b>,<b>56</b>, respectively. The fluid conduit system <b>28</b> further comprises a discharge valve <b>82</b> for controlling fluid flow through the discharge flowline <b>38</b>. The fluid conduit system may further comprise an additional discharge flowline <b>84</b> and discharge valve <b>86</b> for controlling fluid flow through the discharge flowline <b>84</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">With the outlet of the pump <b>22</b> set as shown by direction arrow B, the chamber valves <b>78</b>,<b>80</b> are opened, the discharge valves <b>82</b>,<b>86</b> are closed, and the main flowline valve <b>46</b> is closed. Additionally, although not shown, a valve may close fluid flow through the main flowline <b>36</b> below the tool <b>10</b>. The pump <b>22</b> is started to pump well enhancement fluid from the fluid chamber <b>54</b>, out of the interval access port <b>24</b>, and into the formation interval annulus <b>18</b>. The well enhancement fluid then flows “though” the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b> and into the interval access port <b>26</b> where it then flows into the fluid chamber <b>56</b>. The pump <b>22</b> may then be stopped and the pressure of the fluid in at least one of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> may be monitored by sensor <b>48</b> or multiple sensors <b>48</b> in one or each of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> as described above. The sensor(s) <b>52</b> may also monitor other fluid properties in one or each of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Additionally, the outlet of the pump <b>22</b> may be reversed to flow as illustrated by direction arrow C. The pump <b>22</b> is started to pump well enhancement fluid from the fluid chamber <b>56</b>, out of the interval access port <b>26</b>, and into the formation interval annulus <b>18</b>. The well enhancement fluid then flows “though” the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b> and into the interval access port <b>24</b> where it then flows back into the fluid chamber <b>54</b>. The pump <b>22</b> may then be stopped and the pressure of the fluid in at least one of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> may be monitored by sensor <b>48</b> or multiple sensors <b>48</b> in one or each of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> as described above. The sensor(s) <b>52</b> may also monitor other fluid properties in one or each of the interval flowlines <b>30</b>,<b>32</b> as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The reversible “flow through” process described above may be repeated as many times as desired. Alternatively, the tool <b>10</b> may comprise any number of the fluid chambers <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> with the fluid chambers <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> containing the same or different well enhancement fluids. Also, the tool <b>10</b> may comprise additional pumps <b>22</b> pumping fluid through the additional fluid chambers <b>54</b>,<b>56</b>. At least one of the fluid chambers <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> may also be releasably connected to the downhole tool <b>10</b> for the retrieval of collected fluids. After fluid is collected into the chamber <b>54</b> and/or <b>56</b>, the chamber <b>54</b> and/or <b>56</b> may be closed and released from the tool <b>10</b> into the borehole <b>19</b> above the packed-off interval annulus <b>18</b>. The fluid chamber <b>54</b> and/or <b>56</b> may then be pumped by fluid in the borehole <b>19</b> to the surface.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">With respect to all of the embodiments described, the sensors <b>48</b>,<b>50</b>,<b>52</b> may collect data on the operation of the tool <b>10</b>, the annulus fluid, and/or the well enhancement fluid. This data may be stored locally within the tool <b>10</b> for retrieval once the tool <b>10</b> is removed from the borehole <b>19</b>. Additionally or alternatively, all of the embodiments of the tool <b>10</b> may incorporate the use of at least one writeable and readable data storage unit, or data carrier <b>88</b>, capable of flow within the borehole annulus from the tool <b>10</b> to the surface.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The at least one data carrier <b>88</b> is a data storage device that can be directly or remotely written to and read. The data carrier <b>88</b> preferably comprises a circuit including a data chip and an antenna encapsulated to protect circuit from the fluid flow. A suitable data carrier may be similar in construction to commercially available non-contact identification transponders, for example the AVID identity tags or AVID industrial RFID transponders available from AVID. These identity tags and transponders may comprise an integrated circuit and coil capacitor hermetically sealed in biocompatible glass. For example, the identity tags and transponders may only be 0.45 inches by 0.08 inches, weigh approximately 0.0021 oz., and carry 96 bits. The tag may not have an internal power source, and instead be powered by RF energy from a reader, which generates a 125 KHz radio signal. When the tag is within the electromagnetic field of the reader, the tag transmits its encoded data to the reader, where it can be decoded and stored. Typical read distances range from 4.125 inches (10 cm) to about 10.25 inches (26 cm), and read times are less than 40 msec. The data carrier <b>88</b> may also be any other suitable type of data storage device that can be directly or remotely written to and read.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The tool <b>10</b> also includes at least one writing device <b>90</b> for writing to the data carriers <b>88</b>. The writing device <b>90</b> may directly write to the data carriers <b>88</b> or may be a remote writing device that remotely writes data to the data carriers <b>88</b>. The data carriers <b>88</b> also interact with a reading device <b>92</b> for reading the data carriers <b>88</b>. The reading device <b>92</b> may directly read the data from the data carriers <b>88</b> or may be a remote reading device for remotely reading the data carriers <b>88</b> as they pass the reading device <b>92</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The data written on the data carriers <b>88</b> may also include ordering or sequencing data as well as information data, so that the information data can be properly reassembled. Because spacing between the data carriers <b>88</b> can vary, and in fact the data carriers <b>88</b> can arrive at the reading device <b>92</b> out of sequence, the ordering or sequencing information allows the data to be reassembled correctly. The data may also be redundantly written on at least two data carriers <b>88</b>, to reduce the risk of lost data if some data carriers <b>88</b> become lost or damaged.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a schematic view of a drilling rig incorporating the data carriers <b>88</b>. The drilling rig includes a derrick <b>100</b> with a pipe string <b>102</b>, which may be a drilling string, extending to the tool <b>10</b> in the borehole <b>19</b>. Drilling mud or fluid is circulated down the pipe string <b>102</b> and returns in the borehole annulus surrounding the pipe string <b>102</b>. Although <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates the tool <b>10</b> being on a drill string <b>102</b>, the tool <b>10</b> may also be located on a wireline or a work string.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">At least one data carrier <b>88</b> is circulated in the annulus fluid. Data may be written to the at least one data carrier <b>88</b> directly or remotely as described above with data from at least one of the sensors <b>48</b>,<b>50</b>,<b>52</b>. Other downhole sensors may also write data to the at least one data carrier <b>88</b>. For example, data related to formation pressure, porosity, and resistivity may be collected and written to the at least one data carrier <b>88</b>. There may also be more than one data carrier <b>88</b> for transporting data from the sensors <b>48</b>,<b>50</b>,<b>52</b>. The process of writing data may clear the memory of the data carrier <b>88</b>, or a separate eraser <b>116</b> may be provided to clear previously recorded data. The at least one data carrier <b>88</b> may then be placed in the fluid conduit system <b>28</b> of the tool <b>10</b> and pumped out of the discharge line <b>38</b> into the annulus above the tool <b>10</b> in the borehole <b>19</b>. The at least one data carrier <b>88</b> then flows with the drilling fluid back up the borehole <b>19</b> in the space surrounding the drilling string <b>102</b>. At the top of the well the fluid is drawn off in a conduit <b>118</b>. A data reader <b>120</b> may then read the data from the at least one data carrier <b>88</b>. There may also be a data eraser <b>122</b> provided to erase the at least one data carrier <b>88</b> as it or they flow in the fluid through the conduit <b>118</b>. A separator or shaker table <b>124</b> can collect the at least one data carrier <b>88</b> from the fluid for reuse.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The drilling rig <b>100</b> may also be configured for two way communication so that in addition to permitting information about the underground conditions to be communicated to the surface, instructions from the surface can be communicated to the tool <b>10</b>. A data writer <b>126</b> can be provided at the surface for writing data to at least one data carrier <b>88</b> either before the at least one carrier <b>88</b> is introduced into the borehole fluid or after the at least one data carrier <b>88</b> is introduced into the fluid. The tool <b>10</b> would then also be provided with a data reader <b>128</b> to read the data on the at least one data carrier <b>88</b> as it or they reach the tool <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">While specific embodiments have been illustrated and described, modifications can be made by one skilled in the art without departing from the spirit or teaching of this invention. The embodiments as described are exemplary only and are not limiting. Many variations and modifications are possible and are within the scope of the invention. Accordingly, the scope of protection is not limited to the embodiments described, but is only limited by the claims that follow, the scope of which shall include all equivalents of the subject matter of the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is: </us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A multi-purpose downhole tool comprising:
<claim-text>packers for isolating an interval of a downhole formation traversed by a borehole to form a packed-off interval annulus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a reversible pump;</claim-text>
<claim-text>more than one interval access port located between said packers providing fluid communication with fluid in the packed-off interval annulus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fluid conduit system comprising interval flowlines, each interval flowline associated with one of said interval access ports, said fluid conduit system providing fluid communication between said interval access ports and said reversible pump; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>valves for controlling fluid communication between said interval access ports and said reversible pump.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> where said tool is conveyable downhole on a wireline.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> where said tool is conveyable downhole on a pipe string.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a sensor for obtaining a property of the fluid in said fluid conduit system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> where the interval access ports are spaced apart azimuthally within the borehole.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> where the interval access ports are spaced apart axially within the borehole.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a fluid chamber, said reversible pump being able to move fluid between said fluid chamber and the packed-off interval annulus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said fluid chamber is releasably coupled to the downhole tool, is capable of collecting fluids, and is capable of being released from the downhole tool for retrieval at the surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising more than one fluid chamber, said reversible pump being able to move fluid from one fluid chamber, through the packed-off interval annulus, and into another fluid chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a writable and readable data carrier capable of flowing in a fluid flow;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data writer capable of writing data to said data carrier; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data reader capable of reading data from said data carrier.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The multi-purpose downhole tool of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said reversible pump is operated by power supplied by at least one of surface power, a battery, and a generator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method comprising:
<claim-text>lowering a tool into a borehole;</claim-text>
<claim-text>sealing off an interval of the borehole with inflatable packers to form a packed-off interval annulus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>pumping fluid from the packed-off interval annulus with a reversible pump through a first interval access port located between said inflatable packers and into a first interval flowline; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>pumping fluid from the packed-off interval annulus with said reversible pump through a second interval access port located between said inflatable packers and into a second interval flowline.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising determining the pressure of the fluid in said first interval flowline.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising determining the pressure of the fluid in said second interval flowline.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising collecting fluid pumped into at least one of said first and second interval access ports into a fluid chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>releasing said fluid chamber from the downhole tool; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>retrieving said fluid chamber to the surface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising pumping fluid into the interval with said reversible pump through at least one of said first and second interval access ports.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising determining a property of the fluid in at least one of said first and second interval flowlines.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising pumping a well enhancement fluid into the interval with said reversible pump.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>providing a writable and readable data carrier capable of flowing in a fluid flow;</claim-text>
<claim-text>writing data to said data carrier with a data writer at a first location;</claim-text>
<claim-text>flowing said data carrier from said first location to a second location; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>reading data from said data carrier with a data reader at said second location.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising operating said reversible pump with power supplied by at least one of surface power, a battery, and a generator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A method comprising:
<claim-text>lowering a tool into a borehole;</claim-text>
<claim-text>sealing off an interval of the borehole with inflatable packers to form a packed-off interval annulus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>pumping fluid from the packed-off interval annulus with a reversible pump through a first interval access port located between said inflatable packers and into a first interval flowline;</claim-text>
<claim-text>pumping fluid from the packed-off interval annulus with a reversible pump through a second interval access port located between said inflatable packers and into a second interval flowline; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>pumping fluid with said reversible pump from a first fluid chamber, through the packed off interval annulus, and into a second fluid chamber.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> further comprising determining the pressure of the fluid in said first interval flowline.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> further comprising determining the pressure of the fluid in said second interval flowline.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> further comprising collecting fluid pumped into at least one of said first and second interval access ports into at least one of said first and second fluid chambers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>releasing at least one of said first and second fluid chambers from the downhole tool; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>retrieving at least one of said first and second fluid chambers to the surface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> where pumping fluid through the packed-off interval annulus comprises flowing fluid into the packed-off interval annulus through said first interval access port and out of the packed-off interval annulus through said second interval access port.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> where pumping fluid through the packed-off interval annulus comprises flowing fluid into the packed-off interval annulus through said second interval access port and out of the packed-off interval annulus through said first interval access port.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> further comprising controlling the flow of fluids through said first and second interval access ports using valves.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> where said fluid in said first fluid chamber is a well enhancement fluid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>providing a writable and readable data carrier capable of flowing in a fluid flow;</claim-text>
<claim-text>writing data to said data carrier with a data writer at a first location;</claim-text>
<claim-text>flowing said data carrier from said first location to a second location; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>reading data from said data carrier with a data reader at said second location.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> further comprising operating said reversible pump with power supplied by at least one of surface power, a battery, and a generator.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
