<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298269-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298269</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11202702</doc-number>
<date>20050812</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-019761</doc-number>
<date>20050127</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>201</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>08</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>14</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3405721</main-classification>
<further-classification>3405728</further-classification>
<further-classification>3406861</further-classification>
<further-classification>235492</further-classification>
<further-classification>34820799</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Image taking apparatus having selectively enabled IC tags</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5587700</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Williams</name>
<date>19961200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340541</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6008727</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Want et al.</name>
<date>19991200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3405721</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6127938</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Friedman</name>
<date>20001000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3406936</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0227550</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Manico et al.</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>34820799</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-174578</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3405721-5728</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3406261</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3406862</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3406864</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34820799</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235375</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235492</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060163339</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060727</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Teramoto</last-name>
<first-name>Tougo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wakayama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ban</last-name>
<first-name>Shinichi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kobe</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nanba</last-name>
<first-name>Katsuyuki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sakai</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hamamura</last-name>
<first-name>Toshihiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sidley Austin LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Konica Minolta Photo Imaging, Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hofsass</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffery</first-name>
<department>2612</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Lau</last-name>
<first-name>Hoi C.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A metallic sliding cover that covers an image taking lens system when an image taking apparatus is not in use is attached at the front side of the image taking apparatus, and an IC tag of a type that has an internal power supply and an IC tag of a type that has not an internal power supply are stuck to the front side of the image taking apparatus. A plural number of IC tags are alternatively covered with the sliding cover by movement of the cover. Thereby, communication only by one IC tag becomes possible when the image taking apparatus is in use; meanwhile, communication only by the other IC tag becomes possible when the image taking apparatus is not in use. As a result, interference between a plurality of IC tags having mutually different characteristics can be prevented.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="114.05mm" wi="120.31mm" file="US07298269-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="232.16mm" wi="132.50mm" file="US07298269-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="225.38mm" wi="169.08mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298269-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="204.47mm" wi="137.24mm" file="US07298269-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="179.92mm" wi="97.03mm" file="US07298269-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="201.25mm" wi="163.49mm" file="US07298269-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="114.38mm" wi="120.82mm" file="US07298269-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is based on the application No. 2005-19761 filed in Japan, the contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to an image taking apparatus equipped with a plural number of IC tags.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the field of physical distribution management, instead of a bar code label stuck on a commodity, an IC tag by which information transmission through radio communication is possible (which is also called a wireless tag) has become used. As an application of the IC tag, a technology of acquiring information of a photographic subject from an IC tag held by the subject by using a digital camera has been proposed.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">On the other hand, IC tags are divided into one type that has not an internal power supply in the IC tag but transmits information memorized in the IC tag by using the energy of the radio wave sent from an external reader/writer (this type is called the passive type hereafter), and another type that has an internal power supply in the IC tag and can actively transmit information memorized in the IC tag (this type is called the active type hereafter).</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The passive type IC tag has an advantage in that it can communicate if the power supply of an apparatus having the IC tag malfunctions (when a battery is not loaded, for example), or even if the apparatus is broken. On the contrary, the passive type IC tag has disadvantages in that it generally provides a short communication distance and has a small data capacity to be memorized. Although the active type IC tag has advantages, as compared to the passive type IC tag, in that its communication distance is long and has a large data capacity to be memorized, it is expensive.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Since the active and passive type IC tags having mutually different characteristics have merits and demerits, respectively, it may be reasonable to use both types together in order to utilize advantages of them. However, if both type IC tags are merely used together, a problem may arise that interference occurs by both type IC tags responded to the radio wave from the reader, so that the reader side cannot receive correct information from the IC tags.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In order to solve problems described above, the image taking apparatus comprises: a movable member for moving between a first position and a second position in accordance with a condition of the image taking apparatus; a first IC tag for memorizing information concerning the imaging taking apparatus and that is disposed at a position where is covered with the movable member at said second position and where is not covered with the movable member at said first position; and a second IC tag for memorizing information concerning the imaging taking apparatus and that is disposed at a position where is covered with the movable member at said first position and where is not covered with the movable member at said second position.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In the following description, like parts are designated by like reference numbers throughout the several drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view showing the external structure of an image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view showing the external structure of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram showing the functional structure of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a plan view showing the structure of principal parts of an IC tag T<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a figure for explaining information memorized in the IC tag T<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a plan view showing the structure of principal parts of the IC tag T<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a figure for explaining information memorized in the IC tag T<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a flow chart showing fundamental operation of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a conceptual diagram showing the structure of an information transmission system <b>7</b> having the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="h-0005" num="0000">&lt;Structure of the Image Taking Apparatus&gt;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> are perspective views showing the external structure of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows the status when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is in use, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the status when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is not in use.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is composed as a digital camera, for example, of which a metallic front cover <b>11</b> and a metallic rear cover <b>12</b> form a housing.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Two apertures H<b>1</b> and H<b>2</b> are formed on the front cover <b>11</b>. The aperture H<b>1</b> is formed so that it guides the light from a photographic subject to an image taking lens system <b>30</b>, and a transparent window <b>13</b> made from a plastic, for example, is fit on the aperture. Similarly, a transparent window <b>14</b> made from a plastic is fit on the aperture H<b>2</b>. Behind the window <b>14</b>, both a finder <b>15</b> and a photoflash <b>16</b> are equipped. At the rear side of the window <b>14</b>, an IC tag T<b>1</b> which will be described later is stuck between positions of the finder <b>15</b> and the photoflash <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">On the front cover <b>11</b>, a metallic sliding cover <b>17</b> which is movable in the direction of the Y-axis (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) is attached. While the sliding cover <b>17</b> is placed at the use position P<b>1</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is in use for shooting a subject, for example, when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is not in use it is placed at the nonuse position P<b>2</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) that is located above the use position P<b>1</b>, so that it covers the apertures H<b>1</b> and H<b>2</b>. Accordingly, when the sliding cover <b>17</b> moves from the use position P<b>1</b> to the nonuse position P<b>2</b>, a seal <b>20</b> stuck on the front cover <b>11</b> is exposed. At the rear side of the seal <b>20</b>, an IC tag T<b>2</b> (which will be described later) having different characteristics from the IC tag T<b>1</b> is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">On the upper surface of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>, a release button <b>18</b> for ordering shooting and a power switch <b>19</b> for turning on and off the power supply of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> are equipped.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">On the side of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>, a grip portion <b>21</b> for a photographer to hold the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is formed. The grip portion <b>21</b> works as a rid that covers a battery room in the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> in which a battery is loaded.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram showing the functional structure of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>, the light from the photographic subject enters into an image sensor <b>33</b> through the image taking lens system <b>30</b> that is equipped behind the window <b>13</b>. The image taking lens system <b>30</b> has a zoom lens <b>31</b> and a focusing lens <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The image sensor <b>33</b> is equipped with an aperture diaphragm and an image sensing device that is composed as a CCD, for example, and performs photoelectric conversion of the light image of the photographic subject formed by the image taking lens system <b>30</b>, so as to generate an image signal.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The image signal generated by the image sensor <b>33</b> is inputted into an image processor <b>34</b>. Then, in the image processor <b>34</b>, processes such as A/D conversion, white balance correction, and gamma correction are performed. The image data processed in the image processor <b>34</b> is recorded in a recording medium (a memory card <b>9</b>, for example) which is detachable to the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>, or displayed on an LCD (Liquid Crystal Display) <b>35</b>. By the LCD <b>35</b>, preview displaying of the photographic subject or replay displaying of the recorded image is possible.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">An exposure controller <b>36</b> controls the aperture diaphragm in the image sensor <b>33</b> and the exposure time of the image sensing device based on the control signal from a general controller <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">A focus controller <b>37</b> drives the focusing lens <b>32</b> based on a focus detection result obtained by the general controller <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">A zoom control portion <b>38</b> drives the zoom lens <b>31</b> in order to change the focal length of the image taking lens system <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">An operation portion <b>39</b> has the release button <b>18</b> and the a power switch <b>19</b> both of which are already described, a record/replay mode selection switch equipped on the rear cover <b>12</b> (not illustrated), and others, and accepts operational inputs generated by a photographer.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The general controller <b>40</b> has a CPU which work as a computer and a memory so that it can totally control each part of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>. The general controller <b>40</b> also controls information transmission from the IC tag T<b>1</b> as will be described later.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">A power source <b>41</b> supplies electric power to each portion of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> by using a battery.</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">&lt;IC Tags T<b>1</b> and T<b>2</b>&gt;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a plan view showing the structure of principal parts of an IC tag T<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The IC tag T<b>1</b> has a memory portion <b>50</b> that is composed as an IC chip and a spiral antenna <b>51</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The memory portion <b>50</b> memorizes information concerning the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> and information concerning a user as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The IC tag T<b>1</b> is an active type one in which a power supply portion <b>52</b> with a battery is equipped. The IC tag T<b>1</b> has advantages, as compared to the passive type IC tag T<b>2</b> that will be described later, in that it enables long distance communication and in that information volume memorized in the memory portion <b>50</b> is large. Further, the IC tag T<b>1</b> memorizes information that becomes necessary when connected with a network and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The IC tag T<b>1</b> can, by using a control signal from the general controller <b>40</b> that is electrically connected to the power supply portion <b>52</b>, select whether information transmission from the antenna <b>51</b> is carried out or not.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The IC tag T<b>1</b> is equipped at the position where it is covered by the sliding cover <b>17</b> when the sliding cover is at the nonuse position P<b>2</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) and where it is not covered by the sliding cover <b>17</b> when the sliding cover is at the use position P<b>1</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). Thereby, when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is in operation and the sliding cover <b>17</b> is at the use position P<b>1</b>, it becomes possible for the IC tag T<b>1</b> to communicate. Meanwhile, when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is not in operation and the sliding cover <b>17</b> is at the nonuse position P<b>2</b>, it becomes impossible for the IC tag T<b>1</b> to communicate, since the radio wave is shielded by the metallic sliding cover <b>17</b> that covers the IC tag T<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a plan view showing the structure of principal parts of the IC tag T<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The IC tag T<b>2</b> has a memory portion <b>60</b> that memorizes information concerning the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, and an antenna <b>61</b> that is similar to the one in the IC tag T<b>1</b>. The IC tag T<b>2</b> is composed as a passive type IC tag that is not equipped with a power supply portion. Therefore, in the IC tag T<b>2</b>, information stored in the memory portion <b>60</b> is transmitted by using the energy of the radio wave that is sent from an external reader that reads information concerning the IC tag T<b>2</b>. The IC tag T<b>2</b> can memorize a smaller information volume and provides a shorter communication range, as compared to the IC tag T<b>1</b>. Therefore, in the IC tag T<b>2</b>, only the product information of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>, for example, as the minimum information required for identification of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> and for others (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>) is memorized, among all of the memorized information concerning the IC tag T<b>1</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>). On the other hand, since the IC tag T<b>2</b> can communicate by the radio wave from the reader regardless of the operation status of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>, even when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> cannot operate by any trouble, for example, the reader can receive the identification information of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> and the like (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>), so that such information can be utilized for services such as repair.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The IC tag T<b>2</b> is equipped at the position where it is covered by the sliding cover <b>17</b> when the sliding cover is at the use position P<b>1</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) and where it is not covered by the sliding cover <b>17</b> when the sliding cover is at the nonuse position P<b>2</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Thereby, when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is not in operation and the sliding cover <b>17</b> is at the nonuse position P<b>2</b>, it becomes possible for the IC tag T<b>2</b> to communicate. Meanwhile, when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is in operation and the sliding cover <b>17</b> is at the use position P<b>1</b>, it becomes impossible for the IC tag T<b>2</b> to communicate, since the radio wave is shielded by the metallic sliding cover <b>17</b> that covers the IC tag T<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Operation of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> having the IC tags T<b>1</b> and T<b>2</b> which have mutually different characteristics is described in the following.</p>
<p id="h-0007" num="0000">&lt;Operation of the Image Taking Apparatus <b>1</b>&gt;</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a flow chart showing fundamental operation of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>. The operation is performed by the general controller <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">At the step S<b>1</b>, whether the power supply of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> has been turned on or not by the action of a photographer on the power switch <b>19</b> is judged. When the power supply is turned on, after the sliding cover <b>17</b> is moved to the use position P<b>1</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> by the photographer, the process advances to the step S<b>2</b>. When the power supply is not turned on, the process advances to the step S<b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">At the step S<b>2</b>, the power source <b>41</b> supplies electric power to the inside of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">At the step S<b>3</b>, information transmission by the IC tag T<b>1</b> is performed. More specifically, the general controller <b>40</b> activates the transmission function of the IC tag T<b>1</b> so that information memorized in the memory portion <b>50</b> (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) can be transmitted. Thereby, it becomes possible for an external apparatus that has a reader to read information stored in the memory portion <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">At the step S<b>4</b>, usual shooting, replay of recorded photographed images, and others are performed by the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">At the step S<b>5</b>, whether the power supply of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> has been turned on or not by the action of the photographer on the power switch <b>19</b> is judged. When the power supply is turned off, after the sliding cover <b>17</b> is moved to the nonuse position P<b>2</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> by the photographer, the process advances to the step S<b>6</b>. When the power supply is not turned off, the process returns to the step S<b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">At the step S<b>6</b>, information transmission by the IC tag T<b>1</b> is stopped. More specifically, the general controller <b>40</b> deactivates the transmission function of the IC tag T<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">At the step S<b>7</b>, electric power supply to the inside of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is stopped.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">At the step S<b>8</b>, information transmission by the IC tag T<b>2</b> is performed. More specifically, information memorized in the memory portion <b>60</b> of the IC tag T<b>2</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>) becomes ready for transmission. Thereby, it becomes possible for the external apparatus that has the reader to read information in the memory portion <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Through operation described above, when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is not in use where the power supply is turned off, communication only by the passive type IC tag T<b>2</b> becomes possible. On the other hand, when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is in use where the power supply is turned on, the IC tag T<b>2</b> is covered by the metallic sliding covers <b>17</b>, so that communication only by the active type IC tag T<b>1</b> becomes possible. Namely, since the sliding cover <b>17</b> that covers the image taking lens system <b>30</b> moves only to one of two positions alternatively between the use position P<b>1</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) and the nonuse position P<b>2</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), one of the two IC tags is always covered by the sliding cover <b>17</b>, so that the radio wave is shielded. Thereby, the problem that interference occurs if both of the IC tags T<b>1</b> and T<b>2</b> respond simultaneously to the radio wave from the reader so that the reader side cannot receive correct information from the IC tags can be avoided.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">An example of information transmission systems to which the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> as described above is explained next.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a conceptual diagram showing the structure of an information transmission system <b>7</b> having the image taking apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">While the information transmission system <b>7</b> is equipped with the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> described above, it is also equipped with a digital television (DTV) <b>70</b> that is connected to the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> for communication through a network NW, a LAN, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The DTV <b>70</b> is equipped with a display screen <b>71</b>, as well as a reader <b>72</b> that can read information stored in the IC tags T<b>1</b> and T<b>2</b>. For the DTV <b>70</b>, when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is in operation, the IC tag T<b>2</b> is covered by the sliding cover <b>17</b> as described already, so that information only from the IC tag T<b>1</b> can be acquired.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">According to the information transmission system <b>7</b> described above, after the DTV <b>70</b> has acquired and identified information concerning network connection (such as a user ID and a password as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) from the IC tag T<b>1</b>, for example, it becomes possible for the system to receive a photographed image memorized by the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> through the network NW and to display the image on the display screen <b>71</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">When a plurality of image taking apparatus <b>1</b> that are equipped with a plurality of IC tags T<b>1</b> and T<b>2</b> exist in the neighborhood of the DTV <b>70</b>, the DTV <b>70</b> may receive information from the plurality of image taking apparatus, which produces interfere. In such a case, in order to avoid interference, it is necessary to choose the image taking apparatus with which the DTV <b>70</b> should communicate. Thus, in the information transmission system <b>7</b>, by turning on the power supply of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> that should be communicated with and by opening its sliding cover <b>17</b>, while by turning off power supplies of unnecessary image taking apparatus <b>1</b> that should not be communicated with and by closing their sliding covers <b>17</b>, it becomes possible for the DTV <b>70</b> to communicate only with the IC tag T<b>1</b> of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> of which the power supply is turned on, enabling the solution to the interference problem. For example, if information concerning network connection is memorized in the IC tag T<b>1</b>, only the image from the specified image taking apparatus <b>1</b> can be replayed by the DTV <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">According to the structure and the operation of the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> as described above, since information transmission of one of the two IC tags is disabled by the sliding cover that is opened or shut when the image taking apparatus is in use or not in use, interference in information transmission caused by a plural number of IC tags can be prevented. Since the image taking apparatus is equipped also with the passive type IC tag, even when the active type IC cannot communicate, in such a case as a battery is not loaded in the image taking apparatus or the image taking apparatus fails, it is possible for the external reader that is equipped, for example, in test equipment of a service center, to read camera identifying information that is required for image taking apparatus repair and the like.</p>
<p id="h-0008" num="0000">&lt;Alternatives&gt;</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">According to the image taking apparatus in the embodiment described above, the power supply is turned on and off by the power switch <b>19</b>. However, the power supply may be turned on and off in synchronization with opening and closing of the sliding cover. That is, a structure may be used wherein the power supply is automatically turned on when the sliding cover <b>17</b> is at the use position P<b>1</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and the power supply is automatically turned off when the sliding cover <b>17</b> is at the nonuse position P<b>2</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The IC tag T<b>1</b> in the embodiment described above receives electric power from the power supply in the IC tag T<b>1</b>. However, the IC tag T<b>1</b> may receive electric power from the power source <b>41</b> in the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Two IC tags T<b>1</b> and T<b>2</b> in embodiments described above are the combination of the active type and the passive type. However, type combination is not limited to the above, and two types of IC tags having mutually different frequency characteristics may be used instead. In this case, since the communication distance varies according to the frequency used, the frequency applied to the IC tag which can communicate when the image taking apparatus <b>1</b> is in use and in which information required for network connection is memorized may be set higher than the frequency applied to the other IC tag. Thereby, long distance communication becomes possible, so that convenience for network connection can be raised.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">In the embodiments described above, the status of each of IC tags T<b>1</b> and T<b>2</b> is switched between exposed and covered. As a movable member, the sliding cover <b>17</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) that covers the image taking lens system <b>30</b> and the photoflash <b>16</b> is used. However, a lens cover that covers only the image taking lens system may be used instead.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">According to these embodiments, interference by a plurality of IC tags can be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Since a plurality of IC tags having mutually different characteristics are used, a proper choice of the plurality of IC tags according to the operation status of the image taking apparatus, in use or not in use, becomes possible.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Furthermore, according to these embodiments, equipment space can be reduced by utilizing such members as the lens cover, and since communication by the IC tag covered by the metallic lens cover is shielded, interference can be prevented perfectly.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Although the present invention has been fully described by way of examples with reference to the accompanying drawings, it is to be noted that various change and modifications will be apparent to those skilled in the art. Therefore, unless otherwise such changes and modifications depart from the scope of the present invention, they should be construed as being including therein.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An image taking apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a movable member for moving between a first position and a second position in accordance with a condition of the image taking apparatus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first IC tag for memorizing information concerning the imaging taking apparatus and that is disposed at a position that is covered with the movable member at said second position and that is not covered with the movable member at said first position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second IC tag for memorizing information concerning the imaging taking apparatus and that is disposed at a position that is covered with the movable member at said first position and that is not covered with the movable member at said second position,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said movable member is positioned at said first position when the imaging taking apparatus is in use and that is positioned at said second position when the imaging taking apparatus is not in use.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said first IC tag and said second IC tag have mutually different characteristics.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said first IC tag has a power source and said second IC tag does not have a power source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein frequency characteristics of said first IC tag and said second IC tag are mutually different, and said first IC tag uses a frequency higher than one for said second IC tag.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the information amount memorized in said first IC tag is larger than the information amount memorized in said second IC tag.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said first IC tag memorizes information to connect the image taking apparatus to a network.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said movable member is a member for shielding a radio wave.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said movable member is a metallic cover.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An image taking apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a first IC tag for memorizing a first information concerning the imaging taking apparatus and that is capable of transmitting the first information to an external device when the image taking apparatus is in an operation state;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second IC tag for memorizing a second information concerning the imaging taking apparatus and that is capable of transmitting the second information to an external device when the image taking apparatus is not in an operation state; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switching member for switching between an operation of said first IC tag and that of said second IC tag.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said switching member is a power switch.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said switching member is a lens cover.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said first IC tag and said second IC tag have mutually different characteristics.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said first IC tag has a power source and said second IC tag does not have a power source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein frequency characteristics of said first IC tag and said second IC tag are mutually different, and said first IC tag uses a frequency higher than one for said second IC tag.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the information amount memorized in said first IC tag is larger than the information amount memorized in said second IC tag.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The image taking apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein said first IC tag memorizes information concerning to a network communication.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method of transmitting information concerned with an image taking apparatus by using a plurality of IC tags, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>setting the image taking apparatus in a first condition;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting information memorized in a first IC tag to an external device when the image taking apparatus is in first condition;</claim-text>
<claim-text>setting the image taking apparatus in a second condition; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting information memorized in a second IC tag to an external device when the image taking apparatus is in second condition,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first condition is in power on state and said second condition is in power off state.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of information transmitting according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein said first IC tag and said second IC tag have mutually different characteristics.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
