<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296622-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296622</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11070986</doc-number>
<date>20050303</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>308</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>E</section>
<class>21</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>43</main-group>
<subgroup>34</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1661054</main-classification>
<further-classification>1661051</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Labyrinth seal for pumping system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5588486</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Heinrichs</name>
<date>19961200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>1661055</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>166105-1055</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>166 50</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>166265</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>21017001</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>210520</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060196655</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060907</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wang</last-name>
<first-name>Chengbao</first-name>
<address>
<city>Oklahoma City</city>
<state>OK</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Crowe &amp; Dunlevy, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Wood Group ESP, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Oklahoma City</city>
<state>OK</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Mai</last-name>
<first-name>Lanna</first-name>
<department>3637</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Smith</last-name>
<first-name>Matthew J.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A seal section for a downhole pumping system includes a fluid exchange pathway and a rotatable gravity separator. The rotatable gravity separator preferably includes a chamber, a backwash inlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway and a backwash outlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway. The rotatable gravity separator further includes a weight that causes the rotatable gravity separator to remain in a substantially constant orientation with respect to the force of gravity.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="110.83mm" wi="206.84mm" file="US07296622-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="182.63mm" wi="172.80mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296622-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="214.29mm" wi="130.81mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296622-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="210.31mm" wi="177.80mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296622-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates generally to the field of downhole pumping systems, and more particularly to seal sections for use in horizontal downhole pumping systems.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Submersible pumping systems are often deployed into wells to recover petroleum fluids from subterranean reservoirs. Typically, a submersible pumping system includes a number of components, such as an electric motor coupled to one or more pump assemblies. In many cases, seal sections are placed between pumps and motors. Seal sections are designed to protect intricate internal motor components from harmful wellbore fluids. Seal sections are also used to accommodate the expansion of lubricants from the electric motor and act as a downthrust support during a pumping operation.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Equipment manufacturers have experimented with a number of different types of seal sections. Many seal sections employ an expandable bag or bellows that increases in volume as fluids move through the seal section. Although generally effective, the materials used to manufacture the expandable components are often susceptible to chemical breakdown under the inhospitable downhole environment. Other manufacturers have employed complex labyrinth systems that filter contaminated fluids with gravity-based traps. The labyrinth system often includes a series of ports and chambers that force contaminated fluids to travel upward, thereby allowing gravity to separate heavier contaminated fluids and solids from cleaner, less harmful fluids.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In many installations, modern labyrinth systems effectively filter contaminated fluids moving through the seal section. The success of existing labyrinth systems is, however, dependent on the proper orientation of the seal section with respect to the force of gravity. In non-vertical wells, it is particularly difficult to maintain the proper orientation of labyrinth systems in seal sections. During installation or use, the entire pumping system may rotate, thereby changing the relative positions of the various components within the labyrinth system. If, for example, the labyrinth system becomes inverted or even tipped horizontally, contaminants otherwise trapped by gravity in a proper installation may “fall” into lower portions of the seal section or pumping system. It is to these and other deficiencies in the prior art that the present invention is directed.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In a preferred embodiment, the present invention provides a seal section for a downhole pumping system that includes a fluid exchange pathway and a rotatable gravity separator. The rotatable gravity separator preferably includes a chamber, a backwash inlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway and a backwash outlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway. The rotatable gravity separator further includes a weight that causes the rotatable gravity separator to remain in a substantially constant orientation with respect to the force of gravity.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a front perspective view of a downhole pumping system in a non-vertical installation.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a side cross-sectional view of a seal section of the preferred embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side cross-sectional view of the rotatable gravity separator of the seal section of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a front perspective view of a downhole pumping system <b>100</b> attached to production tubing <b>102</b>. The downhole-pumping system <b>100</b> and production tubing <b>102</b> are disposed in a wellbore <b>104</b>, which is drilled for the production of a fluid such as water or petroleum. The downhole pumping system <b>100</b> is shown in a non-vertical well. This type of angled well is often referred to as a “horizontal” well.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">As used herein, the term “petroleum” refers broadly to all mineral hydrocarbons, such as crude oil, gas and combinations of oil and gas. The production tubing <b>102</b> connects the pumping system <b>100</b> to a wellhead <b>106</b> located on the surface. Although the pumping system <b>100</b> is primarily designed to pump petroleum products, it will be understood that the present invention can also be used to move other fluids. It will also be understood that, although each of the components of the pumping system <b>100</b> are primarily disclosed in a submersible application, some or all of these components can also be used in surface pumping operations.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The pumping system <b>100</b> preferably includes some combination of a pump assembly <b>108</b>, a motor assembly <b>110</b> and a seal section <b>112</b>. In a preferred embodiment, the motor assembly <b>110</b> is an electrical motor that receives its power from a surface-based supply. The motor assembly <b>110</b> converts the electrical energy into mechanical energy, which is transmitted to the pump assembly <b>108</b> by one or more shafts. The pump assembly <b>108</b> then transfers a portion of this mechanical energy to fluids within the wellbore, causing the wellbore fluids to move through the production tubing to the surface. In a particularly preferred embodiment, the pump assembly <b>108</b> is a turbomachine that uses one or more impellers and diffusers to convert mechanical energy into pressure head. In an alternative embodiment, the pump assembly <b>108</b> is a progressive cavity (PC) pump that moves wellbore fluids with one or more screws or pistons.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The seal section <b>112</b> shields the motor assembly <b>110</b> from mechanical thrust produced by the pump assembly <b>108</b>. The seal section <b>112</b> is also preferably configured to prevent the introduction of contaminants from the wellbore <b>104</b> into the motor assembly <b>110</b>. Although only one pump assembly <b>108</b>, seal section <b>112</b> and motor assembly <b>110</b> are shown, it will be understood that the downhole pumping system <b>100</b> could include additional pumps assemblies <b>108</b>, seals sections <b>112</b> or motor assemblies <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Turning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, shown therein is a side cross-sectional view of the seal section <b>112</b>. In a presently preferred embodiment, the seal section <b>112</b> is assembled from several separate pieces. The seal section preferably includes a head <b>114</b>, a base <b>116</b>, a thrust bearing assembly <b>118</b> and one or more labyrinth assemblies <b>120</b>. The head <b>114</b> and base <b>116</b> are preferably configured for connection to the pump assembly <b>108</b> and motor assembly <b>110</b>, respectively. The seal section <b>112</b> also includes a shaft <b>122</b> that transfers mechanical energy from the motor assembly <b>110</b> to the pump assembly <b>108</b>. The thrust bearing assembly <b>118</b> is preferably configured to limit axial movement of the shaft <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The seal section <b>112</b> also includes a fluid exchange pathway <b>124</b> that includes a series of ports, vents, recesses and channels (not separately designated) that permit the movement of fluid within the seal section <b>112</b> and between the motor assembly <b>110</b> and the pump assembly <b>108</b>. In the presently preferred embodiment, the seal section <b>112</b> is filled with a suitable lubricant before installation.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">During use, lubricants from the motor assembly <b>110</b> expand and move into the seal section <b>112</b>, thereby displacing a portion of the fluid in the seal section <b>112</b>. The displaced fluids from the seal section <b>112</b> are directed into the pump assembly <b>108</b>, vented to the wellbore <b>104</b> or contained within an expandable chamber (not shown). In the presently preferred embodiment, lubricants displaced from the seal section <b>112</b> are ported to the pump assembly <b>108</b> through the head <b>114</b>. As the motor assembly <b>110</b> cools, lubricants within the seal section <b>112</b> recede into the motor assembly <b>110</b>. Wellbore fluids are then drawn into the seal section <b>112</b> through the fluid exchange pathway <b>124</b> from the pump assembly <b>108</b> and mixed with clean lubricants. For the purposes of this disclosure, the movement of fluids out of the motor assembly <b>110</b> is referred to as “effluent.” In contrast, movement of fluids through the seal section <b>112</b> from the pump assembly <b>108</b> is herein referred to as “backwash.”</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">To prevent or mitigate the introduction of contaminants into the motor assembly <b>110</b> from backwashed wellbore fluids, the labyrinth assemblies <b>120</b> are placed in fluid communication with the fluid exchange pathway <b>124</b>. The labyrinth assemblies <b>120</b> preferably include a rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b>, one or more bearing assemblies <b>128</b>, one or more mechanical seals <b>130</b> and a housing <b>132</b>. The bearing assemblies <b>128</b> allow the labyrinth assemblies <b>120</b> to independently rotate with respect to the other components within the seal section <b>112</b>. In a particularly preferred embodiment, the bearing assemblies <b>128</b> are constructed using ball bearings. In an alternative embodiment, the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> rotates on hydrodynamic bearings. Although two labyrinth assemblies <b>120</b> are shown, it will be understood that fewer or additional labyrinth assemblies <b>120</b> could be employed. Furthermore, the labyrinth assemblies <b>120</b> could be used in combination with other types of seal devices, such as, for example, expandable bags or bellows (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring now also to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, shown therein is a close-up, cross-sectional view of one of the rotatable gravity separators <b>126</b>. The rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> is preferably configured as a closed-ended canister that includes an outer cylinder <b>134</b>, an inner cylinder <b>136</b> and end walls <b>135</b>, <b>137</b>. A chamber <b>138</b> is defined by the annular space between the coaxial outer and inner cylinders <b>134</b>, <b>136</b> and the end walls <b>135</b>, <b>137</b>. The outer cylinder <b>134</b> is preferably sized and configured to permit the movement of fluids between the outside wall of the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> and the inside wall of the housing <b>132</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). The inner cylinder <b>136</b> is preferably sized and configured to permit the movement of fluids between the inner cylinder <b>136</b> and the shaft <b>122</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> further includes a weight <b>140</b>, a backwash inlet <b>142</b> and a backwash outlet <b>144</b>. The weight <b>140</b> is preferably rigidly attached to the outer cylinder <b>134</b> inside the chamber <b>138</b>. In a preferred embodiment, the weight <b>140</b> is configured as a rectangular member that is longitudinally aligned with the length of the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b>. In this position, the weight <b>140</b> acts as a counter-balance that causes the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> to rotate to decrease its potential energy. The weight <b>140</b> causes the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> to remain in a substantially constant orientation with respect to the force of gravity. In an alternate preferred embodiment, the weight <b>140</b> is attached inside the chamber <b>138</b> to the inner cylinder <b>136</b>. In yet another alternate preferred embodiment, the weight <b>140</b> is secured to the outside of the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In the preferred embodiment, the backwash inlet <b>142</b> is positioned adjacent the weight <b>140</b> at the bottom of the chamber <b>138</b> and extends through the end wall <b>135</b>. In this position, the backwash fluids are introduced through the backwash inlet <b>142</b> into the bottom of the chamber <b>138</b>. The backwash outlet <b>144</b> is preferably located at the top of the chamber <b>138</b> on the opposite side of the chamber <b>138</b> and extends through the end wall <b>137</b>. The backwash outlet <b>144</b> is preferably angled to direct fluid leaving the top of the chamber <b>138</b> to the space adjacent the shaft <b>122</b>. The fluid leaving the backwash outlet <b>144</b> is partitioned from unfiltered fluid entering the chamber <b>138</b> by the mechanical seal <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As fluid passes through the chamber <b>138</b>, solids and heavier fluids are pulled down by the force of gravity and separated from the lighter lubricants, which rise to the top of the chamber <b>138</b>. Because the chamber <b>138</b> has a larger cross-section than the fluid exchange pathway <b>124</b>, the velocity of the backwash fluid passing through the chamber <b>138</b> is reduced, thereby increasing residence time and separation efficiency. Because the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> remains in a position where the weight <b>140</b> and the backwash inlet <b>142</b> are below the backwash outlet <b>144</b>, backwashed fluids will travel upward through the chamber <b>138</b> regardless of the rotational position of the seal section <b>112</b>. Should the seal section <b>112</b> rotate during installation or use, the weighted rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> will return to a position in which the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> is properly filtering backwashed fluid.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Thus, in a typical non-vertical well, fluid moving in the backwash direction into the labyrinth assembly <b>120</b> flows toward the motor assembly <b>110</b> along the outside of the rotatable gravity separator <b>126</b> and into the chamber <b>138</b> through the backwash inlet <b>142</b>. In the chamber <b>138</b>, gravity pulls the heavier, contaminated fluids and solids to the bottom of the chamber <b>138</b>. At the same time, lighter, cleaner fluids travel in a generally upward direction, out of the top of the chamber <b>138</b> through the backwash outlet <b>144</b>. Once outside the backwash outlet <b>144</b>, the filtered fluid is directed along the shaft <b>122</b> toward downstream components, which may include additional rotatable gravity separators <b>126</b>. It will be understood, however, that alternate flow-schemes around the labyrinth assemblies <b>120</b> could be employed with equal success and are contemplated as within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">It is to be understood that even though numerous characteristics and advantages of various embodiments of the present invention have been set forth in the foregoing description, together with details of the structure and functions of various embodiments of the invention, this disclosure is illustrative only, and changes may be made in detail, especially in matters of structure and arrangement of parts within the principles of the present invention to the full extent indicated by the broad general meaning of the terms in which the appended claims are expressed. It will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that the teachings of the present invention can be applied to other systems without departing from the scope and spirit of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A seal section for use in a pumping system, the seal section comprising:
<claim-text>a fluid exchange pathway; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotatable gravity separator, wherein the gravity separator includes:
<claim-text>a chamber;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a backwash inlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a backwash outlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a weight positioned within the chamber, wherein the weight causes the rotatable gravity separator to remain in a substantially constant orientation with respect to the force of gravity; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the weight of the rotatable gravity separator is positioned within the chamber such that, in its position of lowest potential energy, the backwash inlet is below the backwash outlet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the seal section further comprises:
<claim-text>a housing; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bearing assembly captured within the housing, wherein the bearing assembly supports the rotatable gravity separator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the gravity separator further comprises:
<claim-text>an outer cylinder; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inner cylinder concentric with the outer cylinder, wherein the annular space between the outer cylinder and the inner cylinder defines the chamber.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> further comprising a longitudinally oriented shaft, where,in the shaft passes within the inner cylinder of the gravity separator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the chamber of the rotatable gravity separator is sized and configured to reduce the velocity of fluids entering the chamber from the fluid exchange pathway.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A downhole pumping system comprising:
<claim-text>a pump assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a motor assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a seal section connected between the pump assembly and the motor assembly, wherein the seal section comprises:
<claim-text>a fluid exchange pathway, wherein the fluid exchange pathway is configured to direct fluids moving between the pump assembly and the motor assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotatable gravity separator, wherein the gravity separator includes:
<claim-text>a chamber;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a backwash inlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a backwash outlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a weight positioned within the chamber, wherein the weight causes the rotatable gravity separator to rotate to a position of lowest possible potential energy.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The downhole pumping system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the weight of the rotatable gravity separator is positioned within the chamber such that, in its position of lowest possible potential energy, the backwash inlet is below the backwash outlet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The downhole pumping system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the seal section further comprises:
<claim-text>a housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bearing assembly captured within the housing, wherein the bearing assembly supports the rotatable gravity separator; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a mechanical seal that separates fluids entering and exiting the rotatable gravity separator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The downhole pumping system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the bearing assembly includes ball bearings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The downhole pumping system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the gravity separator further comprises:
<claim-text>an outer cylinder; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inner cylinder concentric with the outer cylinder, wherein the annular space between the outer cylinder and the inner cylinder defines the chamber.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The downhole pumping system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> further comprising a longitudinally oriented shaft that transmits mechanical energy from the motor assembly to the pump assembly, wherein the shaft passes within the inner cylinder of the gravity separator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The downhole pumping system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the chamber of the rotatable gravity separator is sized and configured to reduce the velocity of fluids entering the chamber from the fluid exchange pathway.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The downhole pumping system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> further comprising a plurality of rotatable gravity separators.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A seal section for use in a downhole pumping system, the seal section comprising:
<claim-text>a fluid exchange pathway; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotatable gravity separator, wherein the gravity separator includes:
<claim-text>a backwash inlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a backwash outlet connecting the chamber to the fluid exchange pathway; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a weight, wherein the weight causes the gravity separator to rotate to a position of decreased potential energy in which the backwash inlet is lower than the backwash outlet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the rotatable gravity separator further comprises:
<claim-text>an outer cylinder having an outer wall and an inner wall;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inner cylinder having an outer wall and an inner wall; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a chamber defined by the annular space between the inner wall of the outer cylinder and the outer wall of the inner cylinder.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the weight is positioned within the chamber proximate the backwash inlet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the weight is connected to the inner wall of the outer cylinder within the chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the weight is connected to the outer wall of the inner cylinder within the chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The seal section of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the weight is connected to the outer wall of the outer cylinder outside the chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
