<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296941-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296941</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11542737</doc-number>
<date>20061004</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-302392</doc-number>
<date>20051018</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>41</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4006152</main-classification>
<further-classification>400611</further-classification>
<further-classification>400578</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Tape printer and tape creating method</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5454653</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Miwa</name>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6106176</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yanagisawa et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4006152</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7004654</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Shibata et al.</name>
<date>20060200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4006152</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0036817</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wilken et al.</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>0598600</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>19940500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>6-155809</doc-number>
<date>19940600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>6155809</doc-number>
<date>19940600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>400 76</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>400578</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>400611</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4006152</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>10</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>12</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070086821</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070419</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Suzuki</last-name>
<first-name>Yasunori</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nagoya</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Suzuki</last-name>
<first-name>Yuichiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Okazaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tanjima</last-name>
<first-name>Naoki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nisshin</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Day Pitney LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Brother Kogyo Kabushiki Kaisha</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Nagoya-shi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chau</last-name>
<first-name>Minh</first-name>
<department>2854</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">It is intended to provide a tape printer and a tape creating method which can achieve a high degree of accuracy and constant length of printing even when the rotational speed of a DC motor changes due to the increase of a wire-wound resistance value because of the heat generation of the DC motor under the continuous driving and the load change by the replacement of a tape. The print cycle algebra is corrected in each time when a pulse number inputted from the photo sensor reaches a control pulse number. Line printing on the surface tape is performed by means of the thermal head with this print cycle algebra as a print cycle.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="233.26mm" wi="129.62mm" file="US07296941-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="196.77mm" wi="149.18mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296941-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="208.11mm" wi="164.42mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296941-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="217.25mm" wi="123.70mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296941-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="237.83mm" wi="135.13mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296941-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="214.21mm" wi="163.41mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296941-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="242.91mm" wi="139.28mm" file="US07296941-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="190.16mm" wi="120.65mm" file="US07296941-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="245.03mm" wi="130.64mm" file="US07296941-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="211.92mm" wi="122.17mm" file="US07296941-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="237.24mm" wi="159.94mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296941-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority from JP 2005-302392, filed Oct. 18, 2005, the contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The disclosure relates to a tape printer and a tape creating method which performs printing on the long tape by means of a print head while conveying a long tape.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Conventionally, there have been variously proposed tape printers and tape creating methods which performs printing on a long tape by means of a print head while conveying the long tape with a tape conveyance mechanism which is driven by a DC motor.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">For instance, Japanese Patent Application laid-open No. H6(1994)-155809 (paragraphs[0008] to [0021], and FIGS. 2 to 5) discloses a tape printer comprising a print head for printing dot-pattern data on a printing medium, a conveyance mechanism for conveying the printing medium relative to the print head, and control means for controlling the print head and the driving mechanism. The tape printer further comprises a DC motor for driving the conveyance mechanism, and rotating at a constant rotational speed, without detecting a rotation angle. Printing is inhibited while the rotational speed of the DC motor is not constant immediately after the DC motor starts rotating. After the rotational speed of the DC motor becomes constant, printing is performed at a stable frequency.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">As described above, the DC motor which is inexpensive and has a good energy efficiency characteristic can be employed to the drive motor of the conveyance mechanism for conveying the printing medium relative to the print head, thus a low-cost dot printer of which power consumption is low.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The tape printer comprising the conventional structures as above, however, is arranged to previously determine the rotational speed of the DC motor by resistance values of a variable resistance and a control IC. When a wire-wound resistance value increases because of the heat generation of the DC motor under the continuous driving, the rotational speed of the DC motor changes, thereby getting difficult to provide fixed-length printing with high precision. The rotational speed of the DC motor also changes due to the load change depending on the tape type.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">To solve the above problems, the printing operation can be performed with the thermal head at every predetermined number of rotations of the DC motor while an encoder detects the rotational speed of the DC motor. However this causes another problem that a user cannot modify a conveyance length of the tape in accordance with the predetermined rotational speed of the DC motor. Thus, a conveyance length correction to adjust the print length cannot be performed.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The disclosure has been made in view of the above circumstances and has an object to overcome the above problems and to provide a tape printer and a tape creating method which can achieve a high degree of accuracy and constant length of printing of a high quality by correction of a print cycle of a print head even when the rotational speed of a DC motor changes due to the increase of a wire-wound resistance value because of the heat generation of the DC motor under the continuous driving and the load change by the replacement of a tape. It is also intended to provide a tape printer and a tape creating method in which a user can perform a tape length correction to adjust the print length by correcting the print cycle of the print head.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">To achieve the purpose of the disclosure, there is provided a tape printer comprising: a tape conveyance mechanism having a DC motor as a drive source to convey a long tape; a detection device that repeatedly detects a drive time in which the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation; a first storage unit that preliminarily stores an initial print cycle; a correction print cycle calculating unit that calculates a correction print cycle based on the drive time detected by the detection device; a print head that performs printing dot-pattern data on the tape conveyed by the tape conveyance mechanism; and a print control unit that drives and controls the print head, wherein the print control unit drives and controls the print head at the initial print cycle and the correction print cycle calculated by the correction print cycle calculating unit.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Accordingly, even when the rotational speed of the DC motor changes due to the increase of a wire-wound resistance value because of the heat generation of the DC motor under the continuous driving and the load change by the replacement of the tape, the print cycle of the print head is corrected in each time when a degree of rotation of the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation. Thus, constant length of printing of a high quality can be achieved by the correction of the print cycle of the print head.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Further, measurement of the degree of rotation of the DC motor by means of the encoder is achieved by repeated detection of a drive time (for example, a drive time of about 100 msecs) in which the degree of rotation of the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation (for example, four to five rotations). Accordingly, the resolution of the encoder can be reduced, thereby securing reductions in both the load of the control circuit and in manufacturing costs.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to another aspect of the disclosure, there is provided a tape printer comprising: a tape conveyance mechanism having a DC motor as a drive source to convey a long tape; a detection device that repeatedly detects a drive time in which the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation; a first storage unit that preliminarily stores an initial print cycle; a print head that performs printing dot-pattern data on the tape conveyed by the tape conveyance mechanism; and a control circuit that drives and controls the print head, wherein the control unit comprises a processor that executes: a print starting process of starting drive of the print head at the initial print cycle and printing on the tape; a correction print cycle calculating process of repeatedly calculating a correction print cycle based on the drive time detected by the detection device after start of printing on the tape; and a print cycle correcting process of correcting the print cycle of the print head in accordance with the correction print cycle calculated at the correction print cycle calculating process.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Accordingly, even when the rotational speed of the DC motor changes due to the increase of a wire-wound resistance value because of the heat generation of the DC motor under the continuous driving and the load change by the replacement of the tape, the print cycle of the print head is corrected in each time when a degree of rotation of the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation, in the correction print cycle calculating process and the print cycle correction process. Thus, constant length of printing of a high quality can be achieved by the correction of the print cycle of the print head.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Further, measurement of the degree of rotation of the DC motor by means of the encoder in the correction print cycle calculating process is achieved by repeated detection of a drive time (for example, a drive time of about 100 msecs) in which the degree of rotation of the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation (for example, four to five rotations). Accordingly, the resolution of the encoder can be reduced, thereby securing reductions in both the load of the control circuit and in manufacturing costs.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to another aspect of the disclosure, there is provided a tape creating method comprising: a print starting step of starting printing dot-pattern data on a conveyed tape at an initial print cycle preliminarily stored; a correction print cycle calculating step of repeatedly detecting a drive time in which a driving DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation after start of printing on the tape, and repeatedly calculating a correction print cycle based on the detected drive time; and a print cycle correction step of correcting a print cycle in accordance with the correction print cycle calculated at the correction print cycle calculating step.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Accordingly, even when the rotational speed of the DC motor changes due to the increase of a wire-wound resistance value because of the heat generation of the DC motor under the continuous driving and the load change by the replacement of the tape, the print cycle of the print head is corrected in each time when a degree of rotation of the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation, in the correction print cycle calculating step and the print cycle correction step. Thus, constant length of printing of a high quality can be achieved by the correction of the print cycle of the print head.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Further, measurement of the degree of rotation of the DC motor by means of the encoder in the correction print cycle calculating step is achieved by repeated detection of a drive time (for example, a drive time of about 100 msecs) in which the degree of rotation of the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation (for example, four to five rotations). Accordingly, the resolution of the encoder can be reduced, thereby securing reductions in both the load of the control circuit and in manufacturing costs.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of an appearance of a tape printer of an exemplary embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a plan view of a structure of a tape drive print mechanism and a tape storage cassette provided inside the tape printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side view of the tape drive print mechanism of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> when the tape storage cassette is removed therefrom, seen from an arrow A direction;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of a control configuration of the tape printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic diagram of a driver circuit of a tape driving DC motor of the tape printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows an example of a tape type correction table preliminarily stored in an EEPROM of the tape printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows an example of the tape length correction table preliminarily stored in the EEPROM of the tape printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows an example of a display of a liquid crystal display when a length correction key of the tape printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is pressed;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a main flowchart of a print control process of the tape printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a sub-flowchart of a print cycle correction process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a sub-flowchart of a pulse count process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows an example of differences of the print lengths from ideal print length that does not cause tape conveyance errors, specifically a case where, by execution of print control process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the print cycle is corrected successively at every four rotations of the DC motor and a case of non-control, in which the print cycle is not corrected successively at every four rotations of the DC motor.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">A detailed description of an exemplary embodiment of a tape printer and a tape creating method of the disclosure will now be given referring to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a tape printer <b>1</b> of this exemplary embodiment has a keyboard <b>3</b> comprising a character input key <b>3</b>A for creating a text composed of document data; a print key <b>3</b>B for instructing printing of documents or other texts; a length correction key <b>3</b>F for use in inputting a conveyance length correction value, to be described later; a return key <b>3</b>R for executing or selecting a line feed instruction or a variety of processes; and cursor keys <b>3</b>C for moving a cursor vertically and horizontally on a liquid crystal display (LCD) that displays plural lines of characters and the like. The tape printer <b>1</b> includes a tape storage cassette <b>30</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), which is to be described later and which is freely detachable internally, and a tape drive print mechanism <b>10</b> and a cutter <b>17</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) for cutting a tape. After extraction from the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> and printing, a tape is cut out by the cutter <b>17</b> and then discharged from a discharge port <b>5</b> provided on the left side face of the tape printer <b>1</b>. A connection interface <b>67</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) is provided on the right side face of the tape printer <b>1</b> for connecting it, by radio or wire, to an external device <b>78</b> such as a personal computer.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> is mounted detachably in a cassette storage frame <b>11</b> within the tape printer <b>1</b>. The tape storage cassette <b>30</b> includes a tape spool <b>32</b> around which a transparent surface tape <b>31</b> composed of polyethylene terephthalate (PET) is wound; a ribbon supply spool <b>34</b> around which an ink ribbon <b>33</b> is wound; a take-up spool <b>35</b> for winding up used ink ribbon <b>33</b>, a base material supply spool <b>37</b> around which is wound a double-sided tape <b>36</b>, in which a separation tape is bonded to a single face of the double-sided adhesive tape with an adhesive agent layer on both sides, and having the same width as the surface tape <b>31</b>, such that the separation tape faces outward; and a press roller <b>39</b> for bonding together the double-sided tape <b>36</b> and the surface tape <b>31</b>, these components being provided freely and rotatably.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref>, <b>3</b>, an arm <b>20</b> is mounted swingingly around a shaft <b>20</b><i>a </i>on the cassette storage frame <b>11</b>. A platen roller <b>21</b> and a feed roller <b>22</b> having a flexible member such as rubber on their surfaces are rotatably provided at the front end of the arm <b>20</b>. When the arm <b>20</b> is swung fully in a clockwise direction, the platen roller <b>21</b> makes a pressure contact, via the surface tape <b>31</b> and the ink ribbon <b>33</b>, with a thermal head <b>13</b> disposed on a plate <b>12</b> to be described later and the feed roller <b>22</b> makes a pressure contact, via the surface tape <b>31</b> and the double-sided tape <b>36</b>, with the press roller <b>39</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The plate <b>12</b> is erected from the cassette storage frame <b>11</b>. The thermal head <b>13</b> in which a plurality of heat generating devices are arranged in line perpendicularly to this paper is disposed on the plate <b>12</b> on the platen roller <b>21</b> side. When the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> is mounted at a predetermined position, the plate <b>12</b> is embedded in a concave portion <b>14</b> in the tape storage cassette <b>30</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a ribbon take-up roller <b>15</b> and a press roller drive roller <b>16</b> are erected from the cassette storage frame <b>11</b>. When the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> is mounted at a predetermined position, the ribbon take-up roller <b>15</b> and the press roller drive roller <b>16</b> are inserted into the take-up spool <b>35</b> and the press roller <b>39</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">A tape driving DC motor <b>2</b> is mounted on the cassette storage frame <b>11</b>. A rotary drive force driven out of an output shaft <b>41</b> of the DC motor <b>2</b> is transmitted to the ribbon take-up roller <b>15</b>, the press roller drive roller <b>16</b>, the platen roller <b>21</b> and the feed roller <b>22</b> via circular gears <b>42</b>, <b>43</b>, <b>44</b>, <b>45</b>, <b>46</b>, <b>47</b>, <b>48</b> disposed along the cassette storage frame <b>11</b> such that they mesh with each other, and circular gears <b>24</b>, <b>25</b> are arranged so as to connect with the platen roller <b>21</b> and the feed roller <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Thus, when the DC motor <b>2</b> is supplied with electricity so that its output shaft <b>41</b> is rotated, the take-up spool <b>35</b>, the press roller <b>39</b>, the platen roller <b>21</b> and the feed roller <b>22</b> are all correspondingly rotated and the surface tape <b>31</b>, the ink ribbon <b>33</b> and the double-sided tape <b>36</b> within the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> are unwound by a drive force generated by their rotations and carried downstream. The surface tape <b>31</b> and the ink ribbon <b>33</b> are overlapped each other and pass through, between the platen roller <b>21</b> and the thermal head <b>13</b>. The surface tape <b>31</b> and the ink ribbon <b>33</b> are nipped between the platen roller <b>21</b> and the thermal head <b>13</b> and conveyed, and when a plurality of heat generating devices arranged on the thermal head <b>13</b> are supplied with electricity selectively and intermittently, ink on the ink ribbon <b>33</b> is transferred to the surface tape <b>31</b> in units of dots so as to form dot images desired as a mirror image. After the ink ribbon <b>33</b> passes the thermal head <b>13</b> and is wound up by the ribbon take-up roller <b>15</b>, the surface tape <b>31</b> and the double-sided tape <b>36</b> are overlapped each other and pass through between the feed roller <b>22</b> and the press roller <b>39</b>. Consequently, after dots have been printed thereon, a print side face of the surface tape <b>31</b> is overlapped with the double-sided tape <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A lamination tape <b>38</b> in which the surface tape <b>31</b> and the double-sided tape <b>36</b> have been overlapped one another allows a normal image of a printed image to be seen from the opposite side of the print face of the surface tape <b>31</b>, and after it has been cut by the cutter <b>17</b> disposed downstream of the feed roller <b>22</b>, it is discharged from the discharge port <b>5</b>. The cutter <b>17</b> is constructed in the form of scissors in which a rotary blade <b>17</b><i>b </i>is rotated relative to a fixed blade <b>17</b><i>a </i>so as to cut out a object that needs to be cut, and the rotary blade <b>17</b><i>b </i>is swung around a fulcrum point by a DC motor <b>71</b> for the cutter (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) so as to cut out the lamination tape <b>38</b>. The lamination tape <b>38</b> that is cut is available as an adhesive label and by the peeling of its separation tape this adhesive label can be bonded to any place so desired.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the DC motor <b>2</b> is equipped with an encoder <b>49</b> as a sensor for detecting a degree of rotation thereof. The encoder <b>49</b> comprises a rotary disc <b>49</b><i>a </i>having slits spaced in a circumferential direction (nine slits are formed in this exemplary embodiment) and to which the output shaft <b>41</b> of the DC motor <b>2</b> is connected as a rotary shaft; and a photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>in which a light emitting device and a light receiving device are disposed on both sides of the rotary disc <b>49</b><i>a </i>such that they oppose each other. Light beams emitted from the light emitting device of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>are interrupted between the slits, or they pass through the slits in accordance with rotation of the circular disc <b>49</b><i>a</i>, and they reach the light receiving device.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A normal rotation or a reverse rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> can be detected by using a single two-phase photo sensor instead of using the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The tape stored in the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> comprises four types, that is, a “lamination type” (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) in which the surface of the print tape is protected by a transparent film, a “receptor type” in which the surface of the print tape is not covered with protective tape, a “lettering type” in which the surface of the print tape is not covered with any protective film but designed with characters or patterns, and a “fabric type” in which the print tape is of fabric. Each of the four types of tapes has in turn six types in which the widths of tape are respectively 3.5 mm, 6 mm, 9 mm, 12 mm, 18 mm and 24 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, there is provided a tape determination part <b>30</b>A in which the presence/absence of seven sensor holes K<b>1</b>-K<b>7</b> can be combined to detect the type or width of a stored tape on a corner between the top face portion and the bottom face portion of the tape storage cassette <b>30</b>. A cassette sensor <b>7</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) for detecting the presence or absence of each of the sensor holes K<b>1</b>-K<b>7</b>, made up of a push-type micro switch or the like, is provided on a bottom portion opposing the tape determination part <b>30</b>A of the cassette storage frame <b>11</b>. In other words, the cassette sensor <b>7</b> outputs cassette signals on the basis of the presence or absence of each of the sensor holes K<b>1</b> to K<b>7</b> that made up the tape determination part <b>30</b>A. For example, a tape stored in the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> outputs a cassette signal “1011111” when the tape is 9 mm in width and of a lamination type, and “1100111” when the tape is of 9 mm width and of a receptor type; and when the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> is not attached the cassette sensor <b>7</b> outputs a cassette signal “0000000”. Noted that “1” represents the ON signal, and “0” the OFF signal.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Next, the control configuration of the tape printer <b>1</b> will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref>, <b>5</b>. Control boards (not shown) are disposed within the tape printer <b>1</b> and a CPU <b>61</b>, CG-ROM <b>62</b>, EEPROM <b>63</b>, ROM <b>64</b>, RAM <b>66</b>, timer <b>65</b> and three driver circuits <b>68</b>, <b>69</b>, <b>70</b> are disposed on this control board. The CPU <b>61</b>, which executes various arithmetical operations and controls input and output of signals, is connected to the CG-ROM <b>62</b>, the EEPROM <b>63</b>, the ROM <b>64</b>, the RAM <b>66</b>, the timer <b>65</b> and the driver circuits <b>68</b>-<b>70</b>, and further to a liquid crystal display (LCD) <b>6</b>, a cassette sensor <b>7</b>, a photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b</i>, a keyboard <b>3</b> and a connection interface <b>67</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The CG-ROM <b>62</b> is a character generator memory which stores image data such as characters and symbols to be printed in a dot-pattern data corresponding to code data. The EEPROM <b>63</b> includes a tape type correction table <b>81</b> and a tape length correction table <b>82</b>, both of which will be described later. The ROM <b>64</b> includes various types of data including programs for actuating the tape printer <b>1</b>, an “initial print cycle” for driving a print operation of the thermal head, a “reference degree of rotation” of the DC motor <b>2</b> corresponding to the “initial print cycle” and a “shortest time” (about 10 milliseconds (hereinafter, “msecs”) in this exemplary embodiment), which constitutes the shortest print control time require for forming print dots by means of the thermal head <b>13</b>. The RAM <b>66</b> is provided with equipment such as a rotation correction cycle counter for counting clock signals until the degree of rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> reaches a predetermined degree of rotation and stores data inputted through the keyboard <b>3</b>, data that is brought in from an external device <b>78</b>, through a connection interface <b>67</b>, or the result of arithmetical operations in the CPU <b>61</b>. Further, on the basis of a clock signal and as will be described later, the timer <b>65</b> measures a duration of time after the timer <b>65</b> has been initialized (see S<b>7</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The CPU <b>61</b> comprises a print control unit <b>61</b><i>a </i>for controlling print by means of the thermal head <b>13</b>, a tape-motor control unit <b>61</b><i>b </i>for controlling the ON and OFF of the DC motor <b>2</b>, a cutter-motor control unit <b>61</b><i>c </i>for controlling the DC motor <b>71</b>, and a pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d </i>for calculating from the output signal of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>of the encoder <b>49</b>, the quantity of rotational pulses of the DC motor <b>2</b>. Further, with regard to a clock signal generated by the timer <b>65</b>, the driver circuit <b>68</b> supplies a drive signal to the thermal head <b>13</b> on the basis of a control signal from the print control unit <b>61</b><i>a </i>at a corrected print cycle to be described later. Further, on the basis of a control signal from the cutter-motor control unit <b>61</b><i>c</i>, the drive circuit <b>69</b> supplies a drive signal to the DC motor <b>71</b>. The drive circuit <b>70</b> drives the DC motor <b>2</b> on the basis of a control signal from the tape-motor control unit <b>61</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the driver circuit <b>70</b> for driving and controlling the DC motor <b>2</b> is provided with a switching transistor <b>72</b> which turns on and off supply of electricity to the DC motor <b>2</b> according to ON and OFF signals from the CPU <b>61</b> and an electronic governor circuit <b>73</b> for controlling the rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> at a constant speed. This electronic governor circuit <b>73</b> executes proportional current control so that reverse electromotive force of the DC motor <b>2</b> becomes constant on the basis of current in a resistor R. Then, when a certain amount of time has elapsed following the start of the supply of electricity, regardless of the magnitude of the power supply voltage, the DC motor <b>2</b> succeeds in turning at a constant degree of rotation corresponding to a load of the DC motor <b>2</b>. Then, a predetermined degree of rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> (four rotations in this exemplary embodiment) is detected when a predetermined pulse number (36 pulses in this exemplary embodiment) is counted via the encoder <b>49</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Further, this electronic governor circuit <b>73</b> is a control IC, for example, LA5528N (manufactured by SANYO Electronic Co., Ltd.).</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">When the DC motor <b>2</b> is driven at a constant speed, the thermal head <b>13</b> is driven at a print cycle obtained by correcting the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) corresponding to factors such as the type of the tape stored in the tape storage cassette <b>30</b>, as will be described later. After that, the thermal head <b>13</b> is driven at a correction print cycle corrected successively on the basis of a drive time in which each DC motor <b>2</b> reaches a predetermined degree of rotation. Thus, when a thermal head <b>13</b> starts its print operation, the ROM <b>64</b> stores data of the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) which is a reference print cycle. By driving the thermal head <b>13</b> at such a correction print cycle when the DC motor <b>2</b> runs at a constant speed, an adequate data process time (for example, development from outline font data to bit map data, character decoration, horizontal-to-vertical conversion) can be satisfactory secured for print data which is processed when the thermal head <b>13</b> is down, even when the DC motor <b>2</b> is being driven at a constant rotational speed of a substantial degree, thereby eliminating deteriorations in print quality such as occurrences printing errors.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">On the other hand, the driving of the thermal head <b>13</b> is generally terminated on the basis of the output signal of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>of the encoder <b>49</b> except for the period while the DC motor <b>2</b> drives at the constant speed (or equivalently, a period between the termination of the supply of electricity of the DC motor <b>2</b> and the stop of driving of the DC motor <b>2</b>, and a period between the resumption of the supply of electricity of the DC motor <b>2</b> and the start of the driving of the DC motor <b>2</b> at the constant speed).</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The tape type correction table <b>81</b> preliminarily stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b> will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the tape type correction table <b>81</b> comprises a “tape type” indicating the type of tape stored in the tape storage cassette <b>30</b>, and a “tape type correction value” indicating a correction value for correcting the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) for driving the thermal head <b>13</b> corresponding to the tape type, by means of multiplying the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) by the correction value.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The “tape type” stores 12 combinations of types of tape and widths of tape ranging from 3.5 mm to 24 mm. For example, “3.5 mm, receptor” in “tape type” indicates that the width of the tape is 3.5 mm and that the tape is of a “receptor type”. Further, “6 mm, laminate” in “tape type” indicates that the width of the tape is 6 mm and that the type of tape is “lamination type”.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The “tape type correction value” stores a numeral “1” for seven types of “3.5 mm, receptor”, “6 mm, receptor”, “9 mm, receptor” and the like in terms of “tape type”. The “tape type correction value” stores a numeral “0.985” for each of five types of “6 mm, laminate”, “9 mm, laminate”, “12 mm, laminate” and the like in terms of “tape type”. In other words, the five types of initial print cycles of “6 mm, laminate”, “9 mm, laminate”, “12 mm, laminate” and the like in terms of “tape type” are corrected so that the initial print cycle of the thermal head <b>13</b> is slightly shorter, as will be described later (see S<b>2</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Next, the tape length correction table <b>82</b> stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b> will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the tape length correction table <b>82</b> comprises a “conveyance length correction value” indicating the amount of correction of the tape conveyance length which can be changed selectively by a user when the tape conveyance length relative to a degree of rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> changes as a result of factors such as friction of the platen roller <b>21</b>, and a “tape length correction value” corresponding to the “conveyance length correction value” and indicating a correction value for correcting a print cycle (T) at which the thermal head is driven by means of multiplying the print cycle (T) by the correction value.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Further, the “conveyance length correction value” stores “+3” indicating that the tape conveyance length is increased by about 3%, “+2” indicating that the tape conveyance length is increased by about 2%, “+1” indicating that the tape conveyance length is increased by about 1%, “0” indicating that the tape conveyance length is not changed and “−1” indicating that the tape conveyance length is decreased by about 1%.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Further, the “tape length correction value” stores “1.03” corresponding to “+3” of the “conveyance length correction value”, “1.02” corresponding to “+2” of the “conveyance length correction value”, “1.01” corresponding to “+1” of the “conveyance length correction value”, “1” corresponding to “0” of the “conveyance length correction value” and “0.99” corresponding to “−1” of the “conveyance length correction value”. Therefore, the print cycle of the thermal head <b>13</b> is corrected in accordance with the “conveyance length correction value” selected by a user, as will be described later (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Next, an explanation will be given, on the basis of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> of operations undertaken by a user to select a conveyance length selection value.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">When a user presses a length correction key <b>3</b>F of the keyboard <b>3</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, “length correction: 0” is first displayed on the liquid crystal display (LCD) <b>6</b>, indicating that, “0” has been selected as the “conveyance length correction value”. Then, when a user presses a return key <b>3</b>R, “0” is stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b> as the “conveyance length correction value” and the liquid crystal display <b>6</b> is returned to the character input mode.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">On the other hand, if a user presses the length correction key <b>3</b>F repeatedly, the liquid crystal display <b>6</b> displays in succession “length correction +1” indicating that “+1” has been selected as the “conveyance length correction value”, “length correction: +2” indicating that “+2” has been selected as the “conveyance length correction value”, “length correction: +3” indicating that “+3” has been selected as the “conveyance length correction value”, and “length correction: −1” indicating that “−1” has been selected as the “conveyance length correction value”, and when the length correction key <b>3</b>F is pressed, the display is returned to “length correction: 0” indicating that “0” has been selected as the “conveyance length correction value”. Then, if a user presses the return key <b>3</b>R when any display is on, any one of “+1”, “+2”, “+3”, “−1”, and “0” can be stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b> as the “conveyance length correction value” corresponding to the indication on the liquid crystal display <b>6</b>, and the liquid crystal display <b>6</b> is then returned to the character input mode. Furthermore, “0” is stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b> as the “conveyance length correction value” at the time of shipment from the factory.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The print control process for printing on a tape of the tape printer <b>1</b> having such a configuration items such as character data will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9-12</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, in step (hereinafter abbreviated to S) <b>1</b>, when the print key <b>3</b>B of the keyboard <b>3</b> is pressed, the CPU <b>61</b> of the tape printer <b>1</b> reads out the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) (T<b>0</b>=14.1 msecs corresponds to about 5 pulses of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>in this exemplary embodiment) and this initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) is substituted for a print cycle algebra T and its result stored in the RAM <b>66</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">In S<b>2</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> defines, by means of the cassette sensor <b>7</b>, the type and width of the tape stored in the tape storage cassette <b>30</b>. Applying the type and width of the tape to a “tape type” in the tape type correction table <b>81</b> stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b>, the CPU <b>62</b> reads out a “tape type correction value” corresponding to the “tape type”. Then, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the print cycle algebra T and stores again a value produced in the RAM <b>66</b> by multiplying this print cycle algebra T by the “tape type correction value” as a new print cycle algebra T.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">For example, if a cassette signal of “1011111” is inputted to the CPU <b>61</b> from the cassette sensor <b>7</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> specifies that the tape stored in the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> has a width of 9 mm and is of a lamination type, and accordingly reads out a “tape type correction value” of “0.985” corresponding to “9 mm, laminate” in the “tape type” stored in the tape type correction table <b>81</b>. Then, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the print cycle algebra T and again stores a value obtained in the RAM <b>66</b> by multiplying this print cycle algebra T by “0.985” as the print cycle algebra T.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">If a cassette signal of “1100111” is inputted to the CPU <b>61</b> from the cassette sensor <b>7</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> determines that the tape stored in the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> has a width of 9 mm and is of receptor type, and reads out in the tape type correction table <b>81</b> “1” of “tape type correction value” corresponding to “9 mm, receptor” of the “tape type”. Then, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out a print cycle algebra T from the RAM <b>66</b> and again stores into the RAM <b>66</b> a value obtained in the RAM <b>66</b> by multiplying this print cycle algebra T by “1” as a new print cycle algebra T.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Subsequently, in S<b>3</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> executes sub-process of the “print cycle correction process” which will be described later (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">In S<b>4</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> turns on the switching transistor <b>72</b> so as to start supply of electricity to the DC motor <b>2</b>. As a consequence, the electronic governor circuit <b>73</b> executes proportional current control on the DC motor <b>2</b> so that a reverse electromotive force of the DC motor <b>2</b> becomes constant.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">In S<b>5</b>, by detecting a pulse cycle from the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>the CPU <b>61</b> waits for the DC motor <b>2</b> to finish its acceleration region and reaches its constant rotational speed. It is noted that the CPU <b>61</b> can wait for a predetermined period of time after the DC motor <b>2</b> has been started.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">In S<b>6</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the print cycle algebra T at a timing at which the rotational speed of the DC motor <b>2</b> reaches a constant speed and, by means of the thermal head <b>13</b> with this print cycle algebra T as a print cycle (T) for driving the thermal head <b>13</b>, starts line printing on the surface tape <b>31</b> at each print cycle (T). Consequently, dot-pattern data is printed on the surface tape <b>31</b> at intervals of dots corresponding to a conveyance distance of a tape conveyed in the print cycle (T). Because, as will be described later, this print cycle algebra T is corrected in each time when a pulse number inputted from the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>reaches a control pulse number (36 pulses corresponding to four turns of the DC motor <b>2</b> in this exemplary embodiment), the CPU <b>61</b> reads out the print cycle algebra T from the RAM <b>66</b> in each time when the print cycle algebra T is corrected and with this print cycle algebra T as a print cycle (T) for driving the thermal head <b>13</b> executes, by means of the thermal head <b>13</b>, line printing on the surface tape <b>31</b> at each print cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">After the initialization of the timer <b>65</b> as a rotation correction cycle timer in S<b>7</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out a measurement time TM of the timer <b>65</b>, “0” is substituted for the measurement time TM, and its result is again stored in the timer <b>65</b>. After that, the timer <b>65</b> starts to measure time so as to start measurement of a time for the degree of rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> so as to reach a predetermined degree of rotation (four turns, corresponding to 36 pulses of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>in this exemplary embodiment).</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">In S<b>8</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> executes the sub-process of the “pulse count process” which will be described later (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Subsequently, in S<b>9</b>, when the count value of the pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d </i>reaches a number of control pulses, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out the measurement time TM of the timer <b>65</b>, and stores the measurement time TM into the RAM <b>66</b>. Then, the CPU <b>61</b> again reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the measurement time TM and reads out a reference encoder pulse number (in this exemplary embodiment, the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) is 14.1 msecs and a reference encoder pulse number is 5 pulses), and a control pulse number (in this exemplary embodiment, 36 pulses of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>corresponds to four turns of the DC motor <b>2</b>). The CPU <b>61</b> computes the “correction print cycle” by multiplying the measurement time TM by a rate of the reference encoder pulse number relative to the control pulse number. Then, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the print cycle algebra T substitutes this “correction print cycle” for this print cycle algebra T, and the result is again stored in the RAM <b>66</b> as a new print cycle algebra T.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">After that, in S<b>10</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> executes the sub-process (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>) of the “print cycle correction process” described in S<b>3</b> above.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Subsequently, in S<b>11</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> executes determination process, a process of determining whether or not supply of electricity to the thermal head <b>13</b> has been stopped, that is, whether or not all the print data stored in the RAM <b>66</b> has been printed. Then, unless all the print data stored in the RAM <b>66</b> has been printed (S<b>11</b>: NO), the CPU <b>61</b> again executes a process subsequent to S<b>7</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">On the other hand, if all the print data stored in the RAM <b>66</b> has been printed (S<b>11</b>: YES), in S<b>12</b> the CPU <b>61</b> terminates the driving of the thermal head <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">In S<b>13</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> turns off the switching transistor <b>72</b> so as to turn off supply of electricity to the DC motor <b>2</b> and then terminates the process.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">Next, the sub-process of the “print cycle correction process” executed in S<b>3</b> and S<b>10</b> described above will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">In S<b>21</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out the conveyance length correction value stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b>. Applying the conveyance length correction value as a “conveyance length correction value” stored in the tape length correction table <b>82</b> stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out the “tape length correction value” corresponding to the “conveyance length correction value”. Then, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out the print cycle algebra T from the RAM <b>66</b>, and again stores into the RAM <b>66</b>, a value obtained by multiplying this print cycle algebra T by the “tape length correction value” as a new print cycle algebra T.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">For example, if the “conveyance length correction value” read out from the EEPROM <b>63</b> is “0”, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out “1” of the “tape length correction value” corresponding to “0” of the “conveyance length correction value” in the tape length correction table <b>82</b> stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b>. Then, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the print cycle algebra T and again stores into the RAM <b>66</b> a value obtained in the RAM <b>66</b> by multiplying this print cycle algebra T by “1” as a new print cycle algebra T.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">If the “conveyance length correction value” read out from the EEPROM <b>63</b> is “+1”, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out from the tape length correction table <b>82</b> stored in the EEPROM <b>63</b> “1.01” of the “tape length correction value” corresponding to “+1” of the “conveyance length correction value”. Then, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the print cycle algebra T and again stores into the RAM <b>66</b> a value obtained in the RAM <b>66</b> by multiplying this print cycle algebra T by “1.01” as a new print cycle algebra T.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Subsequently, in S<b>22</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out from the ROM <b>64</b> the “shortest time” of the print cycle, that is, “10 msecs” which is the “shortest time” data of the shortest print control time required for the thermal head <b>13</b> to form print dots. The CPU <b>61</b> further reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the print cycle algebra T and executes determination process for determining whether or not this print cycle algebra T is less than 10 msecs.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">If the print cycle algebra T is less than 10 msecs (S<b>22</b>: YES), the CPU <b>61</b> proceeds to a process of S<b>23</b>. In S<b>23</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> again reads out from the RAM <b>66</b> the print cycle algebra T, substitutes <b>10</b> msecs for this print cycle algebra T. After a new print cycle algebra T is stored in the RAM <b>66</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> terminates this sub-process and then returns to the main flow chart.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">On the other hand, if the print cycle algebra T is equal to or more than 10 msecs (S<b>22</b>: NO), the CPU <b>61</b> terminates the sub-process and returns to the main flow chart.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">Next, sub-process on the “pulse count process” to be executed in S<b>8</b> will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, in S<b>31</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> initializes the pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d. </i></p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">In S<b>32</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> detects a pulse inputted through the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b</i>, and if a pulse is detected, it reads out a count value from the pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d</i>, adds “1” to that count value and memorizes its result in the pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d. </i></p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">Subsequently, in S<b>33</b>, the CPU <b>61</b> reads out a count value of the pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d </i>and at the same time, reads out from the ROM <b>64</b> a number of control pulses so as to execute determination process, the processes of determining whether or not the count value becomes equal to or exceeds the number of control pulses (in this exemplary embodiment, 36 pulses equivalent to four rotations of the DC motor <b>2</b>). If the count value of the pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d </i>is less than the number of control pulses (S<b>33</b>: NO), the CPU <b>61</b> again executes process subsequent to S<b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">On the other hand, if the count value of the pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d </i>becomes equal to or exceeds the number of control pulses, that is, the count value of the pulse counter <b>61</b><i>d </i>reaches the number of control pulses (S<b>33</b>: YES), the CPU <b>61</b> terminates this sub-process and returns to the main flow chart.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows an example of differences of the print lengths from ideal print length that does not cause tape conveyance errors, specifically a case where, by execution of print control process (S<b>1</b>-S<b>13</b>), the print cycle is corrected successively at every four rotations of the DC motor <b>2</b> and a case of non-control, in which the print cycle is not corrected successively at every four rotations of the DC motor <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">Noted that the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) of the thermal head <b>13</b> is 14.1 msecs. The quantity of slits formed in the rotating disc <b>49</b><i>a </i>of the encoder <b>49</b> is 9 and the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>outputs 9 pulses per rotation. Therefore, the print cycle of the thermal head <b>13</b> is corrected at every 36 pulses (number of control pulses) of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b</i>. The reference rotational speed of the DC motor <b>2</b> is a rotational speed of 1 revolution per 14.1×9÷5=25.38 msecs. When the DC motor <b>2</b> is rotated regularly, at every 36 pulses of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>the tape is conveyed about 1 mm. Further, the DC motor <b>2</b> generates a rotational speed error of 0.004% at every pulse of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">If the print control process (S<b>1</b>-S<b>13</b>) described above is executed as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> so as to correct the print cycle successively at every four rotations of the DC motor <b>2</b>, a difference with respect to an ideal print length changes as indicated by a correction error curve <b>85</b>, so that when a tape is conveyed about 80 mm, an error of about 0.0026 mm occurs.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">On the other hand, unless process of S<b>7</b>-S<b>10</b> is executed during the print control process (S<b>1</b>-S<b>13</b>), that is, unless the print cycle is corrected at every four rotations of the DC motor <b>2</b>, the difference with respect to the ideal print length changes as indicated by the non-control error curve <b>86</b>, so that an error of about 0.11 mm occurs when the tape is conveyed about 80 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">Therefore, in the tape printer <b>1</b> of this exemplary embodiment, if the rotational speed of the DC motor <b>2</b> while printing on the tape at a constant speed changes due to increase of a wire-wound resistance value because of heat generation of the DC motor <b>2</b> under continuous driving, and load change depending on the tape type, the print cycle algebra T is corrected in every time when the quantity of pulses of the photo sensor <b>49</b><i>b </i>for detecting the degree of rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> reaches a number of control pulses (in this exemplary embodiment, 36 pulses corresponding to four rotations of the DC motor) (S<b>9</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">Accordingly, line printing on the surface tape <b>31</b> is carried out by the thermal head <b>13</b> at every print cycle (T) which is applied the print cycle algebra T for driving the thermal head <b>13</b>, so that a high degree of accuracy and constant length of printing of a high quality can be achieved by correction of the print cycle (T) of the thermal head <b>13</b>, even when the rotational speed of the DC motor <b>2</b> changes.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">Measurement of the degree of rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> by means of the encoder <b>49</b> is achieved by detecting the quantity of control pulses (in this exemplary embodiment, 36 pulses equivalent to four rotations of the DC motor <b>2</b>) corresponding to a drive time (for example, a drive time of about 100 msecs) in which the degree of rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> reaches a predetermined degree of rotation (for example, four to five rotations). Accordingly, the resolution of the encoder <b>49</b> can be reduced, thereby securing reductions in both the load of the control circuit and in manufacturing costs. Repeated detections of the control pulse are permitted to be achieved at the same time in parallel, by shifting them in terms of time, and in this case, smooth correction of the print cycle (T) becomes possible.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">Before the drive of the DC motor <b>2</b> is started, a tape type correction value corresponding to the type of tape detected by the cassette sensor <b>7</b> is corrected by multiplying the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) by the tape type correction value, and then stored in the RAM <b>66</b> as the print cycle algebra T (S<b>2</b>). Thus, even when the rotational speed of the DC motor <b>2</b> changes when the tape storage cassette <b>30</b> is replaced by another tape storage cassette containing a different type of tape, a high degree of accuracy and constant length of printing of a high quality can be achieved by correction of the print cycle (T) of the thermal head <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">Before the drive of the DC motor <b>2</b> is started, a tape length correction value corresponding to the conveyance length correction value specified by the length correction key <b>3</b>F and the return key <b>3</b>D is corrected by multiplying the print cycle algebra T for which the initial print cycle (T<b>0</b>) has been substituted (S<b>3</b>) by the conveyance length correction value and this tape length correction value is corrected by multiplying the print cycle algebra T in which the correction print cycle has been substituted by this tape length correction value (S<b>10</b>). As a result, when a user specifies a conveyance length correction value, the print cycle algebra T is automatically corrected when the thermal head <b>13</b> starts printing, and in each time when the pulse number reaches the control pulse number. Thus, even when a tape conveyance length corresponding to the degree of rotation of the DC motor <b>2</b> changes as a result of friction of the platen roller <b>21</b>, a high degree of accuracy and constant length of printing of a high quality can be achieved by correction of the print cycle of the thermal head <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">If the print cycle algebra T turns to the “shortest time” of the print cycle, that is, “shortest time” which is the shortest print control time required for forming print dots by means of the thermal head <b>13</b>, which is less than “10 msecs” (S<b>22</b>: YES), the print cycle algebra T is read out from the RAM <b>66</b>, “10 msecs” is substituted for this print cycle algebra T and its result is stored in the RAM <b>66</b> (S<b>23</b>). Thus, because the shortest print control time (10 msecs in this exemplary embodiment) required for forming the print dots by means of the thermal head <b>13</b> can be secured, unevenness of print dots due to extreme rotational changes of the DC motor <b>2</b> can be prevented by correcting the print cycle, thereby making possible a higher quality of printing.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">While the presently exemplary embodiment has been shown and described, it is to be understood that this disclosure is for the purpose of illustration and that various changes and modifications may be made without departing from the scope of the disclosure as set forth in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A tape printer comprising:
<claim-text>a tape conveyance mechanism having a DC motor as a drive source to convey a long tape;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detection device that repeatedly detects a drive time in which the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first storage unit that preliminarily stores an initial print cycle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a correction print cycle calculating unit that calculates a correction print cycle based on the drive time detected by the detection device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a print head that performs printing dot-pattern data on the tape conveyed by the tape conveyance mechanism; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a print control unit that drives and controls the print head,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print control unit drives and controls the print head at the initial print cycle and the correction print cycle calculated by the correction print cycle calculating unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The tape printer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, comprising:
<claim-text>a tape type detection device that detects a type of the tape; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second storage unit that preliminary stores a tape type correction value for correcting a print cycle of the print head corresponding to the type of the tape,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print control unit corrects the initial print cycle based on the tape type correction value corresponding to the type of the tape detected by the tape type detection device before start of driving of the DC motor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The tape printer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, comprising:
<claim-text>a third storage unit that stores plural kinds of conveyance length correction values for correcting a tape conveyance length relative to the degree of rotation of the DC motor, and tape length correction values for correcting the print cycle of the print head corresponding to the conveyance length correction values;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a specification mechanism that specifies one of the plural kinds of conveyance length correction values,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print control unit corrects the initial print cycle based on the one tape length correction value corresponding to the conveyance length correction value specified by the specification mechanism before start of driving of the DC motor, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the correction print cycle calculating unit corrects the correction print cycle based on the one tape length correction value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The tape printer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, comprising:
<claim-text>a fourth storage unit that stores a shortest time of the print cycle,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the correction print cycle calculating unit corrects the correction print cycle again by substituting the shortest time for the correction print cycle when the correction print cycle is less than the shortest time.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A tape printer comprising:
<claim-text>a tape conveyance mechanism having a DC motor as a drive source to convey a long tape;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detection device that repeatedly detects a drive time in which the DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first storage unit that preliminarily stores an initial print cycle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a print head that performs printing dot-pattern data on the tape conveyed by the tape conveyance mechanism; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control circuit that drives and controls the print head,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the control circuit comprises a processor that executes:
<claim-text>a print starting process of starting drive of the print head at the initial print cycle and printing on the tape;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a correction print cycle calculating process of repeatedly calculating a correction print cycle based on the drive time detected by the detection device after start of printing on the tape; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a print cycle correcting process of correcting the print cycle of the print head in accordance with the correction print cycle calculated at the correction print cycle calculating process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The tape printer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, comprising:
<claim-text>a tape type detection device that detects a type of the tape; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second storage unit that preliminary stores a tape type correction value for correcting the print cycle of the print head corresponding to the type of the tape,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the processor executes a first initial print cycle correction process of correcting the initial print cycle based on the tape type correction value corresponding to the type of the tape detected by the tape type detection device before start of driving of the DC motor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The tape printer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, comprising:
<claim-text>a third storage unit that stores plural kinds of conveyance length correction values for correcting a tape conveyance length relative to the degree of rotation of the DC motor, and tape length correction values for correcting the print cycle of the print head corresponding to the conveyance length correction values; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a specification mechanism that specifies one of the plural kinds of conveyance length correction values,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the processor executes:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second initial print cycle correction process of correcting the initial print cycle based on the one tape length correction value corresponding to the conveyance length correction value specified by the specification mechanism before start of driving of the DC motor, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tape length correction process of correcting the correction print cycle based on the one tape length correction value corresponding to the conveyance length correction value specified by the specification mechanism at the print cycle correction process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The tape printer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, comprising:
<claim-text>a fourth storage unit that stores a shortest time of the print cycle,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the processor executes:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shortest time correction process of correcting the correction print cycle again by substituting the shortest time for the correction print cycle when the correction print cycle is less than the shortest time.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A tape creating method comprising:
<claim-text>a print starting step of starting printing dot-pattern data on a conveyed tape at an initial print cycle preliminarily stored;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a correction print cycle calculating step of repeatedly detecting a drive time in which a driving DC motor reaches a predetermined degree of rotation after start of printing on the tape, and repeatedly calculating a correction print cycle based on the detected drive time; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a print cycle correction step of correcting a print cycle in accordance with the correction print cycle calculated at the correction print cycle calculating step.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The tape creating method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, comprising:
<claim-text>a first initial print cycle correction step of detecting a type of the tape, and correcting the print cycle based on a tape type correction value for correcting the initial print cycle preliminary stored corresponding to the type of the tape before start of driving of the DC motor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The tape creating method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, comprising:
<claim-text>a second initial print cycle correction step of correcting the initial print cycle based on one tape length correction value corresponding to one conveyance length correction value, after specifying the one of the plural kinds of conveyance length correction values preliminary stored for correcting a tape conveyance length before start of driving of the DC motor,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print cycle correction step comprises a tape length correction step of correcting the correction print cycle based on the one tape length correction value corresponding to the specified conveyance length correction value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The tape creating method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the print cycle correction step comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shortest time correction step of correcting the correction print cycle again by substituting the shortest time for the correction print cycle when the correction print cycle is less than a preliminary-stored shortest time of the print cycle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
