<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297123-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297123</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10907844</doc-number>
<date>20050418</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>239</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>61</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>103</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>61</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>05</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>600590</main-classification>
<further-classification>600587</further-classification>
<further-classification>600547</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Method and apparatus for accessing oral mucositis</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5353802</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ollmar</name>
<date>19941000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0119537</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Campbell et al.</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>600306</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0116587</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ling et al.</name>
<date>20060600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>600485</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>600590</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>600587</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>600547</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60563331</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040419</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050234365</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051020</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sonis</last-name>
<first-name>Stephen T.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wayland</city>
<state>MA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Herbster</last-name>
<first-name>George A.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nova Technology Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Portsmouth</city>
<state>NH</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hindenburg</last-name>
<first-name>Max F.</first-name>
<department>3736</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>H. Q.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Overall and constituent oral mucositis assessment scale scores are generated by the use of a probe to obtain moisture measurements at a particular site. A control collects data samples. A converter produces a value for the oral mucositis assessment scale (OMAS) in response to the collected data (DPM) in accordance with a correlation defined by:</p>
<p id="p-0002" num="0000">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mrow>
  <mi>OMAS</mi>
  <mo>=</mo>
  <mrow>
    <mfrac>
      <mrow>
        <mi>DPM</mi>
        <mo>-</mo>
        <msub>
          <mi>DPM</mi>
          <mi>o</mi>
        </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
        <mi>K</mi>
        <mo>⁡</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mo>(</mo>
          <mi>I</mi>
          <mo>)</mo>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mfrac>
    <mo>.</mo>
  </mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="152.91mm" wi="158.07mm" file="US07297123-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="219.54mm" wi="190.50mm" file="US07297123-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="199.73mm" wi="174.67mm" file="US07297123-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="243.25mm" wi="176.95mm" file="US07297123-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="137.84mm" wi="137.58mm" file="US07297123-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="185.08mm" wi="163.66mm" file="US07297123-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="180.76mm" wi="161.80mm" file="US07297123-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0001">This invention is directed to the assessment of oral mucositis. More specifically, this invention is directed to a method and apparatus for simplifying the assessment of patients afflicted with oral mucositis.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF RELATED ART</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0002">Oral mucositis is a frequent complication of chemotherapy and radiotherapy regimens, hematopoietic stem-cell transplantation and various diseases. Oral mucositis is especially severe for patients who are undergoing stem-cell transplantation because this regimen involves the use of high dose myeloablative chemotherapy for conditioning. During the stem-cell transplantation regimen, oral mucositis can become so severe that patients require parenteral narcotics for relief of pain. In the presence of neutropenia, severe mucositis may predispose patients to septicemia.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0003">Once the complications of oral mucositis were known, various methods were developed for assessing the severity of oral mucositis. Initial diagnoses were qualitative and led to ad hoc treatments. Most prior diagnostic tools and protocols were toxicity scales that emphasized the functional disability engendered by mucositis. However, these tools and protocols neglect anatomic characteristics. The scoring of these various scales was subjective and heavily influenced by the severity of pain experienced by the patient and the use of analgesics that can impart a downward bias to the scores off patients with anatomically severe oral mucositis. The lack of an objective, reliable and valid scale for measuring the extent of oral mucositis was an impediment to research in this area.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0004">More recently a medical team developed a new scoring system for evaluating the anatomic extent and severity of oral mucositis. This study generated an Oral Mucositis Assessment Scale (OMAS) as a tool for assessing the severity of oral mucositis. In accordance with this scale, a physician evaluates multiple regions of the oral cavity for erythema and the presence and size of ulcerations or pseudo membranous. For example, erythema is evaluated as being “none”, “mild/moderate” or “severe.” The presence and size of ulcerations or pseudo membranes are evaluated as being “none”, “&lt;1 cm<sup>2</sup>”, “1 to 3 cm<sup>2</sup>”, or “&gt;3 cm<sup>2</sup>.” In patients receiving ablative chemotherapy and bone marrow transplantation, there is a significant correlation between OMAS scores and oral pain, difficulty swallowing and inability to eat. With the exception of fever, there is a close correlation between peak OMAS scores and selected clinical and economic outcomes in blood and marrow transplantation.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0005">Although OMAS scoring provides at least a pseudo-quantitative approach, scoring a particular patient still requires sophisticated knowledge and the implementation of somewhat subjective evaluation techniques. There is such a strong requirement for training and because the categorization of erythema and the presence and size of ulcerations or pseudo membranes introduce some subjective analysis in assigning a particular rating for scoring. Moreover, such approaches are dependent on the medical personnel who have the requisite training. That is, two physicians examining the same patient are prone to rate the same patient with slightly different scores.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0006">What is needed is an objective repeatable test that will provide an OMAS score as an accurate assessment of oral mucositis. Moreover, what is needed is a method and apparatus that allows support staff to do the diagnosis with a measure of repeatability of OMAS scores with patients of similar levels of oral mucositis.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0007">Therefore it is an object of this invention to provide a method and apparatus for enabling the assessment of oral mucositis.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0008">In accordance with this invention a value or an oral mucositis assessment scale at a site in a patient is obtained by acquiring data samples that represent the moisture content at the site. The acquired data samples are then converted to an oral mucositis assessment scale reading for display.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0009">The appended claims particularly point out and distinctly claim the subject matter of this invention. The various objects, advantages and novel features of this invention will be more fully apparent from a reading of the following detailed description in conjunction with the accompanying drawings in which like reference numerals refer to like parts, and in which:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> depicts the apparatus for obtaining measurements in the oral cavity in accordance with this invention;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of one embodiment of an OMAS converter as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flow diagram of the procedures used to process the data; and</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 through 6</figref> depict the relationship between various measurements and the OMAS scores.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF ILLUSTRATIVE EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> depicts apparatus <b>10</b> for obtaining OMAS scores by means of the measurement of surface moisture. The apparatus <b>10</b> includes a DPM (Dermal Phase Meter) control <b>11</b> with a probe <b>12</b> for insertion in the mouth <b>13</b> of a patient <b>14</b>. The DPM control <b>11</b> and probe <b>12</b> can comprise a dermatological instrument, such as a NOVA DPM 9020/Petite Dermal Phase Meter sold by Nova Technology Corporation, or any equivalent instrument. The Dermal Phase Meter control <b>11</b>, probe <b>12</b> and interconnecting cable <b>15</b> cooperate to make measurements of moisture levels by contacting a sensor in the probe <b>12</b> with the skin or tissue. Specifically, the DPM control <b>11</b> and probe <b>12</b> take successive impedance measurements of the tissue in contact with the probe to obtain a capacitance value that correlates with a biophysical property of the skin, such as moisture level. Typically such Dermal Phase Meters have been used to make measurements of the capacitive reactance of skin, such as the skin on hands and other external surfaces of the body to provide evaluations of other processes and protocols, such as burn therapy.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0015">In accordance with this invention, the output of the DPM control <b>11</b> transfers to an OMAS converter <b>16</b>. An example of an OMAS converter <b>16</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> as including a processor <b>17</b> with a memory <b>18</b>. The processor <b>17</b> and memory <b>18</b> interact to receive DPM signals from the DPM control <b>11</b> through an input interface <b>19</b>. An output interface <b>20</b> transfers signals to an output device, such as an external display <b>21</b> also shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. As will be apparent, the OMAS converter <b>16</b> and display <b>21</b> could be implemented in a personal computer or other similar device that has the capacity for receiving the DPM signal, for performing the necessary data storage and analysis as will be described, and for providing an OMAS value.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> depicts one procedure for implementing this invention as can be performed in a computer-based OMAS converter <b>16</b>. Before discussing this procedure, it will be helpful to understand variations in the protocol for making these measurements and some basic operational characteristics of a Dermal Phase Meter. A Dermal Phase Meter, such as the DPM-9020 Dermal Phase Meter, generates a series of discrete readings at a frequency generally set by the manufacturer, but, in some embodiments, by the user. The rate at which such readings are taken is a reading rate and a reading time represents the time between successive readings. A sample comprises a set of readings. The set can be delimited by time or reading values. For the assessment of this invention, it is assumed that time will delimit the sample. In one assessment protocol the sample time begins shortly after the probe contacts the tissue at a site and terminates about ten seconds later.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0017">An assessment may involve taking samples from multiple sites within the mouth, it may involve taking multiple samples from a single site in the mouth separated by some period of time, usually minutes. An assessment may also involve taking successive sets of multiple samples from multiple sites with readings for a first site in a set starting some time interval after the readings for a prior set have been completed.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0018">The process shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> for obtaining OMAS scores begins by initializing the system in step <b>31</b>. In the particularly disclosed implementation of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the person running the system <b>10</b> sets sample time. That is, the person will identify the time during which readings are taken. Step <b>31</b> would also include setting other variables, such as the reading time, if such initialization were necessary.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0019">Step <b>32</b> selects a site for testing. This provides the operator with the possibility of taking readings from a single or multiple sites. Step <b>33</b> initiates the readings for the sample once the probe <b>12</b> is properly located at a site with a patient's mouth.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0020">Step <b>34</b> is a loop control for receiving and recording data readings from the DPM control <b>11</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Initially step <b>34</b> transfers control to step <b>35</b> that records a data reading usually in a time-stamped format. Step <b>36</b> then establishes a wait interval corresponding to the reading time. This loop continues until the test sample has been completed as defined in step <b>31</b> whereupon control transfers to step <b>37</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0021">Step <b>37</b> represents a step whereby the person conducting the assessment determines whether additional sites are to be sampled. If more sites are to be sampled, control transfers back to step <b>32</b> to perform the selection by moving the probe <b>12</b> to another site. Thus, the loop comprising steps <b>32</b> through <b>37</b> could be used to take a single sample from multiple sites, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0022">When all the sites have been sampled, step <b>37</b> transfers control to step <b>40</b> that represents another control point for the person administering the diagnoses. A test could be considered complete if all the sites have been measured one time. If the test is to involve multiple samples from multiple sites, step <b>40</b> transfers control back to step <b>32</b> to produce another set of samples. Although not shown, it will be apparent that step <b>40</b> could include some time interval or delay or other parameter to control the circumstances under what that control would transfer.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0023">When the test is complete, step <b>40</b> transfers control to step <b>41</b> that converts this sampling to the OMAS score and displays the OMAS score at step <b>42</b>, for example at the display <b>21</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>. Then step <b>43</b> terminates the process of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0024">As previously indicated, an overall OMAS score has two constituents; namely (1) the contribution to the OMAS score of erythema and (2) the contribution to the OMAS score of ulceration. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> depicts a relationship between the average DPM readings at different sites for a set of samples with respect to erythema. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> depicts a relationship between the average DPM rating and ulceration scores; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> depicts a relationship between average DPM readings and overall OMAS scores. In each of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 through 6</figref> this relationship is linear. The slope of each of these graphs then represents the corresponding K(I) constant for that particular relationship.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0025">Each analysis shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 through 6</figref> exhibits a strong correlation between average DPM readings and total and constituent OMAS scores. Letting DPM represent average DPM readings, DPM<sub>0 </sub>represent the DPM ready for a zero OMAS score and OMAS represent the OMAS score, each of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 through 6</figref> define a general correlation of:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>DPM=<i>K</i>(OMAS+DPM<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Solving the OMAS yields:
</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0026">
<maths id="MATH-US-00002" num="00002">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mrow>
  <mi>OMAS</mi>
  <mo>=</mo>
  <mfrac>
    <mrow>
      <mi>DPM</mi>
      <mo>-</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>DPM</mi>
        <mn>0</mn>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
      <mi>K</mi>
      <mo>⁡</mo>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mi>I</mi>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mrow>
  </mfrac>
</mrow>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0027">As will be apparent K(I) will vary with each analysis. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 through 6</figref>, K(I) will be a negative number. For specifically K(erythema)=−6; K(ulceration)=−5; and K(OMAS)=−3.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0028">Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, step <b>41</b> selects the appropriate value of K(I) to convert the data into a desired one of the constituent or overall OMAS score. Such a selection can be programmed into the converter.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0029">It will now be apparent that the apparatus in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> combined with the processing according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, or equivalent apparatus and programming, produces an apparatus and protocol that provides objective OMAS scores based upon simply administered tissue measurements readily taught to nurses and other non-physician staff. Consequently it is possible to train medical staff to perform this diagnosis. Further, the diagnosis should be more consistent with respect to tests conducted by different untrained personnel. It will also be apparent that components of the specific structures and procedures disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 through 3</figref> can be modified to facilitate use of the structure or operation of the structure. It is the intent of the appended claims to cover all such variations and modifications as come within the true spirit and scope of this invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07297123-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07297123-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00002" nb-file="US07297123-20071120-M00002.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00002" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07297123-20071120-M00002.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. Apparatus for providing a value of an oral mucositis assessment scale at an oral site comprising:
<claim-text>A) measurement means for generating measured tissue moisture readings for the site,</claim-text>
<claim-text>B) acquisition means for acquiring data samples of the measured tissue moisture readings for the site, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>C) conversion means for converting the collected data samples to an oral mucositis assessment scale score.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. Apparatus as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said measurement means comprises a dermal phase meter means for generating successive impedance measurements at the site as the tissue moisture readings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. Apparatus as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said measurement means comprises a dermal phase meter means for making successive impedance measurements at a plurality of sites as the tissue moisture readings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. Apparatus for providing a value of an oral mucositis assessment scale at an oral site comprising:
<claim-text>A) measurement means for generating measured tissue moisture readings for the oral site,</claim-text>
<claim-text>B) acquisition means for acquiring data samples of the measured tissue moisture readings for the site, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>C) conversion means for converting the collected data samples to an oral mucositis assessment scale score wherein said conversion means includes means for generating an average of the samples, DPM ,and means for generating the oral mucositis assessment scale score, OMAS, according to OMAS=(DPM-DPM<b>0</b>)/K(I) where K(I) is a constant and DPM<b>0</b> is the value of DPM for a zero OMAS score.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. Apparatus as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein said conversion means includes means for storing values of K(I) for different analyses.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. Apparatus as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the oral mucositis assessment scale score includes erythema and ulceration constituents and said conversion means stores values of K for erythema, ulceration and OMAS.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. Apparatus as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein said measurement means comprises a dermal phase meter means for making successive impedance measurements at the site.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. Apparatus as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said measurement means generates readings at a given rate and said acquisition means includes means for selecting a group of readings as a data sample.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A method for providing a value of an oral mucositis assessment scale at an oral site comprising:
<claim-text>A) generating measured tissue moisture readings for the site,</claim-text>
<claim-text>B) acquiring data samples of the measured tissue moisture readings at the site, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>C) converting the collected data samples to an oral mucositis assessment scale score.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said generation includes making successive impedance measurement readings at the site.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said generation includes making successive impedance measurements readings at a plurality of sites.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein conversion includes generating an average of the samples, DPM, and generating the oral mucositis assessment scale, OMAS, according to OMAS=(DPM-DPM<b>0</b>)/K(I) where K(I) is a constant and DPM<b>0</b> is the value of DPM for a zero OMAS score.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein different values of K(I) are stored for different analyses.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the oral mucositis assessment scale score includes erythema and ulceration constituents and the stored values for K(I) are values for erythema, ulceration and OMAS.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said generation comprises making successive impedance measurements at the site.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein said generation generates readings at a given rate of acquisition and selects a group of readings as a data sample.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
