<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298583-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298583</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11036685</doc-number>
<date>20050114</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-194704</doc-number>
<date>20040630</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>308</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>33</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>360 9701</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Disk drive having holding member to secure control circuit board externally mounted to drive casing</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5768049</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Morehouse et al.</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360 9701</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5822152</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Seaver et al.</name>
<date>19981000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360 9908</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6560097</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Naruo et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361685</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6674608</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Bernett</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360 9701</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6767238</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kitadai</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439378</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0081348</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Watanabe et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2349734</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20001100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-210058</doc-number>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>360 9701</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>360137</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>360 9908</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>720648</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>720650</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361685</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439378</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060002005</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060105</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Miyazaki</last-name>
<first-name>Hideyuki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ome</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sato</last-name>
<first-name>Toshikuni</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fussa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Foley &amp; Lardner LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Kabushiki Kaisha Toshiba</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Tianjie</first-name>
<department>2627</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A disk drive includes a casing having a mount surface. The casing houses a disk-shaped recording medium, a drive motor which supports and rotates the recording medium, a head which performs information processing for the recording medium, a head actuator configured to movably support the head and move the head relative to the recording medium. A control circuit board is arranged to overlap the mount surface of the casing. A holding seal is adhered to the control circuit board and the casing, covering a peripheral portion of the control circuit board to press the peripheral portion to the mount surface.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="106.51mm" wi="149.27mm" file="US07298583-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="210.90mm" wi="165.61mm" file="US07298583-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="212.01mm" wi="151.55mm" file="US07298583-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="204.55mm" wi="153.67mm" file="US07298583-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="205.49mm" wi="155.96mm" file="US07298583-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="216.83mm" wi="144.19mm" file="US07298583-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="100.58mm" wi="108.71mm" file="US07298583-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is based upon and claims the benefit of priority from prior Japanese Patent Application No. 2004-194704, filed Jun. 30, 2004, the entire contents of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a disk drive having a disk for use as a recording medium.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In recent years, disk drives such as magnetic disk drives, optical disk drives, etc. have been widely used as external recording devices or image recording devices for computers.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A magnetic disk drive, as a disk drive, generally comprises a casing in the shape of a rectangular box. The casing houses a magnetic disk serving as a magnetic recording medium, a spindle motor serving as a drive means for holding and rotating the magnetic disk, a plurality of magnetic heads for writing information to and reading information from the magnetic disk, a head actuator for movably supporting plural magnetic heads relative to the magnetic disk, a voice coil motor for rotating and positioning the head actuator, and a board unit having arranged thereon a head IC and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A printed circuit board that controls the operations of the spindle motor, voice coil motor, and magnetic heads through the board unit is screwed to the outer surface of the casing. An interface (I/F) connector for connecting the magnetic disk drive to an external device is soldered to an end portion of the printed circuit board.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Described in Jpn. Pat. Appln. KOKAI Publication No. 2001-210058 is a magnetic disk drive in the form of a thin card which can be loaded into a card slot of a personal computer, for example. The card-shaped magnetic disk drive of this type is required to be made thinner and smaller than a conventional one. To meet this requirement, various components are mounted on a plate-shaped base, a support frame is fixed on the peripheral edge of the base, and a plate-shaped top cover is attached to the support frame. Further, a printed circuit board is arranged on the backside of the base, and an I/F connector on the printed circuit board is positioned and held by means of a dedicated fixing member on the support frame.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Miniaturization of magnetic disk drives these days is being promoted so that they can be used as recording devices for a wider variety of electronic devices, especially for smaller-sized electronic devices. For example, in a magnetic disk drive having housed therein a disk whose diameter is one inch or more, a printed circuit board, which is so arranged as to overlap the surface of a casing, can be made smaller than the area of the casing surface. However, in a magnetic disk drive having housed therein a disk whose diameter is one inch or less, the area of the casing surface on which a printed circuit board is mounted is made small due to miniaturization of a casing. Accordingly, it is required that a printed circuit board be arranged on a casing with approximately the entire casing surface covered thereby. Furthermore, in a small-sized magnetic disk drive, a thinly formed printed circuit board is arranged so as to reduce the thickness of the entire device, which undesirably weakens the device strength.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In such magnetic disk drives, peripheral edge portions of a printed circuit board can be released or detached easily, and when holding the sides of a magnetic disk drive, there is a fear that peripheral edge portions of a printed circuit board may be peeled off or broken. Especially, in miniaturizing magnetic disk drives, it is desired that the number of screw cramp portions on a printed circuit board be small. On the other hand, when the number of screw cramp portions is reduced, it becomes difficult to securely fix a printed circuit board.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to an embodiment of the present invention, a disk drive has a casing having a mount surface on the exterior of the casing; a disk-shaped recording medium arranged in the casing; a drive motor which supports and rotates the recording medium, and is arranged in the casing; a head which performs information processing for the recording medium; a head actuator arranged in the casing and configured to movably support the head and move the head relative to the recording medium; a control circuit board arranged to overlap the mount surface of the casing; and a holding member attached to the casing. The holding member covers at least a portion of the periphery of the control circuit board, and holding at least the portion of the periphery of the control circuit board to the mount surface.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to another embodiment of the invention a disk drive has a casing having a mount surface; a disk-shaped recording medium arranged in the casing; a drive motor which supports and rotates the recording medium, and is arranged in the casing; a head which performs information processing for the recording medium; a head actuator arranged in the casing and configured to movably support the head and move the head relative to the recording medium; a control circuit board arranged to overlap the mount surface of the casing; and a holding seal. The holding seal is adhered to the control circuit board and the casing, and covers at least a portion of a periphery of the control circuit board to hold at least the portion of the periphery to the mount surface.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWING</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The accompanying drawings, which are incorporated in and constitute a part of the specification, illustrate embodiments of the invention, and together with the general description given above and the detailed description of the embodiments given below, serve to explain the principles of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a perspective view of an HDD according to the first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an exploded perspective view of the HDD;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a plan view of a casing and the internal structure of the HDD;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a perspective view of the HDD when viewed from the side of a control circuit board;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a cross-sectional view of the HDD along a line V-V shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows an exploded perspective view of the casing, control circuit board, and a holding seal of the HDD;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows an enlarged cross-sectional view of part of the holding seal;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows a perspective view of an HDD according to the second embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows an exploded perspective view of the HDD in the second embodiment; and</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows a cross-sectional view of the HDD along a line X-X shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">A first embodiment, in which the present invention is applied to a hard disk drive (referred to as HDD, hereinafter), will be described in detail with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the HDD comprises a casing <b>10</b> substantially in the shape of a rectangular box that houses various components, which will be mentioned later, and a rectangular control circuit board <b>12</b> that is so arranged as to overlap a mount surface of the casing <b>10</b>. The casing <b>10</b> and the control circuit board <b>12</b> have a length L of 32 mm and a width W of 24 mm, and a thickness T, including thicknesses of the casing and the control circuit board, of 5 mm or 3.3 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the casing <b>10</b> that constitutes the body of the HDD includes first and second shells <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>b</i>, which have substantially equal dimensions. The first and second shells <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>b </i>are of substantially rectangular metallic structures having sidewalls on their respective peripheral edge portions. The first and second shells <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>b </i>are so arranged as to face each other with their peripheral edge portions facing each other with the respective sidewalls in contact with one another. A belt-shaped sealing member <b>16</b> is wound around the sidewalls of the first and second shells <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>b </i>so that the peripheral edge portions are connected and sealed to each other. In this way, the casing <b>10</b> in the shape of a rectangular box is configured.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The outer surface of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a </i>serves as a first main surface of the casing <b>10</b>, and the first main surface configures a rectangular mount surface <b>11</b>. The outer surface of the second shell <b>10</b><i>b </i>configures a rectangular second main surface <b>13</b> of the casing <b>10</b>, which is opposed to the mount surface <b>11</b>. The casing <b>10</b> has its four corners including the corners of the mount surface <b>11</b> and second main surface <b>13</b> rounded, forming circular arcs. As a result, the sealing member <b>16</b> wound around the peripheral edge portions of the casing <b>10</b> is prevented from being damaged by the corners of the casing, and deterioration of airtightness due to release of the sealing member is prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a plurality of support posts <b>18</b> are arranged on the peripheral edge portions at the inside of the casing <b>10</b>. Each support post <b>18</b> has a proximal end that is fixed to the inner surface of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a</i>, and is substantially perpendicular to the inner surface of the first shell. The mount surface <b>11</b> is provided with screw holes at positions corresponding to the respective support posts <b>18</b>, which extend into the inside of the support posts.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The casing <b>10</b> houses a magnetic disk <b>20</b> having a diameter of, e.g., 0.85 inch and serving as an information recording medium, a spindle motor <b>22</b> serving as a drive motor for supporting and rotating the magnetic disk, magnetic heads <b>24</b> for writing information to and reading information from the magnetic disk, a carriage <b>26</b> for movably supporting the magnetic heads relative to the magnetic disk <b>20</b>, a voice coil motor (referred to as VCM, hereinafter) <b>28</b> for rotating and positioning the carriage, a ramp load mechanism <b>30</b> for unloading the magnetic heads to a position away from the magnetic disk and holding the magnetic head thereat when the magnetic heads are moved to the outer peripheral portion of the magnetic disk, an electromagnetic latch <b>32</b> for holding the carriage in a retreated position, and a board unit <b>34</b> having arranged thereon a head IC etc.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The spindle motor <b>22</b> is mounted on the first shell <b>10</b><i>a</i>. The spindle motor <b>22</b> has a spindle <b>36</b> that is fixed to the inner surface of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a</i>, and is substantially perpendicular to the inner surface. The extended end of the spindle <b>36</b> is fixed to the second shell <b>10</b><i>b </i>by a fixing screw <b>37</b> that is screwed into the second shell from outside. Thus, the spindle <b>36</b> is supported by the first and second shells <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>b </i>from both sides.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">A bearing, not shown, rotatably supports a rotor on the spindle <b>36</b>. The end portion of the rotor at the side of the second shell <b>10</b><i>b </i>constitutes a columnar hub <b>43</b>, on which the magnetic disk <b>20</b> is coaxially fitted. A clamp ring <b>44</b> in the form of a ring is fitted on the end portion of the hub <b>43</b>, thereby holding the inner peripheral portion of the magnetic disk <b>20</b>. Thus, the magnetic disk <b>20</b> is fixed to the rotor, which enables the magnetic disk <b>20</b> to be rotatably supported integrally with the rotor.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">A ring-shaped permanent magnet, not shown, is fixed to the end portion of the rotor at the side of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a </i>such that the permanent magnet is coaxial with the rotor. The spindle motor <b>22</b> has a stator core, not shown, attached to the first shell <b>10</b><i>a</i>, and a plurality of coils wound around the stator core. The stator core and the coils are located outside the permanent magnet with a gap arranged therebetween.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The carriage <b>26</b>, which constitutes a head actuator, is provided with a bearing assembly <b>52</b> that is fixed to the inner surface of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a</i>. The bearing assembly <b>52</b> has a pivot <b>53</b> that is perpendicularly fixed to the inner surface of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a</i>, and a cylindrical hub <b>54</b> that is rotatably supported by the pivot <b>53</b> using a pair of bearings. The extended end of the pivot <b>53</b> is fixed to the second shell <b>10</b><i>b </i>by a fixing screw <b>56</b> that is screwed into the second shell from outside. Thus, the pivot <b>53</b> is supported by the first and second shells <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>b </i>from both sides.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The carriage <b>26</b> is provided with an arm <b>58</b> extending from the hub <b>54</b>, a suspension <b>60</b> in the form of an elongated plate extending from the distal end of the arm, and a support frame <b>62</b> extending from the hub <b>54</b> in a direction opposite to the extending direction of the arm. The extended end of the suspension <b>60</b> supports the magnetic head <b>24</b> through gimbals portion, not shown. A predetermined head load, brought about by spring force of the suspension <b>60</b>, is applied to the magnetic head <b>24</b> in a direction toward the surface of the magnetic disk <b>20</b>. A voice coil <b>64</b>, constituting the VCM <b>28</b>, is unitedly fixed to the support frame <b>62</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The VCM <b>28</b>, which rotates the carriage <b>26</b> about the bearing assembly <b>52</b>, includes a pair of yokes <b>63</b> which are fixed to the first shell <b>10</b><i>a </i>and face each other with a gap provided therebetween, and a magnet, not shown, which is fixed to the inner surface of one of the yokes and faces the voice coil <b>64</b>. When the voice coil <b>64</b> is energized, the carriage <b>26</b> pivots over the surface of the magnetic disk <b>20</b>, leaving from the retreated position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Thereupon, the magnetic head <b>24</b> is positioned on a desired track of the magnetic disk <b>20</b>. The electromagnetic latch <b>32</b>, which is fixed to the first shell <b>10</b><i>a</i>, latches the carriage <b>26</b> in the retreated position, thereby preventing the carriage <b>26</b> from moving from the retreated position to the operating position when the HDD is subjected to external force such as shock.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The ramp load mechanism <b>30</b> comprises a ramp member <b>70</b> that is fixed to the inner surface of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a </i>and faces the outer peripheral portion of the magnetic disk <b>20</b>, and a tab <b>72</b> that extends from the distal end of the suspension <b>60</b> and serves as an engaging member. The ramp member <b>70</b> is formed by bending a plate member and has a ramp surface <b>73</b> with which the tab <b>72</b> can engage. When the carriage <b>26</b> pivots from the inner peripheral portion of the magnetic disk <b>20</b> to the retreated position located around the outer peripheral portion of the magnetic disk, the tab <b>72</b> engages with the ramp surface <b>73</b> of the ramp member <b>70</b>. Thereafter, the tab <b>72</b> is pulled up by the inclination of the ramp surface, whereupon the magnetic head <b>24</b> is unloaded. When the carriage <b>26</b> pivots to the retreated position, the tab <b>72</b> is supported on the ramp surface <b>73</b> of the ramp member <b>70</b>, and the magnetic head <b>24</b> is kept distant from the surface of the magnetic disk <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The board unit <b>34</b> has a body <b>40</b><i>a </i>that is formed of a flexible printed circuit board, and the body <b>40</b><i>a </i>is fixed to the inner surface of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a</i>. The head IC, a head amplifier, and other electronic components are mounted on the body <b>40</b><i>a</i>. The board unit <b>34</b> has a main flexible printed circuit board (referred to as main FPC, hereinafter) <b>41</b> that extends from the body <b>40</b><i>a</i>. The extended end of the main FPC <b>41</b> is connected to the vicinity of the bearing assembly <b>52</b> of the carriage <b>26</b>, and is also electrically connected to the magnetic head <b>24</b> through a cable, not shown, arranged on the arm <b>58</b> and suspension <b>60</b>. A connector <b>34</b><i>c </i>to be connected to the control circuit board <b>12</b> is mounted on the bottom surface of the body <b>40</b><i>a </i>of the board unit <b>34</b>. The connector <b>34</b><i>c </i>is exposed to the mount surface <b>11</b> of the first shell <b>10</b><i>a </i>through an opening provided at the first shell.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the control circuit board <b>12</b> formed of a printed circuit board is of a rectangular shape whose length and width are substantially equal to those of the mount surface <b>11</b> of the casing <b>10</b>. The mount surface <b>11</b> of the casing <b>10</b> has formed thereon a circular convex surface <b>70</b><i>a </i>corresponding to the spindle motor <b>22</b> and a circular convex surface <b>70</b><i>b </i>corresponding to the bearing assembly <b>52</b>. The control circuit board <b>12</b> is provided with circular openings <b>72</b><i>a</i>, <b>72</b><i>b </i>corresponding to the convex surfaces <b>70</b><i>a</i>, <b>70</b><i>b</i>, respectively. Furthermore, the control circuit board <b>12</b> has mounted thereon a plurality of electronic components <b>74</b>, a connector <b>71</b>, and has formed thereon a plurality of connecting terminals <b>79</b> which are arranged along one of short sides thereof. A flexible printed circuit board <b>76</b> for connecting the HDD to an external device is connected to the connecting terminals <b>79</b>. The flexible printed circuit board <b>76</b> is drawn from one of short sides of the control circuit board <b>12</b>, and is provided with a plurality of connecting terminals <b>75</b> at the extended end thereof. The control circuit board <b>12</b> has its four corners cut off obliquely such that the respective cut-off lines form angles of 45 degrees relative to the respective sides, forming cut-off portions <b>77</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Thus formed control circuit board <b>12</b> is arranged to be overlapped on the mount surface <b>11</b> of the casing <b>10</b>, and fixed to the first shell <b>10</b><i>a </i>using a plurality of screws. At this time, the four sides of the control circuit board <b>12</b> fit in with or agree with the four sides of the mount surface <b>11</b>. The convex surfaces <b>70</b><i>a</i>, <b>70</b><i>b </i>formed on the mount surface <b>11</b> are arranged within the openings <b>72</b><i>a</i>, <b>72</b><i>b </i>of the control circuit board <b>12</b>. The connector <b>71</b> mounted on the control circuit board <b>12</b> is connected to the connector <b>34</b><i>c </i>of the board unit <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The cut-off portions <b>77</b> formed at the four corners of the control circuit board <b>12</b> correspond to the four corners of the mount surface <b>11</b>, respectively. Thus, the four corners of the mount surface <b>11</b> are exposed to outside without being covered by the control circuit board <b>12</b>. The four corners of the casing <b>10</b> including the exposed four corners of the mount surface <b>11</b> configure holding potions <b>78</b> for holding the casing without coming into contact with the control circuit board <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a holding seal <b>80</b> is adhered to the outer surface of the casing <b>10</b> and the control circuit board <b>12</b>. The holding seal <b>80</b> serves as a holding member, and has first and second layers <b>80</b><i>a</i>, <b>80</b><i>b </i>made of polyethylene terephthalate, a shield layer <b>80</b><i>c </i>arranged between the first and second layers, and an adhesive layer <b>80</b><i>d </i>formed on the outer surface the first layer, which are layered, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The shield layer <b>80</b><i>c </i>is formed of evaporating aluminum.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the holding seal <b>80</b> unitedly has a rectangular main portion <b>81</b> with its dimensions made to correspond to those of the second main surface <b>13</b> of the casing <b>10</b>, and a plurality of extended portions <b>82</b><i>a</i>, <b>82</b><i>b</i>, <b>82</b><i>c</i>, <b>82</b><i>d</i>, <b>82</b><i>e </i>extending from the four sides of the main portion. The main portion <b>81</b> is provided with a circular through hole <b>83</b> that is so located as to correspond to the position of the bearing assembly <b>52</b>, and a circular through hole <b>84</b> that is so located as to correspond to the position of an air filter, not shown.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The holding seal <b>80</b> has its main portion <b>81</b> attached to substantially the entire area of the second main surface <b>13</b> with the adhesive layer <b>80</b><i>d </i>being in contact with the casing <b>10</b>. The circular through hole <b>83</b> is located to face the bearing assembly <b>52</b>. At the second main surface <b>13</b> of the casing <b>10</b>, a circular cover seal <b>85</b> sealing a screw hole is attached to the position corresponding to the bearing assembly <b>52</b>, and is located within the through hole <b>83</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The extended portion <b>82</b><i>a </i>is attached to the HDD to wind around the longitudinal side of the casing <b>10</b> and the longitudinal edge of the control circuit board <b>12</b>, and cover the outer surface of the sealing member <b>16</b> and the longitudinal edge of the control circuit board. The extended portions <b>82</b><i>b </i>and <b>82</b><i>c</i>, which are located on the opposite side of the extended portion <b>82</b><i>a</i>, are attached to the HDD as to wind around the other longitudinal side of the casing <b>10</b> and the other longitudinal edge of the control circuit board <b>12</b>, and cover the outer surface of the sealing member <b>16</b> and the other longitudinal edge of the control circuit board.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The extended portion <b>82</b><i>d </i>is attached to the HDD to wind around the shorter side of the casing <b>10</b> and the shorter edge of the control circuit board <b>12</b>, and cover the outer surface of the sealing member <b>16</b> and the shorter edge of the control circuit board. The extended portion <b>82</b><i>e </i>is attached to the HDD to wind around the other shorter side of the casing <b>10</b>, and cover the outer surface of the sealing member <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Accordingly, the control circuit board <b>12</b> and the casing <b>10</b> are held by the holding seal <b>80</b> such that the control circuit board <b>12</b> is pressed to the mount surface <b>11</b> with the pair of the opposing longitudinal side edges and one shorter edge located on the opposite side of the connecting terminals <b>79</b> of the control circuit board <b>12</b>, excluding one shorter edge provided with the connecting terminals <b>79</b>, being covered by the holding seal <b>80</b>. The four corners of the casing <b>10</b> including the four corners of the control circuit board <b>12</b> are exposed to outside without being covered by the holding seal <b>80</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, characters, patterns, etc. can be printed on the surface of the holding seal <b>80</b> or the outer surface of the second layer <b>80</b><i>b</i>, that is, the holding seal works as a label.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">According to thus configured HDD, the holding seal <b>80</b> is attached to the outer surface of the casing <b>10</b> and the outer surface of the control circuit board <b>12</b>. The control circuit board <b>12</b> and the casing <b>10</b> are held by the holding seal <b>80</b> such that the control circuit board <b>12</b> is pressed to the mount surface <b>11</b> with at least two facing edges of the control circuit board being covered by the holding seal <b>80</b>. Thus, the peripheral edge portion of the thin control circuit board <b>12</b> of low device strength is protected by the holding seal <b>80</b>, which can prevent release, peel-off, and breakdown of the peripheral edge portion of the control circuit board. Even if the number of screws for fixing the control circuit board <b>12</b> to the casing <b>10</b> is reduced, the control circuit board can be stably held by the holding seal <b>80</b>. The HDD can be further miniaturized by reducing the number of screws for fixing the control circuit board <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In the embodiment, the holding seal <b>80</b> has the shield layer <b>80</b><i>c</i>. Thus, the holding seal <b>80</b> can shield noise generated from the inside of the HDD and noise breaking into the inside of the HDD from the outside, which can improve reliability of the HDD.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The casing <b>10</b> has its four corners including the four corners of the mount surface <b>11</b> rounded, and the control circuit board <b>12</b> arranged on the mount surface has its four corners cut off obliquely to form the cut-off portions <b>77</b> respectively. The four corners of the casing <b>10</b> including the exposed four corners of the mount surface <b>11</b> configure the holding potions <b>78</b> for holding the casing. Accordingly, the HDD can be mounted to an electronic device by holding the four holding potions <b>78</b> without coming into contact with the control circuit board <b>12</b>. Thus, even if the control circuit board <b>12</b> is made thin, and is arranged to be overlapped on the entire area of the mount surface <b>11</b> except its four corner portions, the control circuit board is prevented from being affected by mechanical burden, and the HDD can be stably held without risking peel-off and breakdown of the control circuit board.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The first and second shells <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>b </i>that constitute the casing <b>10</b> are so supported as to face each other with a given gap defined therebetween by the support posts <b>18</b> arranged on one of the shells. Therefore, if any external force acts on the casing <b>10</b>, the casing <b>10</b> and various components arranged therein can be prevented from being damaged. With use of the support posts <b>18</b>, moreover, screwing positions between the first and second shells <b>10</b><i>a </i>and <b>10</b><i>b </i>can be reduced in number, and assemblability and maintainability can be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The card-shaped, portable HDD constructed in this manner can be used as a recording device for various electronic devices such as a cellular phone, digital camera, video camera, personal digital assistant (PDA), etc.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In the first embodiment, the holding seal <b>80</b> has its main portion <b>81</b> attached to substantially the entire area of the second main surface <b>13</b> of the casing <b>10</b>, and makes its plural extended portions wind around the sides of the casing <b>10</b> and the edges of the control circuit board <b>12</b> from the side of the second main surface.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Alternatively, the holding seal <b>80</b> may have its main portion <b>81</b> attached to substantially the entire area of the control circuit board <b>12</b>, and make its plural extended portions wind around the sides of the casing <b>10</b> and the edges of the second main surface <b>13</b> from the side of the control circuit board. In the embodiment, the holding seal <b>80</b> covers the three edges of the control circuit board <b>12</b>. On the other hand, circuit board holding effect can be sufficiently realized by covering at least two facing edges of the control circuit board.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> indicative of the second embodiment, as a holding member of the HDD, a mounting aid <b>120</b> may be used instead of the holding seal <b>80</b>. The mounting aid <b>120</b> has a body <b>122</b> in the shape of a rectangular frame that is fitted around the outer peripheral portion of the casing <b>10</b> as well as around the outer peripheral portion of the control circuit board <b>12</b>, and four brackets <b>125</b> which are fixed to the four corners of the body. The body <b>122</b> is made of elastic material such as rubber, synthetic resin, etc., and is elastically fitted around the outer peripheral portion of the casing <b>10</b>. The body <b>122</b> has its cross-section formed into substantially a channel, and is arranged around the sealing member <b>16</b> to cover the sides of the casing <b>10</b> as well as the edges of the second main surface <b>13</b> of the casing <b>10</b> and the edges of the control circuit board <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The respective brackets <b>125</b> are made of rubber, synthetic resin, etc. The respective brackets <b>125</b> are fitted on the respective corners of the body <b>122</b> from outside. Each bracket <b>125</b> has a pair of engaging members <b>128</b> that extend from the top and bottom portions of the corner of the body toward the inside of the body, and a leg member <b>124</b> that extends outward. The pair of the engaging members <b>128</b> face each other with a gap therebetween. These engaging members <b>128</b> are so engaged with the casing <b>10</b> as to sandwich the holding potions <b>78</b> thereof from upward and from downward. At this time, the engaging members <b>128</b> are engaged with the casing <b>10</b> without coming into contact with the control circuit board <b>12</b>. Each leg member <b>124</b> is provided with a through hole <b>126</b> through which a screw for installing the HDD to an electronic device can pass.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">A slit <b>130</b> is formed at one sidewall of the body <b>122</b>. The flexible printed circuit board <b>76</b>, which extends from the control circuit board <b>12</b> and configures a connecting cable, is drawn out to outside through the slit <b>130</b> of the body <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">In the second embodiment, parts or components other than the HDD are similar to those of the first embodiment, and are indicated with the same reference numerals, and detailed explanation of which will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">According to the HDD constructed as described above, the control circuit board <b>12</b> has its peripheral edge portion covered by the body <b>122</b> of the mounting aid <b>120</b>, and is so held as to be pressed to the mount surface <b>11</b> of the casing <b>10</b>. Thus, the peripheral edge portion of the thin control circuit board <b>12</b> of low device strength is protected by the mounting aid <b>120</b>, which can prevent release, peel-off, and breakdown of the peripheral edge portion of the control circuit board. Even if the number of screws for fixing the control circuit board <b>12</b> to the casing <b>10</b> is reduced, the control circuit board can be stably held by the mounting aid <b>120</b>. Moreover, the HDD can be further miniaturized by reducing the number of screws for fixing the control circuit board <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">By attaching the mounting aid <b>120</b> to the HDD, the HDD can be mounted to a desired position in an electronic device with ease. Since the extended end of the flexible printed circuit board <b>76</b>, which is provided with connecting terminals <b>75</b>, is held at a predetermined position by retaining lugs <b>132</b>, the HDD can be electrically connected to an electronic device easily and reliably.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">It is to be understood that the present invention is not limited to the precise embodiments described above, and that various changes and modifications may be effected therein without departing from the scope or spirit of the invention. Further, various other inventions may be made by suitably combining the components described in connection with the foregoing embodiments. For example, some of the components according to the embodiments may be omitted. Further, the components according to different embodiments may be suitably combined as required.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">For example, material of the holding seal is not restricted to above-described embodiment, and can be selected variedly. Furthermore, the shield layer of the holding seal can be omitted. The number of magnetic disks is not restricted to one, and can be increased according to need. The diameter of the magnetic disk is not restricted to 0.85 inch, and can be 1.5 inch or 2.5 inches. Furthermore, the control circuit board may be provided with a connector for making a connection with an external device instead of a connecting cable.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A disk drive comprising:
<claim-text>a casing having a mount surface on the exterior surface thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a disk-shaped recording medium arranged in the casing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a drive motor which supports and rotates the recording medium, and is arranged in the casing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a head which performs information processing for the recording medium;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a head actuator arranged in the casing and configured to movably support the head and move the head relative to the recording medium;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control circuit board arranged to overlap the mount surface of the casing; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a holding seal adhered to the control circuit board and the casing, covering at least a portion of a periphery of the control circuit board to hold at least the portion of the periphery to the mount surface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the holding seal is adhered to wind around the outer surfaces of the control circuit board and the casing, and covers at least two opposing side edges of the control circuit board.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the control circuit board is of a generally rectangular shape and has connecting terminals arranged along one side thereof, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the holding seal covers two opposing side edges of the control circuit board excluding said one side of the control circuit board.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the casing has a first main surface configuring the mount surface, and a second main surface opposed to the first main surface, and the holding seal is adhered to cover the second main surface and two opposite sides of the casing, and the portion of the periphery of the control circuit board.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the casing is of a generally rectangular shape and has four rounded corners including corners of the mount surface, and the control circuit board is of a generally rectangular shape and has four sides which are aligned with the respective four sides of the mount surface, and has four corners cut off obliquely so as to expose the four corners of the mount surface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the casing has a first shell, and a second shell that is so arranged as to face the first shell and configures the casing together with the first shell, and the first and second shells having peripheral edge portions facing each other,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the casing has a sealing member that is wound around the peripheral edge portions of the first and second shells to seal the peripheral edge portions to each other, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the holding seal is adhered to overlap the sealing member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the holding seal has a shield layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the holding seal has a surface on which a label is printed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the casing and the control circuit board are each of a generally rectangular shape and each have a longitudinal length of approximately 32 mm, a width of approximately 24 mm, and wherein the combined thickness of the casing and the control circuit board is approximately 3.3 mm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said holding seal is adhered to substantially the entire surface of at least one of said control circuit board and said casing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. In a disk drive having a casing having a mount surface on the exterior surface thereof, a disk-shaped recording medium arranged in the casing, a drive motor which supports and rotates the recording medium, and is arranged in the casing, a head which performs information processing for the recording medium, a head actuator arranged in the casing and configured to movably support the head and move the head relative to the recording medium, and a control circuit board arranged to overlap the mount surface of the casing, a method of securing the control circuit board to the casing comprising the step of:
<claim-text>adhering a holding seal to at least a portion of the control circuit board and the casing, said holding seal covering at least a portion of a periphery of the control circuit board to hold the control circuit board to the mount surface of the casing.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
