<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296832-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296832</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11168773</doc-number>
<date>20050628</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>E</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>19</main-group>
<subgroup>18</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>292292</main-classification>
<further-classification>292DIG 17</further-classification>
<further-classification> 16353</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Locking mechanism for door hinge</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>1151397</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Robinson</name>
<date>19150800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 16353</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2462268</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kahi</name>
<date>19490200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 70  1</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4564974</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>McGrail et al.</name>
<date>19860100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 16353</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5590922</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hucknall</name>
<date>19970100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>292300</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5727289</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Reder</name>
<date>19980300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 16375</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6431621</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>De Groot</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>292346</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6591453</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Jenks</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 16353</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>292288</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>292289</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>292292</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>292DIG 17</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>292283</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>292284</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 16331</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 16332</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 16352</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 16353</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Campbell</last-name>
<first-name>John</first-name>
<address>
<street>102 Natchez St.</street>
<city>Starkville</city>
<state>MS</state>
<postcode>39759</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Garvey, Smith, Nehrbass &amp; North, L.L.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Smith</last-name>
<first-name>Gregory C.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Estremsky</last-name>
<first-name>Gary</first-name>
<department>3676</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A locking mechanism for hinges, which includes a butt hinge of the type securable between a door frame jamb and a door stile, having first and second leaves moveable along a common axis; upper and lower loops formed along the upper and lower edges of the leaf secured to the door frame jamb, the loops extending over the leaf of the door stile when the door is in the closed configuration and the leaves abut one another; and a pin insertable into the upper loop and extending into the lower loop, defining a means for blocking the movement of the stile leaf when force is placed upon the door in order to attempt to open it. The leaves are free to open when the pin is removed.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="152.74mm" wi="159.00mm" file="US07296832-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="204.30mm" wi="147.15mm" file="US07296832-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Not applicable</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR DEVELOPMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Not applicable</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">REFERENCE TO A “MICROFICHE APPENDIX”</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Not applicable</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The present invention relates to locking mechanisms for doors. More particularly the present invention relates to a locking device adaptable to door hinges which maintain a door in a closed position until the device is removed.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">2. General Background</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Hinged doors, whether providing ingress and egress between rooms are between the interior and exterior of a building are most often equipped with a lock, which is usually a latch of dead bolt on the door face which engages the edge of the distal edge of the door into the door jam. This is for the most part a universal way of locking doors in the closed orientation.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">One shortcoming of such a lock is that the locking device, for the most part, is only as strong as the door jam into which it engages. That is, particularly with exterior doors, if a burglar wishes to enter a locked premises, oftentimes the burglar will place such force between the door and the jam, that the jam with give way, and the lock, of course, is no longer engaged. Because of this prevalent shortcoming, there is a need to provide a lock for a door which will not be necessarily dependent upon the strength of the jam into which the door is closed. Or, there is a need for a secondary locking device which may supplement the usual dead bolt or other standard door lock.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A locking mechanism for door hinge, usually referred to as a butt hinge, of the type securable between a door frame jamb and a door stile, having first and second leaves moveable along a common axis; upper and lower loops formed along the upper and lower edges of the leaf secured to the door frame jamb, the loops extending over the leaf of the door stile when the door is in the closed configuration and the leaves abut one another; and a pin insertable into the upper loop and extending into the lower loop, blocking the movement of the stile leaf when force is placed upon the door in order to attempt to open it, and when the pin is removed, the leaves are free to open. The locking mechanism would be placed on one or more of the hinges of the door.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">For a further understanding of the nature, objects, and advantages of the present invention, reference should be had to the following detailed description, read in conjunction with the following drawings, wherein like reference numerals denote like elements and wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an overall view of the hinge locking mechanism mounted to an open door; and</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates an overall view of the hinge locking mechanism mounted to a closed door and locked in position.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> illustrate the preferred embodiment of the present invention by the numeral <b>10</b>. As illustrated the locking mechanism <b>10</b> is incorporated into a standard door hinge <b>12</b>, which comprises a first leaf <b>14</b> mounted on a door frame jamb <b>16</b>, through a plurality of screws <b>18</b> securing the leaf <b>14</b> against the jamb <b>16</b>. There is provided a second leaf <b>20</b> secured to the door stile <b>22</b> via a plurality of screws <b>18</b>, the first and second leaves <b>14</b>, rotatingly mounted to one another via a hinge pin <b>24</b> secured through interfitting collars <b>26</b> in each leaf <b>14</b>, <b>20</b>. This type of hinge is standard in the building industry, and is usually referred to as butt hinge <b>12</b>. The hinge <b>12</b>, as seen in the Figures, allows the door <b>13</b> to swing between an open position as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, where the hinge leaves <b>14</b>, <b>20</b> are exposed, to the closed position as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, where the leaves <b>14</b>, <b>20</b> abut one another between the closed door stile <b>22</b> and the frame jamb <b>16</b>. In most cases, the leaves <b>14</b>, <b>20</b> are secured in recessed formed in the stile <b>22</b> and jamb <b>16</b>, so that the door <b>13</b>, when closed, is able to but up against the frame jamb <b>16</b> for a more secure fit.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Reference is now made to the locking mechanism <b>10</b> which is an integral part of the modified hinges <b>12</b>, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>. As stated earlier, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the door <b>13</b> is in the open position away from the door jamb <b>16</b>. There is illustrated a loop member <b>30</b> secured to the upper edge <b>17</b> of the leaf <b>14</b> secured to the door jamb <b>16</b>, having a loop opening <b>19</b>. The loop member <b>30</b> would be integrally secured to the leaf edge <b>17</b> via welding or molded in place, and would extend sufficiently out away from the leaf <b>14</b>, defining an opening <b>19</b>, for the reasons explained latter. There is also a second loop <b>32</b> secured to the lower edge <b>19</b> of the leaf <b>14</b>, which would be vertically aligned with upper loop <b>30</b>, likewise defining an opening <b>19</b>, so that a pin <b>35</b> may be inserted into the opening <b>19</b> of the first loop <b>30</b> and extend downward into and through the opening <b>19</b> in the second loop <b>32</b>. There is provided a head <b>38</b> on pin <b>35</b> which prevents the pin <b>35</b> from sliding through the loops <b>30</b>, <b>32</b> when in place, with the head <b>38</b> of pin <b>35</b> resting on the upper loop <b>30</b>, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Turning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the door <b>13</b> has been swung closed from its open position in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, in the direction of arrow <b>40</b>, so that the leaves <b>14</b>, <b>20</b> abut one another, in when in that position, the loops <b>30</b>, <b>32</b> have overlapped past the hinge leaf <b>20</b>, so that the loop openings <b>19</b> are accessible for the pin <b>35</b> to be inserted. When the pin <b>35</b> is inserted in position, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, should one attempt to open the door <b>13</b>, the pin <b>35</b> would prevent the hinge leaves <b>14</b>, <b>20</b> from moving apart, and the door <b>13</b> would be in effect, locked closed. Of course, all one must do is remove the pin <b>35</b> from loops <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, and the door would be free to open, assuming the door lock is disengaged.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">It is foreseen that the locking mechanism described above would be used on at least one hinge <b>12</b>, but preferably would be used on all of the hinges <b>12</b>, which serve to lock a door <b>13</b> to a door jamb <b>16</b> more securely. With a plurality of these locking mechanisms <b>10</b> positioned on multiple hinges <b>12</b>, the integrity of the system would be more assured as a means for locking a door closed. Also, it is foreseen that this locking device could be retrofitted onto existing hinges, through welding the loops <b>30</b>, <b>32</b> to the hinge leaf <b>14</b> mounted on the jamb <b>16</b>, or they could be sold as hinges <b>12</b> which are modified with the locking mechanism in place.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">It is also understood that this locking device <b>10</b> for door hinges <b>12</b> could be either the primary or secondary means for locking a door closed; but, would in any even add an additional layer of protection from a closed door being forced open when the door lock is compromised.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">All measurements disclosed herein are at standard temperature and pressure, at sea level on Earth, unless indicated otherwise.</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">PARTS LIST</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0000">
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0019"><b>10</b> locking mechanism</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0020"><b>12</b> door hinge</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0003" num="0021"><b>13</b> door</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0004" num="0022"><b>14</b> first leaf</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0005" num="0023"><b>16</b> door frame jamb</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0006" num="0024"><b>17</b> upper leaf edge</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0007" num="0025"><b>18</b> screws</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0008" num="0026"><b>19</b> lower leaf edge</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0009" num="0027"><b>20</b> second leaf</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0010" num="0028"><b>22</b> door stile</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0011" num="0029"><b>24</b> hinge pine</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0012" num="0030"><b>26</b> collars</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0013" num="0031"><b>30</b> upper loop member</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0014" num="0032"><b>32</b> lower loop member</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0015" num="0033"><b>33</b> openings</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0016" num="0034"><b>35</b> pin</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0017" num="0035"><b>38</b> head</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0018" num="0036"><b>40</b> arrow</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0037">All measurements disclosed herein are at standard temperature and pressure, at sea level on Earth, unless indicated otherwise. All materials used or intended to be used in a human being are biocompatible, unless indicated otherwise.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0038">The foregoing embodiments are presented by way of example only; the scope of the present invention is to be limited only by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A locking door hinge, comprising:
<claim-text>a) a first leaf having a thickness, an inner edge, an outer edge, upper and lower edges, first and second planar surfaces, and a plurality of pin receptive sleeves extending along the inner edge, each sleeve having a sleeve bore;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b) a second leaf having a thickness, an inner edge, an outer edge, upper and lower edges, first and second planar surfaces, and a plurality of pin receptive sleeves extending along the inner edge, each sleeve having a sleeve bore;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c) the sleeves of the first and second leaves being offset, enabling the sleeve bores to be aligned along a common axis that defines a hinge pivot;</claim-text>
<claim-text>d) a pivot pin that extends through the sleeve bores, enabling the leaves to move between open and closed positions, the outer edges of the leaves being next to each other in the closed position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>e) a pair of locking flanges placed on the edges of the first leaf at a position that is spaced away from the sleeves;</claim-text>
<claim-text>f) each flange having a locking pin receptive flange opening;</claim-text>
<claim-text>g) the flange opening being spaced a distance from the first leaf that is greater than the thickness of the second leaf;</claim-text>
<claim-text>h) a locking pin that is removably connectable to the flanges at the flange openings in a locking position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>i) wherein in the locking position, the leafs are in the closed position and the locking pin constrains movement of the second leaf relative to the first leaf by contacting a planar surface of the second leaf at a position that is spaced in between the leaf inner and outer edges.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The locking door hinge of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one of the flanges is connected to the leaf at a position that extends along a leaf edge in between the inner and outer edges.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The locking door hinge of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one of the flanges is connected to the leaf at a position that extends along a leaf planar surface in between the inner and outer edges.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The locking door hinge of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein in the locking position, a planar surface of the second leaf transfers a shear load to the locking pin.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The locking door hinge of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein at least one of the flanges occupies a plane generally perpendicular to the hinge axis and the locking pin is generally parallel to the hinge axis in the locking position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The locking door hinge of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the flanges are placed respectively on the upper and lower edges of the first leaf.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The locking door hinge of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the second leaf contacts the locking pin continuously between the upper and lower leaf edges.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The locking door hinge of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the locking pin does not connect to any of the sleeves.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The locking door hinge of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein only sleeves are connected to the leaf inner edges and the locking pin does not connect to any sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A locking door hinge, comprising:
<claim-text>a) a first leaf having a thickness, a planar surface, an inner edge, an outer edge, upper and lower edges, and a plurality of pin receptive sleeves extending along the inner edge, each sleeve having a sleeve bore;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b) a second leaf having a thickness, an inner edge, an outer edge, upper and lower edges, and a plurality of pin receptive sleeves extending along the inner edge, each sleeve having a sleeve bore;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c) the sleeves of the first and second leaves being offset, enabling the sleeve bores to be aligned along a common axis that defines a hinge pivot;</claim-text>
<claim-text>d) a pivot pin that extends through the sleeve bores enabling the leaves to move between open and closed positions, the outer edges of the leaves being next to each other in the closed position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>e) a pair of locking flanges placed on the edges of the first leaf at a position that is spaced away from the sleeves;</claim-text>
<claim-text>f) each flange having a locking pin receptive opening;</claim-text>
<claim-text>g) the locking pin opening being spaced a distance from the first leaf that is greater than the thickness of the second leaf;</claim-text>
<claim-text>h) a locking pin that is removably connectable to the flanges at the flange openings in a locking position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>i) wherein in the locking position, the leaves are in the closed position and the locking pin constrains movement of the second leaf relative to the first leaf by transferring shear load to the pin via the flanges and the planar surface of the second leaf in between the flanges.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An improved locking door hinge, having a first leaf having a thickness, a planar surface, an inner edge, an outer edge, upper and lower edges, and a plurality of pin receptive sleeves extending along the inner edge, each sleeve having a sleeve bore; a second leaf having a thickness, an inner edge, an outer edge, upper and lower edges, and a plurality of pin receptive sleeves extending along the inner edge, each sleeve having a sleeve bore; the sleeves of the first and second leaves being offset, enabling the sleeve bores to be aligned along a common axis that defines a hinge pivot; and a pivot pin that extends through the sleeve bores enabling the leaves to move between open and closed positions, the outer edges of the leaves being next to each other in the closed position; the improvement comprising:
<claim-text>a) a pair of locking flanges placed on the edges of the first leaf at a position that is spaced away from the sleeves;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b) each flange having a locking pin receptive opening;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c) the locking pin opening being spaced a distance from the first leaf that is greater than the thickness of the second leaf;</claim-text>
<claim-text>d) a locking pin that is removably connectable to the flanges at the flange openings in a locking position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>e) wherein in the locking position, the leaves are in the closed position and the locking pin constrains movement of the second leaf relative to the first leaf by transferring shear load to the pin via the flanges and the planar surface of the second leaf in between the flanges.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
