<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297069-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297069</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11220829</doc-number>
<date>20050907</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>0509050.1</doc-number>
<date>20050504</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>218</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>69</main-group>
<subgroup>36</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473173</main-classification>
<further-classification>473221</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Putting practice aid</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2263727</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gensburg</name>
<date>19411100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>273118 A</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4160942</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lynch et al.</name>
<date>19790700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359443</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4560167</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Perreau et al.</name>
<date>19851200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5092602</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Witler et al.</name>
<date>19920300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>473199</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5221082</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Curshod</name>
<date>19930600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>473199</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0252567</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Donovan et al.</name>
<date>20061100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>473173</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO 97/04839</doc-number>
<date>19970200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>22</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473173</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473174</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473180</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473192</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473198</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473199</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473220</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473221</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060252567</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061109</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Donovan</last-name>
<first-name>Michael Kevin</first-name>
<address>
<city>Trentham Park</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>GB</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>GB</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Boyle</last-name>
<first-name>Michael John</first-name>
<address>
<city>Stoke-on-Trent</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>GB</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>GB</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Colton</last-name>
<first-name>Laurence P.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Smith, Gambrell &amp; Russell, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>The Puttalite Company Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Staffordshire</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chiu</last-name>
<first-name>Raleigh W.</first-name>
<department>3711</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A putting practice aid includes a light source to provide a virtual golf hole putting target and a detector to detect a golf ball with respect to the virtual golf hole.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="113.37mm" wi="281.94mm" file="US07297069-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="206.76mm" wi="176.61mm" file="US07297069-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="236.30mm" wi="192.19mm" file="US07297069-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="240.62mm" wi="182.12mm" file="US07297069-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates to a putting practice aid.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A number of putting practice aids have been proposed for golfers over the years. Such aids have generally not been particularly realistic in mimicking a true golf hole. Furthermore, in many instances they have not provided an indication as to whether a golf shot has been hit at a required strength to enter a hole, i.e. if a ball is hit too strongly it will pass over the hole, or run around the edge and not enter the hole.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">An important feature with putting is that a golfer should not move their head whilst playing the shot nor immediately after playing it, and should look downwardly at the ball whilst playing the shot. With many putting aids there is a temptation for a player to raise their head whilst, or at least immediately after playing a shot, to see whether the shot is successful. This feature makes it difficult to improve one's putting significantly using such aids, and it is also difficult to obtain much feedback concerning shots played.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">According to the present invention there is provided a putting practice aid, the aid including an arrangement for producing an image of a golf hole on the ground, and a detecting arrangement for determining the speed and direction of a golf ball directed at the visual image to ascertain whether the golf ball would have fallen into a golf hole at the image.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The detecting arrangement includes means for detecting where a ball crosses the image, and whether this would cause the ball to fall in a hole at the image. The aid may include a frame extendible spaced above the ground. The image producing arrangement may be provided on the frame and may include a light shinable downwardly to produce an image of a golf hole of a required size and shape. The image producing arrangement may include an LED which shines onto a lens.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The detecting arrangement may include the means for producing a plurality of beams which extend across the golf hole image, and means for determining when and for how long the beams are broken by a golf ball.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The beams may be infra red or visible light.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The detecting arrangement may produce a pair of detection beams which are inclined relative to each other and which pass through the golf hole image and permit the speed, position and direction of a golf ball passing through the image to be determined.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The detecting arrangement may produce an outer beam or beams to determine the general direction in which a golf ball is travelling.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The detecting arrangement may produce a beam to determine whether a golf ball remains on or adjacent the golf hole image after a shot has been played.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The detecting arrangement is configured such that the beams extend above the ground at a height substantially equal to the centre of a golf ball.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The frame may include two ground engaging parts each locatable on an opposite side of the golf hole image. The detecting arrangement may include beam transmitters provided on a one of the ground engaging parts, with respective beam receivers provided on the other of the ground engaging parts.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The aid is arranged such that after a golf shot has been played at the golf hole image, and the speed, location and direction of the golf ball has been determined by the detecting arrangement, a signal is provided to indicate whether the golf ball would have fallen into the hole.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The signal may also indicate where the ball crossed the hole and whether this would have caused the ball to fall in the hole.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The signal is audible, and is desirably a spoken message.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagrammatic side view of a putting practice aid according to the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a plan view of the aid of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross sectional side view along the line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic view illustrating part of the operation of the aid of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref> are schematic plan views illustrating operation of the aid of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref> show a putting practice aid <b>10</b> locatable on the ground <b>12</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The aid <b>10</b> includes two spaced ground engaging feet <b>14</b> which are generally rectangular in plan view. The feet <b>14</b> are shown diagrammatically in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>. A generally semi-circular frame <b>16</b> extends in a vertical plane between the feet <b>14</b> and mounts a downwardly directed light unit <b>18</b> at its mid-point. A retractable handle <b>20</b> is provided above the light unit <b>18</b> to permit carrying of the aid <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The light unit <b>18</b> includes a downwardly directing LED light source <b>22</b>. A tube <b>24</b> is provided beneath the light source <b>22</b> and a convex lens <b>26</b> is provided at the lower end of the tube <b>24</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates how the light from the source <b>22</b> is directed by the lens <b>26</b> to provide a circle <b>28</b> of light on the ground of the same size as a standard golf hole, i.e. with a diameter of around 108 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Five beam transmitters <b>30</b> are provided in the left hand foot <b>14</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 3</figref>. The transmitters <b>30</b> produce infra red beams, modulated at 38 kHz (nominal). Corresponding beam receivers <b>32</b> are provided in the right foot <b>14</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 3</figref>. The transmitters <b>30</b> produce five beams <b>34</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> and described in further detail below. The aid <b>10</b> also comprises a control unit and loud speaker.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In use the aid <b>10</b> is located where required which may be indoors or outdoors, and the unit is particularly suited to indoor practice. The light source <b>22</b> is illuminated to produce the circle <b>28</b> on the ground beneath the aid <b>10</b>. A golf ball can then be struck from any direction aiming to pass as near as possible beneath the centre of the circle <b>28</b>. As the ball passes through or near the circle <b>28</b> the respective beams <b>34</b> are broken. The timing and duration of the break of the respective beams <b>34</b> is measured to determine the outcome of the shot as if the circle <b>28</b> had been a real golf hole.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The determination of this outcome will now be described. The transmitters <b>30</b> produce front and rear outer beams <b>40</b>, <b>42</b>. When a one of the beams <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> is broken this commences a measurement sequence for the passage of the golf ball. If the beam <b>40</b> is first broken it will be determined as a forward shot, whilst if the beam <b>42</b> is first broken this will be considered a backward shot. Once the other of the beams <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> is subsequently broken, the measurement sequence will have been completed.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Two detection beams <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> are provided between the outer beams <b>40</b>, <b>42</b>, with the detection beams <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> converging at an angle α towards the right hand foot <b>14</b> as shown in the drawings, but the detection beams <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> do not cross. With a forward shot, following breaking of the beam <b>40</b> to initiate the measurement sequence, the detection beam <b>44</b> nearest the beam <b>44</b> will then be broken. The duration of the breaking of the beam <b>44</b> is measured in msec, and when this is divided into the ball diameter, conventionally 43 mm, this provides a velocity in mm/msec.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The time between breaking of the detection beam <b>44</b> and the detection beam <b>46</b> is also measured. This is then multiplied by the velocity to provide the distance travelled in the direction of the ball movement. The direction of movement is shown by the line <b>48</b>, and the distance travelled between the beams <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> is illustrated by the line <b>50</b>. The gap is then divided by the tangent of the angle α to provide the lateral position of the gap along the beam system, from the right foot <b>14</b>. This lateral position is shown by the line <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The ball then proceeds through the rear outer beam <b>42</b> to complete the sequence. All of the beams <b>40</b>, <b>42</b>, <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> are located at a height above the ground so as to be substantially level with the centre of the ball. This sequence is obviously reversed for backward putts. If a velocity of greater than 1.14 mm/msec is detected, the putt is classed as over hit, i.e. the ball would jump over or around the hole without entering it.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Once the lateral position of the line of the ball has been established, the result of the putt is calculated by comparison with preset values corresponding to five zones within the hole as shown by the circle <b>28</b>, and two zones outside the hole. These zones are illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> and from left to right are respectively: missed left <b>54</b>; left lip <b>56</b>; left of centre <b>58</b>; centre of hole <b>60</b>; right of centre <b>62</b>; right lip <b>64</b>; and missed right <b>66</b>. If the ball passes through one of the five zones within the hole, and the velocity is not greater than 1.14 mm/msec, the ball is considered as entering the hole.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Once the position and speed of the ball has been determined, an audible message will be given through the loud speaker to indicate whether the shot has been successful or is a miss and where in or outside of the hole the ball passed. A central beam <b>68</b> is also provided which is only considered if the measurement sequence fails to complete because both of the outer beams <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> have not been broken. The beam <b>68</b> if activated will detect if a ball remains in or adjacent the circle <b>28</b>, and an appropriate audible signal will be provided to suggest that the ball should now be removed from this location.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">There is thus described a putting practice aid which by virtue of a virtual golf hole provides a realistic target. The aid also provides a signal as to whether the ball would have landed in the hole, and where it would have entered the hole. This provides verbal feedback to the player, relating to the line and speed of each putt, to allow them to modify their action or technique as required.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">As an audible signal is provided there is no requirement for a player to raise their head to see where the putt has gone. An indication of whether or not the ball was over hit and therefore would not have landed in the hole is provided, and again without the requirement for a player to look up to see where a ball has finally come to rest.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The aid is of relatively simple construction and can thus be robustly manufactured for long term reliable use. No calculations are required by a user, but an accurate indication of the outcome of shots is readily and rapidly provided.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Various modifications may be made without departing from the scope of the arrangement. For instance, a different arrangement of beams may be used, and the beams could be other than infra red, and could be light beams. A different light unit could be provided. A different arrangement of zones could be used.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Accordingly, while the invention has been described with reference to the structures and processes disclosed, it is not confined to the details set forth, but is intended to cover such modifications or changes as may fall within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Applicants claim priority to UK Patent Application No. 0509050.1, filed in the United Kingdom on May 4, 2005.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A putting practice aid comprising a light source to project a visible image of a virtual golf hole as a putting target and a detector to determine the presence of a golf ball with respect to the virtual golf hole.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a speaker receiving instructions from the detector to provide an audible signal as to whether a detected golf ball represents a successful putt to the virtual golf hole.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the audible signal includes verbal feedback indicating to a player where in or outside of the virtual hole the ball has passed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The puffing practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the detector includes a beam transmitter and a beam receiver, and wherein the detector determines the presence of a golf ball as it breaks a beam produced by the transmitter and received by the receiver.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The pulling practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the detector includes a plurality of infrared beam transmitters and a plurality of infrared beam receivers, and wherein the detector determines the speed and direction of a golf ball as it breaks a plurality of beams between the transmitters and receivers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The pulling practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the detector includes a plurality of light beam transmitters and a plurality of light beam receivers, and wherein the detector determines the speed and direction of a golf ball as it breaks a plurality of beams between the transmitters and receivers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the detector includes a beam transmitter and a beam receiver, and wherein the detector determines the presence of a golf bail as it breaks a beam produced by the transmitter and received by the receiver.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the detector includes a plurality of infrared beam transmitters and a plurality of infrared beam receivers, and wherein the detector determines the speed and direction of a golf ball as it breaks a plurality of beams between the transmitters and receivers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the detector includes a plurality of light beam transmitters and a plurality of light beam receivers, and wherein the detector determines the speed and direction of a golf bail as it breaks a plurality of beams between the transmitters and receivers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A putting practice aid comprising an illumination source to provide a visible image of a virtual golf hole and beams detection means for detecting the presence of a golf ball with respect to the virtual golf hole.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein said beam detection means is an infrared beams detection means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> further comprising audible feedback means for communicating putt results information based on the determination of the infrared beams detection means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein said beam detection means is a light beams detection means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising audible feedback means for communicating putt results information based on the determination of the light beams detection means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A putting practice aid comprising:
<claim-text>(a) an illumination source to project a visible image of a virtual golf hole as a putting target; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) a detector comprising a plurality of beam transmitters projecting a plurality of beams to a plurality of beam receivers,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the detector detects the presence of a golf ball with respect to the virtual golf hole as the golf ball breaks at least one of the plurality of beams projected between the beam transmitters and beam receivers.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the detector further detects whether the golf ball crosses the virtual golf hole.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the detector further determines the speed, position, and direction of the golf ball crossing the virtual golf hole.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein each of the plurality of beam transmitters transmits one of the plurality of beams to a respective one of the plurality of beam receivers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the beam transmitters and the beam receivers are located on opposite sides of the virtual golf hole and the detector detects the golf ball as the golf ball passes between the beam transmitters and the beam receivers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The pulling practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of beams are located at a height so as to be substantially level with the center of the golf ball.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref>, wherein the audible signal includes verbal feedback indicating to a player where in or outside of the virtual hole the ball has passed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The putting practice aid of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, further comprising a speaker receiving instructions from the detector to provide an audible signal as to whether a detected golf ball represents a successful pull to the virtual golf hole.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
