<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297606-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297606</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11116903</doc-number>
<date>20050428</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>351</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>336</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438301</main-classification>
<further-classification>438306</further-classification>
<further-classification>438E21435</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Metal-oxide-semiconductor device including a buried lightly-doped drain region</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5565700</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chou et al.</name>
<date>19961000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0132405</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Disney</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438197</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00003">
<othercit>D.R. Disney et al., “A New 800V Lateral MOSFET with Dual Conduction Paths,” Proceedings of International Symposium on Power Semiconductor Devices and ICs, 2001, pp. 399-402.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>17</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438306</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438307</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438299</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438301</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438E21437</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21382</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21417</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21435</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10675633</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030930</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6927453</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11116903</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050191815</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050901</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Shibib</last-name>
<first-name>Muhammed Ayman</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wyomissing</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Xu</last-name>
<first-name>Shuming</first-name>
<address>
<city>Schnecksville</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Agere Systems Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Allentown</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Tran</last-name>
<first-name>Minh-Loan</first-name>
<department>2826</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An MOS device includes a semiconductor layer of a first conductivity type, a source region of a second conductivity type formed in the semiconductor layer, and a drain region of the second conductivity type formed in the semiconductor layer and spaced apart from the source region. A gate is formed proximate an upper surface of the semiconductor layer and at least partially between the source and drain regions. The MOS device further includes a buried LDD region of the second conductivity type formed in the semiconductor layer between the gate and the drain region, the buried LDD region being spaced laterally from the drain region, and a second LDD region of the first conductivity type formed in the buried LDD region and proximate the upper surface of the semiconductor layer. The second LDD region is self-aligned with the gate and spaced laterally from the gate such that the gate is non-overlapping relative to the second LDD region.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="123.36mm" wi="146.64mm" file="US07297606-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="243.50mm" wi="147.74mm" file="US07297606-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="199.64mm" wi="115.15mm" file="US07297606-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="202.01mm" wi="108.29mm" file="US07297606-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO PRIOR APPLICATION(S)</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a division of U.S. application Ser. No. 10/675,633 filed on Sep. 30, 2003 now U.S. Pat. No. 6,927,453, the disclosure of which is incorporated by reference herein.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to semiconductor devices, and more particularly relates to a metal-oxide-semiconductor (MOS) device having a lightly-doped drain (LDD) region configured for providing improved high-frequency performance.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Power MOS devices, including laterally diffused metal-oxide-semiconductor (LDMOS) devices, are employed in a variety of applications, such as, for example, power amplifiers in wireless communications systems. In conventional LDMOS devices, which typically include an LDD region, the LDD region is often formed at or near an upper surface interface between the silicon and oxide of the device. Locating the LDD region in close relative proximity to the silicon/oxide interface, however, significantly increases the likelihood that ionized carriers will become trapped at the interface, thereby resulting in undesirable hot carrier degradation (HCD) in the device.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">HCD in an MOS device generally results from heating and subsequent injection of carriers into the gate oxide of the device, which results in a localized and nonuniform buildup of interface states and oxide charges near and underneath a gate of the device. This phenomenon can produce variations in certain characteristics of the MOS device, including threshold voltage, transconductance, drain current, etc., thus undesirably affecting the operation and reliability of the device. It is well known that HCD is a strong function of the internal electric field distributions at the interface of the MOS device.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In many applications, such as, for example, power applications and applications in which high-frequency operation is desired, such as in a radio frequency (RF) range (e.g., above 1 gigahertz (GHz)), it is desirable to minimize the on-resistance, R<sub>ON</sub>, associated with the MOS device. In an LDMOS device, since the on-resistance is dominated primarily by the characteristics of the LDD region, one known methodology for reducing the on-resistance is to increase the doping concentration of the LDD region. However, since the LDD region is typically formed at the silicon/oxide interface of the device, increasing the doping concentration of the LDD region also undesirably increases HCD in the device.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Other attempts at reducing the on-resistance of the MOS device have included increasing the junction depth of the LDD region. However, since the gate-to-drain capacitance, Cgd, of the device is generally proportional to the junction depth of the LDD region, as the depth of the LDD region increases the gate-to-drain capacitance also increases, thereby undesirably affecting the high-frequency performance of the device. Thus, prior attempts to improve the high-frequency performance of the MOS device have primarily focused on optimizing a trade-off between on-resistance, HCD and gate-to-drain capacitance in the device.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Conventional methodologies for reducing the on-resistance of the LDMOS device without significantly increasing HCD and/or the gate-to-drain capacitance in the device have generally been unsuccessful thus far. Accordingly, it would be desirable to form an MOS device exhibiting improved on-resistance characteristics without significantly increasing HCD or impacting the high-frequency performance of the device.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention provides techniques for reducing the on-resistance of an MOS device without significantly increasing HCD and/or the gate-to-drain capacitance in the device, thereby improving a high-frequency performance and reliability of the device. Moreover, the techniques of the present invention can be used to fabricate an integrated circuit (IC) device, for example, an LDMOS device, using conventional CMOS-compatible process technology. Consequently, the cost of manufacturing the IC device is not significantly increased.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In accordance with one aspect of the invention, an MOS device is formed including a semiconductor layer of a first conductivity type, a source region of a second conductivity type formed in the semiconductor layer, and a drain region of the second conductivity type formed in the semiconductor layer and spaced apart from the source region. A gate is formed proximate an upper surface of the semiconductor layer and at least partially between the source and drain regions. The MOS device further includes a buried LDD region of the first conductivity type formed in the semiconductor layer between the gate and the drain region, the buried LDD region being spaced laterally from the drain region, and a second LDD region of the second conductivity type formed in the buried LDD region and proximate the upper surface of the semiconductor layer. The second LDD region is self-aligned with the gate and spaced laterally from the gate such that the gate is non-overlapping relative to the second LDD region. In this manner, the LDMOS device exhibits improved high-frequency performance, and is also substantially compatible with a CMOS process technology.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">These and other features and advantages of the present invention will become apparent from the following detailed description of illustrative embodiments thereof, which is to be read in connection with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional view illustrating at least a portion of an LDMOS device in which the techniques of the present invention can be implemented.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional view depicting at least a portion of an exemplary LDMOS device, formed in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-5</figref> are cross-sectional views depicting steps in an illustrative semiconductor fabrication process which may be used in forming the exemplary LDMOS device shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view depicting at least a portion of an exemplary LDMOS device, formed in accordance with an another embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The present invention will be described herein in the context of an illustrative CMOS integrated circuit fabrication technology suitable for forming discrete RF LDMOS transistors, as well as other devices and/or circuits. It should be appreciated, however, that the present invention is not limited to the fabrication of this or any particular device or circuit. Rather, the invention is more generally applicable to an MOS device comprising a novel buried LDD region which advantageously enables the MOS device to provide improved high-frequency performance without significantly increasing HCD effects and/or gate-to-drain capacitance in the device. Moreover, the device is fully compatible with a CMOS process technology.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Although implementations of the present invention are described herein with specific reference to an LDMOS device, it is to be appreciated that the techniques of the present invention are similarly applicable to other devices, such as, but not limited to, a vertical diffused MOS (DMOS) device, an extended drain MOS device, etc., with or without modifications thereto, as will be understood by those skilled in the art. Furthermore, although the invention will be described herein in the context of a p-channel MOS device, it is well understood by those skilled in the art that an n-channel MOS device could be formed by simply substituting opposite polarities to those given for the p-channel embodiment, and that the techniques and advantages of the present invention will similarly apply to the alternative embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">It is to be understood that the various layers and/or regions shown in the accompanying figures may not be drawn to scale. Furthermore, certain semiconductor layers of a type commonly used in such integrated circuit structures may have been omitted in a given figure for ease of explanation.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional view of at least a portion of a semiconductor wafer <b>100</b> that can be modified to implement the techniques of the invention. The wafer <b>100</b> includes an LDMOS device formed on a substrate <b>102</b>. The LDMOS device includes a source region <b>106</b> and a drain region <b>108</b> formed in an epitaxial layer <b>104</b> of the wafer <b>100</b>. The LDMOS device further includes a gate <b>110</b> formed above a channel region <b>112</b> of the device. The channel region <b>112</b> is at least partially formed between the source and drain regions. An n-type drift region is generally formed in the epitaxial layer <b>104</b> of the LDMOS device which may comprise a first LDD region <b>114</b> and a second LDD region <b>116</b> formed between the channel region <b>112</b> and drain region <b>108</b>. The source region <b>106</b> in the LDMOS device may include an enhancement region <b>118</b> formed in the epitaxial layer <b>104</b> adjacent to the source region <b>106</b> and extending laterally opposite the channel region <b>112</b>. An oxide layer <b>124</b> is generally formed on an upper surface of the wafer <b>100</b> to electrically isolate the source, drain and gate areas of the device as well as to protect the device.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The LDMOS device further includes a drain contact <b>120</b> and a source contact <b>122</b>, each of which may be formed through the oxide layer <b>124</b> and electrically connected to the drain region <b>108</b> and source region <b>106</b>, respectively. Electrical contact to the source region <b>106</b> may also be made from a bottom of the substrate <b>102</b> via one or more trench sinkers <b>128</b> formed through the epitaxial layer <b>104</b> which provide a low-resistance (e.g., less than about 1 ohm per square) electrical path between the source region <b>106</b> and the substrate <b>102</b>. A gate contact (not shown) is also included for providing an electrical connection to the gate <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Due at least in part to the relatively high electric field concentration near the corners of the gate <b>110</b> and the close relative proximity of the gate to an interface between the upper surface of the silicon and the oxide layer <b>124</b>, HCD often occurs at the silicon/oxide interface near the first LDD region <b>114</b> immediately proximate the edge of the gate <b>110</b> (i.e., in the vicinity of area <b>1</b>). In order to reduce HCD in area <b>1</b> of the LDMOS device, a shielding structure <b>130</b>, referred to herein as a dummy gate, may be formed proximate the gate <b>110</b>, between the gate <b>110</b> and drain region <b>108</b>. The dummy gate <b>130</b> is formed in close relative proximity (e.g., 200 nanometers (nm)) to the upper surface of the wafer <b>100</b>. Although not shown, the dummy gate <b>130</b>, if used, is electrically connected (e.g., strapped) to the source region <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">While employing a dummy gate <b>130</b> may help reduce HCD at the silicon/oxide interface in the vicinity of area <b>1</b> in the device, HCD will substantially increase at the silicon/oxide interface near the second LDD region <b>116</b> immediately proximate an edge of the dummy gate <b>130</b> (i.e., in the vicinity of area <b>2</b>). HCD can be reduced in area <b>2</b> by lowering the doping concentration of at least the second LDD region <b>116</b>. However, this will undesirably result in an increase in the on-resistance associated with the device. Thus, in using the LDMOS configuration depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, there is a trade-off which exists between on-resistance and HCD in the device.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional view of at least a portion of a semiconductor wafer <b>200</b> in which the techniques of the present invention are implemented. As previously stated, the various layers and/or regions shown in the figure may not be drawn to scale and certain semiconductor layers may have been omitted for ease of explanation. The wafer <b>200</b> includes an exemplary LDMOS device formed on a semiconductor substrate <b>202</b>. The substrate <b>202</b> is commonly formed of single-crystal silicon, although alternative materials may be used, such as, but not limited to, germanium (Ge), gallium arsenide (GaAs), etc. Additionally, the substrate <b>202</b> may have been modified by adding an impurity or dopant, such as by a diffusion or implant step, to change the conductivity of the material (e.g., n-type or p-type). In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the substrate <b>202</b> is of p-type conductivity, and hence may be referred to as a p-substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The term “semiconductor layer” as may be used herein refers to any semiconductor material upon which and/or in which other materials may be formed. The semiconductor layer may comprise a single layer, such as, for example, the substrate <b>202</b>, or it may comprise multiple layers, such as, for example, the substrate <b>202</b> and an epitaxial layer <b>204</b>. The semiconductor wafer <b>200</b> comprises the substrate <b>202</b>, with or without the epitaxial layer <b>204</b>, and preferably includes one or more other semiconductor layers formed on the substrate. The term “wafer” is often used interchangeably with the term “silicon body,” since silicon is typically employed as the semiconductor material comprising the wafer. It should be appreciated that although the present invention is illustrated herein using a portion of a semiconductor wafer, the term “wafer” may include a multiple-die wafer, a single-die wafer, or any other arrangement of semiconductor material on or in which a circuit element may be formed.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The exemplary LDMOS device includes a source region <b>206</b> and a drain region <b>208</b> formed in the epitaxial layer <b>204</b> of the wafer <b>200</b>, such as by an implant or diffusion process. The source and drain regions are preferably doped, such as by an implant process, with an impurity (e.g., boron, phosphorus, etc.) of a known concentration level to selectively change the conductivity of the material as desired. Preferably, the source and drain regions <b>206</b>, <b>208</b> have a conductivity type associated therewith which is opposite a conductivity type of the substrate <b>202</b>, so that active regions can be formed in the device. In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the source and drain regions <b>206</b>, <b>208</b> are of n-type conductivity. A low-resistance (e.g., less than about 1 ohm per square) electrical path between the source region <b>206</b> and the substrate <b>202</b> may be provided by forming one or more trench sinkers <b>228</b> through the epitaxial layer <b>204</b> of the wafer <b>200</b>. The trench sinkers <b>228</b> may be formed in a conventional manner, such as, for example, by forming openings in the epitaxial layer <b>204</b> (e.g., by photolithographic patterning and etching) to expose the substrate <b>202</b>, and filling the openings with an electrically conductive material, as will be understood by those skilled in the art. In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the trench sinkers <b>228</b> are of p-type conductivity.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">It is to be appreciated that, in the case of a simple MOS device, because the MOS device is symmetrical in nature, and thus bidirectional, the assignment of source and drain designations in the MOS device is essentially arbitrary. Therefore, the source and drain regions may be referred to generally as first and second source/drain regions, respectively, where “source/drain” in this context denotes a source region or a drain region. In an LDMOS device, which is generally not bidirectional, such source and drain designations may not be arbitrarily assigned.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The exemplary LDMOS device may include an enhancement region <b>218</b> formed in the epitaxial layer <b>204</b>, such as by a conventional implant and diffusion process. The enhancement region <b>218</b> is preferably formed adjacent to the source region <b>206</b> and extends laterally in a direction opposite the drain region <b>208</b>. A source electrode of the MOS device may comprise at least a portion of the source region <b>206</b> and at least a portion of the enhancement region <b>218</b>. The enhancement region <b>218</b> is preferably doped, such as by a conventional implant step, with an impurity of a known concentration level to selectively change the conductivity of the material as desired. Preferably, the enhancement region <b>218</b> has a conductivity type associated therewith which is opposite a conductivity type of the source region <b>206</b>. In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the enhancement region <b>218</b> is of p-type conductivity.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">A channel region <b>212</b> and a drift region, which may comprise a first LDD region <b>214</b> and a second LDD region <b>216</b>, is formed proximate an upper surface of the exemplary LDMOS device, just beneath an interface between the silicon epitaxial layer <b>204</b> and an insulating layer <b>224</b>, which in a preferred embodiment is formed of an oxide (e.g., silicon dioxide (SiO<sub>2</sub>), etc.). This interface may thus be referred to as a silicon/oxide interface. The unique configuration of the first and second LDD regions <b>214</b>, <b>216</b> represents an important aspect of the present invention and will be described in further detail below. The channel region <b>212</b> is formed at least partially below and adjacent to the source region <b>206</b> while the drift region extends laterally between the channel region <b>212</b> and the drain region <b>208</b> in the LDMOS device. The channel region <b>212</b> may be formed of a material having the same conductivity type as the substrate, preferably p-type in the exemplary device, and may therefore be referred to as a p-channel.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The exemplary LDMOS device further includes a gate <b>210</b> formed above at least a portion of the channel region <b>212</b> and proximate the silicon/oxide interface of the wafer <b>200</b>. The gate may be formed of, for example, polysilicon material, although alternative suitable materials (e.g., metal, etc.) may be similarly employed. A shielding electrode <b>230</b>, which may be referred to herein as a dummy gate, may be formed in the exemplary LDMOS device between the gate <b>210</b> and the drain region <b>208</b>. The dummy gate <b>230</b> is spaced laterally from the gate <b>210</b> and preferably substantially non-overlapping relative to the gate. Although not shown, the dummy gate <b>230</b> in the exemplary LDMOS device, when used, is preferably electrically connected (i.e., strapped) to the source region <b>206</b>, such as by forming a conductive layer (e.g., aluminum, etc.) between the dummy gate and the source region. The dummy gate <b>230</b> beneficially reduces HCD proximate the silicon/oxide interface in the vicinity of area <b>1</b>, as previously explained. A dummy gate suitable for use in conjunction with the present invention can be found in a related U.S. application Ser. No. 10/623,983 entitled “Shielding Structure for Use in a Metal-Oxide-Semiconductor Device” filed on Jul. 15, 2003 and assigned attorney docket number Xie 3-4, which is incorporated by reference herein.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In a preferred embodiment of the invention, the dummy gate <b>230</b> is formed concurrently with the gate <b>210</b> in the same processing step. In this manner, the dummy gate <b>230</b> is preferably self-aligned to the gate <b>210</b>. The thickness of the insulating material (e.g., silicon dioxide) beneath the gate <b>210</b> and dummy gate <b>230</b>, often referred to as gate oxide, may be substantially the same. Thus, like the gate <b>210</b>, the dummy gate <b>230</b> is preferably formed in close relative proximity (e.g., 200 nanometers (nm)) to the silicon/oxide interface of the wafer <b>200</b>. Furthermore, the size and shape of the dummy gate <b>230</b> relative to the gate <b>210</b> may be substantially the same. It is to be appreciated, however, that the dummy gate <b>230</b> is not limited to the precise size or shape shown, but may be formed in virtually any configuration and/or shape, as will be understood by those skilled in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">A source contact <b>222</b> and a drain contact <b>220</b> may be formed on an upper surface of the insulating layer <b>224</b>, such as, for example, by forming openings in the insulating layer <b>224</b> (e.g., by photolithographic patterning and etching) to expose the source region <b>206</b> and drain region <b>208</b>, respectively, and filling the openings with an electrically conductive material (e.g., aluminum, gold, etc.), as will be understood by those skilled in the art. Connection to the source region may also be made through a bottom surface of the substrate, since the trench sinkers <b>228</b> provide a relatively low-resistance electrical path between the source region <b>206</b> and the substrate <b>202</b>, as previously explained. A gate contact (not shown) may also be formed on the upper surface of the insulating layer <b>224</b>, or in an alternative location, for providing an electrical connection to the gate <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In accordance with a preferred embodiment of the invention, the first LDD region <b>214</b> in the exemplary LDMOS device is formed of a material having the same conductivity type as the substrate, preferably p-type, although the relative doping concentration of the first LDD region compared to the substrate is typically lower. The second LDD region <b>216</b> may be formed of a material having a conductivity type that is the same as the conductivity type of the source and drain regions and opposite the conductivity type of the first LDD region <b>214</b>, preferably n-type, although the relative doping concentration of the second LDD region compared to the source and drain regions is typically lower. Traditionally, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the second LDD region <b>116</b> is formed proximate the silicon/oxide interface of the LDMOS device, between the first LDD region <b>114</b> and the drain region <b>108</b>. As previously stated, the use of a dummy gate, while reducing HCD proximate the silicon/oxide interface in the vicinity of area <b>1</b>, causes a substantial increase in HCD proximate the silicon/oxide interface in the vicinity of area <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">An important aspect of the present invention is that the second LDD region <b>216</b> comprises a buried LDD layer, as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The second LDD region <b>216</b> may be formed in the epitaxial layer <b>204</b> using, for example, an implant or diffusion process. The second LDD region <b>216</b> is preferably formed below at least a portion of the drain region <b>208</b> and extends laterally to below at least a portion of the gate <b>210</b>. The first LDD region <b>214</b> is formed within the second LDD region <b>216</b> proximate the silicon/oxide interface using, for example, an implant process. However, the first LDD region <b>214</b> may be spaced apart from the drain region <b>208</b>, also formed in the second LDD region <b>216</b>. Moreover, the first LDD region <b>214</b> is preferably formed below at least a portion of the dummy gate <b>230</b> and extends laterally toward the drain region <b>208</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The first LDD region <b>214</b> is formed substantially more shallow compared to the second LDD region <b>216</b>. For example, in a preferred embodiment, a depth of the second LDD region <b>216</b> in the epitaxial layer <b>204</b> is in a range from about 0.5 micron to about 2.0 micron and the depth of the first LDD region <b>214</b> is in a range from about 0.05 micron to about 0.5 micron, for a 0.25 micron CMOS fabrication process.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Using the novel LDD arrangement illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the dummy gate <b>230</b> can be placed in closer relative proximity to the gate <b>210</b>, compared to the LDMOS device shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, thereby substantially eliminating HCD in the vicinity of area <b>1</b> in the device. The relatively high impact ionization that would ordinarily occur at the corner of the dummy gate <b>230</b> in the vicinity of area <b>2</b> is substantially enclosed by the p-type first LDD region <b>214</b>, which is not part of the drain current path and does not affect the buried n-type second LDD region <b>216</b>. The presence of the p-type first LDD region <b>214</b> proximate the silicon/oxide interface of the wafer <b>100</b> helps direct current flow away from the silicon/oxide interface. Consequently, carriers are not be as likely to become trapped in the oxide <b>224</b> proximate the interface, thereby significantly reducing HCD at area <b>2</b>. Therefore, HCD immunity in the exemplary LDMOS device is significantly improved. Furthermore, the configuration of the p-type first LDD region <b>214</b> in the buried n-type second LDD region <b>216</b> helps deplete the second LDD region by increasing a drain bias due primarily to a junction field-effect-transistor (JFET) effect, thereby enabling the doping concentration in the second LDD region <b>216</b> to be increased without significantly reducing the breakdown voltage of the device. As previously explained, increasing the doping concentration advantageously results in a reduced on-resistance associated with the device.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As previously explained, forming the first LDD region <b>214</b> in the manner thus described allows the dummy gate <b>230</b> to be placed in closer relative proximity to the gate <b>210</b>. The dummy gate <b>230</b> and gate <b>210</b> are preferably formed in the same processing step, thus leaving the first LDD region <b>214</b> self-aligned to the gate <b>210</b>. This is advantageous in that it enables a distance between the first LDD region <b>214</b> and the gate <b>210</b> to be precisely controlled, thereby ensuring that a proper conduction path is formed between the second LDD region <b>216</b> and the channel region <b>212</b>. Due to the presence of the dummy gate <b>230</b>, the first LDD region <b>214</b> will be self-aligned to the gate <b>210</b>, at an edge proximate the source region, and spaced laterally from the gate, regardless of the length of the gate, such that the gate is non-overlapping relative to the first LDD region. Forming the gate <b>210</b> and dummy gate <b>230</b> in the same process step also simplifies the semiconductor fabrication process, thereby reducing the overall cost of manufacturing the MOS device. Moreover, since the dummy gate can be formed closer to the silicon/oxide interface, the buried LDD region <b>216</b> depletes more easily with increased drain bias (in comparison to conventional MOS devices), beneficially resulting in a substantially reduced gate-to-drain capacitance. Thus, by forming an MOS device in accordance with the techniques of the present invention, a reduction in on-resistance, HCD and gate-to-drain capacitance can be concurrently achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Although the dummy gate should be formed in the same process step in order for the first LDD region <b>214</b> to be self-aligned with the gate <b>210</b>, at least a portion of the dummy gate <b>230</b> may be removed, such as by using an etching process, after forming the first LDD region. Subsequently, the dummy gate can be reformed, either in the same or an alternative configuration, between the gate <b>210</b> and drain region <b>208</b>. By forming the dummy gate <b>230</b> in a separate process step, the gate oxide <b>224</b> under the dummy gate, as well as other features of the dummy gate (e.g., shape), may be individually adjusted as desired. In a preferred embodiment of the invention, for example, the gate oxide <b>224</b> beneath the dummy gate <b>230</b> may be thinned by a predetermined amount, such as by using an etching process, compared to the gate oxide <b>224</b> under the gate <b>210</b>. In this manner, the dummy gate can be used during the formation of the gate <b>210</b> as a structure for self-aligning the first LDD region <b>214</b> with the gate, and then subsequently at least partially removed and reformed such that certain characteristics of the dummy gate <b>230</b> (e.g., gate oxide thickness, shape, etc.) are independently controlled.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 through 5</figref> depict steps in an illustrative methodology which may be used to form the exemplary LDMOS device shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. The illustrative methodology will be described in the context of a conventional CMOS compatible semiconductor fabrication process technology. It is to be understood that the invention is not limited to this or any particular methodology for fabricating the device. As previously stated, the various layers and/or regions shown in the figures may not be drawn to scale and certain semiconductor layers may have been omitted for ease of explanation.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> depicts a cross section of at least a portion of an exemplary semiconductor wafer <b>300</b>. The wafer <b>300</b> includes a substrate <b>302</b> and an epitaxial layer <b>304</b> formed on the substrate <b>302</b>. The substrate <b>302</b> is preferably a P+ type substrate having a high conductivity, although an N+ type substrate may alternatively be employed. As will be understood by those skilled in the art, a P+ substrate may be formed by adding a p-type impurity or dopant (e.g., Boron) of a desired concentration (e.g., about 5×10<sup>18 </sup>to about 5×10<sup>19 </sup>atoms) to the substrate material, such as by a diffusion or implant step, to change the conductivity of the material as desired. The epitaxial layer <b>304</b> is then grown over the entire surface of the wafer. The epitaxial layer <b>304</b> may also be modified by adding a p-type impurity. A breakdown voltage of the resulting transistor structure is determined, at least in part, by the thickness and impurity concentration of the epitaxial layer <b>304</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A buried LDD layer <b>306</b> is formed in the epitaxial layer <b>304</b>, such as, for example, by using a diffusion or implant step. During the formation of the buried LDD layer <b>306</b>, an n-type impurity <b>310</b> (e.g., arsenic or phosphorous) of a known concentration level is preferably employed, and thus the buried LDD layer may be referred as an N-LDD layer. As previously stated, the depth of the buried LDD layer <b>306</b> is preferably in a range from about 0.2 micron to about 2.0 microns. The buried LDD layer <b>306</b> will form at least a portion of the drift region in the resulting LDMOS device.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">After forming the buried LDD layer <b>306</b> in the epitaxial layer <b>304</b>, a thin oxide layer <b>308</b> is formed on the epitaxial layer. The thin oxide layer <b>308</b> may comprise an insulating material, such as, for example, silicon dioxide, that is grown or deposited on an upper surface of the wafer <b>300</b> to a desired thickness (e.g., about 300-400 angstroms). It is typically in this oxide layer <b>308</b> that carriers may become trapped as a result of HCD.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a p-body region <b>320</b> is formed in the epitaxial layer <b>304</b> such as, for example, by using a deep diffusion or implant step. During the diffusion step, a p-type impurity (e.g., boron) of a predetermined concentration level is preferably used. A gate <b>316</b> and dummy gate <b>318</b> are formed on an upper surface of the oxide layer <b>308</b> in the LDMOS device. The gate <b>316</b> may be fabricated from a polycrystalline silicon (polysilicon) layer formed over the thin oxide layer <b>308</b>, such as, for example, using a chemical vapor deposition (CVD) technique. The thin oxide layer <b>308</b> under the gate <b>316</b> is often referred to as gate oxide. The polysilicon layer is generally patterned using, for example, a conventional photolithographic process, followed by an etching step (e.g., dry etching) to form gate <b>316</b>, as will be understood by those skilled in the art. The dummy gate <b>318</b> may be fabricated from polysilicon material in a similar manner to the formation of the gate <b>316</b>. Preferably, the dummy gate <b>318</b> is formed concurrently with the gate <b>316</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">A source region <b>312</b> is formed in the p-body region <b>320</b> and a drain region <b>314</b> is formed in the buried LDD region <b>306</b>. The source and drain regions <b>312</b>, <b>314</b> may be formed, for example, by diffusing or implanting an n-type impurity (e.g., arsenic or phosphorous) of a known concentration level into respective regions <b>320</b>, <b>306</b> of the device. The source region <b>312</b> preferably uses a peripheral end of the gate <b>316</b> to at least partially define the source region, and thus the source region <b>312</b> may be considered to be self-aligned with the gate <b>316</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> depicts a step for forming a second LDD region <b>322</b> in the buried N-LDD region <b>306</b>. The second LDD region <b>322</b> may be formed, for example, by implanting a p-type impurity <b>326</b> (e.g., boron) of a know concentration level into the N-LDD region <b>306</b>, and thus the second LDD region may be referred as a P-LDD region. The P-LDD region <b>322</b> is preferably formed at a considerably more shallow depth compared to the buried LDD region <b>306</b>. As previously stated, the depth of the P-LDD region <b>322</b> is preferably in a range from about 0.05 micron to about 0.5 micron.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As apparent from the figure, the P-LDD region <b>322</b> is formed between the dummy gate <b>318</b> and the drain region <b>314</b>. In forming the P-LDD region <b>322</b>, a layer of photoresist <b>324</b> is preferably deposited on the upper surface of the wafer <b>300</b>, such as by using a conventional photolithographic patterning and etching process. By terminating the photoresist layer <b>324</b> at the dummy gate <b>318</b>, thereby leaving the oxide layer <b>308</b> between the dummy gate <b>318</b> and the drain region <b>314</b> exposed, the P-LDD region <b>322</b> formed as a result of the p-implant step will be self-aligned with the dummy gate <b>318</b>, and thus will also be self-aligned with the gate <b>316</b>. This is desirable for accurately controlling the distance between the P-LDD region <b>322</b> and the gate, thereby ensuring that a proper electrical conduction path is formed between the buried N-LDD layer <b>306</b> and a channel region (not shown) of the LDMOS device.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional view of at least a portion of a semiconductor wafer <b>600</b> in which an exemplary LDMOS device is formed, in accordance with an alternative embodiment of the present invention. Like the embodiment depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the exemplary LDMOS device is formed comprising a buried LDD layer <b>602</b>, preferably of n-type conductivity. An insulating layer <b>616</b>, which may comprise an oxide (e.g., silicon dioxide) is formed over an upper surface of the wafer <b>600</b>. The exemplary LDMOS device further comprises a gate <b>610</b>, a dummy gate <b>612</b>, and an alignment structure <b>614</b> formed on the insulating layer <b>616</b>. The gate <b>610</b> is formed substantially over a body region <b>618</b>, which is preferably of p-type conductivity. The dummy gate <b>612</b> is formed between the gate <b>610</b> and the alignment structure <b>614</b>, and the alignment structure <b>614</b> is preferably formed between the dummy gate <b>612</b> and the drain region <b>606</b>. In a preferred embodiment, the gate <b>610</b>, dummy gate <b>612</b> and alignment structure <b>614</b> are formed substantially concurrently, such as during the same processing step.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">A source region <b>608</b>, which is preferably of n-type conductivity, is formed in the body region <b>618</b> such as by using an implant or diffusion process. The source region is self-aligned with an edge of the gate <b>210</b>. Likewise, a drain region <b>606</b> is formed in the buried LDD layer <b>602</b> such as by using an implant or diffusion process. The drain region <b>606</b> is preferably self-aligned with a first edge of the alignment structure <b>614</b>. A second LDD region <b>604</b>, preferably of p-type conductivity, may be formed in the buried LDD layer <b>602</b> between the gate <b>610</b> and drain region <b>606</b>. The second LDD region <b>604</b> is preferably formed having a first edge that is self-aligned with a second edge of the alignment structure <b>614</b>, and thus self-aligned with the drain region <b>606</b>. By forming the second LDD region <b>604</b> in this manner, a breakdown voltage between the second LDD region <b>604</b> and the drain region <b>606</b> can be controlled substantially more precisely, thereby providing improved reliability in the LDMOS device. Furthermore, a second edge of the second LDD region <b>604</b> is self-aligned with the dummy gate <b>612</b>, and thus self-aligned with the gate <b>610</b>, thereby allowing the electrical conduction path formed between the buried LDD layer <b>602</b> and a channel region (not shown) of the LDMOS device to be more precisely controlled.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Although illustrative embodiments of the present invention have been described herein with reference to the accompanying drawings, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited to those precise embodiments, and that various other changes and modifications may be made therein by one skilled in the art without departing from the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of forming a metal-oxide-semiconductor (MOS) device, the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>forming source and drain regions of a first conductivity type in a semiconductor layer of a second conductivity type, the source and drain regions being spaced apart relative to one another;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a gate proximate an upper surface of the semiconductor layer and at least partially between the source and drain regions;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a buried lightly-doped drain (LDD) region of the first conductivity type in the semiconductor layer between the gate and the drain region, the buried LDD region being formed below at least a portion of the drain region and extending laterally from the drain region to below at least a portion of the gate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second LDD region of the second conductivity type in the buried LDD region and proximate the upper surface of the semiconductor layer, the second LDD region being self-aligned with a first alignment structure formed substantially concurrently with the gate in a same processing step, the second LDD region being spaced laterally from the gate such that the gate is non-overlapping relative to the second LDD region.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of forming the second LDD region comprises the steps of:
<claim-text>forming an insulating layer on at least a portion of the upper surface of the semiconductor layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a shielding structure on a least a portion of the insulating layer and at least partially between the gate and the drain region, the shielding structure being self-aligned to the gate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming the second LDD region in the buried LDD region such that the second LDD region is self-aligned to the shielding structure.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of removing the shielding structure after forming the second LDD region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the step of removing the shielding structure comprises etching at least the shielding structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>removing the shielding structure;</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing at least a portion of the insulating layer under the shielding structure; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a new shielding structure on at least a portion of the insulating layer on which the removed shielding structure was formed.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the shielding structure and the gate are formed in a same processing step.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of forming an electrical connection between the shielding structure and the source region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the first alignment structure comprises the shielding structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of forming a second alignment structure proximate the upper surface of the semiconductor layer and at least partially between the second LDD region and the drain region, the drain region and the second LDD region being self-aligned with the second alignment structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of removing the second alignment structure after forming the second LDD region and drain region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the alignment structure is formed substantially concurrently with the gate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of forming a second alignment structure proximate the upper surface of the semiconductor layer and at least partially between the second LDD region and the drain region, the drain region and the second LDD region being self-aligned with the second alignment structure, wherein the drain region is self-aligned to a first edge of the second alignment structure and the second LDD region is self-aligned to a second edge of the second alignment structure such that the second LDD region is self aligned with the drain region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the buried LDD region is formed in the semiconductor layer at a depth in a range from about 0.5 micron to about two microns, and the second LDD region is formed in the semiconductor layer at a depth in a range from about 0.05 micron to about 0.5 micron.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the MOS device is a diffused MOS (DMOS) device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the MOS device lateral DMOS (LDMOS) device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the MOS device is a vertical DMOS device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method of forming an integrated circuit including at least one metal-oxide-semiconductor (MOS) device, the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>forming source and drain regions of a first conductivity type in a semiconductor layer of a second conductivity type, the source and drain regions being spaced apart relative to one another;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a gate proximate an upper surface of the semiconductor layer and at least partially between the source and drain regions;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a buried lightly-doped drain (LDD) region of the first conductivity type in the semiconductor layer between the gate and the drain region, the buried LDD region being formed below at least a portion of the drain region and extending laterally from the drain region to below at least a portion of the gate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second LDD region of the second conductivity type in the buried LDD region and proximate the upper surface of the semiconductor layer, the second LDD region being self-aligned with a first alignment structure formed substantially concurrently with the gate in a same processing step, the second LDD region being spaced laterally from the gate such that the gate is non-overlapping relative to the second LDD region.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
