<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298183-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298183</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11142705</doc-number>
<date>20050601</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327115</main-classification>
<further-classification>327117</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">High frequency divider circuits and methods</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5907598</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mandalia et al.</name>
<date>19990500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6163181</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nishiyama</name>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6683480</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Zhang et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0097072</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wakada et al.</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327117</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0048117</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Tung et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0189449</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Zhang et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0193355</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Leifso et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0140831</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wang</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>Hung, et al. “Fully Integrated 5.35-GHz CMOS VCOs and Prescalers”, IEEE Transactions on Microwave Theory and Techniques, vol. 49, No. 1, Jan. 2001, pp. 17-22.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00010">
<othercit>Fujishima, et al., “A 1.0V 10.2 CHz CMOS Frequency Divider with Differential Injection Locking”, IEEE Topical Conference on Wireless Communication Technology 2003, pp. 164-165.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>Craninckx, et al., “A CMOS 1.8GHz Los-Phase-Noise Voltage-Contollered Oscillator with Prescaler”, IEEE International Solid-State Circuits Conference 1995, pp. 266-267.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>Betancourt-Zamora, “1-GHz and 2.8-GHz CMOS Injection-locked Ring Oscillator Prescsller”, Symosium on VLSI Circuits, Kyoto, Japan, Jun. 14, 2001.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>30</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327117</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070024330</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070201</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mirzaei</last-name>
<first-name>Ahmad</first-name>
<address>
<city>Los Angeles</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Heidari</last-name>
<first-name>Mohammad E</first-name>
<address>
<city>Los Angeles</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Djafari</last-name>
<first-name>Masoud</first-name>
<address>
<city>Marina Del Rey</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bagheri</last-name>
<first-name>Rahim</first-name>
<address>
<city>Los Angeles</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fountainhead Law Group P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Walsh</last-name>
<first-name>Chad R.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>WiLinx Corp.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Los Angeles</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Linh My</first-name>
<department>2816</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Almo</last-name>
<first-name>Khaeem E.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Embodiments of the present invention include circuits and methods for dividing high frequency signals. In one embodiment the present invention includes a divider circuit comprising a differential circuit having first and second inputs to receive a first differential signal, a first frequency control input and first and second differential outputs, wherein the differential circuit has a first bias current. The divider circuit further includes a cross-coupled circuit having outputs coupled to the differential circuit outputs and a second frequency control input, wherein the cross-coupled circuit has a second bias current. Embodiments of the present invention may include circuits for controlling the relationship between bias currents and circuit parameters that vary with process or temperature or both.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="154.52mm" wi="236.56mm" file="US07298183-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="222.50mm" wi="123.02mm" file="US07298183-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="227.75mm" wi="150.62mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298183-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="225.81mm" wi="163.75mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298183-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="231.65mm" wi="147.66mm" file="US07298183-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="230.46mm" wi="158.83mm" file="US07298183-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="237.66mm" wi="141.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298183-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="237.07mm" wi="169.84mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298183-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="244.35mm" wi="178.99mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298183-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to divider circuits, and in particular, to circuits and methods that may be used to implement a high frequency division.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Electronic systems often have many different components that include voltage or current signals that have different frequencies. It is often desirable to modify the frequencies of such signals as the signals are used to perform different tasks. One common modification to a signal is frequency division. Frequency division is the process of dividing a signal's frequency by some value (e.g., an integer or fraction). Circuits that perform frequency division are referred to as “Dividers” and are found in a wide variety of electronic applications.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a prior art divider circuit. A divider circuit <b>100</b> receives an input signal, Vin, and generates an output signal, Vout. The input signal, Vin, may be a square wave, for example, having a period, T<b>1</b>, and a corresponding frequency, F<b>1</b>=1/T<b>1</b>. The output signal, Vout, of divider circuit <b>100</b> may have some frequency that is less than the frequency of the input signal, Vin. For example, the output signal, Vout, may have a period, T<b>2</b>, that is twice the value of the input signal period, T<b>1</b>, and thus the output frequency, Fout, has a frequency that is one-half the frequency of the input signal, Vin.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a prior art D-Flip Flop divider circuit. The circuit includes two D-flip flops (“DFF”) <b>201</b> and <b>202</b> connected in series. In this example, each DFF has differential inputs (+in, −in), differential outputs (+out, −out) and differential clock inputs (CK and <o ostyle="single">CK</o>). DFF <b>201</b> will load data at its input (i.e., from DFF <b>202</b>) on the rising edge of CK. Similarly, DFF <b>202</b> will load data at its input (i.e., from DFF <b>201</b>) on the falling edge of CK, which is the rising edge of <o ostyle="single">CK</o>. Thus, each DFF output will transition between logic states once for every period of CK. Consequently, the period of each DFF output is twice the period of the clock, and the output of the divider (+OUT_DIV<b>2</b>, −OUT_DIV<b>2</b>) has one-half the frequency of the clock. DFFs <b>201</b> and <b>202</b> have, thus, divided the clock frequency by two. Such a circuit is one example of a divide-by-two circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates another prior art divider circuit <b>300</b>. Divider <b>300</b> shows an implementation of the divider of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Divider <b>300</b> includes two differential DFFs. The first DFF includes a first pair of differential transistors M<b>3</b> and M<b>4</b> having common sources coupled to ground through transistor M<b>1</b>. The first DFF further includes cross-coupled transistors M<b>5</b> and M<b>6</b>. M<b>5</b> and M<b>6</b> have common sources that are similarly coupled together and to ground through transistor M<b>2</b>. Transistors M<b>5</b> and M<b>6</b> form a cross-coupled circuit because the inputs are coupled to the circuit's complementary output. In divider circuit <b>300</b>, the gate of M<b>5</b> is coupled to the drain of M<b>6</b>, and the gate of M<b>6</b> is coupled to the drain of M<b>5</b>. Furthermore, the drain of M<b>5</b> is coupled to the drain of M<b>4</b> and the drain of M<b>6</b> is coupled to the drain of M<b>3</b>. Thus, the cross-coupled devices and the differential pair transistors have common outputs. Differential pair transistors M<b>3</b>/M<b>4</b> and cross-coupled pair transistors M<b>5</b>/M<b>6</b> receive bias current from PMOS transistors M<b>7</b> and M<b>8</b>, which have sources coupled to supply Vdd and gates coupled to a bias voltage Vbias. Transistors M<b>7</b> and M<b>8</b> also provide a load impedance to both the differential and cross-coupled pairs.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">When transistor M<b>1</b> receives rising edge transition of the clock input, CK, M<b>1</b> turns on and activates differential pair M<b>3</b>/M<b>4</b>. Thus, signal values at the gate inputs of M<b>3</b>/M<b>4</b> (i.e., +in<b>1</b> and −in<b>1</b>) will drive the outputs of the first DFF (i.e., −out<b>1</b> and +out<b>1</b>) on the rising edge of CK. During this phase of the clock signal, bias current from transistors M<b>7</b>/M<b>8</b> is directed through M<b>3</b>, M<b>4</b> and M<b>1</b>, and the data value at the gate input is stored on the output nodes of the differential pair M<b>3</b> and M<b>4</b>. When transistor M<b>2</b> receives a rising edge transition of <o ostyle="single">CK</o> (i.e., the falling edge of CK), M<b>2</b> turns on while M<b>1</b> turns off, and cross-coupled pair M<b>5</b>/M<b>6</b> is activated. During this phase of the clock signal, bias current from transistors M<b>7</b> and M<b>8</b> is redirected through M<b>5</b>, M<b>6</b> and M<b>2</b>, and the data value in the first DFF is maintained by the cross-coupled pair.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The second DFF stage includes transistors M<b>9</b>-M<b>16</b> connected is the same way as transistors M<b>1</b>-M<b>8</b> in the first DFF stage. The rising edge of <o ostyle="single">CK</o> triggers the differential input of the second DFF stage (i.e., transistors M<b>11</b>/M<b>12</b>), which causes the data value from the first DFF to drive the outputs of the second DFF. Thus, the signal values at the gate inputs of M<b>11</b> and M<b>12</b> (i.e., −in<b>2</b> and +in<b>2</b>) will drive the outputs of the second DFF (+out<b>2</b> and −out<b>2</b>) on the rising edge of <o ostyle="single">CK</o>. Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the two DFFs form a two-stage ring oscillator. The outputs of the second DFF are cross-coupled to the inputs of the first DFF, wherein the positive output of the second DFF (i.e., +out<b>2</b>) is coupled to the negative input of the first DFF (i.e., −in<b>1</b>) and the negative output of the second DFF (i.e., −out<b>2</b>) is coupled to the positive input of the first DFF (i.e., +in<b>1</b>). Thus, the two DFFs operate in opposite states and transition at a frequency of one-half the clock frequency. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates an equivalent implementation wherein resistors and capacitors are used for the load impedance, and bias current is generated using a current source “I” coupled to the sources of transistors M<b>1</b>, M<b>2</b>, M<b>7</b> and M<b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In high frequency applications, each DFF stage, such as the ones in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-4</figref>, may be interpreted as injection-locked oscillators. For example, cross-coupled transistors M<b>5</b> and M<b>6</b>, together with load transistors M<b>7</b> and M<b>8</b> form an oscillator having a center frequency, ω<sub>c</sub>. When an input signal is provided (e.g., the clock signal in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>), the divider circuit oscillates at one-half the frequency of the input. However, if the input signal amplitude is too small, or if the frequency of the input signal is outside the lock range of the circuit, then the divider circuit will self-oscillate at a frequency determined by the fundamental frequency (i.e., the center frequency), ω<sub>c</sub>, of each DFF stage. Thus, in high frequency applications the circuit may operate properly only if the input signal to be divided is within a certain range of frequencies (i.e., the lock range) near the center frequency of the oscillator. To optimize the lock range, it is desirable to have the center frequency, ω<sub>c</sub>, as close to the center of the lock range as possible. When the center frequency is in the center of the lock range, the input signal may deviate both above and below the center frequency an approximately equal amount and the system will still lock. However, the center frequency of such circuits is subject to deviation from process and temperature variations. These variations can reduce the effective lock range of the circuit, and may cause the circuit to become inoperable.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Thus, there is a need for improved divider circuits, and in particular, for improved circuits and methods that may be used to implement high frequency division with optimized lock range.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Embodiments of the present invention improve high frequency performance of divider circuits. In one embodiment, the present invention includes a divider circuit comprising a differential circuit having first and second inputs to receive a first differential signal, a first frequency control input and first and second differential output nodes, wherein the differential circuit has a first bias current, and a cross-coupled circuit having a first control terminal coupled to a second output of the cross-coupled circuit and the first differential output node, a second control terminal coupled to a first output of the cross coupled circuit and the first differential output node, and a second frequency control input, wherein the cross-coupled circuit has a second bias current that is independent of the first bias current.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In another embodiment, the second bias current is a constant current and the first bias current is calibrated so that the ratio of the first bias current and a resistance is a constant. In yet another embodiment, the first bias current is a constant current and the second bias current is calibrated so that the product of the second bias current and a resistance is a constant.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In another embodiment, the present invention includes a first resistor having a first resistance coupled between the first differential output node and a supply terminal and a second resistor having a second resistance coupled between the second differential output node and the supply terminal. The first bias current may be generated by a first bias generator that is calibrated so that the ratio of the first bias current and the first or second resistance is a constant across process or temperature. In another embodiment, the second bias current is generated by a second bias generator that is calibrated so that the product of the second bias current and the first or second resistance is a constant across process or temperature.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In another embodiment, the present invention includes a load impedance coupled between first and second differential output nodes and a supply voltage, the load impedance including a control terminal for changing the impedance between the first and second differential output nodes and the supply voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In another embodiment, the present invention includes a divider circuit comprising a differential circuit having first and second inputs to receive a first differential signal, a first frequency control input and first and second differential output nodes, wherein the differential circuit is coupled to a first bias current generator, and a cross-coupled circuit having a first control terminal coupled to a second output of the cross-coupled circuit and the first differential output node, a second control terminal coupled to a first output of the cross coupled circuit and the first differential output node, and a second frequency control input, wherein the cross-coupled circuit is coupled to a second bias current generator.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In another embodiment, the present invention includes a divider circuit comprising first and second transistors having sources coupled together to form a differential circuit, the first transistor having a first output terminal and the second transistor having a second output terminal, first and second cross-coupled transistors having sources coupled together, the first cross-coupled transistor having a first output terminal coupled to the first output terminal of the first transistor and the second cross-coupled transistor having a second output terminal coupled to the second output terminal of the second transistor, a first resistor coupled between the first output terminal of the first transistor and a supply terminal, the first resistor having a first resistance value, a second resistor coupled between the second output terminal of the second transistor and the supply terminal, the second resistor having a second resistance value approximately equal to the first resistance value, a third transistor having a control terminal coupled to a signal to be divided and a first terminal coupled to the sources of the first and second transistors, wherein the third transistor is coupled to a first bias generator that generates first bias current in the first and second transistors, and a fourth transistor having an control terminal coupled to a complement of the signal to be divided and a first terminal coupled to the sources of the cross-coupled transistors, wherein the fourth transistor is coupled to a second bias generator that generates second bias current in the first and second cross-coupled transistors.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The following detailed description and accompanying drawings provide a better understanding of the nature and advantages of the present invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a prior art divider circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a prior art D-Flip Flop divider circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates another prior art divider circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates yet another prior art divider circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates one aspect of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates an electronic circuit according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a bias generator according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a bias generator according to another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates a divider circuit according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> illustrates a divider circuit according to another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> illustrates a divider circuit according to yet another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Described herein are techniques for implementing high frequency division with optimized lock range. In the following description, for purposes of explanation, numerous examples and specific details are set forth in order to provide a thorough understanding of the present invention. It will be evident, however, to one skilled in the art that the present invention as defined by the claims may include some or all of the features in these examples alone or in combination with other features described below, and may further include modifications and equivalents of the features and concepts described herein.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates one aspect of the present invention. In contemporary electronic circuits such as those described in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the differential circuits and cross-coupled circuits operate using the same bias current. One aspect of the present invention includes operating a differential circuit <b>501</b> using a first bias current and operating a cross-coupled circuit <b>502</b> using a second bias current. The two bias currents may be substantially independent to a first order, for example. The differential circuit may include a frequency control input to receive a first input signal to be divided (e.g., CK), and the cross-coupled circuit may include a frequency control input to receive a complementary input signal to be divided (e.g., <o ostyle="single">CK</o>). While complementary signals CK and <o ostyle="single">CK</o> (i.e., signals that differ in phase by 180 degrees) are shown here for illustration, it is to be understood that some applications may use other input signals that have other phase differences such as I and Q signals, for example. The outputs of the differential and cross coupled circuits may be coupled together and used in a variety of applications, such as stages in a divider or ring oscillator, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates an electronic circuit according to one embodiment of the present invention. Circuit <b>600</b> includes a differential circuit <b>601</b>, cross-coupled circuit <b>602</b> and load impedance <b>603</b>. Differential circuit <b>601</b> includes NMOS transistors M<b>3</b> and M<b>4</b> having sources coupled together and to current source Ix. The drains of M<b>3</b> and M<b>4</b> are coupled through load impedance <b>603</b> to supply terminal Vdd. A bias current, Ix, in differential circuit <b>601</b> is set by current source, Ix. Differential circuit <b>601</b> includes a frequency control input <b>605</b> for receiving a signal to be divided. Here the frequency control input <b>605</b> couples an input signal (designated here as CK) to the bias current Ix in differential circuit <b>601</b>. Cross-coupled circuit <b>602</b> includes NMOS transistors M<b>5</b> and M<b>6</b> having sources coupled together. The drains of M<b>5</b> and M<b>6</b> are also coupled through load impedance <b>603</b> to supply terminal Vdd. The control terminal of M<b>5</b> (e.g., here, the gate of NMOS transistor M<b>5</b>) is coupled to the drain of M<b>6</b>, and the control terminal of M<b>6</b> (e.g., here, the gate of NMOS transistor M<b>6</b>) is coupled to the drain of M<b>5</b>. The bias current, Iy, in cross-coupled circuit <b>602</b> is set by current source, Iy. Cross-coupled circuit <b>602</b> also includes a frequency control input <b>606</b> for receiving a complement of the signal to be divided. Here frequency control input <b>606</b> couples the complement of the input signal (designated here as <o ostyle="single">CK</o>) to the bias current Iy in cross-coupled circuit <b>602</b>. Advantageously, the differential circuit bias current, Ix, is different than the cross-coupled circuit bias current, Iy. Currents Ix and Iy may be generated independently, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">One advantage of using different bias currents is that the lock performance of the circuit may be improved. The lock range is a function of the amplitude of oscillation and the center frequency, ω<sub>c</sub>, of the circuit. The amplitude of oscillation is given by the following equation:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>Vs=</i>4<i>IyR/π,</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
where R is the resistance of the load impedance. The center frequency of the circuit is given by:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>ω<sub>c</sub>=(1<i>/RC</i>)<i>Ix/Iy,</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
where R is the resistance of the load impedance and C is the capacitance at the output nodes (i.e., +out<b>1</b> and −out<b>1</b>). In one embodiment, Iy is maintained constant using a constant process and temperature invariant current source, and the differential bias current source, Ix, is calibrated so that the ratio of a differential bias current and a resistance is a constant (i.e., Ix/R=constant). In another embodiment, Ix is maintained constant using a constant process and temperature invariant current source, and the cross-coupled bias current source, Iy, is calibrated so that the product of a cross-coupled bias current and a resistance is a constant (i.e., R*Iy=constant).
</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a bias generator <b>700</b> according to one embodiment of the present invention. Bias generator <b>700</b> generates a bias voltage, Ix_bias, that may be used to produce a current, Ix, for constant Ix/R. Bias generator <b>700</b> includes a resistor (“R”) <b>701</b>, which may be a replica of a resistor used in load impedance <b>603</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. Thus, as a resistor in the load impedance varies with process and temperature, resistor <b>701</b> will vary in a substantially similar manner. Resistor <b>701</b> is coupled to a process and temperature invariant current source (“Io”) <b>702</b>. Thus, the current Io will generate a voltage, V<b>1</b>=R*Io, which will change with process and temperature as resistor <b>701</b> changes with process and temperature. V<b>1</b> is coupled to an input of a differential amplifier <b>710</b>. The other input of differential amplifier <b>710</b> is coupled to a reference voltage, Vref, which may be a calibrated reference voltage, for example. For instance, voltage, Vref, may be generated using a variable resistor <b>730</b> (“Ro”) coupled in series with transistor <b>720</b> (“Mbias”) between reference voltages, such as Vdd and ground. In this example, variable resistor <b>730</b> is a switched resistor network, which may comprise a plurality of resistors (e.g., resistors <b>721</b>-<b>724</b>, R<sub>A</sub>, R<sub>B</sub>, R<sub>C </sub>and R<sub>D</sub>) and switches (e.g., switches <b>732</b>-<b>734</b>). Switches <b>732</b>-<b>734</b> may be MOS transistor switches, for example. It is to be understood that other variable resistor techniques or switching techniques may be used. Variable resistor <b>730</b> is coupled to the drain of transistor <b>720</b>, and the gate of transistor <b>720</b> is coupled to the output of differential amplifier <b>710</b>. The output of differential amplifier <b>710</b>, Ix_bias, is also used as the bias voltage for other stages in the circuit (e.g., the differential stage of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> or <b>6</b>). Thus, the current in transistor <b>720</b>, Ix, is a replica of the current in such stages.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Since the output of differential amplifier <b>710</b> is coupled back to the differential amplifier input, the feedback action will result in V<b>1</b> and Vref being approximately equal. Variable resistor, Ro, can be calibrated using resistors <b>722</b>-<b>724</b> and switches <b>732</b>-<b>734</b>. Such calibration may include a calibration for process variations (e.g., a one time process calibration) or a real-time calibration for temperature variations, or both, resulting in a substantially constant value for Ro. Since Io is a constant current source, the ratio of Io/Ro is constant. Constant Ix/R can be seen from the following equations:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Vref=V1<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>Ix*Ro=Io*R</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>Ix/R=Io/Ro</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Therefore, since the voltage at the output of differential amplifier <b>710</b>, Ix_bias, is used as the bias voltage for other stages in the circuit (e.g., the differential stage of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> or <b>6</b>), the ratio of the bias current, Ix, and resistance, R, will be constant. Consequently, the center frequency of the circuit may be maintained across process and temperature variations so that the lock range of the circuit is optimized.
</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Maintaining a constant Ix/R, as illustrated above, will ensure that the center frequency of the oscillator will not vary with process or temperature. However, variation of resistance in the load impedance will also affect amplitude. For example, if the process resistance is low, the amplitude may be reduced and higher currents may be required for the circuit to operate properly. Alternatively, if the process resistance is high, the amplitude may be increased, which means that the circuit has more current than necessary for proper operation. Amplitude variations thus translate into increased power consumption because the current in the circuit is not optimized. To reduce the adverse effects of both center frequency variation and amplitude variation, embodiments of the present invention may use a constant current source for Ix, and use another bias generator that may be used to produce a cross-coupled bias current, Iy, wherein the product of Iy and a load resistance is a constant (i.e., R*Iy=constant).</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a bias generator <b>800</b> according to another embodiment of the present invention. Bias generator <b>800</b> generates a bias voltage, Iy_bias, that may be used to produce a current, Iy, for constant Iy*R. Bias generator <b>800</b> includes a resistor (“R”) <b>801</b>, which may be a replica of a resistor used in load impedance <b>603</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. Thus, as a resistor in the load impedance varies with process and temperature, resistor <b>801</b> will vary in a substantially similar manner. Resistor <b>801</b> is coupled to the drain of transistor <b>820</b> (“Mbias”). The current Iy through transistor <b>820</b> and resistor R will produce a voltage, V<b>2</b>, which is coupled to an input of differential amplifier <b>810</b>. The other input to amplifier <b>810</b> is coupled to a reference voltage, Vref, which is substantially process and temperature invariant (i.e., substantially constant). The output of amplifier <b>810</b> is coupled to the gate of transistor <b>820</b>. The output of differential amplifier <b>810</b>, Iy_bias, is also used as the bias voltage for other stages in the circuit (e.g., the cross-coupled stage of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> or <b>6</b>). Thus, the current in transistor <b>820</b>, Iy, is a replica of the current in such stages.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Since the output of differential amplifier <b>810</b> is coupled back to the differential amplifier input, the feedback action will result in V<b>2</b> and Vref being approximately equal. Vref may be maintained constant across process and temperature. Thus, constant Iy*R can be seen from the following equations:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>V2=Vref<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>Iy*R=Vref=</i>Constant<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Therefore, since the voltage at the output of differential amplifier <b>810</b>, Iy_bias, is used as the bias voltage for other stages in the circuit (e.g., the cross-coupled stage of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> or <b>6</b>), the product of the bias current, Iy, and resistance, R, will be constant. Consequently, the center frequency and amplitude of the circuit may be maintained across process and temperature variations so that both the lock range and power consumption of the circuit are optimized.
</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates a divider circuit according to one embodiment of the present invention. Divider circuit <b>900</b> includes first and second stages <b>901</b> and <b>902</b>. Each stage includes a differential circuit (e.g., M<b>3</b>-M<b>4</b> and M<b>9</b>-M<b>10</b>) and a cross-coupled circuit (e.g., M<b>5</b>-M<b>6</b> and M<b>11</b>-M<b>12</b>) coupled to a load impedance such as resistors R<b>1</b>-R<b>4</b> and capacitors C<b>1</b>-C<b>4</b>. Inductors may also be included in certain high frequency applications but have been omitted here. Each differential circuit includes a bias current, Ix, and each cross-coupled circuit includes a bias current Iy. Each differential circuit further includes a frequency control input. Here the frequency control inputs are the control terminals of transistors M<b>1</b> and M<b>7</b>, which in this example are NMOS devices. When the input signals are received on the control terminals of M<b>1</b> or M<b>7</b> (i.e., input signals CK and <o ostyle="single">CK</o>, respectively), each transistor will generate an AC current component of the input signal on bias current Ix, which will couple into the corresponding differential circuit. Each cross-coupled circuit also includes a frequency control input. Here the frequency control inputs are the control terminals of transistors M<b>2</b> and M<b>8</b>, which in this example are NMOS devices. When the input signals are received on the control terminals of M<b>2</b> or M<b>8</b> (i.e., input signals <o ostyle="single">CK</o> and CK, respectively), each transistor will generate an AC current component of the input signal on bias current Iy, which will couple into the corresponding cross-coupled circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In this example, the bias current values in the differential circuit and cross-coupled circuit are set by bias voltages. Bias voltage Ix_bias is coupled to the control terminals of NMOS transistors M<b>1</b> and M<b>7</b> through resistors R<b>5</b> and R<b>7</b>, respectively. Bias voltage Iy_bias is coupled to the control terminals of NMOS transistors M<b>2</b> and M<b>8</b> through resistors R<b>6</b> and R<b>8</b>, respectively. In each stage, the differential circuit receives a bias voltage Ix_bias to produce a bias current Ix, and the cross-coupled circuit receives a bias voltage Iy_bias to produce a bias current Iy. Bias voltages Ix_bias and Iy_bias may be generated by bias generators (not shown), which may be of the type described above and illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7-8</figref>, for example. The bias generators may include replicas of load resistors R<b>1</b>-R<b>4</b>. Such resistors may be designed to have the same resistance values, but the values may be slightly different after manufacturing. Replica resistors may be used to tune the circuit so that the ratio of Ix/R is constant over process or temperature or both. Replica resistors may also be used to tune the circuit so that the product of Iy*R is constant over process or temperature or both.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> illustrates a divider circuit according to another embodiment of the present invention. Divider circuit <b>1000</b> includes first and second stages <b>1001</b> and <b>1002</b>. Each stage includes a differential circuit (e.g., M<b>3</b>-M<b>4</b> and M<b>9</b>-M<b>10</b>) and a cross-coupled circuit (e.g., M<b>5</b>-M<b>6</b> and M<b>11</b>-M<b>12</b>) coupled to a load impedance (e.g., <b>1010</b> and <b>1011</b>). Load impedances <b>1010</b> and <b>1011</b> may include resistors, inductors and capacitors, for example, and the inductors or capacitors may include parasitic inductance or capacitance. In this example, the bias currents in the differential circuit and cross-coupled circuit are set by bias generators. Bias current <b>2</b>Ix is coupled to the source terminals of NMOS transistors M<b>1</b> and M<b>7</b>. Thus, each of these devices has a current of Ix. Bias current <b>2</b>Iy is coupled to the source terminals of NMOS transistors M<b>2</b> and M<b>8</b>. Thus, each of these devices has a current of Iy. Therefore, each differential circuit receives a bias current Ix, and each cross-coupled circuit receives a bias current Iy. Bias generators <b>2</b>Ix and <b>2</b>Iy may be of the type described above and illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7-8</figref>, for example, for generating constant Ix/R or Iy*R over process or temperature or both.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> illustrates a divider circuit according to yet another embodiment of the present invention. Divider circuit <b>1100</b> is an example of a folded cascade implementation, which is particularly advantageous for low supply voltage applications. Divider circuit <b>1100</b> includes first and second stages <b>1101</b> and <b>1102</b>. Each stage includes a differential circuit (e.g., M<b>3</b>-M<b>4</b> and M<b>9</b>-M<b>10</b>) and a cross-coupled circuit (e.g., M<b>5</b>-M<b>6</b> and M<b>11</b>-M<b>12</b>) coupled to a load impedance (e.g., <b>1110</b> and <b>1111</b>). Load impedances <b>1110</b> and <b>1111</b> may include resistors, inductors and capacitors, for example, and the inductors or capacitors may include parasitic inductance or capacitance. In this example, the bias currents in the differential circuit and cross-coupled circuit are set by bias generators.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The above description illustrates various embodiments of the present invention along with examples of how aspects of the present invention may be implemented. The above examples and embodiments should not be deemed to be the only embodiments, and are presented to illustrate the flexibility and advantages of the present invention as defined by the following claims. Based on the above disclosure and the following claims, other arrangements, embodiments, implementations and equivalents will be evident to those skilled in the art and may be employed without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as defined by the claims. The terms and expressions that have been employed here are used to describe the various embodiments and examples. These terms and expressions are not to be construed as excluding equivalents of the features shown and described, or portions thereof, it being recognized that various modifications are possible within the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A divider circuit comprising:
<claim-text>a differential circuit having first and second inputs to receive a first differential signal and first and second differential output nodes, wherein the differential circuit has a first bias current generated by a first bias generator; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cross-coupled circuit having a first control terminal coupled to a second output of the cross-coupled circuit and the first differential output node and a second control terminal coupled to a first output of the cross coupled circuit and the second differential output node, and wherein the cross-coupled circuit has a second bias current generated by a second bias generator that is independent of the first bias current,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the differential circuit is coupled to a first transistor having a control terminal to receive a signal to be divided, and wherein the first bias generator is coupled to the differential circuit through the first transistor, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the cross-coupled circuit is coupled to a second transistor having a control terminal to receive the complement of the signal to be divided, and wherein the second bias generator is coupled to the cross-coupled circuit through the second transistor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the second bias current is a constant current and the first bias current is calibrated so that die ratio of the first bias current and a resistance is a constant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first bias current is a constant current and the second bias current is calibrated so that the product of the second bias current and a resistance is a constant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a first resistor having a first resistance coupled between the first differential output node and a supply terminal and a second resistor having a second resistance coupled between the second differential output node and the supply terminal, wherein the first bias generator is calibrated so that the ratio of the first bias current and the first or second resistance is a constant across process or temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a first resistor having a first resistance coupled between the first differential output node and a supply terminal and a second resistor having a second resistance coupled between the second differential output node and the supply terminal, wherein the second bias generator is calibrated so that the product, of the second bias current and the first or second resistance is a constant across process or temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a load impedance coupled between first and second differential output nodes and a supply voltage, the load impedance including a control terminal for changing the impedance between the first and second differential output nodes and the supply voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A divider circuit comprising:
<claim-text>a differential circuit having first and second inputs to receive a first differential signal, and first and second differential output nodes, wherein the differential circuit is coupled to a first bias current generator; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cross-coupled circuit having a first control terminal coupled to a second output of the cross-coupled circuit and the first differential output node and a second control terminal coupled to a first output of the cross coupled circuit and the second differential output node, wherein the cross-coupled circuit is coupled to a second bias current generator,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the differential circuit is coupled to a first transistor having a control terminal for receiving a signal to be divided, and wherein the first bias current generator is coupled to the differential circuit through the first transistor, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the cross-coupled circuit is coupled to a second transistor having a control terminal for receiving the complement of the signal to be divided, and wherein the second bias current generator is coupled to the differential circuit through the second transistor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further comprising a first resistor coupled between the first differential output node and a supply terminal and a second resistor coupled between the second differential output node and the supply terminal, the first and second resistors having approximately equal resistance values, wherein the first bias current generator includes a third resistor having an approximately equal resistance value as the first and second resistors for generating a replica current, wherein, the ratio of the replica current and the resistance value of the third resistor is a constant across process or temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further comprising a first resistor coupled between the first differential output node and a supply terminal and a second resistor coupled between the second differential output node and the supply terminal, die first and second resistors having approximately equal resistance values, wherein the first bias current generator includes a third resistor having an approximately equal resistance value as the first and second resistors for generating a replica current, wherein the product of the replica current and the resistance value of the third resistor is a constant across process or temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The divider circuit or <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the first bias current generator is coupled through the first transistor in a folded cascade configuration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the second bias current generator is coupled through the second transistor in a folded cascade configuration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A divider circuit comprising:
<claim-text>first and second transistors having sources coupled together to form a differential circuit, the first transistor having a first output terminal and the second transistor having a second output terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first and second cross-coupled transistors having sources coupled together, the first cross-coupled transistor having a first output terminal coupled to the first output terminal of the first transistor and the second cross-coupled transistor having a second output terminal coupled to the second output terminal of the second transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first resistor coupled between the first output terminal of the first transistor and a supply terminal, the first resistor having a first resistance value;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second resistor coupled between the second output terminal of the second transistor and the supply terminal, the second resistor having a second resistance value approximately equal to the first resistance value;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third transistor having a control terminal coupled to a signal to be divided and a first terminal coupled to the sources of the first and second transistors, wherein the third transistor is coupled to a first bias generator that generates first bias current in the first and second transistors; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth transistor having an control terminal coupled to a complement of the signal to be divided and a first terminal coupled to the sources of the cross-coupled transistors, wherein the fourth transistor is coupled to a second bias generator that generates second bias current in the first and second cross-coupled transistors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the first bias generator is calibrated so that the ratio of the first bias current arid the first resistance value is constant across process or temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the first bias generator comprises a third resistor having a third resistance value approximately equal to the first resistance value, an amplifier, and a fifth transistor coupled between a first amplifier input and an output of the amplifier for generating a replica current in the fifth transistor, wherein the ratio of the replica current and the first resistance value is a constant across process or temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the second bias generator is calibrated so that the product of the second bias current and the first resistance value is a constant across process or temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the second bias generator comprises a third resistor having a third resistance value approximately equal to the first resistance value, an amplifier, and a fifth transistor coupled between a first amplifier input and an output of the amplifier for generating a replica current in the fifth transistor, wherein the product of the replica current and the first resistance value is a constant across process or temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein first bias generator is coupled to the control terminal of the third transistor and the second bias generator is coupled to the control terminal of the fourth transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein first bias generator is coupled to a second terminal of the third transistor and the second bins generator is coupled to a second terminal of the fourth transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A divider circuit comprising:
<claim-text>a differential circuit having first and second inputs to receive a first differential signal and first and second differential output nodes;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cross-coupled circuit having a first control terminal coupled to a second output of the cross-coupled circuit and the first differential output node and a second control terminal coupled to a first output of the cross coupled circuit and the second differential output node;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first transistor coupled to the differential circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second transistor coupled to the cross coupled circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first bias means for biasing the differential circuit with a first bias current coupled to the differential circuit through the first transistor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>second bias means for biasing the cross-coupled circuit with a second bias current coupled to the cross-coupled circuit through the second transistor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the second bias means generates a constant current and the first bias means is calibrated so that the ratio of the first bias current and a resistance is a constant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the first bias means generates a constant current and the second bias means is calibrated so that the product of the second bias current and a resistance is a constant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> further comprising means for calibrating the first bias means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The divider circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> further comprising means for calibrating the second bias means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A method of dividing a signal comprising:
<claim-text>receiving a first input signal to be divided on a frequency control input of a first transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving a complement of the first input signal on a frequency control input of a second transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling the first input signal to a differential circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling the complement of the first input signal to a cross-coupled circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling a first bias current through the first transistor to the differential circuit using a first bias current generator;</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling a second bias current through the second transistor to the cross-coupled circuit using a second bias current generator;</claim-text>
<claim-text>operating the differential circuit using the first bias current; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>operating the cross-coupled circuit using the second bias current.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the first and second bias current generators output first and second voltages, and wherein the first voltage is coupled to a control terminal of the first transistor for generating the first bias current in the differential circuit, and wherein the second voltage is coupled to a control terminal of the second transistor for generating the second bias current.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the first and second bias current generators output first and second currents, and wherein the first voltage is coupled to a terminal of the first transistor for generating the first bias current in the differential circuit, and wherein the second current is coupled to a terminal of the second transistor for generating the second bias current.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00026">claim 26</claim-ref> wherein the first and second bias current generators are folded cascade circuits.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the second bias current is a constant current and the first bias current is calibrated so that the ratio of the first bias current and a resistance is a constant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the first bias current is a constant current and the second bias current is calibrated so that the product of the second bias current and a resistance is a constant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the second bias current is independent of the first bias current.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
