<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298807-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298807</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10672853</doc-number>
<date>20030926</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>659</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>375355</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Circuit, apparatus and method for adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in response to incoming serial data</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5742798</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Goldrian</name>
<date>19980400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6525520</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Davidsson et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324 7654</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6886106</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Brock et al.</name>
<date>20050400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>713500</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0206419</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kizer et al.</name>
<date>20050900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327158</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>02000035831</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20000200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>27</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>375355</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>375359</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>375360</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>375375</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>375376</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>713400-601</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60446491</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030211</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040161068</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040819</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zerbe</last-name>
<first-name>Jared</first-name>
<address>
<city>Woodside</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Horowitz</last-name>
<first-name>Mark</first-name>
<address>
<city>Menlo Park</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Werner</last-name>
<first-name>Carl</first-name>
<address>
<city>Los Gatos</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Vierra Magen Marcus &amp; DeNiro LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Rambus Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Los Altos</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Vo</last-name>
<first-name>Don N.</first-name>
<department>2611</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A circuit, apparatus and method for maximizing system margins by adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in a receive circuit to whatever duty-cycle is optimal for the particular incoming serial data, rather than the typical 50% duty-cycle, is provided in embodiments of the present invention. A receive circuit, including duty-cycle-correction logic, is included in a double-data rate communication apparatus having a transmit circuit transmitting serial data having duty-cycle distortion. A receive circuit includes a first and second sampler to obtain data and edge values of an incoming serial data responsive to a data and edge clock, respectively. A duty-cycle-correction logic generates a duty-cycle-correction signal to a duty-cycle clock integrator that adjusts the edge clock signals while maintaining quadrature to the data clocks. In an embodiment of the present invention, a duty-cycle-correction logic includes an evaluator circuit to generate an up or down signal responsive to the data and/or edge values. In a further embodiment of the present invention, an evaluator circuit is coupled to a counter and a DAC to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal to the duty-cycle clock integrator. A digital filter or coding scheme is also used to reduce the likelihood of misinterpreting malevolent incoming serial data for duty-cycle distortion in an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="137.84mm" wi="251.29mm" file="US07298807-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="254.59mm" wi="178.48mm" file="US07298807-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="251.88mm" wi="160.10mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298807-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="250.19mm" wi="168.99mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298807-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="253.49mm" wi="170.01mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298807-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="248.41mm" wi="180.17mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298807-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="226.57mm" wi="126.58mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298807-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="225.13mm" wi="164.59mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298807-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="243.59mm" wi="145.03mm" file="US07298807-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="233.68mm" wi="142.16mm" file="US07298807-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">PRIORITY CLAIM</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application claims priority to U.S. Provisional Patent Application Ser. No. 60/446,491, entitled, “A CIRCUIT, APPARATUS AND METHOD FOR ADJUSTING A DUTY-CYCLE OF A CLOCK SIGNAL IN RESPONSE TO INCOMING SERIAL DATA”, which application was filed on Feb. 11, 2003.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to communication systems, and in particular, double-data rate communication systems.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE RELATED ART</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A double-data rate (“DDR”) system includes a transmit circuit for transmitting serial data, having a particular duty-cycle, to a receiving circuit. Most receive circuits include a clock circuit for synchronizing the incoming serial data. In particular, the sampling clocks are recovered by looking at the incoming data stream and aligning sampling edges to the center of the data eyes or data cells. Ideally, the incoming serial data has a 50% duty-cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">However, a receive circuit may receive incoming data that has duty-cycle distortion and does not have the ideal 50% duty-cycle. First, a transmit clock circuit may generate a clock signal used for transmitting the data that does not have the ideal 50% duty-cycle. The transmit clock circuit may include Complementary Metal Oxide Semiconductor (“CMOS”) transistors that may be prone to random variations that introduce errors in the transmit clock signal. Second, a receive circuit introduces errors. For example, the receive circuit observes or reacts to rising edges faster than falling edges of a received data signal. Once again, this may cause a receiver recovered clock that is not centered at a data eye. Third, channel effects may cause duty-cycle distortion. For example, the medium used in transferring the serial data between the transmit circuit and receive circuit introduces delays that skew the expected data eye. Fourth, the receive clock itself may have a duty-cycle distortion present in it which may cause the input data to appear distorted when sampled by the receive clock.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Therefore, it is desirable to provide a circuit, apparatus and method for reducing the errors in obtaining data values caused by duty-cycle distortion.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram illustrating signals that may be used in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating obtaining edge and data values for adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram illustrating obtaining edge values for adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram illustrating using an offset signal in adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block diagram illustrating using a digital filter and coding scheme in adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a waveform illustrating a malevolent data pattern in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a block diagram illustrating a communication system in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8-9</figref> are flow charts of methods in accordance with embodiments of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A circuit, apparatus and method for maximizing system margins by adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in a receive circuit to whatever duty-cycle is optimal for the particular incoming serial data, rather than the typical 50% duty-cycle, in an embodiment of the present invention. A receive circuit, including duty-cycle-correction logic, is included in a double-data rate communication apparatus having a transmit circuit transmitting serial data having duty-cycle distortion. A receive circuit includes a first and second sampler to obtain data and edge values of an incoming serial data responsive to a data and edge clock, respectively. A duty-cycle-correction logic generates a duty-cycle-correction signal to a duty-cycle clock integrator that adjusts the clock signal including the edge clocks while maintaining the same relative phase position to the data clocks. In an embodiment of the present invention, a duty-cycle-correction logic includes an evaluator circuit to generate an up or down signal responsive to the data and/or edge values. In a further embodiment of the present invention, an evaluator circuit is coupled to a counter and a digital-to-analog converter (“DAC”) to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal to the duty-cycle clock integrator. A digital evaluator on the input of the integrator or digital counter or a coding scheme is also used to reduce the likelihood of misinterpreting malevolent incoming serial data as duty-cycle distortion in an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In an over sampled, DDR clock recovery circuit, two adjacent data symbols are sampled with a rising and a falling edge of the same clock. The accuracy of the clock duty cycle in a DDR system is critical as it impacts the final symbol size and thus the worst-case timing margins. In a DDR clock recovery circuit as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> sampled data feedback is used to keep sampling edges d<b>0</b> and d<b>1</b> centered in the data cells D<b>1</b> and D<b>2</b>, respectively, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Edge sampling clocks e<b>0</b> and e<b>1</b> are generated at “quadrature” or 90 degree phase offsets to data clock edges d<b>0</b> and d<b>1</b> respectively. Phase comparator logic that provides this feedback over-samples the incoming received signal to determine if the recovered clock is early or late with respect to the ideal sampling point of data eyes D<b>1</b> and D<b>2</b> and then advances or delays the sampling clock in response to the early or late data. The logic will determine that the sampling clock is late (compared to ideal) if edge and data samplers clocked by e<b>0</b> and d<b>0</b> consistently receive the same data. Similarly, the sampling clock is said to be early if edge and data samplers clocked by d<b>0</b> and e<b>1</b> are consistently the same. In a system that has ideal duty cycle, and is perfectly locked, the edge samplers clocked by e<b>0</b> and e<b>1</b> will produce data that is uncorrelated to the data samplers clocked by d<b>0</b> and d<b>1</b>. This condition represents the condition where the edge clocks are perfectly positioned in the noisy transition region of data eyes D<b>1</b> and D<b>2</b>. Phase mixers receiving fixed reference clock data from a phase-locked-loop (PLL) or other clock source advance or delay the reference clock signal in response to the early and late indications. An exemplary logic for an over-sampled CDR and phase mixing is described in Chih-Kong Ken Yang; Ramin Farjad-Rad; Horowitz, M. A., “A 0.5-μm CMOS 4.0-Gbit/s serial link transceiver with data recovery using oversampling,” IEEE Journal of Solid State Circuits, Volume 33, Issue 5, May 1998, pp. 713-722 which is incorporated by reference herein.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In an embodiment of the present invention, early and late data may be accumulated over some number of clock cycles. In this embodiment an additional logic circuit, a majority voter, can be used to produce a single early or late output only if a majority of the accumulated edge and data sample pairs were early or late. In an embodiment of the present invention, two to ten votes could be counted. This voting creates an averaging effect which may be desirable to prevent spurious adjustment of the recovered clock and filtering the received timing information. In DDR systems that use multi-level signaling or N-PAM signaling a similar method of clock recovery may be used in an embodiment of the present invention. An exemplary method is described in Farjad-Rad, R.; Yang, C. -K. K.; Horowitz, M. A.; Lee, T. H., “A 0.4-μm CMOS 10-Gb/s 4-PAM pre-emphasis serial link transmitter,” IEEE Journal of Solid-State Circuits, Volume 34, Issue 5, May 1999, pp. 580-585 which is incorporated by reference herein.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates serial data and clock signals <b>50</b> in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention. Serial data din<b>50</b> represents the alternating transitions of serial data that may be transported on a medium to a receive circuit. Serial data din<b>50</b> is shown having an ideal duty-cycle of 50%. Duty-cycle is defined as the amount of time a signal is at a predetermined phase value (for example, a high value) divided by the period of the signal T (or cycle). Data cell or data eye D<b>1</b> represents a period of time in serial data din<b>50</b> in which a data value may have a high value <b>52</b> or low value <b>53</b>. Edge clock eclk is used to determine the boundary of data cell D<b>1</b>, as well as data cells D<b>2</b>, D<b>3</b> and D<b>4</b>, or the transition from high to low or from low to high. For example, the rising edge e<b>0</b> and falling edge e<b>1</b> of edge clock eclk are used to define data cell D<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Data clock signal dclk is 90° offset or out of phase from edge clock eclk and is used to sample the value of the actual data cell. For example, the data clock dclk rising edge d<b>0</b> is used to determine the time at which the value of serial data din<b>50</b> is sampled, in particular, the time at which to sample serial data din<b>50</b> in order to determine the value of data cell D<b>1</b>. Data clock dclk and edge clock eclk are input into respective samplers whose outputs are also used to adjust the timing of the eclk and dclk edges with respect to din<b>50</b>. Data cell D<b>1</b> may have a binary one value corresponding to high value <b>52</b> or a binary zero value corresponding to low value <b>53</b> in an embodiment of the present invention. Likewise, data clock dclk falling edge d<b>1</b> is used to determine the sampling time associated with data cell D<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> also illustrates incoming serial data din<b>70</b> having a high duty-cycle, for example an approximate 70% duty-cycle, caused by duty-cycle distortion. As can be seen, edges e<b>0</b> and e<b>2</b> no longer define the data cells for a serial data din<b>70</b> and should be adjusted to edges ae<b>0</b> and ae<b>2</b>, respectively, in order to maximize margins and reduce error rates. Similarly, data clock dclk edges d<b>0</b>-d<b>3</b> are no longer centered on the data cells D<b>1</b>-D<b>4</b> when the incoming serial data has a high duty-cycle and data clock edges d<b>0</b>-d<b>3</b> should be likewise adjusted to adjusted data edges ad<b>0</b>-ad<b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Similarly, data clock dclk and edge clock eclk should be adjusted to a more optimal placement of edges if the incoming signal has a low duty-cycle, or less than 50% duty-cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As described below in various embodiments of the present invention, the duty cycle of a clock recovered from a received signal, and in particular a data clock dclk and edge clock eclk, is adjusted in response to the duty-cycle of the incoming serial data in order to reduce error rates. In an embodiment the edge clock is adjusted to best match the duty cycle of the incoming data stream whereas the data clock is kept as close to 50% as possible, but is kept at a 90 degree phase position to the adjusted edge clock. In alternate embodiments, the relative phase position of the edge and data clocks can be adjusted via an offset register in order to best position the data clocks within eyes which have inherent distortions present.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating obtaining edge and data values for adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in receive circuit <b>90</b> in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention. In this embodiment of the present invention, one of the edge samplers (for example, a rising edge sampler or falling edge sampler) outputs an edge value used to determine the phase of the incoming serial data and the other sampler outputs an edge value used to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal. Accordingly, a duty-cycle of a clock signal in receive circuit <b>90</b> is adjusted; and in particular, the duty-cycle of the edge clock eclk is adjusted to match the duty-cycle of the incoming serial data din on line <b>126</b> at the same time that the phase of the incoming clock is adjusted by the outputs of the majority detector for phase <b>107</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Serial data din having a particular duty-cycle is input to receive circuit <b>90</b> on line <b>126</b> coupled to the inputs of data samplers <b>103</b>-<b>104</b> and edge samplers <b>105</b>-<b>106</b>. In an embodiment of the present invention, data sampler <b>103</b> samples serial data din in response to the rising edge of data clock dclk on line <b>124</b> (relative phase 0 degrees), and data sampler <b>104</b> samples serial data din in response to the falling edge of data clock dclk on line <b>125</b> (relative phase 180 degrees—i.e. complementary to the signal on line <b>124</b>). Similarly, edge sampler <b>105</b> samples serial data din in response to the rising edge of edge clock eclk on line <b>127</b> (relative phase 90 degrees—i.e. in quadrature to the signal on line <b>124</b>) and edge sampler <b>106</b> samples serial data din in response to the falling edge of edge clock eclk on line <b>128</b> (relative phase 270 degrees—i.e. complementary to <b>127</b> and in quadrature to the signal on line <b>125</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Data clock dclk is generated from phase mixer/comparator (Phmix/cmp) <b>101</b> and edge clock eclk is generated from phase mixer/comparator (Phmix/cmp) <b>102</b> responsive to an output from a phase mixer and duty-cycle-correction signals output from duty-cycle clock (“DCC”) integrators <b>109</b><i>a </i>and <b>109</b><i>b</i>, respectively. A data clock dclk on line <b>142</b> (by way of lines <b>124</b> and <b>125</b>) is fed back to DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>a </i>and an edge clock eclk on line <b>143</b> (by way of lines <b>127</b> and <b>128</b>) is fed back to DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Buffers <b>120</b>-<b>123</b> allow the clock drive signal strength to be increased to be able to drive the significant load of the samplers and any following stages of latches.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">A first data value obtained using a rising edge data clock dclk and a second data value obtained using a falling edge data clock dclk are output from samplers <b>103</b> and <b>104</b> on lines <b>129</b> and <b>130</b>, respectively, to majority detector for phase <b>107</b> and evaluator circuit for duty-cycle <b>108</b>. A first edge value, obtained using a rising edge of edge clock eclk, is output on line <b>131</b> to majority detector for phase <b>107</b>. A second edge value obtained using a falling edge of edge clock eclk is output on line <b>132</b> to evaluator circuit <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Majority detector for phase <b>107</b> generates up and down signals on lines <b>133</b> and <b>134</b> to a phase mixer, responsive to the inputted data values and an edge value in order to align the edge clocks to the transition regions and thus the data clocks in the center of the valid data region. Accordingly, phase adjustment is determined by using an output from a single edge sampler <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Evaluator circuit for duty-cycle <b>108</b> generates up and down signals on lines <b>136</b> and <b>135</b>, respectively, to DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b </i>in order to adjust a clock duty-cycle. In an embodiment of the present invention, evaluator circuit <b>108</b> generates an up signal or a down signal responsive to a first data value, a first edge value and a second data value. For example, if a first data value is a logical “1”, an edge value is a logical “0” and a second data value is a logical “0”, a determination is made that the edge of edge clock eclk arrived late and a down signal is generated in order to reduce a clock signal duty-cycle. Conversely, if a first data value is a logical “1”, an edge value is a logical “1” and the second data value is a logical “0”, a determination is made that the edge of the edge clock eclk arrived early and an up signal is generated to increase a clock signal duty-cycle. Signals on lines <b>135</b> &amp; <b>136</b> are then combined with the actual feedback edge clock on line <b>143</b> in the DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b </i>and used to generate an offset from 50% in the DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b </i>output on line <b>138</b>. Data clock signals are also feedback on line <b>142</b> and input to DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>a </i>and used to generate DCC output <b>137</b> without an offset, i.e. as close to 50% as possible.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Thus, in this embodiment, edge values from one of the edge samplers (either edge sampler <b>105</b> or <b>106</b>) determine phase and the other determines duty-cycle for a clock signal.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram illustrating simultaneously acquiring phase and a duty-cycle of incoming serial data in receive circuit <b>200</b> in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates components having the same reference numbers as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and described above.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Unlike <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, evaluator circuit <b>108</b> is coupled to both edge samplers <b>105</b> and <b>106</b> by line <b>231</b>. Edge samplers <b>105</b> and <b>106</b> outputs are also coupled to majority detector <b>107</b> by line <b>231</b>. Data samplers <b>103</b> and <b>104</b> outputs are coupled to majority detector <b>107</b> by line <b>229</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Evaluator circuit for duty-cycle <b>108</b> generates up and down signals on lines <b>136</b> and <b>135</b>, respectively, to DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b </i>in order to adjust a clock duty-cycle responsive to edge values. For example, if a first edge value e<b>0</b> is a logical “1”, a second edge value e<b>1</b> is a logical “0”, a third edge value e<b>2</b> is a logical “1” and a fourth edge value e<b>3</b> is a logical “0”, a determination is made that a duty-cycle of the incoming data is high and a down signal is generated in order to reduce a clock signal duty-cycle. Conversely, if a first edge value e<b>0</b> is a logical “0”, a second edge value e<b>1</b> is a logical “1”, a third edge value e<b>2</b> is a logical “0” and a fourth edge value e<b>3</b> is a logical “1”, a determination is made that a duty-cycle of the incoming data is low and an up signal is generated in order to increase a clock signal duty-cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The embodiment described above and illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> provides advantages over the other embodiments. The receive circuit <b>200</b> has better transition density and tracking compared to the embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and thus provides better edge placement and lower jitter. The present embodiment may, however, incorrectly interpret a malevolent data pattern or signal in incoming serial data din caused by inter-symbol interference (“ISI”) as duty-cycle distortion.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">For example, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a malevolent data signal. An ideal data signal <b>701</b> having a bit cell time is shown in comparison to a malevolent data signal <b>702</b>. The malevolent signal <b>702</b> has a single falling edge occurring before the ideal falling edge <b>703</b>. Thus, a data signal with a single early falling edge appears as a data eye that was generated with a duty-cycle larger than 50% or duty-cycle distortion. If such a pattern is repeated with no transitions on the alternate clock edge the offset due to ISI can be misinterpreted as duty-cycle error. The fact that there are only transitions on one clock edge makes it difficult for the circuit to determine if there is in fact a duty-cycle error or if all edges suffer from ISI.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In one embodiment of the present invention as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> the duty cycle evaluator <b>108</b> is coupled to a counter <b>310</b> and a DAC <b>311</b>. This embodiment provides several advantages over the other embodiments provided herein. First, receive circuit <b>300</b> has relatively simple loop dynamics compared to the other embodiments. Second, if desired, one of the DCC integrators, <b>109</b><i>b </i>can be eliminated and the phase mixer/comparator <b>102</b> driven directly by the DAC <b>311</b>. This can reduce circuit complexity, cost and size. Note that this embodiment eliminates the direct feedback loop <b>143</b> and maintains a full digital state for duty-cycle correction. Counter <b>310</b> and DAC <b>311</b> are used to eliminate DCC integrators in other embodiments of the present invention. Additionally, an embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> provides reduced transition density and improved phase acquisition as both edge samplers are used simultaneously for phase and duty-cycle adjustment.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows similar components seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. However, evaluator circuit <b>108</b> generates an adjust signal on line <b>340</b> to a counter <b>310</b> that provides a count value on line <b>341</b>. An input of DAC <b>311</b> is coupled to line <b>341</b> and outputs an analog offset signal on line <b>335</b> to an offset port of DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates an embodiment of the present invention that reduces the likelihood of misinterpreting a malevolent data signal in serial data din as being duty-cycle distortion. In particular, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a block diagram using an offset signal in adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in receive circuit <b>400</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows similar components seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> except for the addition of digital filter <b>410</b> coupled to edge samplers <b>105</b>-<b>106</b> on line <b>231</b> and evaluator <b>108</b> on line <b>411</b>. Edge samplers <b>105</b>-<b>106</b> output edge values to digital filter <b>410</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In order to reduce the likelihood that a malevolent data signal is misinterpreted as duty-cycle distortion, a coding scheme or digital filter is used in embodiments of the present invention. In using a coding scheme, transmit circuit <b>20</b> transmits identical or nearly identical even and odd data cell transitions in coded serial data din.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Alternatively in one embodiment, a digital filter <b>410</b> is used which allows edge values to pass to evaluator <b>108</b> only when there are an equal, or substantially equal, number of odd/even transitions and even/odd transitions that have accumulated. As ISI distortion will be present on all transitions, a difference in phase location of odd &amp; even edges can then be correctly interpreted as a duty-cycle error. In alternate embodiments of the present invention, a digital filter <b>410</b> as described above is included in the embodiments illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-3</figref> as well to eliminate the potential of a malevolent pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In alternate embodiments illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> the offset output signal on line <b>335</b> is also provided as an input to the data clock DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b</i>. The function of the offset input on the data clock DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b </i>is not to alter the duty-cycle of the data clocks but rather to provide an input whereby the data clocks can be adjusted in phase to track the edge clocks and best remain in quadrature. This function is needed in an embodiment of the present invention in which the DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>a </i>and Phmix/cmp <b>102</b> alter the duty-cycle of edge clocks on lines <b>127</b>/<b>128</b> in such a way as will alter their quadrature phase relationship to the data clocks on lines <b>124</b>/<b>125</b>. This can happen if Phmix/cmp <b>102</b> adds delay in the adjustment of duty-cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a double-data rate communication system <b>10</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention. In particular, system <b>10</b> maximizes margins and reduces data error rates by adjusting a duty-cycle of a clock signal in receive circuit <b>30</b> responsive to a duty-cycle of incoming serial data din. In an embodiment of the present invention, serial data din is a double-data rate signal.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In an embodiment of the present invention, communication system <b>10</b> includes a transmit circuit <b>20</b> and a receive circuit <b>30</b> coupled by medium <b>11</b>. In an embodiment of the present invention, transmit circuit <b>20</b>, and in particular serial circuit <b>21</b>, generates serial data din having a non 50% duty-cycle on medium <b>11</b> to receive circuit <b>30</b>. In an embodiment of the present invention, transmit circuit <b>20</b> generates coded serial data din.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In an embodiment of the present invention, transmit circuit <b>20</b> is included in a memory controller and receive circuit <b>30</b> is included in a memory module.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">In an embodiment of the present invention, reference clocks are used in receiver circuit <b>30</b> to facilitate clock recovery.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Receive circuit <b>30</b> actively looks for transitions in the incoming serial data din and phase aligns data clock dclk and edge clock eclk with respect to the incoming data din. Receive circuit <b>30</b> samples the serial data din by data/edge samplers <b>34</b>. In an embodiment of the present invention, data/edge samplers <b>34</b> are shown as data samplers <b>103</b>-<b>104</b> and edge samplers <b>105</b>-<b>106</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-5</figref>. In an embodiment of the present invention, the sampled serial data din is converted to parallel data. Clock circuit <b>32</b>, includes duty-cycle-correction logic <b>33</b>, that generates a clock signal for receive circuit <b>30</b> corresponding to the duty-cycle of serial data din. Duty-cycle-correction logic <b>33</b> is shown as evaluator circuit <b>108</b> coupled to data samplers <b>103</b>-<b>104</b> and edge sampler <b>106</b>, as well as coupled to DCC integrator <b>109</b><i>b </i>as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Other embodiments of duty-cycle-correction logic <b>33</b> are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-5</figref> and described above.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In an embodiment of the present invention, medium <b>11</b> is a wire or set of wires for transporting signals, such as waveforms. In an embodiment of the present invention, medium <b>11</b> is a bidirectional double-data rate data bus that may carry data information, control information or both. In an alternate embodiment of the present invention, medium <b>11</b> is a unidirectional bus. In an alternate embodiment of the present invention medium <b>11</b> is a unidirectional point-to-point transmission line.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8-9</figref> illustrate methods <b>800</b> and <b>900</b> according to embodiments of the present invention. In alternate embodiments of the present invention, steps illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8-9</figref> are carried out by hardware, software or a combination thereof. In alternate embodiments, the steps illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 9</figref> are carried out by the components illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-5</figref> and <b>7</b>, respectively. As one of ordinary skill in the art would appreciate, other steps that are not shown may be included in various embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Method <b>800</b> begins at step <b>801</b> where serial incoming data is received. Serial data is then sampled to obtain data values as illustrated by step <b>802</b>. In an embodiment of the present invention, samplers <b>103</b> and <b>104</b> obtain data values in response to a data clock dclk as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Serial data is sampled to obtain an edge value as illustrated by step <b>803</b>. In an embodiment of the present invention, sampler <b>106</b> obtains an edge value in response to an edge clock eclk as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. A determination is made whether to adjust a duty-cycle of a clock signal as shown in step <b>804</b>. If a clock signal duty-cycle needs to be adjusted, control transfers to step <b>805</b> where a edge clock signal duty-cycle is adjusted in response to the data values and edge value while maintaining quadrature to the data clock signal; otherwise, method <b>800</b> ends. In an embodiment of the present invention, an evaluator circuit <b>108</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, outputs an up or down signal to adjust a clock signal duty-cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Method <b>900</b>, similar to method <b>800</b>, begins at step <b>901</b> where serial incoming data is received. Serial data is sampled to obtain a first edge value and a second edge value as illustrated by steps <b>902</b> and <b>903</b>, respectively. In an embodiment of the present invention, samplers <b>105</b> and <b>106</b> obtain a first edge value and a second edge value in response to an edge clock eclk as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. A determination is made whether to adjust a duty-cycle of a clock signal as shown in step <b>904</b>. If a clock signal duty-cycle needs to be adjusted, control transfers to step <b>905</b> where a clock signal duty-cycle is adjusted; otherwise, method <b>900</b> ends. In an embodiment of the present invention, an evaluator circuit <b>108</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, outputs an up or down signal to adjust a clock signal duty-cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The foregoing description of the preferred embodiments of the present invention has been provided for the purposes of illustration and description. It is not intended to be exhaustive or to limit the invention to the precise forms disclosed. Obviously, many modifications and variations will be apparent to practitioners skilled in the art. The embodiments were chosen and described in order to best explain the principles of the invention and its practical applications, thereby enabling others skilled in the art to understand the invention for various embodiments and with the various modifications as are suited to the particular use contemplated. It is intended that the scope of the invention be defined by the following claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A circuit capable to receive an input signal having a duty-cycle, comprising:
<claim-text>a first sampler capable to obtain a first edge value from the input signal responsive to an edge clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second sampler capable to obtain a first data value from the input signal responsive to a data clock signal; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle-correction logic, coupled to the first and the second samplers, capable to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal that adjusts the edge clock signal to the duty-cycle of the input signal duty-cycle responsive to the first edge value and first data value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the data clock signal has an approximate 50% duty-cycle and is in quadrature with an adjusted edge clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a third sampler, coupled to the duty-cycle-correction logic, capable to obtain a second data value; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the duty-cycle-correction logic is capable to generate the duty-cycle-correction signal responsive to the first data value, first edge value and second data value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the duty-cycle-correction logic comprises:
<claim-text>an evaluator circuit capable to generate at least one of an up signal and a down signal, responsive to the first data value, first edge value and second data value; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle clock integrator, coupled to the evaluator circuit, capable to generate the duty-cycle-correction signal responsive to the at least one of the up and down signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a first phase comparator, coupled to the first sampler, capable to generate the data clock signal; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second phase comparator, coupled to the first duty-cycle clock integrator and the second sampler, capable to generate the edge clock signal responsive to the duty-cycle-correction signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the input signal is a double-data rate signal and the circuit is included in a double-data rate system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the circuit is included in a memory module coupled to a double-data rate bus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A circuit capable to receive an input signal having a duty-cycle, comprising:
<claim-text>a first sampler capable to obtain a first edge value from the input signal responsive to an edge clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second sampler capable to obtain a second edge value from the input signal responsive to the edge clock signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle-correction logic, coupled to the first and the second samplers, capable to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal that adjusts the edge clock signal to the duty-cycle of the input signal duty-cycle responsive to the first and second edge values.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein a data clock signal has an approximate 50% duty-cycle and is in quadrature with an adjusted edge clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the duty-cycle-correction logic comprises:
<claim-text>an evaluator circuit capable to generate at least one of an up signal and a down signal, responsive to the first and second edge values; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle clock integrator, coupled to the evaluator circuit, capable to generate the duty-cycle-correction signal responsive to the at least one of the up and down signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a first phase comparator, coupled to the duty-cycle clock integrator and the first and second samplers, capable to generate the edge clock signal responsive to the duty-cycle-correction signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the input signal is a double-data rate signal and the circuit is included in a double-data rate system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the circuit is included in a memory module coupled to a double-data rate bus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A circuit capable to receive an input signal having a duty-cycle, comprising:
<claim-text>a first sampler capable to obtain a first edge value from the input signal responsive to an edge clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second sampler capable to obtain a second edge value from the input signal responsive to the edge clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle-correction logic, coupled to the first and the second samplers, capable to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal that adjusts the edge clock to the duty-cycle of the input signal responsive to the first and second edge values;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the duty-cycle-correction logic includes,
<claim-text>an evaluator circuit, coupled to the first and second samplers, capable to generate an adjust signal, responsive to the first and second edge values;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a counter, coupled to the evaluator circuit, capable to output a count value responsive to the adjust signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a digital-to-analog-converter, coupled to the counter, capable to generate an analog offset signal responsive to the count signal; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle clock integrator, coupled to the digital-to-analog-converter, capable to generate the duty-cycle-correction signal responsive to the analog offset signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein a data clock signal has an approximate 50% duty-cycle and is in quadrature with an adjusted edge clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising;
<claim-text>a digital filter coupled to first and second samplers and the evaluator circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the input signal is a coded input signal having an approximate same number of even and odd data transitions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a first phase comparator, coupled to the duty-cycle clock integrator and the first and second samplers, capable to generate the edge clock signal responsive to the duty-cycle-correction signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the input signal is a double-data rate signal and the circuit is included in a double-data rate system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the circuit is included in a memory module coupled to a double-data rate bus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. An apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text>a transmit circuit capable to transmit a serial signal having a duty-cycle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a receive circuit, coupled to the transmit circuit, including
<claim-text>a first sampler capable to obtain a first edge value from the serial signal responsive to an edge clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second sampler capable to obtain a first data value from the serial signal responsive to a data clock signal; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle-correction logic, coupled to the first and the second samplers, capable to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal that adjusts the edge clock signal to the duty-cycle of the serial signal duty-cycle responsive to the first edge value and first data value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. An apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text>a transmit circuit capable to transmit a serial signal having a duty-cycle; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a receive circuit, coupled to the transmit circuit, including
<claim-text>a first sampler capable to obtain a first edge value from the serial signal responsive to an edge clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second sampler capable to obtain a second edge value from the serial signal responsive to the edge clock signal; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle-correction logic, coupled to the first and the second samplers, capable to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal that adjusts the edge clock to the duty-cycle of the serial signal duty-cycle responsive to the first and second edge values.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. An apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text>a transmit circuit capable to transmit a serial signal having a duty-cycle; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a receive circuit, coupled to the transmit circuit, including,
<claim-text>a first sampler capable to obtain a first edge value from the serial signal responsive to an edge clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second sampler capable to obtain a second edge value from the serial signal responsive to the edge clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a duty-cycle-correction logic, coupled to the first and the second samplers, capable to generate a duty-cycle-correction signal that adjusts the edge clock to the duty-cycle of the serial signal responsive to the first and second edge values;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the duty-cycle-correction logic includes,</claim-text>
<claim-text>an evaluator circuit, coupled to the first and second samplers, capable to generate an adjust signal, responsive to the first and second edge values;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a counter, coupled to the evaluator circuit, capable to output a count value responsive to the adjust signal; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a digital-to-analog-converter, coupled to the counter, capable to generate the duty-cycle-correction signal responsive to the count signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A method, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>receiving an input signal having a first duty-cycle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>sampling the input signal to obtain a plurality of edge values from the input signal responsive to an edge clock signal having a second duty-cycle; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>adjusting the second duty-cycle of the edge clock signals to the first duty-cycle of the input signal responsive to the plurality of edge values.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref>, further comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>sampling the input signal to obtain a plurality of data values from the input signal responsive to a data clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, wherein the adjusting step includes adjusting the data clock signal to have an approximate 50duty-cycle and be in quadrature with an adjusted edge clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. A circuit capable to receive an input signal having a duty-cycle, comprising:
<claim-text>a sampler capable to obtain a plurality of edge values from the input signal responsive to an edge clock signal having a duty-cycle; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>means, coupled to the sampler, for adjusting the edge clock signal duty-cycle to the input signal duty-cycle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
