<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298111-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298111</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10554055</doc-number>
<date>20040225</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>103 19 064</doc-number>
<date>20030425</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>32</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318625</main-classification>
<further-classification>318 47</further-classification>
<further-classification>318 34</further-classification>
<further-classification>318 51</further-classification>
<further-classification>318632</further-classification>
<further-classification>318563</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Method and device for controlling a production unit</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4000449</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gripp</name>
<date>19761200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4554774</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Miyashita</name>
<date>19851100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5175680</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yoneda et al.</name>
<date>19921200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>700 71</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6536572</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Amanuma et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192 5332</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>36 14979</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19871100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>39 37 536</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19900500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>43 07 839</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19940900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>195 22 447</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19970100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>243 728</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>19871100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>385459</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>19900900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>436 209</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>19910700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>Lorenz R.D. et al “Synchronized motion control for process automation” Conference Record of the Industry Applications Society Annual Meeting, Oct. 1, 1989, pp. 1693-1698, XP010091171, New York, US, p. 1695, left-hand column, lines 1-6.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318625</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318 47</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318 34</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318 51</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318700</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318705</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318715</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318434</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318 85</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318632</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318563</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318567</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318569</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318611</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318615</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318675</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>364176</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060267536</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061130</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Linke</last-name>
<first-name>Wolfgang</first-name>
<address>
<city>Berlin</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>DE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>DE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sughrue Mion Pllc.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Focke &amp; Co. (GmbH &amp; Co. KG)</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Verden</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Masih</last-name>
<first-name>Karen</first-name>
<department>2837</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/EP2004/001834</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040225</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20051024</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2004/097538</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20041111</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method and a device for controlling a production unit in a production installation are specified, controlling referring to the controlling and monitoring of speeds of rotation or angles of rotation of individual drives (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) such that the movements of these are monitored in respect of a synchronous value (<b>37</b>) and/or a limit value (<b>33</b>). The monitoring in respect of the limit value (<b>33</b>) results in a safely limited speed of the individual drives. The monitoring in respect of the synchronous value (<b>37</b>) permits detection of asynchronies. The monitoring can be carried out in normal operating mode and/or in setup mode, and, in setup mode, it serves particularly to protect the operating personnel from drives (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) that start up suddenly or are running too fast.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="154.88mm" wi="120.01mm" file="US07298111-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="219.71mm" wi="172.80mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298111-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="204.81mm" wi="138.94mm" file="US07298111-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="203.54mm" wi="141.14mm" file="US07298111-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a method and a device for controlling a production unit of a production installation. Said production installation is, in particular, a production and packaging installation, preferably one for cigarettes or other articles for smoking. Such an installation comprises a number of different production units, which however are combined with one another in the production and packaging process, for example a cigarette production machine (maker), a packaging machine (packer), a film-wrapping machine, and, if appropriate, a multipacker and a carton packer. The speeds within the individual production units are coordinated in respect of a speed of a central drive of the respective production unit, also referred to as master drive or master shaft. The speeds of all other drives (slave drives) of the production unit are derived from the speed of the master shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">For servicing, it is necessary to gain access into the production installation or into an individual production unit. During such access, the installation or the production unit is in principle shut down. However, it may be necessary that the installation or production unit, hereinafter referred to jointly as installation, is started up again at a controlled speed during the service work, for example to permit access also to otherwise concealed sections of individual units, for example a section of a revolver in the area of the film-wrapping machine. This has hitherto been achieved by the installation or a central part of the installation being covered by a protective arrangement, for example in the form of a hood. To gain access into the installation, the hood has to be opened. When the hood is opened, the installation shuts down. The master shaft can now be turned further using a handwheel. The speed of rotation thus set for the master shaft influences the speeds of rotation of the dependent drives. Even with a comparatively low speed of rotation of the master shaft, it is possible for there to be a high speed of rotation of individual dependent drives. For this reason, all the dependent drives are safeguarded by in each case a further hood, as it were a “hood within a hood”. When a hood of a dependent drive is opened, further movement of the master shaft is blocked.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The object of the invention is to make available a simple and safe method for controlling a production unit and also a device for carrying out this method. In particular, in the event of servicing, access into the installation must be possible while maintaining the possibility of moving the central drive and dependent drives.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The object is achieved by the claimed method and by the claimed device. Accordingly, provision is made for the monitoring of limit values,namely limit values concerning speed or position, for example limit speeds or synchronous rotation positions.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The monitoring of the limit speeds is useful when generating desired speed values (desired speeds) for the individual drives. Moreover, the speed actually achieved can be monitored in respect of a limit speed (safely limited speed). The speed actually achieved for the individual drives can furthermore be monitored in respect of the respective desired speed, because synchrony of the individual drives with one another and with the central drive is guaranteed only if the desired speed is maintained exactly (synchronous speed).</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The monitoring of the synchronous rotation positions is in principle analogous to the monitoring of the limit speeds or synchronous speeds, the only difference being that the positions of rotation of the respective drives, that is to say the angle positions, are monitored instead of the speeds of rotation. This is expedient for dependent drives which, for example, do not execute a complete revolution but instead execute oscillating movements or the like. Even in the case of dependent drives that execute complete revolutions, the monitoring of the position of rotation and the comparison of the respective position of rotation with the position of rotation of the central drive permit the best possibility of monitoring the synchrony of the movement of the respective dependent drive with the corresponding movement of the central drive. The actually achieved position of the individual drives can moreover be monitored in respect of a limit value functionally corresponding to the limit speed in the speed monitoring. Such a limit value sets a tolerance range in the environment of the respective desired position, because an exact synchrony of position is often not possible to attain in practice. The tolerance range set by the limit value can be adapted by changing the limit value, that is to say made smaller or larger. Because of the theoretical analogy of a limit value in the form of a limit speed and a limit value in the form of a position-related tolerance range, both are referred to hereinafter simply as limit value.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A particular feature of the method according to the invention is that, in the event of access being made into the installation, which access is detected through opening of a protective arrangement, for example a hood or the like, a related signal (hood signal) is generated and this signal is used to reduce the speed of rotation, in particular the speed of rotation of the central drive, so that the drives automatically run more slowly in the event of such access being made. By reducing the speed of rotation of the central drive, a corresponding reduction in the speeds of rotation of the dependent drives is automatically obtained. This modified pattern of movement can additionally be monitored by means of the respective limit values also being correspondingly reduced. Reducing the limit value for the central drive ensures that, if for any reason a speed above the respective desired speed is reached, the central drive is stopped or switched off, at least when the speed set by the limit value is reached. In the case of the dependent drives, a corresponding reduction of the limit values has the effect that, if the respective set desired speed is exceeded, these drives also only reach at most a speed set by the limit value. This thus ensures safe limiting of the speed, so that sufficient safety of the operating personnel is guaranteed.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another particular feature of the invention is that speed information concerning a speed of rotation or angle of rotation of the central drive (speed of rotation or angle of rotation of master shaft) is evaluated such that, at a master shaft speed of rotation with the value zero, the limit value for the drives, in particular the limit value for the dependent drives, is likewise set to zero or kept at zero. This ensures that dependent drives do not incorrectly start running (i.e. they are safely stopped) and thus increases the safety of the operating personnel.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Finally, one particular feature of the invention is that the safely limited speed thus achieved is also guaranteed in the normal operating mode of the installation. In this way it is possible to avoid asynchronies of the dependent drives with one another or in relation to the master drive even in the normal operating mode.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Further particular features of the invention are explained in more detail below with reference to the drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a schematic representation of a production installation,</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a schematic representation of a chain of action for individual drives of the installation, and</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a schematic representation of the chain of action with the master drive integrated into the chain of action.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The illustrative embodiment shown in the drawings relates to a production and packaging installation for cigarettes as production installation. This usually comprises a number of production units, for example a cigarette-production machine, namely a maker, a packaging machine following the latter, that is to say a packer, a subsequent film-wrapping machine <b>10</b>, a packaging machine for producing multipacks from a plurality of cigarette packs, that is to say a multipacker and a cartoner which packages multipacks, that is to say cigarette multipacks, in a shipping carton. Cigarettes produced by the maker are fed to the packer which is provided for producing hinge-lid boxes for receiving the cigarettes. The cigarette packs formed by the packer, that is to say the combination of hinge-lid box and the cigarettes contained in them, are delivered to the film-wrapping machine <b>10</b>. The latter has the task of wrapping the cigarette packs in an outer film or plastic blank. The finished cigarette packs are used to form pack groups which are provided with a multipack wrapper in the region of the multipacker and thus produce a cigarette multipack comprising usually ten cigarette packs. These cigarette multipacks are fed, by a multipack conveyor, to the cartoner which transfers finished shipping cartons, with a plurality of cigarette multipacks, to a removal conveyor. Each of these production units comprises one or more drives. Of these drives, one has the function of a central drive or master drive <b>11</b>. The speeds or angles of rotation of all the other drives (dependent drives) are derived directly or indirectly from the speed of the master drive <b>11</b> or from the respective angle of rotation. If appropriate, account is taken in this case of predefined or predefinable laws of movement which describe mathematically, for example, an oscillating movement of a dependent drive synchronously to a rotation movement of the master drive <b>11</b> or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The film-wrapping machine <b>10</b> is shown in a side view as a detail from the installation. The (concealed) master drive <b>11</b> is shown by broken lines. To protect the operating personnel, the film-wrapping machine <b>10</b> has a central hood <b>12</b> which can be opened via a handle <b>13</b>. The central hood <b>12</b> conceals a unit <b>14</b> with its own drive, namely a dependent drive <b>20</b>. The unit <b>14</b> is a cutter block. The unit is covered by a hood <b>15</b> provided within the central hood <b>12</b> (hood within a hood). The hood <b>15</b> is shown in the closed state, while the opened state is indicated by broken lines. The hood <b>15</b> can be opened only when the central hood <b>12</b> has first been opened. Finally, a handwheel <b>16</b> is shown which cannot be accessed or cannot be actuated when the central hood <b>12</b> is closed. The master drive <b>11</b> can be turned with the handwheel <b>16</b>. The production unit comprises, if appropriate, further dependent drives (not shown in detail). Further dependent drives may form part of further production units, for example of the maker and/or of the packer.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a schematic representation of a chain of action for individual drives <b>20</b>, <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> of the installation. The drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> are dependent drives. They are referred to hereinafter simply as drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>. Each drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> is assigned a servo actuator <b>23</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>25</b>, hereinafter referred to in short as servo <b>23</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>25</b>, and is also assigned, as transducer <b>26</b>, <b>27</b>, <b>28</b>, a sensor for speed of rotation and/or angle of rotation. The or each servo <b>23</b>-<b>25</b> sets a desired value <b>29</b> for the respective drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>, in particular in the form of a desired speed or a desired angle of rotation. The actual movement of each drive <b>20</b>-<b>23</b> is determined by the transducer <b>26</b>-<b>28</b> assigned in each case to the drive <b>20</b>-<b>23</b> and is transmitted as actual value <b>30</b>, in particular as actual value of the instantaneous speed or as actual value of the instantaneous position, that is to say the angle of rotation, to a comparator <b>31</b>. The comparator <b>31</b> is provided for comparing desired value <b>29</b> and actual value <b>30</b> for each drive.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Each servo <b>23</b>-<b>25</b> comprises at least one input at which it can receive a transmitted speed of rotation or angle of rotation of the master shaft, hereinafter referred to jointly as the master shaft default <b>34</b>. From the master shaft default <b>34</b>, the servo <b>23</b>-<b>25</b> derives a default speed or default position and transmits this as desired value <b>29</b> in the form of a default speed or default angle of rotation to the respective drive <b>20</b>-<b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The desired value <b>29</b> is derived using not only the master shaft default <b>34</b> but also a limit value <b>33</b> which is either stored in a memory <b>35</b> of the respective servo <b>23</b>-<b>25</b> or is transmitted to this in the form of a limit value signal <b>36</b>. The limit value <b>33</b> is taken into account by the servo <b>23</b>-<b>25</b> such that the desired value <b>29</b> never exceeds the limit value <b>33</b>. The storage of the limit value <b>33</b> in the memory <b>35</b> or its transmission as limit value signal <b>36</b> can exist alternately or concurrently. Limit value <b>33</b> and limit value signal <b>36</b> are also referred to hereinafter as “safe value”. In the variant in which the safe value is either only stored in the memory <b>35</b> as limit value <b>33</b> or is only transmitted as limit value signal <b>36</b>, the respectively available safe value is used to derive the desired value <b>29</b>. In the variant in which the safe value is both stored in the memory <b>35</b> and is also transmitted as limit value signal <b>36</b>, it is conceivable that the limit value <b>33</b> stored in the memory <b>35</b> acts as an upper limit, so that the limit value signal <b>36</b> is used to derive the desired value <b>29</b> as long as the limit value signal <b>36</b> remains below the limit value <b>33</b>, and that, with a limit value signal <b>36</b> above the limit value <b>33</b>, the limit value <b>33</b> stored in the memory <b>35</b> is always used to derive the desired value <b>29</b>. Of course, exactly the reverse scenario or similar variants are conceivable.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The master shaft default <b>34</b> is taken in a manner not shown in detail either from the master shaft itself or from the handwheel <b>16</b>, specifically for example with a transducer coupled to the master shaft or to the handwheel <b>16</b>, for example an incremental transducer. Taking speed information or position information from the handwheel <b>16</b> is provided for only in setup mode, because in normal operation the handwheel <b>16</b> is not accessible for actuation, since it is covered by the central hood <b>12</b>. Moreover, taking information from the handwheel <b>16</b> is provided for exclusively when the handwheel <b>16</b> acts not directly but only indirectly on the master shaft, for example via an electronic transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The desired value <b>29</b> derived from the master shaft default <b>34</b> is delivered not only to the respective drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> but also to the comparator <b>31</b>. Each desired value <b>29</b> is stored as synchronous value <b>37</b> in the memory <b>32</b> of the comparator <b>31</b>. During operation, the actual value <b>30</b> taken for each drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> can be compared with the respective synchronous value <b>37</b> by the comparator <b>31</b>. If the actual value <b>30</b> of a drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> exceeds the respective synchronous value <b>37</b>, a corresponding stop signal <b>38</b> is generated which switches off either all the drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> or the drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> which is no longer running synchronously, in particular also the master drive <b>11</b> too. In addition, or as an alternative, provision can be made for the stop signal <b>38</b> to be generated not only when the synchronous value <b>37</b> is exceeded, but for said stop signal <b>38</b> to be generated when the actual value <b>30</b> departs from a predefined or predefinable range about the synchronous value <b>37</b>. It is then possible, for example, to also detect asynchronies caused by drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> erroneously running too slowly. In addition, the individual actual values <b>30</b> are also monitored in respect of the limit value <b>33</b>, i.e. the limit value <b>33</b> forms an upper limit which must not be exceeded by the desired value <b>29</b> given a corresponding default. When the limit value <b>33</b> is exceeded, the stop signal <b>38</b> is therefore also triggered. The limit value <b>33</b> can be an upper limit common to all drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> or can be set individually for each drive. The limit value <b>33</b> is then a field of possibly respectively different individual speed limits or position tolerance ranges. The or each stop signal <b>38</b> is routed through a display device <b>39</b> which for example supplies information, about the drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> causing the error, via optical display elements (not shown), for example a screen, in particular with clear-text display, or control lights. Instead of the situation shown, each drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> can be provided with its own comparator. Each of these comparators then comprises its own memory in which at least the limit value <b>33</b> set for the respective drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> and the actual synchronous value <b>37</b> are stored. The stop signal <b>38</b> possibly generated by an individual comparator of this kind is either delivered individually to the respective drive <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> or delivered to all the drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>, in particular also the master drive <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In the normal operation of the installation, that is to say during ongoing production, the synchrony of the individual drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> with one another and with the master drive <b>11</b> can be assured in this way. This is done by monitoring the synchronous value <b>37</b>. Moreover, it is possible to ensure that none of the drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> exceeds a predefined or predefinable upper limit, for example an upper speed limit. This is done by monitoring the limit value <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">When access is made into the installation, for example for maintenance or inspection purposes, that is to say in what is called a setup mode, monitoring of the movement of the individual drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> is likewise necessary. The setup mode differs from the normal operating mode in that the drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> run at much reduced speed. This is achieved by the fact that, in the setup mode, the speed of rotation of the master shaft is reduced. The speed of rotation of the master shaft can be predefined by the handwheel <b>16</b> or an otherwise suitable setting device, for example a modifiable resistance, that is to say a potentiometer or the like. When a handwheel <b>16</b> acting directly on the master shaft is used, the speed of the master shaft is limited on account of the limited physical power of the operator actuating the handwheel <b>16</b>. When using a handwheel <b>16</b> coupled only indirectly to the master shaft, for example via an electronic transmission, or when using for example a potentiometer instead of the handwheel <b>16</b>, the speed of the master shaft is limited by suitable monitoring of limit values. This is explained below with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Access into the installation is possible only when the central hood <b>12</b> is opened. In other words, at least a hood signal <b>40</b> is present from the central hood <b>12</b>. With the hood signal <b>40</b>, the limit value <b>33</b> is reduced. This can be done by virtue of the fact that, on the one hand, a limit value for the normal operating mode and, on the other hand, a limit value for the setup mode are stored as limit value <b>33</b> in the memory <b>32</b> of the comparator <b>31</b> and in the memory <b>35</b> of the respective servo <b>23</b>-<b>25</b>, and the respective limit value <b>33</b> is chosen depending on the status of the hood signal <b>40</b>. Alternatively, it is possible, for example, that the limit value <b>33</b> in the setup mode, that is to say when a hood signal <b>40</b> is present, is reduced in a defined manner, which can be easily done, for example, by a mathematical or logic operation (division or shift operation, respectively). Finally, it is also conceivable that the limit value signal <b>36</b> is reduced in a defined manner when the hood signal <b>40</b> is present. In the setup mode, the reduced speed of the master shaft thus also results in reduced desired values <b>29</b> for the drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>. The desired values <b>29</b> are maintained through monitoring the synchronous value <b>37</b> by the comparator <b>31</b> in the same way as in the normal operating mode. Likewise, limiting the movement of the drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>, that is to say safely avoiding a speed of rotation or a position outside the range defined by the limit value <b>33</b>, is also ensured in the same way as in the normal operating mode.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">To limit the speed of the master shaft, the master drive <b>11</b> itself is integrated in the chain of action according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The conditions that arise are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The master drive <b>11</b>, in the same way as the dependent drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>, is assigned its own transducer, namely the master shaft transducer <b>41</b>. The speed of rotation or position of rotation of the master shaft is, like the speed of rotation or position of rotation of the dependent drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>, detected as actual value <b>30</b> and delivered to the comparator <b>31</b>. Upstream of the master drive <b>11</b> there is a master shaft servo <b>42</b> which provides the same function as the servos <b>23</b>-<b>25</b> of the dependent drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>, i.e. a default, in particular a speed default, is determined from an input signal <b>43</b> and this default is conveyed onward as master shaft default <b>34</b> to the master drive <b>11</b>. The input signal <b>43</b> is derived from the handwheel <b>16</b> or from an otherwise suitable setting device. The master shaft default <b>34</b> is at the same time input of the servos <b>23</b>-<b>25</b> of the dependent drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>. On determination of the master shaft default <b>34</b>, a master shaft limit value <b>45</b> stored in a memory <b>44</b> of the master shaft servo <b>42</b> is taken into account so that the master shaft default <b>34</b> never exceeds this master shaft limit value <b>45</b>. In other words, upon calculation of the master shaft default <b>34</b>, each value for the master shaft default <b>34</b> above or outside the master shaft limit value <b>45</b> is discarded and, instead, the master shaft limit value <b>45</b> itself is used. In the presence of the hood signal <b>40</b>, the master shaft limit value <b>45</b> can be reduced exactly like the limit value <b>33</b> of the servos <b>23</b>-<b>25</b>, so that, when access is made into the installation, the master shaft default <b>34</b> can be reduced immediately.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Through monitoring of the limit value <b>33</b> and of the synchronous value <b>37</b>, the installation can be operated with a safely limited movement in respect of position and/or speed, specifically both in the normal operating mode and also in the setup mode. A safe stopping of the drives, in particular of the master drive <b>11</b> and of the dependent drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b>, is possible by delivering the master shaft default <b>34</b> or the input signal <b>43</b> of the master shaft to the comparator <b>31</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows that the master shaft default <b>34</b> is delivered not only to the servos <b>23</b>-<b>25</b> but also to the comparator <b>31</b>. In the comparator <b>31</b>, the respective value of the master shaft default <b>34</b> has the effect that for a master shaft default <b>34</b> not equal to zero the instantaneous limit value <b>33</b> is used and for a master shaft default <b>34</b> equal to zero the limit value <b>33</b> itself is set to zero. In case of integration of the master drive <b>11</b> in the chain of action, as is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the master shaft default <b>34</b> is also delivered to the comparator <b>31</b> and in a particularly preferred embodiment also the input signal <b>43</b>. In this arrangement, the limit value <b>33</b> is set to zero if either the master shaft default <b>34</b> or the input signal <b>43</b> is equal to zero. This also takes account of any errors in the determination of the master shaft default <b>34</b> in the master shaft servo <b>42</b> from the input signal <b>43</b>. With a limit value <b>33</b> equal to zero, starting up of each drive, that is to say of the dependent drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> or of the dependent drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> including the master drive <b>11</b>, is safely avoided, because the comparator <b>31</b> switches off the respective drive or all drives immediately by means of a corresponding stop signal <b>38</b> upon each movement of a drive and when there is thus an actual value <b>30</b> different than zero for this drive.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In a preferred embodiment, the or each transducer <b>26</b>-<b>28</b>, in particular also the master shaft transducer <b>41</b>, can be designed as a combined movement transducer and torque transducer or as a combination of a separate transducer for recording movement information, i.e. position and/or speed, and a separate torque transducer. Correspondingly, at least the limit value <b>33</b> then comprises on the one hand a limit value related to speed of rotation or position and on the other hand a limit value relating to torque. In this way it is also possible to avoid damage to the installation when the drives, in particular also the master shaft, are blocked.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">An advantage of the invention lies in the fact that it is possible to cut down on the safety mechanisms hitherto required for the dependent drives, that is to say the hoods or the like. On the other hand, an advantage of the invention is also the fact that, in the case where safety mechanisms are still present on individual dependent drives, a speed reduction adapted to signals from these safety mechanisms is possible, for example such that, with the central hood <b>12</b> opened, the speed of the central drive is reduced by 90% for example and, with additional opening of a specific further hood, there is a further speed reduction of a further 50% for example, and when another hood is opened, by contrast, a further speed reduction of, for example, 30% and so on. Such combinations and links can be easily stored in the comparator <b>31</b> and/or in the servo <b>23</b>-<b>25</b>, if appropriate also in the master shaft servo <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In summary, the invention can be described as follows: A method and a device are made available for controlling a production unit in a production installation, controlling referring to the controlling and monitoring of speeds of rotation or angles of rotation of individual drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> such that the movements of these are monitored in respect of a synchronous value <b>37</b> and/or a limit value <b>33</b> according to position and/or speed. The monitoring in respect of the limit value <b>33</b> results in a safely limited movement of the individual drives. The monitoring in respect of the synchronous value <b>37</b> permits detection of asynchronies. The monitoring can be carried out in normal operating mode and/or in setup mode, and, in setup mode, it serves particularly to protect the operating personnel from drives <b>20</b>-<b>22</b> that start up suddenly or are running too fast.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">LIST OF REFERENCE NUMBERS</heading>
<p id="p-0030" num="0000">
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0029"><b>10</b> film-wrapping machine</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0002" num="0030"><b>11</b> central drive</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0003" num="0031"><b>12</b> central hood</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0004" num="0032"><b>13</b> handle</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0005" num="0033"><b>14</b> unit</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0006" num="0034"><b>15</b> hood</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0007" num="0035"><b>16</b> handwheel</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0008" num="0036"><b>17</b> —</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0009" num="0037"><b>18</b> —</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0010" num="0038"><b>19</b> —</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0011" num="0039"><b>20</b> drive</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0012" num="0040"><b>21</b> drive</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0013" num="0041"><b>22</b> drive</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0014" num="0042"><b>23</b> servo actuator (servo)</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0015" num="0043"><b>24</b> servo actuator (servo)</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0016" num="0044"><b>25</b> servo actuator (servo)</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0017" num="0045"><b>26</b> transducer</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0018" num="0046"><b>27</b> transducer</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0019" num="0047"><b>28</b> transducer</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0020" num="0048"><b>29</b> desired value</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0021" num="0049"><b>30</b> actual value</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0022" num="0050"><b>31</b> comparator</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0023" num="0051"><b>32</b> memory</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0024" num="0052"><b>33</b> limit value</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0025" num="0053"><b>34</b> master shaft default</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0026" num="0054"><b>35</b> memory</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0027" num="0055"><b>36</b> limit value signal</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0028" num="0056"><b>37</b> synchronous value</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0029" num="0057"><b>38</b> stop signal</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0030" num="0058"><b>39</b> display device</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0031" num="0059"><b>40</b> hood signal</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0032" num="0060"><b>41</b> master shaft transducer</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0033" num="0061"><b>42</b> master shaft servo</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0034" num="0062"><b>43</b> input signal</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0035" num="0063"><b>44</b> memory</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0036" num="0064"><b>45</b> master shaft limit value</li>
</ul>
</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for controlling a production unit of a production installation for the production and/or packaging of cigarettes or other articles for smoking with at least one master drive (<b>11</b>), and at least one dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) whose movement depends directly or indirectly on the movement of a master shaft of the master drive (<b>11</b>), characterized
<claim-text>in that the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) is in each case assigned a servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) determines, from an input signal, a desired value (<b>29</b>) for the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) and conveys this desired value (<b>29</b>) to the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that, when determining the desired value (<b>29</b>), account is taken of a limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that this limit value or, if appropriate, a corresponding limit value that is taken into account for the determination of a desired value for the master drive, is reduced in the event of access being made into the production installation when a protective arrangement of the production unit is opened.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the input signal of the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) is information with regard to a speed of rotation or an angle of rotation of the master shaft (<b>34</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A method for controlling a production unit of a production installation for the production and/or packaging of cigarettes or other articles for smoking with at least one master drive (<b>11</b>), and at least one dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) whose movement depends directly or indirectly on movement of a master shaft of the master drive (<b>11</b>), characterized
<claim-text>in that the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) is in each case assigned a transducer (<b>26</b>-<b>28</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that a movement of the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) is detected by the transducer (<b>26</b>-<b>28</b>) and is transmitted as an actual value (<b>30</b>) to a comparator (<b>31</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the comparator (<b>31</b>) compares the actual value (<b>30</b>) with a limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and, in the event of a deviation, generates a stop signal (<b>38</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that the desired value (<b>30</b>) is stored in a memory (<b>32</b>) of the comparator (<b>31</b>) as a synchronous value (<b>37</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the comparison with the actual value (<b>30</b>) relates to the stored synchronous value (<b>37</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that each dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) has its own synchronous value (<b>37</b>) and/or its own limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the comparator (<b>31</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that the master drive (<b>11</b>) is assigned its own servo actuator, master shaft servo (<b>42</b>), and its own transducer, master shaft transducer (<b>41</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that, from an input signal (<b>43</b>) of the master shaft servo (<b>42</b>), a master shaft default for the master drive (<b>11</b>) is determined and is delivered to the comparator (<b>31</b>) for the master drive (<b>11</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the comparator (<b>31</b>) compares an actual value (<b>30</b>), detected by the master shaft transducer (<b>41</b>), with a limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and/or with the master shaft default and, in the event of a deviation, generates a stop signal (<b>38</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that, when determining the master shaft default, account is taken of a limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the master shaft servo (<b>42</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that the master shaft default (<b>34</b>) is delivered to an input of the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) of the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that a hood signal (<b>40</b>) is delivered to the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and if appropriate also to the master shaft servo (<b>42</b>) and/or to the comparator (<b>31</b>), which hood signal (<b>40</b>) is triggered when access is made into the production installation, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that, in the presence of a hood signal (<b>40</b>), the limit value (<b>33</b>) in the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and/or in the comparator (<b>31</b>), if appropriate also a master shaft limit value (<b>45</b>) in the master shaft servo (<b>42</b>), is reduced.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that the input signal or master shaft default of the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) is delivered to the comparator (<b>31</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the limit value (<b>33</b>) is set to or kept at zero as long as the input signal or master shaft default (<b>34</b>) has a zero value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method for controlling a production unit of a production installation for the production and/or packaging of cigarettes or other articles for smoking with at least one master drive (<b>11</b>), and at least one dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) whose movement depends directly or indirectly on movement of a master shaft of the master drive (<b>11</b>), characterized
<claim-text>in that the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) is in each case assigned a servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and a transducer (<b>26</b>-<b>28</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) determines, from an input signal, a desired value (<b>29</b>) for the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) and conveys this desired value (<b>29</b>) to the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) and to a comparator (<b>31</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that a movement of the dependent drive is detected by the transducer (<b>26</b>-<b>28</b>) and is transmitted as an actual value (<b>30</b>) to the comparator (<b>31</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the comparator (<b>31</b>) compares the desired value (<b>29</b>) with the actual value (<b>30</b>) and, in the event of a deviation, generates a stop signal (<b>38</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A device for controlling a production unit of a production installation for the production and/or packaging of cigarettes or other articles for smoking with at least one master drive (<b>11</b>), and at least one dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) whose movement depends directly or indirectly on a movement of a master shaft of the master drive (<b>11</b>), characterized
<claim-text>in that the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) is in each case assigned a servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) can determine, from an input signal, a desired value (<b>29</b>) for the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) and can deliver this desired value (<b>29</b>) to the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the desired value (<b>29</b>) is limited by a limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that this limit value or, if appropriate, a corresponding limit value, which is taken into account for the determination of a desired value for the master drive, is reduced in the event of access being made into the production installation when a protective arrangement of the production unit is opened.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that the input signal is information with regard to a speed of rotation or an angle of rotation of the master shaft (<b>34</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A device for controlling a production unit of a production installation for the production and/or packaging of cigarettes or other articles for smoking with at least one master drive (<b>11</b>), and at least one dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>), whose movement depends directly or indirectly on a movement of a master shaft of the master drive (<b>11</b>), characterized
<claim-text>in that the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) is in each case assigned a transducer (<b>26</b>-<b>28</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that a movement of the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) can be detected by the transducer (<b>26</b>-<b>28</b>) and can be transmitted as an actual value (<b>30</b>) to a comparator (<b>31</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the comparator (<b>31</b>) is provided for comparing the actual value (<b>30</b>) with a limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and for generating a stop signal (<b>38</b>) in the event of a deviation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that the actual value (<b>30</b>) can be stored in a memory (<b>32</b>) of the comparator (<b>31</b>) as a synchronous value (<b>37</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the comparison with the actual value relates to the stored synchronous value (<b>37</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that each dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) can have its own synchronous value (<b>37</b>) and/or its own limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the comparator (<b>31</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, characterized in that the master drive (<b>11</b>) is assigned its own master shaft servo (<b>42</b>) and its own master shaft transducer (<b>41</b>),
<claim-text>in that, from an input signal (<b>43</b>) of the master shaft servo (<b>42</b>), a master shaft default, for the master drive (<b>11</b>) can be determined and can be delivered to the comparator (<b>31</b>) for the master drive (<b>11</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the comparator (<b>31</b>) is provided for comparing an actual value (<b>30</b>) of the master drive (<b>11</b>), detectable by the master shaft transducer (<b>41</b>), with a limit value (<b>33</b>) which can be stored in the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and/or with the master shaft default and for generating a stop signal (<b>38</b>) in the event of a deviation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that the master shaft default is limited by a limit value (<b>33</b>) stored in the master shaft servo (<b>42</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that the master shaft default can be delivered to an input of the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) of the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, characterized
<claim-text>in that a hood signal (<b>40</b>) can be delivered to the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and if appropriate also to the master shaft servo (<b>42</b>) and/or to the comparator (<b>31</b>), which hood signal (<b>40</b>) can be triggered when access is made into the production installation, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that, as a function of a status of the hood signal (<b>40</b>), the limit value (<b>33</b>) in the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and/or in the comparator (<b>31</b>), if appropriate also a master shaft limit value (<b>45</b>) in the master shaft servo (<b>42</b>), can be reduced.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A device for controlling a production unit of a production installation for the production and/or packaging of cigarettes or other articles for smoking with at least one master drive (<b>11</b>), and at least one dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>), whose movement depends directly or indirectly on a movement of a master shaft of the master drive (<b>11</b>), characterized
<claim-text>in that the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) is in each case assigned a servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) and a transducer (<b>26</b>-<b>28</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the servo actuator (<b>23</b>-<b>25</b>) can determine, from an input signal, a desired value (<b>29</b>) for the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) and can deliver this desired value (<b>29</b>) to the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) and to a comparator (<b>31</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that a movement of the dependent drive (<b>20</b>-<b>22</b>) can be detected by the transducer (<b>26</b>-<b>28</b>) and can be transmitted as actual value (<b>30</b>) to the comparator (<b>31</b>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in that the comparator (<b>31</b>) is provided for comparing the actual value (<b>30</b>) with the desired value (<b>29</b>) and for generating a stop signal (<b>38</b>) in the event of a deviation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
