<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296620-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296620</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11393677</doc-number>
<date>20060331</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>69</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>28</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>047</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165150</main-classification>
<further-classification>165175</further-classification>
<further-classification>165910</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Heat exchanger apparatus incorporating elliptically-shaped serpentine tube bodies</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3106958</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Simpelaar</name>
<date>19631000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>165181</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4800955</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hagemeister et al.</name>
<date>19890100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>165163</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6820685</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Carter et al.</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>165150</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0023744</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kim et al.</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>165177</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165150</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165152</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165163</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165171</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165175</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165910</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165903</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165177-179</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>165113</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>261152</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>261153</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>18</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070227712</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20071004</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bugler, III</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas William</first-name>
<address>
<city>Frederick</city>
<state>MD</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Shriver</last-name>
<first-name>George Robert</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sykesville</city>
<state>MD</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Merrill</last-name>
<first-name>Richard Preston</first-name>
<address>
<city>Columbia</city>
<state>MD</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Rader, Fishman &amp; Grauer PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>EVAPCO, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Westminster</city>
<state>MD</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Walberg</last-name>
<first-name>Teresa J.</first-name>
<department>3744</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A heat exchanger apparatus includes an inlet header, an inlet connection connected to the inlet header, an outlet header, an outlet connection connected to the outlet header and a plurality of serpentine tube bodies. The plurality of serpentine tube bodies interconnect and are in communication with the inlet header and outlet header. Each serpentine tube body has a plurality of straight tube sections and a plurality of U-shaped return bend sections. Each one of the straight tube sections and each one of the return bend sections have an elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration. The plurality of serpentine tube bodies are arranged in a juxtaposed manner with consecutive ones of the serpentine tube bodies contacting each other at a point defining a series of stacked common planes disposed parallel with one another.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="94.57mm" wi="71.88mm" file="US07296620-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="238.34mm" wi="161.46mm" file="US07296620-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="222.25mm" wi="147.15mm" file="US07296620-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="161.37mm" wi="155.11mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296620-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="165.27mm" wi="158.50mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296620-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="127.25mm" wi="144.61mm" file="US07296620-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="178.82mm" wi="151.21mm" file="US07296620-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="216.07mm" wi="146.90mm" file="US07296620-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="169.16mm" wi="111.17mm" file="US07296620-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a heat exchanger apparatus. More particularly, the present invention is directed to a heat exchanger apparatus that incorporates serpentine tube bodies having elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configurations.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Commonly known in the art in the fabrication of the heat exchangers, straight tubes are bent in an approximate range of bend angles of 170° and 190° so as to form a unitary construction of two straight tube sections integrally connected with a return bend formed at a selected bend angle. A skilled artisan would appreciate that if the straight tube is bent precisely 180°, the two straight tube sections would extend parallel to one another while if the straight tube is bent at a selected bend angle anywhere in the approximate range other than 180°, the straight tube sections would extend generally parallel with one another. For simplicity, the term “generally parallel” shall refer to the relationship of the two straight tube sections after the straight tube is bent at any selected angle in the approximate range of 170° and 190° including the precise bend angle of 180°.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">By way of example only, variations of a conventional heat exchanger are illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-6</figref>. Although not by way of limitation, a conventional heat exchanger <b>100</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> includes an upper inlet manifold <b>102</b> and a lower outlet manifold <b>104</b>. A skilled artisan would appreciate that the inlet manifold and the outlet manifold can switch locations such that the inlet manifold is located at the bottom of the conventional heat exchanger <b>100</b> and considered a lower inlet manifold while the outlet manifold is located at the top of the conventional heat exchanger <b>100</b> and considered an upper outlet manifold. The manifolds <b>102</b> and <b>104</b> are held in place by a bracket <b>106</b><i>a </i>on a side wall <b>108</b><i>a</i>. Inlet and outlet fluid conduits <b>110</b> and <b>112</b> extend through the side wall <b>108</b><i>a </i>and communicate with the upper and lower manifolds <b>102</b> and <b>104</b> respectively. A plurality of serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> are connected between the upper and lower manifolds <b>102</b> and <b>104</b>. The serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> are arranged relative to each other in a vertically-staggered array as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A</figref>, <b>3</b>A and <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Each serpentine heat exchanger tube <b>114</b> includes a plurality of straight tube sections <b>116</b> and a plurality of return bends <b>118</b>. The plurality of straight tube sections <b>116</b> are arranged in a plurality of generally parallel rows and disposed in a common plane as is known in the art. The plurality of return bends <b>118</b> are connected to the plurality of straight tube sections <b>116</b> in a manner such that a respective one of the return bends <b>118</b> connects sequential ones of the plurality of straight tube sections <b>116</b> to form a serpentine configuration. To support the serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b>, horizontally extending support rods <b>120</b> are mounted on brackets <b>106</b><i>a </i>and <b>106</b><i>b</i>. A respective one of the brackets <b>106</b><i>a </i>and <b>106</b><i>b </i>is mounted on respective ones of the side walls <b>108</b><i>a </i>and <b>108</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Various cross-sectional configurations of the serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> as is known in the prior art and any selected ones of the various cross-sectional configurations can be employed as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A-6</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>, the cross-sectional configuration of the serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> is circular. Specifically, both the straight tube sections <b>116</b> and the return bends <b>118</b> are circular in cross-section. By way of example, the circular cross-sectional serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> occupy an imaginary heat exchange box B. As best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, consecutive ones of the serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> contact each other at juxtaposed return bends <b>118</b> at respective points Pt.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref>, the cross-sectional configuration of the serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> is partially circular and partially elliptical. Specifically, the straight tube sections <b>116</b> are elliptical in cross-section and the return bends <b>118</b> are circular in cross-section. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>, consecutive ones of the serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> contact each other at juxtaposed return bends at respective points Pt.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-6</figref>, the cross-sectional configuration of the serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> is generally circular. Specifically, the straight tube sections <b>116</b> are circular in cross-section and the return bends <b>118</b> are primarily circular in cross-section. The return bends <b>118</b> are considered primarily circular because each return bend includes at least one dimple <b>122</b> that defines a recess <b>124</b> formed into the return bend <b>118</b> as best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the recess <b>124</b> is sized to receive a portion of the adjacent return bend <b>118</b> in such a manner that surface-to-surface contact is made between contacting return bends. Such surface-to-surface contact slightly reduces heat exchange capacity of the heat exchanger incorporating this structure and might result in corrosion at a level greater than point contact between contacting return bends. However, this design provides a higher density of packing of the serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> into an identical space of the heat exchanger packed with circular serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b>. By way of example, the circular cross-sectional serpentine heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> occupy and define the imaginary heat exchange box B. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the four heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> are packed in the imaginary heat exchange box B sized identically as the one in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>. One of ordinary skill in the art would appreciate that the structure in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is more densely packed into the imaginary heat exchange box B because the recesses <b>124</b> formed by the dimples <b>122</b> in the respective return bends <b>118</b> receive the juxtaposed contacting one of the return bends <b>118</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Because the heat exchanger tubes <b>114</b> are more densely packed in the imaginary heat exchange box B, more heat exchanger tubes can be added to an identically-sized heat exchanger thereby increasing heat exchange capacity.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">It would be advantageous to provide a heat exchanger incorporating serpentine heat exchanger tubes that result in a densely-packed heat exchanger. It would be advantageous to provide a heat exchanger incorporating serpentine heat exchanger tubes that provides point contact with consecutive ones of the return bends while simultaneously providing a densely packed heat exchanger. The present invention provides these advantages.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">OBJECTS AND SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">An object of the present invention is to provide a heat exchanger apparatus incorporating serpentine tube bodies that result in a densely-packed heat exchanger.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Another object of the present invention is to provide a heat exchanger apparatus incorporating serpentine tube bodies that provide point contact with consecutive ones of the return bends while simultaneously providing a densely-packed heat exchanger.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A heat exchanger apparatus of the present invention is hereinafter described that includes an inlet header, an inlet connection connected to the inlet header, an outlet header, an outlet connection connected to the outlet header and a plurality of serpentine tube bodies. The plurality of serpentine tube bodies interconnect and are in communication with the inlet header and outlet header. Each serpentine tube body has a plurality of straight tube sections and a plurality of U-shaped return bend sections. The plurality of straight tube sections are arranged in a plurality of generally parallel rows and disposed in a common plane with the return bend sections. The plurality of return bend sections are connected to the plurality of straight tube sections in a manner such that a respective one of the return bend sections connects sequential ones of the plurality of straight tube sections to form a serpentine configuration. Each one of the straight tube sections and each one of the return bend sections have an elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration. The plurality of serpentine tube bodies are arranged in a juxtaposed manner with consecutive ones of the serpentine tube bodies contacting each other to define a series of stacked common planes disposed parallel with one another.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">These objects and other advantages of the present invention will be better appreciated in view of the detailed description of the exemplary embodiments of the present invention with reference to the accompanying drawing figures.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side elevational view partially in cross-section of a prior art heat exchanger apparatus incorporating serpentine tube bodies.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the four prior art serpentine tube bodies in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> having circular cross sections.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the four serpentine tube bodies taken a long line <b>2</b>B-<b>2</b>B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the four prior art serpentine tube bodies in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> having alternate cross-sectional configurations, namely elliptically-shaped straight tube sections connected together with circularly-shaped return bend sections.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the four serpentine tube bodies taken a long line <b>3</b>B-<b>3</b>B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the four prior art serpentine tube bodies in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> having alternate cross-sectional configurations, namely circularly-shaped return bend sections and circularly-shaped straight tube sections with dimples formed in the circularly-shaped return bend sections.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a side elevational view of the prior art serpentine tube body in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a partial side elevational view of the prior art serpentine tube body taken a long line <b>6</b>-<b>6</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a perspective view of an exemplary embodiment of a heat exchanger apparatus of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a perspective view of a serpentine tube body as a component of the heat exchanger apparatus of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a partial perspective view partially in cross-section of the serpentine tube body in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a top planar view of the serpentine tube body in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the serpentine tube body taken along line <b>11</b>-<b>11</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the serpentine tube body taken along line <b>12</b>-<b>12</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the serpentine tube body taken along line <b>13</b>-<b>13</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a partial perspective view of four prior serpentine tube bodies illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8-10</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the four serpentine tube bodies taken along lines <b>15</b>-<b>15</b>-<b>15</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> is a side elevational view of two serpentine tubes illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8-10</figref> arranged in a vertically staggered manner and contacting each other at a point.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE EXEMPLARY EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Hereinafter, the exemplary embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to the attached drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">An exemplary embodiment of a heat exchanger apparatus <b>10</b> of the present invention is hereinafter described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7-16</figref>. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the heat exchanger apparatus <b>10</b> of the present invention includes an inlet header <b>12</b>, an inlet connection <b>14</b> connected to the inlet header <b>12</b>, an outlet header <b>16</b>, an outlet connection <b>18</b> connected to the outlet header <b>16</b> and a plurality of serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b>. The plurality of serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> interconnect and are in communication with the inlet header <b>12</b> and outlet header <b>16</b>. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8-13</figref>, each serpentine tube body <b>20</b> has a plurality of straight tube sections <b>22</b> and a plurality of U-shaped return bend sections <b>24</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the plurality of straight tube sections <b>22</b> are arranged in a plurality of generally parallel rows and disposed in a common plane P along with the return bend sections <b>24</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. The plurality of return bends <b>24</b> are connected to the plurality of straight tube sections <b>22</b> in a manner such that a respective one of the return bend sections <b>24</b> connects sequential ones of the plurality of straight tube sections <b>22</b> to form a serpentine configuration as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9-15</figref>, each one of the straight tube sections <b>22</b> and each one of the return bend sections <b>24</b> have an elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the plurality of serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> are arranged in a juxtaposed manner. Illustrated in more detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 14-16</figref>, consecutive ones of the serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> contact each other. Again, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the consecutive ones of the serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> define a series of stacked common planes P<b>1</b> through Pn that are disposed parallel with one another.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10-13</figref>, the elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration of the serpentine tube body <b>20</b> is generally constant. More particularly, each one of the straight tube sections <b>22</b> and the return bend sections <b>24</b> of each serpentine tube body <b>20</b> is generally constant. One of ordinary skill in the art would appreciate that, in practice, it would be difficult to maintain an identical cross-sectional configuration of the straight tube sections <b>22</b> and the return bend sections <b>24</b> because the return bend sections <b>24</b> are formed conventionally by bending a straight elliptically-shaped tube about a bend die. Thus, variations of the elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration might exist and therefore the elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration of the serpentine tube body <b>20</b> is considered to be generally constant.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Furthermore, the term “elliptically-shaped” shall be defined to include “oval-shaped” since by definition found in The American Heritage College Dictionary, third edition, “oval” is defined as resembling an ellipse in shape. A skilled artisan would appreciate that in view of FIGS. <b>9</b> and <b>11</b>-<b>15</b>, the cross-sectional shape of the serpentine tube body or bodies <b>20</b> can be construed as either “elliptically-shaped” or “oval-shaped”. In other words, the term “elliptically-shaped” can be construed as “generally elliptically-shaped”.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, the straight tube section <b>22</b> defines an internal straight tube cross-sectional area CAst and, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12 and 13</figref>, the return bend section <b>24</b> defines an internal return bend cross-sectional area CArb. It is appreciated that each straight tube section <b>22</b> of each one of the serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> also has internal straight tube cross-sectional areas CAst's and each return bend section <b>24</b> of each serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> also has internal return bend cross-sectional areas CArt's. The internal straight tube cross-section area CAst and the internal return bend cross-sectional area CArb are generally equal in size relative to one another. One of ordinary skill in the art would appreciate that, in practice, it would be difficult to maintain identical internal straight tube cross-section areas Cast's and internal return bend cross-sectional areas CArb's because, as mentioned above, the return bend sections <b>24</b> are formed conventionally by bending a straight elliptically-shaped tube about a bend die. Thus, variations of the internal straight tube cross-sectional areas Cast's and the internal return bend cross-sectional areas CArb's might exist and therefore the internal straight tube cross-section areas Cast's and the internal return bend cross-sectional areas CArb's are considered generally equal in size relative to one another.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 14-16</figref>, a plurality of serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> are arranged juxtaposed to one another and consecutive ones of the plurality of serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> are vertically staggered relative to each other. Further, as best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 15 and 16</figref>, consecutive ones of the return bend sections <b>24</b> contact each other at points Pt.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Superimposing the imaginary heat exchange box B referred to in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, note that the four serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> occupy only a portion of the imaginary heat exchange box B as viewed from left to right. Also, small portions of the straight tube sections <b>22</b> of only two of the four serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> project slightly outwardly from the imaginary heat exchange box B. In any regard, the additional space is available within the imaginary heat exchange box B to include additional serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> if desired. As is known in the art, adding such additional serpentine tube bodies <b>20</b> in the imaginary heat exchange box B will increase heat exchange capacity of the heat exchanger apparatus <b>10</b> without increasing a width W of the imaginary heat exchange box B but slightly adding to a height H of the imaginary heat exchange box B.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">By comparison of the prior art heat exchanger <b>100</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b>A and <b>2</b>B with the heat exchanger apparatus <b>10</b> of the present invention, empirical data indicates that the heat exchange surface area increases by approximately 23% and that heat transfer improves within a range of approximately 3% and 19%.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The heat exchanger apparatus of the present invention incorporating elliptically-shaped serpentine tube bodies result in a densely-packed heat exchanger providing increased heat exchange surface area and improved heat transfer properties. The heat exchanger apparatus of the present invention incorporating elliptically-shaped serpentine tube bodies provides point contact with consecutive ones of the return bends. Such point contact between consecutive ones on the return bends minimizes concerns for corrosion relative to the densely-packed conventional heat exchanger described in FIGS. of <b>4</b>-<b>6</b>. Further, since the elliptically-shaped return bend sections are the same shape as the elliptically-shaped straight tube sections, there is an increased heat exchange efficiency higher than the prior art described herein. It is theorized that an increase in heat exchange efficiency occurs because the elliptically-shaped return bend sections are now as aerodynamically beneficial as the aerodynamic elliptically-shaped straight tube sections. It is further theorized that at least a portion of the elliptically-shaped return bend sections are aerodynamically aligned in a direction of flow of the fluid medium which might also contribute to the increased heat exchange efficiency.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The exemplary embodiment of the present invention, may, however, be embodied in various different forms and should not be construed as limited to the exemplary embodiment set forth herein; rather, the exemplary embodiment is provided so that this disclosure will be thorough and complete and will fully convey the scope of the present invention to those skilled in the art. Further, it is appreciated that all of the objects of the present invention may not be encompassed in each one of the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A heat exchanger apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text>an inlet header;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inlet connection connected to the inlet header;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an outlet header;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an outlet connection connected to the outlet header; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of serpentine tube bodies interconnecting and in communication with the inlet header and outlet header, each serpentine tube body having a plurality of straight tube sections and a plurality of U-shaped return bend sections, the plurality of straight tube sections arranged in a plurality of generally parallel rows, the plurality of return bend sections connected to the plurality of straight tube sections in a manner such that a respective one of the return bend sections connects sequential ones of the plurality of straight tube sections to form a serpentine configuration, each one of the straight tube sections and each one of the return bend sections having an elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration, the plurality of serpentine tube bodies arranged in a juxtaposed manner with consecutive ones of the serpentine tube bodies contacting each other to define an interfacing plane, and with respective ones of the plurality of straight tube sections and the plurality of return bend sections of one of the consecutive ones of the serpentine tube bodies and respective ones of the plurality of straight tube sections and the plurality of return bend sections of a next one of the consecutive ones of the serpentine tube bodies each being coexistent with the interfacing plane.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A heat exchanger apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration of each one of the straight tube sections and the return bend sections is generally constant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A heat exchanger apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each one of the straight tube sections defines an internal straight tube cross-section area, the return bend section defines an internal return bend cross-sectional area, the internal straight tube cross-section area and the internal return bend cross-sectional area are generally equal in size relative to one another.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A heat exchanger apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the elliptically-shaped cross-sectional configuration of each one of the straight tube sections and the return bend sections is generally constant.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A heat exchanger apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein consecutive ones of the return bend sections contact each other.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A heat exchanger apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein consecutive ones of the return bends contact each other at a point.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A heat exchanger apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein consecutive ones of the plurality of serpentine tube bodies are vertically staggered relative to each other.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
