<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298426-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298426</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11040126</doc-number>
<date>20050121</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-000264</doc-number>
<date>20040126</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>548</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>50</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348731</main-classification>
<further-classification>375345</further-classification>
<further-classification>455334</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Television tuner having variable gain reduction</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6566953</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Yamamoto</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-320647</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-368639</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>4</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348725</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348731</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551802</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551882</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4552321</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>455334</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>375345</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330277</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>334 47</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>334 52</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050162567</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050728</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yamamoto</last-name>
<first-name>Masaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fukushima</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Calvaruso</last-name>
<first-name>Joseph A.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Chadbourne &amp; Parke LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Alps Electric Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Yenke</last-name>
<first-name>Brian P.</first-name>
<department>2622</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An integrated circuit comprises a switching transistor having an emitter connected to a grounding terminal, a first resistor connected between a first gate of a first field-effect transistor and the grounding terminal, a second resistor connected between the first gate of the field-effect transistor and a collector of the switching transistor, and a third resistor connected between the collector of the switching transistor and a drain of the field-effect transistor. The integrated circuit further comprises a bias voltage terminal connected to the collector of the switching transistor to apply a voltage to the bias voltage terminal from the outside of the integrated circuit via a sixth resistor.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="88.39mm" wi="158.83mm" file="US07298426-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="236.05mm" wi="171.62mm" file="US07298426-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a television tuner capable of receiving a UHF-band television signal and a VHF-band television signal.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The structure of a known television tuner is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. A VHF- or UHF-band television signal is input to an input terminal <b>1</b>. A VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> capable of switching bands is connected to the input terminal <b>1</b> via a filter <b>2</b>. A UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b> is connected to the filter <b>2</b> via a switching diode <b>4</b>. A voltage from the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is applied to the anode of the switching diode <b>4</b>. The output terminal of the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> and the output terminal of the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b> are connected to an integrated circuit <b>20</b>. First and second dual-gate field-effect transistors (FETs) <b>21</b> and <b>22</b>, a third single gate FET <b>23</b>, and a plurality of resistors are disposed inside the integrated circuit <b>20</b>, wherein the resistors mutually connect the first, second, and third FETs <b>21</b>, <b>22</b>, and <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Inside the integrated circuit <b>20</b>, a first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>21</b> and a drain D of the third FET <b>23</b> are connected by a first resistor <b>24</b>, a second gate G<b>2</b> of the first FET <b>21</b> and a second gate G<b>2</b> of the second FET <b>22</b> are connected by a second resistor <b>25</b>, a source S of the first FET <b>21</b> and a source S of the second FET <b>22</b> are connected by third resistor <b>26</b>, and a gate G of the third FET <b>23</b> and the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>22</b> are connected by a fourth resistor <b>27</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The integrated circuit <b>20</b> includes a first external terminal <b>20</b><i>a </i>connected to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>21</b>, a second external terminal <b>20</b><i>b </i>connected to the second gate G<b>2</b> of the first FET <b>21</b>, a third external terminal <b>20</b><i>c </i>connected to the drain D of the third FET <b>23</b>, a fourth external terminal <b>20</b><i>d </i>connected to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>22</b>, a fifth external terminal <b>20</b><i>e </i>connected to the source S of the second FET <b>22</b>, a sixth external terminal <b>20</b><i>f </i>connected to a drain D of the second FET <b>22</b>, a seventh external terminal <b>20</b><i>g </i>connected to the source S of the first FET <b>21</b>, and an eighth external terminal <b>20</b><i>h </i>connected to a drain D of the first FET <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is connected to the first external terminal <b>20</b><i>a, </i>and the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b> is connected to the fourth external terminal <b>20</b><i>d. </i>The second external terminal <b>20</b><i>b </i>is connected to an automatic gain control (AGC) terminal <b>8</b>. An AGC voltage is applied to the AGC terminal <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">One end of a peaking coil <b>9</b> is connected to the fourth external terminal <b>20</b><i>d. </i>The other end is connected to a direct current (DC) cutting capacitor <b>10</b> for high-frequency grounding and is also connected to a switching terminal <b>11</b>. The level of the switching voltage applied to the switching terminal <b>11</b> increases when the switching terminal <b>11</b> receives a UHF-band television signal and decreases when the switching terminal <b>11</b> receives a VHF-band television signal.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The third external terminal <b>20</b><i>c </i>is connected to the cathode of the switching diode <b>4</b> via a resistor <b>12</b> and is connected to a power terminal <b>14</b> via a pull-up resistor <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The eighth external terminal <b>20</b><i>h </i>is connected to a VHF inter-stage tuning circuit (not shown in the drawing). A power-supply voltage is applied to the VHF inter-stage tuning circuit and is further applied to the first FET <b>21</b> via the eighth external terminal <b>20</b><i>h. </i>The seventh external terminal <b>20</b><i>g </i>is directly grounded.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The sixth external terminal <b>20</b><i>f </i>is connected to a UHF inter-stage tuning circuit (not shown in the drawing). A power-supply voltage is applied to the UHF inter-stage tuning circuit and is further applied to the drain D of the second FET <b>22</b> via the sixth external terminal <b>20</b><i>f. </i>The fifth external terminal <b>20</b><i>e </i>is grounded by a capacitor <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to the above-described structure, when the television tuner receives a UHF-band television signal, a predetermined bias voltage required for operation is applied to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>22</b> by applying a high-level switching voltage to the switching terminal <b>11</b>. In this way, the television tuner enters an operational state. Simultaneously, the third FET <b>23</b> turns on, causing the switching diode <b>4</b> to turn on. Consequently, the television signal can be input to the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b>. The television signal selected by the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b> is input to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">When the third FET <b>23</b> turns on, the voltage at the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>21</b> becomes a bias voltage, and, thus, the television tuner enters a not-ready state.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">When the television tuner receives a VHF-band television signal, a low level switching voltage is applied to the switching terminal <b>11</b>. Accordingly, the bias voltage at the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>22</b> becomes zero, and the second FET <b>22</b> enters a not-ready state. Moreover, since the third FET <b>23</b> turns off, the switching diode <b>4</b> also turns off. Thus, a television signal is not input to the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b>. Since the third FET <b>23</b> is turned off, a predetermined bias voltage required for operation is applied to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>21</b>, enabling the operation of the first FET <b>21</b>. Although not shown in the drawing, a resistor for adjusting the bias voltage to a correct value is connected between the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>21</b> and the source S of the first FET <b>21</b>. A VHF-band television signal selected by the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is input to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>21</b> and is amplified (for example, refer to Japanese Unexamined Patent Application Publication No. 2002-368639).</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to the above-described known structure of a television tuner, the bias voltages applied to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>21</b> and the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>22</b> are determined by the resistors disposed inside the integrated circuit <b>20</b>. Therefore, the values of the voltages are predetermined and the gain reduction versus AGC voltage characteristics (i.e., AGC curve) cannot be changed.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">An object of the present invention is to provide a television tuner in which the gain reduction versus AGC voltage characteristics (i.e., AGC curve) can be easily changed from the outside of the integrated circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">To achieve the above-mentioned object, the present invention provides a television tuner comprising: a first field-effect transistor for amplifying a television signal of a first frequency, the first field-effect transistor being disposed inside the television tuner; a second field-effect transistor for amplifying a television signal of a second frequency, the second field-effect transistor being disposed inside the television tuner; and an integrated circuit. The integrated circuit comprises a grounding terminal connected to the sources of the first and second field-effect transistors; a first input terminal for inputting the television signal of a first frequency, the first input terminal being connected to a first gate of the first field-effect transistor; a second input terminal for inputting the television signal of a second frequency, the second input terminal being connected to a first gate of the second field-effect transistor; a switching transistor having an emitter connected to the grounding terminal; a first resistor connected between the first gate of the first field-effect transistor and the switching transistor; a second resistor connected between the first gate of first field-effect transistor and a collector of the switching transistor; a third resistor connected between the collector of the switching transistor and a drain of the second field-effect transistor; and a fourth resistor connected between a base of the switching transistor and the first gate of the second field-effect transistor. A power-supply voltage is applied to drains of the first and second field-effect transistors. An automatic gain control voltage is applied to second gates of the first and second field-effect transistors. A bias voltage is applied to the second input terminal via a fifth resistor from outside of the integrated circuit when the television signal of a second frequency is received. A voltage is applied to a bias voltage terminal from outside the integrated circuit via a sixth resistor, the bias voltage terminal being connected to the collector of the switching transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The above-mentioned bias voltage terminal is grounded via the sixth resistor.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">A power-supply voltage is applied to the above-mentioned bias voltage terminal via the sixth resistor.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A seventh resistor is interposed between the above-mentioned bias voltage terminal and the connecting point of the collector of the switching transistor, the second resistor, and the third resistor.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">According to a first aspect of the present invention, a bias voltage is applied to the second input terminal via a fifth resistor from outside of the integrated circuit when the television signal of a second frequency is received, and a voltage is applied to a bias voltage terminal from outside the integrated circuit via a sixth resistor, the bias voltage terminal being connected to the collector of the switching transistor. Therefore, the bias voltages of the first gates of the first and second FETs can be set to any value. Consequently, the gain reduction characteristic of each FET can be changed by resistors outside the integrated circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">According to the second aspect of the present invention, a bias voltage terminal is grounded via the sixth resistor. Therefore, the bias voltage of the first gate of the first FET can be reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">According to the third aspect of the present invention, a power-supply voltage is applied to the bias voltage terminal via the sixth resistor. Therefore, the bias voltage of the first gate of the first FET can be increased.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">According to the fourth aspect of the present invention, a seventh resistor is interposed between the bias voltage terminal and the connecting point of the collector of the switching transistor, the second resistor, and the third resistor. Therefore, the switching transistor can be protected.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a circuit diagram illustrating the structure of a television tuner according to the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a circuit diagram illustrating the structure of a known television tuner.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The structure of the television tuner according to the present invention is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the components that are the same as those in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, illustrating the structure of a known television tuner, are indicated by the same reference numerals. A VHF- or UHF-band television signal is input to an input terminal <b>1</b>. A VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is connected to the input terminal <b>1</b> via a filter <b>2</b> for removing unwanted signals. The VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is a band-switching tuning circuit. A voltage is applied to the anodes of a switching diode <b>3</b><i>a </i>and a varactor diode <b>3</b><i>b </i>disposed inside the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b>. The VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is switched to tune in the high or low frequency band of the VHF-band in accordance with the on and off state of the switching diode <b>3</b><i>a. </i>The tuning frequency changes due to the varactor diode <b>3</b><i>b. </i>The circuit for switching the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> and the switching diode <b>3</b><i>a </i>between on and off states is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The filter <b>2</b> is connected to a UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b> via a switching diode <b>4</b>. The VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> applies a voltage to the anode of the switching diode <b>4</b>. A varactor diode <b>5</b><i>a </i>for changing the tuning frequency is disposed inside the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b>. Output terminals of the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> and the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b> are connected to an integrated circuit <b>30</b>. The integrated circuit <b>30</b> includes first and second dual gate FETs <b>31</b> and <b>32</b>, a switching transistor <b>33</b>, and a plurality of resistors for mutually connecting the first and second FETs <b>31</b> and <b>32</b> and the switching transistor <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Inside the integrated circuit <b>30</b>, sources S of the first and second FETs <b>31</b> and <b>32</b> are mutually connected. A first resistor <b>34</b> is connected between the sources S of the first and second FETs <b>31</b> and <b>32</b> and a first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b>, a second resistor <b>35</b> is connected between the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b> and a collector C of the switching transistor <b>33</b>, and a third resistor <b>36</b> is connected between the collector C of the switching transistor <b>33</b> and a drain D of the second FET <b>32</b>. The third resistor <b>36</b> may instead be connected between the collector C of the switching transistor <b>33</b> and the drain D of the first FET <b>31</b>. A fourth resistor <b>37</b> is connected between a base B of the switching transistor <b>33</b> and the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>32</b>, and a resistor <b>38</b> is connected between a second gate G<b>2</b> of the first FET <b>31</b> and the a second gate G<b>2</b> of the second FET <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The integrated circuit <b>30</b> includes a first input terminal <b>30</b><i>a </i>connected to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b>, a second input terminal <b>30</b><i>b </i>connected to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>32</b>, a first output terminal <b>30</b><i>c </i>connected to the drain D of the first FET <b>31</b>, a second output terminal <b>30</b><i>d </i>connected to the drain D of the second FET <b>32</b>, an AGC voltage terminal <b>30</b><i>e </i>connected to the second gate G<b>2</b> of the first FET <b>31</b>, and a grounding terminal <b>30</b><i>f </i>connected to the sources S of the first and second FETs <b>31</b> and <b>32</b>. Furthermore, the integrated circuit <b>30</b> includes a switching terminal <b>30</b><i>g </i>and a bias voltage terminal <b>30</b><i>h. </i>A resistor <b>39</b> is connected between the switching terminal <b>30</b><i>g </i>and a connecting point of the collector C of the switching transistor <b>33</b>, the second resistor <b>35</b>, and the third resistor <b>36</b>. A resistor <b>40</b> is connected between the connecting point and the bias voltage terminal <b>30</b><i>h. </i></p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The output terminal of the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is connected to the first input terminal <b>30</b><i>a, </i>and the output terminal of the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b> is connected to the second input terminal <b>30</b><i>b</i>. Accordingly, a first television signal having a VHF-band frequency is input to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b>, and a second television signal having a UHF-band frequency is input to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>32</b>. The AGC voltage terminal <b>30</b><i>e </i>is connected to a direct current-cutting capacitor <b>6</b> for high-frequency grounding and is connected to an AGC terminal <b>8</b> via a resistor <b>7</b>. An AGC voltage is applied to the AGC terminal <b>8</b>. In this way, the AGC voltage is applied to the second gates G<b>2</b> of the first and second FETs <b>31</b> and <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">A switching voltage is applied to the second input terminal <b>30</b><i>b </i>from a fifth resistor <b>41</b> disposed outside the integrated circuit <b>30</b> via a U/V switching terminal <b>42</b>. The level of this switching voltage increases when the television tuner receives a UHF-band television signal and decreases when the television tuner receives a VHF-band television signal.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The switching terminal <b>30</b><i>g </i>of the integrated circuit <b>30</b> is connected to the cathode of the switching diode <b>4</b>. A sixth resistor <b>43</b> is connected to, for example, a power source B or is grounded so as to apply a predetermined voltage to the bias voltage terminal <b>30</b><i>h </i>via the sixth resistor <b>43</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">A VHF inter-stage tuning circuit (not shown in the drawing) is connected to the first output terminal <b>30</b><i>c. </i>A power-supply voltage is applied to the VHF inter-stage tuning circuit and is further applied to the drain D of the first FET <b>31</b> via the first output terminal <b>30</b><i>c. </i>The grounding terminal <b>30</b><i>f </i>is directly grounded.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">A UHF inter-stage tuning circuit (not shown in the drawing) is connected to the second output terminal <b>30</b><i>d. </i>A power-supply voltage is applied to the UHF inter-stage tuning circuit and is further applied to the drain D of the second FET <b>32</b> via the second output terminal <b>30</b><i>d. </i></p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">According to the above-described structure, the bias voltage applied to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b> is basically determined by the resistance of the first resistor <b>34</b>, the second resistor <b>35</b>, and the third resistor <b>36</b>. The value of the bias voltage, however, may be increased or decreased depending on whether the sixth resistor <b>43</b> is connected to the power source B or is grounded, and also depending on the resistance of the resistors. As a result, the change pattern in gain of the AGC voltage applied to the second gate G<b>2</b> of the first FET <b>31</b> (i.e., the AGC voltage when gain reduction begins) and the change pattern in gain reduction after the gain reduction begins can be changed. In this case, the seventh resistor <b>40</b> is not required. If the seventh resistor <b>40</b> is not included in television tuner, the switching terminal <b>30</b><i>g </i>and the connecting point of the collector C of the switching transistor <b>33</b>, the second resistor <b>35</b>, and the third resistor <b>36</b> may be directly connected to each other. However, it is recommended to include the seventh resistor <b>40</b> since it effectively protects the switching transistor <b>33</b> and the first FET <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">According to the above-described structure, when a UHF-band television signal is received, a high-level switching voltage is applied to the U/V switching terminal <b>42</b>. Accordingly, the switching transistor <b>33</b> turns on, causing a predetermined bias voltage that is divided at the fourth and fifth resistors <b>37</b> and <b>41</b> and that is required for operation to be applied to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>32</b>. As a result, the second FET <b>32</b> enters an operational state. Since the switching diode <b>4</b> simultaneously turns on, the television signal can be input to the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b>. The television signal selected by the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b> is input to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>32</b>. Since, at this time, the fourth resistor <b>37</b> is connected between the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>32</b> and the base B of the switching transistor <b>33</b>, the input UHF-band television signal does not undergo gain reduction.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">When the switching transistor <b>33</b> is turned on, the bias voltage at the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b> becomes zero, and the first FET <b>31</b> enters a not-ready state.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">An AGC voltage is applied to the second gate G<b>2</b> of the second FET <b>32</b> via the resistor <b>38</b>. Accordingly, parasitic oscillation is suppressed by negative feedback, and distortion is suppressed when the AGC voltage is reduced so that the gain is reduced by about 35 dB. Furthermore, by changing the resistance of the fifth resistor <b>41</b> disposed outside the integrated circuit <b>30</b>, the bias voltage of the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>32</b> can be changed. Consequently, the change pattern of the gain of the second FET <b>32</b> due to the AGC voltage or, in other words, the gain reduction characteristics, can be changed.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">When a VHF-band television signal is received, a low-level switching voltage is applied to the U/V switching terminal <b>42</b>. Accordingly, the bias voltage at the first gate G<b>1</b> of the second FET <b>32</b> becomes zero, and the second FET <b>31</b> enters a not-ready state. Since the switching transistor <b>33</b> turns off, the switching diode <b>4</b> also turns off. Consequently, a television signal is not input to the UHF input tuning circuit <b>5</b>. Furthermore, since the switching transistor <b>33</b> is turned off, a predetermined bias voltage required for operation is applied to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b>, and the first FET <b>31</b> enters an operational state.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The VHF-band television signal selected by the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is input to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b> and is amplified. In this case, since the collector C of the switching transistor <b>33</b> and the first gate G<b>1</b> of the first FET <b>31</b> are connected by the second resistor <b>35</b>, the output capacitance component of the switching transistor <b>33</b> is not directly sent to the first gate G<b>1</b> of the FET <b>31</b>. Thus, the output capacitance component is not added to the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b>, and the range of change in the tuning frequency of the VHF input tuning circuit <b>3</b> is not reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">According to the above-described television tuner, the switching transistor <b>33</b> is a bipolar transistor. The switching transistor <b>33</b>, however, may be a field-effect transistor (FET). If an FET is used, the collector, source, and base in the description above should be changed to a drain, emitter, and gate, respectively.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A television tuner comprising:
<claim-text>a first field-effect transistor for amplifying a television signal of a first frequency, the first field-effect transistor being disposed inside the television tuner;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second field-effect transistor for amplifying a television signal of a second frequency, the second field-effect transistor being disposed inside the television tuner; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an integrated circuit, the integrated circuit including a grounding terminal coupled to the sources of the first and second field-effect transistors; a first input terminal for inputting the television signal of a first frequency, the first input terminal being coupled to a first gate of the first field-effect transistor; and a second input terminal for inputting the television signal of a second frequency, the second input terminal being coupled to a first gate of the second field-effect transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a switching transistor having an emitter coupled to the grounding terminal, a first resistor disposed between the first gate of the first field-effect transistor and the grounding terminal, a second resistor disposed between the first gate of the first field-effect transistor and a collector of the switching transistor, a third resistor disposed between the collector of the switching transistor and a drain of the first or second field-effect transistor, and a fourth resistor disposed between a base of the switching transistor and the first gate of the second field-effect transistor are disposed inside the integrated circuit,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a power-supply voltage is appliable to the drains of the first and second field-effect transistors,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein an automatic gain control voltage is appliable to second gates of the first and second field-effect transistors,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a bias voltage is appliable to the second input terminal via a fifth resistor from outside of the integrated circuit when the television signal of a second frequency is received, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a voltage is appliable to a bias voltage terminal from outside the integrated circuit via a sixth resistor, the bias voltage terminal being coupled to the collector of the switching transistor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The television tuner according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the bias voltage terminal is grounded via the sixth resistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The television tuner according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a power-supply voltage is appliable to the bias voltage terminal via the sixth resistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The television tuner according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a seventh resistor is interposed between a bias voltage terminal and the connecting point of the collector of the switching transistor, the second resistor, and the third resistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
