<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298981-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298981</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11175134</doc-number>
<date>20050707</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-200137</doc-number>
<date>20040707</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>194</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399 45</main-classification>
<further-classification>399322</further-classification>
<further-classification>399406</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Fixing device and image forming apparatus with guide having adjustable biasing angle</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5978645</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Miyazaki</name>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399406</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-228198</doc-number>
<date>19980800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-352887</doc-number>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-295657</doc-number>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399 45</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399322</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399323</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399328</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399329</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399406</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060008283</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060112</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Oohara</last-name>
<first-name>Shunichi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ushiku</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Seki</last-name>
<first-name>Hiroyuki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hitachi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ogiso</last-name>
<first-name>Toshio</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hitachi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Obata</last-name>
<first-name>Shigeru</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ishioka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hiraoka</last-name>
<first-name>Chikara</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hitachi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="006" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hanashima</last-name>
<first-name>Toru</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hitachi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="007" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wakamatsu</last-name>
<first-name>Kazuhiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hitachi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Antonelli, Terry, Stout &amp; Kraus, LLP.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ricoh Printing Systems, Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ngo</last-name>
<first-name>Hoang</first-name>
<department>2852</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A fixing device includes a first fixing part having a heater disposed therein, a second fixing part, disposed to oppose to the first fixing part, for pinching a recording medium to form a first nip portion, a pair of transfer rollers, disposed at a downstream side of the recording medium, for forming a second nip portion, a guide for biasing the recording medium discharged from the transfer rollers towards the first fixing part side from one of the transfers rollers, and means part for biasing the guide towards the recording medium side.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="110.91mm" wi="129.37mm" file="US07298981-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="246.38mm" wi="153.42mm" file="US07298981-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="250.53mm" wi="150.11mm" file="US07298981-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="154.77mm" wi="163.32mm" file="US07298981-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CLAIM OF PRIORITY</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority from Japanese Application Ser. No. 2004-200137, filed on Jul. 7, 2004, the content of which is incorporated by reference into this application.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a fixing device for an electrophotographic type image forming apparatus and an image forming apparatus using the fixing device.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">RELATED ART</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In a fixing device using a belt, only an image forming side of the belt is heated so as to shorten a rise time to a temperature at which fixing can be done. In such case, since a temperature at the non-heating side just after the rising does not elevate to a desired temperature and since heat is adsorbed in a recording medium when the recording medium is continuously supplied, a temperature difference between the heated side and the non-heated side (the image forming side and the non-image forming side) becomes large. This temperature difference accelerates curling of the recording medium. The degree of curling depends on brands of recording media. Further, it depends on water adsorption degree in the recording media. In general, the larger the water adsorption, the larger the curling becomes large.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">When in order to remove curling of the non-image forming side, the recording medium is bent towards the direction of winding of the recording medium with respect to the belt or roller, the recording medium wreaths around the roll or brings about offset where a toner for forming the image adheres again to the heated belt or roller may take place. Therefore, it is difficult to remove curling effectively by bending the recording medium strongly just after the heated belt or the heated roller; in the case where curling of a recording medium with a high water content is large, curling can not be removed sufficiently. On the other hand, if a decurl mechanism is disposed to remove curling at a position after the recording medium has passed through the fixing device, the temperature of the recording medium lowers and reformation of the recording medium is difficult, it is necessary to deform the recording medium more greatly. This leads to clogging of the recording medium in the fixing device.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">As disclosed in Patent document No. 1, a device for removing curling of the recording medium is proposed wherein a belt member has a heating member therein, a nip is formed between a pressure roll and the belt, and the recording medium is bent by pressing it towards a guide in the recording medium transferring direction at the nip exit. In this technology, since the end of the recording medium that has passed through a contact face between a discharging roller and a discharging runner is open, there is a fear that the curling is not removed sufficiently depending on kinds or quality of recording media.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In Patent document No. 2, there is disclosed a technology wherein a pressing roll with a small diameter for restricting curling is pushed towards a heat roll to transfer the recording medium along the guide face of the curling restriction member. Further, it is disclosed in the Patent document No. 2 a technology wherein a position of the curling restriction member is optimized by detecting a recording medium pressure. In these technologies, there is a fear that decurling is not surely done because the recording medium is in an open state during the transfer by the curling restriction member. Since the recording medium should be withdrawn at a speed slightly faster than a speed of the fixing roll after transfer from the fixing roll for the purpose of decurling. It should be difficult to do in the technology disclosed in Patent document No. 2.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Further, in Patent document No. 3, a decurler comprising a transfer roll and a pressing member to be pressured towards the transfer roller; curling is removed of the recording medium by utilizing the contact face between the transfer roller and the decurler. The traveling speed of the recording medium, i.e. a rotating speed of a nip portion between the transfer roller and the decurler must be larger than the speed of the recording medium at the fixing roller; it is considered to be difficult to increase the speeds of the transfer roller and the decurler, because the contact resistance in the contact face between the transfer roller and the decurler is large.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Patent document No. 1; Japanese patent laid-open 2000-352887</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Patent document No. 2; Japanese patent laid-open 10-228198</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Patent document No. 3; Japanese patent laid-open 2003-295657</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">It is an object of the present invention to provide a fixing device that is capable of surely removing curling of the recording medium after a fixing step in accordance with qualities of various recording media and also to provide an image forming apparatus using the fixing device.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present invention provides a fixing device comprising first fixing means having a heating member therein, second fixing means, disposed in an opposite relation to the first fixing means, for forming a first nip portion by pinching a recording medium, a pair of transfer rollers, disposed downstream of the recording medium, for forming a second nip portion, a guide for biasing the recording medium discharged from the transfer rollers towards the first fixing means, and means for biasing the guide towards the recording medium side.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side cross sectional view of a diagram of a fixing device according to an embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a structure of a decurl roller and a decurl guide of a fixing device according to an embodiment; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>) is a plan view of a divided roller and a decurl guide, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>b</i>) a plan view of a roller that is opposite to the divided roller to form a second nip portion.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view showing a detailed structure the decurl guide of the fixing device according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a side cross sectional view showing that a thick recording medium passes through the fixing device according to the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an image forming apparatus using the fixing device according to the first embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Reference numerals in the drawings are:</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><b>1</b>; an image forming apparatus, <b>2</b>; an intermediate transfer belt, <b>3</b>; a photosensitive belt, <b>4</b>; a driving roller, <b>5</b>; a driving motor, <b>7</b>; a photosensitive member side roller, <b>8</b>; a motor driver, <b>9</b>; a calculating means, <b>10</b>; a recording medium cassette, <b>15</b>; a developing unit, <b>16</b>; a retract means, <b>18</b>; fur brush, <b>19</b>; a developing roller, <b>21</b>; a sensor, <b>22</b>; a transfer side roller, <b>23</b>; an intermediate tension belt roller, <b>24</b>; an intermediate transfer belt, <b>30</b>; a fixing device, <b>31</b>; a heat roller, <b>32</b>; a heating member, <b>33</b>; a fixing belt, <b>34</b>; a first pad, <b>35</b>; a first pad pressure spring, <b>36</b>; a pressure stay, <b>37</b>; a second pad, <b>38</b>; a pressure roller, <b>41</b>; a decurl guide, <b>44</b>; a non-image side decurl roller, <b>45</b>; an image forming side decurl guide, <b>151</b>, <b>152</b>, <b>153</b>, <b>154</b>; developing units.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The transfer rollers of the fixing device according to the present invention transfer the recording medium and perform necessary decurling at the same time.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Further, the fixing device may be provided with means for adjusting a biasing angle of the guide. Further, the fixing device may be provided with means for adjusting a biasing angle of the guide by detecting a thickness or a weight of the recording medium. The fixing device may be provided with means for adjusting a position of the second nip portion, formed by the pair of the transfer rollers, with respect to the first nip portion. The second nip portion is preferably located at a position closer to the first fixing device than is the first nip portion.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The present invention provides a fixing device comprises a heat roller having a heating element therein and driven rotatably, a belt pressed by a pressure member towards the heat roller, an image forming side decurl roller, a non-image side decurl roller, the decurl rollers being disposed to oppose to each other at a position downstream of the first nip portion formed by the heat roller and the belt, and a decurl guide, disposed at a position downstream of the second nip portion, formed by the image forming side decurl roller and the non-image forming side decurl roller, for guiding the direction of transfer of the recording medium, whereby the recording medium is wound around the image forming side decurl roller.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The decurl guide is supported to be capable of inclining towards the heat roller, wherein the decurl guide in inclined to wind the recording medium around the decurl roller. The image forming side decurl roller has an approximately constant diameter in the direction of the image and the surface of the decurl guide has fluorine-resin layer.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The present invention also provides an image forming apparatus comprising:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0025">means for forming an electrostatic latent image;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0026">means for developing the electrostatic latent image;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0003" num="0027">means for transferring the developed image to a recording medium; and</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0004" num="0028">a fixing device for fixing the transferred image, which comprises first fixing means enclosing heating means therein; second fixing means, disposed in opposite relation to the first fixing means, for forming a first nip portion; a pair of transferring rollers, disposed downstream of the recording medium, for forming a second nip portion; a guide for biasing the recording medium discharged from the transfer rolls towards the first fixing means from the backward of one of the transferring rollers; and means for biasing the guide towards the recording medium.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0029">In the image forming apparatus, it is preferable to provide means for adjusting the biasing angle of the guide to the image forming apparatus. Further, it is preferable to adjust the biasing angle by detecting a thickness or a weight of the recording medium. A position of the second nip portion formed by the pair of the transfer rollers with respect to the first nip portion is adjusted. The second nip portion is preferably closer to the first fixing device than is the first nip portion.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0030">The present invention also provides a fixing device comprising a heat roller rotatably driven and having a heating member therein, a belt pressed towards the heat roller by a pressing member, an image forming side decurl roller, and a non-image forming side decurl roller, wherein the image forming side decurl roller and the non-image forming side decurl roller are disposed downstream of the nip portion formed by the heat roller and the belt, and a decurl guide for guiding the direction of winding the recording medium, wherein the decurl guide guids the recording medium to wind it around the image surface side decurl roller.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0031">The present invention provides an image forming apparatus, which is capable of removing curling sufficiently under such a condition that a water content of recording medium such as paper is high so that curling is remarkable. And the fixing device of the invention brings about less clogging. Preferred embodiments of the present invention;</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Embodiment 1</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a fixing device of one embodiment according to the present invention. The fixing device <b>30</b> comprises a heat roller <b>31</b> having an elastic layer on the surface thereof and a fixing belt which is a thin-endless belt <b>33</b> made of such as polyimide, etc. The heat roller <b>31</b> rotates by receiving a driving force, and is heated by a heating member <b>32</b> disposed in the heat roller <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0033">The fixing belt <b>33</b> is pressed towards the heat roller <b>31</b> by the first pad <b>34</b>, second pad <b>37</b> and pressing roller <b>38</b> to form a first nip. The first pad <b>34</b> is disposed to a pressing stay <b>36</b> by means of a pressing spring <b>35</b> for the first pad <b>34</b>, and a second pad <b>37</b> is disposed to the pressing stay <b>36</b>. The pressing stay <b>36</b> is pressed towards the heat roller <b>31</b> side by means of a heating mechanism (not shown). The pressing roller <b>38</b> is pressed towards the heat roller <b>31</b> side by means of a pressing mechanism (not shown). The toner image on the recording paper is fixed by fusion with heat and pressure at the first nip formed by the heat roller <b>31</b> and the fixing belt <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0034">A decurl guide <b>41</b> is supported being able to incline and is pressed towards an A direction in the center by means of a pressing spring <b>43</b> for the decurl guide. A non-image side decurl guide roller <b>44</b> rotates by the driving force from a driving means.</p>
<p id="h-0008" num="0000">The image side decurl roller <b>45</b> is pressed towards the non-image side decurl roller <b>44</b> by means of a pressing means (not shown) to rotate invertedly thereby to form a second nip portion.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0035">A transfer speed of the recording paper of the non-image side decurl roller <b>44</b> is set to be 5 to 15% higher than the recording paper transfer speed of the heat roller <b>31</b>. If the transfer speed of the recording paper of the non-image side decurl roller <b>44</b> is slower than the recording paper transfer speed of the heat roller <b>31</b>, the recording paper may loose between the first nip portion and the second nip portion so that the image contacts the heat roller again, which leads to a hot off-set or coiling.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0036">When the tip portion of the recording paper comes into the second nip portion, wherein the tip portion of the recording paper first comes into contact with one of the decurl rollers, the tip of the recording paper becomes to have an angle with respect to a tangential line of the decurl roller. As a result, an effective speed of the recording paper transfer becomes lower than that of the speed in the tangential direction. Therefore, even if the speed of the non-image side decurl roller <b>44</b> is the same as that of the heat roller <b>31</b>, loosing of the recording paper takes place between the nip portions.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> show an arrangement of the decurl roller and decurl guide of the fixing device, wherein <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a plan view thereof and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view. The non-image side decurl rollers <b>44</b> are arranged in the axial direction, and decurl guides <b>41</b> enter between the rolls. The guides between the divided rollers protrude until the vicinity of the second nip portion so that the recording paper is pressed towards the image side decurl roller <b>45</b> just after the second nip portion. Crook of the recording paper becomes large to increase decurl effect. The image side decurl roller <b>44</b> is covered with a fluorine-resin, which is good in peeling effect. The stain is hard to adhere to the roller and the recording paper is not blotted.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0038">The tip of the recording paper that has passed through the nip portion is guided to the first guide <b>39</b> and the second guide <b>40</b>, and then is pinched between the non-image side decurl roller <b>44</b> and the image side transfer roller <b>45</b> (this is the decurl roller, too), thereby to transfer out it from the fixing device. The recording paper is crooked in the direction (the arrow B direction in the figure) for winding around the image side decurl roller <b>45</b> by means of the decurl roller <b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0039">Curling of the recording paper takes place towards the belt side whose temperature is low so that the recording paper is bent in the arrow direction B in the figure to remove curling. Since the recording paper that has been heated has a high temperature and is easy to reform, the decurl effect is remarkable.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0040">Further, since the recording paper is crooked just after the nip between the non-image side decurl roller <b>44</b> and the image side decurl roller <b>45</b>, the recording paper does not bring about buckling at the time that the recording paper hits the decurl roller <b>41</b>; clogging of the recording paper is hard to take place. As a result, even if the recording paper is strongly crooked by the decurl guide <b>41</b>, the clogging of the recording paper does not occur. Therefore, it is possible to remove curling even in the case of the recording paper whose curling in a circumstance is remarkable.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0041">On the other hand, if the position of the decurl guide <b>41</b> is inclined more towards the arrow direction B so as to increase an effect of decurling, the curling towards the image side may increase in the case of thick recording paper (weighing: 150g/m<sup>2 </sup>or more).</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a mechanism of the decurl guide <b>41</b> at the time when a thick recording paper (weighing: 150 g/cm<sup>2 </sup>or more) is supplied to the fixing device according to the present embodiment. The decurl guide <b>41</b> is supported to be able to incline, and the guide <b>41</b> is pressed towards the arrow A direction in the figure by means of the pressing spring <b>43</b>; the decurl guide <b>41</b> is inclined towards the arrow C direction in the figure by the effect of the stiffness of the thick recording paper to lessen the winding angle in the image side decurl roller <b>45</b> so that curling in the image side does not increase. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a side elevational view of an image forming apparatus <b>1</b> that utilizes the fixing device according to the present embodiment. In this apparatus, an intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b> is rotated 4 times so as to impose four colors of images to produce color images, which is a so-called a color laser printer.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0043">In the following, units arranged in the apparatus <b>1</b> are explained. A photosensitive belt <b>3</b> is moved to the arrow direction a by means of a driving roller <b>4</b>, which is driven by a driving motor <b>5</b> through a motor driving system <b>6</b>. The intermediate belt <b>2</b> is driven by a transfer force of the nip portion n that is in contact with the photosensitive belt <b>3</b>. The photosensitive belt <b>4</b> comprises a base member made of polycarbonate resin, polyethyrene terephthalate or polyimide resin, a conductive layer and a photosensitive layer. A thickness of the photosensitive layer is preferably 0.075 to 0.15 mm. The intermediate belt <b>2</b> is a seamless belt made of polycarbonate, polyethyrene terephthalate or polyimide resin, is given semiconductivity and has a volume resistivity of <b>108</b> to loll Q cm. Its thickness is preferably 0.075 to 0.15 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0044">The intermediate belt <b>2</b> is hung over the photosensitive member side roller <b>7</b> and the transfer side roller <b>22</b>, and the photosensitive belt <b>3</b> is wound around the photosensitive member side roller <b>7</b> by means of the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b>. The photosensitive member side roller <b>7</b> has a large diameter and a nip width with the photosensitive belt is made 20 mm or more. The transfer side roller <b>22</b> has a smaller diameter than that of the transfer side roller <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0045">The intermediate transfer belt tension roller <b>23</b> is means for imparting tension to the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b>, wherein the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b> is pushed by means of a spring, etc. The driving motor <b>5</b> is controlled by a motor driver so as to maintain a constant speed of the motor <b>5</b>. The intermediate belt <b>2</b> has a marker by which a sensor <b>21</b> can detect its passage. The signal is read out by a calculating means <b>9</b> to give the motor driver <b>8</b> an instruction so as to transfer the intermediate transfer belt at a constant speed.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0046">A developing unit <b>15</b> as an image forming means stores toner and forms a thin toner layer on the surface of the developing roller <b>19</b>. When a toner image is formed on the photosensitive belt <b>3</b>, a retract means <b>16</b> is rotated in the direction of an arrow d to advance the developing unit <b>15</b> in the direction e and the developing roller <b>19</b> is brought into contact with the photosensitive belt <b>3</b>. After image forming, the retract means <b>16</b> is rotated in the arrow direction d to separate the developing unit <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0047">A fur brush <b>18</b> for eliminating means makes a contact with the intermediate transfer belt to remove remaining toner thereon after the toner image is transferred to the recording paper by means of the retract means (not shown), and then separates. The transfer roller <b>13</b> as the transfer means presses the recording paper towards the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b> in the transfer step by means of the retracting means (not shown) and after the recording paper passes through the transfer roller <b>13</b>, the transfer roller separates.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0048">A recording paper storing cassette <b>10</b> is placed almost horizontally with respect to the plane where the apparatus is placed at the lower position of the apparatus. The recording paper cassette <b>10</b>, a pickup roller <b>11</b>, a resist roller <b>12</b>, a transfer roller <b>13</b> and a fixer <b>30</b> are arranged on the recording paper transfer passage c. The recording paper transfer passage c, the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b>, the photosensitive belt <b>3</b> and the developing unit <b>15</b> are arranged in order. Next, the image forming process is explained. When an image is formed, the photosensitive layer of the photosensitive belt is charged with the fur brush <b>20</b>. Then, laser light in accordance with images is directed to the photosensitive layer from a laser optical unit <b>17</b> to remove a potential. A developing roller <b>19</b> while rotating is brought into contact with the photosensitive belt <b>3</b> to form a toner image according to the image on the photosensitive belt <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0049">In this example, a rotating direction of the developing roller is in a g direction, which is the same direction as that of the photosensitive belt, so as to form homogeneous toner images. A circumferential speed of the developing roller is set to be higher than that of the photosensitive belt <b>3</b>. The toner image on the photosensitive belt <b>3</b> is transferred temporarily to the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b>. In a color laser printer, there are four colors developing units <b>151</b>, <b>152</b>, <b>153</b> and <b>154</b> of black, yellow, magenta and cyan; each of the mono color images formed on the photosensitive belt <b>3</b> is superimposed on the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b> to produce a color image.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0050">The recording paper stored in the recording paper cassette <b>10</b> is sent page-by-page by means of a pickup roller <b>11</b> and skew is corrected by means of a resist roller <b>12</b>. Before the tip of recording paper arrives at the position between the transfer roller <b>3</b> and the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b>, the transfer roller <b>13</b> is pressed towards the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b> by means of the retract means (not shown) and the recording paper is pressed towards the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b>. At the same time, a high potential is applied to the transfer roller <b>13</b> and the toner image on the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b> is transferred to the recording paper. Thereafter, the recording paper arrives at the fixing device <b>30</b> so that the toner image on the paper is fixed by heat and pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0051">Remaining images on the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b> after image transfer is removed by contacting the fur brush <b>18</b> with the intermediate transfer belt <b>2</b>, while the brush is rotating. In order to increase the removal performance of images, the rotating direction shown by an arrow f of the fur brush is set to be opposite to the rotating direction of the intermediate transfer belt in this example.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0052">In the image forming apparatus according to this example, it is possible to sufficiently remove curling and there is little of possibility of paper clogging, even when a water content is high, which leads to a remarkable curling. Further, since decurl performance appropriately changes in accordance with stiffness of paper, it is possible to remove curling of from thin paper to thick paper.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0053">One of the examples of an image forming apparatus comprises a heat roller having a heating member, which is driven and rotated, a belt pressed towards the heat roller by means of a pressing member, an image side decurl roller and a non-image side decurl roller, the decurl rollers being disposed in opposite relation at a downstream of a nip portion formed by the heat roller and the belt. A decurl guide is disposed at a downstream of a nip portion formed by the decurl rollers, the decurl guide guiding the transfer direction of the recording paper so as to wind it around the image side decurl roller, thereby to remove curling.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0054">In the above examples, although there are shown the heat roller as the first fixing roller and the belt as the second fixing means, it may be possible to utilize other embodiments within the spirit of the present invention. For example, the first fixing means may be a roller having a heating member therein and the second fixing means may be a roller having no heating member. The first fixing means may be a belt having a heating member therein.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A fixing device comprising a first fixing means having a heating means disposed therein, a second fixing means, disposed to oppose to the first fixing means, for pinching a recording medium to form a first nip portion, a pair of transfer rollers, disposed at a downstream side of the recording medium with regard to a conveying direction of the recording medium, for forming a second nip portion, a guide for biasing the recording medium discharged from the transfer rollers towards the first fixing means side from one of the transfer rollers, means for biasing the guide towards the recording medium side, and means for adjusting a biasing angle of the guide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The fixing device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the means for adjusting the biasing angle of the guide detects a weight or a thickness of the recording medium.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The fixing medium according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, which further comprises means for adjusting a position of the second nip portion, formed by the pair of transfer rollers, with respect to the first nip portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The fixing device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the second nip portion is located at a position closer to the first fixing means than the first nip portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A fixing device comprises a heat roller having a heating element therein and driven rotatably, a belt pressed by a pressure member towards the heat roller, an image forming side decurl roller, a non-image side decurl roller, the decurl rollers being disposed to oppose to each other at a position downstream from a first nip portion formed by the heat roller and the belt, and a decurl guide, disposed at a position downstream of a second nip portion, formed by the image forming side decurl roller and the non-image forming side decurl roller, for guiding the direction of transfer of the recording medium, whereby the recording medium is wound around the image forming side decurl roller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The fixing device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the decurl guide is supported to be capable of being so inclined as to wind on the image forming side decurl roller with respect to the heat roller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The fixing device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the image forming side decurl roller has a constant diameter in a direction of a width of the image and has a fluorine-resin layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An image forming apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>means for forming a electrostatic latent image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for developing the electrostatic latent image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transferring the developed image to a recording medium; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixing device for fixing the transferred image, which comprises first fixing means enclosing heating means therein; second fixing means, disposed in opposite position to the first fixing means, for forming a first nip portion; a pair of transferring rollers, disposed downstream of the recording medium with regard to a conveying direction of the recording medium, for forming a second nip portion; a guide for biasing the recording medium discharged from the transfer rolls towards the first fixing means from the backward of one of the transferring rolls; means for biasing the guide towards the recording medium, and means for adjusting a biasing angle of the guide.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The image forming apparatus to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, the means for adjusting the angle of the guide detects a weight or a thickness of the recording medium.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, which further comprises means for adjusting a position of the first nip portion formed by the pair of the transferring rollers with respect to the position of the first nip portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the second nip portion is located at a position closer to the first fixing means side than is the first nip portion.                                                                     </claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
