<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296845-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296845</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11038808</doc-number>
<date>20050119</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>141</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>62</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>62</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>10</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2961466</main-classification>
<further-classification>29619311</further-classification>
<further-classification>180 6921</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Combined palm-latch reinforcement for closure panels</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5535841</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cobes, Jr. et al.</name>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180 692</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5538094</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cobes, Jr. et al.</name>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180 692</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5833024</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kaneko</name>
<date>19981100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180 692</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6247744</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Townsend et al.</name>
<date>20010600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>29614611</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6394211</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Palenchar et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180 6921</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6450276</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Latcau</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180 684</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6502653</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Balzer et al.</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180 684</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6692057</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Igarashi et al.</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>29619311</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>296191</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>296202</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2961466</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 692</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 6921</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 6912</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 684</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060158007</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060720</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Seksaria</last-name>
<first-name>Dinesh C.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Novi</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sokol</last-name>
<first-name>Richard A.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Harrison City</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Long</last-name>
<first-name>Russell S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Murrysville</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Greenberg Traurig LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Borghetti</last-name>
<first-name>Peter J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Alcoa Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Pittsburgh</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Pedder</last-name>
<first-name>Dennis H.</first-name>
<department>3612</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Black</last-name>
<first-name>Melissa A</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A reinforcement for a closure panel including an outer panel and an inner panel includes a palm area reinforcement for attachment to the outer panel and a latch area reinforcement for attachment to the inner panel, the latch area reinforcement being disposed on a depression in the reinforcement which is integral with the palm area reinforcement.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="146.30mm" wi="338.07mm" file="US07296845-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="149.78mm" wi="166.71mm" file="US07296845-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="233.60mm" wi="169.76mm" file="US07296845-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="191.52mm" wi="132.84mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296845-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="132.25mm" wi="158.41mm" file="US07296845-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="181.36mm" wi="180.59mm" file="US07296845-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="256.46mm" wi="160.36mm" file="US07296845-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to structural aspects of hoods, deck lids and other closure panels, and, in particular, relates to reinforcement of hoods and deck lids for motor vehicles.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Closure panels such as hoods and deck lids of motor vehicles generally include an inner panel and an outer panel. The inner and outer panels are connected to each other at various locations so they cooperate to provide a structure which is more rigid than either panel separately, and which has a stiffness which is much greater than the sum of the separate stiffnesses of the panels. For hoods and deck lids, the outer panel lies above the inner panel and is part of the exterior of the vehicle. The inner panel is only visible when the hood or deck lid is open.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Typically, when a closure panel is manufactured, the inner and outer panels are formed separately. The exact shape of the outer panel is defined by the desired form of the vehicle. The inner panel is designed to mate with the outer panel. For example, there may be truncated cones formed on the inner panel. Adhesive is placed on the truncated surfaces of these cones and then the outer panel is placed over the inner panel, so the truncated surfaces of the cones are adhered to the outer panel. The perimeters of the inner and outer panels are then joined in a hemming operation. In this operation, the edge of the outer panel is bent around the edge of the inner panel.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The closure panel is generally secured in a closed position by a latch on the vehicle which engages a latch engagement member on the closure panel. The latch is on the frame or other portion of the vehicle which is not part of the closure panel. The latch engagement member may be a striker plate, or a loop of metal which is referred to as a wire loop. Generally, the latch engagement member is at the end of the closure panel which is farthest from the hinges which attach the closure panel to the vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The latch engagement member for a hood, deck lid or other closure panel is typically located on the inner panel. The latch area of the inner panel, where the latch engagement member is attached, may experience high forces due to wind loads, inertial forces, or closure forces. Also, the outer panel, in the vicinity of the latch area of the inner panel, may experience large forces due to persons pressing on the outer panel to close the hood, deck lid or other closure panel, and engage the latch. If it is not sufficiently stiff, this area may deform when it is pressed to close the panel.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">It is known in the art to attach various reinforcement members to the inner panel and the outer panel to withstand these forces. In the most common arrangement, a palm area reinforcement is attached to the outer panel. For a hood or deck lid, the palm area reinforcement is attached to the underside of the outer panel. For a hood, the palm area reinforcement is attached to the outer panel at its front end. For a deck lid, the palm area reinforcement is attached at the rear end of the outer panel.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Also, for a hood or deck lid, a latch area reinforcement is usually attached to an upper surface of the inner panel. The latch area reinforcement provides added strength and stiffness to the portion of the inner panel adjacent the latch engagement member. For a hood, it is attached to the front end of the inner panel, for a deck lid, it is attached at the rear end of the inner panel.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a sketch of a prior art reinforcement assembly <b>10</b> which provides reinforcement for both the palm area and the latch area. The reinforcement assembly <b>10</b> is shown inverted in order to show details.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Reinforcement assembly <b>10</b> includes a palm area reinforcement <b>12</b> which, during assembly of the closure panel, is adhesively bonded to the palm area of the outer panel. Palm area reinforcement <b>12</b> may have grooves <b>14</b> and <b>15</b> to provide increased rigidity. Grooves <b>14</b> and <b>15</b> appear as ridges in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> because reinforcement assembly <b>10</b> is shown inverted.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Reinforcement assembly <b>10</b> also includes a latch area reinforcement <b>16</b> which is assembled to the palm area reinforcement <b>12</b> at <b>18</b> and <b>19</b>. Latch area reinforcement <b>16</b> has an opening <b>17</b> which is to be aligned with an opening on the inner panel (not shown in this figure) where the latch engagement member is mounted.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">During assembly of the hood or deck lid, the assembly <b>10</b> is inverted and the latch area reinforcement <b>16</b> is attached to the inner panel, positioned so that opening <b>17</b> is aligned with the latch opening in the inner panel. Adhesive is then placed on the palm area reinforcement <b>12</b> on the side <b>11</b> which is opposite the side shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Then, when the outer panel is put in place, the palm area of the hood or deck lid is pressed down onto the surface <b>11</b> of the palm area reinforcement <b>12</b> of the reinforcement assembly <b>10</b>. Typically, the adhesive on the reinforcement assembly <b>10</b> is a thermosetting adhesive. When the paint bake operation is subsequently performed on the hood or deck lid, the adhesive is cured.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In addition to the art cited above, which is standard practice in the motor vehicle industry, a number of patents relate to reinforcement in the palm and latch areas of closure panels.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">U.S. Pat. No. 5,538,094 and the related patent, U.S. Pat. No. 5,535,841, teach a reinforcement member attached to both the inner and outer panels in the latch area of a car hood. The reinforcement member is elongate and has a C-shaped cross section. It is mounted transversely relative to the hood. The C-shaped member is made of a lightweight material such as aluminum or plastic.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The C-shaped member encloses a plate made of a strong material such as steel. The steel plate has a flanged hole, and the hood is secured in a closed position by a latch member which passes through the flanged hole, and engages the flange. The steel flange resists wear.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">U.S. Pat. No. 6,247,744 teaches sub assemblies having self-aligning members for hinges and latches of vehicle doors, hoods or trunks. The sub assemblies may be used with vehicle hoods, trunks, liftgates and deck lids. They serve to integrate the closure member with the vehicle body.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">U.S. Pat. No. 6,394,211 teaches a latch system for a hood and fender assembly on a truck.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">U.S. Pat. No. 6,450,276 provides an illustration of the typical mounting of a hood latch on a front end assembly of a motor vehicle.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">INTRODUCTION TO THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The present invention is for closure panels, particularly for hoods and deck lids of motor vehicles. It is for closure panels comprised of an outer panel and an inner panel. The invention provides reinforcement in the latch area on the inner panel. The latch which secures the panel in a closed position engages a latch engagement member attached to the latch area on the inner panel. The latch, itself, is generally connected to the frame or other portion of the vehicle, which is not a part of the panel. The latch area reinforcement stiffens the inner panel in the latch area, and distributes the latch loads to the inner panel.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The invention also provides palm area reinforcement. It reinforces the outer panel in the palm area, which is the region adjacent the latch area on the inner panel. It is to resist forces due to a person pressing on the panel to close it. For the hood of a motor vehicle, it is the front end of the hood. For a deck lid of a motor vehicle, it is at the rear of the lid.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">One objective of the present invention is to provide a single element which provides reinforcement in the palm area and also reinforcement in the latch area of a closure panel such as a hood or deck lid.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Another objective is to provide a combined palm area and latch area reinforcement which is an integral unit which does not itself require assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Another objective of the present invention is to provide a palm-latch reinforcement which can be made from sheet metal by punching and stamping operations.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In one aspect, the present invention is a reinforcement for a closure panel including an outer panel and an inner panel. The inner panel includes a latch area and the outer panel includes a palm area adjacent the latch area of the inner panel. The reinforcement includes a palm area reinforcement, the palm area reinforcement being for attachment to the palm area of the outer panel. There is also a depression integral with the palm area reinforcement, the depression including an integral latch area reinforcement which is for attachment to the latch area of the inner panel.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In another aspect, the present invention is a closure panel for a motor vehicle, the closure panel including an inner panel and an outer panel, the inner panel including a latch area, the outer panel including a palm area adjacent the latch area of the inner panel. The closure panel further includes a reinforcement including a palm area reinforcement attached to the palm area of the outer panel, the reinforcement further including a depression integral with the palm area reinforcement, the depression including an integral latch area reinforcement attached to the latch area of the inner panel.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In an additional aspect, the present invention is a method of making an integral palm-latch reinforcement. The method includes stamping a sheet of metal to form a palm area reinforcement, and a depression integral with the palm area reinforcement, the depression including an integral latch area reinforcement.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In a further aspect, the present invention is a method of making a closure panel for a motor vehicle. The method includes stamping a first sheet of metal to make an outer panel for the closure panel, the outer panel being configured in accordance with the exterior design of the motor vehicle. A second sheet of metal is also stamped to make an inner panel for the closure panel, the inner panel including a plurality of raised portions for attachment to the outer panel. A third sheet of metal is also stamped to make an integral palm-latch reinforcement. The method further includes attaching the palm-latch reinforcement to the inner panel, placing adhesive on a palm area reinforcement portion of the integral palm-latch reinforcement, placing adhesive on the plurality of raised portions of the inner panel, placing the outer panel over the inner panel and the integral palm-latch reinforcement, hemming a perimeter of the closure panel, and causing the adhesive on the palm-latch reinforcement portion of the integral palm-latch reinforcement and the adhesive on the raised portions of the inner panel to set.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective sketch of a prior art reinforcement assembly including a palm area reinforcement and a latch area reinforcement.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective sketch of a combined palm-latch reinforcement according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an end view of the palm-latch reinforcement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective sketch of a typical inner panel of a hood for a motor vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a perspective sketch of a palm-latch reinforcement according to the present invention, after it has been assembled to the inner panel illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a top view of the assembly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a sketch illustrating a median section cut through a motor vehicle hood after the palm-latch reinforcement has been attached to the inner panel, and the outer panel has been attached to both.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates an alternative embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates another alternative embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In this description of the invention, terms denoting direction including upper, depression, raised, front, rear, etc. relate to the invention applied to a hood of a motor vehicle. When applied to other closure panels, directional terms would be changed appropriately.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> illustrate a palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> according to the present invention. Palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> may be made by punching and stamping a sheet metal blank. Palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> includes a palm area reinforcement <b>22</b> having inner portions <b>23</b> and <b>25</b>. Reinforcement <b>20</b> includes a depression <b>28</b> having a latch area reinforcement <b>26</b> at a bottom portion of depression <b>28</b>. Latch area reinforcement <b>26</b> includes an opening <b>27</b> which is for the latch.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Preferably, the palm area reinforcement <b>22</b> includes a transverse groove <b>24</b> including a groove center portion <b>29</b>. The transverse groove <b>24</b> including groove center portion <b>29</b> serves to stiffen the palm area reinforcement <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective sketch showing one half of an inner panel <b>30</b> for a hood of a motor vehicle. Inner panel <b>30</b> has rear end <b>32</b> and front end <b>34</b>. Inner panel <b>30</b> has a latch area, <b>36</b>, and the outline of opening <b>38</b> is sketched. Opening <b>38</b> is for receiving the latch (not shown). Inner panel <b>30</b> may include truncated cones <b>40</b> including truncated surfaces <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Rear surface <b>44</b> is for attachment of the inner back portion <b>23</b> of the combined palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b>. Front surface <b>46</b> is for attachment of the inner front portion <b>25</b> of the combined palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b>. When the combined palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> is assembled to the inner panel <b>30</b>, the latch area reinforcement <b>26</b> of the palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> is in contact with latch area <b>36</b>. Opening <b>27</b> in latch area reinforcement <b>26</b> is aligned with opening <b>38</b> in latch area <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates the palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> assembled to the inner panel <b>30</b>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a top view of this assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a median section of the hood <b>80</b> of a motor vehicle. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows inner panel <b>30</b> having rear surface <b>44</b>, latch area <b>36</b>, and front surface <b>46</b>. The inner panel <b>30</b> has overlaid thereon the combined palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> having inner back portion <b>23</b>, center portion of stiffening groove <b>29</b>, depression <b>28</b> including latch area reinforcement <b>26</b> and inner front portion <b>25</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">After the inner panel <b>30</b> and combined palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> are assembled, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>, the outer panel <b>70</b> is placed over the assembly. Preferably, outer panel <b>70</b> is attached by adhesive placed on portions of the inner panel <b>30</b> such as the truncated surfaces <b>42</b> of cones <b>40</b> and the palm area <b>22</b> of the palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b> which contacts the outer panel <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The inner panel <b>30</b> and outer panel <b>70</b> are also joined by a hemming operation in which the edge of the outer panel <b>70</b> is bent around the edge of the inner panel to form a hemmed edge <b>82</b>. The front end of the hood <b>80</b> is denoted <b>84</b>. In a typical process, a paint bake operation follows the assembly of the inner panel <b>30</b>, palm latch reinforcement <b>20</b> and outer panel <b>70</b>. During the paint bake operation, the adhesive joining inner panel <b>30</b>, palm latch reinforcement <b>20</b> and outer panel <b>70</b> is set.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a sketch of an alternative embodiment of the present invention. Combined palm-latch reinforcement <b>50</b> includes a palm area reinforcement <b>52</b> and a depression <b>58</b> including an oval latch area reinforcement <b>56</b>. This is in contrast to the latch area reinforcement <b>26</b> of the palm-latch reinforcement, which is shaped as a rectangle with rounded corners, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Furthermore, the palm-latch reinforcement <b>50</b> has stiffening grooves <b>54</b>, which do not cross the central region, as did the stiffening groove <b>24</b> having center portion <b>29</b> in the palm-latch reinforcement <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates another embodiment <b>60</b> including stiffening grooves <b>64</b> and also additional stiffening grooves <b>65</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The present invention has been described in reference to a hood of a motor vehicle. Of necessity, the hood shown had a particular shape, which dictated the particular shape of the embodiments shown. The invention is also applicable to vehicle hoods having different configurations, as well as to deck lids and other closure panels. The scope of the invention is best established by reference to the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A combined palm-latch reinforcement for a closure panel, the reinforcement comprising:
<claim-text>a single piece of sheet metal blank having two substantially planar sections and a center section therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the two substantially planar sections include at least one stiffening member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the center section includes a depression formed therein that defines a top portion and a bottom portion being spaced apart by at least three side abutting walls therebetween, wherein the bottom portion includes an opening adapted for receiving a latch,</claim-text>
<claim-text>whereby, the reinforcement is an integral unit which does not require separate assembly of the two substantially planar sections and the center section to each other to form the reinforcement.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The reinforcement, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the reinforcement is comprised of stamped and punched sheet metal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The reinforcement, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one stiffening groove includes at least two stiffening grooves.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The reinforcement, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the bottom portion is shaped as a rectangle with rounded corners.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The reinforcement, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the bottom portion is shaped as an oval.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The reinforcement, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the top portion includes at least one inner back portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The reinforcement, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the top portion includes at least one inner front portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The reinforcement, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the top portion includes at least one inner back portion and at least one inner front portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A closure panel for a motor vehicle, the closure panel comprising: an inner panel, the inner panel including a latch area; an outer panel, the outer panel including a palm area adjacent the latch area of said inner panel; a reinforcement being disposed between the outer panel and the inner panel; the reinforcement being a single piece of sheet metal blank having two substantially planar sections and a center section therebetween, wherein each of the two substantialy planar sections include at least one stiffening member, wherein the center section includes a depression formed therein that defines a top portion and a bottom portion spaced apart by at least three side abutting walls therebetween, wherein the bottom portion includes an opening adapted for receiving a latch.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The closure panel, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the two substantially planar sections and the top portion are attached by an adhesive to the palm area of the outer panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The closure panel, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the outer panel is joined to the inner panel by adhesives placed at various positions on the inner panel, and by a hem around a perimeter of the closure panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The closure panel, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the closure panel is a hood for a motor vehicle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The reinforcement according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one inner back portion is substantially parallel with and directly adjacent to the two substantially planar sections.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The reinforcement according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one inner front portion is substantially parallel with and directly adjacent to the two substantially planar sections.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The reinforcement according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one inner back portion and the at least one inner front portion are substantially parallel with and directly adjacent to the two substantially planar sections.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The reinforcement according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the center section includes at least one stiffening member.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
