<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298245-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298245</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11260040</doc-number>
<date>20051026</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>260</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>08</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340331</main-classification>
<further-classification>340321</further-classification>
<further-classification>340458</further-classification>
<further-classification>3408154</further-classification>
<further-classification>34081545</further-classification>
<further-classification>362 72</further-classification>
<further-classification>362240</further-classification>
<further-classification>362500</further-classification>
<further-classification>362546</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Emergency light</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4613847</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Scolari et al.</name>
<date>19860900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340473</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6265984</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Molinaroli</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3408154</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6953260</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Allen</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362194</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7158020</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Grady, Jr.</name>
<date>20070100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340473</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340331</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340332</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340321</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340458</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3408154</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34081545</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362 72</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362157</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362240</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362251</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362362</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362500</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362545</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362546</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>VanHoose</last-name>
<first-name>Harold D.</first-name>
<address>
<street>3739 Winward Lakes Dr.</street>
<city>Tampa</city>
<state>FL</state>
<postcode>22611</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Thomson</last-name>
<first-name>Richard K</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Hung</first-name>
<department>2612</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An emergency light includes a flash light lamp and a plurality of LED lamps activated in strobe-like fashion to alert emergency personnel in transit the proper household needing their assistance. The LED lamps activated in excess of 120 times per minute is visible at distances in excess of one mile. The emergency light may be mounted to a window pane using suction cups, to a steel door or other ferrous-metallic surface using magnetic strips, hung on a door using an integral hanger or stood on a flat bottom surface.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="206.59mm" wi="122.68mm" file="US07298245-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="215.14mm" wi="124.71mm" file="US07298245-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="243.16mm" wi="115.49mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298245-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="230.55mm" wi="119.38mm" file="US07298245-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="176.45mm" wi="172.55mm" file="US07298245-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND AND SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention is directed to the field of emergency lighting. More particularly, the present invention is directed to a light that can be readily attached to a residence or vehicle to enable emergency medical and rescue teams to more easily identify the point of need.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In medical emergencies, seconds can literally mean the difference between life and death; between being able to restore a patient to full health and merely extending the quantity of life at the expense of quality. One of the most problematic issues for emergency medical personnel is identifying the residence where the patient is located following a 911 call. Locating the residence is particularly difficult at night when house numbers and distinguishing characteristics of the home are obscured.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present emergency light has a plurality of LED lamps which are connected in series to flash in strobe-like fashion at in excess of 120 times a minute. At night, the light can be detected from as far away as one mile enabling the emergency team to easily identify the residence, facilitating rapid access to and treatment of the patient. A plurality of mounting means are provided enabling the emergency light to 1) be secured to a window pane using suction cups attached to the front face of the light; 2) magnetically be attached to a steel door and to a portion of a motor vehicle using magnets on the rear of the light body; 3) hung over the top of a door or on a door handle using a hanger attached to an upper portion of the emergency light; and, 4) stood by means of a flat bottom on any available surface. The emergency light further has a flash light positioned on a second portion of the front face should existing conditions warrant.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Other features, advantages, and characteristics ofthe present invention will become apparent after a reading of the following detailed description of the preferred embodiments.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The preferred embodiment(s) of the present invention is/are described in conjunction with the associated drawings in which like features are indicated with like reference numerals and in which</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a front view of a first embodiment of the emergency light of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a side view of the first embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a rear view of the first embodiment and,</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic depiction of the electrical circuit used in the first embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT(S)</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A first embodiment of the emergency light of the present invention is depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref> generally at <b>20</b>. This light has a generally rectangular body <b>22</b> with a plurality of LED lamps <b>24</b> mounted on front face <b>26</b>. While ten lamps <b>24</b> have been depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, it will be appreciated that other numbers could be used without departing from the scope ofthe invention. In fact, a smaller version featuring only six lamps <b>24</b> (and four batteries) is contemplated for applications, such as automotive, requiring more compact lights <b>20</b>. A battery pack <b>30</b>, depicted here as comprising six AA batteries <b>11</b>, provide power to operate the emergency light <b>20</b>. Access to change the batteries will preferably be through a panel <b>29</b> in the rear face <b>28</b>. A plastic cover <b>25</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) is preferably transparent or translucent and may be tinted amber, red or blue.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A single white lamp <b>34</b> is positioned on a second portion of front face <b>26</b> and functions as a flashlight in case of a power outage or when used in vehicular applications. First mounting means in the form of clear suction cups <b>36</b> are secured to the front face. Suction cups <b>36</b> permit emergency light <b>20</b> to be secured to the inside of a window pane where it can be readily viewed from the street. A second mounting means in the form of a plurality (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> as two) magnetic plates <b>38</b> are secured to the rear face <b>28</b> of emergency light <b>20</b>. Magnetic plates <b>38</b> permit emergency light to be hung on a ferrous-metallic surface such as the front of a steel door or mounted on the roof or hood of a car. A third mounting means in the form of a hangar hook <b>40</b> is secured to the upper portion of body portion <b>22</b>. Hangar <b>40</b> permits the emergency light to be suspended on the front of a door by either securing it over the upper edge, as with a screen door, for example, or hung on a handle; in addition, hangar <b>40</b> can permit the emergency light <b>20</b> to be suspended beneath the hood of a car with the flashlight <b>34</b> illuminated as the owner attempts to remedy the “it's-not-running-right” blues. Finally the bottom <b>42</b> of the body portion <b>22</b> is preferably flat enabling the emergency light to stand on any flat surface should none of the remaining mounting techniques be adequate in a particular situation.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A schematic electrical diagram is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> generally at <b>50</b>. Battery pack <b>30</b> is wired by means of a first circuit <b>52</b> to LED lamps <b>24</b> and in parallel to flash light lamp <b>34</b> by a second circuit <b>54</b>. Both circuits <b>52</b> and <b>54</b> are connected to <b>3</b>-position switch <b>60</b> which is shown, by way of example and not limitation, as being positioned on the rear face <b>28</b> of body portion <b>22</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). Three position switch <b>60</b> includes a first off position; then a second position to illuminate LED lamps <b>24</b>, actuated on a rotating basis by flasher <b>55</b>; and, a third position for illuminating flash light lamp <b>34</b>. Flasher <b>55</b> causes LED lamps <b>24</b> to flash at a rate exceeding 120 per minute, by way of example, <b>142</b> times per minute, this strobe-like flashing calling attention to the home or vehicle where it is mounted.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">When 911 is called, the emergency team dispatcher can be informed that the emergency light <b>20</b> will be activated and clearly visible from the road. Then, while awaiting the team's arrival, emergency light <b>20</b> can be supported by whichever means desired to provide maximum visibility and permit ready identification of the household in need of attention. Alternatively, in the automotive application, both the flashlight lamp <b>34</b> and the LED lamps <b>24</b> can be of assistance to the owner of a disabled vehicle in identifying the problem and summoning assistance, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Various changes, alternatives and modifications will become apparent to one of ordinary skill in the art following a reading of the foregoing specification. By way of example, although 10 LED lamps are shown, one preferred embodiment having an overall length of only 5.5″, has only 8 lamps which are powered by a single 9v battery. It is intended that any such changes, alternatives and modifications as fall within the scope of the appended claims be considered part of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An emergency light comprising
<claim-text>a) a generally rectangular body portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b) a plurality of LED lamps connected in series on a portion of a front face of said body portion to flash strobe-as fashion in excess of a total of 120 times per minute;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c) a plastic cover enclosing said LED lamps;</claim-text>
<claim-text>d) a battery pack for powering said LED lamps;</claim-text>
<claim-text>e) first mounting means on said front surface for securing said emergency light to a window pane;</claim-text>
<claim-text>f) second mounting means for securing said emergency light to an alternative surface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The emergency light of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said plastic cover is made of a opaque material having a color selected from a group consisting of amber, red and blue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The emergency light of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said first mounting means comprises a plurality of suction cups attached to said front face of said body portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The emergency light of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a conventional white light mounted on a second portion of said front face operable as a flash light.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The emergency light of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said second mounting means comprises a plurality of magnets enabling attachment a) to a steel door and b) to portion of a vehicle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The emergency light of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> further comprising a third mounting means comprising a hangar attached to an upper portion of said rectangular body portion by which said emergency light can be suspended.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The emergency light of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a flat bottom surface upon which said emergency light can stand.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
