<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298428-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298428</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10637115</doc-number>
<date>20030808</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>302</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>1335</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349 18</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Liquid crystal device and method for optical performance monitoring in fiber optic communication systems</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5666174</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cupolo, III</name>
<date>19970900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349 64</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6208774</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Sorin et al.</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 11</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6522467</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Li et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359484</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6680797</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Juday</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359484</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0122444</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Tsai</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>372 18</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0035605</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Bouevitch et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385  1</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0103718</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chen</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 22</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0194165</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Silberberg et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 11</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349194</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349196-198</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349201-202</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349 17</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 11</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60439380</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030110</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yuan</last-name>
<first-name>Haijun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fremont</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Liu</last-name>
<first-name>Yongsheng</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Jose</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zhao</last-name>
<first-name>Xingzhong</first-name>
<address>
<city>Newark</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Patterson &amp; Sheridan, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Avanex Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Fremont</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nelms</last-name>
<first-name>David</first-name>
<department>2871</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Vu</last-name>
<first-name>Phu</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A liquid crystal optical performance monitor is described that employs a liquid crystal tunable filter for receiving a P-polarization beam and a rotated S-polarization beam from a C-polarizer. The rotated S-polarization beam from a birefringent crystal in C-polarizer propagates through a waveplate which rotates the polarization by 90 degrees, resulting in the rotated S-polarization beam having the same polarization orientation as the P-polarization beam. The liquid crystal tunable filter therefore receives just the P-polarization orientation. The C-polarizer and a small beam collimator are rotated so that the polarization orientation of the P-polarization beam and the rotated S-polarization beam matches the orientation of the LC inside the LC cavity of the LC tunable filter. In a first embodiment, the liquid crystal optical performance monitor is implemented with a photodiode. In a second embodiment, the liquid crystal optical performance monitor is implemented with a bi-cell photo diode.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="179.83mm" wi="112.10mm" file="US07298428-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="223.01mm" wi="171.53mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298428-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="150.96mm" wi="132.84mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298428-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="157.65mm" wi="122.43mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298428-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="128.27mm" wi="94.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298428-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="181.36mm" wi="146.64mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298428-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="160.27mm" wi="111.93mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298428-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="186.61mm" wi="143.93mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298428-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="210.82mm" wi="188.98mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298428-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims benefit of U.S. provisional patent application Ser. No. 60/439,380, entitled “Method and Apparatus for a Fiber Optic Housing and Aligning Device” by Giovanni Barbarossa et al., filed on Jan. 10, 2003, which is incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND INFORMATION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The invention relates generally to the field of optics, and more particularly to optical communication networks.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">An optical performance monitor (OPM) is a key element in current proliferative and complex optical communication networks. An optical performance monitor provides information such as the wavelength power, wavelength drift and optical signal-to-noise ratio (OSNR) to each node in an optical communication network.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Currently, there are two basic optical performance monitor architectures, a parallel system and a series system. A parallel design typically uses a dispersing element, such as a grating, for separating spectral signals of light while detecting spectral information with a photodiode array. A series system employs a tunable filter and a single detector coupled to the tunable filter. One drawback in the parallel approach is that it requires an expensive detector array, and typically the dimension of this component is quite bulky. Although the series approach can be compact and flexible, this approach necessitates the use of a high performance tunable filter.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Typical designs of tunable filters are based on thermal, piezo-mechanical or electro-optic effects. One feature of a conventional tunable filter is the parallelism in the Fabry-Perot cavity, which affects the passband of the tunable filter, and consequently defines the performance of an optical performance monitor using such filter. The processing techniques for making such a tunable filter are based on microelectromechanical systems (MEMS) technology, which can be complicated as well as requiring expensive semiconductor manufacturing facilities. Therefore, an optical performance monitor which uses a tunable filter based upon MEMS technology is an expensive solution.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Accordingly, it is desirable to have a tunable filter based optical performance monitor that is more compact than a parallel system but yet is cost effective for deployment in optical performance monitor applications.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The invention describes a liquid crystal (LC) optical performance monitor that employs a liquid crystal tunable filter for receiving a P-polarization beam and a S-polarization beam from a C-polarizer. The S-polarization beam propagates through a waveplate which rotates the S-polarization beam by 90 degrees, resulting in the S-polarization beam having the same polarization as the P-polarization beams. The liquid crystal tunable filter therefore affects just the P-polarization beam. The C-polarizer and a small beam collimator are rotated so that the polarization orientation of the P-polarization beam and the S-polarization beam matches the orientation of a polarization direction of the liquid crystal material inside the liquid crystal cavity of the liquid crystal tunable filter. In a first embodiment, the liquid crystal optical performance monitor is implemented with a photodiode. In a second embodiment, the liquid crystal optical performance monitor is implemented with a bi-cell photodiode.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The selection of a small beam collimator is designed so as to create a minimal space separation between the P-polarization beam and the S-polarization beam while maintaining a maximum extinction ratio of the polarization. Combining the features of a small beam collimator with small beam waists located on the center of the cavity, the present invention significantly reduces the parallelism requirement for a liquid crystal cavity. Moreover, the present invention advantageously simplifies the manufacturing process as well as providing a cost-effective OPM apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Other structures and methods are disclosed in the detailed description below. This summary does not purport to define the invention. The invention is defined by the claims.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a system diagram illustrating a liquid crystal tunable-filter-based optical performance monitor in a dense wavelength division multiplexing (DWDM) system in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating a first embodiment of the optical path using a liquid crystal tunable filter with a photodiode in a liquid crystal optical performance monitor in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a pictorial diagram illustrating a liquid crystal cavity in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a graphical diagram illustrating a sample spectral response of a liquid crystal Fabry-Perot cavity in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating a second embodiment of a liquid crystal optical performance monitor comprising a bi-cell photodiode configuration in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> is a pictorial exploded diagram illustrating a mechanical package of the optical path of a liquid crystal optical performance monitor in accordance with the present invention; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> is a pictorial cross-sectional diagram illustrating the mechanical package of the optical path of the liquid crystal optical performance monitor in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flow diagram illustrating the process of the signal processing steps in the liquid crystal tunable-filter-based optical performance monitor in accordance with the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, there is shown a system diagram that illustrates a liquid crystal tunable-filter-based optical performance monitor <b>100</b> in a dense wavelength division multiplexing system. The optical performance monitor <b>100</b> typically taps a small portion of light from a main express fiber optic <b>110</b> from a coupler <b>115</b> and processes the small portion of light to obtain the spectral information of the signal carried by the main fiber optic <b>110</b>. The optical performance monitor <b>100</b> comprises a liquid crystal etalon <b>120</b>, a PIN diode <b>130</b>, an amplifier <b>140</b>, an analog-to-digital converter (ADC) <b>150</b>, control and processing electronics <b>160</b>, a temperature sensor/controller <b>170</b>, a digital-to-analog converter (DAC) <b>180</b>, drive electronics <b>185</b>, and a display and reporting interface <b>190</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A voltage is applied to the liquid crystal etalon <b>120</b> to detect the spectral information signal of a light from the main fiber optic <b>110</b>. The signal is processed through the PIN diode <b>130</b> and amplified by the amplifier <b>140</b>. The ADC <b>150</b> converts the analog format of the light signal to a digital format. The control and processing electronics <b>160</b> synchronize the scanning and processing data, and obtains the spectral information of the signal sampled from main express fiber optic <b>110</b>, such as the power level, the channel wavelength drift, as well as the optical signal-to-noise ratio (OSNR). A temperature sensor and controller <b>170</b> is coupled to the liquid crystal etalon <b>120</b> and the control and processing electronics <b>160</b>. The DAC <b>180</b> converts the digital signal from the control and processing electronics <b>160</b> to an analog signal. The drive electronics <b>195</b> provides a driving circuit to the liquid crystal etalon <b>120</b>. The result from the optical performance monitor <b>100</b> is reported and displayed by interface <b>190</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating the optical path using a liquid crystal tunable filter with a photodiode in the first embodiment of a liquid crystal optical performance monitor <b>200</b> in accordance with the present invention. The liquid crystal optical performance monitor <b>200</b> comprises a beam collimator <b>210</b> (preferably small, i.e. small beam collimator), a C-polarizer <b>220</b>, a LC tunable filter <b>240</b>, and a photodiode <b>250</b>. The C-polarizer <b>220</b> comprises a birefringent crystal <b>221</b> (preferably comprising YVO<sub>4</sub>) and a waveplate <b>222</b> (preferably a half waveplate). The birefringent crystal <b>221</b> separates a collimated beam into a first linearly polarized beam and a second polarized beam that is polarized orthogonally to the first beam, for instance a S-polarization beam <b>225</b> and a P-polarization beam <b>226</b>. The waveplate <b>222</b> rotates the polarization orientation of one of the linearly polarized beams, for instance, the S-polarization beam <b>225</b> by 90 degrees so that the S-polarization beam <b>225</b> has the same polarization as the P-polarization beam <b>226</b>. After the polarization orientation of the S-polarization beam <b>225</b> has been rotated 90 degrees by the waveplate <b>222</b>, the rotated S-polarization beam <b>225</b> has the same polarization as the P-polarization beam <b>226</b>. Effectively, the rotated S-polarization <b>225</b> has become a P-polarization beam. To describe it from another perspective, as the liquid crystal tunable filter <b>240</b> affects the P-polarized optical beams (i.e., the P-polarized beam <b>226</b> and the rotated S-polarized beam <b>225</b>), the input beam has to be converted to a polarized beam by using the C-polarizer <b>220</b>. After the C-polarizer, the polarization orientation for both the beams <b>225</b> and <b>226</b> has to match a polarization orientation of the liquid crystal material inside the liquid crystal cavity in the liquid crystal tunable filter <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The small beam collimator <b>210</b> is designed to yield minimal space separation between the S-polarization beam <b>225</b> and P-polarization beam <b>226</b>, while still maintaining a maximum extinction ratio of the polarization. The beam waists are located on the center of the cavity. As discussed above, the parallelism of the walls of the liquid crystal tunable cavity is a significant requirement for the performance of an optical performance monitor. The small beam waists on the cavity and the minimal separation between the two separated beams <b>225</b> and <b>226</b> significantly reduce the parallelism requirement for the cavity. Therefore, the liquid crystal optical performance monitor can be manufactured easily and is cost effective.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">One of ordinary skill in the art should recognize that the term liquid crystal tunable filter can refer to as a liquid crystal cell, a liquid crystal etalon, or to other similar terminologies.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a pictorial diagram illustrating a liquid crystal cavity <b>300</b>. The liquid crystal cavity <b>300</b> comprises a first anti-reflective (AR) coating layer <b>310</b>, a first glass plate <b>320</b>, a first ITO electrode layer <b>330</b>, a first high reflective (HR) coating layer <b>340</b>, a liquid crystal <b>350</b>, a second HR coating layer <b>360</b>, a second ITO layer <b>370</b>, a second glass plate <b>380</b>, and a second AR coating layer <b>390</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In addition, a first alignment layer is added between the first HR coating layer <b>340</b> and the liquid crystal <b>350</b>. A second alignment layer is added between the liquid crystal <b>350</b> and the second HR coating layer <b>360</b>. The first and second alignment layers are also referred to as buffer layers.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Table 1 shown below is an example of design parameters of a liquid crystal Fabry-Perot cavity and small beam collimator. A sample spectral response of a liquid crystal etalon is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="1">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="217pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="1" rowsep="1">TABLE 1</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="1" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>LC Filter Parameters</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="5">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="63pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="56pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="28pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>Cavity</entry>
<entry>FSR</entry>
<entry>Reflectivity</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>FWHM</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Spacing (um)</entry>
<entry>(nm)</entry>
<entry>(%)</entry>
<entry>Finesse</entry>
<entry>(nm)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="5" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>8~12</entry>
<entry>45~60</entry>
<entry>99.5</entry>
<entry>&gt;350</entry>
<entry>&lt;0.025</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="5" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="1">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="217pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>Collimator Parameters</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="5">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="56pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Working</entry>
<entry>Beam</entry>
<entry>Extinction</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Beam Size</entry>
<entry>Distance</entry>
<entry>Separation</entry>
<entry>Ratio</entry>
<entry>Pointing Error</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>(um)</entry>
<entry>(mm)</entry>
<entry>(mm)</entry>
<entry>(dB)</entry>
<entry>(°)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="5" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>100~125</entry>
<entry>15~20</entry>
<entry>~0.25</entry>
<entry>&gt;30 dB</entry>
<entry>&lt;0.10</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="5" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating a second embodiment of a liquid crystal optical performance monitor <b>500</b>. The optical performance monitor <b>500</b> is designed with a bi-cell photodiode configuration. The bi-cell photodiode configuration <b>500</b> comprises a small beam collimator <b>510</b>, a C-polarizer <b>520</b>, a liquid crystal tunable filter <b>550</b>, and a bi-cell photodiode <b>550</b>. The bi-cell photodiode <b>540</b> employs a cell_<b>1</b> <b>541</b> for receiving a P-polarization beam <b>526</b> and a cell_<b>2</b> <b>542</b> for receiving a rotated S-polarization beam <b>525</b>. The two beams, the rotated S-polarization beam <b>525</b> and the P-polarization beam <b>526</b>, are received by the two-separated cells <b>541</b> and <b>542</b> in the photodiode <b>540</b>. As result of the arrangement, the parallelism requirement for the liquid crystal tunable filter is further reduced while the whole device remains compact.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Alternatively, the two beams, the rotated S-polarization beam <b>525</b> and the P-polarization beam <b>526</b>, can be separated further by using two individual photodiodes (instead of a bi-cell photodiode) to perform the same function as described above. The tradeoff is that the overall package will be larger.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> is a pictorial exploded diagram, with the cross-sectional view shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, illustrating a mechanical package <b>600</b> of a liquid crystal optical performance monitor in accordance with the present invention. The mechanical package <b>600</b> comprises a collimator with a mounting tube <b>610</b>, a ball join adaptor collimator <b>620</b>, a liquid crystal filter mount <b>630</b>, a liquid crystal tunable filter <b>640</b>, a photodiode mount <b>650</b>, a washer <b>660</b>, and a photodiode <b>670</b>. A join structure (the collimator with mounting tube <b>610</b>, the ball join adaptor <b>620</b> and the liquid crystal filter mount <b>630</b>) between the collimator with mounting tube <b>610</b>, the ball join adaptor <b>620</b> and the liquid crystal tunable filter <b>640</b> is used to maintain the tip/tilt alignment capability. The purpose of the join structure is to ensure that the beam waists of the both beams (the rotated S-polarization beam <b>525</b> and the P-polarization beam <b>526</b>) are within the center of the cavity of the liquid crystal tunable filter <b>640</b>. On the photodiode component, the photodiode <b>670</b> is inserted through the washer <b>660</b> and into the photodiode mount <b>650</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The LC tunable filter <b>640</b> is mounted on the LC filter mount <b>630</b> which has a same or similar thermal expansion coefficient as the material used for the LC tunable filter <b>640</b>. The LC filter mount <b>630</b> serves as a buffer layer for minimizing the stress and strain caused to the LC tunable filter <b>640</b> during an assembly process. The LC tunable filter <b>640</b> and the LC filter mount <b>630</b> are then attached to the ball join adaptor <b>620</b>. The collimator <b>210</b> and the C-polarizer <b>220</b> are mounted in the mounting tube <b>610</b>, which has a concave ball join structure at one of its ends. The ball join structure between the join adaptor <b>620</b> and the collimator tube <b>610</b> allows for tight contact between the two parts, while still maintaining the angular adjustment capability. The collimator <b>210</b> and the C-polarizer <b>220</b> can be adjusted along an axis of the mount tube <b>610</b>, thereby allowing the beam waist on the center of LC cavity. The photodiode <b>670</b> is pre-mounted on a washer <b>660</b>, and actively aligned on the photodiode mount <b>650</b> until the maximum photo signal is received.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Currently, the dimension of the liquid crystal filter <b>640</b> is a limitation on the size of the apparatus. Potentially, if the size of the liquid crystal filter <b>640</b> is reduced sufficiently, the whole package should be able to accommodate inside an industry-standard TO-type can.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flow diagram illustrating the process <b>700</b> of the signal processing steps in the liquid crystal tunable-filter-based optical performance monitor in accordance with the present invention. At step <b>710</b>, the small beam collimator <b>210</b> collimates an incoming light beam to become a collimated beam. At step <b>720</b>, the C-polarizer <b>220</b> first separates the collimated beam into the S-polarization beam <b>225</b> and the P-polarization beam <b>226</b>, and then (at step <b>730</b>), rotates the polarization orientation of the S-polarization beam by 90 degrees. The polarization orientation of the P-polarization beam in this step matches a polarization orientation of a liquid crystal tunable filter. After the rotation, the two beams <b>225</b> and <b>226</b> have the same polarization orientation. At step <b>740</b>, the P-polarization beam and the rotated S-polarization beams <b>226</b>, <b>225</b> are input into a liquid crystal filter that has a polarization orientation that matches that of the beams output from the C-polarizer <b>220</b>. At step <b>750</b>, a controlled scanning voltage is applied to the mid-section <b>241</b> of the liquid crystal tunable filter, resulting in the change of the refractive index of the liquid crystal, thus affecting the change of the spectral property (pass band) of the LC filter. At step <b>760</b>, the scanned spectral signal of the optical beams <b>225</b> and <b>226</b> is detected by the photodiode <b>250</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The above embodiments are only illustrative of the principles of this invention and are not intended to limit the invention to the particular embodiments described. Accordingly, various modifications, adaptations, and combinations of various features of the described embodiments can be practiced without departing from the scope of the invention as set forth in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A liquid crystal (LC) optical performance monitor (OPM), comprising:
<claim-text>a C-polarizer having a birefringent crystal having a first face and a second face for receiving a collimated beam and separating the collimated beam into a P-polarization beam and a S-polarization beam;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a waveplate coupled to the second face of the crystal for rotating the S-polarization beam by 90 degrees, thereby causing the rotated S-polarization beam to have the same polarization as the P-polarization beam; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a liquid crystal tunable filter for receiving and processing the P-polarization beam and the rotated S-polarization beam from the C-polarizer, wherein the P-polarization beam and the rotated S-polarization beam are separate from one another, and beam waists of the P-polarization beam and the rotated S-polarization beam are located substantially on a center of a liquid crystal cavity in the liquid crystal tunable filter.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The LC OPM of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a beam collimator coupled to the first face of the C-polarizer, the beam collimator providing a minimal space separation between the P-polarization beam and the rotated S-polarization beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The LC OPM of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein C-polarizer and the beam collimator are rotated to match a polarization orientation of the LC material inside a LC cavity of the LC tunable filter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The LC OPM of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, further comprising a photodiode for receiving the P-polarization beam and rotated S-polarization beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The LC OPM of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a bi-cell photodiode having a first cell and a second cell, the first cell of the bi-cell photodiode receiving the P-polarization beam, the second cell of the bi-cell photodiode receiving the rotated S-polarization beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A method of a LC OPM, comprising:
<claim-text>separating a collimated beam into a P-polarization beam and a S-polarization beam;</claim-text>
<claim-text>rotating the S-polarization beam by 90 degrees, thereby the S-polarization beam having the same polarization as the P-polarization beam; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>scanning to filter the spectral information of the S-polarization beam and the P-polarization beam by a liquid crystal tunable filter, wherein the P-polarization beam and the S-polarization beam are separate from one another, and beam waists of the P-polarization beam and the S-polarization beam are located substantially on a center of a liquid crystal cavity in the liquid crystal tunable filter.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising collimating an input beam to generate the collimated beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising matching the alignment of the LC filter in the direction of the liquid crystal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising applying a voltage to an LC tunable filter to affect the rotated S-polarization beam and the P-polarization beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method of a LC OPM, comprising:
<claim-text>separating a collimated beam into a first beam comprising a first linear polarization and a second beam comprising a second linear polarization that is orthogonal to the first linear polarization;</claim-text>
<claim-text>rotating the polarization of one of the first beam or the second beam by 90 degrees, thereby causing the first and second beams to have the same polarization; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>scanning to filter the spectral information of the first beam and the second beam by a liquid crystal tunable filter, wherein the first beam and the second beam are separate from one another, and beam waists of the first beam and the second beam are located substantially on a center of a liquid crystal cavity in the liquid crystal tunable filter.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising collimating an input beam to generate the collimated beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising matching the alignment of the LC filter in the direction of the liquid crystal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising applying a voltage to an LC tunable filter to affect the rotated first beam and the second beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
