<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298093-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298093</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11245517</doc-number>
<date>20051007</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>CN</country>
<doc-number>2005 1 0073970</doc-number>
<date>20050519</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>189</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>24</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>37</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315116</main-classification>
<further-classification>315117</further-classification>
<further-classification>315291</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Method and device for driving CCFL circuit</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5336976</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Webb et al.</name>
<date>19940800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>315134</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5907742</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Johnson et al.</name>
<date>19990500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399 51</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6198234</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Henry</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>315291</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0071601</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Yamada et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313634</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-305196</doc-number>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>I226788</doc-number>
<date>20050100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>Taiwan Patent Office Action mailed Mar. 7, 2006.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315112</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315117</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315291</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315307</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315309</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315362</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315113</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315116</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060261750</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061123</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chang</last-name>
<first-name>Ching-Chung</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Thomas, Kayden, Horstemeyer &amp; Risley</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Lite-On Technology Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Tran</last-name>
<first-name>Thuy Vinh</first-name>
<department>2821</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A driving device for a CCFL circuit comprising at least one CCFL is provided. The driving device comprising at least one heating device controlling the temperature of the at least one CCFL, a power supply outputting a first voltage, and a switching device having a first input terminal receiving the first voltage and a first and second output terminal; wherein the first output terminal is coupled to the CCFL circuit outputting a second voltage when the first voltage is higher than a first level, and the second output terminal is coupled to the at least one heating device outputting a third voltage when the first voltage is lower than the first level. The driving device further comprises a controller controlling the power supply to output the first voltage higher than the first level to lighting up the at least one CCFL, and lower than the first level to control the temperature of the at least one CCFL.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="142.58mm" wi="338.75mm" file="US07298093-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="173.14mm" wi="78.23mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298093-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="243.33mm" wi="105.33mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298093-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="252.90mm" wi="160.10mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298093-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention relates to a cold cathode fluorescent lamp (CCFL) circuit and, more particularly, to devices for rapidly lighting a CCFL.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">CCFL is a widely used light source in electronic devices such as scanners, LCD panels, notebook PCs and LCD televisions. Illumination of a conventional CCFL, however, may take up to 3 minutes to achieve stability after power up. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a conventional electronic device <b>10</b> comprising a CCFL circuit. Electronic device <b>10</b> comprises a power supply <b>11</b> and a CCFL circuit <b>12</b> comprising at least one CCFL <b>121</b>. Power supply <b>11</b> provides a voltage DC<b>1</b> to the CCFL circuit <b>12</b>. CCFL circuit <b>12</b> generates a high voltage AC supply according to the voltage DC<b>1</b> to light CCFL <b>121</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A method to drive a CCFL is provided by Johnson, et al. (U.S. Pat. No. 5,907,742, “Lamp control scheme for rapid warm-up of fluorescent lamp in office equipment”). The lamp is over-driven with high current for up to a predetermined time limit to accelerate mercury vaporization. The drive current is then reduced to a normal level. Between each use, the lower lamp current is 40% of the normal level to keep the lamp warm while extending the life of the product.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Using Johnson's Method, a certain amount of power is required when the CCFL is not working to maintain the temperature of the CCFL. The power consumed at the lower lamp current state is significant and additional logic circuits are required for controlling current in different states. Furthermore, if a longer length CCFL is utilized in electronic device <b>10</b>, to raise the current when lighting the CCFLs, the CCFL circuit <b>12</b> receives higher voltage DC<b>1</b> and generates higher voltage AC power. Consequently, transformers used in CCFL circuit <b>12</b> may not be capable of sustaining such a high voltage and may need to be upgraded, which leads to additional manufacturing cost.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A driving device for a CCFL circuit comprising at least one CCFL is provided. The driving device comprises: at least one heating device controlling the temperature of the CCFL; a power supply outputting a first voltage; a switching device having a first input terminal receiving the first voltage and a first and second output terminal outputting a second and third voltage respectively. The first output terminal is coupled to the CCFL circuit to output the second voltage when the first voltage is higher than a first level. The second output terminal is coupled to the heating device to output the third voltage when the first voltage is lower than the first level. The driving device further comprises a controller controlling the power supply to output the first voltage higher than the first level to light the CCFL, and lower than the first level to control the temperature of the CCFL.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The accompanying drawings, which are incorporated in and constitute a part of this specification, illustrate embodiments of the invention and, together with the description, serve to explain the features, advantages, and principles of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a conventional electronic device comprising a CCFL circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a block diagram of an electronic device according to an embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2B and 2C</figref> are block diagrams of different embodiments of the switching device of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The invention provides a heating device maintaining the temperature of an idle CCFL, and enabling rapid lighting thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a block diagram of an electronic device <b>20</b> according to an embodiment of the invention. Electronic device <b>20</b> comprises CCFLs as a light source and may be a scanner, an LCD panel, a notebook PC or an LCD television, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The electronic device <b>20</b> comprises a driving device <b>21</b> and a CCFL circuit <b>22</b> comprising at least one CCFL <b>221</b>. Driving device <b>21</b> comprises a controller <b>211</b>, a power supply <b>212</b>, a switching device <b>213</b> and a heating device <b>214</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Power supply <b>212</b> outputs a first voltage DC<b>1</b>, controlled by the controller <b>211</b>. Switching device <b>213</b> has a first input terminal receiving the first voltage DC<b>1</b> and a first and second output terminal. The first output terminal is coupled to the CCFL circuit <b>22</b> outputting the second voltage DC<b>2</b> when the first voltage DC<b>1</b> is higher than a first level V<b>1</b>. The second output terminal is coupled to the heating device <b>214</b> outputting the third voltage DC<b>3</b> when the first voltage DC<b>1</b> is lower than the first level V<b>1</b>. In this embodiment, the controller <b>211</b> controls the power supply <b>212</b> to output the first DC voltage DC<b>1</b> higher than the first level V<b>1</b> to light the CCFL <b>221</b>. The voltage switching device <b>213</b> provides the second DC voltage DC<b>2</b> to the CCFL circuit <b>22</b> for lighting the CCFL <b>221</b>. Simultaneously, the third DC voltage DC<b>3</b> is cut off. Thus, the heating device stops working.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Additionally, controller <b>211</b> controls the power supply <b>212</b> to output the first DC voltage DC<b>1</b> lower than the first level V<b>1</b> to control the temperature of the CCFL <b>211</b> when the CCFL <b>211</b> is idle. The voltage switching device <b>213</b> cuts off the second DC voltage DC<b>2</b> and the power supply <b>212</b> snuffs out the CCFL <b>221</b>. Simultaneously, the third DC voltage DC<b>3</b> is output. The heating device <b>214</b> heats the CCFL <b>221</b> such that the CCFL <b>221</b> is rapidly lit when required next time.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a block diagram of an embodiment of the switching device <b>23</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>. Switching device comprise switching units <b>2131</b> and <b>2132</b>. Switching unit <b>2131</b> is ON when the first voltage is higher than the first level V<b>1</b>, and is OFF when the first voltage is lower than the first level V<b>1</b>. Switching unit <b>2132</b> is OFF when the first voltage is higher than the first level V<b>1</b>, and is ON when the first voltage is lower than the first level V<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In this embodiment, a simply two-state DC voltage control method is utilized to control a boot mode and a sleep mode of the CCFL. In the sleep mode, the CCFL is idle and stops receiving current. In the sleep mode, the temperature of the CCFL is maintained such that the power consumption caused by the CCFL is solved.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">A second level V<b>2</b> higher than the first level V<b>1</b> is provided for an extra function of this embodiment. The function of the first output terminal of switching device <b>23</b> remains the same. The second output terminal of switching device <b>23</b> outputs the third voltage DC<b>3</b> when the first voltage DC<b>1</b> is lower than the first level V<b>1</b> or higher than the second level V<b>2</b>. In this embodiment, when the first voltage is higher than the second level V<b>2</b>, the CCFL is lit and the heating device <b>214</b> heats the CCFL <b>221</b>. The temperature of the CCFL <b>221</b> may be increased rapidly and illumination of the CCFL <b>221</b> may rapidly reach the working illumination.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> is a block diagram of another embodiment of the switching device <b>23</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>. Switching device <b>23</b> comprises switching units <b>2131</b> and <b>2132</b>. Switching unit <b>2131</b> is ON when the first voltage DC<b>1</b> is higher than the first level V<b>1</b>, and is OFF when the first voltage is lower than the first level V<b>1</b>. Switching unit <b>2132</b> is OFF when the first voltage DC<b>1</b> is between the first level V<b>1</b> and the second level V<b>2</b>, and ON when the first voltage is lower than the first level V<b>1</b> or higher than the second level V<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In this embodiment, controller <b>211</b> controls the power supply <b>21</b> to light the CCFL <b>221</b> when the first DC voltage DC<b>1</b> is higher than the first level V<b>1</b> and lower than the second level V<b>2</b>. The voltage switching device <b>213</b> provides the second DC voltage DC<b>2</b> to the CCFL circuit <b>22</b> for lighting the CCFL <b>221</b>. Simultaneously, the third DC voltage DC<b>3</b> is cut off such that the heating device stops working.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Additionally, controller <b>221</b> controls the power supply <b>21</b> to output the first DC voltage DC<b>1</b> lower than the first level V<b>1</b> when the CCFL stops working. The voltage switching device <b>213</b> cuts off the second DC voltage DC<b>2</b> such that the CCFL circuit <b>22</b> snuffs out the CCFL <b>221</b>. Simultaneously, the third DC voltage DC<b>3</b> is output such that the heating device <b>214</b> heats the CCFL <b>221</b>. Thus, the CCFL <b>221</b> is lit rapidly when required next time.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Controller <b>211</b> further controls the power supply <b>21</b> to output the first DC voltage DC<b>1</b> higher than the second level V<b>2</b> to rapidly light the CCFL <b>221</b>. The voltage switching device <b>213</b> provides the second DC voltage DC<b>2</b> to the CCFL circuit <b>22</b> for lighting the CCFL <b>221</b>. Simultaneously, the third DC voltage DC<b>3</b> is output such that the heating device <b>214</b> heats the CCFL <b>221</b>. Thus, the temperature of the CCFL <b>221</b> rapidly arrives an operation temperature.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In this embodiment, a simply three-state DC voltage control method is utilized to control a rapid light mode, a boot mode, and a sleep mode of the CCFL. In the rapid light mode, since the CCFL is heated, the CCFL is not required to receiving a higher current and the CCFL is rapidly lit. In the sleep mode, the CCFL is idle and the CCFL is not required to receive current. In the sleep mode. the temperature of the CCFL is maintained such that the power consumption caused by the CCFL is solved.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">While the invention has been described by way of example and in terms of preferred embodiment, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited thereto. Those who are skilled in this technology can still make various alterations and modifications without departing from the scope and spirit of this invention. Therefore, the scope of the present invention shall be defined and protected by the following claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A driving device for a cold cathode fluorescent lamp (CCFL) circuit comprising at least one CCFL, comprising:
<claim-text>at least one heating device heating the at least one CCFL;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply outputting a first voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switching device having a first input terminal receiving the first voltage and a first and second output terminal outputting a second and third voltage respectively; wherein the first output terminal is coupled to the CCFL circuit and outputs the second voltage when the first voltage is higher than a first level, and the second output terminal is coupled to the at least one heating device and outputs the third voltage when the first voltage is lower than the first level; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller controlling the power supply to output the first voltage higher than the first level to light the at least one CCFL, and lower than the first level to heat the at least one CCFL.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The driving device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the switching device comprises a first switching unit coupled between the input terminal and the first output terminal, and a second switching unit coupled between the input terminal and the second output terminal; wherein the first and second switching unit is ON and OFF respectively when the first voltage is higher than the first level, and OFF and ON respectively when the first voltage is lower than the first level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The driving device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the switching device further outputs both the second and third voltage when the first voltage is higher than a second level; wherein the second level is higher than the first level; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the controller further controls the power supply to output the first voltage higher than the second level to rapidly light the at least one CCFL.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The driving device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the switching device comprises a first switching unit coupled between the input terminal and the first output terminal, and a second switching unit coupled between the input terminal and the second output terminal; wherein the first switching unit is ON when the first voltage is higher than the first level, and is OFF when the first voltage is lower than the first level; and the second switching unit is ON when the first voltage is higher than the second level or lower than the first level, and is OFF when the first voltage is between the first and second level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The driving device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein when the at least one CCFL is to be in a sleep mode, the controller controls the power supply to output the first voltage lower than the first level to heat the at least one CCFL.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The driving device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein when the at least one CCFL is to be in a boot mode, the controller controls the power supply to output the first voltage higher than the first level to light the at least one CCFL.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The driving device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein when the at least one CCFL is to be in a rapid mode, the controller controls the power supply to output the first voltage higher than a second level to heat and light the at least one CCFL, and wherein the second level is higher than the first level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The driving device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein when the at least one CCFL is to be in the rapid mode, the switching device outputs both the second and third voltage when the first voltage is higher than the second level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An electronic device comprising:
<claim-text>a CCFL circuit comprising at least one CCFL;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one heating device heating the at least one CCFL;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply outputting a first voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switching device having a first input terminal receiving the first voltage and a first and second output terminal outputting a second and third voltage respectively; wherein the first output terminal is coupled to the CCFL circuit and outputting the second voltage when the first voltage is higher than a first level, and the second output terminal is coupled to the at least one heating device and outputting the third voltage when the first voltage is lower than the first level; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller controlling the power supply to output the first voltage higher than the first level to lighting up the at least one CCFL, and lower than the first level to heat the at least one CCFL.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the switching device comprises a first switching unit coupled between the input terminal and the first output terminal, and a second switching unit coupled between the input terminal and the second output terminal; wherein the first and second switching unit is ON and OFF respectively when the first voltage is higher than the first level, and OFF and ON respectively when the first voltage is lower than the first level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the switching device further outputs both the second and third voltage when the first voltage is higher than a second level; wherein the second level is higher than the first level; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the controller further controls the power supply to output the first voltage higher than the second level to rapidly light the at least one CCFL.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the switching device comprises a first switching unit coupled between the input terminal and the first output terminal, and a second switching unit coupled between the input terminal and the second output terminal; wherein the first switching unit is ON when the first voltage is higher than the first level, and is OFF when the first voltage is lower than the first level; and the second switching unit is ON when the first voltage is higher than the second level or lower than the first level, and is OFF when the first voltage is between the first and second level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein when the at least one CCFL is to be in a sleep mode, the controller controls the power supply to output the first voltage lower than the first level to heat the at least one CCFL.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein when the at least one CCFL is to be in a boot mode, the controller controls the power supply to output the first voltage higher than the first level to light the at least one CCFL.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein when the at least one CCFL is to be in a rapid mode, the controller controls the power supply to output the first voltage higher than a second level to heat and light the at least one CCFL, and wherein the second level is higher than the first level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein when the at least one CCFL is to be in the rapid mode, the switching device outputs both the second and third voltage when the first voltage is higher than the second level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method for driving a CCFL circuit comprising at least one CCFL, comprising:
<claim-text>providing a heating device heating the at least one CCFL;</claim-text>
<claim-text>utilizing a power supply to provide a first voltage:</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a second voltage to the CCFL circuit when the first voltage is higher than a first level; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a third voltage to the heating device when the first voltage is lower than a first level.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>providing both the second and third voltage when the first voltage is higher than a second level, to light up the at least one CCFL and heating the at least one CCFL at the same time; wherein the second level is higher than the first level.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
