<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298087-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298087</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10885598</doc-number>
<date>20040708</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2003-45935</doc-number>
<date>20030708</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>91</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>17</main-group>
<subgroup>49</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313587</main-classification>
<further-classification>313582</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Plasma display panel</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5851732</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kanda et al.</name>
<date>19981200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>430321</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6727648</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kang</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313582</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6781308</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hayashi</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313582</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6855196</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kawamura et al.</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>106 316</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6870316</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Sano et al.</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313583</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-125228</doc-number>
<date>19980500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>1020010007076</doc-number>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313582-587</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345 60</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>445 23- 25</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050007017</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050113</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kim</last-name>
<first-name>Joong Kyun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Sang Kook</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kumi-shi</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ked &amp; Associates, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>LG Electronics Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Williams</last-name>
<first-name>Joseph</first-name>
<department>2879</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A plasma display panel is provided which evenly deposits a phosphorus layer by forming a buffer layer before forming the phosphorus layer within a discharge cell of a rear surface substrate. The plasma display panel includes a front substrate on which are formed common sustain electrode and scan sustain electrodes and through which light is emitted and a rear substrate on which discharge cells are formed by barrier ribs and address electrodes. The rear substrate may be bonded to the front substrate by frit glass.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="101.09mm" wi="123.61mm" file="US07298087-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="214.80mm" wi="142.66mm" file="US07298087-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="176.53mm" wi="128.52mm" file="US07298087-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="173.74mm" wi="124.97mm" file="US07298087-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the benefit of the Korean Patent Application No. P2003-45935 filed on Jul. 8, 2003, which is hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a plasma display panel, and more particularly to a plasma display panel that is adaptive for evenly depositing a phosphorus layer by forming a buffer layer before the phosphorus layer is formed within a discharge cell of a rear surface substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Recently, Flat Panel Displays have briskly been developed, which include Liquid Crystal Displays (hereinafter ‘LCD’), Field Emission Displays (hereinafter ‘FED’), Plasma Display Panels (hereinafter ‘PDP’). The PDP among them has advantages of easy production due to its simple structure, excellence of high brightness and high light-emission efficiency, memory function, and wide viewing angle of over 160°, in addition, being realized into a large screen of over 40 inches.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram representing the structure of a three-electrode AC surface discharge PDP of prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the plasma display panel includes a front substrate <b>10</b> on which pictures are displayed and a rear substrate <b>20</b> which is formed separate from the front substrate <b>10</b> with a designated distance. The front and rear substrates are bonded and sealed by frit glass.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The front substrate <b>10</b> includes a common sustain electrode Z, scan sustain electrodes Y, a dielectric layer <b>12</b> and a protective layer <b>13</b>. The common sustain electrode Z and the scan sustain electrodes Y are arranged in pair to keep the luminescence of cells by discharges between them. The dielectric layer <b>12</b> limits the discharge current of the common sustain electrode Z and the scan sustain electrode Y and makes each of the electrodes insulated. And, the protective layer <b>13</b> prevents damage of the dielectric layer <b>12</b> and makes the efficiency of secondary discharge improved.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The rear substrate <b>20</b> includes a plurality of address electrode X, a dielectric layer <b>22</b>, barrier ribs <b>21</b> and a phosphorus layer <b>23</b> of each R, G, B. The address electrode X generates vacuum ultraviolet ray by performing address discharge at areas where the common sustain electrode Z and the scan sustain electrodes Y are crossed. The dielectric layer <b>22</b> makes the address electrodes X insulated. The barrier ribs <b>21</b> are formed on one side of the dielectric layer <b>22</b> to be arranged in parallel so as to form a plurality of discharge spaces, i.e., cells.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The phosphorus layer <b>23</b> of each RGB is deposited at an area between the side surface of the barrier ribs <b>21</b>, one barrier rib and another barrier rib to emit visible ray.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Also, the common sustain electrode Z includes a transparent electrode Za of ITO electrode, a bus electrode Zb made of metal and a black layer B. The black layer B is formed between the common electrode Za and the bus electrode Zb and made of a conductive material such as ruthenium oxide and lead oxide or carbon family to improve the contrast.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Further, the scan sustain electrode Y includes a transparent electrode Ya of ITO electrode, a bus electrode Yb made of metal and a black layer B. The black layer B is formed between the common electrode Ya and the bus electrode Yb and made of a conductive material such as ruthenium oxide and lead oxide or carbon family to improve the contrast.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">And, a discharge gas is filled between the front substrate <b>10</b> the rear substrate <b>20</b> at a pressure of 300˜400 Torr. The discharge gas is mainly penning mixture gas and has He, Ne, Ar or their mixed gas as its buffer gas. A little of Xe gas is used as a source of vacuum ultraviolet ray which makes the phosphorus layer <b>23</b> emit light.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">With the basis of the above-mentioned composition, the operation of the plasma display panel of prior art is described.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram explaining the operation of the plasma display panel of prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">For reference, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram showing a rear substrate <b>20</b> in 90 angle to the front substrate for the sake of convenience of explanation.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, to describe the operation of the plasma display panel, the plasma display panel displays images by Address and Display Separate where a data input period and a display period are divided in time.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">First of all, if a voltage of 150˜300V is supplied between the san sustain electrode Y and the address electrode X in an arbitrary discharge cell, a writing discharge is generated inside the cell that is located between the scan sustain electrode Y and the address electrode X to form wall charges on the internal surface of the corresponding discharge cell, thereby leaving the wall charges on the dielectric layer <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In the cells selected by such an address discharge, a sustain discharge is generated by an AC signal supplied to the common sustain electrode Z and the scan sustain electrode Y, and the discharge causes electric fields to be generated within the cell, thereby accelerating micro-electrons among the discharge cell.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The accelerated electrons collide with neutrons among the gas to electrolytically dissociate them into electron and ion, and the dissociated electron makes another collision with other neutron, thereby causing the neutrons to be electrolytically dissociated into electron and ion more and more rapidly so that the discharge gas becomes in the state of plasma and, at the same time, vacuum ultraviolet ray is generated.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The ultraviolet ray generated in this way excites the R, G and B phosphorus layer <b>23</b> to generate visible ray, and the generated visible ray is irradiated to the outside, thus the luminescence of an arbitrary cell, i.e., the displayed image can be perceived from the outside.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Each cell that forms such an image constitutes a unit cell being separated from others by minute barrier ribs <b>21</b>. In case of making the plasma display panel in real, it is not easy to form unit discharge cells of 100 μm on a glass substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Especially, because high resolution plasma display panel is required recently, the size of discharge cell is further decreased and because the phosphorus layer is deposited over the decreased discharge cell, there occurs a problem of the phosphorus layer being deposited unevenly.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Since the phosphorus layer is deposited unevenly, there occurs a problem that the efficiency of converting the vacuum ultraviolet ray into the visible ray and decay time, i.e., time when the phosphorus is excited and light is emitted, become un-uniform in accordance with each discharge cell.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Furthermore, since the phosphorus layer is deposited unevenly, the life span of the phosphorus is deteriorated.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Accordingly, it is an object of the present invention to provide a plasma display panel that is adaptive for evenly depositing a phosphorus layer by forming a buffer layer before the phosphorus layer is formed within a discharge cell of a rear surface substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In order to achieve these and other objects of the invention, a plasma display panel including a front substrate where a common sustain electrode and scan sustain electrodes are formed and light is emitted and a rear substrate where discharge cells are formed by barrier ribs and address electrodes are formed for address discharge, and wherein the rear substrate is bonded with the front substrate by frit glass, according to an aspect of the present invention includes a phosphorus layer deposited on a buffer layer and the upper part of the buffer layer in a discharge cell between the barrier ribs.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In the plasma display panel, the buffer layer is formed of oxide.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In the plasma display panel, the buffer layer is made of at least one or a combination of two or more among ZnO, Al-doped ZnO and In-doped ZnO.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In the plasma display panel, the buffer layer is made of CaO or BaO.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In the plasma display panel, the buffer layer is formed in a thickness of around 10˜20 μm.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">These and other objects of the invention will be apparent from the following detailed description of the embodiments of the present invention with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram describing the structure of a three-electrode AC surface discharge plasma display panel of prior art;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram describing the operation of the plasma display panel of prior art; and</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a diagram describing that a buffer layer is formed in a plasma display panel according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Reference will now be made in detail to the preferred embodiments of the present invention, examples of which are illustrated in the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, embodiments of the present invention will be explained as follows.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a diagram describing a plasma display panel according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the plasma display panel according to the present invention includes a front substrate <b>10</b> on which pictures are displayed and a rear substrate <b>20</b> which is formed separate from the front substrate <b>10</b> with a designated distance. The front and rear substrates are bonded and sealed by frit glass.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The front substrate <b>10</b> includes a common sustain electrode Z, scan sustain electrodes Y, a dielectric layer <b>12</b> and a protective layer <b>13</b>. The common sustain electrode Z and the scan sustain electrodes Y are arranged in pair to keep the luminescence of cells by discharges between them. The dielectric layer <b>12</b> limits the discharge current of the common sustain electrode Z and the scan sustain electrode Y and makes each of the electrodes insulated. And, the protective layer <b>13</b> prevents damage of the dielectric layer <b>12</b> and makes the efficiency of secondary discharge improved.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The rear substrate <b>20</b> includes a plurality of address electrode X, a dielectric layer <b>22</b>, barrier ribs <b>21</b>, a phosphorus layer <b>23</b> of each R, G, B, and a buffer layer <b>30</b>. The address electrode X generates vacuum ultraviolet ray by performing address discharge at areas where the common sustain electrode Z and the scan sustain electrodes Y are crossed. The dielectric layer <b>22</b> makes the address electrodes X insulated. The barrier ribs <b>21</b> are formed on one side of the dielectric layer <b>22</b> to be arranged in parallel so as to form a plurality of discharge spaces, i.e., cells. The buffer layer <b>30</b> is deposited inside the cell before depositing the phosphorus layer <b>23</b> in order to enable the phosphorus layer <b>23</b> uniformly deposited.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The buffer layer <b>30</b> is of an oxide. And, as the buffer layer <b>30</b> is formed, the buffer layer <b>30</b> plays role of a medium or seed to make the deposition of the phosphorus layer <b>23</b> more uniform.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Especially, because high resolution plasma display panel is required recently, the size of discharge cell is further decreased and the phosphorus layer is deposited unevenly. The buffer layer <b>30</b> causes the phosphorus layer <b>23</b> to be deposited evenly, thereby improving the picture quality characteristic of the plasma display panel.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The buffer layer <b>30</b> is of an oxide. Especially, it is desirable to be composed of zinc oxide (at lease one or a combination of two or more among ZnO, Al-doped ZnO and In-doped Zno), CaO or BaO.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Also, the buffer layer <b>30</b> is desirable to be formed in the thickness of around 10˜20 μm in light of securing the discharge space and uniformly depositing the phosphorus layer <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In this way, the phosphorus layer <b>23</b> can be induced to be evenly deposited by forming the buffer layer <b>30</b> before depositing the phosphorus layer <b>23</b>. Thus, a variety of picture quality characteristics can be improved due to the uniform deposition of the phosphorus layer <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Especially, the buffer layer <b>30</b> also affects the residual image characteristic among the picture quality characteristics of the plasma display panel. The residual image duration is reduced to less than half of it when depositing the phosphorus layer after forming the buffer layer <b>30</b> than when depositing the phosphorus layer <b>23</b> without the buffer layer <b>30</b> as in the prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As described above, the plasma display panel according to the present invention forms the buffer layer before depositing the phosphorus layer, thereby enabling the phosphorus layer to be deposited more uniformly.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Since the phosphorus layer is deposited uniformly, a variety of picture quality characteristics can be improved, and especially, the high resolution plasma display panel, considered as important recently, might be achieved in forming the phosphorus layer.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Although the present invention has been explained by the embodiments shown in the drawings described above, it should be understood to the ordinary skilled person in the art that the invention is not limited to the embodiments, but rather that various changes or modifications thereof are possible without departing from the spirit of the invention. Accordingly, the scope of the invention shall be determined only by the appended claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A plasma display panel having a plurality of discharge cells, comprising:
<claim-text>a front substrate having a common sustain electrode and a scan sustain electrode formed thereon, wherein at least one of the common sustain electrode or scan sustain electrode includes a bus electrode and a transparent electrode, the bus electrode extending in a first direction and configured to be electrically coupled to the transparent electrode, and wherein a black layer is formed under the bus electrode;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rear substrate having barrier ribs and address electrodes, the address electrodes extending in a second direction, the first and second directions being different; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a phosphorus layer deposited on a buffer layer in discharge cells between the barrier ribs, wherein the buffer layer has curved corners and tapered ends.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the buffer layer is formed of oxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the buffer layer comprises at least one or a combination of two or more among ZnO, Al-doped ZnO and In-doped ZnO.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the buffer layer comprises CaO or BaO.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the buffer layer has a thickness of around 10˜20 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the buffer layer comprises at least one of ZnO, Al-doped ZnO, In-doped ZnO, CaO, or BaO.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the rear substrate is bonded with the front substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the rear substrate is bonded with the front substrate by frit glass.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the black layer underlays a full area underneath the bus electrode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the tapered ends of the buffer layer end below a top of the barrier ribs.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the buffer layer is non-uniform in thickness.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a bottom portion of the buffer layer differs in thickness from the corner portions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a bottom portion of the buffer layer differs in thickness from the tapered end portions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the black layer extends in the first direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the transparent electrode has a rectangular shape with a first prescribed width and the bus electrode has a rectangular shape with a second prescribed width in the second direction, and wherein the first width is larger than the second width.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the bus electrode partially overlaps the transparent electrode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each discharge cell is formed between adjacent barrier ribs extending in at least the second direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The plasma display panel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the barrier ribs have a substantially constant width.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
