<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298595-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298595</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10672992</doc-number>
<date>20030926</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>432</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>39</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>360314</main-classification>
<further-classification>36032412</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Differential GMR sensor with multi-layer bias structure between free layers of first and second self-pinned GMR sensors</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5648885</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nishioka et al.</name>
<date>19970700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>36032412</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5751521</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gill</name>
<date>19980500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5768069</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mauri</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360314</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6259586</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Gill</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6275363</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Gill</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3603242</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6449134</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Beach et al.</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>36032412</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0075608</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kawato</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0126426</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Gill</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360314</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0011939</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Gill</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0012898</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hasegawa</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>36032411</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0086751</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hasegawa et al.</name>
<date>20040500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>428692</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0218311</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Saito et al.</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360314</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000215421</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>360314</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>36032412</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050068683</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050331</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gill</last-name>
<first-name>Hardayal Singh</first-name>
<address>
<city>Palo Alto</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lynch</last-name>
<first-name>David W.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Merchant &amp; Gould</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hitachi Global Storage Technologies Netherlands B.V.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<country>NL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Renner</last-name>
<first-name>Craig A.</first-name>
<department>2627</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method for providing a self-pinned differential GMR sensor and self-pinned differential GMR sensor. The differential GMR head includes two self-pinned GMR sensors separated by a gap layer. The gap layer may act as a bias structure to provide antiparallel magnetizations for the first and second free layers without using an antiferromagnetic layer. The gap layer may include four NiFe ferromagnetic layers separated with three interlayers. The gap may also be formed to include a structure defined by Ta/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>/NiFeCr/CuOx. One of the pinned layer may include three ferromagnetic layers so that the top ferromagnetic layer of the bottom pinned layer and the bottom ferromagnetic layer of the bottom pinned layer have a magnetization 180° out of phase. The self-pinned GMR sensors may include synthetic free layers that includes a first free sublayer, an interlayer and a second free sublayer that are biased 180° out of phase.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="205.23mm" wi="183.30mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="153.08mm" wi="155.45mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="132.33mm" wi="146.39mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="179.66mm" wi="131.57mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="238.25mm" wi="158.24mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298595-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="222.25mm" wi="184.57mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="232.66mm" wi="178.22mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="215.98mm" wi="182.03mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="219.54mm" wi="175.43mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="218.44mm" wi="132.67mm" file="US07298595-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates in general to sensors for magnetic storage devices, and more particularly to a method for providing a self-pinned differential GMR sensor and self-pinned differential GMR sensor.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Magnetic recording is a key segment of the information-processing industry. While the basic principles are one hundred years old for early tape devices, and over forty years old for magnetic hard disk drives, an influx of technical innovations continues to extend the storage capacity and performance of magnetic recording products. For hard disk drives, the areal density or density of written data bits on the magnetic medium has increased by a factor of more than two million since the first disk drive was used for data storage. Areal density continues to grow due to improvements in magnet recording heads, media, drive electronics, and mechanics.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Magnetic recording heads have been considered the most significant factor in areal-density growth. The ability of the magnetic recording heads to both write and subsequently read magnetically recorded data from the medium at data densities well into the gigabits per square inch (Gbits/in<sup>2</sup>) range gives hard disk drives the power to remain the dominant storage device for many years to come.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Important components of computing platforms are mass storage devices including magnetic disk and magnetic tape drives, where magnetic tape drives are popular, for example, in data backup applications. Write and read heads are employed for writing magnetic data to and reading magnetic data from the recording medium. The read and write heads are connected to processing circuitry that operates according to a computer program to implement the writing and reading functions.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A magnetoresistive (MR) sensor changes resistance in the presence of a magnetic field. Recorded data can be read from a recorded magnetic medium, such as a magnetic disk, because the magnetic field from the recorded magnetic medium causes a change in the direction of magnetization in the read element, which causes a corresponding change in the sensor resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">A magnetoresistive (MR) sensor detects magnetic field signals through the resistance changes of a sensing element as a function of the strength and direction of magnetic flux being sensed by the sensing element. Conventional MR sensors, such as those used as MR read heads for reading data in magnetic recording disk and tape drives, operate on the basis of the anisotropic magnetoresistive (AMR) effect of the bulk magnetic material, which is typically permalloy. A component of the read element resistance varies as the square of the cosine of the angle between the magnetization direction in the read element and the direction of sense current through the read element. Recorded data can be read from a magnetic medium, such as the magnetic disk in a magnetic disk drive, because the external magnetic field from the recorded magnetic medium (the signal field) causes a change in the direction of magnetization in the read element, which in turn causes a change in resistance of the read element. This change in resistance may be used to detect magnetic transitions recorded on the recording media.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In the past several years, prospects of increased storage capacity have been made possible by the discovery and development of sensors based on the giant magnetoresistance (GMR) effect, also known as the spin-valve effect. In a spin valve sensor, the GMR effect varies as the cosine of the angle between the magnetization of the pinned layer and the magnetization of the free layer. Recorded data can be read from a magnetic medium because the external magnetic field from the recorded magnetic medium, or signal field, causes a change in the direction of magnetization of the free layer, which in turn causes a change in the resistance of the spin valve sensor and a corresponding change in the sensed current or voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Magnetic sensors utilizing the GMR effect are found in mass storage devices such as, for example, magnetic disk and tape drives and are frequently referred to as spin-valve sensors. The spin-valve sensors are divided into two main categories, the Anti-FerroMagnetically (AFM) pinned spin valve and the self-pinned spin valve. An AFM pinned spin valve comprises a sandwiched structure consisting of two ferromagnetic layers separated by a thin non-ferromagnetic layer. One of the ferromagnetic layers is called the pinned layer because it is magnetically pinned or oriented in a fixed and unchanging direction by an adjacent AFM layer, commonly referred to as the pinning layer, which pins the magnetic orientation of the pinned layer through anti-ferromagnetic exchange coupling by the application of a sense current field. The other ferromagnetic layer is called the free or sensing layer because the magnetization is allowed to rotate in response to the presence of external magnetic fields.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In the self-pinned spin valve, the magnetic moment of the pinned layer is pinned in the fabrication process, i.e., the magnetic moment is set by the specific thickness and composition of the film. The self-pinned layer may be formed of a single layer of a single material or may be a composite layer structure of multiple materials. It is noteworthy that a self-pinned spin valve requires no additional external layers applied adjacent thereto to maintain a desired magnetic orientation and, therefore, is considered to be an improvement over the anti-ferromagnetically pinned spin valve.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">As systems are pushed to higher read density, higher magnetic bit size or decreased recording media size, the available magnetic flux is decreased. In addition, sensitivity may be decreased from thermal noise. For example, while the head is flying over the disk surface, it may hit a particle (contamination). The energy of this collision will be dissipated in the form of heat causing the temperature of the head to increase, causing an increase in the resistance of the head ultimately resulting in a signal that may be even higher than the magnetic signal from a transition. In order to sense these smaller signals and increase areal density, read heads with greater sensitivities are needed.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A scheme to increase the signal to noise ratio of a spin valve head is to employ first and second spin valve sensors, which are differentially detected for common mode noise rejection. A differential spin valve structure employs first and second spin valve sensors that produce responses of opposite polarities in reaction to a magnetic field of a single polarity. The opposite polarity responses are processed by a differential amplifier for common mode rejection of noise and for producing an enhanced combined signal. The first and second spin valve sensors are magnetically separated by a gap layer. The first spin valve sensor is connected in series with first and second leads and the second spin valve sensor is connected in series with third and fourth leads. The second and fourth leads are electrically interconnected and the first and third leads are adapted for connection to the differential amplifier.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">While a differential GMR head provides an increased signal to noise ratio, the differential GMR head is significantly thicker than a single pinned spin valve sensor because of the thicknesses of the first and second pinning layers. While the thicknesses of the various layers of a typical spin valve sensor range between 10 Å-70 Å, the thicknesses of the antiferromagnetic pinning layers vary in a range from 120 Å-425 Å. Iridium manganese (IrMn) permits the thinnest antiferromagnetic pinning layer of about 120 Å whereas an antiferromagnetic pinning layer composed of nickel oxide (NiO) is typically 425 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Further, the range of blocking temperature for the interface at the antiferromagnetic layer is relatively low. These temperatures can be reached by certain thermal effects during operation of the disk drive, such as an increase in the ambient temperature inside the drive, heating of the SV sensor due to the bias current, and rapid heating of the SV sensor due to the head carrier contacting asperities on the disk. In addition, during assembly of the disk drive the SV sensor can be heated by current resulting from an electrostatic discharge. If any of these thermal effects cause the SV sensor to exceed the antiferromagnet's blocking temperature the magnetization of the pinned layer will no longer be pinned in the desired direction. This will lead to a change in the SV sensor's response to an externally applied magnetic field, and thus to errors in data read back from the disk.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">It can be seen that there is a need for a method for providing a differential GMR sensor and GMR sensor that is smaller and more sensitive.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">To overcome the limitations in the prior art described above, and to overcome other limitations that will become apparent upon reading and understanding the present specification, the present invention discloses a method for providing a self-pinned differential GMR sensor and self-pinned differential GMR sensor.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The present invention solves the above-described problems by providing a differential GMR head that eliminates the need for antiferromagnetic (AFM) pinning layers.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">A method in accordance with the principles of the present invention includes forming a first shield and first gap layer, forming a first self-pinned GMR sensor having a first pinned layer, a first spacer layer and a first free layer, forming a bias structure over the first free layer, wherein the bias structure is formed to provide antiparallel magnetizations for the first and second free layers without using an antiferromagnetic layer and forming a second self-pinned GMR sensor having a second pinned layer, a second spacer layer and a second free layer.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In another embodiment of the present invention, a differential GMR sensor is provided. The differential GMR sensor includes a first self-pinned GMR sensor having a first pinned layer, a first spacer layer and a first free layer, a bias structure over the first free layer, wherein the bias structure is formed to provide antiparallel magnetizations for the first and second free layers without using an antiferromagnetic layer and a second self-pinned GMR sensor having a second pinned layer, a second spacer layer and a second free layer.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In another embodiment of the present invention, a magnetic disk recording system is provided. The magnetic disk recording system includes a magnetic storage medium having a plurality of tracks for recording of data and a magnetic transducer maintained in a closely spaced position relative to the magnetic storage medium during relative motion between the magnetic transducer and the magnetic storage medium, the magnetic transducer including a magnetoresistive read sensor, the magnetoresistive read sensor further includes a first self-pinned GMR sensor having a first pinned layer, a first spacer layer and a first free layer, a bias structure over the first free layer, wherein the bias structure is formed to provide antiparallel magnetizations for the first and second free layers without using an antiferromagnetic layer and a second self-pinned GMR sensor having a second pinned layer, a second spacer layer and a second free layer.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In another embodiment of the present invention, another differential GMR sensor is provided. This differential GMR sensor includes first means having a first pinned layer, a first spacer layer and a first free layer, a second self-pinned GMR sensor having a second pinned layer, a second spacer layer and a second free layer and means for biasing the first and second pinned layers to provide antiparallel magnetizations for the first and second free layers without using an antiferromagnetic layer.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">These and various other advantages and features of novelty which characterize the invention are pointed out with particularity in the claims annexed hereto and form a part hereof. However, for a better understanding of the invention, its advantages, and the objects obtained by its use, reference should be made to the drawings which form a further part hereof, and to accompanying descriptive matter, in which there are illustrated and described specific examples of an apparatus in accordance with the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Referring now to the drawings in which like reference numbers represent corresponding parts throughout:</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a storage system according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates one storage system according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a slider mounted on a suspension according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates an ABS view of the slider and the magnetic head according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates a differential spin valve read head <b>500</b> that employs first and second spin valve sensors;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a differential GMR head with self-pinned sensors according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a differential GMR head with synthetic free layers having antiparallel magnetizations according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a differential GMR head having an in-stack exchange bias structure according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates a differential GMR head having a gap layer structure according to an embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> illustrates a method for forming a differential GMR head according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In the following description of the embodiments, reference is made to the accompanying drawings that form a part hereof, and in which is shown by way of illustration the specific embodiments in which the invention may be practiced. It is to be understood that other embodiments may be utilized because structural changes may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The present invention provides a method for providing a self-pinned differential GMR sensor and self-pinned differential GMR sensor. The structure of the differential GMR head eliminates the need for antiferromagnetic (AFM) pinning layers.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an exemplary storage system <b>100</b> according to the present invention. A transducer <b>110</b> is under control of an actuator <b>120</b>, whereby the actuator <b>120</b> controls the position of the transducer <b>110</b>. The transducer <b>110</b> writes and reads data on magnetic media <b>130</b>. The read/write signals are passed to a data channel <b>140</b>. A signal processor <b>150</b> controls the actuator <b>120</b> and processes the signals of the data channel <b>140</b> for data exchange with external Input/Output (I/O) <b>170</b>. I/O <b>170</b> may provide, for example, data and control conduits for a desktop computing application, which utilizes storage system <b>100</b>. In addition, a media translator <b>160</b> is controlled by the signal processor <b>150</b> to cause the magnetic media <b>130</b> to move relative to the transducer <b>110</b>. The present invention is not meant to be limited to a particular type of storage system <b>100</b> or to the type of media <b>130</b> used in the storage system <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates one particular embodiment of a multiple magnetic disk storage system <b>200</b> according to the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a hard disk drive storage system <b>200</b> is shown. The system <b>200</b> includes a spindle <b>210</b> that supports and rotates multiple magnetic disks <b>220</b>. The spindle <b>210</b> is rotated by motor <b>280</b> that is controlled by motor controller <b>230</b>. A combined read and write magnetic head <b>270</b> is mounted on slider <b>260</b> that is supported by suspension <b>250</b> and actuator arm <b>240</b>. Processing circuitry exchanges signals that represent information with read/write magnetic head <b>270</b>, provides motor drive signals for rotating the magnetic disks <b>220</b>, and provides control signals for moving the slider <b>260</b> to various tracks. Although a multiple magnetic disk storage system is illustrated, a single magnetic disk storage system is equally viable in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The suspension <b>250</b> and actuator arm <b>240</b> position the slider <b>260</b> so that read/write magnetic head <b>270</b> is in a transducing relationship with a surface of magnetic disk <b>220</b>. When the magnetic disk <b>220</b> is rotated by motor <b>280</b>, the slider <b>240</b> is supported on a thin cushion of air (air bearing) between the surface of disk <b>220</b> and the ABS <b>290</b>. Read/write magnetic head <b>270</b> may then be employed for writing information to multiple circular tracks on the surface of magnetic disk <b>220</b>, as well as for reading information therefrom.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a sensor assembly <b>300</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a slider <b>320</b> is mounted on a suspension <b>322</b>. First and second solder connections <b>302</b> and <b>308</b> connect leads from the sensor <b>318</b> to leads <b>310</b> and <b>314</b>, respectively, on suspension <b>322</b> and third and fourth solder connections <b>304</b> and <b>306</b> connect to the write coil (not shown) to leads <b>312</b> and <b>316</b>, respectively, on suspension <b>322</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an ABS view of slider <b>400</b> and magnetic head <b>410</b>. The slider has a center rail <b>420</b> that supports the magnetic head <b>410</b>, and side rails <b>430</b> and <b>460</b>. The support rails <b>420</b>, <b>430</b> and <b>460</b> extend from a cross rail <b>440</b>. With respect to rotation of a magnetic disk, the cross rail <b>440</b> is at a leading edge <b>450</b> of slider <b>400</b> and the magnetic head <b>410</b> is at a trailing edge <b>470</b> of slider <b>400</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The above description of a typical magnetic recording disk drive system, shown in the accompanying <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref>, is for presentation purposes only. Storage systems may contain a large number of recording media and actuators, and each actuator may support a number of sliders. In addition, instead of an air-bearing slider, the head carrier may be one that maintains the head in contact or near contact with the disk, such as in liquid bearing and other contact and near-contact recording disk drives.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates a differential spin valve read head <b>500</b> that employs first and second spin valve sensors <b>530</b> and <b>532</b>. Spin valve sensors <b>530</b> and <b>532</b> are separated by a gap or insulation layer <b>534</b>, such as Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the first spin valve sensor <b>530</b> is connected in series with first and second leads <b>536</b> and <b>538</b>, and the second spin valve sensor <b>532</b> is connected in series with third and fourth leads <b>540</b> and <b>542</b>. The type of connections may be contiguous junctions, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The leads <b>538</b> and <b>542</b> may be interconnected to ground and the leads <b>536</b> and <b>540</b> may be connected across a differential amplifier <b>544</b> via first and second capacitors <b>546</b> and <b>548</b>. First and second sense current sources <b>550</b> and <b>552</b> are connected to the second and fourth leads <b>536</b> and <b>540</b> respectively so that a sense current I<sub>s </sub>is conducted through each of the spin valve sensors <b>530</b> and <b>532</b> to ground.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The spin valve sensors <b>530</b> and <b>532</b> are configured so as to produce response signals with opposite polarity so that the response signals can be differentially processed by the differential amplifier <b>544</b> to achieve common mode noise rejection. The differential amplifier <b>544</b> is part of the processing circuitry <b>150</b> or data channel <b>140</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The 180° out of phase response signals produced by the spin valve sensors <b>530</b> and <b>532</b> are added by the differential amplifier <b>544</b> while the common mode noise is cancelled.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The spin valve sensor <b>530</b> includes a first thin spacer layer <b>554</b>, which is sandwiched between a pinned layer <b>556</b> and a laminated free layer <b>558</b>. The spin valve sensor <b>532</b> includes a thin spacer layer <b>560</b>, which is sandwiched between a pinned layer <b>562</b> and a laminated free layer <b>564</b>. The spin valve sensor <b>530</b> further includes an antiferromagnetic layer (AFM) <b>566</b> which interfaces with the pinned layer <b>556</b> to pin its magnetic orientation into the paper by exchange coupling, as shown by the arrow <b>568</b>. In a like manner, the spin valve sensor <b>532</b> includes an antiferromagnetic layer (AFM) <b>570</b> which interfaces with the pinned layer <b>562</b> to orient the magnetization of the pinned layer into the paper by exchange coupling, as shown by the arrow <b>572</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The antiferromagnetic layers <b>566</b> and <b>570</b> may be constructed of the same material, such as FeMn, with the same blocking temperature, so that the magnetic orientations <b>568</b> and <b>572</b> are parallel with respect to one another and perpendicular to the ABS. Optionally, the magnetic orientations <b>568</b> and <b>572</b> could be directed out of the paper if desired. With this arrangement, the magnetic orientations of the antiferromagnetic layers <b>566</b> and <b>570</b> are established during fabrication by subjecting these layers to heat of 200 C. under a magnetic field, which is directed out of the paper.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The laminated free layer <b>558</b> includes a very thin ruthenium (Ru) layer <b>574</b>, which is sandwiched between first and second ferromagnetic free layers <b>576</b> and <b>578</b>. The laminated free layer <b>564</b> includes a very thin ruthenium (Ru) layer <b>580</b>, which is sandwiched between third and fourth ferromagnetic free layers <b>582</b> and <b>584</b>. There is a strong exchange coupling between the first and second ferromagnetic free layers <b>576</b> and <b>578</b> and between the ferromagnetic free layers <b>582</b> and <b>584</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In the differential spin valve read head <b>500</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the orientations of the magnetic moments of the second and third ferromagnetic free layers <b>578</b> and <b>582</b> are aligned parallel with respect to one another in the same direction parallel to the ABS during fabrication, such as shown by the magnetic moments <b>586</b> and <b>588</b>. Optionally, these magnetic moments could be aligned in an opposite direction. Since the second ferromagnetic free layer <b>578</b> is antiferromagnetically exchange coupled to the first ferromagnetic free layer <b>576</b>, the magnetic moment <b>590</b> of the first ferromagnetic free layer <b>576</b> is antiparallel to the magnetic moment <b>586</b>. In the same manner, since the third ferromagnetic free layer <b>582</b> is antiferromagnetically exchange coupled to the fourth ferromagnetic free layer <b>584</b>, the magnetic moment <b>592</b> of the fourth ferromagnetic free layer is antiparallel to the magnetic moment <b>588</b> of the third ferromagnetic free layer.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In a quiescent state of the read head <b>500</b>, namely during sense current conduction but no applied signal, the magnetic orientations of the free layers are as shown at <b>586</b>, <b>588</b>, <b>590</b> and <b>592</b>. Upon excitation by a field signal from a rotating disk, these magnetic moments will be rotated relative to the fixed magnetic moments <b>568</b> and <b>572</b> of the pinned layers <b>556</b> and <b>562</b>. The spin valve effect for the first spin valve <b>530</b> occurs only between the relative rotation of the magnetic moment <b>586</b> of the second ferromagnetic free layer <b>578</b> and the magnetic moment <b>568</b> of the pinned layer <b>556</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Since the first free layer <b>576</b> is located outside of the mean free path of the conduction electrons of the sense current, the rotation of its magnetic moment <b>590</b> has no influence upon the spin valve effect. In a like manner, it is the rotation of the magnetic moment <b>592</b> of the fourth ferromagnetic free layer <b>584</b> relative to the magnetic moment <b>572</b> of the pinned layer <b>562</b> which causes a spin valve effect for the spin valve sensor <b>532</b>. In a like manner, since the third ferromagnetic free layer <b>582</b> is beyond the mean free path of the conduction electrons of the sense current, the rotation of its magnetic moment <b>588</b> has no influence upon the spin valve effect.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">When encountering a magnetic field from a rotating disk, the thicker free layers <b>578</b> and <b>582</b> will rotate in the same direction. Since the thinner ferromagnetic free layers <b>576</b> and <b>584</b> are strongly exchange-coupled to the thicker layers <b>578</b> and <b>582</b>, their magnetic moments <b>590</b> and <b>592</b> will follow the magnetic moments <b>586</b> and <b>588</b> respectively. Free layer <b>1</b> <b>576</b> is rigidly antiparallel-coupled to free layer <b>2</b> <b>578</b> and similarly free layer <b>3</b> <b>582</b> is rigidly antiparallel-coupled to free layer <b>4</b> <b>584</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">These layers maintain antiparallel magnetization orientation while responding to magnetic fields. Assuming a magnetic field directed into the paper, the magnetic moment <b>586</b> of the second ferromagnetic free layer <b>578</b> will rotate into the paper toward saturation, as shown by the arrow <b>594</b>. When the magnetic moment <b>594</b> of the second ferromagnetic free layer is parallel to the magnetic moment <b>568</b> of the pinned layer <b>556</b>, the resistance of the spin valve sensor <b>530</b> is minimum. The magnetic moment <b>590</b> of the ferromagnetic free layer <b>576</b> will rotate in an opposite direction to the magnetic moment <b>586</b> of the second ferromagnetic free layer <b>578</b>, as shown by the arrow <b>596</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In a like manner, with an applied signal into the paper, the magnetic moment <b>588</b> of the third ferromagnetic free layer <b>582</b> will rotate into the paper toward saturation, as shown by the arrow <b>598</b>. The magnetic moment <b>592</b> of the fourth ferromagnetic free layer <b>584</b> will rotate out of the paper, as shown by the arrow <b>599</b>. Since the magnetic moment <b>599</b> of the fourth ferromagnetic free layer is out of the paper, and the magnetic moment <b>572</b> of the pinned layer <b>562</b> is into the paper, they are antiparallel and the resistance of the spin valve sensor <b>532</b> is at a maximum to the sense current. If the field signal from the rotating disk was out of the paper instead of into the paper, the arrows <b>594</b>, <b>596</b>, <b>598</b> and <b>599</b> would be reversed in direction.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Accordingly, when the spin valve read head <b>500</b> is subjected to a magnetic field of one polarity, the spin valve sensor <b>530</b> will produce a response signal of one polarity and the spin valve sensor <b>532</b> will produce a second signal of opposite polarity. The response signals are 180° out of phase with respect to one another and are differentially detected by the differential amplifier <b>544</b>, which combines the response, signals to produce an enhanced response signal free of the noise picked up by the sensors due to common mode noise rejection.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">While a differential GMR head provides an increased signal to noise ratio, the differential GMR head is significantly thicker than a single pinned spin valve sensor because of the thicknesses of the first and second pinning layers. While the thicknesses of the various layers of a typical spin valve sensor range between 10 Å-70 Å, the thicknesses of the antiferromagnetic pinning layers vary in a range from 120 Å-425 Å. Iridium manganese (IrMn) permits the thinnest antiferromagnetic pinning layer of about 120 Å whereas an antiferromagnetic pinning layer composed of nickel oxide (NiO) is typically 425 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Further, the range of blocking temperature for the interface at the antiferromagnetic layer is relatively low. These temperatures can be reached by certain thermal effects during operation of the disk drive, such as an increase in the ambient temperature inside the drive, heating of the SV sensor due to the bias current, and rapid heating of the SV sensor due to the head carrier contacting asperities on the disk. In addition, during assembly of the disk drive the SV sensor can be heated by current resulting from an electrostatic discharge. If any of these thermal effects cause the SV sensor to exceed the antiferromagnet's blocking temperature the magnetization of the pinned layer will no longer be pinned in the desired direction. This will lead to a change in the SV sensor's response to an externally applied magnetic field, and thus to errors in data read back from the disk.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Accordingly, a differential GMR head is needed that eliminates the need for antiferromagnetic (AFM) pinning layers. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a stack <b>600</b> representing a differential GMR head with self-pinned sensors according to an embodiment of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the differential GMR head <b>600</b> is simplified by using self-pinned GMR sensors <b>610</b>, <b>612</b> without antiferromagnetic (AFM) layers. The AFM layer is usually used to pin the direction of the reference (pinned) ferromagnetic layer, while the free, ferromagnetic layer rotates due to the magnetic field from the recording medium. However, the total spin valve thickness must significantly decrease, and the sensitivity and stability must increase for future heads. Because the AFM film is by far the thickest layer, reducing or eliminating this thickness is crucially important. This is especially true in a differential GMR head wherein two spin valve sensors are employed.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, first <b>610</b> and second <b>612</b> self-pinned GMR sensors are formed proximate to shield one <b>614</b> and shield two <b>616</b> respectively. Gap layers <b>618</b>, <b>620</b> are formed between the first <b>610</b> and second <b>612</b> self-pinned GMR sensors and the shields <b>614</b>, <b>616</b>. An in-stack stabilization structure <b>630</b> separates the first <b>610</b> and second <b>612</b> self-pinned GMR sensors. The in-stack stabilization structure <b>630</b> may include an AFM layer and thus may easily be set in the longitudinal direction indicated by arrow <b>670</b>. Those skilled in the art will recognize that the arrow could be set to point in the opposite direction. A seed layer <b>632</b> is formed between the bottom gap layer <b>618</b> and the bottom self-pinned GMR sensor <b>610</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The top self-pinned GMR sensor <b>612</b> includes a free layer <b>644</b>, a copper spacer <b>642</b> and a pinned layer <b>640</b>. The pinned layer <b>640</b> includes two ferromagnetic layers <b>652</b>, <b>654</b> and an interlayer <b>656</b>. The bottom self-pinned GMR sensor <b>610</b> includes a free layer <b>646</b>, a copper spacer <b>648</b> and a pinned layer <b>650</b>. The bottom pinned layer <b>650</b> is implemented using three ferromagnetic layers <b>658</b>, <b>660</b>, <b>662</b> and two interlayers <b>664</b>, <b>666</b> in the bottom self-pinned GMR sensor <b>610</b>. The bottom ferromagnetic layer <b>662</b> of the bottom spin valve <b>610</b> and the top ferromagnetic layer <b>652</b> of the top spin valve <b>612</b> are set using a high field reset allowing 180° magnetization phase between the pinned layers <b>656</b>, <b>658</b> that are next to the copper layers <b>642</b>, <b>648</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a stack <b>700</b> representing a differential GMR head with synthetic free layers having antiparallel magnetizations according to an embodiment of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, first <b>710</b> and second <b>712</b> self-pinned GMR sensors are formed proximate to shield one <b>714</b> and shield two <b>716</b> respectively. Gap layers <b>718</b>, <b>720</b> are formed between the first <b>710</b> and second <b>712</b> self-pinned GMR sensors and the shields <b>714</b>, <b>716</b>. An in-stack stabilization structure <b>730</b> separates the first <b>710</b> and second <b>712</b> self-pinned GMR sensors. Again, the in-stack stabilization structure <b>730</b> may include an AFM layer and thus may easily be set in the longitudinal direction indicated by arrow <b>770</b>. Those skilled in the art will recognize that the arrow could be set to point in the opposite direction. A seed layer <b>732</b> is formed between the bottom gap layer <b>718</b> and the bottom self-pinned GMR sensor <b>710</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The top self-pinned GMR sensor <b>712</b> includes a synthetic free layer <b>744</b>, a copper spacer <b>742</b> and a pinned layer <b>740</b>. The bottom self-pinned GMR sensor <b>710</b> includes a synthetic free layer <b>746</b>, a copper spacer <b>748</b> and a pinned layer <b>750</b>. The synthetic free layers <b>744</b>, <b>746</b> include first free layers <b>772</b>, <b>771</b>, interlayers <b>774</b>, <b>776</b> and second free layers <b>778</b>, <b>780</b>. The synthetic free layers <b>744</b>, <b>746</b> are set 180° out of phase by in-stack exchange stabilization <b>730</b>. The bias of the in-stack exchange bias structure <b>730</b> achieves 180° out of phase bias through arrangement of the bias layers. The net magnetostatic bias from the pinned layers <b>760</b>/<b>758</b> and <b>752</b>/<b>754</b> is set to zero. It is also possible to achieve 180° out of phase biasing using opposite sign of exchange bias, either by spacer <b>756</b>/<b>764</b> thickness selection or material selection, e.g., Ru, Cu, etc. The pinned layers <b>740</b>, <b>750</b> are self-pinned for both top <b>712</b> and bottom <b>710</b> sensors—either by magnetostriction/stress or H<sub>c </sub>pinned. The thicknesses of the synthetic free layers <b>744</b>, <b>746</b> are selected to provide differential operation together with in-phase pinned layers <b>740</b>, <b>750</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a stack <b>800</b> representing a differential GMR head having an in-stack exchange bias structure according to an embodiment of the present invention. The in-stack exchange bias structure <b>830</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> achieves antiparallel magnetizations for the free layers <b>844</b> without using antiferromagnetic layer in the bias structure <b>830</b>. The in-stack exchange bias structure <b>830</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> also allows changing the gap length.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, first <b>810</b> and second <b>812</b> self-pinned GMR sensors are formed proximate to shield one <b>814</b> and shield two <b>816</b> respectively. The first <b>810</b> and second <b>812</b> self-pinned GMR sensors include pinned layers <b>840</b>, <b>850</b>, spacers <b>842</b>, <b>848</b> and free layers <b>844</b>, <b>846</b>. Gap layers <b>818</b>, <b>820</b> are formed between the first <b>810</b> and second <b>812</b> self-pinned GMR sensors and the shields <b>814</b>, <b>816</b>. A seed layer <b>832</b> is formed between the bottom gap layer <b>818</b> and the bottom self-pinned GMR sensor <b>810</b>. The in-stack exchange bias structure <b>830</b> separates the first <b>810</b> and second <b>812</b> self-pinned GMR sensors. The in-stack exchange bias structure <b>830</b> includes four ferromagnetic layers <b>882</b>, <b>883</b>, <b>884</b>, <b>885</b>, such as NiFe, separated by interlayers <b>886</b>, <b>887</b>, <b>888</b>, such as Ru.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The net moment of the in-stack exchange bias structure <b>830</b> is chosen to be zero. The Ni content of the ferromagnetic layers <b>882</b>, <b>883</b>, <b>884</b>, <b>885</b> is preferably greater than 90%. The stress induced magnetic anisotropy of the ferromagnetic layers <b>882</b>, <b>883</b>, <b>884</b>, <b>885</b> achieves pinning parallel to the air bearing surface. The in- stack exchange bias structure <b>830</b> provides antiparallel magnetizations of the free layers <b>844</b>, <b>846</b> through exchange coupling. The thickness of the in-stack exchange bias structure <b>830</b> can be tailored by selecting an even number of ferromagnetic layers <b>882</b>, <b>883</b>, <b>884</b>, <b>885</b>. Removal of antiferromagnet (AFM) from the in-stack exchange bias structure <b>830</b> removes unwanted series resistance as well as makes setting of the ferromagnetic layers <b>882</b>, <b>883</b>, <b>884</b>, <b>885</b> easier. The thicknesses of the spacer layers <b>888</b>/<b>886</b> should be selected to provide the desired bias.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a stack <b>900</b> representing a differential GMR head having a gap layer structure according to an embodiment of the present invention. The intermediate gap layer structure <b>930</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention achieves a high dR/R for the top GMR sensor <b>912</b> as well as providing less current shunting. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, first <b>910</b> and second <b>912</b> self-pinned GMR sensors are formed proximate to shield one <b>914</b> and shield two <b>916</b> respectively. Gap layers <b>918</b>, <b>920</b> are formed between the first <b>910</b> and second <b>912</b> self-pinned GMR sensors and the shields <b>914</b>, <b>916</b>. A seed layer <b>932</b> is formed between the top gap layer <b>920</b> and the top self-pinned GMR sensor <b>912</b>. An intermediate gap layer <b>930</b> separates the first <b>910</b> and second <b>912</b> self-pinned GMR sensors. The intermediate gap layer has a structure defined as Ta/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>/NiFeCr/CuO<sub>x</sub>990-993. The bottom GMR sensor <b>910</b> is disposed over an antiferromagnet layer <b>994</b>. The Antiferromagnet layer <b>994</b> is disposed over a cap layer <b>996</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> illustrates a method <b>1000</b> for forming a differential GMR head according to an embodiment of the present invention. The method described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> includes features from all of the embodiments described above. However, one skilled in the art will recognize that the method for forming a differential GMR head according to embodiments of the present invention is not meant to require every feature shown.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, a first shield and gap layer are formed. A first GMR sensor is formed <b>1010</b>. The first GMR sensor includes a pinned layer implemented using three ferromagnetic layers <b>1020</b> to provide 180° magnetization phase between the pinned layers that are next to the spacer layers. The first GMR sensor also includes a spacer layer and a free layer <b>1030</b>. The free layer includes a first free layer an interlayer and a second free layer. A gap layer is formed over the first GMR sensor <b>1040</b>. The gap layer provides an in-stack exchange bias structure that provides antiparallel magnetizations for the free layers without using antiferromagnetic layer. The gap layer may include four ferromagnetic layers such as NiFe separated by an interlayer such as Ru. The gap layer may alternatively includes a layer have a structure of Ta/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>/NiFeCr/CuO<sub>x</sub>. A second GMR sensor is formed over the gap layer. The second GMR sensor includes a pinned layer implemented using three ferromagnetic layers <b>1050</b> to provide <b>1800</b> magnetization phase between the pinned layers that are next to the spacer layers. The second GMR sensor also includes a spacer layer and a free layer <b>1060</b>. The free layer includes a first free layer, an interlayer and a second free layer.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The foregoing description of the exemplary embodiment of the invention has been presented for the purposes of illustration and description. It is not intended to be exhaustive or to limit the invention to the precise form disclosed. Many modifications and variations are possible in light of the above teaching. It is intended that the scope of the invention be limited not with this detailed description, but rather by the claims appended hereto.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A differential GMR sensor, comprising:
<claim-text>a first self-pinned GMR sensor having a first pinned layer, a first spacer layer and a first free layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second self-pinned GMR sensor having a second pinned layer, a second spacer layer and a second free layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bias structure disposed between the first free layer of the first self-pinned GMR sensor and the second free layer of the second self-pinned GMR sensor, wherein the bias structure is configured to provide antiparallel magnetizations for the first and second free layers without using an antiferromagnetic layer, wherein the bias structure further comprises four ferromagnetic layers separated with three interlayers.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the four ferromagnetic layers separated with three interlayers are selected to provide a desired gap length.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the four ferromagnetic layers further comprise four NiFe layers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the four NiFe layers comprise a nickel composition of 90%.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the three interlayers further comprise ruthenium.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A magnetic disk recording system, comprising:
<claim-text>a magnetic storage medium having a plurality of tracks for recording of data; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a magnetic transducer maintained in a closely spaced position relative to the magnetic storage medium during relative motion between the magnetic transducer and the magnetic storage medium, the magnetic transducer including a magnetoresistive read sensor, the magnetoresistive read sensor further comprising:
<claim-text>a first self-pinned GMR sensor having a first pinned layer, a first spacer layer and a first free layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second self-pinned GMR sensor having a second pinned layer, a second spacer layer and a second free layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bias structure disposed between the first free layer of the first self-pinned GMR sensor and the second free layer of the second self-pinned GMR sensor, wherein the bias structure is configured to provide antiparallel magnetizations for the first and second free layers without using an antiferromagnetic layer, wherein the bias structure further comprises four ferromagnetic layers separated with three interlayers.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The magnetic disk recording system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the four ferromagnetic layers separated with three interlayers are selected to provide a desired gap length.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The magnetic disk recording system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the four ferromagnetic layers further comprise four NiFe layers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The magnetic disk recording system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the four NiFe layers comprise a nickel composition of 90%.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The magnetic disk recording system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the three interlayers further comprise ruthenium.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
