<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298612-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298612</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11259467</doc-number>
<date>20051025</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>70</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361685</main-classification>
<further-classification>720601</further-classification>
<further-classification>370364</further-classification>
<further-classification>361695</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Server with vertical drive arrangement</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6614652</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>White et al.</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361684</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6785132</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Medin et al.</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0259395</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Espinoza-Ibarra et al.</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361695</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2007/0006239</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kasahara et al.</name>
<date>20070100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>720601</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>720601</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370364</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361695-697</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361679-687</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361724-727</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>12</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>15</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070091559</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070426</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Malone</last-name>
<first-name>Christopher G.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Loomis</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hewlett-Packard Development Company, L.P.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Houston</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Duong</last-name>
<first-name>Hung Van</first-name>
<department>2835</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A planar backplane is arranged in a horizontal orientation in a server configured for rack mounting. The planar backplane is configured to accept and mount a plurality of disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="67.48mm" wi="152.99mm" file="US07298612-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="152.57mm" wi="174.67mm" file="US07298612-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="213.28mm" wi="177.72mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298612-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="186.10mm" wi="173.48mm" file="US07298612-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="149.86mm" wi="176.61mm" file="US07298612-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="205.82mm" wi="177.72mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298612-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="165.44mm" wi="80.77mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298612-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="158.16mm" wi="90.76mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298612-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="157.56mm" wi="116.08mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298612-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="248.24mm" wi="164.76mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298612-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="174.67mm" wi="167.22mm" file="US07298612-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="145.12mm" wi="175.68mm" file="US07298612-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="183.98mm" wi="137.24mm" file="US07298612-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Rack-optimized servers can have severe volumetric constraints resulting from market demand for multiple features and extensive functionality implemented within a chassis with a limited vertical height and limited depth. For example, a chassis is configured to house hard disk drives, Peripheral Component Interconnect (PCI) cards, processors, memory, and others. Chassis depth is commonly defined and limited by cable management constraints. For example, standard 36-inch deep racks may be the maximum allowable in light of bulkiness and/or electromagnetic interference reduction for rack input/output and power cable constraints.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Typically, hard disk drives make electrical and power connection to server electronics via a vertical backplane as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref>. The arrangement consumes a significant amount of the total available chassis depth due to the alignment of the longest dimension of the hard disk drive with chassis depth. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A and 9B</figref> show approximate volumes of two standard versions of hard disk drives used in servers. For example, a conventional four-inch format drive has a longest dimension or length (L<sub>4</sub>) of 7.3 inches, a width (W<sub>4</sub>) of 4.3 inches, and a thickness (T<sub>4</sub>) of 1.05 inches. A conventional 2.5 format drive has a longest dimension or length (L<sub>2.5</sub>) of 5.9 inches, a width (W<sub>2.5</sub>) of 3 inches, and a thickness (T<sub>2.5</sub>) of 0.62 inches. A typical arrangement may have a 0.045 inch gap between drives.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A further difficulty with the conventional vertical backplane arrangement is that the backplane is a solid impediment positioned essentially perpendicular to airflow pathways of cooling fans. Accordingly, the vertical backplane forms a blockage which obstructs airflow, creating a significant airflow resistance.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In accordance with an embodiment of a server, a planar backplane is arranged in a horizontal orientation in a server configured for rack mounting. The planar backplane is configured to accept and mount a plurality of disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Embodiments of the invention relating to both structure and method of operation may best be understood by referring to the following description and accompanying drawings:</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, and <b>1</b>C are perspective, side, and frontal pictorial diagrams respectively illustrating an embodiment of a server internally arranged for vertical alignment of components enabling a dense architecture;</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective pictorial diagram showing an embodiment of a server implementing a double-sided backplane arranged to increase disk drive capacity;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A</figref>, <b>3</b>B, and <b>3</b>C are perspective, side, and frontal pictorial diagrams respectively depicting another embodiment of a server with one or more disk drives installed;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective pictorial diagram illustrating another embodiment of a server with a densely-arranged configuration of disk drives;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a perspective pictorial view showing a server with multiple disk drive connectors coupled to the top and bottom surfaces of the planar backplane and configured to hold disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement on both sides of the planar backplane;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a perspective pictorial view depicting a server with multiple disk drives coupled on both sides of a planar backplane in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a pictorial drawing illustrating an embodiment of a disk drive connector engagement apparatus including a four-bar linkage adapted to couple to a server housing;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a schematic pictorial diagram which shows a side view of a server including four-bar linkage connectors for engaging and disengaging disk drives; and</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A</figref>, <b>9</b>B, and <b>9</b>C, labeled PRIOR ART, are pictorial diagrams respectively showing a conventional server with horizontally-oriented disk drives and format of two conventional disk drives that are commonly installed for storage in a server.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A server has a novel hard disk drive arrangement in which hard disk drives are vertically-oriented and connected to the server via a horizontal backplane.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, and <b>1</b>C, perspective, side, and frontal pictorial diagrams respectively illustrate an embodiment of a server <b>100</b> which is internally arranged for vertical alignment of components enabling a dense architecture. The server <b>100</b> comprises a planar backplane <b>102</b> adapted for operation in a horizontal orientation in the server <b>100</b> which is configured for rack mounting. The server <b>100</b> further comprises a plurality of disk drive connectors <b>104</b> coupled to the planar backplane <b>102</b> and configured to hold disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In some arrangements, disk drives configured for vertical alignment in the server <b>100</b> are added or removed from the server <b>100</b> through top or bottom doors, covers, or panels on the server chassis, for example by sliding the drives into position similar to the manner of entry of horizontal drives into a conventional server. In other embodiments, the server <b>100</b> may be designed to facilitate installation and removal of disk drives from an entry way on a side of the server <b>100</b>, for instance through a frontal orifice entry to the server interior. For example, hard disk drives can be inserted and removed from the front of the server using a four-bar linkage <b>106</b> which enables a drive to move with essentially pure horizontal motion while passing the drive into and out of the server <b>100</b> during installation and removal, and enables the drive to move with essentially pure vertical translations while engaging and disengaging the electrical and power connections by rotating a lever. The essentially pure horizontal motion and vertical translation have only minor incidental displacement in the direction outside the plane of the essentially pure motion.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Accordingly, the server <b>100</b> may further comprise one or more four-bar linkages <b>106</b> coupled to the planar backplane <b>102</b> and adapted to insert and remove disk drives from the disk drive connectors <b>104</b>. The four-bar linkage <b>106</b> enables the disk drives to be installed and removed via a horizontal motion and engaged and disengaged via a vertical motion, facilitating drive access in a compact structure.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The configuration enables disk drives to be mounted aligning the disk drives' maximum dimension, the length, in the vertical orientation whereby server depth is reduced or minimized.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, and <b>1</b>C show a configuration in which drives can be loaded on one side of the backplane <b>102</b>. The concept of a backplane arranged in a horizontal plane may be extended so that drives may be loaded on both sides of the backplane in conditions of sufficient vertical clearance. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a perspective pictorial diagram illustrates an embodiment of a server <b>200</b> which implements a double-sided backplane <b>202</b> arranged to increase disk drive capacity. The double-sided backplane <b>202</b> has a plurality of disk drive connectors <b>204</b> coupled to the top and bottom surfaces of the planar backplane <b>202</b>. The disk drive connectors <b>204</b> are configured to hold disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement on both sides of the planar backplane <b>202</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The longest dimension of a disk drive is aligned in the vertical direction to conserve product depth, enabling, if desired, the conserved space to be used for other features. Conservation of product depth is highly valuable in many applications, for example Network Equipment Building Systems (NEBS) class products which have a stringent limited depth specification.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A</figref>, <b>3</b>B, and <b>3</b>C, perspective, side, and frontal pictorial diagrams illustrate another embodiment of a server <b>300</b> with one or more disk drives <b>308</b> installed. The server <b>300</b> may further comprise a chassis <b>310</b> configured to contain the disk drives <b>308</b> and a planar backplane <b>302</b>. The server <b>300</b> may further comprise one or more disk drives <b>308</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The server <b>300</b> may be configured with the planar backplane <b>302</b> arranged as a printed circuit assembly <b>312</b>. Usage of the horizontal board <b>302</b> for hard disk drive connections may enable all functionality to be supported in an implementation with only a single printed circuit assembly <b>312</b>, a configuration which may be produced at lower cost.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In a specific embodiment, a single printed circuit assembly <b>312</b> is populated with integrated circuits and devices which support all desired server functionality so that the server <b>300</b> is fully operational with only the single printed circuit assembly <b>312</b> installed.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The illustrative server <b>300</b> is arranged with one or more fans <b>314</b> positioned to direct airflow horizontally across the horizontally-oriented planar backplane <b>302</b>. The fans <b>314</b> generate airflow pathways flowing laterally through the chassis <b>310</b>, thereby cooling integrated circuits on the printed circuit assembly <b>312</b> and cooling the hard disk drives <b>308</b>. The horizontal backplane <b>302</b> avoids obstruction of the airflow pathways and enables a lower airflow resistance in comparison to the conventional vertical backplane. The horizontal backplane <b>302</b> enables higher airflow rates and/or usage of lower cost, lower performance fans for server thermal systems.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a perspective pictorial diagram illustrates another embodiment of a server <b>400</b> with a densely-arranged configuration of disk drives <b>408</b>. The dense structure is formed by arranging a planar backplane <b>402</b> in a horizontal orientation in a server <b>400</b> which is configured for rack mounting. The planar backplane <b>402</b> is designed to accept and mount disk drives <b>408</b> in a vertical orientation in the dense server arrangement. The server <b>400</b> comprises a chassis <b>410</b> and a single printed circuit assembly <b>412</b> mounted interior to the chassis <b>410</b>. The printed circuit assembly <b>412</b> comprises a planar backplane <b>402</b> adapted for operation in a horizontal orientation. The server <b>400</b> further includes one or more disk drives attached in a vertical orientation on the planar backplane <b>402</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The illustrative chassis <b>410</b> is configured to address volumetric constraints to support a wide variety of features inside the chassis <b>410</b>, for example including hard disk drives <b>408</b>, interfaces, processors, memory, and others in a minimum vertical height. Accordingly, the chassis <b>410</b> is designed to contain multiple disk drives <b>408</b> and the planar backplane <b>402</b>. The server <b>400</b> depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is designed in a reduced-cost implementation by arranging the horizontally-oriented planar backplane <b>402</b> as a printed circuit assembly <b>412</b> and configuring the server <b>400</b> to be fully functional with only the single printed circuit assembly <b>412</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The illustrative planar backplane <b>402</b> is configured to hold the disk drives <b>408</b> in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement. For example, the server <b>400</b> may be designed so that the disk drives <b>408</b> are mounted with the maximum disk drive dimension aligned in the vertical orientation, thereby reducing or minimizing server depth.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">A conventional server <b>900</b>, as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref>, hard disk drives <b>908</b> make electrical and power connections to server electronics via a vertical backplane <b>902</b>. Disk drives <b>908</b> are typically installed into the server <b>900</b> by inserting the drives <b>908</b> into sockets in the vertical backplane <b>902</b> by horizontal motion from an opened side of the server <b>900</b> and pressing the drives <b>908</b> into the sockets with a suitable horizontally-directed force, typically a manual force. Servers implementing the horizontal backplanes shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, <b>1</b>C, <b>2</b>, <b>3</b>A, <b>3</b>B, <b>3</b>C, <b>5</b>, and <b>6</b> support a larger number of hard disk drives with elevated density in comparison to the conventional arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, although some embodiments of a server may enable access to the server interior via doors or openings on top or bottom server panels, generally the server interior access is most convenient and efficient by doors on the front of the server <b>500</b>. Doors on the server sides or back surfaces may also or alternatively supply interior access, typically with less convenience than frontal access, although more convenient than top or bottom surface doors.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Vertical insertion forces for mounting the vertically-oriented disk drives <b>508</b> may be difficult to apply for disk drives <b>508</b> inserted from doors on the front, back, or sides of the server <b>500</b>. Accordingly, the server <b>500</b> can be designed with one or more four-bar linkages <b>506</b> couple to the planar backplane <b>502</b>. Four-bar linkage elements <b>506</b> may be positioned to facilitate insertion and removal of disk drives <b>508</b> from disk drive connectors <b>504</b>. The illustrative server <b>500</b> has one or more disk drive connectors <b>504</b> with associated four-bar linkage elements <b>506</b> coupled to the planar backplane <b>502</b>. The four-bar linkage elements <b>506</b> are adapted to insert and remove disk drives from the disk drive connectors <b>504</b>, enabling the disk drives <b>508</b> to be installed and removed via a horizontal motion and engaged and disengaged via a vertical motion.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The horizontal backplane <b>502</b> reduces airflow resistance in comparison to the conventional arrangement which implements the backplane in a vertical plane. One or more fans <b>514</b> are arranged to direct airflow horizontally across the horizontally-oriented planar backplane <b>502</b>. Fans <b>514</b> may be arranged in a configuration that propels airflow through spatial planes between the disk drives <b>508</b> and horizontally across the horizontally-oriented planar backplane <b>502</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In a design with sufficient vertical clearance, a horizontal backplane may be designed to mount disk drives on both top and bottom surfaces of the backplane. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a perspective pictorial view shows a server <b>600</b> with a plurality of disk drive connectors <b>604</b> coupled to the top and bottom surfaces of the planar backplane <b>602</b> and configured to hold disk drives <b>608</b> in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement on both sides of the planar backplane <b>602</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a pictorial drawing illustrates an embodiment of a disk drive connector engagement apparatus <b>700</b> including a four-bar linkage <b>702</b> adapted to couple to a server housing. The four-bar linkage <b>702</b> is configured to accept and enable a disk drive <b>704</b> to travel in a first direction <b>706</b> until a connector <b>708</b> on the disk drive <b>704</b> and a corresponding backplane or midplane connector or socket <b>710</b> coupled to the housing are aligned. The four-bar linkage <b>702</b> further enables the disk drive <b>704</b> to travel essentially orthogonal <b>712</b> to the first direction to engage the connector <b>708</b> with the socket <b>710</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">By definition, a four-bar linkage assembly has four axes of rotation connected by four rigid linkages.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In a particular example, the four-bar linkage <b>702</b> further includes a base link <b>714</b> that can be firmly affixed to the housing and forms a stationary link of the four-bar linkage <b>702</b>. The four-bar linkage <b>702</b> also includes first <b>716</b> and second <b>718</b> rotating links, each of which is pivotally coupled to the base link <b>714</b> at pivots or hinges <b>720</b> and <b>722</b>, respectively, and form movable levers of the four-bar linkage <b>702</b>. At least one of the levers <b>716</b>, <b>718</b> is accessible for manipulation and rotation to engage and disengage the connector <b>708</b> from the socket <b>710</b>. The four-bar linkage <b>702</b> also has a coupler link <b>724</b> that is pivotally coupled to the first <b>716</b> and second <b>718</b> rotating links at pivots or hinges <b>726</b> and <b>728</b> and functions as a board guide for the disk drive <b>704</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The illustrative four-bar linkage <b>702</b> has slots <b>730</b> formed in the coupler link <b>724</b> configured to engage with pins and/or rollers <b>732</b> on the disk drive <b>704</b>. The pins or rollers <b>732</b> transfer forces from the four-bar linkage <b>702</b> to the connector <b>708</b> The four-bar linkage <b>702</b> is configured so that rotation of an accessible lever, for example rotating link <b>716</b>, translates the disk drive <b>704</b> in the first direction <b>706</b> and the orthogonal direction <b>712</b> so that pins <b>734</b> coupled to the disk drive <b>704</b> engage with corresponding apertures <b>736</b> in the housing, preventing further translation in the first direction <b>706</b>, aligning the connector <b>708</b> and socket <b>710</b>, and causing additional rotation of the accessible lever <b>716</b> to result in orthogonal motion alone to fully engage the connector <b>708</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The slots <b>730</b> have sufficient length to enable the disk drive <b>704</b> to be located in approximate alignment with the housing connector or socket <b>710</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In various embodiments, a four-bar linkage can be configured to engage a single connector to a single socket or multiple connectors on the disk drive to multiple sockets in the housing.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, a schematic pictorial diagram illustrates a side view of a server <b>800</b> that includes four-bar linkage connectors <b>802</b> for engaging and disengaging disk drives <b>804</b>. A connector apparatus <b>802</b> includes a backplane or midplane socket <b>806</b> configured to couple to a first surface <b>808</b> of a server housing <b>810</b> and a four-bar linkage <b>812</b>. The four-bar linkage <b>812</b> can be coupled to a second surface <b>814</b> of the server housing <b>810</b> that is substantially parallel with and opposing the first surface <b>808</b>. The four-bar linkage <b>812</b> is configured to accept and enable a disk drive <b>804</b> to travel in a first direction <b>816</b> until a connector <b>802</b> on the disk drive <b>804</b> and the socket <b>806</b> are aligned, enabling the disk drive <b>804</b> to travel essentially orthogonal <b>818</b> to the first direction <b>816</b> to engage the connector <b>802</b> with the socket <b>806</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In the illustrative embodiment, the housing <b>810</b> is configured to accept a multiple disk drive <b>804</b> in a vertical layout so that vertical disk drives <b>804</b> connect to a horizontal backplane or midplane <b>820</b> coupled to the housing <b>810</b> with disk drives <b>804</b> loaded into the housing <b>810</b> from the front and/or rear of the housing <b>810</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The illustrative server <b>800</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> has sockets <b>806</b> positioned to receive disk drives <b>804</b> in both the front and rear portions of the housing <b>810</b> so that multiple disk drives <b>804</b> can be connected to the midplane or backplane <b>820</b> in multiple side-by-side columns and forward and rear rows. The illustrative server <b>800</b> has sockets <b>806</b> connected on both top and bottom sides of the horizontal midplane or backplane <b>820</b> so that the columns and rows of disk drives <b>804</b> can be inserted both above and below the midplane or backplane <b>820</b>. Other configurations may accept more rows of disk drives or accept only a single row. Some configurations may accept disk drives on only a single side of the backplane.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The second surface <b>814</b> of the housing <b>810</b> forms a base or stationary link of the four-bar linkage <b>812</b>. The four-bar linkage <b>812</b> further includes rotating links <b>822</b> and <b>824</b> that are pivotally coupled to the base link <b>814</b> and function as movable levers for manipulation and rotation, enabling engagement and disengagement of the disk drive connectors <b>802</b> from the sockets <b>806</b>. A coupler link <b>826</b> is also pivotally coupled to the rotating links <b>822</b>, <b>824</b> to complete the four-bar linkage <b>812</b> and operate as a disk drive guide. The four-bar linkage <b>812</b> is constructed to accommodate a disk drive <b>804</b>, for example using slots <b>828</b> formed in the coupled link <b>826</b> in a geometry and position that enable engagement with pins and/or rollers <b>830</b> on a disk drive <b>804</b> that is configured for acceptance by the four-bar linkage <b>812</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The four-bar linkage <b>812</b> has a form that enables functionality in facilitating engagement and disengagement of a disk drive <b>804</b> from a socket <b>806</b>. The rotating links <b>822</b>, <b>824</b> include at least one lever that is accessible for manipulation. On rotation of the accessible lever, the disk drive is translated in a first direction <b>816</b>, in the illustrative embodiment in a horizontal direction into the housing <b>810</b>, and also in a direction <b>818</b> orthogonal to the first direction. Structures in the disk drives <b>804</b>, for example guide pins, can be used to arrest the horizontal movement of the disk drive so that additional rotation of the lever causes the orthogonal, or vertical, motion alone to fully engage the connector <b>802</b> with the socket <b>806</b>. In various embodiments, the disk drives may have single connectors or multiple connectors, and similarly single or multiple sockets may be configured to accept the connector or connectors.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">While the present disclosure describes various embodiments, these embodiments are to be understood as illustrative and do not limit the claim scope. Many variations, modifications, additions and improvements of the described embodiments are possible. For example, those having ordinary skill in the art will readily implement the steps necessary to provide the structures and methods disclosed herein, and will understand that the process parameters, materials, and dimensions are given by way of example only. The parameters, materials, and dimensions can be varied to achieve the desired structure as well as modifications, which are within the scope of the claims. Variations and modifications of the embodiments disclosed herein may also be made while remaining within the scope of the following claims. For example, a few specific examples of horizontal-backplane servers are depicted. Any suitable architecture may be implemented, for example including multiple horizontal backplanes within a single chassis or a system with multiple columns of horizontal backplanes. The illustrative techniques may be used with any suitable data center configuration and with any suitable servers, computers, and devices.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In the claims, unless otherwise indicated the article “a” is to refer to “one or more than one.”</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A server comprising:
<claim-text>a planar backplane mounted in a horizontal orientation in a rack mount server; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of disk drive connectors mounted to and extending vertically from the planar backplane that connect disk drives to the planar backplane and hold the disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of disk drive connectors coupled to the top and bottom surfaces of the planar backplane that connect the disk drives to the planar backplane and hold the disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement on both sides of the planar backplane.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the disk drives are mounted aligning a maximum disk drive dimension in the vertical orientation whereby server depth is minimized.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>at least one disk drive; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a chassis configured to contain the at least one disk drive and the planar backplane.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the planar backplane is arranged as a printed circuit assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the server includes only the single printed circuit assembly.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>at least one fan arranged to direct airflow horizontally across the horizontally-oriented planar backplane.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A server comprising:
<claim-text>a planar backplane adapted for operation in a horizontal orientation in a server configured for rack mounting;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of disk drive connectors coupled to the planar backplane and configured to hold disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one four-bar linkage coupled to the planar backplane and adapted to insert and remove disk drives from the disk drive connectors, enabling the disk drives to be installed and removed via a horizontal motion and engaged and disengaged via a vertical motion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A server comprising:
<claim-text>a chassis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a single printed circuit assembly mounted interior to the chassis, the printed circuit assembly further comprising a planar backplane mounted in a horizontal orientation; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one disk drive mounted to the planar backplane and attached in a vertical orientation on the planar backplane.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the planar backplane connects the at least one disk drive to the planar backplane to hold the at least one disk drive in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of disk drive connectors coupled to the top and bottom surfaces of the planar backplane that connect the disk drives to the planar backplane and hold the disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement on both sides of the planar backplane.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the disk drives are mounted aligning a maximum disk drive dimension in the vertical orientation whereby server depth is minimized.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The server according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>at least one fan arranged to direct airflow horizontally across the horizontally-oriented planar backplane in airflow channels between the vertically oriented disk drives whereby flow resistance is reduced.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A server comprising:
<claim-text>a chassis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a single printed circuit assembly mounted interior to the chassis, the printed circuit assembly further comprising a planar backplane adapted for operation in a horizontal orientation;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one disk drive attached in a vertical orientation on planar backplane; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one four-bar linkage coupled to the planar backplane and adapted to insert and remove disk drives from the disk drive connectors, enabling the disk drives to be installed and removed via a horizontal motion and engaged and disengaged via a vertical motion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method comprising:
<claim-text>arranging a planar backplane in a horizontal orientation in a rack mount server; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>configuring the planar backplane to connect to and mount a plurality of disk drives on at least one planar side of the planar backplane in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>configuring the planar backplane to connect to and mount the plurality of disk drives on at least one planar side of the planar backplane in a vertical orientation on top and bottom planar backplane surfaces.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>configuring the planar backplane to connect to and mount the plurality of disk drives on at least one planar side of the planar backplane in an alignment with a maximum disk drive dimension in the vertical orientation whereby server depth is minimized.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>configuring a chassis to contain the at least one disk drive and the planar backplane;</claim-text>
<claim-text>arranging the planar backplane as a printed circuit assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>configuring the server to include only the single printed circuit assembly.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>arranging at least one fan to direct airflow horizontally across the horizontally-oriented planar backplane in airflow channels between the vertically oriented disk drives whereby flow resistance is reduced.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method comprising:
<claim-text>arranging a planar backplane in a horizontal orientation in a server configured for rack mounting;</claim-text>
<claim-text>configuring the planar backplane to accept and mount a plurality of disk drives in a vertical orientation in a dense server arrangement; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling at least one four-bar linkage to the planar backplane; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>adapting the at least one four-bar linkage to insert and remove disk drives from the disk drive connectors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>configuring the at least one four-bar linkage to install and remove the disk drives in a horizontal motion and to engage and disengage the disk drives in a vertical motion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
