<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296987-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296987</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10546272</doc-number>
<date>20050106</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>IT</country>
<doc-number>BO2004A0014</doc-number>
<date>20050106</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>330</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>29</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>43</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>30</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>10</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425121</main-classification>
<further-classification>4251291</further-classification>
<further-classification>425345</further-classification>
<further-classification>425348 R</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Tablet press machine</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2471139</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Benander et al.</name>
<date>19490500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4943227</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Facchini</name>
<date>19900700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5685349</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mihail et al.</name>
<date>19971100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>141144</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5928590</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fabbri</name>
<date>19990700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>425345</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6068465</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wilson</name>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>425193</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6866493</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Trebbi et al.</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>425345</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO 95/20484</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19950800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>6</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425 78</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425 90</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4251291</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4251292</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425344-345</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425348 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425351</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060147573</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060706</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Rossi</last-name>
<first-name>Sauro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Bologna</city>
<country>IT</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>IT</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>IT</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Trebbi</last-name>
<first-name>Roberto</first-name>
<address>
<city>Castenaso</city>
<country>IT</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>IT</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>IT</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Arent Fox LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>I.M.A. Industria Macchine Automatiche S.p.A.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Bologna</city>
<country>IT</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Gupta</last-name>
<first-name>Yogendra N.</first-name>
<department>1722</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Thu Khanh T.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/IB2005/000024</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20050106</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20050819</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2005/068170</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20050728</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A tablet press (<b>1</b>) of the type with a rotary turret (<b>3</b>) for the production of tablets comprises a hopper (<b>2</b>) containing the pharmaceutical product in powder or granular form to be compressed; a rotary disc (<b>4</b>) equipped with matrices (<b>5</b>) designed to contain defined quantities of the pharmaceutical product fed to them by the hopper (<b>2</b>); reciprocating punches (<b>8, 9</b>) for compressing the powdered product and constituting a plurality of compressing operating stations (<b>10</b>); at least one set (A) f operating stations (<b>10</b><i>a</i>) having a modified structure to inhibit operation, each modified structure station (<b>10</b><i>a</i>) comprising barrier means (<b>11</b>) designed to be fitted at the matrices (<b>5</b>) in such a way as to prevent the passage of the product from the hopper (<b>2</b>) to the matrices (<b>5</b>), and opposing elastic means (<b>12</b>) designed to be coupled to, and act in conjunction with, the reciprocating punches (<b>8, 9</b>) and with the barrier means (<b>11</b>) in order to simulate the presence of powdered product.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="210.90mm" wi="131.15mm" file="US07296987-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="224.54mm" wi="162.05mm" file="US07296987-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="213.95mm" wi="133.69mm" file="US07296987-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="200.74mm" wi="124.54mm" file="US07296987-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a National Stage entry of International Application Number PCT/IB2005/000024, filed Jan. 6, 2005. The disclosure of the prior application is hereby incorporated herein in its entirety by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a tablet press machine for the production of tablets, especially tablets used in the pharmaceutical field.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">It is known that tablets, especially tablets for pharmaceutical use, are currently made by machines known as tablet presses which work by compressing a powdered or granular substance or product.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">One prior art tablet press substantially comprises a feed hopper that contains and feeds the powdered or granular substance to a turret consisting of a first rotary disc having uniformly distributed around its edge a plurality of seats or matrices for volumetrically dosing and forming the tablets.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The tablets are formed by oppositely reciprocating punches uniformly distributed around two further discs forming part of said turret. These two further discs are located above and below the first disc and rotate continuously about the axis of the first disc and in synchrony with the latter.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The two punches in each pair—one above and one below—access a single matrix simultaneously and compress the dose of product inside the matrix with a predetermined force that gradually increases as the discs rotate and until a tablet is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The tablet press therefore has a precise angular position where the powdered or granular product is loaded into the forming seats or matrices; another position where the product is compressed and yet another position, close to the first, where the formed tablets are fed out towards an outfeed chute: in practice, the tablet is formed in one complete rotation of the aforementioned discs.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The tablet presses of the type described above, usually with high-output features (hence, typically not for laboratory use) may also be used for research or experimental purposes, for example to test tablets made with a new powdered product.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">To do this, a limited quantity of the powdered product to be tested is fed into the tablet press. Before this is done (since the machine has to work with a partial load), some of the operating stations of the compression turret, within a defined arc of the rotary discs, are inhibited so that they do not produce any tablets.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In other words, the pairs of punches of the seats or matrices to be inhibited are physically removed from the rotary discs, together with all the mechanical parts that allow their reciprocating motion.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In addition, the powder feed channels leading to the inhibited compression seats are sealed using suitable plugs.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">With the turret set up in this way, therefore, there are operating units capable of making tablets for experimental purposes on only a limited angular sector of the machine, whilst the rest of the turret continues to rotate at the usual angular speeds but without producing any tablets since the operating elements have been removed.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">This particular set-up, however, may lead to problems.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Indeed, removal and reassembly of the operating units is a slow and laborious task which, in high-output machines, is a serious drawback. Also, removing the punches from the operating stations to be inhibited creates the risk of unwanted materials such as lubricating oil or grease penetrating the stations that remain operative owing to leaks caused by imperfect seals of the elements used to plug the inhibited parts. This in turn leads to contamination which is likely to invalidate the test being carried out. Another serious problem is the uneven distribution of forces during the test because, during rotation of the turret, the punches remaining on the single operating sector of the turret exert forces that are not counterbalanced at the inhibited stations of the remaining sector from which the punches have been removed.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">This may damage the active punches-and produce a test result that is ineffectual for the purposes of tablet production with the tested powder.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The present invention therefore has for an object to overcome the above mentioned disadvantages by providing a tablet press machine that can be quickly and effectively adapted to produce tablets for research and experimental purposes at only some of its operating stations, while maintaining a balanced distribution of forces at all the stations of the turret, including the inoperative stations.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The invention accordingly provides a tablet press machine of the type with a rotary turret for the production of tablets, comprising a hopper containing pharmaceutical product in powder or granular form to be compressed; a rotary disc equipped with matrices designed to contain defined quantities of the pharmaceutical product fed to them by the hopper; reciprocating punches for compressing the powdered product and constituting a plurality of compressing operating stations; the machine being characterised in that said plurality of stations comprises at least one set of operating stations having a modified structure to inhibit operation, each station with a modified structure comprising barrier means designed to be fitted at the matrices in such a way as to prevent the passage of the product from the hopper to the matrices, and opposing elastic means designed to be coupled to, and act in conjunction with, the reciprocating punches and with the barrier means in order to simulate the presence of the powdered product.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The technical characteristics of the invention, with reference to the above aims, are clearly described in the claims below and its advantages are apparent from the detailed description which follows, with reference to the accompanying drawings which illustrate a preferred embodiment of the invention provided merely by way of example without restricting the scope of the inventive concept, and in which:</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic top view of a central portion of a tablet press machine;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a side detail view, with some parts in cross section and others cut away for clarity, of a part of the machine illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a detail of the tablet press machine according to the present invention, showing an operating station in a partial side view, with some parts in cross section and others cut away in order to better illustrate some novel parts;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a planar development view of two operating stations of the tablet press machine of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> in two different constructional solutions.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the numeral <b>1</b> denotes in its entirety a tablet press machine used for making tablets (of customary type and therefore not illustrated), especially, but not restricted to, tablets for pharmaceutical use.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The machine <b>1</b> basically comprises, a hopper <b>2</b> for feeding a powdered or granular product to a turret <b>3</b> consisting of a first disc <b>4</b> rotating about a vertical axis Z (indicated by the arrow F in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), said disc <b>4</b> having uniformly distributed around its circumference matrices or seats <b>5</b> to which the hopper <b>2</b> feeds the product through a radial channel <b>5</b><i>a </i>which starts at the hopper <b>2</b> and opens into the seats <b>5</b> as they pass in such a way as to fill them and then level them off to the required dosage; a second and a third disc <b>6</b> and <b>7</b> located, respectively, above and below the first disc <b>4</b>, rotating about said vertical axis Z, and mounting respective pluralities of upper and lower reciprocating punches <b>8</b> and <b>9</b>, driven by cam means <b>8</b><i>a, </i><b>9</b><i>a, </i>and constituting respective operating stations <b>10</b> that compress the powdered product to form individual tablets.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In order to permit experimental tests to be carried out for research purposes, that is to say, to enable the machine <b>1</b> to operate with limited quantities of powdered product, the operating stations <b>10</b> of the tablet press machine <b>1</b> according to the invention are divided into two separate sets or groups (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). The set B of stations, labelled <b>10</b><i>b</i>, located around a first defined circular arc L have a traditional, unmodified operating structure, whilst another set A of operating stations, labelled <b>10</b><i>a, </i>located around a second circular arc K, complementary to the first arc L, are structurally adapted/modified as described in more detail below in such a way that they can be inhibited and made to operate under “no-load” conditions.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Each of the no-load stations <b>10</b><i>a </i>in the set A comprises means <b>11</b> for creating a barrier that obstructs the channel <b>5</b><i>a </i>to prevent the powdered product from reaching the seat <b>5</b>; and opposing elastic means <b>12</b> coupled to and acting in conjunction with the means <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">As better illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, the opposing means <b>12</b> are positioned between the means <b>11</b> and the respective punch <b>8</b>, <b>9</b>, which, in the non-restricting example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, is the upper punch <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Again with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, the means <b>11</b> comprise a hollow cylindrical body <b>13</b> which is fitted at the respective seat <b>5</b> on the disc <b>4</b> in the place of the seat <b>5</b> itself, and whose hollow interior houses an elastic element <b>14</b>, constituting the aforementioned opposing elastic means <b>12</b>, in contact, at the top, with the punch <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In practice, the hollow body <b>13</b> is shaped to form a “blind” seat or matrix, that is to say, a sealed seat designed to prevent the passage of the powdered product.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The element <b>14</b> is preferably a spring <b>14</b> wound around the working end of the upper punch <b>8</b> and in contact, at its other end, with the closed bottom <b>13</b><i>a </i>of the cylindrical body <b>13</b>, in such a way as to simulate the opposing force which, in the operating configuration of the stations <b>10</b><i>b </i>of the set B, is normally applied to the punch <b>8</b> when the punch a is lowered and impacts the powdered product located in the seat <b>5</b>. Thus, the tablet press machine <b>1</b> can operate correctly even with reduced quantities of powdered product and, in practice, as if all the stations <b>10</b> had the same structural set-up as those of set B.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In one possible solution for the modified operating stations <b>10</b><i>a, </i>the spring <b>14</b> is attached directly to the aforementioned working area of the upper punch <b>8</b> at a first collar <b>8</b><i>b </i>of the upper punch <b>8</b> itself (see operating station <b>10</b><i>a </i>on the right-hand side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In this particular solution, the upper punches <b>8</b> fitted with springs <b>14</b> can be prepared beforehand.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The lower punches <b>9</b> of all the stations <b>10</b><i>a </i>are removed.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">A second possible solution is also shown in the operating station <b>10</b><i>a </i>on the right-hand side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In this specific case, the cylindrical body <b>13</b> has a second, lower collar <b>13</b><i>b </i>forming the above mentioned bottom <b>13</b><i>a </i>on which the lower end of the spring <b>14</b> rests.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">More specifically, the second collar <b>13</b><i>b </i>forms a lower opening in the cylindrical body <b>13</b> with a diameter D greater than the diameter D<b>1</b> of the lower punch <b>9</b> so as to avoid interference when the lower punch <b>9</b> is partly inserted into the cylindrical body <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Obviously, in this case, the load of the spring <b>14</b> to oppose the force applied by the upper punch <b>8</b> must, be calculated in such a way as to avoid direct contact between the two punches <b>8</b> and <b>9</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The operating station <b>10</b><i>a </i>on the right-hand side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates yet another solution for the means <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In this constructional solution, the cylindrical body <b>13</b> is cup-shaped and houses the spring <b>14</b> that opposes the upper punch <b>8</b>, which is fitted.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The cup-shaped cylindrical body <b>13</b> therefore has a bottom surface <b>13</b><i>c </i>that is closed at a working area of the lower punch <b>9</b> which, in this case, is removed from the operating station <b>10</b><i>a </i>forming part of set A before the tablet press machine <b>1</b> is used for experimental purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">A tablet press machine <b>1</b> structured in this way and, in particular, adapted for use even with limited quantities of powdered product, is therefore perfectly balanced in terms of the mechanical forces involved, eliminating the risk of damage to its component parts and thus achieving the aforementioned aims.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In other words, the possibility of reconfiguring the idle stations optimises the operation of the machine <b>1</b> with reduced quantities of powdered product, making it possible to achieve a correct balance of the mechanical forces involved. Damage and wear to the mechanical parts are practically nil and there is practically no risk of undesired materials such as lubricants getting into the seats or matrices.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Furthermore, thanks to the cylindrical body and spring, it is possible to quickly and easily set the individual operating stations.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">It will be understood that the tablet press described can be modified and adapted in several ways without thereby departing from the scope of the inventive concept. Moreover, all the details of the machine may be substituted by technically equivalent elements.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A tablet press machine (<b>1</b>) of the type with a rotary turret (<b>3</b>) for the production of tablets, comprising a hopper (<b>2</b>) containing pharmaceutical product in powder or granular form to be compressed; a rotary disc (<b>4</b>) equipped with matrices (<b>5</b>) designed to contain defined quantities of the pharmaceutical product fed to them by the hopper (<b>2</b>); reciprocating punches (<b>8</b>, <b>9</b>) for compressing the powdered product and constituting a plurality of compressing operating stations (<b>10</b>); the machine being characterised in that said-plurality of stations (<b>10</b>) comprises at least one set (A) of operating stations (<b>10</b><i>a</i>) having a modified structure to inhibit operation, each station (<b>10</b><i>a</i>) with a modified structure comprising barrier means (<b>11</b>) designed to be fitted at the matrices (<b>5</b>) in such a way as to prevent the passage of the product from the hopper (<b>2</b>) to the matrices (<b>5</b>), and opposing spring means (<b>12</b>) designed to be coupled to, and act in conjunction with, the reciprocating punches (<b>8</b>, <b>9</b>) and with the barrier means (<b>11</b>) in order to simulate the presence of the powdered product.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The machine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that the barrier means (<b>11</b>) comprise a hollow cylindrical body (<b>13</b>) mounted at a respective matrix (<b>5</b>) and designed to house an elastic element (<b>14</b>), constituting the opposing means (<b>12</b>), in contact with the reciprocating punches (<b>8</b>, <b>9</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The machine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, characterised in that the cylindrical body (<b>13</b>) has a closed bottom end (<b>13</b><i>a</i>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The machine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> or <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">3</claim-ref>, characterised in that the elastic element consists of a spring (<b>14</b>) wound around the punches (<b>8</b>, <b>9</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The machine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, characterised in that the punches (<b>8</b>, <b>9</b>) comprise a plurality of pairs of reciprocating punches (<b>8</b>, <b>9</b>), each pair consisting of an upper punch (<b>8</b>) and a respective lower punch (<b>9</b>); the spring (<b>14</b>) being associated with at least one of the two punches (<b>8</b>, <b>9</b>) in each pair.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The machine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, characterised in that the spring (<b>14</b>) is associated with the upper punch (<b>8</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
