<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297943-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297943</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11472392</doc-number>
<date>20060622</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>49</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>49</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>250288</main-classification>
<further-classification>250281</further-classification>
<further-classification>250282</further-classification>
<further-classification>250423 R</further-classification>
<further-classification>2101982</further-classification>
<further-classification>210748</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Polymer based electrospray nozzle for mass spectrometry</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5994696</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tai et al.</name>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>250288</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6633031</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Schultz et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>250288</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6864480</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Staats</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>250288</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>09442843</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>19991118</date>
</document-id>
<parent-status>ABANDONED</parent-status>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11472392</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60109264</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>19981119</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60114900</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>19990105</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070085038</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070419</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tai</last-name>
<first-name>Yu-Chong</first-name>
<address>
<city>Pasadena</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wang</last-name>
<first-name>Xuan-Qi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Los Angeles</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Desai</last-name>
<first-name>Amish</first-name>
<address>
<city>Altadena</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Terry D.</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Diego</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Licklider</last-name>
<first-name>Lawrence</first-name>
<address>
<city>Arlington</city>
<state>MA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Foley &amp; Lardner LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>California Institute of Technology</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Pasadena</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>City of Hope National Medical Center and Beckman Research Institute</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Duarte</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Wells</last-name>
<first-name>Nikita</first-name>
<department>2881</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A MEMS device with an overhanging ‘polymer’ capillary provides vital and significant improvements in interfacing a MEMS electrospray nozzle to an MS inlet or other macroscopic instrumentation. The fabrication methodology associated therewith is easily expanded to include built-in micro particle filters and centimeter long serpentine micro channels provided on-chip and fabricated using a low temperature process.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="101.18mm" wi="157.73mm" file="US07297943-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="237.24mm" wi="167.89mm" file="US07297943-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="256.20mm" wi="113.62mm" file="US07297943-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="238.00mm" wi="133.35mm" file="US07297943-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of Ser. No. 09/442,843 filed Nov. 18, 1999 now abandoned, which claims priority benefit to U.S. provisional application Nos. 60/109,264 filed Nov. 19, 1998 and 60/114,900 filed Jan. 5, 1999, each of which are incorporated herein by reference in their entirety.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?GOVINT description="Government Interest" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT AS TO FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The U.S. Government may have certain rights in this invention pursuant to a Grant No. 2 R01 RR06217-06 awarded by the National Institute of Health.</p>
<?GOVINT description="Government Interest" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">This disclosure relates to chip-based chemical analysis systems such as electrospray mass spectroscopy (MS). More specifically, this disclosure relates to fabrication of a micron-sized micro-electromechanical systems (“MEMS”) electrospray nozzle.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Over the past decade, there has been increasing interest in the development of miniaturized chemical analysis systems using micro-electromechanical (MEMS) technology. Until more recently, the prior art in MEMS technology has included UV absorbance and electro-chemi-luminescence for on-chip detection. These optical methods are not viable for detection of many biomolecules. A viable commercial product should be able to process/analyze a wide range of samples.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Mass spectrometers (“MS”) are one type of widely used macroscopic instrument for the analysis of biomolecular structures such as proteins, carbohydrates, lipids and polynucleotides. MS is widely used due to its ability to analyze large proteins and peptides. MS also has high sensitivity, e.g., as high as 10<sup>−12 </sup>moles.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Much experimentation has focused on an on-chip interface that has the advantage of directly coupling a MEMS electrospray nozzle to an MS inlet.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The present disclosure describes a MEMS device with an overhanging ‘polymer’ capillary that allows interfacing a MEMS electrospray nozzle to an MS inlet or other macroscopic instrumentation. The fabrication methodology associated therewith is easily expanded to include built-in micro particle filters and centimeter long serpentine micro channels provided on-chip and fabricated using a low temperature process.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In an embodiment, the core structured material is parylene polymer, aluminum and photoresist are used as sacrificial layers, and bromine trifluoride (BrF<sub>3</sub>) gas phase etching is employed for final microcapillary releasing.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">These and other aspects will be described with reference to the drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a three dimensional view of a silica-based micromachined electrospray nozzle;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a three dimensional view of a polymer-based micromachined electrospray nozzle constructed in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the fabrication sequence of the nozzle in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a mass spectrum analysis of myoglobin using a polymer-based nozzle structure vs. a silica-based nozzles structure.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Electrospray ionization (ESI) can be used with MEMS chemical systems to generate ions for MS analysis.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">ESI is an atmospheric pressure ionization technique in which gaseous ionized molecules are produced in a fine spray from a liquid droplet in the presence of a strong electric field between a capillary tip and an MS inlet. The released ionized molecules are then directed into the MS inlet by the applied field. The applied electric field changes the shape of the fluid droplet from a spherical shape to a cone called the Taylor cone. The base of this cone is dependent on the geometry and the wetted area (wall thickness) of the capillary. Hence, reduction of these parameters reduces the size of the Taylor cone, thus reducing dead-volume.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">ESI can form a simple and direct way to interface a MEMS device to a mass spectrometer. The MEMS device needs an electrospray nozzle from which fluid can be injected toward the mass spectrometer inlet.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The capability to fabricate micron-sized tips with micromachining is advantageous in many ways: 1) the shape and finish of the tip can be reproducible from chip to chip, 2) complex MEMS filter structures can be constructed inside the micromachined liquid channel in order to filter out debris, and 3) mass production is available due to batch processing.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">A silica-based micromachined nozzle construction is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The silica-based nozzle structure <b>10</b> is shown constituted by a support silicon substrate <b>15</b>. The support silicon substrate <b>15</b> is formed to have a sample inlet window <b>17</b>. The sample inlet window <b>17</b> is positioned on the underside of the silicon substrate <b>15</b> in contact with the nozzle structure <b>10</b>, represented by dashed lines. A capillary tubing <b>20</b> is attached to the sample inlet window <b>17</b> to supply liquid sample into the nozzle structure <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The liquid sample is intended for flow into the channel field <b>25</b> of the nozzle structure <b>10</b>. In the illustrated nozzle structure, the channel field <b>25</b> is a micro-channel formed with multiple filter structures <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The silica-based nozzle structure <b>10</b> is formed by a “sandwich” fabrication sequence. The sequence involves depositing two silicon nitride (Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>) layers on the silicon substrate <b>15</b> during the manufacturing process to form outer portions of a sandwich. An interior/sacrificial layer of phosphosiligate glass (PSG) material is deposited between the sandwiching Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y </sub>nitride layers and this interior layer selectively etched to form the illustrated filter structures which function as filters and space inhibitors in the interior of the channel field <b>25</b>. The channel field <b>25</b> and the tip channel <b>35</b> occupy the volume where the PSG layer was located before the PSG layer is etched away.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The nozzle structure <b>10</b> is ultimately finally etched to form the nozzle structure with an overhanging electrospray capillary. The tip orifice of the nozzle structure is micron-sized. This resultant MEMS device with its overhanging micro-channel was found to reduce the wetted surface area at the ESI tip. Reduction of this orifice diameter and tip surface area correspondingly reduce the size of the fluid cone during electrospray, thus reducing the internal volume that the liquid occupies from the inlet of the device to the actual point of analysis. This internal volume is called the dead volume. In addition to reducing dead volume, the nozzle has integrated particle filter structures that function to reduce MEMS ESI tip clogging.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">An outward sloping sidewall <b>19</b> combined with the short length (l) of the silicon nitride nozzle tip <b>35</b> limits the tip-to-inlet distance as well as interferes with the electric field profile at the channel tip end. Furthermore, it is well known that fabrication of mm-long silicon nitride overhanging structures poses significant challenges. Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y </sub>capillaries longer than a few hundred microns can curve due to film stress gradients (typically 200 MPa for LPCVD Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>). To achieve channels longer than a few hundred microns long, etching holes on Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y </sub>channels are necessary. Such etching holes can be sealed after sacrificial layer etching. Etching holes not only complicate the process, but the resulting stress concentration around such etching holes could cause released microchannels to easily crack. Another drawback is that the fragile silicon nitride capillaries shatter with the slightest contact with the MS inlet during chemical analysis.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Many of the above-mentioned drawbacks of Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y </sub>ESI tips are found to be eliminated with an overhanging “polymer”-based nozzle structure <b>50</b> described below in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-4</figref>. The polymer material utilized is Parylene-C (“Parylene”). Parylene is a bio-compatible polymer material used to make MEMS microchannels and microvalves. The properties of Parylene produce advantages when forming an improved nozzle structure. In contrast to the silica-based nozzle structure <b>10</b>, polymer material is ideal for fabrication of high aspect ratio overhanging structures due to its low tensile stress (&lt;100 Mpa).</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Because Parylene allows for deposition at room temperature, a photoresist is used in place of the sacrificial material used in the fabrication of silica-based nozzle structures. Unlike PSG etching, a photoresist sacrificial etching (with acetone) does not require etching. holes along the channel. Thus, structures that are orders of magnitude longer can be easily fabricated. The Young's modulus of Parylene (˜3 GPa) is only about one hundredth of. Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y </sub>In terms of robustness, the fabricated Parylene microcapillaries are far superior. While Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y </sub>capillaries can shatter easily with the slightest contact with other objects, Parylene capillaries, even when up to 600 times longer, flex and return to their original shape.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Parylene ESI tips possess improved plasticity. Despite a longer overhanging tip structure than Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y </sub>ESI tips, Parylene ESI tips were found to even be able to survive table-top falls and mishandling without having the tips break. In short, the robustness of the parylene nozzles coupled with the simple to manufacture process makes polymer-based technology very much more commercially viable.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">An illustrative embodiment of a polymer-based nozzle structure <b>50</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The polymer-based nozzle structure is a micromachined electrospray-type nozzle formed on a support substrate <b>55</b>, preferably a silicon substrate. The support substrate <b>100</b> is formed with first and second inlet windows <b>56</b> and <b>57</b> (shown in dashed lines). Inlet windows <b>56</b>, <b>57</b> extend vertically through the silicon substrate <b>55</b> to make contact, at an underside thereof, with a capillary tubing through which is to be supplied liquid sample(s) during chemical analysis.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The liquid sample flows into a filtered channel field <b>70</b> of the nozzle structure <b>50</b>. In the illustrative nozzle structure, the filtered channel field <b>70</b> is a micro-channel comprised of circumferentially integrated filter elements <b>71</b> formed about each of first and second inlet windows <b>56</b> and <b>57</b>. Filtered channel field <b>70</b> further comprises serpentine channels <b>75</b> disposed downstream from the back of the channel field <b>25</b> closest to first inlet window <b>56</b>. Both filter elements <b>71</b> and serpentine channels <b>75</b> function to separately trap debris and other particles in the liquid sample.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Liquid sample introduced to nozzle structure <b>50</b> through first inlet window <b>56</b> travels through associated filter elements <b>71</b> downstream, through serpentine channels <b>75</b>, and ultimately out through a substantially rectangularly-shaped orifice at tip channel <b>78</b> extending axially through microcapillary tip <b>80</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Liquid sample introduced to nozzle structure <b>50</b> through second inlet window <b>57</b> bypasses filtration through the serpentine channels <b>75</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">It should be appreciated that while serpentine channels and filter elements have been shown as a manner to provide filtration, other orientations are possible. For example, the nozzle structure <b>50</b> may be fabricated with only serpentine channels, or only with filter elements, and such may be of variable dimensions and sizes. An important consideration in designing the positioning of filtration means is selecting appropriate spacing and dimensioning so as to achieve sufficient filtration. Clogging between the nozzle-structure Parylene layers by particulates in the liquid sample also must be considered.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Use of more than one sample inlet window <b>56</b>, <b>57</b> facilitates mixing or adding other liquids to the sample before ionization.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A to 3F</figref> will now be used to explain the fabrication steps associated with the formation of a polymer-based nozzle structure. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A to 3F</figref> only show a limited cross-section of the nozzle structure <b>50</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> taken along zigzag path A-A′.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The nozzle structure <b>50</b> is generally similar in fabrication to the “sandwich” layering of the silica-based nozzle structure <b>10</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. However, instead of Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y </sub>upper and lower layers, two Parylene polymer layers are used to form layers that will eventually become the floor and roof of the nozzle structure <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The polymer-based “sandwich” is constituted by a 5 μm thick photoresist <b>110</b> enclosed by two Parylene layers <b>101</b>, <b>102</b>, each 3 μm thick on a 500 μm thick silicon substrate <b>55</b>. The overhanging capillary nozzle structure <b>50</b> is created by gas phase etching of the Si support substrate <b>55</b> underneath.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Nozzle structure <b>50</b> could be formed on a 1 cm×0.7 cm die. Serpentine channels may be either 5 or 10 cm long, for example, and selected based on desired separation of course, all dimensions are only exemplary and may be varied based on liquid sample properties and flow requirements.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">During fabrication, appropriate windows <b>57</b> are opened in a silicon wafer preferably coated on both sides with 1.5 μm silicon dioxide (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>). Next, backside cavities are etched by potassium hydroxide (KOH) to leave a 10 μm silicon membrane left with a SiO<sub>2 </sub>mask layer <b>103</b>. The SiO<sub>2 </sub>layer on wafer top side is patterned and etched with BHF. BrF<sub>3 </sub>gas phase etching follows, to roughen the silicon surface for adhesion enhancement (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>). Next, a 3 μm thick layer <b>101</b> of Parylene is deposited on the wafer front side only. After patterning the Parylene with oxygen plasma, a 5000 Å thick Al layer is evaporated and patterned to form filter elements <b>71</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A photoresist layer of 5 μm thickness is then spun and patterned. The wafer is then hard baked at 120° C. for 10 minutes to evaporate the solvent in the photoresist. Baking helps prevent buckle and burst if heat is applied later on. A 3 μm thick Parylene layer <b>102</b> is then deposited on the front side. A 0.1 μm thick Al layer evaporated and patterned as a masking layer thereover follows this. Afterwards, oxygen plasma etching is performed and the microcapillary tip <b>80</b> is given form (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3D</figref>). Next, the wafer is diced, and the thin silicon membrane is etched away with BrF<sub>3 </sub>to open up the backside inlet window <b>56</b> and release the overhanging polymer tip <b>80</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3E</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The photoresist layer is then dissolved away with acetone to establish the channel field <b>25</b> through which liquid sample flows downstream and out to tip <b>80</b>. The MEMS nozzle structure <b>50</b> is eventually rinsed and immersed in alcohol and deionized water for several hours (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3F</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">To minimize tip clogging, particle filters can also be incorporated in several other designs by employing a double sacrificial material method. Using sub-micron channel heights in the filter areas, and larger channel heights for the remaining microchannel length forms filter elements <b>71</b>. To achieve this type of bi-level sacrificial structure, careful control of both thicknesses is essential. In a preferred embodiment, a sub-micron Al layer is used for the filter region and a thicker photoresist for the rest of the structure. The flexibility of polymer material selected must also be taken into account when designing structures that are subject to mechanical pressure. For example, fluidic pressure can cause deformation in the sub-micron filter area and nullify its effectiveness as a sub-micron filter. To address this deformation problem, polymer anchor structures are fabricated in this region to hold the top and bottom of the channel together.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The gas phase silicon etchant BrF<sub>3 </sub>is used to release the microcapillaries. This etching method serves two purposes in this process: 1) to partially roughen the silicon surface for increased adhesion to the Parylene, and 2) to release the microcapillaries from the silicon substrate <b>55</b> in the last fabrication step.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Compared to other silicon etching methods, plasma etching offers less silicon undercutting and tends to damage the Parylene film on the structure. Even though potassium hydroxide (KOH) or tetramethyl ammonium hydroxide (TMAH) do not attack Parylene at low temperature, they do attack the Parylene-silicon interface significantly and cause Parylene to peel off from the substrate. In contrast, the gas phase silicon isotropic etchant, BrF<sub>3</sub>, can etch silicon spontaneously at room temperature and maintain the integrity of a Parylene-silicon interface.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The ability to fabricate precise micrometer-sized tip geometries expands the uses of micro-electrospray phenomena. In addition to experimentally derived empirical data, mathematical models also facilitate prediction calculations. For instance, the following mathematical model models a circular cone with a specific cone tip angle, where r<sub>e </sub>represents the radius of the emission region at the tip of the Taylor cone, γ the surface tension of the liquid, ρ the density of the liquid, U<sub>a </sub>the applied voltage, U<sub>t </sub>the voltage at which the cone is formed, υ the cone angle, and dV/dt the flow rate. The equation below predicts that r<sub>e</sub>, the emission radius can be reduced with a reduction in flow rate. However, in the illustrative nozzle structure <b>50</b>, the orifice through the tip <b>80</b> is rectangular and initial measurements of the cone angle show significant deviation from that of a circular capillary Taylor cone (˜49°).</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mrow>
  <msub>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
  </msub>
  <mo>=</mo>
  <mrow>
    <msup>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mfrac>
          <mi>ρ</mi>
          <mrow>
            <mn>4</mn>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <msup>
              <mi>π</mi>
              <mn>2</mn>
            </msup>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mi>γ</mi>
              <mo>⁡</mo>
              <mrow>
                <mo>[</mo>
                <mrow>
                  <msup>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mfrac>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>U</mi>
                          <mi>a</mi>
                        </msub>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>U</mi>
                          <mi>t</mi>
                        </msub>
                      </mfrac>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                  </msup>
                  <mo>-</mo>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </mrow>
                <mo>]</mo>
              </mrow>
            </mrow>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mi>tan</mi>
              <mo>⁡</mo>
              <mrow>
                <mo>(</mo>
                <mrow>
                  <mfrac>
                    <mi>π</mi>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                  </mfrac>
                  <mo>-</mo>
                  <mi>υ</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mo>)</mo>
              </mrow>
            </mrow>
          </mrow>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
        <mn>1</mn>
        <mo>/</mo>
        <mn>3</mn>
      </mrow>
    </msup>
    <mo>·</mo>
    <msup>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mfrac>
          <mrow>
            <mo>ⅆ</mo>
            <mi>V</mi>
          </mrow>
          <mrow>
            <mo>ⅆ</mo>
            <mi>t</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
        <mn>2</mn>
        <mo>/</mo>
        <mn>3</mn>
      </mrow>
    </msup>
  </mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The improved polymer-base nozzle structure makes possible coupling a MEMS device to an MS interface. The nozzle structure represents vital and significant improvements in MEMS process technology and MS functionality with respect to the silicon-nitride ESI nozzles reported before. The-tests validate the tremendous advantages and viability of Parylene polymer technology particularly when combined with gas phase etching to form mm-long rugged overhanging capillary structures. The integration of micro-particle filters sandwiched between polymer layers has made the nozzle a more convenient tool for MS. In the context of a MEMS application for chemical analysis, the invention renders MEMS ESI more cost-efficient and practical.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Employed as a MEMS device, the nozzle structure now has the possibility to be integrated with other chip-based chemical analysis systems, thus increasing the potential of high sensitivity chemical detection with MEMS systems.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Although only a few embodiments have been described in detail above, those having ordinary skill in the art will certainly understand that many modifications are possible in the preferred embodiment without departing from the teachings thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">All such modifications are intended to be encompassed within the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07297943-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="10.58mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07297943-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A polymer nozzle for electrospray ionization, comprising:
<claim-text>a support structure formed of a semiconductor material;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a MEMS electrospray nozzle structure, formed of a polymer material, having a first portion which is supported by said support structure, and a second portion which is unsupported by said support structure; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first inlet window, fluidly coupled to said nozzle structure, said first inlet window being supported by said support structure.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said nozzle structure which is unsupported is flexible.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said polymer material includes Parylene.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a filtering element formed supported by said support structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said filtering element comprises a serpentine shaped filtering part, coupled between said first inlet window, and said nozzle structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said filtering element is also formed from a polymer material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a second inlet window, separate from said inlet window and spaced from said inlet window.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising a first filtering element coupled between said first inlet window and said nozzle, and a second filtering element coupled between said first inlet window and said nozzle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A polymer nozzle for electrospray ionization, comprising:
<claim-text>a support structure, formed of a silicon material;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a MEMS electrospray nozzle structure, having an exterior portion, and a hollow interior portion, having a first nozzle part which is supported by said silicon support structure, and a second nozzle part which extends beyond said support structure and forms a freestanding part, said nozzle structure being flexible.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, further comprising an inlet window, fluidly coupled to said nozzle structure, and supported on said support structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising a filtering element, coupled between said inlet window and said support structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein said filtering element is formed of Parylene.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising a second inlet window, also connected fluidly to said nozzle structure, and enabling a second fluid communication to said nozzle structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A nozzle as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the nozzle is a Parylene nozzle.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
