<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297250-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297250</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10972270</doc-number>
<date>20041025</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>129</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>10</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>14</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>10</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>208132</main-classification>
<further-classification>208 50</further-classification>
<further-classification>208 86</further-classification>
<further-classification>208 92</further-classification>
<further-classification>208 94</further-classification>
<further-classification>208251 R</further-classification>
<further-classification>208309</further-classification>
<further-classification>422189</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Method of and apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbon feeds</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4039429</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>VAN Klinken et al.</name>
<date>19770800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>208 50</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4087354</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hessler</name>
<date>19780500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>208251 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4500416</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>van Dongen et al.</name>
<date>19850200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>208 86</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5976361</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hood et al.</name>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>208309</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>1</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>208 50</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>208 86</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>208 92</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>208132</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>208251 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>208309</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>208 94</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>422189</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>10</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>09431159</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>19991101</date>
</document-id>
<parent-status>ABANDONED</parent-status>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10972270</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060032789</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060216</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bronicki</last-name>
<first-name>Yoram</first-name>
<address>
<city>Rehovot</city>
<country>IL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>IL</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>IL</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>The Nath Law Group</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nath</last-name>
<first-name>Gary M.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Meyer</last-name>
<first-name>Jerald L.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ormat Industries Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Yavne</city>
<country>IL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Caldarola</last-name>
<first-name>Glenn</first-name>
<department>1764</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Singh</last-name>
<first-name>Prem C.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention comprises a method for processing a heavy hydrocarbon feed including: supplying the heavy hydrocarbon feed to a heater for heating the heavy hydrocarbon feed; supplying the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed to an atmospheric fractionating tower for fractionating the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed fed to the inlet of the atmospheric fractionating tower producing light atmospheric fractions and atmospheric bottoms; supplying the atmospheric bottoms to a further heater for heating the atmospheric bottoms and producing heated atmospheric bottoms; supplying the heated atmospheric bottoms to a vacuum fractionating tower for fractionating the heated atmospheric bottoms and producing light vacuum fractions and vacuum residue; supplying the vacuum residue to a solvent deasphalting (SDA) unit for producing deasphalted oil (DAO) and asphaltenes from the vacuum residue; supplying the deasphalted oil to a deasphalted oil thermal cracker for thermally cracking the deasphalted oil and producing a thermally cracked product which is recycled only to the inlet of the atmospheric fractionating tower; and supplying the light vacuum fractions to a light vacuum fraction thermal cracker for thermally cracking the light vacuum fractions for producing a further cracked product which is recycled only to the inlet of the atmospheric fractionating tower.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="137.41mm" wi="235.63mm" file="US07297250-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="260.52mm" wi="160.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="257.13mm" wi="158.50mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="249.85mm" wi="159.26mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="241.38mm" wi="146.64mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="237.91mm" wi="156.63mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="244.26mm" wi="160.02mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="239.10mm" wi="171.28mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="235.37mm" wi="169.93mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="242.32mm" wi="171.37mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="237.41mm" wi="166.79mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297250-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This is a divisional of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 09/431,159, filed Nov. 1, 1999 now abandoned.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to processing heavy hydrocarbon feeds containing sulfur, metals and asphaltenes which may be used in refineries and/or producing power, and more particularly, to a method of and apparatus for upgrading heavy crude oils or fractions thereof.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Many types of heavy crude oils contain high concentrations of sulfur compounds, organo-metallic compounds, and heavy non-distillable fractions called asphaltenes that are insoluble in light paraffins such as n-pentane. Because most petroleum products used for fuel must have a low sulfur content, the sulfur compounds in the non-distillible fractions reduce their value to petroleum refiners and increase their cost to users of such fractions as fuel or as raw material for producing other products. In order to increase the saleability of these non-distillable fractions, refiners must resort to various expedients for removing sulfur compounds.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A conventional approach to removing sulfur compounds in distillable fractions of crude oil, or its derivatives, is catalytic hydrogenation in the presence of molecular hydrogen at moderate pressure and temperature. While this approach is cost effective in removing sulfur from distillable oils, problems arise when the feed includes metallic containing asphaltenes. Specifically, the presence of metallic containing asphaltenes results in catalyst deactivation by reason of the coking tendency of the asphaltenes, and the accumulation of metals on the catalyst, especially nickel and vanadium compounds commonly found in the asphaltenes.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Alternative approaches include coking, high-pressure, desulfurization and fluidized catalytic cracking of non-distillable oils, and production of asphalt for paving and other uses. All of these processes, however, have disadvantages that are intensified by the presence of high concentrations of metals, sulfur and asphaltenes. In the case of coking non-distillable oils, the cost is high and a disposal market for the resulting high sulfur coke must be found. Furthermore, the products produced from the asphaltene portion of the feed to a coker are almost entirely low valued coke and cracked gases. In the case of residual oil desulfurization, the cost of high pressure equipment, catalyst consumption, and long processing times make this alternative undesirably expensive.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In U.S. Pat. No. 4,191,636, heavy oil is continuously converted into asphaltenes and metal-free oil by hydrotreating the heavy oil to crack asphaltenes selectively and remove heavy metals such as nickel and vanadium simultaneously. The liquid products are separated into a light fraction of an asphaltene-free and metal-free oil and a heavy fraction of an asphaltene and heavy metal-containing oil. The light fraction is recovered as a product and the heavy fraction is recycled to the hydrotreating step.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In U.S. Pat. No. 4,528,100, a process for the treatment of residual oil is disclosed, the process comprising the steps of treating the residual oil so as to produce a first extract and a first raffinate using supercritical solvent extraction, and then treating the first raffinate so as to produce a second extract and a second raffinate again by second raffinate again by supercritical solvent extraction using a second supercritical solvent and then combining the first extract and the raffinate to a product fuel. In accordance with a particular embodiment of the invention disclosed in the U.S. '100 patent, the supercritical solvents are particularly selected to concentrate vandium in the second extract. Thus, even though the amount of vandium present in the produce fuel is low and consequently beneficial for reducing gas turbine maintenance problems as stated in this '100 patent, some amount of vanadium does still remain therein.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another example of a user of the heavier, higher boiling range portion of a hydrocarbon is a refinery with a fluid catalytic cracking unit (a FCC unit). FCC units typically are operated with a feedstock quality constraint of very low metals asphaltenes, and CCR (i.e., less than 10 wppm metals, less than 0.2 wt % asphaltenes, and less than 2 wt % CCR). Utilization of feedstocks with greater levels of asphaltenes of CCR results in increased coke production and a corresponding reduction in unit capacity. In addition, use of feedstocks with high levels of metals and asphaltenes results in more rapid deactivation of the catalyst, and thus increased catalyst rates and increased catalyst replacement costs.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In U.S. Pat. No. 5,192,421, a process for the treatment of whole crude oil is disclosed, the process comprising the steps of deasphalting the crude by first mixing the crude with an aromatic solvent, and then mixing the crude-aromatic solvent mixture with an aliphatic solvent. The U.S. '421 patent (at page 9, lines 43-45) identifies that certain modifications must be made to prior art solvent deasphalting technologies, such as that described in U.S. Pat. Nos. 2,940,920, 3,005,769, and 3,053,751 in order to accommodate the process described in the U.S. '421 patent, in particular since the prior art solvent deasphalting technologies have no means to remove that portion of the charge oil that will vaporize concurrently with the solvent and thus contaminate the solvent used in the process. In addition to being burdened by the complexity and cost resulting from the use of two solvents, the U.S. '421 process results in a deasphalted product that still contains a non-distilled portion with levels of CCR and metals that exceed the desired levels of such contaminants.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In U.S. Pat. No. 4,686,028 a process for the treatment of whole crude oil is disclosed, the process comprising the steps of deasphalting a high boiling range hydrocarbon in a two-stage deasphalting process to separate asphaltene, resin, and deasphalted fractions by hydrogenation or visbreaking. The U.S. '028 patent is burdened by the complexity and cost of a two-stage solvent deasphalting system used to separate the resin fraction from the deasphalting oil. In addition, like the U.S. '421 patent, the '028 process results in an upgraded product that still contains a non-distilled fraction—the DAO—that is contaminated with CCR and metals.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Metals contained in heavy oils contaminate and spoil the performance of catalysts in fluidized catalytic cracking units. Asphaltenes present in such oils are converted to high yields of coke and gas which burden an operator with high burning requirements.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Another alternative available to a refiner or heavy crude user is to dispose of the non-distillable heavy oil fractions as fuel for industrial power generation or as bunker fuel for ships. Disposal of such fractions as fuel is not particularly profitable to a refiner because more valuable distillate oils must be added in order to reduce viscosity sufficiently (e.g. producing heavy fuel oil, etc.) to allow handling and shipping. Furthermore, the presence of high sulfur and metals contaminants lessens the value to the users. In addition, this does not solve the problem of the non-distillable heavy oil fractions in a global sense since environmental regulations restrict the use of high sulfur fuel oil. Refiners frequently use a thermal conversion process, e.g., visbreaking, for reducing the heavy fuel oil yield. This process converts a limited amount of the heavy oil to lower viscosity light oil, but has the disadvantage of using some of the higher value distillate oils to reduce the viscosity of the heavy oil sufficiently to allow handling and shipping. Moreover, the asphaltene content of the heavy oil restricts severely the degree of visbreaking conversion possible due to the tendency of the asphaltenes to condense into heavier materiels, even coke, and cause instability in the resulting fuel oil. Furthermore, this process reduces the amount of heavy fuel oil that the refiner has to sell and is not useful in a refinery processing heavy crudes.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Many proposals thus have been for dealing with crude oil and metals. And while many are technically viable, they appear to have achieved little or no commercialization, due, in large measure, to the high cost of the technology involved. Usually such cost takes the form of increased catalyst contamination by the metals and/or the carbon deposition resulting from the attempted conversion of the asphaltene fractions.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">An example of the processes proposed in order to cope with high metals and asphaltenes is disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 4,500,416. In one embodiment, an asphaltene-containing hydrocarbon feed is solvent deasphalted in a deasphalting zone to produce a deasphalted oil (DAO) fraction, and an asphaltene fraction which is catalytically hydrotreated in a hydrotreating zone to produce a reduced asphaltene stream that is fractionated to produce light distillate fractions and a first heavy distillate fraction. Both the first heavy distillate fraction and the DAO fraction are thermally cracked into a product stream that is then fractionated into light distillate fractions and a second distillate fraction which is routed to the hydrotreating zone.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In an alternative embodiment, an asphaltene-containing hydrocarbon feed is solvent deasphalted in a deasphalting zone to produce a deasphalted oil (DAO) fraction, and an asphaltene fraction which is catalytically hydrotreated in a hydrotreating zone to produce a reduced asphaltene stream that is fractionated to produce light distillate fractions and a first heavy distillate fraction. The first heavy distillate fraction is routed to the deasphalting zone for deasphalting, and the DAO fraction is thermally cracked into a product stream that is then fractionated into light fractions and a second heavy distillate fraction which is routed to the hydrotreating zone.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In each embodiment in the '416 patent, asphaltenes are routed to a hydrotreating zone wherein heavy metals present in the asphaltenes cause a number of problems. Primarily, the presence of the heavy metals in the hydrotreater causes deactivation of the catalyst that increases the cost of the operation. In addition, such heavy metals also result in having to employ higher pressures in the hydrotreater which complicates its design and operation and hence its cost.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">It is therefore an object of the present invention to provide a new and improved method of and apparatus for processing and upgrading heavy hydrocarbon feeds containing sulfur, metals, and asphaltenes, wherein the disadvantages as outlined are reduced or substantially overcome.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Apparatus for processing a heavy hydrocarbon feed, in accordance with the present invention, comprises firstly a heater for heating the heavy hydrocarbon feed. The heated heavy hydrocarbon feed produced is fed to an atmospheric fractionating tower for fractionating the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed fed to the inlet of the atmospheric fractionating tower producing light atmospheric fractions and atmospheric bottoms. In addition, the apparatus includes a vacuum fractionating tower for fractionating heated atmospheric bottoms, heated by a further heater, and producing lighter vacuum fractions and vacuum residue. Furthermore, the apparatus includes a solvent deasphalting (SDA) unit for producing deasphalted oil (DAO) and asphaltenes from the vacuum residue as well as a thermal cracker for thermally cracking the deasphalted oil and producing a thermally cracked product which is recycled to the inlet of the atmospheric fractioning tower. Moreover, the apparatus can include a further thermal cracker for thermally cracking the lighter vacuum fractions for producing a further thermally cracked product which is recycled to the inlet of the atmospheric fractionating tower. If preferred, the lighter vacuum fractions can be supplied to the thermal cracker in addition to the deasphalted oil. In such a case, the further thermal cracker previously mentioned is not used.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Furthermore, the present invention includes a method for processing a heavy hydrocarbon feed comprising the steps of: heating a heavy hydrocarbon feed and fractionating the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed in an atmospheric fractionating tower for producing light atmospheric fractions and atmospheric bottoms. Heated atmospheric bottoms, heated by a further heater, are fractioned in a vacuum fractioning tower for producing lighter vacuum fractions and vacuum residue while the vacuum residue are solvent deasphalted in a solvent deasphalting (SDA) unit for producing deasphalted oil (DAO) and asphaltenes. The deasphalted oil is then thermally cracked in a thermal cracker for producing a thermally cracked product that is recycled to the inlet of the atmospheric fractionating tower. In addition, the lighter vacuum fractions can be thermally cracked for producing a further thermally cracked product that is recycled to the inlet of the atmospheric fractionating tower. Thermal cracking of the lighter vacuum fractions can be carried out in a separate thermal cracker or in the same thermal cracker in which the deasphalted oil is thermally cracked. Similar apparatus and methods are disclosed in U.S. patent application Ser. No. 08/910,102, the disclosure of which is hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Embodiments of the present invention are described by way of example, and with reference to the accompanying drawings wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a first embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a </i>is a block diagram of a modification of the first embodiment of the present invention mentioned above for processing a hydrocarbon feed;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of a second embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram of a third embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of a further embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block diagram of a still further embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a block diagram of another embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a block diagram of another embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a block diagram of another embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed; and</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a block diagram of another embodiment of the present invention for processing a hydrocarbon feed.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Like reference numerals and designations in the various drawings refer to like elements.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Turning to the drawings, numeral <b>10</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> designates apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention wherein heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b> and the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>. Atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b> produces light atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b> and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>15</b>. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>15</b> are then supplied to heater <b>16</b> and the heated atmospheric bottoms are supplied to vacuum fractionating tower <b>18</b> which produces light vacuum fractions in line <b>20</b> and vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b> is then supplied to solvent deasphalting unit <b>24</b> which produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b> and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b> is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b> that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b> that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b> of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>. Moreover, the light vacuum fractions in line <b>20</b> are supplied to further thermal cracker <b>35</b> for thermally cracking the lighter vacuum fractions and a further thermally cracked product is produced in line <b>37</b> that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b> of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>. If preferred, rather than using further thermal cracker <b>35</b>, the light vacuum fractions in line <b>20</b> can be thermally cracked in thermal cracker <b>30</b> together with the deasphalted oil supplied in line <b>26</b>, see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Numeral <b>10</b>A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> designates another embodiment of apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention wherein heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b>A and the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>A. Atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>A produces light atmospheric fractions in lines <b>14</b>A and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>A. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>A are then supplied to heater <b>17</b>A and heated atmospheric bottoms are supplied vacuum frationating tower <b>18</b>A which produces light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>A, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b> and vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>A. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>A are then supplied to solvent deasphalting unit <b>24</b>A which produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>A and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>A. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>A is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>A that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b>A that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>A of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>A. Moreover, the heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b> are supplied to further thermal cracker <b>35</b>A for thermally cracking the heavier vacuum fractions and a further thermally cracked product is produced in line <b>37</b>A which is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>A of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Turning now to the embodiment described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, numeral <b>10</b>B designates a further embodiment of apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention. In this embodiment, heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b>B and the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>B. Atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>B produces light atmospheric fractions in lines <b>14</b>B and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>B. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>B are then supplied to heater <b>17</b>B and the heated, atmospheric bottoms are supplied to vacuum fractionating tower <b>18</b>B which produces light vacuum fractions in line <b>20</b>B, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>B as well as vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>B. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>B is then supplied to solvent deasphalting unit <b>24</b>B which produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>B and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>B. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>B is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>B that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b>B that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>B of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>B. Moreover, the heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>B are supplied to line <b>26</b>B to form a combined product that is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>B.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In another embodiment of the present invention, described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, numeral <b>10</b>C designates a still further embodiment of apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention. In this embodiment, heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b>C and the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>C. Atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>C produces lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>C, light atmospheric fractions in line <b>15</b>C and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>C. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>C are then supplied to heater <b>17</b>C and the heated atmospheric bottoms are supplied to vacuum fractionating tower <b>18</b>C which produces light vacuum fraction in lines <b>20</b>C, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>C and vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>C. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>C are then supplied to solvent deasphalting unit <b>24</b>C which produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>C and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>C. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>C is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>C that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b>C that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>C of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>C. Moreover, the heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>C are supplied to further thermal cracker <b>35</b>C for thermally cracking the heavier vacuum fractions and a further thermally cracked product is produced in line <b>37</b>C which is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>C of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>C. Furthermore, this embodiment includes hydrogen donor apparatus <b>40</b>C having hydrotreater <b>45</b>C to which light fraction product in line <b>39</b>C is supplied and which produces treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>C. Treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>C is supplied to heater <b>43</b>C and the heated, treated hydrocarbon feed is then fed to further atmospheric fractionating tower <b>42</b>C. Further atmospheric fractionating tower <b>42</b>C produces further light atmospheric fractions in lines <b>44</b>C and further atmospheric bottoms in line <b>46</b>C. The further atmospheric bottoms in line <b>46</b>C are then supplied to heater <b>47</b>C and the heated, further atmospheric bottoms are supplied to further vacuum fractionating tower <b>48</b>C that produces further light vacuum fractions in lines <b>50</b>C, further heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>51</b>C and further vacuum residue in line <b>52</b>C. In this embodiment, portion of further heavier vacuum fractions or hydrogen donor stream present in line <b>51</b>C is fed via line <b>60</b> to line <b>26</b>C for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>C. A further portion of the hydrogen donor stream is fed to line <b>21</b>C using line <b>61</b> for input into thermal cracker <b>35</b>C.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Preferably, the ratio of the deasphalted oil present in line <b>26</b>C to the amount of hydrogen donor stream present in line feed <b>60</b> is 0.25 to 4. Also, preferably, the ratio of the heavier vacuum fraction present in line <b>21</b>C to the amount of hydrogen donor stream present in line <b>61</b> is also 0.25 to 4.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In a further embodiment of the present invention, described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, numeral <b>10</b>D designates an even further embodiment of apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention. In this embodiment, heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b>D and the heated, heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractioning tower <b>12</b>D. Atmospheric fractioning tower <b>12</b>D produces lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>D, light fractions in line <b>15</b>D and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>D. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>D are then supplied to heater <b>17</b>D and the heated atmospheric bottoms are supplied to vacuum fractioning tower <b>18</b>D that produces light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>D, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>D and vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>D. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>D are then supplied to solvent deasphalting unit <b>24</b>D that produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>D and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>D. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>D is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>D that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b>D that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>D of atmospheric fractioning tower <b>12</b>D. Moreover, the heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>D are also supplied to line <b>26</b>D for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>D. Furthermore, this embodiment includes hydrogen donor apparatus <b>40</b>D including hydrotreater <b>45</b>D to which light fraction product in line <b>39</b>D is supplied and that produces treated hydrocarbon in line <b>41</b>D. Treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>D is supplied to heater <b>43</b>D and heated, treated hydrocarbon feed is fed to further atmospheric fractioning tower <b>42</b>D. Further atmospheric fractioning tower <b>42</b>D produces further light atmospheric fractions in lines <b>44</b>D and further atmospheric bottoms in lines <b>46</b>D. The further atmospheric bottoms in line <b>46</b>D are then supplied to heater <b>47</b>D and the heated, further atmospheric bottoms are supplied to further vacuum fractionating tower <b>48</b>D that produces further light vacuum fractions in lines <b>50</b>D, further heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>51</b>D and further vacuum residue in line <b>52</b>D. In this embodiment, further heavier vacuum fractions or hydrogen donor stream present in line <b>51</b>D are fed via line <b>60</b>D to line <b>26</b>D for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>D.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Preferably, the ratio of the hydrocarbon feed present in line <b>26</b>D to the amount of hydrogen donor stream present in line feed <b>60</b>D is 0.25 to 4.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As far as the embodiment of the present invention is concerned, described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, numeral <b>10</b>E designates another embodiment of apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention. In this embodiment, heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b>E and the heated, heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>E. Atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>E produces lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>E, light fractions in line <b>15</b>E and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>E. The lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>E and light fractions in line <b>15</b>E are combined and the combined product is supplied to hydrotreater <b>19</b>E that produces a hydrotreated product. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>E are then supplied to heater <b>17</b>E and the heated, atmospheric bottoms are supplied to vacuum fractionating tower <b>18</b>E which produces light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>E, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>E and vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>E. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>E is then supplied to deasphalting unit <b>24</b>E which produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>E and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>E. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>E is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>E that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b>E that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>E of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>E. Moreover, the light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>E, and heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>E are supplied to line <b>39</b>E. Portion of these fractions is supplied to further thermal cracker <b>35</b>E for thermally cracking these vacuum fractions and a further thermally cracked product is produced in line <b>37</b>E that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>E of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>E. Furthermore, this embodiment includes a further hydrotreater <b>40</b>E to which a further portion of fractions present in line <b>39</b>E is supplied and that produces treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>E. In this embodiment, portion of treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>E is supplied via line <b>60</b>E to line <b>26</b>E for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>E. Preferably, the ratio of the deasphalted oil present in line <b>26</b>E to the amount of treated hydrocarbon feed present in line <b>60</b>E is 0.25 to 4. A further portion of the treated hydrocarbon feed in <b>41</b>E is supplied to line <b>42</b>E via line <b>62</b> for input into thermal cracker <b>35</b>E.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Preferably, the ratio of the vacuum fractions present in line <b>42</b>E to the amount of treated hydrocarbon feed present in line feed <b>62</b> is also 0.25 to 4.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Turning to the embodiment of the present invention described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> similar apparatus to that described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is shown wherein numeral <b>10</b>F designates a further embodiment of apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention. In this embodiment, heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b>F and the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>F. Atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>F produces lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>F, light fractions in line <b>15</b>F and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>F. The lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>F and light fractions in line <b>15</b>F are combined and the combined product is supplied to hydrotreater <b>19</b>F that produces a hydrotreated product. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>F are then supplied to heater <b>17</b>F and the heated atmospheric bottoms are supplied to vacuum fractionating tower <b>18</b>F which produces light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>F, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>F and vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>F. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>F is then supplied to deasphalting unit <b>24</b>F which produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>F and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>F. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>F is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>F that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b>F that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>F of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>F. Moreover, the light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>F, and heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>F are supplied to line <b>39</b>F. Portion of these fractions is supplied to line <b>26</b>F for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>F. Furthermore, this embodiment includes a further hydrotreater <b>40</b>F to which a further portion of fractions present in line <b>39</b>F is supplied and which produces treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>60</b>F. All of treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>60</b>F, in this embodiment, is supplied to line <b>26</b>F for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>F. Preferably, the ratio of the hydrocarbon feed present in line <b>26</b>F to the amount of treated hydrocarbon feed present in line feed <b>60</b>F is 0.25 to 4.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Numeral <b>10</b>G in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> designated an additional embodiment of apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention. In this embodiment, heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b>G and the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>G. Atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>G produces lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>G, light fractions in line <b>15</b>G and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>G. The lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>G and light fractions in line <b>15</b>G are combined and the product is supplied to hydrotreater <b>19</b>G that produces a hydrotreated product. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>G are then supplied to heater <b>17</b>G and the heated atmospheric bottoms are supplied to vacuum fractionating tower <b>18</b>G that produces light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>G, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>G and vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>G. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>G is then supplied to solvent deasphalting unit <b>24</b>G which produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>G and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>G. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>G is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>G that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b>G that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>G of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>G. Moreover, the light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>G are supplied to line <b>39</b>G. Portion of these fractions is supplied to further thermal cracker <b>35</b>G for thermally cracking these vacuum fractions and a further thermally cracked product is produced in line <b>37</b>G which is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>G of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>G. In addition, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>G are supplied to this portion of fractions supplied to further thermal cracker <b>35</b>G. Furthermore, this embodiment includes a further hydrotreater <b>40</b>G to which a further portion of fractions present in line <b>39</b>G is supplied and which produces treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>G. In this embodiment, portion of treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>G is supplied via line <b>60</b>G to line <b>26</b>G for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>G. A further portion of the treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>G is supplied via line <b>62</b>G to line <b>42</b>G for input into further thermal cracker <b>35</b>G. Preferably, the ratio of the vacuum fractions present in line <b>42</b>G to the amount of treated hydrocarbon feed present in line feed <b>62</b>G is 0.25 to 4. Also in this embodiment, portion for the hydrotreated product exiting hydrotreater <b>19</b>G is supplied via line <b>64</b>G to treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>G exiting further hydrotreater <b>40</b>G. Consequently, portion of the hydrotreated product supplied to line <b>41</b>G is supplied to line <b>26</b>G for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>G while another portion of the hydrotreated product supplied to line <b>41</b>G is supplied to further thermal cracker <b>35</b>G.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Preferably, the ratio of the deasphalted oil present in line <b>26</b>G to the amount of treated hydrocarbon feed present in line feed <b>60</b>G is 0.25 to 4.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As far as the embodiment of the present invention described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is concerned, similar apparatus to that described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is shown wherein numeral <b>10</b>H designates a further embodiment of apparatus for processing heavy hydrocarbons in accordance with the present invention. In this embodiment, heavy hydrocarbon feed is supplied to heater <b>11</b>H and the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed is fed to atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>H. Atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>H produces lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>H, light fractions in line <b>15</b>H and atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>H. The lighter atmospheric fractions in line <b>14</b>H and light fractions in line <b>15</b>H are combined and the combined product is supplied to hydrotreater <b>19</b>H that produces a hydrotreated product. The atmospheric bottoms in line <b>16</b>H are then supplied to heater <b>17</b>H and the heated atmospheric bottoms are supplied to vacuum fractionating tower <b>18</b>H which produces light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>H, heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>H and vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>H. The vacuum residue in line <b>22</b>H is then supplied to solvent deasphalting unit <b>24</b>H which produces deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>H and asphaltenes in line <b>28</b>H. Deasphalted oil in line <b>26</b>H is supplied to thermal cracker <b>30</b>H that produces thermally cracked product in line <b>32</b>H that is recycled to inlet <b>13</b>H of atmospheric fractionating tower <b>12</b>H. Moreover, the light vacuum fractions in lines <b>20</b>H are supplied to line <b>39</b>H for input into further hydrotreater <b>40</b>H which produces treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>H that is supplied via line <b>60</b>H to line <b>26</b>H for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>H. Heavier vacuum fractions in line <b>21</b>H are also supplied to line <b>26</b>H for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>H. In this embodiment, portion for the hydrotreated product exiting hydrotreater <b>19</b>H is supplied via line <b>64</b>H to treated hydrocarbon feed in line <b>41</b>H exiting further hydrotreater <b>40</b>H. Consequently, the portion of the hydrotreated product supplied to line <b>41</b>H is supplied to line <b>26</b>H for input into thermal cracker <b>30</b>H.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Preferably, the ratio of the hydrocarbon feed present in line <b>26</b>H to the amount of treated hydrocarbon feed present in line feed <b>60</b>H is 0.24 to 4.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The present invention permits the efficient control of the final boiling point of the product stream. This has importance since the value of the upgraded product produced in accordance with the present invention changes for each specific refinery configuration. Refineries are sensitive to the final boiling point of this upgraded product and material that has high value for one may be valued at the value of vacuum residue by another. Thus, the value of the product or synthetic crude produced in accordance with the present invention and supplied to the refinery can be different for a different balance of the different fractions produced. Refineries are differentiated one from another by the products and fractions they are willing to accept. Consequently, sometimes, the value of a product in the boiling range between 650-1050° F. is low even if its quality is high. Here, refineries may prefer different divisions of boiling point ranges of the improved products in accordance with the processing units or apparatus downstream. As a result if e.g. a refinery is the client of the product or the user of the process, there is an advantage of flexibility of the final boiling point in general and in the actual balance between the vacuum gas oil and the atmospheric product fractions. Furthermore, often a diluent needs to be added to the crude oil in order to meet the pipeline specifications for conveying the heavy oils. Thus, the present invention permits conversion of part of the crude oil into diluent that can be used in the transportation of more viscous oil.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Moreover, as far as combustion turbines are concerned, it is important to control the viscosity and density of the product thus permitting substantially avoiding potential risks from occurring in the fuel system and injectors of the turbine.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In addition, it should be noted that supply means or lines mentioned in this specification refer to suitable conduits, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Furthermore, it should be pointed out that the present invention includes as well the method for operating the apparatus disclosed with reference to the above-described figures.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">It is believed that the advantages and improved results furnished by the method and apparatus of the present invention are apparent from the foregoing description of the invention. Various changes and modifications may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as described in the claims that follow.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for processing a heavy hydrocarbon feed including the steps comprising, in sequential order:
<claim-text>a) supplying said heavy hydrocarbon feed to a heater for heated said heavy hydrocarbon feed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b) supplying said heated heavy hydrocarbon feed to an atmospheric fractionating tower for fractionating the heated heavy hydrocarbon feed fed to the inlet of the atmospheric fractionating tower producing light atmospheric fractions and atmospheric bottoms;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c) supplying said atmospheric bottoms to a further heater for heating said atmospheric bottoms and producing heated atmospheric bottoms;</claim-text>
<claim-text>d) supplying said heated atmospheric bottoms to a vacuum fractionating tower for fractionating said heated atmospheric bottoms and producing light vacuum fractions and vacuum residue;</claim-text>
<claim-text>e) supplying said vacuum residue to a solvent deasphalting (SDA) unit for producing deasphalted oil (DAO) and asphaltenes from said vacuum residue;</claim-text>
<claim-text>f) supplying said deasphalted oil to a deasphalted oil thermal cracker for thermally cracking said deasphalted oil and producing a thermally cracked product which is recycled only to the inlet of said atmospheric fractionating tower; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>g) supplying only a heavy portion of said light vacuum fractions to a light vacuum fraction thermal cracker for thermally cracking said light vacuum fractions for producing a further cracked product which is recycled only to the inlet of said atmospheric fractionating tower;</claim-text>
<claim-text>h) supplying said light atmospheric fractions produced by said atmospheric fractionating tower to a hydrogen donor producing system for processing a portion of said light atmospheric fractions produced by said atmospheric fractionating tower and producing a hydrogen donor stream, such that the following steps are carried out in sequence;</claim-text>
<claim-text>i) supplying a portion of said light atmospheric fractions produced by said atmospheric fractionating tower to a hydrotreater for producing a treated hydrocarbon feed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>j) supplying said treated hydrocarbon feed to a still further heater for producing a heated, treated hydrocarbon stream;</claim-text>
<claim-text>k) supplying said heated, treated hydrocarbon stream to a further atmospheric fractionating tower for fractionating said heated, treated hydrocarbon stream for producing further light atmospheric fractions and further atmospheric bottoms;</claim-text>
<claim-text>l) supplying said further atmospheric bottoms to an additional heater for heating said further atmospheric bottoms and producing heated further atmospheric bottoms; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>m) supplying said heated further atmospheric bottoms to a further vacuum fractionating tower for fractionating said heated further atmospheric bottoms and producing further lighter vacuum fractions and further vacuum residue wherein a portion of the heavier portion of said further lighter vacuum fractions or hydrogen donor stream is supplied to said deasphalted oil thermal cracker and a further portion of the heavier portion of said further lighter vacuum fractions or hydrogen donor stream is supplied to said light vacuum fraction thermal cracker.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
