<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296735-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296735</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11305574</doc-number>
<date>20051216</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>25</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>07</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>19</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235379</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Media thickness sensor assembly</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3624494</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Turan</name>
<date>19711100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324653</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4107606</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Typpo et al.</name>
<date>19780800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324229</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4446427</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lovrenich</name>
<date>19840500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>32420716</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4989520</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hain</name>
<date>19910200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>109 241</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6218729</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Zavrel et al.</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257698</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0013541</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Modi</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>235379</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0035836</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Howard et al.</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>335205</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235379</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235439</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>902 19</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070138278</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070621</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tennant</last-name>
<first-name>Alan</first-name>
<address>
<city>Drum</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>GB</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>GB</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Priest &amp; Goldstein PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>NCR Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Dayton</city>
<state>OH</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Michael G.</first-name>
<department>2876</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Savusdiphol</last-name>
<first-name>Paultep</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A thickness sensor assembly (<b>200</b>) for a self-service terminal (SST) arranged to dispense media from at least one media cassette. The sensor assembly comprises a platform (<b>202</b>) and a resonant circuit (<b>300</b>) mounted on the platform (<b>202</b>) and resiliently biased towards a rest position, the sensor assembly (<b>200</b>) being arranged such that the displacement of the resonant circuit (<b>300</b>) can be detected by an SST in which the platform (<b>202</b>) is mounted. In use, the platform (<b>202</b>) is mounted in an SST adjacent to a feed path (<b>72</b>) of media being dispensed thereby such that media moving along the feed path (<b>72</b>) displaces the resonant circuit (<b>300</b>). Such a sensor assembly (<b>200</b>) can be used to detect, for example, when two media sheets have been picked up instead of one.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="139.87mm" wi="152.82mm" file="US07296735-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="233.00mm" wi="177.12mm" file="US07296735-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="172.13mm" wi="151.72mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296735-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="152.82mm" wi="141.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296735-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="191.69mm" wi="141.14mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296735-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="182.37mm" wi="94.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296735-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a media thickness sensor assembly. It is particularly related to, but in no way limited to, a media thickness sensor assembly in a self-service terminal (SST) such as an automated teller machine (ATM).</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Thickness sensors are usually employed in SSTs or ATMs to determine whether the expected number of media sheets is present at a particular point during processing of the media and in particular to detect double or multiple picking where only one item of media should have been picked. In an ATM, the thickness of notes which go to make up the stack of notes which is presented to a user of the machine is checked during their transportation through the dispenser unit. If a reading is thicker than expected, it is assumed that the pick means has, for example, picked up two notes rather than one and the stack of notes is not presented to the user. Instead, the stack is diverted to a purge bin.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The use of a note thickness sensor in an ATM can be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> which shows a schematic side elevation view of a cash dispenser unit <b>73</b> of an ATM. The cash dispenser unit <b>73</b> holds a number of currency cassettes <b>89</b> each holding a stack of currency notes <b>68</b>. Each cassette <b>89</b> holds only one denomination of currency notes, but different cassettes may contain different denominations. The notes <b>68</b> are held in place in the cassette by means of a pusher plate <b>69</b> which urges the stack of notes to one end of the cassette.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">When one or more notes are to be dispensed from a particular cassette <b>89</b>, the pick mechanism <b>74</b> associated with the cassette <b>89</b> draws a note from the cassette <b>89</b> such that its leading edge is gripped between drive rollers <b>90</b>. The note is then fed along the feed path <b>72</b> by further drive rollers <b>92</b>, through a retard mechanism <b>10</b> to a stacker wheel assembly <b>75</b>. The stacker wheel assembly <b>75</b> comprises a hub <b>76</b> bearing tines <b>78</b> and is arranged to rotate on a shaft <b>77</b>. As each note passes along the feed path <b>72</b>, its thickness is checked by a compensated capacitance thickness sensor <b>118</b>, in order to detect whether more than one note has been picked up inadvertently. In operation, the stacker wheel assembly <b>75</b>, which comprises a hub <b>76</b> bearing tines <b>78</b> and arranged to rotate on a shaft <b>77</b>. The stacker wheel assembly <b>75</b> rotates continuously in a counter-clockwise direction (for the arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) and the note is fed into a compartment <b>81</b> formed between adjacent tines <b>78</b>. If more than one note is to be dispensed, each note is fed into a successive compartment <b>81</b> as the stacker wheel assembly <b>75</b> rotates. Having completed half a rotation, the note is removed from the stacker wheel assembly <b>75</b> by fingers <b>94</b> of a stripper plate assembly <b>96</b> pivotally mounted on a shaft <b>98</b>. Once removed from the stacker wheel, the note is placed on a belt <b>100</b> resting against the stripper plate assembly <b>96</b> and any subsequent notes which are to be dispensed simultaneously with the first note are placed on top of the first note to form a bundle <b>68</b>′. When the required amount of notes (which may be just one note) have been assembled into the bundle <b>68</b>′, a pair of belts <b>102</b> (only one of which is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) is rotated on a shaft <b>104</b> such that the bundle <b>68</b>′ is trapped between the belts <b>100</b>, <b>102</b>. The bundle is then fed between belts <b>100</b>, <b>102</b>, <b>106</b>, <b>108</b> through a note exit slot <b>110</b> in the housing <b>112</b> of the cash dispenser unit <b>73</b> usually to a position where the bundle <b>68</b>′ can be collected by the user of the ATM.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">If a multiple feeding is detected by the thickness sensor <b>118</b> or one or more of the notes are rejected for any reason, the bundle is not fed to the note exit slot <b>110</b>. Instead the stripper plate assembly <b>96</b> is pivoted into a position as shown by the dashed outline <b>96</b>′ and the belts <b>100</b>, <b>102</b> are operated in the reverse direction to deposit the bundle <b>68</b>′ into a reject note container <b>114</b> via an opening <b>116</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The compensated capacitance sensor <b>118</b> is neither as cheap nor as robust as is desirable. In normal use and in particular during maintenance and replacing media cassettes <b>89</b>, sensors <b>118</b> tend to become inaccurate or become offset. This either results in multiple feeding not being detected or correctly assembled bundles being rejected. This means that the purge bin <b>114</b> becomes full and has to be emptied and the media cassettes <b>89</b> run out of notes more quickly than could otherwise be the case, requiring refilling. Faults require servicing the compensated capacitance sensor <b>118</b>, which is a part of the machine which is not readily accessible.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to a first aspect of the present invention, there is provided a thickness sensor assembly for a self-service terminal (SST) arranged to dispense media, the sensor assembly comprising a platform and a resonant circuit mounted on the platform and resiliently biased towards a rest position, the sensor assembly being arranged such that a displacement of the resonant circuit from its rest position can be detected by an aerial and the platform being arranged to be mounted in an SST adjacent to a feed path of media being dispensed thereby such that media moving along the feed path displaces the circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">This is advantageous as a resonant circuit is more robust and cheaper to manufacture than prior art solutions such as compensated capacitance sensors. Further, the displacement of a resonant circuit from its rest position may be detected, rather than its distance from a sensor. This means that there will be no absolute measurement errors due to incorrect placement or shifting of the sensor.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Preferably, the resonant circuit is electrically passive. This is advantageous as it contributes to the robustness of the sensor; an electrically passive sensor is less likely to fail.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Preferably, the platform comprises mounting means arranged such that the platform is readily removable from an SST in which the sensor assembly is installed. This may be achieved by situating the platform towards the back, or the service side, of the SST. The platform may comprise a ‘slide-out’ member, or drawer, designed to slot, slide or similarly be brought into place in the SST. This is advantageous as it provides a solution to thickness sensing which is in-line with the desire to make machines such as SSTs modular, allowing components thereof to be removed and replaced if faulty, rather than requiring on-site repair or the complex and expensive process of moving the SST to a repair shop. As the sensor is a resonant circuit, it is more robust than prior art solutions and is therefore more suited to being mounted on a removable platform. Where the resonant circuit is electrically passive, it will not require disconnection from an input/output means and is also more suited to being mounted on a removable platform.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The thickness sensor assembly may further comprise at least one aerial mounted on the platform comprising at least one receive circuitry and at least one output means, the aerial being arranged, in use, to detect the displacement of the or each resonant circuit based on a signal received by the aerial and to output a signal indicative or the detected displacement via the output means. This is advantageous as such as assembly therefore comprises all the components necessary to detect media thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Preferably the aerial further comprises transmit circuitry for generating an alternating electromagnetic field. This advantageously provides a magnetic field which will be affected by a displacement of the resonant circuit, and this effect may be detected by the aerial.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Preferably, in embodiments where the aerial comprises transmit circuitry, the aerial and the resonant circuit are arranged such that a face of the aerial is opposed to and substantially parallel to the face of the resonant circuit and further arranged such that, in use of the sensor assembly, a displacement by media moving along the feed path of the resonant circuit is substantially parallel to the plane of the opposed faces. This is advantageous as the relative movement of the faces will have an effect on the alternating electromagnetic field which is readily detectable.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Preferably the sensing assembly further comprises processing means for calculating media thickness based on the displacement of the or each resonant circuit. Advantageously this provides an accurate indication of the media thickness which can be compared to an expected thickness to determine whether the media has been correctly placed.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Preferably, the platform comprises a rigid member. This is advantageous as any flexing in the platform will contribute to errors in measuring the thickness of media passing through the sensor assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">According to a second aspect of the present invention, there is provided a self service terminal (SST) comprising at least one media cassette, at least one pick means arranged to pick media from the or each media cassette and a transport mechanism arranged to transport media picked by the pick means to an outlet of the SST, the SST further comprising an aerial and at least one thickness sensor assembly comprising at least one resonant circuit resiliently mounted on a platform and arranged such that the or each resonant circuit is displaced by media moving through the transport mechanism and further arranged such that, in use of the SST, the displacement of the or each resonant circuit may be detected by the aerial.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In perhaps a preferred embodiment, the SST comprises an ATM.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The SST may further comprise processing means for calculating media thickness based on the displacement of the or each resonant circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The thickness sensor assembly of the SST may have any of the features described in relation to the first aspect of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A third aspect of the present invention provides a method of detecting thickness of media comprising generating an alternating magnetic field, arranging a arranging a resonant circuit sensor assembly in that field, causing the media to move along a feed path such that the resonant circuit sensor assembly is displaced by the media, detecting the effect of the displacement on the magnetic field and determining, from the detected effect, the thickness of the media.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The method may be performed by firmware or software in machine readable form on a storage medium.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">This acknowledges that firmware and software can be valuable, separately tradable commodities. It is intended to encompass software, which runs on or controls “dumb” or standard hardware, to carry out the desired functions. For similar reasons, it is also intended to encompass software which “describes” or defines the configuration of hardware, such as HDL (hardware description language) software, as is used for designing silicon chips, or for configuring universal programmable chips, to carry out desired functions.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The preferred features may be combined as appropriate, as would be apparent to a skilled person, and may be combined with any of the aspects of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Embodiments of the invention will be described, by way of example, with reference to the following drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic side elevation of a cash dispenser unit of a prior art ATM;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a simplified schematic diagram of a portion of a back view of a cash dispenser unit including a thickness sensor according to one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a schematic arrangement for a thickness sensor assembly according to one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a simplified schematic diagram of a portion of a back view of a cash dispenser unit including a thickness sensor according to a second embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a schematic arrangement for a thickness sensor assembly according to the second embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Common reference numerals are used throughout the figures to indicate similar features.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Embodiments of the present invention are described below by way of example only. These examples represent the best ways of putting the invention into practice that are currently known to the Applicant although they are not the only ways in which this could be achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a side view of prior art cash dispenser unit <b>73</b> of an Automated Teller Machine (ATM) and has been described above.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a back view of a portion of a cash dispenser unit <b>73</b>′ according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The cash dispenser unit <b>73</b>′ is similar to that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> but differs in that it the compensated capacitance sensors <b>118</b> have been removed and replaced with resonant circuit sensor assemblies <b>200</b> mounted on a rigid metal platform <b>202</b>, which in turn is mounted on the housing <b>112</b> of the cash dispenser unit <b>73</b>′ at four mounting points <b>204</b> which comprise bolt holes and provide mounting means for removably mounting the platform <b>202</b> in the cash dispenser unit <b>73</b>′. The view shown is at the top of the feed path, adjacent the uppermost drive rollers <b>92</b>, which in this case comprise a pair of wheels <b>206</b><i>a</i>, <b>206</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The resonant circuit sensor assemblies <b>200</b> are illustrated in greater detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> and each comprise a printed circuit board (PCB) <b>300</b> mounted on the platform <b>202</b> on a resilient mounting <b>302</b> and an aerial <b>304</b>, which comprises a further resonant circuit PCB and which is linked via an output means <b>310</b> to processing means <b>312</b> in the dispenser unit <b>73</b>′ (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The aerials <b>304</b> each comprise transmit circuitry <b>314</b> arranged to generate an alternating electromagnetic field and receive circuitry <b>316</b>, also shown schematically in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The resiliently mounted resonant circuit <b>300</b> may, for example, comprise a Sensopad (trade mark) puck, and the aerial <b>304</b> may, for example, comprise a Sensopad (trademark) pad as produced by Sensopad Technologies Ltd. The resiliently mounted resonant circuit <b>300</b> will be referred to herein a puck and the aerial <b>304</b> will be referred to herein as a pad, however a skilled person will appreciate that resonant circuits and aerials other than those supplied by Sensopad Technologies Ltd may be used.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The sensing system relies on inductance to operate, with transmit circuitry <b>314</b> in the pad <b>304</b> generating an alternating electro-magnetic field which induces currents in the puck <b>300</b>. As a result of these induced currents, each puck generates an alternating electromagnetic field and the resultant electromagnetic field is detected by receive circuitry <b>316</b> in the pad <b>304</b>. The receive circuitry <b>316</b> in the pad are electrically isolated from the transmit circuitry <b>314</b> in the pad <b>304</b>. The processing means <b>312</b> can determine, from the received signal, the positions of a puck <b>300</b> relative to the pad <b>304</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Each puck <b>300</b> further comprises a contact member <b>308</b>. When in position within the dispenser unit <b>73</b>′ as is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, each contact member is urged against a wheel <b>206</b><i>a</i>, <b>206</b><i>b</i>. The arrangement is such that, when a note moves along the feed path <b>72</b>, it passes between the wheels <b>206</b><i>a</i>, <b>206</b><i>b </i>and the contact member <b>306</b>. This causes the pucks <b>300</b> to move relative to their adjacent pads <b>304</b>. This causes a signal indicative of the displacement to be sent via the output means <b>310</b> to the processing circuitry, which then determines whether double or multiple picking has occurred by comparing the measured thickness with a predetermined expected thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Relative movements of puck <b>300</b> and the pad <b>304</b> as small as 5 microns can be detected with such a system. Bank notes tend to have a thickness on the order of 50 to 100 microns, depending on currency, the denomination and the like. Therefore the puck <b>300</b> and the pad <b>304</b> provide a sensor accurate enough to determine whether one or two bank notes are passing.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">As will be appreciated by the person skilled in the art, the expected thickness of a note will vary for different currencies but will be known for a specific currency.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">If a ‘multiple feeding’ is detected by the resonant circuit sensor <b>200</b> in feeding the notes, a bundle <b>68</b>′ including the multiple feeding is not fed to the note exit slot <b>110</b>. Instead the stripper plate assembly <b>96</b> is pivoted into a position as shown by the dashed outline <b>96</b>′ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and the belts <b>100</b>, <b>102</b> are operated in the reverse direction to deposit the bundle <b>68</b>′ into a reject note container <b>114</b> via an opening <b>116</b>. The pick operation then repeats to assemble a new bundle.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">A second embodiment of the invention is now discussed with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the platform is provided by a removable drawer <b>400</b> on which the resonant circuit sensor assembly <b>200</b> is mounted. The drawer <b>400</b> as shown in greater detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> comprises mounting means in the form of ‘click-in’ connection means <b>502</b>. These comprise C-shaped resilient plastic members arranged to co-operate with parts of the cash dispenser unit <b>73</b>′ (not shown), such that it clicks into place but can be removed there from. The connection means <b>502</b> therefore comprise mounting means for removably mounting the drawer <b>400</b> in the cash dispenser unit <b>73</b>′. The drawer <b>400</b> further comprises a pair of belts <b>504</b> which are driven to move a note along the feed path <b>72</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">In this embodiment, the puck <b>300</b> and the pad <b>304</b> are mounted on the side of the drawer <b>400</b> away from the feed path <b>72</b> and the contact member <b>306</b> protrudes through the drawer into the feed path <b>72</b>. The puck <b>300</b> and the contact member <b>306</b> are resiliently mounted on a leaf spring <b>404</b>, one end of which is fixed to the drawer <b>400</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">When in position within the cash dispenser unit <b>73</b>′, as is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, each contact member <b>306</b> is urged against a rigid plastic chassis portion <b>402</b>. The arrangement is such that, when a note moves along the feed path <b>72</b>, it passes between chassis portion <b>402</b> and the contact member <b>306</b>. This causes the pucks <b>300</b> to move relative to their adjacent pads <b>304</b>. This causes a signal indicative of the displacement to be sent via the output means <b>308</b> to the processing circuitry <b>312</b>, which then determines whether double picking has occurred by comparing the measured thickness with a predetermined expected thickness, as discussed above.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Other embodiments and/or combinations of features from the above embodiments will be readily apparent to the man skilled in the art. For example, sensor assemblies according to one aspect may be embodied in self service terminals other than ATMs. Other components of the dispensing unit may vary from those described herein. For example, the bundle of notes may be formed in a shuttle which transports the bundle to the note exit point <b>110</b>.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A thickness sensor assembly for a self-service terminal (SST) arranged to dispense media, the sensor assembly comprising a platform and a resonant circuit mounted on the platform and resiliently biased towards a rest position, the resonant circuit comprising a contact member urged against a surface when the resonant circuit is in the rest position, displacement of the resonant circuit from the rest position occurring when media passes between the surface and the contact member, forcing the contact member away from the surface, the sensor assembly being arranged such that a displacement of the resonant circuit from its rest position can be detected by an aerial and the platform being arranged to be mounted in an SST adjacent to a feed path of media being dispensed thereby such that media moving along the feed path displaces the circuit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A thickness sensor assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> in which the resonant circuit is electrically passive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A thickness sensor assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> in which the platform comprises mounting means arranged such that the platform is readily removable from an SST in which the sensor assembly is installed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A thickness sensor assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> which comprises at least one aerial mounted on the platform comprising at least one receive circuitry and at least one output means, the aerial being arranged, in use, to detect the displacement of the or each resonant circuit based on a signal received by the aerial and to output a signal indicative or the detected displacement via the output means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A thickness sensor assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> in which the aerial further comprises transmit circuitry for generating an alternating electro-magnetic field.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A thickness sensor assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> in which the aerial and the resonant circuit are arranged such that a face of the aerial is opposed and substantially parallel to the face of the resonant circuit and further arranged such that, in use of the sensor assembly, a displacement caused by media moving along the feed path of the resonant circuit is substantially parallel to the plane of the opposed faces.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A thickness sensor assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> which comprises processing means for calculating media thickness based on the displacement of the or each resonant circuit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A thickness sensor assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> in which the platform comprises a rigid member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A self service terminal comprising at least one media cassette, at least one pick means arranged to pick media from the or each media cassette and a transport mechanism arranged to transport media picked by the pick means to an exit of the self service terminal, the self service terminal further comprising at least one thickness sensor assembly comprising at least one resonant circuit mounted on a platform and resiliently biased against the transport mechanism, the sensor assembly being arranged such that the or each resonant circuit is displaced by media moving through the transport mechanism, each resonant circuit comprising a contact member urged against a surface when the resonant circuit is in the rest position, displacement of the resonant circuit from the rest position occurring when media passes between the surface and the contact member, forcing the contact member away from the surface, and further arranged such that, in use of the self service terminal, the displacement of the or each resonant circuit may be detected by the aerial.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A self service terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> which further comprises processing means for calculating media thickness based on the displacement of the or each resonant circuit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method of detecting thickness of media comprising generating an alternating magnetic field, arranging a resonant circuit sensor assembly in that field, causing the media to move along a feed path such that the resonant circuit sensor assembly is displaced by the media, the resonant circuit comprising a contact member urged against a surface when the resonant circuit is in a rest position, displacement of the resonant circuit from the rest position occurring when media passes between the surface and the contact member, forcing the contact member away from the surface, detecting the effect of the displacement on the magnetic field and determining, from the detected effect, the thickness of the media.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
