<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299000-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299000</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11118412</doc-number>
<date>20050502</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-320500</doc-number>
<date>20041104</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>261</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>20</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399322</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Image forming apparatus having a recording material transporting path</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6259881</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Nakamura</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399323</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7118843</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Teshima</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399328</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7149463</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Fujisawa et al.</name>
<date>20061200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399323</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-195668</doc-number>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-233405</doc-number>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399322</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399323</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399328</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060092258</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060504</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Taira</last-name>
<first-name>Seiji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hara</last-name>
<first-name>Kenji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Miba</last-name>
<first-name>Keiji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tainaka</last-name>
<first-name>Yoshiaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Onuma</last-name>
<first-name>Yumiko</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="006" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sato</last-name>
<first-name>Keiichiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="007" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Miyoshi</last-name>
<first-name>Noriyuki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="008" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Eda</last-name>
<first-name>Masakatsu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="009" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yano</last-name>
<first-name>Keita</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="010" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Suzuki</last-name>
<first-name>Tomofumi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ebina</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Morgan, Lewis &amp; Bockius</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fuji Xerox Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Royer</last-name>
<first-name>William J.</first-name>
<department>2852</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An image forming apparatus includes a recording material transporting path that extends in a direction from bottom to top of a body of the image forming apparatus and transports a recording material, a fixing device provided on the recording material transporting path, which includes a rotatable heating member that has an internal heat source and a rotatable pressure member that forms a nip area with the heating member by being located in contact with and pressed against the heating member, to nip the recording material for carrying out a fixing process, and an ejection guide member that guides a recording material ejected from the nip area to the outside of the image forming apparatus. The ejection guide member has a guide surface formed to intersect a tangent line of the heating member at the most downstream point of the nip area, and the guide surface intersects the tangent line at an obtuse angle.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="164.59mm" wi="117.35mm" file="US07299000-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="152.99mm" wi="134.79mm" file="US07299000-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="135.13mm" wi="113.79mm" file="US07299000-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="201.68mm" wi="108.29mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299000-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="198.88mm" wi="143.34mm" file="US07299000-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="197.27mm" wi="118.53mm" file="US07299000-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="195.24mm" wi="118.19mm" file="US07299000-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="206.67mm" wi="103.21mm" file="US07299000-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to image forming apparatus using, for example, an electrophotographic process, and more particularly, to an image forming apparatus that forms an image on a recording material, while transporting the recording material in an approximately vertical direction.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In an electrophotographic image forming apparatus such as copiers and printers, by evenly charging a photoreceptor, for example, formed in a drum-like shape (photoreceptor drum) and exposing the photoreceptor drum to light controlled, based on image information, an electrostatic latent image is formed on the photoreceptor drum. Then, by applying toner to the electrostatic latent image, a visible image (applied toner image) is developed. After a transfer unit transfers this applied toner image from the surface of the photoreceptor drum onto a recording material, a fixing device fixes the toner image to the recording material.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The fixing device for use in such an image forming apparatus is generally a combination of a fusing roller and a pressure roller pressed against each other. The fusing roller is made up of a cylindrical metal core member with an internal heat source and multiple layers formed surrounding the core including an elastic body layer and a release layer which are thermally resistive. The pressure roller is made up of a metal core member and multiple layers formed surrounding the core including a heat-resistive elastic body layer and a release layer made up of a heat-resistive resin film or a rubber film. In this configuration of the fixing device, the recording material carrying an unfixed toner image is allowed to pass between the rotating fusing roller and pressure roller. At this time, the unfixed toner image is heated and pressurized and thereby fixed to the recording material.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A configuration of the image forming apparatus is known in which the above fixing device is located vertically above the photoreceptor drum, a transport path is formed to transport the recording material supplied from a paper tray located vertically below the photoreceptor drum upward in an approximately vertical direction, the transfer unit located along the transport path transfers the toner image on the photoreceptor drum to the recording material, and the recording material is transported to the fixing device.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The image forming apparatus having this configuration features a very short transport path of the recording material and a most part of the transport path can be exposed only by opening one side of the apparatus. Thus, the image forming time from paper feed to paper ejection can be shortened and the recording material can be transported more readily. In the event of a paper jam, the jammed recording material can be removed more easily. Moreover, another merit is that the image forming apparatus can be designed to be installed in a smaller area.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, in the image forming apparatus that transports the recording material upward in the approximately vertical direction (vertical transport), because the fixing device is located on the recording material transport path from down to up against the force of gravity, when the recording material is transported after the toner image has been fixed to it at the fixing device, the gravity is exerted on the recording material being ejected from the fixing device in an opposite direction on approximately the same line as the transport direction. For this reason, unlike a conventional image forming apparatus that transports the recording material horizontally, for the image forming apparatus with the vertical transport path, it is difficult to provide a stable support of the recording material being transported, utilizing the force of gravity, and the behavior of the recording material is liable to become unstable. Because of difficulty of stable support in the horizontal direction of the recording material being transported upward in the approximately vertical direction, nipped between and driven by the fusing roller and the pressure roller rotating, pressed against each other, the recording material becomes unstable in the horizontal direction. Consequently, the recording material may move in variable directions while being transported and wave-like flexure (so-called “paper cockle”) toward the forward direction is liable to occur in the recording material. In addition, the recording material is liable to touch any of the members surrounding the transport path. Depending on an angle at which the medium touches such a member, there is a fear of bending or folding of a lead edge corner of the recording material (so-called “dog-ear”).</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The present invention has been made to address the above-described technical problems and to prevent the paper cockle and dog-ear of the recording material in the image forming apparatus in which the fixing device is installed on the recording material transport path from down to up against the force of gravity.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According to an aspect of the present invention, an image forming apparatus includes a recording material transporting path that extends in a direction from bottom to top of a body of the image forming apparatus and transports a recording material, a fixing device provided on the recording material transporting path, which includes a rotatable heating member that has an internal heat source and a rotatable pressure member that forms a nip area with the heating member by being located in contact with and pressed against the heating member, to nip the recording material for carrying out a fixing process, and an ejection guide member that guides a recording material ejected from the nip area to the outside of the image forming apparatus. The ejection guide member has a guide surface formed to intersect a tangent line of the heating member at the most downstream point of the nip area, and the guide surface intersects the tangent line at an obtuse angle.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Embodiments of the present invention will be described in detail based on the following figures, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic view showing an image forming apparatus;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross sectional view showing a configuration of a fixing unit;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a view showing paper eject guides and peeling claws arranged across the set width of paper;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view to explain arrangements of components surrounding the transport path;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a view to explain a paper eject guide located on the ejection side of the fixing unit;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a view to explain a limit of setting a pressure-roller-side of paper eject guide surface in relation with the peeling claw; and</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a view showing positional relationship of a fusing roller, paper eject guide, and peeling claw to determine an upper limit of the angle β of intersection.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">An embodiment of the present invention will be described in detail hereinafter with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic view showing an image forming apparatus to which this embodiment is applied. The image forming apparatus <b>1</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> includes a photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> as an example of a toner image carrier rotating in the direction of arrow A and electrophotographic devices installed around the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> such as a charger <b>11</b> to charge the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>, a laser exposure unit <b>12</b> (a light beam is denoted by Bm in the figure) by which flash exposure takes place to form an electrostatic latent image on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>, a development unit <b>13</b> which houses toner and makes the electrostatic latent image visible by applying the toner to the latent image on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>, a transfer roller <b>14</b> which transfers the toner image formed on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> to paper P which is a recording material, and a drum cleaner <b>15</b> by which residual toner on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> is removed. Moreover, the apparatus includes a fixing unit <b>60</b> which fixes an unfixed toner image transferred to the paper P and a controller <b>40</b> which controls the operations of the devices (units).</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Furthermore, the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> of this embodiment includes, as elements forming a paper transport path, a paper tray <b>50</b> which houses sheets of paper P, a pickup roller <b>51</b> which draws one of the paper sheets P stacked in the paper tray <b>50</b> from the paper tray <b>50</b> at predetermined timing and transports the paper sheet P, transport rollers <b>52</b> which transport the paper sheet P drawn by the pickup roller <b>51</b>, registration rollers <b>53</b> which feed the paper sheet P transported by the transport rollers <b>52</b> into the transfer roller <b>14</b> at a predetermined timing, an inlet chute <b>54</b> which guides the paper sheet P fed by the registration rollers <b>53</b> to a transfer nip area C, a transport guide <b>55</b> which transports the paper sheet P to the fixing unit <b>60</b> after the toner image transfer by the transfer roller <b>14</b>, a fixing inlet guide <b>80</b> which guides the paper sheet P being transported onto which the toner image was transferred to the fixing unit <b>60</b>, and paper eject guides <b>90</b>, <b>91</b> as paper eject guide members to guide the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> to an ejected paper stack <b>58</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In the configuration of the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> of this embodiment, the fixing unit <b>60</b> is located approximately vertically above the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> and the paper tray <b>50</b> is located approximately vertically below the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>. A sheet of paper P fed from the paper tray <b>50</b> is transported on the transport path formed upward in an approximately vertical direction. At the transfer nip area C located along this transport path, a toner image formed on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> is transferred to the paper sheet P. The paper sheet P is further moved to the fixing unit <b>60</b> located above the transfer nip area C and a fixing process is performed on the paper.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The thus configured image forming apparatus <b>1</b> features a very short transport path of paper P and it is easy to expose a most part of the transport path only by opening one side of the image forming apparatus <b>1</b>. Thus, the image forming time from paper feed to paper ejection can be shortened and the paper P can be transported more readily. In the event of a paper jam, the jammed paper P can be removed more easily. Moreover, another merit is that the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> can be designed to be installed in a smaller area.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Next, a basic image forming process of the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> according to this embodiment is described. In conjunction with the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an image processing device not shown performs predetermined image processing on image data that is output from an image reading device (IIT) not shown, a personal computer (PC) not shown, or the like. The image processing device can perform a prescribed set of image processing such as shading correction, displacement correction, gamma correction, and image editing including edge erase, move editing, and the like on reflectance data that has been input to the image processing device. The thus processed image data is output to the laser exposure unit <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The laser exposure unit <b>12</b> applies a light beam Bm emitted from, for example, a semiconductor laser to the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>, according to the image data that has been input to laser exposure unit <b>12</b>. After the surface of the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> is charged by the charger <b>11</b> made up of a charging roller to a predetermined charging potential (e.g., −750V), the drum surface is scanned and exposed to the light beam from the laser exposure unit <b>12</b> and an electrostatic latent image is formed on the drum surface.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The formed electrostatic latent image is developed through a reversal development of negatively charged toner by the development unit <b>13</b>. Specifically, by applying a developing bias of DC voltage or AC voltage superimposed with DC voltage from a power source not shown to a developer carrier (development sleeve) <b>13</b><i>a </i>that carries a developer in which toner particles with shape factors SF<b>1</b> of 100 to 140 produced by, e.g., a polymerization method are mixed with carriers of magnetic particles, a development field is formed between the development unit <b>13</b> and the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>. Thereby, the toner is transferred from the development sleeve <b>13</b><i>a </i>to the imaging portions of the electrostatic latent image (exposed to the light) and the electrostatic latent image is visualized.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Next, as the toner image formed on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> is moved to the transfer nip area C where the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> and the transfer roller <b>14</b> are brought into contact, a sheet of paper P of a given size is supplied from the paper tray <b>50</b> by rotation of the pickup roller <b>51</b> and put on the paper transport path in timing with the toner image movement to the transfer nip area C. The paper sheet P supplied by the pickup roller <b>51</b> is transported by the transport rollers <b>52</b> and come to the registration rollers <b>53</b>. At the registration rollers <b>53</b>, the paper sheet P is stopped and the registration rollers <b>53</b> rotate in timing with the motion of the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> carrying the toner image. Thereby, the paper sheet P position and the toner image position are aligned and the paper sheet P is guided by the inlet chute <b>54</b> and moved to the transfer nip area C.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">At the transfer nip area C, the transfer roller <b>14</b> is located in contact with and pressed against the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>. The transfer roller <b>14</b> is made up of a shaft and a sponge layer as an elastic layer bonded around the shaft. The shaft is a cylindrical metal bar made of iron, SUS, and the like. The sponge layer is made of a blended rubber of NBR, SBR, and EPDM mixed with a conductive agent such as carbon black and a cylindrical spongy roll with volume resistivity of 10<sup>7 </sup>to 10<sup>9 </sup>Ωcm.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Current-controlled constant current, for example, is supplied to the transfer roller <b>14</b> so that a transfer bias with polarity (positive) opposite to the polarity (negative) of the charges of the toner is steadily applied from a transfer power source (not shown). Thereby, charges with polarity opposite to the polarity of the charges of the toner on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> are applied from the transfer roller <b>14</b> to the paper sheet P. The transfer bias is set to be applied only when the region of an image formed on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> passes through the transfer nip area C and not to be applied when an inter-image region between image regions passes through the transfer nip area C.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The paper sheet P being transported in timing with the image is transported to the transfer nip area C and nipped between the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> and the transfer roller <b>14</b>. At this time, by applying the transfer bias from the transfer roller <b>14</b>, the unfixed toner image carried on the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> is electrostatically transferred to the paper sheet P.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Then, the paper sheet P onto which the toner image has been transferred electrostatically is peeled from the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> by electrostatic adsorptive power from the transfer roller <b>14</b> and stiffness of the paper sheet P and transported to the fixing unit <b>60</b> located downstream of the transfer roller <b>14</b> in the paper sheet P transport direction. A peeling claw <b>16</b> is provided downstream of the transfer nip area C and near the surface of the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> to separate the paper sheet P from the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>, if the paper sheet P remains sticking to the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> without being peeled from the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The unfixed toner image on the paper sheet P transported to the fixing unit <b>60</b> is fixed onto the paper sheet P by undergoing a fixing process with heat and pressure in the fixing unit <b>60</b>. The paper sheet P having a fixed image formed thereon is transported to the ejected paper stack <b>58</b> provided in the ejection part of the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> and a series of image forming actions is complete.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Next, the configuration of the fixing unit <b>60</b> is described.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross sectional view showing the configuration of the fixing unit <b>60</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the fixing unit <b>60</b> is configured as a unit including a first casing <b>65</b> to rotatably support a fusing roller <b>61</b> and a second casing <b>66</b> to rotatably support a pressure roller <b>62</b>. Both the casings <b>65</b> and <b>66</b> are installed such that a line connecting the center of the fusing roller <b>61</b> with the center of the pressure roller <b>62</b> is approximately horizontal in the image forming apparatus <b>1</b>. The pressure roller <b>62</b> is pressed against the fusing roller <b>61</b> by an elastic body (not shown) made up of a coil spring or the like and a fixing nip area N is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The fusing roller <b>61</b> is made up of a cylindrical core <b>611</b> and a release layer <b>612</b> coating the surface of the core <b>611</b>. The core <b>611</b> has an outside diameter of, for example, 25 mm and a thickness of, for example, 1 to 1.5 mm. The core <b>611</b> is made of high thermal conductivity metal material, for example, iron, aluminum, SUS, and the like. For the release layer <b>612</b>, a heat-resistive resin such as a silicon resin and a fluorocarbon resin can be used; the fluorocarbon resin is more suitable from a perspective of toner releasability and abrasion resistance. As the fluorocarbon resin, tetrafluoroethylene-perfluoroalkylvinylether copolymer (PFA), polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE), tetrafluoroethylene-hexafluoropropylene copolymer (FEP), and the like can be used. The release layer <b>612</b> is formed to have a thickness of, for example, 5 to 100 μm</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Inside the fusing roller <b>61</b>, for example, halogen heaters <b>67</b> with a rating of 600 W are installed to heat the fusing roller <b>61</b>. A temperature sensor <b>69</b> is installed in contact with the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b>. The controller <b>40</b> of the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> performs on/off control of the halogen heaters <b>67</b>, based on temperature measurement by the temperature sensor <b>69</b>, and makes an adjustment to maintain the surface temperature of the fusing roller <b>61</b> at a predetermined temperature setting (e.g., 175° C.). Moreover, a thermostat <b>70</b> is installed near the fusing roller <b>61</b> inside the first casing <b>65</b> to prevent a fault of the fusing roller <b>61</b> due to overtemperature.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The pressure roller <b>62</b> is made up of a solid-core shaft <b>621</b> which is, for example, columnar, a heat-resistive elastic body layer <b>622</b> formed around the shaft <b>621</b>, and a release layer <b>623</b> coating the surface of the heat-resistive elastic body layer <b>622</b>. The shaft <b>621</b> is made of, for example, iron or aluminum and may be hollow. The heat-resistive elastic body layer <b>622</b> is formed of a heat-resistive material with hardness of 45° (Asker C), for example, a silicon sponge or silicon rubber. The heat-resistive elastic body layer <b>622</b> is formed to have a thickness of 6 mm or more to provide an approximately constant nip width when the pressure roller <b>62</b> is pressed against the fusing roller <b>61</b>. A suitable range of the thickness of the heat-resistive elastic body layer <b>622</b> is 6 to 8 mm. The release layer <b>623</b> is made of, for example, PFA having good toner releasability and abrasion resistance. . A suitable range of the thickness of the release layer <b>623</b> is, for example, 30 to 100 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The paper transport path is formed upstream and downstream of the fixing nip area N formed between the fusing roller <b>61</b> and the pressure roller <b>62</b> and a sheet of paper P is transported from down to up. Upstream of the fixing nip area N (paper feed side), the fixing inlet guide <b>80</b> made up of, a plate metal which forms a part of the paper transport path is installed. Downstream of the fixing nip area N (paper ejection side), the paper eject guides <b>90</b>, <b>91</b> which form a part of the paper transport path are installed. The paper eject guides <b>90</b>, <b>91</b> are formed of multiple ribs and installed on the side of the first casing <b>65</b> and on the side of the second casing <b>66</b>, respectively, to allow the sheet of paper P to pass between the paper eject guide <b>90</b> and the paper eject guide <b>91</b>. Moreover, at the vertex of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> facing toward the paper eject guide <b>91</b>, a rotating roller <b>93</b> is installed to avoid abrasion of the paper sheet P passing between the paper eject guide <b>90</b> and the paper eject guide <b>91</b>, thus implementing smooth paper transport.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Downstream of and near the fixing nip area N, plural peeling claws <b>92</b> are arranged on the first casing <b>65</b> in an axial direction (across the width of paper) of the fusing roller <b>61</b>. These peeling claws <b>92</b> are forced toward the fusing roller <b>61</b> with a small force so as not to damage the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> and arranged to peel a paper sheet P that is going to wind around the fusing roller <b>61</b> with their tips being pressed against the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a view showing paper eject guides <b>90</b> and peeling claws <b>92</b> arranged across the set width of paper. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the paper eject guides <b>90</b> and peeling claws <b>92</b> are arranged roughly alternately at predetermined intervals in a paper eject guide holder <b>94</b>. Rotating rollers <b>93</b> are installed at the respective vertexes of the paper eject guides <b>90</b>. Through this arrangement, the paper sheet P passed across the fixing nip area N is transported to the ejected paper stack <b>58</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Next, the arrangement of components surrounding the transport path is described.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view to explain the arrangement of the components surrounding the transport path. First, positional relationship between the transfer roller <b>14</b> and the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> is explained. In the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> of this embodiment, the paper transport path is formed from down to up in an approximately vertical direction. At the exit (downstream) of the transfer nip area C where the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> and the transfer roller <b>14</b> are brought into contact, if the paper sheet P is ejected leaning toward the side of the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> from the vertical direction, then the paper sheet P will be transported with its surface having the toner image transferred thereto leaning toward the side of the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>. In that event, the toner image touches the members arranged in the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> and is disturbed, resulting in an image defect. Thus, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the position where the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> and the transfer roller <b>14</b> are brought into contact is set slightly below a horizontal plane passing through the center of the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b>. By this arrangement, the paper sheet P that has passed across the transfer nip area C is ejected leaning toward the side of the transfer roller <b>14</b> from the vertical direction and, therefore, the toner image on the paper sheet P is restrained from touching the members such as the peeling claw <b>16</b> and a start wheel <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Next, positional relationship between the fusing roller <b>61</b> and the pressure roller <b>62</b> in the fixing unit <b>60</b> is explained. In the fixing unit <b>60</b>, the fusing roller casing <b>65</b> and the pressure roller casing <b>66</b> are installed such that the line connecting the center of the fusing roller <b>61</b> with the center of the pressure roller <b>62</b> is approximately horizontal in the image forming apparatus <b>1</b>, as described above. However, when the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> is allowed to pass between the paper eject guide <b>90</b> and the paper eject guide <b>91</b> and transported to the ejected paper stack <b>58</b>, if the curvature radius of the transport path formed between the paper eject guide <b>90</b> and the paper eject guide <b>91</b> is small (forming a steep curve), the paper sheet P is liable to curl immediately after being heated by the fixing unit <b>60</b>. Thus, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the pressure roller <b>62</b> is installed slightly above a horizontal plane passing through the center of the fusing roller <b>61</b> in the fixing unit <b>60</b>. By this arrangement, the paper sheet P passed across the fixing nip area N is ejected leaning toward the side of the fusing roller <b>61</b>, in other words, the side of the ejected paper stack <b>58</b> from the vertical direction. Consequently, between the paper eject guide <b>90</b> and the paper eject guide <b>91</b>, the transport path can be formed with a large curvature radius and the paper sheet P can be restrained from curling.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Moreover, positional relationship in the horizontal direction between the transfer nip area C between the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> and the transfer roller <b>14</b> and the fixing nip area N where the fusing roller <b>61</b> is pressed against the pressure roller <b>62</b> in the fixing unit <b>60</b> is explained. In the horizontal direction, if the fixing nip area N is positioned nearer to the center of the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> inward from the transfer nip area C, when the paper sheet P that has passed across the transfer nip area C is transported to the fixing unit <b>60</b>, it is needed to bend the paper path toward the fixing nip area N. In this arrangement, it becomes easy for the paper sheet P to touch the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> and this is undesirable. On the other hand, in the horizontal direction, the fixing nip area N is positioned nearer to the center of the transfer roller <b>14</b> outward from the transfer nip area C, it is needed to transport the paper sheet P while bringing the paper sheet P in contact with the transfer roller <b>14</b> longer to ensure stable transportation of the paper sheet P. In this case, the area where the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> is installed becomes larger. In view of the above, the horizontal position of the fixing nip area N may be virtually the same as the horizontal position of the transfer nip area C or somewhat shifted toward the transfer roller side from the position of the transfer nip area C.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">By this placement of the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> and the transfer roller <b>14</b> and the placement of the fusing roller <b>61</b> and the pressure roller <b>62</b> in the fixing unit <b>60</b>, the paper transport path from the transfer nip area C to fixing nip area N is slightly bent away from the photoreceptor drum <b>10</b> downstream of the exit of the transfer nip area C and slightly bent to the photoreceptor drum side before entering the fixing unit <b>60</b>. Through this arrangement, the paper transport path from the transfer nip area C to the fixing nip area N draws a gently curved line outward from the vertical direction toward the transfer roller side (pressure roller side), as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, which makes it hard for the paper sheet P surface carrying the toner image to touch the members installed surrounding the transport path.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In particular, in the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> of this embodiment, the distance from the transfer nip area C to the fixing nip area N is shorter than a lengthwise dimension of, for example, A<b>4</b> size paper sheet P and, therefore, it might occur that the lead edge of a paper sheet P enters the fixing nip area N while its trail edge is still nipped by the transfer nip area C. To avoid a transfer deviation or defect caused by a paper sheet P whose trail edge is nipped by the transfer nip area C pulled by the nip of its lead edge in the fixing nip area N, the roller speed in the fixing unit <b>60</b> is set somewhat slower than the roller speed in the transfer nip area C. Thereby, the paper sheet P on the transport path from the transfer nip area C to the fixing nip area N becomes slack slightly. Therefore, to make it hard for the paper sheet P to touch the members installed surrounding the transport path, the paper transport path is formed to have a gently curved line outward from the vertical direction toward the transfer roller side (pressure roller side) as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Next, after the paper sheet P is transported from the transfer nip area C to the fixing unit <b>60</b> on the above-described transport path and the fixing process is performed in the fixing unit <b>60</b>, a transport path along which the paper sheet P is ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> is explained.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a view to explain the paper eject guide <b>90</b> located on the ejection side of the fixing unit <b>60</b>. As described above, the paper eject guides <b>90</b>, <b>91</b> formed of ribs are installed on the ejection side of the fixing unit <b>60</b>. The paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> is guided to pass between the paper eject guide <b>90</b> and the paper eject guide <b>91</b> and transported to the ejected paper stack <b>58</b> provided in the ejection part of the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> also). At this time, to prevent wave-like flexure (so-called “paper cockle”) toward the forward direction and bending or folding of a lead edge corner (so-called “dog-ear”) of the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b>, the paper eject guide <b>90</b> of this embodiment is designed as follows. A transport-path-side guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is formed to intersect a tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> at an exit point N<b>2</b> from the fixing nip area N at an obtuse angle β near the fusing roller <b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Now, a mechanism of producing paper cockle on the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> is described. First, force f<b>1</b> that pushes the paper sheet P along the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> at the exit point N<b>2</b> from the fixing nip area N is strongly exerted on the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b>, produced by the fusing roller <b>61</b> and the pressure roller <b>62</b> that rotate while being pressed against each other. This is an experimentally proven event and considered to be produced as a result of balancing the adsorptive power of the fusing roller <b>61</b> and the adsorptive power of the pressure roller <b>62</b> on the paper sheet P, as the fusing roller <b>61</b> and the pressure roller <b>62</b> rotate, pressed against each other in the fixing nip area N. Because the toner image is carried on the surface of the paper sheet P brought in contact with the fusing roller <b>61</b>, adherence is exerted between the toner image and the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b>. Thereby, force f<b>2</b> toward the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> is also exerted on the paper sheet P. Because this force f<b>2</b> toward the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> is the adherence between the toner image and the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b>, it changes depending on the ratio of the area occupied by the toner image on the surface of the paper sheet P. Because the direction of gravity is approximately opposite to the paper sheet P transport direction, its effect as force exercised on the paper sheet P is extremely small.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Under the condition where these forces are exercised, the force fl pushing the paper sheet P out of the fixing nip area N is mainly exerted on the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b>. However, by action of the force f<b>2</b> toward the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b>, which changes depending on the amount of the toner forming the image, the direction in which the paper sheet P moves is deflected toward the fusing roller surface from the direction of the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b>. Specifically, when the force f<b>2</b> exerted on the fusing roller surface is relatively strong, the paper sheet P is oriented toward the fusing roller surface. When the force f<b>2</b> exerted on the fusing roller surface is relatively weak, the paper sheet P is oriented toward the direction of the tangent line m. Because of such unstable behavior of the paper sheet P, paper cockle is considered to occur on the paper sheet P.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In the paper eject guide <b>90</b> of this embodiment, the transport-path-side guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is formed to intersect the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> at the exit point N<b>2</b> from the fixing nip area N at an obtuse angle β near the fusing roller <b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">As described above, in the fixing unit <b>60</b>, the center Q<b>2</b> of the pressure roller <b>62</b> is positioned slightly above the horizontal plane passing through the center Q<b>1</b> of the fusing roller <b>61</b> by an angle of α (α&gt;0). Accordingly, the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> at the exit point N<b>2</b> from the fixing nip area N is set tilting toward the fusing roller <b>61</b>. Thus, the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is installed on the side of and near the fusing roller <b>61</b> and the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>is formed to intersect the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> at an obtuse angle β, so that the force f<b>1</b> that is strongly exerted on the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> to push the paper sheet P along the tangent line m will strongly push the paper sheet P against the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b>. Thereby, the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> will be strongly supported by both the fixing nip area N and the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Because the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> is thus strongly supported by the fixing nip area N and the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b>, even if the force f<b>2</b> toward the fusing roller surface is exerted on the paper sheet P when the paper sheet P is ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b>, the supporting force of the fixing nip area N and the reactive force from the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> produce force that counteracts the force f<b>2</b> on the paper sheet P. Consequently, the direction in which the paper sheet P moves is made stable and deflection from the direction of the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> to the fusing roller <b>61</b> is made stable, and paper cockle on the paper sheet P is prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Because the tangent line m intersects the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> at an obtuse angle β, after the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>contacts the paper eject guide <b>90</b>, the paper sheet P is transported smoothly along the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a</i>. Because an unwanted force that checks the paper sheet P in its course is not exerted on the lead edge of the paper sheet P, the dog-ear can be prevented in both lead edge comers of the paper sheet P.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">By the way, in this configuration, when the force f<b>1</b> that pushes the paper along the tangent line m strongly pushes the paper sheet P against the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b>, transmission of the force f<b>1</b> pushing the paper along the tangent line m to the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> depends on the rigidity (so-called “stiffness”) of the paper sheet P. Therefore, to keep the rigidity of the paper sheet P strong, the distance from the exit point N<b>2</b> of the fixing nip area N to the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> may be set short. Thus, the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is located near the fusing roller <b>61</b>. Specifically, the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is set up so that the intersection with the tangent line m is positioned near the pressure roller <b>62</b> in relation to the vertical line passing through the center Q<b>1</b> of the fusing roller <b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Next, setting the angle of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> in relation with the peeling claw <b>92</b> is described.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a view to explain a range of setting of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> in relation with peeling claw <b>92</b>. Now, let us consider an instance where the bottom end P<b>3</b> (the end near to the fusing roller <b>61</b>) of the guide surface <b>90</b>a of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is set to protrude toward the pressure roller <b>62</b> and a point at which extension of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>toward the fusing roller <b>61</b> interests the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> is set near the pressure roller <b>62</b> in relation to a point P<b>2</b> where the peeling claw <b>92</b> touches the fusing roller surface (at the left-hand side of the point P<b>2</b>). In this instance, the bottom end P<b>3</b>′ of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is positioned closer to the pressure roller <b>62</b> than the peeling claw <b>92</b>. When the peeling claw <b>92</b> peels the paper sheet P that is going to wind around the fusing roller <b>61</b>, the peeled paper sheet P is guided by the peeling claw <b>92</b> and hits against the bottom end P<b>3</b>′. As a result, a dog-ear may occur by the bottom end P<b>3</b>′ or a paper jam may occur in the worst case. Therefore, it is required to set the bottom end P<b>3</b> of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> in an inner position than the peeling claw <b>92</b> over the fusing roller <b>61</b> (at the right-hand side of the point P<b>2</b>). In other words, it is needed to set the angle β of intersection at which the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> intersects the tangent line m smaller than a predetermined value</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Determining an upper limit β′ of the angle of β intersection is described below. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a view showing positional relationship of the fusing roller <b>61</b>, paper eject guide <b>90</b>, and peeling claw <b>92</b> to determine the upper limit β′ of the angle β of intersection. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>: P<b>1</b> is a point at which the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> at the exit point N<b>2</b> from the fixing nip area N contacts the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b>; P<b>5</b> is a point at which an extension line p of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>(which is set as denoted by <b>90</b><i>a′</i> in this case) passes through a point P<b>2</b> and intersects a line segment q connecting the exit point N<b>2</b> and the center Q<b>1</b> of the fusing roller <b>61</b>, if the bottom end P<b>3</b> of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>is set to protrude to the position of the peeling claw <b>92</b> (the bottom end P<b>3</b> is set in a position P<b>3</b>′); and P<b>4</b> is a point at which a line from the point P<b>2</b>, where the peeling claw <b>92</b> touches the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b>, perpendicularly intersects the line segment q connecting the exit point N<b>2</b> with the center Q<b>1</b> of the fusing roller <b>61</b>; β′ is the angle of intersection of the tangent line m with the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b>, if the bottom end P<b>3</b> of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>is set to protrude to the position of the peeling claw <b>92</b>; L is the distance from the exit point N<b>2</b> to the point P<b>1</b>; r is the radius of the fusing roller <b>61</b>; <u style="single">a</u> is the length of a line segment connecting the exit point N<b>2</b> with the point P<b>5</b>; b is the length of a line segment connecting the point P<b>4</b> and the point P<b>5</b>; γ is an angle formed between the exit point N<b>2</b> and the point P<b>2</b> from the center Q<b>1</b> of the fusing roller <b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">In the above setting, a condition of avoiding that the bottom end P<b>3</b> of the guide surface <b>906</b><i>a </i>protrudes toward the pressure roller <b>62</b>, exceeding the position of the peeling claw <b>92</b>, is that the point at which the extension line p of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>intersects the line segment q connecting the exit point N<b>2</b> with the center Q<b>1</b> of the fusing roller <b>61</b> is positioned closer to the center Q<b>1</b> of the fusing roller <b>61</b> than the point P<b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">First, from ΔP<b>1</b>, N<b>2</b>, P<b>5</b>, we get:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=L·</i>(180°−β′)   (1)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Then, from ΔQ<b>1</b>, P<b>2</b>, P<b>4</b> and ·ΔP<b>2</b>, P<b>4</b>, P<b>5</b>, we get:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>b=r·</i>sinγ×tan(180°−β′)   (2)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">and
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=r−</i>(<i>r·</i>cos γ−<i>b</i>)   (3)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Therefore, from equations (2) and (3), we get:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=r−</i>(<i>r·</i>cos γ−<i>r·</i>sin γ<i>c </i>tan(180°−β′))   (4)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
From equations (1) and (4), we get:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>L·</i>tan(180°−β′))<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>=r−</i>(<i>r·</i>cos γ−<i>r</i>·sin γ×tan(180°−β′))   (5)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Therefore, from equation (5), we get:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>tan(180°−β′)<i>=r</i>(1 −cos γ)/(<i>L−r·</i>sin γ)   (6)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Then, the upper limit β′ of the angle β of intersection can be obtained.
</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Accordingly, the guide surface <b>906</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is set so that the angle β of intersection of the tangent line m with the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> fulfills the following constraint from equation (6):
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>tan(180°−β)<i>≧r</i>(<i>L−</i>cos γ)/(<i>L−r·</i>sin γ)   (7)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
where β&gt;90°
<br/>
Consequently, it does not occur that the bottom end P<b>3</b> of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>protrudes toward the pressure roller <b>62</b>, exceeding the position of the peeling claw <b>92</b>. The dog-ear and paper jam at the bottom end P<b>3</b> can be prevented.
</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">As described above, in the image forming apparatus <b>1</b> of this embodiment, the center Q<b>2</b> of the pressure roller <b>62</b> is positioned slightly above the horizontal plane passing through the center Q<b>1</b> of the fusing roller <b>61</b> by an angle of α(α&gt;0) in the fixing unit <b>60</b>. Moreover, in the paper eject guide <b>90</b>, the transport-path-side guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is formed to intersect the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> at the exit point N<b>2</b> from the fixing nip area N at an obtuse angle near the fusing roller <b>61</b>. By this arrangement, the paper sheet P ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b> is strongly supported by the fixing nip area N and the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b>. Therefore, even if the force f<b>2</b> toward the fusing roller surface is exerted on the paper sheet P when the sheet is ejected from the fixing unit <b>60</b>, the supporting force of the fixing nip area N and the reactive force from the guide surface <b>906</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> produce a force that counteracts the force f<b>2</b> on the paper sheet P. Consequently, the direction in which the paper sheet P moves is made stable and deflection from the direction of the tangent line m on the surface of the fusing roller <b>61</b> to the fusing roller <b>61</b> is made stable, and paper cockle on the paper P is prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Because the tangent line m intersects the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> at an obtuse angle, after the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>contacts the paper eject guide <b>90</b>, the paper sheet P is transported smoothly along the guide surface <b>906</b><i>a</i>. Because an unwanted force that checks the paper sheet P in its course is not exerted on the lead edge of the paper sheet P, the dog-ear can be prevented in both lead edge corners of the paper sheet P.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Furthermore, the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> is set so that the angle β of intersection of the tangent line m with the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>of the paper eject guide <b>90</b> fulfills the following constraint:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>tan(180°−β)<i>≧r</i>(1−cos γ)/(<i>L−r·</i>sin γ)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
where β&gt;90°
<br/>
Consequently, it does not occur that the bottom end P<b>3</b> of the guide surface <b>90</b><i>a </i>protrudes toward the pressure roller <b>62</b>, exceeding the position of the peeling claw <b>92</b>. The dog-ear and paper jam at the bottom end P<b>3</b> can be prevented.
</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Examples of application of the present invention involve application to an electrophotographic copying machine, printer, facsimile, and a multifunction machine including their functions.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">As described above, an image forming apparatus according to an aspect of the present invention includes a recording material transporting path that extends in a direction from bottom to top of a body of the image forming apparatus and transports a recording material, a fixing device provided on the recording material transporting path, which includes a rotatable heating member that has an internal heat source and a rotatable pressure member that forms a nip area with the heating member by being located in contact with and pressed against the heating member, to nip the recording material for carrying out a fixing process, and an ejection guide member that guides a recording material ejected from the nip area to the outside of the image forming apparatus. The ejection guide member has a guide surface formed to intersect a tangent line of the heating member at the most downstream point of the nip area, and the guide surface intersects the tangent line at an obtuse angle.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The pressure member may be located with its center positioned vertically above a horizontal plane passing through a center of the heating member. The image forming apparatus may further include a peeling member to peel the recording material from the heating member. The guide surface of the ejection guide member may be set so that an angle β of intersection of the guide surface with the tangent line satisfies the following expression:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>tan(180°−β)<i>≧r</i>(1−cos γ)/(<i>L−r·</i>sin γ)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
where, γ is an angle formed between the most downstream point of the nip area for fixing and a point where the peeling member touches the surface of the heating member from the center of the heating member, r is a radius of the heating member, and L is a distance between the most downstream point of the fixing nip area and intersection of the guide surface with the tangent line. Moreover, the guide surface of the ejection guide member may be formed so that the intersection of the guide surface with the tangent line is positioned near the pressure member in relation to a vertical line passing through the center of the heating member. The ejection guide member may be formed in a rib shape.
</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">An image forming apparatus according to another aspect of the present invention includes a recording material transporting path that extends in a direction from bottom to top of a body of the image forming apparatus and transports a recording material, a fixing device provided on the recording material transporting path, including a rotatable fusing roller that has an internal heat source and a rotatable pressure roller, whose center is positioned vertically above a horizontal plane passing through a center of the fusing roller, that forms a nip area with the fusing roller by being located in contact with and pressed against the fusing roller to nip the recording material for carrying out a fixing process, and plural ribs each of which has a guide surface formed to intersect, at a position downstream and near the nip area, a tangent line of the fusing roller at the most downstream point of the nip area, the guide surface intersecting the target angle at an obtuse angle.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The image forming apparatus may further include a peeling member to peel the recording material from the fusing roller, wherein a bottom end of the guide surface of the rib may be positioned near the fusing roller in relation to a pressure-member-side surface of the peeling member. The plural ribs may be arranged at predetermined intervals in a width direction of the recording material. Moreover, a rotating roller may be installed on the rib downstream of the intersection of the rib with the tangent line. In addition, the rib may guide the recording material to the outside of the apparatus while supporting the recording material.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">According to another aspect of the present invention, an image forming apparatus includes a recording material transporting path that extends in a direction from bottom to top of a body of the image forming apparatus and transports a recording material, a fixing device provided on the recording material transporting path, including a rotatable heating member that has an internal heat source and a rotatable pressure member that forms a nip area with the heating member by being located in contact with and pressed against the heating member, to nip the recording material for carrying out a fixing process, and an ejection guide member that guides the recording material ejected from the nip area to the outside of the image forming apparatus. The pressure member is located with its center positioned vertically above a horizontal plane passing through the center of the heating member.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">According to the aspects of the invention, in the image forming apparatus in which the fixing device is installed on the recording material transport path from down to up against the force of gravity, paper cockle and dog-ear defects of recording material can be prevented. Thereby, flatness of the recording material is maintained after an image is fixed onto the recording material and a high-quality fixed image can be formed.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">The present invention may be embodied in other specific forms without departing from its spirit or characteristics. The described embodiments are to be considered in all respects only as illustrated and not restrictive. The scope of the invention is, therefore, indicated by the appended claims rather than by the foregoing description. All changes which come within the meaning and range of equivalency of the claims are to be embraced within their scope.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">The entire disclosure of Japanese Patent Application No. 2004-320500 filed on Nov. 4, 2004 including specification, claims, drawings and abstract is incorporated herein by reference in its entirety.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An image forming apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a recording material transporting path that extends in a direction from bottom to top of a body of the image forming apparatus and transports a recording material;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixing device provided on the recording material transporting path, comprising a rotatable heating member that has an internal heat source and a rotatable pressure member that forms a nip area with the heating member by being located in contact with and pressed against the heating member, to nip the recording material for carrying out a fixing process; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an ejection guide member that guides a recording material ejected from the nip area to the outside of the image forming apparatus,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the ejection guide member has a guide surface formed to intersect a tangent line of the heating member at the most downstream point of the nip area, the guide surface intersecting the tangent line at an obtuse angle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the pressure member is located with its center positioned approximately vertically above a horizontal plane passing through the center of the heating member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a peeling member that peels the recording material from the heating member,
<claim-text>wherein the guide surface of the ejection guide member is set so that an angle β of intersection of the guide surface with the tangent line satisfies the following expression:
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>tan(180°−β)≧<i>r</i>(1−cos γ)/(<i>L−r·</i>sin γ)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>where, γ is an angle formed between the most downstream point of the nip area for fixing and a point where the peeling member touches the surface of the heating member from the center of the heating member, r is a radius of the heating member, and L is a distance between the most downstream point of the nip area for fixing and the intersection of the guide surface with the tangent line.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the guide surface of the ejection guide member is formed so that the intersection of the guide surface with the tangent line is positioned near the pressure member in relation to a vertical line passing through the center of the heating member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the ejection guide member is formed in a rib shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An image forming apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a recording material transporting path that extends in a direction from bottom to top of a body of the image forming apparatus and transports a recording material;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixing device provided on the recording material transporting path, comprising a rotatable fusing roller that has an internal heat source and a rotatable pressure roller, whose center is positioned approximately vertically above a horizontal plane passing through a center of the fusing roller, that forms a nip area with the fusing roller by being located in contact with and pressed against the fusing roller to nip the recording material for carrying out a fixing process; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of ribs each of which has a guide surface formed to intersect, at a position downstream and near the nip area, a tangent line of the fusing roller at the most downstream point of the nip area, the guide surface intersecting the tangent line at an obtuse angle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising a peeling member that peels the recording material from the fusing roller,
<claim-text>wherein a bottom end of the guide surface of the rib is positioned near the fusing roller in relation to a pressure-roller-side surface of the peeling member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of ribs are arranged at predetermined intervals in a width direction of the recording material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein a rotating roller is installed on each of the plurality of ribs downstream of the intersection of the rib with the tangent line.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The image forming apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of ribs guide the recording material to the outside of the image forming apparatus while supporting the recording material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An image forming apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a recording material transporting path that extends in a direction from bottom to top of a body of the image forming apparatus and transports a recording material;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixing device provided on the recording material transporting path, comprising a rotatable heating member that has an internal heat source and a rotatable pressure member that forms a nip area with the heating member by being located in contact with and pressed against the heating member, to nip the recording material for carrying out a fixing process; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of ribs each of which has a guide surface formed to intersect, at a position downstream and near the nip area, a tangent line of the fusing roller at the most downstream point of the nip area, the guide surface intersecting the tangent line at an obtuse angle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
