<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297086-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297086</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10543213</doc-number>
<date>20040127</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>206</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>48</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475331</main-classification>
<further-classification>475346</further-classification>
<further-classification>475348</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Epicyclic gear systems</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3303713</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hicks</name>
<date>19670200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3402622</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Matut Archanco</name>
<date>19680900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475338</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5716300</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sammataro et al.</name>
<date>19980200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475346</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0008748</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Fox</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0123984</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wilde et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0232692</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chen</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475331</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0038770</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Flamang et al.</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475348</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0105753</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Christensen</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>415  41</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>ESTU-R-95 Report, “The 3MW Wind Turbine Project on Orkney”, 1981-1995, L A W Bedford et al, Edited by Dr. D. I. Page, Jan. 1996.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475331</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475338</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475346</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475348</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60442883</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030127</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060142114</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060629</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fox</last-name>
<first-name>Gerald P.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Massillon</city>
<state>OH</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Polster, Lieder, Woodruff &amp; Lucchesi, L.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>The Timken Company</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Canton</city>
<state>OH</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Estremsky</last-name>
<first-name>Sherry</first-name>
<department>3681</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Young</last-name>
<first-name>Edwin A</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/US2004/002157</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040127</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20050722</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2004/067998</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20040812</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An epicyclic gear system (A, B), which is highly compact, yet capable of transferring substantial torque, includes a sun gear (<b>2, 62</b>), a ring gear (<b>4, 64</b>) around the sun gear, and planet gears (<b>6, 8, 66, 68</b>) organized in two rows between the sun and ring gears. In addition, the gear system has a carrier (<b>10, 70</b>) provided with one or two flanges (<b>14, 72, 74</b>) and flexible pins (<b>20, 22, 80, 82</b>) around which the planet gears revolve. The planet gears are mounted on the pins in a double cantilever arrangement to improve the mesh with the sun and ring gears and achieve better load distribution.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="178.48mm" wi="205.91mm" file="US07297086-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="209.72mm" wi="177.80mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297086-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="243.59mm" wi="162.56mm" file="US07297086-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="231.56mm" wi="185.42mm" file="US07297086-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="165.18mm" wi="135.04mm" file="US07297086-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application derives and claims priority from U.S. provisional application 60/442,883 filed 27 Jan. 2003 for the invention of G. Fox entitled “Epicyclic Gear System” and from International Application PCT/US2004/002157 (WO 2004/067998), filed on 27 Jan. 2004, by the Timken Company.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates in general to gear systems, and more particularly to epicyclic gear systems.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The typical epicyclic or planetary gear system basically has a sun gear provided with external teeth, a ring gear provided with internal teeth, and several planet gears located between the sun and ring gears and having external teeth which mesh with the teeth on the sun and ring gears. In addition to its gears, the typical system has a carrier to which the planet gears are coupled. Typically the sun gear, the ring gear, or the carrier is held fast, while power is delivered to and taken from the remaining two components, and thus power is transferred through the planetary system with a change in angular velocity and an inverse change torque. However, in some epicyclic systems all three rotate.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The sun and ring gears for all intents and purposes share the same axis—a central axis—while the planet gears revolve about radially offset axes that are parallel to the central axis—or at least they should be. Often the offset axes and the central axis are not parallel, and as a consequence the planet gears skew slightly between sun and ring gears. This causes excessive wear along the teeth of the planet, sun and ring gears, generates friction and heat, and renders the entire system overly noisy.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The problem certainly exists in straddle-designed planetary carriers. With this type of carrier the pins on which the planet gears rotate extend between two carrier flanges in which the pins are anchored at their ends. The carrier experiences torsional wind up which causes one carrier flange to rotate slightly ahead of the other flange and produce a poor mesh between the planet gears and the sun and ring gears. Each pin at its ends in cross section should possess enough shear area and section modulus to withstand the shear forces and bending moments exerted on the pin by the flanges.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Another type of epicyclic gear system utilizes a single flange carrier and flexible pins anchored in and projected from the flange. In this arrangement the single carrier flange is offset axially from planet gears, and the carrier pins project from that flange into—and indeed through—the planet gears. Each carrier pin has one end anchored in the carrier flange and at its other end is fitted within a sleeve which returns back over the pin, yet is spaced radially from the pin, to support the planet gear—a double cantilever so to speak. U.S. Pat. No. 3,303,713 to R. J. Hicks shows such a double cantilevered arrangement. But the sleeves occupy space which could otherwise be utilized to enlarge the pin diameter, and when an antifriction bearing is interposed between the sleeve and the planet gear that is around the sleeve, even less space is available for the pin.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Essentially, the double cantilever, with a sleeve interposed between a planet gear and the pin about which the gear rotates, reduces the cross section of the pin and of course the shear area and section modulus. This can reduce the torque capacity of the system, so frequently more pins are added to increase the available total cross-sectional area of the pins and regain some of the lost torque capacity. Using more pins necessarily spaces the peripheries of the planetary gears closer together. Sometimes the number of pins required to achieve the required torque capacity will result in interference between the planetary gears.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view, partially broken away and in section, of an epicyclic gear system constructed in accordance with an embodying the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a sectional view taken along line <b>2</b>-<b>2</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an exploded perspective view showing one of the carrier pins, the planet gear for that pin, and the bearing on which the planet gear rotates;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective view partially broken away and in section of another epicyclic gear system constructed in accordance with and embodying the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is another perspective view, partially broken away and in section, of the epicyclic gear system shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BEST MODE FOR CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Referring now to the drawings, epicyclic gear systems A and B, each of which is organized about a center axis X, have the traditional sun and ring gears together with planet gears, but the planet gears in number exceed those found in more conventional epicyclic systems, While the systems A and B occupy little space, they have the capacity to transfer torque of a relatively high magnitude. Each system has a carrier to which its planet gears are coupled through flexible pins in a double cantilever arrangement. The pins establish offset axes Y about which the planet gears rotate, and the axes Y closely parallel the center axis X, thus producing a good mesh between the planet and ring gears so as to have a good load distribution across each planet gear and a generally uniform load distribution among the several planet gears. The total cross-sectional area of the pins is high to provide the shear area and section modulus required to withstand the transfer of substantial torque.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Turning now to the epicyclic gear system A (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), it includes a sun gear <b>2</b>, a ring gear <b>4</b> located around the sun gear <b>2</b>, and planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> located in two rows between the sun gear <b>2</b> and ring gear <b>4</b>, with planet gears <b>6</b> occupying one row and the planet gears <b>8</b> occupying the other row. Moreover, the planet gears <b>6</b> are staggered with respect to the planet gears <b>8</b>, that is to say, they are offset circumferentially. Thus, the peripheries of the gears <b>6</b> may overlap the peripheries of the gears <b>8</b> without interference between the gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b>, this by reason of the gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> being organized in the two rows. All the gears <b>2</b>, <b>4</b>, <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> have teeth, and the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> mesh with sun gear <b>2</b> and ring gear <b>4</b> along the teeth of those gears <b>2</b>, <b>4</b>, <b>6</b> and <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In addition, the system A has a carrier <b>10</b> to which the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> are coupled, so that the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> do not displace axially and interfere with each other or migrate out of the annular space between the sun gear <b>2</b> and ring gear <b>4</b>. The sun gear <b>2</b>, ring gear <b>4</b>, and carrier <b>10</b> represent components of the system A at which power may be supplied to the system A and delivered from the system A.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The carrier <b>10</b> includes (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) a single flange <b>14</b> which lies adjacent to the row of planet gears <b>6</b>, yet beyond the ends of those planet gears <b>6</b> and beyond the ends of the sun gear <b>2</b> and ring gear <b>4</b> as well. The flange <b>14</b> contains bores <b>16</b> which are arranged at equal circumferential intervals and at equal radii from the center axis X. Fitted to the bores <b>16</b> are short pins <b>20</b> and long pins <b>22</b>, with the pins <b>20</b> and <b>22</b> alternating. Thus, every other bore <b>16</b> contains a short pin <b>20</b>, and the remaining bores <b>22</b> contain long pins <b>22</b>. The pins <b>20</b> and <b>22</b> project from the flange <b>14</b> into the annular space between the sun gear <b>2</b> and ring gear <b>4</b> in the form of a cantilevers which give the pins <b>20</b> and <b>22</b> a measure of flexibility. The gears <b>6</b> of the inner row rotate about the short pins <b>20</b>, whereas the gears <b>8</b> of the outer row rotate about the long pins <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Each pin <b>20</b> has (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 &amp; 3</figref>) a shank <b>26</b> at its fixed end where it is anchored in the flange <b>10</b> and at its free end a head <b>28</b>. Between the shank <b>26</b> and head <b>28</b> the pin <b>20</b> may also have a groove <b>30</b> to enhance the flexibility of the pin <b>20</b>. The shank <b>26</b> extends out of one of the bores <b>16</b> of the flange <b>10</b> and into the planet gear <b>6</b> for the pin <b>20</b>. The head <b>28</b> also has a cylindrical surface of uniform diameter, and that diameter may be slightly greater than the diameter of the shank <b>26</b>. While the head <b>28</b> may be somewhat shorter than the shank <b>26</b>, it still is long enough to lie partially within its planet gear <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The planet gears <b>6</b> rotate around their respective carrier pins <b>20</b> on antifriction bearings <b>34</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 &amp; 3</figref>), each lying within its gear <b>6</b> and around its pin <b>20</b>. Actually, each bearing <b>34</b> utilizes its planet gear <b>6</b> as its outer race, in that the gear <b>6</b>, itself, has two tapered raceways <b>36</b> that are presented inwardly toward the axis Y of rotation for the gear <b>6</b> and taper downwardly toward each other. Each bearing <b>34</b> also includes (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) an inner race in the form of a unitary race sleeve <b>38</b> and a separately formed rib ring <b>40</b> at one of the sleeve <b>38</b>. The race sleeve <b>38</b> has a through bore <b>42</b>, which at its one end receives the enlarged head <b>28</b> on the pin <b>20</b>. An interference fit exists between the head <b>28</b> and the surface of the bore <b>42</b> in the sleeve <b>38</b>, but even so, head <b>28</b> of the sleeve <b>38</b> and the head <b>28</b> are joined together along a circular weld <b>44</b>. Beyond the head <b>28</b> the surface of the bore <b>44</b> is spaced from the shank <b>26</b> of the pin <b>20</b>, thus creating the second cantilever. The sleeve <b>38</b> projects through the interior of the planet gear <b>6</b>, and here is provided with two tapered raceways <b>46</b> which taper downwardly toward each other and are presented outwardly toward the raceways <b>36</b> in the planet gear <b>6</b>. The raceway <b>46</b> toward the free end of the race sleeve <b>38</b> leads up to a thrust rib <b>48</b> which is formed as an integral part of the sleeve <b>38</b>. The other raceway <b>46</b> at its large end leads into a rabbet <b>50</b> at the mounted end of the sleeve <b>38</b>. The rib ring <b>40</b> fits into the rabbet <b>50</b> and is secured to the sleeve <b>38</b> at another weld <b>52</b> to provide a rib at the large end of the adjoining raceway <b>46</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The bearing <b>34</b> also has (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 &amp; 3</figref>) tapered rollers <b>54</b> arranged in two rows between the tapered raceways <b>36</b> of the planet gear <b>38</b> and the tapered raceways <b>46</b> on the race sleeve <b>38</b>. The large end faces of the rollers <b>54</b> in one row move along and are confined by the rib ring <b>40</b> on the race sleeve <b>38</b>, while the large ends of the rollers <b>54</b> in the other row move along and are confined by the integral thrust rib <b>48</b>. By virtue of the position in which the rib ring <b>40</b> is secured to the race sleeve, <b>38</b>, the bearing <b>34</b> is in a condition of slight preload, so no clearances exist between the raceways <b>36</b> and <b>46</b> and the rollers <b>54</b>. Moreover, the rollers <b>54</b> of the two rows are on apex, meaning that the conical envelopes in which their side faces lie have their apices at a common point along the axis Y for planet gear <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/680,043 of G. Fox and E. Jallat, filed Oct. 7, 2003, and entitled “Epicyclic Gear System”, describes the bearing <b>34</b> in more detail, and that application is incorporated herein by reference. The pins <b>22</b> are similar to the pins <b>20</b>, except that their shanks <b>26</b> are longer. The planet gears <b>8</b> rotate on similar bearings <b>34</b> located around those pins <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The grooves <b>30</b> between the shanks <b>26</b> and the heads <b>28</b> of the pins <b>20</b> and <b>22</b> impart a measure of flexibility to the pins <b>20</b> at <b>22</b>, but irrespective of whether the pins <b>20</b> and <b>22</b> have grooves <b>30</b>, they should flex such that the axes Y of the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> lie generally parallel to the axis X. This insures that the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> mesh properly with the sun gear <b>2</b> and ring gear <b>4</b> and that loads are distributed evenly across the widths of the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> and uniformly between the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In the operation of the epicyclic gear system A the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> of the two rows transfer torque and power between the sun gear <b>2</b> and ring gear <b>4</b>. By reason of their increased number, the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> individually have less width than their counterparts in more traditional epicyclic systems. Should they skew, the skewing will have less detrimental effects than had the skewing occured with wider and more conventional planet gears. Indeed, this extends the life of the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> and their bearings <b>34</b>, as well as the lives of the sun gear <b>2</b> and ring gear <b>4</b>. It also enables the entire gear system A to be highly compact—all without compromising the cross sectional area of the flexible carrier pins <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>. The staggered arrangement of the planet gears <b>6</b> and <b>8</b> in two rows permits more planet gears and an increase in the total cross-sectional area for the pins <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, particularly at the flange <b>14</b> of the carrier <b>10</b> where moments are greatest.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The epicyclic gear system B (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 &amp; 5</figref>) likewise has a sun gear <b>62</b>, a ring gear <b>64</b>, and planet gears <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> located in two rows between the sun gear <b>62</b> and ring gear <b>64</b>, with the gears <b>66</b> being in one row and the gears <b>68</b> being in the other row. Moreover, the planet gears <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> are coupled to a carrier <b>70</b> which defines the axes Y about which the planet gears <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> rotate.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In contrast to the carrier <b>10</b> for the epicyclic gear system A, the carrier <b>70</b> for the system B has two flanges <b>72</b> and <b>74</b>, the former being adjacent to the planet gears <b>66</b> and the latter being adjacent to the planet gears <b>68</b>. The two flanges <b>72</b> and <b>74</b> are connected by bridges <b>76</b> which extend between them, and in that sense the carrier <b>70</b> resembles a straddle carrier.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The gears <b>66</b> rotate around the pins <b>80</b> that are anchored in the flange <b>72</b>, whereas the gears <b>68</b> rotate on pins <b>82</b> that are anchored in the flange <b>74</b>. For every pin <b>80</b> that projects from the flange <b>72</b>, a pin <b>82</b> projects from the flange <b>74</b>, and while corresponding pins <b>80</b> and <b>82</b> align, they are not connected. Thus each pin <b>80</b> or <b>82</b> is free to flex relative to any other pin <b>80</b> or <b>82</b> including the pin <b>80</b> or <b>82</b> with which it aligns. The pins <b>80</b> and <b>82</b> resemble the short pins <b>20</b> of the carrier <b>10</b> for the planetary system A. Moreover the planetary gears <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> rotate on bearings <b>84</b> similar to the bearings <b>34</b>, including race sleeves <b>38</b> which provide a double cantilever.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In the epicyclic system B, with its opposed planet gear arrangement, it is more likely that the deflection characteristics of each of flexible pins <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> can have the same torque characteristics. However, the entire epicyclical arrangement will wind up from input to output side when torque is applied to or taken from the carrier <b>70</b>. So care must be taken to profile the teeth of the planetary gears <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> according to the nominal wind up at each of their design mesh points.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In both the gear systems A and B the rolling elements of the bearings <b>34</b> and <b>84</b> need not be tapered rollers, but may assume other shapes such as balls, cylindrical or spherical rollers, or needles. Indeed, the bearings need not contain rolling elements at all. Instead, each race sleeve <b>38</b> itself may function as a journal for the planet gear <b>6</b>, <b>8</b>, <b>66</b> or <b>68</b> that is around it. When the bearings <b>34</b> and <b>84</b> have rolling elements, the raceways <b>36</b> and <b>46</b> may be on races that are formed separately from the planet gears <b>6</b>, <b>8</b>, <b>66</b> and <b>68</b>, on one hand, and the race sleeves <b>38</b>, on the other.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An epicyclic gear system comprising:
<claim-text>a sun gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a ring gear located around the sun gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first planet gears located between and engaged with the sun and ring gears in a first row;</claim-text>
<claim-text>second planet gears located between and engaged with the sun and ring gears in a second row, with the second gears being displaced axially from the first gears; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a carrier having first pins on which the first planet gears rotate and second pins on which the second planet gears rotate, the first and second pins being cantilevered from the carrier and being detached from each other.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein each pin provides a double cantilevered mounting for the planet gear which rotates on it.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the carrier has a single flange and the first and second pins are anchored in and extend from the flange such that they are cantilevered from the flange.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the planet gears revolve about their respective pins on bearings, with each bearing including a race sleeve which extends through the planet gear and over the pin, the sleeve being anchored to its pin remote from the flange and being directed toward the flange and through the planet gear from where it is anchored, whereby the planet gear is mounted on the carrier through a double cantilever.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the first and second pins are organized alternately in a circular row on the flange of the carrier, and the second pins are located between the first planet gears.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the carrier has first and second flanges, with the first flange being located adjacent to the first planet gears and the second flange being located adjacent to the second planet gears; and wherein the first pins extend from the first flange and the second pins extend from the second flange.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the first and second pins are cantilevered from the first and second flanges, respectively, of the carrier; and wherein the planet gears revolve about their respective pins on bearings, with each bearing including a race sleeve which extends through the planet gear and over the pin, the sleeve being anchored to its pin remote from the flange and being directed toward the flange and through the planet gear from where it is anchored, whereby the planet gear is mounted on the carrier through a double cantilever.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein each first pin aligns axially with a different second pin.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the carrier also has bridges connecting the first and second flanges.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. An epicyclic gear system comprising:
<claim-text>a sun gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a ring gear located around the sun gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first planet gears located in a row between the sun and ring gears and being engaged with the sun and ring gears; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>second planet gears located in another row between the sun and ring gears and being engaged with the sun and ring gears;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a carrier having a single flange and first and second pins anchored in and projecting from the flange, with the first pins projecting into the first planet gears so that the first gears revolve about the first pins and the second pins projecting into the second planet gears so that the second gears revolve about the second pins, the first and second pins being cantilevered from the flange of the carrier and being detached from each other.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> and wherein the planet gears revolve about their respective pins on bearings, with each bearing including a race sleeve which extends through the planet gear and over the pin, the sleeve being anchored to its pin remote from the flange and being directed toward the flange and through the planet gear from where it is anchored, whereby the planet gear is mounted on the carrier through a double cantilever.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein the first and second pins alternate and the second pins extend between the first planet gears.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein each bearing includes rolling elements located between the race sleeve and the planet gear that is around the race sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the second pins are longer than the first pins.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. An epicyclic gear system comprising:
<claim-text>a sun gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a ring gear located around the sun gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first planet gears located in a row between the sun and ring gears and being engaged with the sun and ring gears;</claim-text>
<claim-text>second planet gears located in another row between the sun and ring gears and being engaged with the sun and ring gears; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a carrier having a first flange located adjacent to the first planet gears and a second flange located adjacent to the second planet gears and further having first pins cantilevered from the first flange and extended into the first gears and second pins cantilevered from the second flange and extended into the second gears, all such that the first gears rotate about the first pins and the second gears rotate about the second pins, the first and second pins being detached from each other.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the planet gears revolve about there respective pins on bearings, with each bearing including a race sleeve which extends through the planet gear and over the pin, the sleeve being anchored to its pin remote from the flange and being directed toward the flange for its pin and through the planet gear from where it is anchored, whereby the planet gear is mounted on the carrier through a double cantilever.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> wherein each bearing includes rolling elements located between its race sleeve and the planet gear that is around the race sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein each first pin aligns axially with a different second pin, so the first and second planet gears are arranged in pairs.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A gear system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein the carrier also has bridges which connect the first and second flanges and extend between adjacent pairs of first and second planet gears.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
