<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298302-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298302</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11437396</doc-number>
<date>20060517</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>M</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>341101</main-classification>
<further-classification>341100</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">System and method for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5367300</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fong et al.</name>
<date>19941100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>341101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5951669</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bailey et al.</name>
<date>19990900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710260</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6184808</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Nakamura</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>341 95</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6684275</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Goldstein</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710 71</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6839783</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Samuel et al.</name>
<date>20050100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710107</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7215263</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Dietrich et al.</name>
<date>20070500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>341101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0098517</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Goldstein</name>
<date>20040500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710  1</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0219084</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Dietrich et al.</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>341101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2007/0024476</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Saeki et al.</name>
<date>20070200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>341101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2007/0030184</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Nguyen et al.</name>
<date>20070200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>341100</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2007/0073981</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Im et al.</name>
<date>20070300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>711149</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>341100</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>341101</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chard</last-name>
<first-name>Gary Franklin</first-name>
<address>
<city>Garland</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Koh</last-name>
<first-name>T-Pinn Ronnie</first-name>
<address>
<city>Allen</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Brady, III</last-name>
<first-name>Wade J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Telecky, Jr.</last-name>
<first-name>Frederick J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Texas Instruments Incorporated</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Dallas</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Linh</first-name>
<department>2819</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of parallel data signals includes: a controller; a serializer coupled with the controller; and a tri-state logic device coupled with the serializer. The controller provides parallel logic state signals to the serializer. The serializer treats the parallel data signals to present a serial data signal representing the parallel data signals at a first output locus, and treats the parallel logic state signals to present a serial logic state signal representing the parallel logic state signals at a second output locus. The tri-state logic device receives the serial data signal and the serial logic state signal for logical evaluation. The tri-state logic device presents the serial drive signals at a third output locus. Each respective drive signal has a respective drive state. Each respective drive state is determined by the logical evaluation.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="85.77mm" wi="164.00mm" file="US07298302-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="105.66mm" wi="146.47mm" file="US07298302-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="169.25mm" wi="170.52mm" file="US07298302-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="225.13mm" wi="150.45mm" file="US07298302-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention is directed to input-output (IO) devices, and especially to serializer/deserializer (SERDES) devices. Analog SERDES modules operating at high speeds may experience a problem in controlling the tri-state output device of the SERDES module with sufficient accuracy to meet standards requirements that establish constraints more stringent than the slower clock period of digital control circuitry that controls the SERDES module. A solution to this problem in the past has been to operate the digital control circuitry of the SERDES module at a high speed in order to meet requirements.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">There are disadvantages to such high speed operation of the digital control circuitry of the SERDES module including, by way of example and not by way of limitation, higher power consumption, increased difficulty in maintaining timing, more expensive parts for handling higher speed technology and more complex logic in the data path.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">There is a need for a system and method for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality parallel data signals that permits operation of digital control circuitry at a speed less than the output speed of the module.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">There is a need for a serializer/deserializer (SERDES) module that may operate control circuitry at a lower speed than the operational speed of output signals from the module.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of parallel data signals includes: a controller; a serializer coupled with the controller; and a tri-state logic device coupled with the serializer. The controller provides the parallel data signals and parallel logic state signals to the serializer. The serializer treats the parallel data signals to present a serial data signal representing the parallel data signals at a first output locus, and treats the parallel logic state signals to present a serial logic state signal representing the parallel logic state signals at a second output locus. The tri-state logic device receives the serial data signal and the serial logic state signal for logical evaluation. The tri-state logic device presents the serial drive signals at a third output locus. Each respective drive signal has a respective drive state. Each respective drive state is determined by the logical evaluation.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A method for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals includes the steps of: (a) in no particular order: (1) providing a control unit; (2) providing a serializing unit coupled with the control unit; and (3) providing a tri-state logic device coupled with the serializing unit; (b) operating the control unit to provide the plurality of parallel data signals and to provide a plurality of parallel logic state signals to the serializing unit; (c) in no particular order: (1) operating the serializing unit to treat the plurality of parallel data signals to present a serial data signal at a first output locus; the serial data signal representing the plurality of parallel data signals; and (2) operating the serializing unit to treat the plurality of parallel logic state signals to present a serial logic state signal at a second output locus; the serial logic state signal representing the plurality of parallel logic state signals; (d) operating the tri-state logic device to receive the serial data signal and the serial logic state signal for logical evaluation; and (e) operating the tri-state logic device to present the serial drive signals at a third output locus. Each respective drive signal has a respective drive state of a plurality of drive states. Each respective drive state is determined by the logical evaluation.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It is therefore an object of the present invention to provide a system and method for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality parallel data signals that permits operation of digital control circuitry at a speed less than the output speed of the module.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">By way of example and not by way of limitation, the present invention is representatively configured to provide a serializer/deserializer (SERDES) module that may operate control circuitry at a lower speed than the operational speed of output signals from the module.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Further objects and features of the present invention will be apparent from the following specification and claims when considered in connection with the accompanying drawings, in which like elements are labeled using like reference numerals in the various figures, illustrating the preferred embodiments of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating a representative prior art SERDES (serializer/deserializer) module.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating a SERDES (serializer/deserializer) module configured according to the teaching of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an illustration of a representative logic table for effecting logical evaluation by a tri-state device employed in the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow chart illustrating the method of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Serializer/deserializer (SERDES) applications have increased recently to meet a demand for denser, higher-speed communications. By compressing numerous parallel data inputs into a serial data stream, SERDES modules facilitate data transfers in circuitry. SERDES modules are well-suited for effecting data transfers where circuit layout or other design considerations make provision of parallel data paths from point-to-point in a circuit impractical or undesirable. By way of example and not by way of limitation, SERDES circuitry may be advantageously employed in circuit paths traversing a flexible or exposed circuit juncture such as the hinge area connecting a flip cover and a main body of a mobile telephone, in circuit paths across a printed circuit board, or in other crowded or congested configurations where it is desirable to reduce the number of connecting structures between loci.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The term “locus” is intended herein to indicate a place, location, locality, locale, point, position, site, spot, volume, juncture, junction or other identifiable location-related zone in one or more dimensions. A locus in a physical apparatus may include, by way of example and not by way of limitation, a corner, intersection, curve, line, area, plane, volume or a portion of any of those features. A locus in an electrical apparatus may include, by way of example and not by way of limitation, a terminal, wire, circuit, circuit trace, circuit board, wiring board, pin, connector, component, collection of components, sub-component or other identifiable location-related area in one or more dimensions. A locus in a flow chart may include, by way of example and not by way of limitation, a juncture, step, site, function, query, response or other aspect, step, increment or an interstice between junctures, steps, sites, functions, queries, responses or other aspects of the flow or method represented by the chart.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">SERDES modules may generate a differential output signal in order to enjoy benefits of such signaling such as, by way of example and not by way of limitation, LVDS (Low Voltage Differential Signal) signaling with its advantageous common-mode noise rejection characteristic. Other differential signaling output arrangements may be used such as, by way of further example and not by way of limitation, emitter-coupled logic (ECL) like LVPECL (Low-Voltage Positive Emitter-Coupled Logic). In the interest of simplicity of drawings and straightforwardness of explanation, only single-ended output arrangements are illustrated here. One skilled in the art of circuit design will recognize how the teachings of the present invention may be advantageously employed for differential signaling output arrangements.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating a representative prior art SERDES (serializer/deserializer) module. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a serializer/deserializer (SERDES) module <b>10</b> includes a SERDES unit <b>12</b> and a tri-state device <b>14</b>. SERDES unit <b>12</b> has a low speed side <b>11</b> and a high-speed side <b>13</b>. A timing source <b>16</b> provides a timing signal on a timing line <b>18</b>. Timing source <b>16</b> may be embodied, by way of example and not by way of limitation, in a phase-locked loop (PLL) circuit. A multiplier <b>20</b> effects multiplication or speeding up of timing signals on line <b>18</b> to present high-speed clock signals to a high-speed clock input locus <b>23</b> at high-speed side <b>13</b> of SERDES unit <b>12</b> via a high-speed clock line <b>22</b>. A divider <b>24</b> effects division or slowing down of timing signals from multiplier <b>20</b> to present low-speed clock signals to a low-speed clock input locus <b>27</b> at low-speed side <b>11</b> of SERDES unit <b>12</b> via a low-speed clock line <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">SERDES unit <b>12</b> includes a control unit <b>30</b> at high-speed side <b>13</b>. By way of example and not by way of limitation, control unit <b>30</b> is embodied in a Tristate control State Machine (TSM) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">A plurality of low-speed parallel data lines <b>40</b> receive data input at low-speed side <b>11</b> of SERDES unit <b>12</b>. SERDES unit <b>12</b> presents a serial data signal at a serial data output locus <b>42</b> at high-speed side <b>13</b> of SERDES unit <b>12</b>. It is preferred that serial output signals presented at serial data output locus <b>42</b> faithfully represent parallel input data signals received from parallel data lines <b>40</b> at low-speed side <b>11</b>. Division by a factor N is indicated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> to indicate that division of timing signals from multiplier <b>20</b> may be effected variously. Factor N is customarily related to the number of data lines <b>40</b> so that factor N may be established as N=8 for SERDES module <b>10</b>. Factor N may be assigned integer values where,
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>1≦N&lt;∞  [1]<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Control unit <b>30</b> is coupled serially with high-speed clock input locus <b>23</b> and employs high-speed clock signals from high-speed clock input locus <b>23</b> to present a control signal at a control signal output locus <b>44</b> at high-speed side <b>13</b>. Serial data signals are received by tri-state device <b>14</b> from serial data output locus <b>42</b>. Tri-state device <b>14</b> also receives control signals from control signal output locus <b>44</b>. Tri-state device <b>14</b> effects a logical evaluation of received serial data signals and control signals and presents drive signals at a signal locus <b>50</b>. Tri-state device <b>14</b> may, by way of example and not by way of limitation, present a DRIVE 1 signal indicating a data element “1”, a DRIVE 0 signal indicating a data element “0” or a Z signal. A Z signal may indicate a control operation from control unit <b>30</b> such as, by way of example and not by way of limitation, a mode in which SERDES unit <b>12</b> operates to receive signals from a remote device (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) via signal locus <b>50</b> and a return path <b>48</b> to SERDES unit <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">A significant shortcoming of SERDES module <b>10</b> is that assuring time-incidence of signals presented at signal locus <b>50</b> with input signals received via low-speed data lines <b>40</b> requires operating control unit <b>30</b> at a high speed approximating operational speeds extant at high-speed side <b>13</b> of SERDES unit <b>12</b>. Such a high speed of operation is disadvantageous, as may be manifested in SERDES module <b>10</b>, by way of example and not by way of limitation, by higher power consumption, by increased difficulty in maintaining timing, by requiring more expensive parts for effecting higher speed technology and by more complex logic in the data path within SERDES unit <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating a SERDES (serializer/deserializer) module configured according to the teaching of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a serializer/deserializer (SERDES) module <b>100</b> includes a SERDES unit <b>112</b> and a tri-state device <b>114</b>. SERDES unit <b>112</b> has a low speed side <b>111</b> and a high-speed side <b>113</b>. A timing source <b>116</b> provides a timing signal on a timing line <b>118</b>. Timing source <b>116</b> may be embodied, by way of example and not by way of limitation, in a phase-locked loop (PLL) circuit. A multiplier <b>120</b> effects multiplication or speeding up of timing signals on line <b>118</b> to present high-speed clock signals to a high-speed clock input locus <b>123</b> at high-speed side <b>113</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b> via a high-speed clock line <b>122</b>. A divider <b>124</b> effects division or slowing down of timing signals from multiplier <b>120</b> to present low-speed clock signals to a low-speed clock input locus <b>127</b> at low-speed side <b>111</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b> via a low-speed clock line <b>126</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">A plurality of low-speed parallel data lines <b>140</b> receive data input at low-speed side <b>111</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b>. SERDES unit <b>112</b> presents a serial data signal at a serial data output locus <b>142</b> at high-speed side <b>113</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b>. It is preferred that serial output signals presented at serial data output locus <b>142</b> faithfully represent parallel input data signals received from parallel data lines <b>140</b> at low-speed side <b>111</b>. Division by a factor N is indicated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> to indicate that division of timing signals from multiplier <b>120</b> may be effected variously. Factor N is customarily related to the number of data lines <b>140</b> so that factor N may be established as N=8 for SERDES module <b>100</b>. Factor N may be assigned integer values according to expression [1] above.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">SERDES unit <b>112</b> responds to a state machine <b>162</b>. By way of example and not by way of limitation, state machine <b>162</b> is embodied in a Tristate control State Machine (TSM) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. State machine <b>162</b> provides a plurality of parallel control signal lines <b>160</b> to provide a control input at low-speed side <b>111</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b>. The number of parallel control signal lines <b>160</b> is related to the number of data lines <b>140</b>, preferably according to the relationship,</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mfrac>
        <mi>N</mi>
        <mi>M</mi>
      </mfrac>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>[</mo>
        <mn>2</mn>
        <mo>]</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Factor N is established according to expression [1], and factor M is an integer. A preferred embodiment of SERDES module <b>100</b> establishes factor M=1, so that the number of data lines <b>140</b> is equal with the number of control signal lines <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">State machine <b>162</b> is coupled with divider <b>124</b> in parallel with SERDES unit <b>112</b> so that low-speed clock line <b>126</b> also provides a low-speed clock signal to state machine <b>162</b> via a low-speed clock line <b>164</b>. As a result, state machine <b>162</b> and low-speed side <b>111</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b> are driven by the same low speed clock signal. As a consequence, state machine <b>162</b> and low-speed side <b>111</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b> are assured to operate synchronously.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">State machine <b>162</b> is controlled by a control unit <b>130</b>. By way of example and not by way of limitation, control unit <b>130</b> is embodied in a digital microprocessor in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">SERDES unit <b>112</b> receives data signals via low-speed parallel data lines <b>140</b> and presents a serial data signal at a serial data output locus <b>142</b> at high-speed side <b>113</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b>. It is preferred that serial output signals presented at serial data output locus <b>142</b> faithfully represent parallel input data signals received from parallel data lines <b>140</b> at low-speed side <b>111</b>. Control unit <b>130</b> operates to cause state machine <b>162</b> to present control information via control signal lines <b>160</b> appropriately to present a control signal at a control signal output locus <b>144</b> at high-speed side <b>113</b>. Serial data signals are received by tri-state device <b>114</b> from serial data output locus <b>142</b>. Tri-state device <b>114</b> also receives control signals from control signal output locus <b>144</b>. Tri-state device <b>114</b> effects a logical evaluation of received serial data signals and control signals and presents drive signals at a signal locus <b>150</b>. A representative logical evaluation table appropriate for use by tri-state device <b>114</b> is described in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Tri-state device <b>114</b> may, by way of example and not by way of limitation, present a “DRIVE 1” signal indicating a data element “1”, a “DRIVE 0” signal indicating a data element “0” or a “Z” signal. A Z signal may indicate a control operation from control unit <b>130</b> such as, by way of example and not by way of limitation, a mode in which SERDES unit <b>112</b> operates to receive signals from a remote device (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) via signal locus <b>150</b> and a return path <b>148</b> to SERDES unit <b>112</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">An important feature of SERDES module <b>100</b> is that control unit <b>130</b> generates low-speed control signals via control signal lines <b>160</b> at low-speed side <b>111</b> of SERDES unit <b>112</b>. Control signals on control signal lines <b>160</b> and data signals on data lines <b>140</b> are treated simultaneously by SERDES unit <b>112</b> using the same high-speed clock signals received at high-speed clock input locus <b>123</b> from high-speed clock line <b>122</b>. That is, data signals (received via data lines <b>140</b>) and control signals (received via control signal lines <b>160</b>) are treated by SERDES unit <b>112</b> in lock-step using a common clocking signal (high-speed clock signals from high-speed clock locus <b>123</b>). As a result, serialized data signals presented at serial data output locus <b>142</b> representing data received from data lines <b>140</b> are in synchrony with serialized control signals presented at control signal output locus <b>144</b> representing control signals received from control signal lines <b>160</b>. Of importance is the result that control unit <b>130</b> is configured to effect generation of control signals for conveyance via control signal lines <b>160</b> at a low speed. It is not necessary to operate a control unit (e.g., control unit <b>30</b>; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) generate control signals at high speed as was required in SERDES module <b>10</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Synchrony of data signals at serial data output locus <b>142</b> and control signal output locus <b>144</b> is assured in SERDES module <b>100</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), thereby assuring time-incidence of signals presented at signal locus <b>150</b> with input signals received via low-speed data lines <b>140</b> without operating control unit <b>130</b> at a high speed. Such low-speed of operation of control unit <b>130</b> contributes to avoiding disadvantages such as, by way of example and not by way of limitation, high power consumption, difficulty in maintaining timing, expensive parts for effecting higher speed technology and complex logic in the data path within SERDES unit <b>112</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an illustration of a representative logic table for effecting logical evaluation by a tri-state device employed in the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a representative logical evaluation table <b>151</b> for use by SERDES module <b>100</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) includes data rows <b>152</b>, <b>154</b>, <b>156</b> arranged in data columns <b>160</b>, <b>162</b>, <b>164</b>. Column <b>160</b> contains data presented at serial data output locus <b>142</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Column <b>162</b> contains data presented at control signal output locus <b>144</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Column <b>164</b> contains data presented at signal locus <b>150</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As indicated by row <b>152</b>, when data presented at serial data output locus <b>142</b> is a “0” and data presented at control signal output locus <b>144</b> is “0”, then data presented at signal locus <b>150</b> is a “DRIVE 0” signal. As indicated by row <b>154</b>, when data presented at serial data output locus <b>142</b> is a “1” and data presented at control signal output locus <b>144</b> is “0”, then data presented at signal locus <b>150</b> is a “DRIVE 1” signal. As indicated by row <b>156</b>, when data presented at serial data output locus <b>142</b> is any value (represented by “X” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) and data presented at control signal output locus <b>144</b> is “1”, then data presented at signal locus <b>150</b> is a “Z” signal. Other logical relationships among data presented at loci <b>142</b>, <b>144</b>, <b>150</b> may be established to satisfy various operational requirements as desired, as will be understood by one skilled in the art of circuit design.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow chart illustrating the method of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a method <b>200</b> for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals begins at a START locus <b>202</b>. Method <b>200</b> continues by, in no particular order: (1) Providing a control unit, as indicated by a block <b>204</b>. (2) Providing a serializing unit coupled with the control unit, as indicated by a block <b>206</b>. (3) Providing a tri-state logic device coupled with the serializing unit, as indicated by a block <b>208</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Method <b>200</b> continues by operating the control unit to provide the plurality of parallel data signals and to provide a plurality of parallel logic state signals to the serializing unit, as indicated by a block <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Method <b>200</b> continues by, in no particular order: (1) Operating the serializing unit to treat the plurality of parallel data signals to present a serial data signal at a first output locus, as indicated by a block <b>212</b>. The serial data signal represents the plurality of parallel data signals. (2) Operating the serializing unit to treat the plurality of parallel logic state signals to present a serial logic state signal at a second output locus, as indicated by a block <b>214</b>. The serial logic state signal represents the plurality of parallel logic state signals.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Method <b>200</b> continues by operating the tri-state logic device to receive the serial data signal and the serial logic state signal for logical evaluation, as indicated by a block <b>216</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Method <b>200</b> continues by operating the tri-state logic device to present the serial drive signals at a third output locus, as indicated by a block <b>218</b>. Each respective drive signal has a respective drive state of a plurality of drive states. Each respective drive state is determined by the logical evaluation.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Method <b>200</b> terminates at an END locus <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">It is to be understood that, while the detailed drawings and specific examples given describe preferred embodiments of the invention, they are for the purpose of illustration only, that the apparatus and method of the invention are not limited to the precise details and conditions disclosed and that various changes may be made therein without departing from the spirit of the invention which is defined by the following</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07298302-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298302-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals; the system comprising:
<claim-text>(a) a control unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) a serializing unit coupled with said control unit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) a tri-state logic device coupled with said serializing unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said control unit providing said plurality of parallel data signals and providing a plurality of parallel logic state signals to said serializing unit; said serializing unit treating said plurality of parallel data signals to present a serial data signal at a first output locus; said serial data signal representing said plurality of parallel data signals; said serializing unit treating said plurality of parallel logic state signals to present a serial logic state signal at a second output locus; said serial logic state signal representing said plurality of parallel logic state signals; said tri-state logic device receiving said serial data signal and said serial logic state signal for logical evaluation; said tri-state logic device presenting said serial drive signals at a third output locus; each respective said drive signal having a respective drive state of a plurality of drive states; each said respective drive state being determined by said logical evaluation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said control unit operates at a first operating speed and wherein said tri-state logic device receives said serial data signal and said serial logic state signal at a second operating speed; said first operating speed being slower than said second operating speed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals is effected using a first clock signal and wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals is effected using a second clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein said first clock signal and said second clock signal are each derived from a common original clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals and said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals are effected using the same clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals is effected using a first clock signal and wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals is effected using a second clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said first clock signal and said second clock signal are each derived from a common original clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A system for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals is effected and said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals are effected using the same clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A system for effecting communication of data according to a communication scheme;
<claim-text>the system comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>(a) a state machine unit operating at a first operating speed; said state machine presenting a plurality of parallel data signals at a first signal speed and presenting a plurality of parallel logic state signals at said first signal speed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) a serializing unit coupled with said state machine unit for receiving said plurality of parallel data signals and receiving said plurality of parallel logic state signals; said serializing unit treating said plurality of parallel data signals to present a serial data signal at a first signal locus at a second signal speed and treating said plurality of parallel logic state signals to present a serial logic state signal at a second signal locus at said second signal speed; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) A tri-state logic device coupled with said serializing unit for receiving said serial data signal and said serial logic state signal; said tri-state logic device presenting serial drive signals for effecting said communication scheme; each respective said drive signal having a respective drive state of a plurality of drive states; each said respective drive state being determined by logical evaluation of said serial digital signal and said serial logic state signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A system for effecting communication of data according to a communication scheme as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said first signal speed is slower than said second signal speed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A system for effecting communication of data according to a communication scheme as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals is effected using a first clock signal and wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals is effected using a second clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A system for effecting communication of data according to a communication scheme as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said first clock signal and said second clock signal are each derived from a common original clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A system for effecting communication of data according to a communication scheme as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals and said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals are effected using the same clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A system for effecting communication of data according to a communication scheme as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals is effected using a first clock signal and wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals is effected using a second clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A system for effecting communication of data according to a communication scheme as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said first clock signal and said second clock signal are each derived from a common original clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A system for effecting communication of data according to a communication scheme as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals and said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals are effected using the same clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals; the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>(a) in no particular order:
<claim-text>(1) providing a control unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(2) providing a serializing unit coupled with said control unit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(3) providing a tri-state logic device coupled with said serializing unit;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) operating said control unit to provide said plurality of parallel data signals and to provide a plurality of parallel logic state signals to said serializing unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) in no particular order:
<claim-text>(1) operating said serializing unit to treat said plurality of parallel data signals to present a serial data signal at a first output locus; said serial data signal representing said plurality of parallel data signals; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(2) operating said serializing unit to treat said plurality of parallel logic state signals to present a serial logic state signal at a second output locus; said serial logic state signal representing said plurality of parallel logic state signals;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>(d) operating said tri-state logic device to receive said serial data signal and said serial logic state signal for logical evaluation; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(e) operating said tri-state logic device to present said serial drive signals at a third output locus; each respective said drive signal having a respective drive state of a plurality of drive states; each said respective drive state being determined by said logical evaluation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein said control unit operates at a first operating speed and wherein said tri-state logic device receives said serial data signal and said serial logic state signal at a second operating speed; said first operating speed being slower than said second operating speed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals is effected using a first clock signal and wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals is effected using a second clock signal; said first clock signal and said second clock signal each being derived from a common original clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A method for presenting serial drive signals for effecting communication of a plurality of parallel data signals as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel data signals is effected and said serializing unit treating of said plurality of parallel logic state signals are effected using the sane clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
