<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296431-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296431</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11235782</doc-number>
<date>20050927</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>294</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>25</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 62380</main-classification>
<further-classification> 62 62</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Apparatus and method for freezing food products</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2223972</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sterling</name>
<date>19401200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3166383</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Morris</name>
<date>19650100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3611737</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Alaburda et al.</name>
<date>19711000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 62 63</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3611745</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schlemmer</name>
<date>19711000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 62333</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3889488</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Maeda et al.</name>
<date>19750600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 62218</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4171625</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Morgan et al.</name>
<date>19791000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 62380</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5299426</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lermuzeaux</name>
<date>19940400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>1 426 715</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>518660</doc-number>
<date>19400300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>33</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>626 62</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>626380</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60615214</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20041001</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060070393</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060406</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Muscato</last-name>
<first-name>Robert</first-name>
<address>
<city>Monmouth Junction</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Boddaert</last-name>
<first-name>Robert</first-name>
<address>
<city>Washington</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>McCormick</last-name>
<first-name>Stephen A</first-name>
<address>
<city>Warrington</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hamilton</last-name>
<first-name>John</first-name>
<address>
<city>Edmond</city>
<state>OK</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lau</last-name>
<first-name>Bernard</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>The BOC Group, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Murray Hill</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Jones</last-name>
<first-name>Melvin</first-name>
<department>3744</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An apparatus and method of cooling products includes a conveyor for transporting the products, through a refrigeration medium for cooling the products, agitation means disposed proximate to the conveyor for selective, intermittent contact with the conveyor to displace the conveyor from a plane of travel, thereby displacing the products on the conveyor during freezing to prevent the products from adhering to the conveyor or other of the products during freezing, at least one of the agitation means and the conveyor constructed and arranged to be positioned away from each other for the conveyor to move uninterrupted along the plane of travel.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="96.27mm" wi="159.34mm" file="US07296431-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="164.76mm" wi="160.36mm" file="US07296431-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="183.73mm" wi="116.84mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296431-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="264.67mm" wi="147.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296431-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the benefit of the filing date of U.S. Provisional Application for Patent Application Ser. No. 60/615,214 filed Oct. 1, 2004, the disclosure of which is incorporated by reference herein.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to cooling and freezing food products.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">There are many ways in which products, such as food products, may be chilled or frozen. One example calls for the product to be placed into trays. In many cases, a tray is used to enhance the display of the product in the package. It may also be used to contain a fluid such as water or sauce to be chilled or frozen with the product. The tray is part of the final product packaging. Loading trays is labor intensive and is typically done for premium type products which will demand a higher price to offset the additional cost of production. The trays are then placed onto a rack, then placed into a chiller or freezer, or the trays are placed on a moving belt moving through a chiller or freezer.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Another type of freezing for a product is individual quick-frozen (“IQF”). IQF freezing of products provides products that are frozen, but not stuck together. There are several known ways that IQF product is produced. One process is to simply freeze the products without allowing same to contact each other. This may be done by spacing individual product on a freezer belt or rack so they are not in contact with each other. In most cases, this is not done for smaller products because it requires staff to arrange the product fed into the freezer and is an inefficient use of manpower and space, thus reducing capacity. Accordingly, as the pieces to become frozen become smaller, it becomes increasingly more time consuming and difficult to do. Another process is by placing the products into a tray or compartments, which is constructed to keep the individual pieces separated. This is not as desired a process due to the additional cost, labor and increased package size.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Other methods of producing IQF products include fluidized beds, nitrogen immersion or multi-pass tunnels. All of these allow for product to be randomly placed on a belt for freezing. Movement is created between adjacent pieces of product to prevent sticking, thereby creating IQF, to keep pieces of product moving in relation to one another. For example, in nitrogen immersion, the pieces are not permitted to contact each other when dropped into a nitrogen bath and are thereby frozen at the surface of the bath before they can contact and adhere to one another. Multi-pass tunnels (including flighted tunnels) drop the pieces from one belt to another repeatedly to break the product apart before it is frozen solid. However, none of these methods is suitable for processing product contained in trays, since known methods would scatter the trays and displace the product from the trays.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">To efficiently process tray and IQF products, different types of equipment are employed which are suitable for one, but not both, freezing processes. In many cases, companies make both IQF and tray types of products and attempt to have both processed with the same equipment. Attempts to achieve this are done by removing or bypassing the IQF portion of the freezing line when tray product freezing is desired. This typically requires relocation of equipment and results in a reduction in production capacity due to the removal of part of the process line.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">An apparatus for chilling or freezing products is provided including a conveyor for transporting the products through a refrigeration medium for chilling or freezing the products; agitation means disposed proximate to the conveyor for selective, intermittent contact with the conveyor to displace the conveyor from a plane of travel, thereby displacing the products on the conveyor during chilling or freezing to prevent the products from adhering to the conveyor or other of the products during chilling or freezing, at least one of the agitation means and the conveyor constructed and arranged to be positioned away from each other for the conveyor to move uninterrupted along the plane of travel; and drive means operatively associated with the agitation means to move the agitation means to displace the conveyor and the products thereon.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">An apparatus for cooling products is provided including a conveyor for transporting the products through a refrigeration medium for cooling the products; an agitation assembly that interchangeably engages with the conveyor for selective, intermittent contact with the conveyor so as to displace the conveyor from the plane of travel, or disengages from the conveyor thereby enabling the conveyor to move uninterrupted along the plane of travel; and drive means operatively associated with the agitation means to engage or disengage the agitation means to displace the conveyor and the products thereon.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A method of individually quick freezing products is provided which comprises conveying products on a conveyor in a freezing zone; providing freezing means to the freezing zone; and providing agitating means to selectively displace the conveyor along at least part of the conveyed path of travel to prevent the products from adhering to the conveyor or to each other during freezing; wherein at least one of the agitating means and the conveyor are constructed and arranged to be positioned away from the other for the conveyor to move uninterrupted along the conveyed path of travel.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">For a more complete understanding of the present invention, reference may be had to the accompanying FIGS., of which:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows an apparatus for chilling and freezing different types of individual quick-frozen food products.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a portion of the apparatus with the food product contained in trays.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a view of the conveyor and agitation means of the apparatus of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a view of the conveyor disengaged from the agitation means of the apparatus in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a view of the conveyor engaged to the agitation means of the apparatus in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The apparatus for cooling products; while conveying, such as a tray product in such a way so as not to disturb the product or products contained in the tray, or selectively agitate product which is disposed upon the conveyor to be individually quick frozen (IQF). The apparatus is suitable for use in chilling and freezing food products such as for example, meat, chicken and seafood products. As used herein, cooling refers to a temperature reduction of a product to either chilling or freezing, depending on the total heat extraction from the product.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The apparatus comprises a sophisticated arrangement of at least one cam and a conveyor, such as a conveyor belt, which produces an agitation or vibration that provides intermittent contact between the conveyor and the food products, while the food products are being conveyed through the cooling and freezing equipment. A method of using the apparatus shown conveying a product, whether IQF or in trays, so as not to disturb the product in the trays. The system allows the flexibility of IQF or freezing in trays with one touch of a button.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The apparatus provides a system for chilling or freezing products, and comprises a conveyor, such as a conveyor belt, that transports the products through refrigeration, such as mechanical refrigeration or a refrigerated medium for chilling or freezing the products, but with the additional feature of actuating or agitating the belt through an agitation assembly comprising an agitation means. In certain embodiments, the agitation means comprises a camshaft. The employed agitation means makes selective, intermittent contact with the conveyor, displacing the conveyor from its plane of travel, thereby displacing the products on the conveyor during freezing to prevent products from adhering to the conveyor or to other products being conveyed. Agitation of the conveyor and injection of any refrigeration medium can take place in the same or different zones.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The system can freeze and convey different types of food products, and in various product forms; so as not to adversely affect the integrity of the product while being conveyed through the system. The food products may be IQF or non-IQF, and by way of example, raw or cooked, may require specific shape and orientation, may be breaded or unbreaded, marinated or unmarinated, or food products comprising any type of coating.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In one embodiment, the system is flexible in that it can switch between IQF and non-IQF products, including but not limited to, products that can tolerate layering in the freezer, wherein they are conveyed and quick frozen by the apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The apparatus and method may employ the total conveyor area for utilization of the capacity, without allowing food product to be removed from sections of the conveyor between the inlet and outlet of the freezer housing and the freezing zone, regardless of the product/process type. The freezing zone may comprise a single freezing zone or multiple freezing zones wherein the temperature of the product is reduced to about or below the freezing point of the product. The apparatus of the present invention may include one or a plurality of chilling or freezing zones.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In one embodiment of the system, the agitation assembly utilizes an agitation means such as at least one cam, each one of which may be mounted to a corresponding shaft connected for rotation to a drive means such as a chain. In another embodiment, the agitation assembly includes intermediate members that are positioned between the cam or cams and the conveyor, such that the intermediate member can contact and translate the impact of the cam to the load carrying part of the conveyor. The cam has an irregular form such that its motion imparts a rocking or reciprocating motion to a part or parts in contact with it, such as the conveyor. The agitation means imparts to the conveyor a forward component of velocity, such that each agitation means contacts the belt at select time intervals. In certain embodiments, a pulse like motion may be produced through the conveyor (and such motion observed) when at least one agitation means contacting the conveyor is out of phase with at least one other agitation means.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The agitation means may be set such that the agitation in the adjacent sections can be in phase or out of phase, whereby a pulse like motion is set up through the conveying system. Additionally, the amplitude and the frequency of the pulse may be varied by adjusting the degree of interaction between the conveying mechanism (e.g., belt) and the agitation means (e.g., cam).</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The agitation of the product may maximize product surface area exposed to the refrigeration medium, in which the refrigeration medium works either intermittently, simultaneously or continuously with the agitation. In certain embodiments of the system, the agitation assembly is present either in part of or along the entire length of the conveying section and the refrigeration equipment housing. In other embodiments, the agitation assembly is present so as to provide the conveying mechanism with alternating sections of non-agitating sections followed by agitating sections, or agitating sections followed by non-agitating sections, or in any desired arrangement.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The agitation increases the heat transfer rates by maximizing the product surface area exposed to the refrigeration medium, that is normally not achieved when the product is touching other products or parts of the conveying mechanism. This results in more uniform heat transfer, leading to shorter freezing times, improved yields, higher product quality, and better cryogenic efficiency. A 50 to 100% increase in heat transfer rates and 25 to 50% decrease in dwell times may be achieved compared to existing freezing equipment.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 3</figref>, the apparatus <b>10</b> is shown generally, and may be incorporated into a typical belt freezer. The apparatus <b>10</b> includes a conveyor belt <b>12</b> to move product <b>11</b> through the freezer housing <b>14</b>. The conveyor belt <b>12</b> may be continuous as it passes through the length of the freezer housing <b>14</b>, or it may comprise several conveyor belts <b>12</b> with product transfers appropriate for handling product on trays. The housing <b>14</b>, is cooled by mechanical refrigeration, carbon dioxide or nitrogen, or some other means using a refrigeration medium, including a combination of cryogenic and mechanical refrigeration techniques. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a carbon dioxide or nitrogen spray outlet <b>22</b> provides the refrigeration medium.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">An agitation assembly <b>32</b> is provided to agitate or vibrate the product conveyed on the conveyor belt <b>12</b> to produce an IQF freeze. The agitation assembly <b>32</b> comprises a plurality of cams <b>18</b>. A section comprising the cams <b>18</b> runs either along the entire section of the freezer housing <b>14</b>, or a portion thereof. Each of the cams <b>18</b> is mounted on a corresponding rotating shaft <b>16</b> (or a conveyor belt shaking support system; not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). The agitation assembly <b>32</b> may be constructed and arranged with an interlocking mechanism to agitate the conveyor belt <b>12</b>. The agitation assembly <b>32</b> comprises the cams <b>18</b> and shafts <b>16</b>, and is driven by chains <b>20</b> or any other power transmission mechanism.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Rotation of the cams <b>18</b> causes them to contact the conveyor belt <b>12</b> at select intervals of time, such contact displacing the conveyor belt <b>12</b> from its plane of travel. The rotating sequence of the cams <b>18</b> may be staggered (i.e., in-phase and out of phase), and their intermittent, but repetitive impact on the conveyor belt <b>12</b> causes same to rise above the plane of travel, providing a vibratory/agitating movement of the conveyor belt <b>12</b>. Such action prevents the product traveling along the conveyor belt <b>12</b> from adhering to the conveyor belt <b>12</b> or to one another.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The conveyor belt <b>12</b> may also be vibrated by agitating the frames or supports <b>28</b> using any other vibrating or agitation means, e.g., mechanical, hydraulic, pneumatic, electro-magnetic, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In one embodiment, when products for which vibration or agitation is not desired are processed in the freezer (e.g., for products in trays <b>17</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), disengaging the cams <b>18</b> from the conveyor belt <b>12</b> ceases the vibration/agitation. When vibration or agitation is desired, the cams <b>18</b> contact the conveyor belt <b>12</b> when actuated and rotated or otherwise moved to a position where they intermittently contact and displace the conveyor belt <b>12</b>. Circulation means such as fans <b>24</b> may be used to enhance heat transfer in either IQF or tray mode of operation.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Operatively, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the conveyor belt <b>12</b> is supported by an upper belt running rail <b>36</b> and a lower running rail <b>38</b>. Raising the upper belt running rail <b>36</b> increases the distance between the edge of the conveyor belt <b>12</b> and the cam <b>18</b> such that cam <b>18</b> does not contact the conveyor belt <b>12</b>. In this embodiment, the cam <b>18</b> does not result in repetitive impact on the conveyor belt <b>12</b> to cause the conveyor belt <b>12</b> to rise above the plane of travel. A carrier, such as a tray <b>17</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), can be placed on the conveyor belt <b>12</b> without the possibility of falling off the conveyor belt <b>12</b> by any vibratory/agitation movement of the conveyor belt <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the upper belt running rail <b>36</b> may be lowered to lower the distance between the edge of the conveyor belt <b>12</b> and the cam <b>18</b>, such that cam <b>18</b> impinges onto the lower surface of the conveyor belt <b>12</b>. In this embodiment, the cam <b>18</b> results in repetitive impact on the conveyor belt <b>12</b> to cause the conveyor belt <b>12</b> to rise above the plane of travel. In one embodiment, IQF products may be placed on the surface of the conveyor belt <b>12</b> for chilling or freezing to prevent the IQF from adhering from one another.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In another embodiment, when vibration or agitation is not necessary for processing of the food products, the conveyor belt <b>12</b> can be moved or displaced away from the cams <b>18</b>, while the cams <b>18</b> may continue to move. In this arrangement, the conveyor belt <b>12</b> is not subjected to the displacing motion of the cams <b>18</b>, and can thereby travel along a continuous plane of travel. When it is again desirable to vibrate or agitate the conveyor belt <b>12</b>, the conveyor belt <b>12</b> and/or the cams <b>18</b> are moved into position so the cams <b>18</b> resume contact with the conveyor belt <b>12</b> in an intermittent manner.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In another embodiment, the agitation assembly comprising the cam <b>18</b> may be permanently held in position relative to the conveyor belt <b>12</b> to perform only the IQF mode of operation.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In a further embodiment, the agitation assembly includes at least one intermediate member (not shown) that may be disposed between the conveyor belt <b>12</b> and cams <b>18</b> in such a manner that the rotation of the cams <b>18</b> contacts the intermediate member, and the impact causes the intermediate member to contact the conveyor belt <b>12</b>, causing the conveyor belt <b>12</b> to rise above the plane of travel, providing a vibratory/agitating movement of the conveyor belt <b>12</b>. When vibration/agitation is not necessary for processing of the food products, the intermediate member(s) can be moved or displaced away from the cams <b>18</b>, while the cams <b>18</b> may continue to move. This way, the conveyor belt <b>12</b> is not subjected to the displacing motion of the cams translated through the intermediate member(s), and can thereby travel along a continuous plane of travel. When it is again desirable to vibrate the conveyor belt <b>12</b>, the intermediate member(s) are moved into position so the cams <b>18</b> resume contact with the intermediate member(s).</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In a further embodiment, the conveyor belt <b>12</b> is disposed at an angle to the horizontal and may comprise multiple conveyor sections, with transfers of product between the sections. Each section can be agitated/actuated or non-agitated/actuated as desired by the apparatus <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">On the conveyor belt <b>12</b> may be a retaining means (not shown) for retaining products on the conveyor belt <b>12</b>. These retaining means are generally known to those skilled in the art, and include, for example, projections raised above the top surface of the conveyor belt <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Adjacent to the conveyor belt <b>12</b> may be means such as sidewalls <b>15</b> or guard rails to retain the product being displaced on the surface of the conveying mechanism, while the product is traveling through the equipment housing. The guard rails can be folded to allow access to the conveyor belt <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In certain embodiments, the agitation assembly may include self-propelling mechanisms to effectuate movement of the cam <b>18</b> without outside power.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In another embodiment, each of the cams <b>18</b> may comprise an individual motor.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The process may include estimating the product heat load so as to control the degree of cryogen injection. One embodiment utilizes a weigh scale or a laser or any other optical measuring means that estimates/calculates the volume/weight of the product, or other characteristics of same, so as to control the amount of injection of the refrigeration medium conducive to that product. This embodiment may use a sensor <b>26</b> to sense the throughput of the product, the sensor utilizes a controller <b>30</b> to actuate the valve <b>34</b>, which controls the amount of cryogen injection.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The agitation and the injection of any refrigeration medium may take place in the same freezing zone or in different freezing zones. The temperature established in the freezing zone may be isothermal, co-current or counter-current. Convective processes may be used to disperse the refrigeration medium uniformly in the freezing zone for better heat transfer. Such processes can utilize, but are not limited to, fans, impingement or directed gas jets to disperse the refrigeration medium.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The freezer apparatus <b>10</b> of the invention permits a user to consolidate separate freezer lines (of IQF and trayed products) by being able to switch or alternate between the “vibratory” mode and the non-vibrating or “tunnel” mode.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">In summary, depending upon the geography for which particular freezing applications are to be employed, the invention ensures that frozen food products will not adhere to one another, the conveyor or the tray transporting the food products during freezing.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">It will be understood that the embodiment(s) described herein are merely exemplary, and that one skilled in the art may make variations and modifications without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. All such variations and modifications are intended to be included within the scope of the invention as described hereinabove. Further, all embodiments disclosed are not necessarily in the alternative, as various embodiments of the invention may be combined to provide the desired result.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An apparatus for chilling or freezing products comprising:
<claim-text>a conveyor for transporting the products through a refrigeration medium for chilling or freezing the products;</claim-text>
<claim-text>agitation means disposed proximate to the conveyor for selective, intermittent contact with the conveyor to displace the conveyor from a plane of travel, thereby displacing the products on the conveyor during chilling or freezing to prevent the products from adhering to the conveyor or other of the products during chilling or freezing, at least one of the agitation means and the conveyor constructed and arranged to be positioned away from each other for the conveyor to move uninterrupted along the plane of travel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>drive means operatively associated with the agitation means to move the agitation means to displace the conveyor and the products thereon.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the products are food products.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the agitation means comprises at least one cam and each of the at least one cam is mounted to a corresponding shaft connected for rotation to the drive means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the drive means comprises a chain.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising an intermediate member disposed between the agitation means and the conveyor to transmit the selective, intermittent contact of the agitation means to the conveyor to displace the conveyor from its plane of travel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the conveyor is at an angle with the horizontal and comprises multiple conveyor sections adapted to permit transfer of the products between said multiple conveyor sections.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the conveyor comprises alternating agitating and non-agitating sections.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the refrigeration medium comprises at least one of mechanical refrigeration or cryogenic refrigeration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the conveyor is additionally displaced by agitating frames or supports by using at least one of mechanical means, hydraulic means, pneumatic means, or electromagnetic means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the conveyor is a belt.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the conveyor belt comprises a retaining means for retaining product on the belt.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the retaining means comprises at least one guard rail.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising means for sensing features of the products to determine the amount of the refrigeration medium to be provided to the products.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. An apparatus for cooling products comprising:
<claim-text>a conveyor for transporting the products through a refrigeration medium for cooling the products;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an agitation assembly that interchangeably engages with the conveyor for selective, intermittent contact with the conveyor so as to displace the conveyor from the plane of travel, or disengages from the conveyor thereby enabling the conveyor to move uninterrupted along the plane of travel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>drive means operatively associated with the agitation means to engage or disengage the agitation means to displace the conveyor and the products thereon.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the agitation assembly that engages with the conveyor displaces the products on the conveyor to prevent the products from adhering to each other during freezing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the agitation assembly that engages with the conveyor displaces the products on the conveyor to prevent the products from adhering to the conveyor or the products from adhering on the surface of a carrier placed on the conveyor during freezing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> wherein the carrier is a tray.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the products are food products.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the agitation means comprises at least one cam and each of the at least one cam is mounted to a corresponding shaft connected for rotation to the drive means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein each of the at least one cam comprises an individual motor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the drive means comprises a chain.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising an intermediate member disposed between the agitation means and the conveyor to transmit the selective, intermittent contact of the agitation means tot the conveyor to displace the conveyor from its plane of travel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the refrigeration medium comprises at least one of mechanical refrigeration or cryogenic refrigeration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the conveyor is a belt.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising means for sensing features of the products to determine the amount of the refrigeration medium to be provided to the products.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. A method of individually quick freezing products, comprising:
<claim-text>conveying products on a conveyor in a freezing zone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing freezing means to the freezing zone; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing agitating means to selectively displace the conveyor along at least part of the conveyed path of travel to prevent the products from adhering to the conveyor or to each other during freezing;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein at least one of the agitating means and the conveyor are constructed and arranged to be positioned away from the other for the conveyor to move uninterrupted along the conveyed path of travel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00026">claim 26</claim-ref>, wherein the agitating means comprises at least one cam imparting force to the conveyor conveying the products.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref>, comprising driving the at least one cam mounted to a corresponding shaft connected for rotation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref>, comprising positioning at least one of the conveyor and the at least one cam away from the other for the conveyor to move uninterrupted along the conveyed path of travel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00026">claim 26</claim-ref>, comprising disposing an intermediate member between the agitating means and the conveyor for transmitting the selective, intermittent contact of the at least agitating means to the conveyor to displace the conveyor from the conveyed path of travel and positioning the intermediate member away from the conveyor for the conveyor to move uninterrupted along its plane of travel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref>, comprising producing a pulse-like motion through the conveyor when the at least one cam contacting the conveyor is out of phase with at least one other cam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00031">claim 31</claim-ref>, comprising varying amplitude and frequency of the pulse like motion by adjusting a degree of interaction between the conveyor and the at least one cam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00033" num="00033">
<claim-text>33. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00026">claim 26</claim-ref>, wherein the freezing means is at least one of mechanical refrigeration or cryogenic refrigeration.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
