<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296413-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296413</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10965176</doc-number>
<date>20041015</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>374</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>22</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>143</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60772</main-classification>
<further-classification> 60 39465</further-classification>
<further-classification> 60728</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Power generating system and method</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5400588</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yamane et al.</name>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 60 39465</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5457951</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Johnson et al.</name>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 60 39182</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6367258</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wen et al.</name>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 606417</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0005698</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Keller</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 60643</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00005">
<othercit>Dharam Punwani, “Cool Your Jets! Hybrid Systems &amp; LNG For Turbine Inlet Cooling (TIC)”, Oct. 2004, pp. 19-20, Energy-Tech.com.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>25</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60 39182</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60 39465</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60 3953</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60772</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60728</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>1</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060080963</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060420</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Brenneke</last-name>
<first-name>Glenn S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lee's Summit</city>
<state>MO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Stratman</last-name>
<first-name>Jason</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lee's Summit</city>
<state>MO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kinney, Jr.</last-name>
<first-name>Ohler L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Overland Park</city>
<state>KS</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mockry</last-name>
<first-name>Eldon F.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lenexa</city>
<state>KS</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hentschel</last-name>
<first-name>Gregory P.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Overland Park</city>
<state>KS</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="006" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Clubine</last-name>
<first-name>Darrin Ray</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kansas City</city>
<state>MO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="007" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yang</last-name>
<first-name>Jidong</first-name>
<address>
<city>Overland Park</city>
<state>KS</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Baker &amp; Hostetler LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Marley Cooling Technologies, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Overland Park</city>
<state>KS</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Casaregola</last-name>
<first-name>L. J.</first-name>
<department>3746</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A power generating system having a liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit and an energy generating circuit. The LNG vaporization circuit includes a heat exchange assembly and a heating tower connected to the heat exchange assembly. The LNG vaporization circuit also includes a LNG vessel connected to the heat exchange assembly. The energy generating circuit includes a gas turbine connected to the heating tower along with a first electrical generator connect to the gas turbine.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="135.72mm" wi="217.85mm" file="US07296413-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="221.83mm" wi="144.10mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296413-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates generally to an apparatus and method for both imparting heat to a circulating fluid using water heated by a heating tower apparatus and providing cool, moist air to a gas turbine or the like. More particularly, the present invention relates, for example, to an apparatus and method whereby liquefied natural gas or the like, is vaporized via heat exchange, while the air temperature of the inlet air charged to the gas turbine is simultaneously reduced or cooled.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">There are times when it is desirable to cool or reduce the temperature of the inlet air charged to a gas turbine. This circumstance can arrive with respect to increasing the thermal output and efficiency of gas turbines or the like. Likewise, there are times when it is desirable to impart heat from ambient air to a relatively cool liquid to “heat” the liquid. This circumstance can arrive with respect to liquefied natural gas.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Gas turbines, which typically can comprise an air inlet, a compressor, a combustion chamber, turbines and an exhaust, function to compress incoming air flow that mixes with fuel prior to ignition of the air-fuel mixture. This ignition of the air-fuel mixture typically occurs in the combustion chamber or chambers, and causes the generation of high-temperature gas or gasses, which in turn drive the turbine. Gas turbines similar to the ones described above, are typically utilized for the generation of mechanical power for vehicles, for example aircraft power generation. Gas turbines like the ones described above are also typically utilized in the electrical power generating industry, especially during peak load periods, wherein the turbines are coupled to an electrical generator and function to drive the electrical generator.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Gas turbine usage for electrical power generation, or a gas turbine generator, is particularly prevalent during summer months to supplement normal power, such as steam or hydroelectric, generating plant during peak power demand time periods. The gas turbine generators are also used for base-load systems in smaller utilities, and for co-generation systems. It is however noted that gas generator KW output rating, or thermal efficiency, is inversely proportional to the inlet air temperature to the gas turbine generator. In other words, the gas turbine generator is less efficient with inlet air at temperatures that are elevated, while it is more efficient with inlet air temperatures that are cool or cold. Thus it is desirable to provide gas inlet streams that are cool or cold, and therefore various apparatuses and methods for reducing the temperature of inlet air to a gas turbine generator exist in the art today.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The cryogenic liquefaction of natural gas is routinely practiced as a means for converting natural gas into a more convenient form for transportation. Such liquefaction typically reduces the volume by about 600 fold and results in an end product that can be stored and transported more easily. Also, it is desirable to store excess natural gas so that it may be easily and efficiently supplied when the demand for natural gas increases. One practical means for transporting natural gas and also for storing excess natural gas, is to convert the natural gas to a liquefied state for storage and/or transportation and then vaporize the liquid as demand requires.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Natural gas often is available in areas remote from where it will ultimately be used, therefore the liquefaction of natural gas is even of greater importance. Typically, natural gas is transported via pipeline from the supply source directly to the user market. However, it has become more common that the natural gas be transported from a supply source which is separated by great distances from the user market, where a pipeline is either not available or is impractical. This is particularly true of marine transportation where transport must be made by ocean-going vessels. Ship transportation of natural gas in the gaseous state is generally not practical because of the great volume of the gas in the gaseous state, and because appreciable pressurization is required to significantly reduce the volume of the gas. Therefore, in order to store and transport natural gas, the volume of the gas is typically reduced by cooling the gas to approximately −240° F. to approximately −260° F. A this temperature, the natural gas is converted into liquefied natural gas (LNG), which possesses near atmospheric vapor pressure. Upon completion of transportation and/or storage of the LNG, the LNG must be returned to the gaseous state prior to providing the natural gas to the end user for consumption.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Typically, the re-gasification or vaporization of LNG is achieved through the employment of various heat transfer fluids, systems and processes. For example, some processes used in the art utilize evaporators that employ hot water or steam to heat the LNG to vaporize it. Other processes currently used in the art employ open rack evaporators, intermediate fluid evaporators and submerged combustion evaporators.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Open rack evaporators typically use sea water or like as a heat source for countercurrent heat exchange with LNG, while other processes employ an intermediate fluid or refrigerant such as propane, fluorinated hydrocarbons or the like, having a low freezing point. In these processes, the refrigerant can be heated with hot water or steam, and then the heated refrigerant or refrigerant mixture is passed through the evaporator and used to vaporize the LNG.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">One practice currently employed in combination with the above referenced processes, is the use of atmospheric water towers, by themselves or in combination with heaters or boilers, to heat the refrigerant that acts to vaporize the LNG. In these systems, water is passed into a water tower wherein the temperature of the water is elevated. The elevated temperature water is then used to heat the refrigerant such as glycol via a first evaporator, which in turn is used to vaporize the LNG via a second evaporator.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Accordingly, there is a need in the art to provide an apparatus and method for pre-cooling or reducing the temperature of inlet air to a gas turbine generator along with providing efficient power generation.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The foregoing needs are met, to a great extent, by the present invention, wherein aspects of an energy generating apparatus and method are provided.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In accordance with an embodiment of the present invention, a power generating system is provided, comprising: a liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit, comprising: a heat exchange assembly; a heating tower connected to said heat exchange assembly; a liquid natural gas (LNG) connected to said heat exchange assembly; and an energy generating circuit connected to said liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit, said energy generating circuit, comprising: a gas turbine connected to said heating tower; and a first electrical generator connected to said gas turbine.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In accordance with another embodiment of the present invention, a method for generating power using a gas turbine having an air inlet and heating water using a heating tower is provided, comprising: drawing an air stream into the heating tower through an inlet to define an air inlet stream; passing the air inlet stream over a fill medium; passing the water over the fill medium; discharging the air stream from the heating tower through an outlet to define an air outlet stream; isolating the inlet air stream from the outlet air stream; and providing the outlet air stream to the gas turbine air inlet.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In accordance with yet another embodiment of the present invention, a power generating system having a gas turbine is provided, comprising: means for drawing an air stream into the heating tower through an inlet to define an air inlet stream; means for passing the air inlet stream over a fill medium; means for passing the water over the fill medium; means for discharging the air stream from the heating tower through an outlet to define an air outlet stream; means for isolating the inlet air stream from the outlet air stream; and means for providing the outlet air stream to the gas turbine air inlet.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In accordance with another embodiment of the present invention, a power generating system is provided, comprising: a liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit, comprising: a heat exchange assembly; a liquid natural gas (LNG) vessel connected to said heat exchange assembly; a heating tower connected to said heat exchange assembly that produces cool water; an energy generating circuit, comprising: a gas turbine connected to said heating tower; a first electrical generator connected to said gas turbine; and a cooling tower; and a cool liquid conduit that transports the cool water between said liquid (LNG) vaporization circuit and said energy generating circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In accordance with yet another embodiment of the present invention, a power generating system having an energy generating circuit, comprising a gas turbine connected to the power generating system and a first electrical generator connected to the gas turbine is provided, comprising: a liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit, comprising: a heat exchange assembly; a heating tower connected to said heat exchange assembly; and a liquid natural gas (LNG) vessel connected to said heat exchange assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">There has thus been outlined, rather broadly, certain embodiments of the invention in order that the detailed description thereof herein may be better understood, and in order that the present contribution to the art may be better appreciated. There are, of course, additional embodiments of the invention that will be described below and which will form the subject matter of the claims appended hereto.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In this respect, before explaining at least one embodiment of the invention in detail, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited in its application to the details of construction and to the arrangements of the components set forth in the following description or illustrated in the drawings. The invention is capable of embodiments in addition to those described and of being practiced and carried out in various ways. Also, it is to be understood that the phraseology and terminology employed herein, as well as the abstract, are for the purpose of description and should not be regarded as limiting.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">As such, those skilled in the art will appreciate that the conception upon which this disclosure is based may readily be utilized as a basis for the designing of other structures, methods and systems for carrying out the several purposes of the present invention. It is important, therefore, that the claims be regarded as including such equivalent constructions insofar as they do not depart from the spirit and scope of the present invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of a power generating system in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Various preferred embodiments of the present invention provide for a power generating system, wherein a system for imparting heat to a circulating liquid employed to cool the inlet air of a gas turbine for example. In some arrangements, the system for imparting heat to circulating liquid employs a heating tower and is utilized in vaporization of gasification systems and/or processes utilized for the vaporization of liquid natural gas (LNG). It should be understood, however, that the present invention is not limited in its application to gas turbines or gas turbine generators, but, for example, with other air consuming systems and/or other air consuming processes such as engines or heat exchangers. Preferred embodiments of the invention will now be further described with reference to the drawing FIGURE, in which like reference numerals refer to like parts throughout.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Referring now <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an energy generating apparatus, generally designated <b>10</b>, includes both a liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit or assembly, generally designated <b>12</b>, and an energy generating circuit or assembly, generally designated <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the LNG vaporization circuit <b>12</b> includes a LNG storage tank or vessel <b>16</b> that stores the LNG to be vaporized. The LNG storage vessel <b>16</b> is in fluid communication with, or connected to, via a conduit <b>20</b>, a heat exchanger assembly <b>18</b> that preferably employs two heat exchangers <b>18</b><i>a </i>and <b>18</b><i>b</i>. The LNG vaporization circuit <b>12</b> also includes a heating tower <b>22</b> which is also in fluid communication with the heat exchanger <b>18</b> via conduits <b>24</b> and <b>26</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the heating tower <b>22</b>, in combination with conduits <b>28</b> and <b>30</b>, connects the LNG vaporization circuit <b>12</b> to the energy generating circuit <b>14</b> and vice versa.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The heating tower <b>22</b> is preferably a mechanical draft heating tower that includes a water basin and frame assembly. The heating tower further includes an inlet duct or shell that defines the heating tower air inlet and functions to isolate the air inlet and outlet streams of the heating tower <b>22</b>. The inlet duct can be of any geometry however the duct is preferably has a generally hyperbolic geometry. The heating tower <b>22</b> may either have a counter flow configuration or a cross-flow configuration, depending upon the fill employed in the heating tower <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">As depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the energy generating circuit <b>14</b> includes a standard gas turbine <b>32</b> having a fuel source or supply <b>33</b>, wherein the turbine <b>32</b> is connected to the heating tower <b>22</b> via conduit <b>28</b>. The gas turbine <b>32</b> is a standard turbine and includes a combustion chamber, turbines and an exhaust. The gas turbine <b>32</b> functions to compress incoming air flow from the heating tower <b>22</b> and then mix the compressed air with fuel prior to ignition of the air-fuel mixture. The gas turbine <b>32</b> is also connected to a first electric generator <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The energy generating circuit <b>14</b> further includes a steam generator <b>36</b> and a condenser <b>38</b>. The steam generator <b>36</b> and condenser <b>38</b> are connected to one another via a conduit <b>40</b>. The energy generating circuit <b>14</b> also includes a fluid cooler <b>42</b> which is in fluid communication with the condenser <b>38</b> via conduits <b>44</b> and <b>46</b>. As the name suggests, the fluid cooler <b>42</b> functions to cool the fluid exiting the condenser <b>38</b>. The fluid cooler <b>42</b> may include any cooling means, for example a cooling tower, a natural water source such as river water, lake water or ocean water or a cooling tower.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">For energy generating circuits the utilize a cooling tower as the fluid cooler <b>42</b>, the cooling tower is preferably a standard cooling tower. By standard cooling tower, it is understood that the cooling tower is a mechanical draft tower that may have either a cross-flow configuration or a counter flow configuration, depending upon the fill media employed in the tower. It is further understood that during operation of the tower <b>42</b>, water is sprayed onto the fill media while ambient air is drawn across the media and heat exchange occurs.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Returning to the energy generating circuit <b>14</b>, as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the circuit <b>14</b> additionally includes a steam turbine <b>48</b> that is also in communication with the steam generator <b>36</b> via conduit <b>50</b>. The steam turbine <b>48</b> is connected to a second electric generator <b>52</b> via a rotatable shaft <b>54</b> that turns the second electric generator <b>52</b>. The steam turbine <b>48</b> is also in fluid communication with the condenser via conduit <b>56</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">For clarity purposes, each of the circuits, the LNG vaporization circuit <b>12</b> and the energy generating circuit <b>14</b>, will be described separately in detail, however it is understood that during operation of the power generating system <b>10</b>, both circuits <b>12</b>, <b>14</b> are in operation simultaneously.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">During operation of the LNG vaporization circuit <b>12</b>, LNG to be vaporized is pumped from the LNG storage vessel <b>16</b>, through the conduit <b>20</b> and into the heat exchanger assembly <b>18</b>. While the LNG is pumped into the heat exchanger assembly <b>18</b>, ambient air is simultaneously being drawn into the heating tower <b>22</b> as indicated by the arrow <b>58</b> via mechanical drafting means. Also during this time period, cool or cold water from the exchanger assembly <b>18</b> is also delivered to the heating tower <b>22</b> via conduit <b>24</b>. Upon its arrival at the heating tower <b>22</b>, the cool water is delivered to a water distribution assembly or the like <b>23</b>, where the water is in turn sprayed on a fill media while the ambient air is drawn through the fill media. As the ambient air contacts the fill media and the cool liquid falling thereon, a heat exchange occurs, imparting heat on the water, elevating the temperature of the water within the heating tower <b>22</b>, while causing the air to become very cool and moist. Furthermore, as the aforementioned heat exchange occurs, moisture is condensed out of the air and a quantity of water is produced. This quantity of water is then transported or pumped to the energy generating circuit <b>14</b> via conduit <b>30</b>, as illustrated, where it is utilized to replenish or restore the water of the cooling tower <b>42</b> that evaporates during its operation.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the cool, moist air is transported out of the heating tower via conduit <b>28</b> while the warm water is pumped through conduit <b>26</b> to the heat exchanger assembly <b>18</b>. Once the heated water reaches the heat exchanger assembly <b>18</b>, it passes through the first heat exchanger <b>18</b><i>a </i>where it travels through suitable fins, coils and other passages or the like, so as to transfer heat from the heated water to a circulating, intermediate fluid. The intermediate fluid preferably has a low freezing point, such as glycol or the like, and therefore does not freeze when it enters the second heat exchanger and interacts with the LNG. The intermediate fluid is typically very cold due to its heat exchange interaction with the LNG, which will be described in further detail below, therefore after the heat exchange between the water and the intermediate fluid, the water becomes very cold. This cold water is then returned to the heating tower <b>22</b> via the conduit <b>24</b> where it is reheated as previously described above.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The intermediate fluid preferably has a low freezing point, such as glycol or the like, and therefore does not freeze when it enters the second heat exchanger and carries out the heat exchange with the LNG, which effects the elevation of the temperature of the intermediate fluid.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Once the heated intermediate fluid leaves the first heat exchanger <b>18</b><i>a </i>of the heat exchange assembly <b>18</b>, it proceeds to the second heat exchanger <b>18</b><i>b </i>within the heat exchange assembly <b>18</b> where the heat exchange between the LNG and the intermediate liquid occurs. At the second heat exchanger <b>18</b><i>b</i>, the heated intermediated fluid flows through suitable fins, coils and/or other passages or the like, similar to the first exchanger <b>18</b><i>a</i>. As the heated intermediate fluid flows through the aforementioned passages, heat is imparted on the LNG, which simultaneously flows through a separate set of fins, coils and/or other passages. As the aforementioned heat exchange occurs, the temperature of the LNG rises to the extent that the LNG starts to vaporize and the LNG converts from the liquid state into the gaseous state. The natural gas is then pumped from the heat exchanger assembly <b>18</b> via a conduit <b>60</b> where it may be utilized in marketplace.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">As previously mentioned, while the LNG vaporization circuit <b>12</b> is in operation, the energy generating circuit <b>14</b> is also in operation simultaneously. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, during operation of the energy generating circuit <b>14</b>, cool air is provided to the inlet of the gas turbine <b>32</b> via conduit <b>28</b>. As previously described in connection with the operation of the heating tower <b>22</b>, the cool air results from the heat exchange action that occurs between the cold liquid and ambient air within the heating tower <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The cool air travels through the conduit <b>28</b> to the gas turbine <b>32</b> inlet where it enters the gas turbine and where it is compressed by compressor of the turbine <b>32</b>. Next, fuel, which is provided by the fuel supply <b>33</b>, is mixed with the compressed, cool air and the mixture then moves onto the combustion chamber(s) where the mixture is ignited to generate high temperature gases which in turn drive the turbine <b>32</b>. This driving of the turbine causes the generator <b>34</b> to generate power or electricity which, like the vaporized natural gas of the LNG vaporization circuit <b>12</b>, can now be utilized in the marketplace. During operation of the gas turbine <b>32</b> as previously described, the exhaust from the gas turbine <b>32</b>, generally designated <b>62</b>, is utilized by the steam generator <b>36</b> to generate steam.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">As depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the gas turbine exhaust <b>62</b> is utilized by the steam generator to generate steam to power the steam turbine <b>48</b>. During operation of the energy generating circuit <b>14</b>, hot water from the condenser <b>38</b> is pumped to the cooling tower <b>42</b> via conduit <b>44</b> where heat exchange takes place and the water subsequently cooled. Once the water is cooled, it returns to the condenser <b>38</b> via conduit <b>46</b> where the cool water temperature assists to condense the hot steam exiting from the steam turbine <b>48</b>, via conduit <b>56</b>. The condensate then flows out of the condenser <b>38</b> through the conduit <b>40</b> and enters the steam generator <b>36</b> where it is heated and converted into steam. The steam then proceeds through conduit <b>50</b> where it enters and drives the steam turbine <b>48</b> and then returns to the condenser <b>38</b> via conduit <b>56</b>. The aforementioned driving of the steam turbine <b>48</b>, similar to that of the gas turbine <b>32</b>, in turn drives the second generator <b>52</b> which accordingly generates electricity to be used in the marketplace.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The many features and advantages of the invention are apparent from the detailed specification, and thus, it is intended by the appended claims to cover all such features and advantages of the invention which fall within the true spirit and scope of the invention. Further, since numerous modifications and variations will readily occur to those skilled in the art, it is not desired to limit the invention to the exact construction and operation illustrated and described, and accordingly, all suitable modifications and equivalents may be resorted to, falling within the scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A power generating system, comprising:
<claim-text>a liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit, comprising:
<claim-text>a heat exchange assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heating tower connected to said heat exchange assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a liquid natural gas (LNG) vessel connected to said heat exchange assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an energy generating circuit connected to said liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit,</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>said energy generating circuit, comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gas turbine connected to said heating tower; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first electrical generator connected to said gas turbine,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said heat exchange assembly comprises:
<claim-text>a first heat exchanger that provides heat exchange between heated water and an intermediate fluid; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second heat exchanger that provides heat exchange between the intermediate fluid and the liquid natural gas (LNG).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said energy generating circuit further comprises:
<claim-text>a steam generator connected to said gas turbine and a steam turbine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a condenser connected to said steam generator; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fluid cooler, wherein said fluid cooler is connected to said condenser and said heating tower.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said energy generating circuit further comprises:
<claim-text>a steam turbine connected to said steam generator and to said condenser; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second electric generator connected to said steam turbine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said fluid cooler is at least one of a natural water source and a cooling tower.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said fluid cooler is a counter flow cooling tower.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said fluid cooler is a cross-flow cooling tower.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said intermediate fluid is glycol.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said heating tower comprises:
<claim-text>an air flow inlet that provides an inlet air flow stream, wherein said air inlet comprises an inlet duct;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an air flow outlet that provides an outlet air flow stream;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a water distribution assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fill medium, wherein said liquid distribution assembly distributes water onto said fill medium,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said inlet duct isolates the inlet air flow stream from the outlet air flow stream.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said inlet duct is generally hyperbolic in shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said fill medium is cross-flow fill medium.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said fill medium is counter flow fill medium.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>an air flow inlet that provides an inlet air flow stream;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an air flow outlet that provides an outlet air flow stream, wherein said air flow outlet comprises an outlet duct; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a water distribution assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fill medium, wherein said water distribution assembly distributes water onto said fill medium,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said outlet duct functions to isolate the inlet air flow stream from the outlet air flow stream.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said outlet duct has a generally rectangular shaped geometry and is oriented in a position that is approximately perpendicular to the vertical axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said fill medium is cross-flow medium.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said fill medium is counter flow medium.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method for generating power using a gas turbine having an air inlet and heating water using a heating tower, comprising:
<claim-text>drawing an air stream into the heating tower through an inlet to define an air inlet stream;</claim-text>
<claim-text>passing the air inlet stream over a fill medium;</claim-text>
<claim-text>passing the water over the fill medium;</claim-text>
<claim-text>discharging the air stream from the heating tower through an outlet to define an air outlet stream;</claim-text>
<claim-text>isolating the inlet air stream from the outlet air stream, wherein said step of isolating the inlet air stream utilizes an inlet duct that is generally hyperbolic in shape; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing the outlet air stream to the gas turbine air inlet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, further comprising providing the water to a heat exchanger, wherein the water is utilized to vaporize liquid natural gas (LNG).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A power generating system, comprising:
<claim-text>a liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit, comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat exchange assembly wherein said heat exchange assembly comprises a first heat exchanger that provides heat exchange between heated water and an intermediate fluid; and a second heat exchanger that provides heat exchange between the intermediate fluid and the liquid natural gas (LNG);</claim-text>
<claim-text>a liquid natural gas (LNG) vessel connected to said heat exchange assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heating tower connected to said heat exchange assembly that produces cool water;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an energy generating circuit, comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gas turbine connected to said heating tower;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first electrical generator connected to said gas turbine; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cool liquid conduit that transports the cool water between said liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit and said energy generating circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein said energy generating circuit further comprises:
<claim-text>a steam generator connected to said gas turbine and a steam turbine; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a condenser connected to said steam generator and a fluid cooler, wherein said fluid cooler cools condensate from said condenser.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein said energy generating circuit further comprises:
<claim-text>a steam turbine connected to said steam generator and to said condenser; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second electric generator connected to said steam turbine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein said fluid cooler is at least one of a natural water source and a cooling tower.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A power generating system having an energy generating circuit, comprising a gas turbine connected to the power generating system and a first electrical generator connected to the gas turbine, comprising:
<claim-text>a liquid natural gas (LNG) vaporization circuit, comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat exchange assembly wherein said heat exchange assembly comprises a first heat exchanger that provides heat exchange between heated water and an intermediate fluid; and a second heat exchanger that provides heat exchange between the intermediate fluid and the liquid natural gas (LNG);</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heating tower connected to said heat exchange assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a liquid natural gas (LNG) vessel connected to said heat exchange assembly.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein said energy generating circuit further comprises:
<claim-text>a steam generator connected to said gas turbine and a steam turbine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a condenser connected to said steam generator; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fluid cooler, wherein said fluid cooler is connected to said condenser and said heating tower.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref>, wherein said energy generating circuit further comprises:
<claim-text>a steam turbine connected to said steam generator and to said condenser; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second electric generator connected to said steam turbine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The power generating system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref>, wherein said fluid cooler is at least one of a natural water source and a cooling tower.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
