<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296997-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296997</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11076440</doc-number>
<date>20050309</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>61</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>8</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>433173</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Apparatus for simulating interdental papilla</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2552134</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Berliner</name>
<date>19510500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>433143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2760628</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Briggs</name>
<date>19560800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206104</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3890714</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gores</name>
<date>19750600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>433149</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5499918</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Morgan et al.</name>
<date>19960300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>433173</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>D379250</doc-number>
<kind>S</kind>
<name>Brewer</name>
<date>19970500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>D28 65</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6019604</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gougeon</name>
<date>20000200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4331681</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6213774</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lazarof</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>433173</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6220258</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Briggs et al.</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>132329</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>433173</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>433141</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>132321</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>132329</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60552651</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040312</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050282113</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051222</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fraiman</last-name>
<first-name>Howard</first-name>
<address>
<street>20 E. Princeton Rd.</street>
<city>Bala Cynwyd</city>
<state>PA</state>
<postcode>19004</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Quinn, Esq.</last-name>
<first-name>Charles N.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lewis</last-name>
<first-name>Ralph A.</first-name>
<department>3732</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An apparatus for simulating interdental papilla having a support for interdental gingival tissue and an attachment for securing the support to an interimplant bone.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="82.04mm" wi="89.49mm" file="US07296997-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="226.91mm" wi="145.37mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296997-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="229.62mm" wi="205.15mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296997-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="222.42mm" wi="198.63mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296997-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="236.39mm" wi="122.94mm" file="US07296997-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED PATENT APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This patent application claims the benefit under 35 U.S.C. 119 and 120 of the filing date and priority of provisional U.S. patent application Ser. No. 60/552,651 filed Mar. 12, 2004.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The invention disclosed herein relates generally to an apparatus for simulating interdental papilla between dental implants. More specifically, preferred embodiments of the disclosed invention relate to a papilla tack for supporting gingival tissues between osseointegrated dental implants.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is known in the art to use dental implants to replace human teeth. Under circumstances known in the art, there are cases when multiple dental implants are used to replace multiple human teeth. The dental implants are anchored into the bone of the jaw and are referenced as osseointegrated dental implants. A problem occurs when multiple dental implants are adjacent one another, replacing adjacent teeth. Healthy teeth are usually surrounded by healthy gingival tissues appearing papilla-like to an onlooker. However, in the case of adjacent dental implants, the interdental gingival tissue is flat, leaving a visible embrasure between the teeth. This embrasure is not aesthetically pleasing for onlookers, and the open embrasure is a give away that dental implants are being utilized in place of real teeth. This is quite embarrassing for individuals having dental implants and presents additional problems as well (e.g. food can get stuck in the embrasure). What is needed is an apparatus for simulating interdental papilla to increase the aesthetic appeal of the interdental region and to minimize any embarrassment and/or discomfort that might be felt by the individual having the dental implants.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Disclosed herein is an apparatus for simulating interdental papilla. The preferred apparatus preferably comprises a base, a front stabilizing pin and a rear stabilizing pin. The base is preferably sized to be positioned between osseointegrated dental implants within an interdental embrasure and beneath at least a portion of the interdental gingival tissue. In some aspects, the apparatus for simulating interdental papilla comprises a papilla tack.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The base preferably comprises a bottom surface, a left side surface, a right side surface and a top surface. The bottom surface is preferably rectangular and preferably comprises a left bottom edge, a right bottom edge, a front bottom edge and a rear bottom edge. The enclosed surface area of the left side surface is preferably defined by the left bottom edge and a left curved edge connecting the endpoints of the left bottom edge. The left side interior angle formed between the left side surface and the bottom surface is preferably greater than about sixty degrees and less than about ninety degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The enclosed surface area of the right side surface is preferably defined by the right bottom edge and a right curved edge connecting the endpoints of the right bottom edge. A right side interior angle is preferably formed between the right side surface and the bottom surface that is about equal to the left side angle. The top surface is preferably defined by the front bottom edge, the rear bottom edge, the left curved edge and the right curved edge.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The base is preferably characterized by dimensions comprising a top width, a bottom width, a length and a height. The top width, preferably measured at a highest point of the base, is preferably about one half millimeter. The bottom width is preferably about three times the top width, and more preferably about one and one half millimeters. The length is preferably about six times the top width, and more preferably about three millimeters. The height is preferably about three times the top width, and more preferably about one and one half millimeters.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The rear stabilizing pin and the front stabilizing pin preferably extend downwardly from the base for securing the base to an interimplant bone. Each of the front and rear stabilizing pins preferably comprise a substantially triangular plane joining with the bottom surface at an edge of the substantially triangular plane. Each of the front and rear stabilizing pins preferably have hardness and sharpness of a magnitude such that each of the front and rear stabilizing pins may be anchored into the interimplant bone.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">These and other features and objects of the invention will be more fully understood from the following detailed description of the preferred embodiments, which should be read in light of the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The accompanying drawings, which form a part of the specification, illustrate the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a </i>is a front view showing a preferred embodiment of a papilla tack.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>b </i>is a rear view showing the preferred embodiment of the papilla tack shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>c </i>is a left side view showing the preferred embodiment of the papilla tack shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>d </i>is a right side view showing the preferred embodiment of the papilla tack shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>e </i>is a bottom view showing a preferred embodiment of a base of the papilla tack shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>f </i>is a top view showing the preferred embodiment of the base shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>e. </i></p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>a </i>is a front view showing an embrasure between osseointegrated interdental implants.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>b </i>is a front view showing the preferred embodiment of the papilla tack shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a </i>positioned within the embrasure shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>a. </i></p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS AND BEST MODE KNOWN FOR PRACTICING THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In describing a preferred embodiment of the invention illustrated in the drawings, specific terminology will be used for the sake of clarity. However, the invention is not intended to be limited to the specific terms so selected, and it is to be understood that each specific term includes all technical equivalents which operate in a similar manner to accomplish a similar purpose.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">With principal reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref><i>a </i>through <b>1</b><i>f</i>, an embodiment of a papilla tack is shown and designated generally <b>100</b>. Papilla tack <b>100</b> preferably comprises base <b>110</b> and at least one stabilizing pin, preferably a front stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>a </i>and a rear stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>b</i>. Base <b>110</b> comprises a preferably bottom surface <b>120</b> a left side surface <b>130</b>, a right side surface <b>140</b> and a top surface <b>150</b>. With principal reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>e</i>, the enclosed surface area of bottom surface <b>120</b> is preferably defined by a left bottom edge <b>122</b>, a right bottom edge <b>124</b>, a front bottom edge <b>126</b> and a rear bottom edge <b>128</b>. Bottom surface <b>120</b> is preferably planar.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">With principal reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>c</i>, the enclosed surface area of left side surface <b>130</b> is preferably defined by left bottom edge <b>122</b> and a left curved edge <b>132</b> connecting the endpoints of left bottom edge <b>122</b>. A left side interior angle Z<sub>L </sub>is formed between left side surface <b>130</b> and bottom surface <b>120</b>. Left side interior angle Z<sub>L </sub>is preferably greater than about sixty degrees and preferably less than about ninety degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">With principal reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>e</i>, the enclosed surface area of right side surface <b>140</b> is preferably defined by right bottom edge <b>124</b> and a right curved edge <b>142</b> connecting the endpoints of right bottom edge <b>124</b>. A right side interior angle Z<sub>R </sub>is formed between right side surface <b>140</b> and bottom surface <b>120</b>. Right side interior angle Z<sub>R </sub>is preferably greater than about sixty degrees and preferably less than about ninety degrees. In preferred embodiments, left side interior angle Z<sub>L </sub>is about equal to right side interior angle Z<sub>R</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">With principal reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>f</i>, the enclosed area of top surface <b>150</b> is preferably defined by front bottom edge <b>126</b>, rear bottom edge <b>128</b>, left curved edge <b>132</b> and right curved edge <b>142</b>. As shown, top surface <b>150</b> curves along with left curved edge <b>132</b> and right curved edge <b>142</b>, preferably reaching height H approximately half way along length L. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref><i>a </i>through <b>1</b><i>b</i>, preferred embodiments of base <b>110</b> appears substantially trapezoidal from front and rear views.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Base <b>110</b> is preferably sized to be positioned between osseointegrated dental implants, within an interdental embrasure and beneath at least a portion of the interdental gingival tissue. In addition to length L and height H, the dimensions of base <b>110</b> preferably also includes a top width TW measured at the highest point of base <b>110</b>. Top width TW is preferably measured across top surface <b>150</b> half way along length L. Furthermore, the dimensions of base <b>110</b> preferably include a bottom width BW, which is about three times top width TW. In preferred embodiments, length L is about six times top width TW, height H is about three times top width TW and bottom width BW is about three times top width TW. More preferably, top width TW is about one half millimeter, bottom width BW is about one and one half millimeters, length L is about three millimeters and height H is about one and one half millimeters.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Base <b>110</b> is the preferred embodiment of support means for supporting interdental gingival tissue. However, a base of any suitable shape and/or other dental scaffolding can be used to support the interdental tissue. Any suitable support means can be utilized so long as it supports interdental gingival tissue in a manner such as to simulate the appearance of an interdental papilla.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Continuing with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref><i>a </i>through <b>1</b><i>d</i>, base <b>110</b> preferably includes front stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>a </i>and rear stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>b</i>, both preferably extending downward from bottom surface <b>120</b>. Each of front stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>a </i>and rear stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>b </i>preferably define an angle of ninety degrees with respect to bottom surface <b>120</b>. In preferred embodiments, each of front stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>a </i>and rear stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>b </i>comprise a substantially triangular plane sharing an edge of the triangle with bottom surface <b>120</b>. Furthermore, each of front stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>a </i>and rear stabilizing pin <b>105</b><i>b </i>have a hardness and sharpness of a magnitude such that each is adapted to be anchored into the interimplant bone.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">At least one stabilizing pin <b>105</b> is a preferred means for securing the supporting means (the base, other means, etc.) to an interimplant bone. Stabilizing pins <b>105</b> of any suitable shape can be utilized. Any suitable securing means (glue, clamp, etc.) can be utilized so long as it secures the supporting means in a manner such as to simulate the appearance of an interdental papilla.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">With principal reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref><i>a</i>, a pair of osseointegrated dental implants are shown with an open embrasure <b>200</b> between the dental implants. The gingival tissue <b>210</b> is located between the dental implants. However, absent implantation of papilla tack <b>100</b>, interdental gingival tissue <b>210</b> is typically unraised and fails to maintain a papilla-like appearance.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">With principal reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>b</i>, a pair of osseointegrated dental implants are shown with an embodiment of papilla tack <b>100</b> implanted there between. Using stabilizing pins <b>105</b> or other securing means, papilla tack <b>100</b> is anchored into the bone between the dental implants either at the time of dental implant placement or in a subsequent surgical intervention. Papilla tack is preferably implanted beneath the interdental gingival tissues <b>210</b>, forcing interdental gingival tissue <b>210</b> outward.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Papilla tack <b>100</b> provides support for interdental gingival tissue <b>210</b>, such support not otherwise being present. This provides an appearance between the two dental implants of an interdental embrasure <b>200</b> that is filled with normal gingival tissue. Base <b>110</b> (and/or other support means) provides a scaffolding for interimplant gingival tissue <b>210</b> over a prolonged period of time, while stabilizing pins <b>105</b> (and/or other securing means) anchor the base and/or other support means to the implant bone.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Although there has been hereinabove described an apparatus for simulating interdental papilla, in accordance with the present invention, for the purposes of illustrating the manner in which the invention may be used to advantage it should be appreciated that the invention is not limited thereto. Accordingly, any and all modifications, variations, or equivalent arrangements which may occur to one skilled in the art should be considered to be within the scope of the present invention as defined in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An apparatus for simulating interdental papilla, comprising:
<claim-text>means in the form of a generally trapezoidal polyhedron for supporting interdental gingival tissue; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pair of pin means extending outwardly from a single surface of said polyhedron for securing the means for supporting interdental gingival tissue to an interimplant bone.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the means for supporting interdental gingival tissue comprises a rectangular base and the pin means extends outwardly therefrom parallel one with another.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the means for supporting interdental gingival tissue is sized to be positioned within an interdental embrasure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the means for supporting interdental gingival tissue is sized to be positioned beneath at least a portion of the interdental gingival tissue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the base is planar and sized to be positioned between osseointegrated dental implants.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein at least one pin extends perpendicularly outwardly from the planar base of the support means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the pair of pin means stabilizing pin comprise a front stabilizing pin and a rear stabilizing pin, both of which extend outwardly perpendicularly from the planar base of the support means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. Apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein at least one stabilizing pin has a hardness and sharpness sufficient for the pin to be anchored into interimplant bone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. Apparatus for simulating interdental papilla, comprising:
<claim-text>support means for supporting interdental gingival tissue; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>securing means for securing the supporting means to an interimplant bone;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the support means comprises a base; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the base comprises:
<claim-text>a bottom surface with a left bottom edge, a right bottom edge, a front bottom edge and a rear bottom edge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a left side surface defined by the left bottom edge and a left curved edge connecting the endpoints of the left bottom edge, wherein a left side interior angle formed between the left side surface and the bottom surface is greater than about sixty degrees and less than about ninety degrees;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a right side surface defined by the right bottom edge and a right curved edge connecting the endpoints of the right bottom edge, wherein a right side interior angle formed between the right side surface and the bottom surface is about equal to the left side interior angle; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a top surface defined by the front bottom edge, the rear bottom edge, the left curved edge and the right curved edge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the base is characterized by dimensions comprising:
<claim-text>a top width measured at a highest point of the base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bottom width about three times the top width;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a length about six times the top width; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a height about three times the top width.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the top width is to 0.5 millimeters, wherein the bottom width is about 1.5 millimeters, wherein the length is about 3 millimeters and wherein the height is about 1.5 millimeters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An apparatus for simulating interdental papilla, comprising:
<claim-text>support means for supporting interdental gingival tissue; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>securing means for securing the supporting means to an interimplant bone</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the securing means comprises at least one stabilizing pin and wherein at least one stabilizing pin extends downward from the support means and wherein at least one stabilizing pin comprises a substantially triangular plane sharing an edge with a bottom surface of the support means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. An apparatus for simulating interdental papilla, comprising:
<claim-text>a base sized to be positioned within an interdental embrasure and beneath at least a portion of the interdental gingival tissue; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one stabilizing pin downwardly extending from the base for securing the base to an interimplant bone,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the base comprises:
<claim-text>a bottom surface with a left bottom edge, a right bottom edge, a front bottom edge and a rear bottom edge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a left side surface defined by the left bottom edge and a left curved edge connecting the endpoints of the left bottom edge, wherein a left side interior angle formed between the left side surface and the bottom surface is greater than about sixty degrees and less than about ninety degrees;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a right side surface defined by the right bottom edge and a right curved edge connecting the endpoints of the right bottom edge, wherein a right side interior angle formed between the right side surface and the bottom surface is about equal to the left side interior angle; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a top surface defined by the front bottom edge, the rear bottom edge, the left curved edge and the right curved edge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one stabilizing pin further comprises a front stabilizing pin and a rear stabilizing pin.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein at least one of the stabilizing pins has a hardness and sharpness sufficient for anchoring into the interimplant bone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A papilla tack for simulating interdental papilla, comprising:
<claim-text>a base sized to be positioned between osseointegrated dental implants, within an interdental embrasure and beneath at least a portion of the interdental gingival tissue, the base comprising:
<claim-text>a bottom surface with a left bottom edge, a right bottom edge, a front bottom edge and a rear bottom edge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a left side surface defined by the left bottom edge and a left curved edge connecting the endpoints of the left bottom edge, wherein a left side interior angle formed between the left side surface and the bottom surface is greater than about sixty degrees and less than about ninety degrees;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a right side surface defined by the right bottom edge and a right curved edge connecting the endpoints of the right bottom edge, wherein a right side interior angle formed between the right side surface and the bottom surface is about equal to the left side interior angle; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a top surface defined by the front bottom edge, the rear bottom edge, the left curved edge and the right curved edge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the base is characterized by dimensions comprising:
<claim-text>a top width measured at a highest point of the base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bottom width about three times the top width;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a length about six times the top width; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a height about three times the top width;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a front stabilizing pin downwardly extending from the base for securing the base to an interimplant bone; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rear stabilizing pin downwardly extending from the base for securing the base to an interimplant bone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the front and rear stabilizing pins comprise a substantially triangular plane sharing an edge with the bottom surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the front and rear stabilizing pins have a hardness and sharpness of a magnitude such that each of the front and rear stabilizing pins are adapted to be anchored into the interimplant bone.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the top width is about 0.5 millimeters, wherein the bottom width is about 1.5 millimeters, wherein the length is about 3 millimeters and wherein the height is about 1.5 millimeters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. Apparatus for simulating interdental papilla, comprising:
<claim-text>a) generally trapezoidally shaped polyhedron configured means for supporting gingival tissue, comprising:
<claim-text>i) a planar rectangular base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>ii) a continuously curved convex surface extending between respective ends of the base and tapering from wider at junction with the ends of the base to narrower at a position equidistant therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>iii) planar surfaces extending between respective sides of the base and corresponding edges of the convex surface; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>b) pins extending outwardly and perpendicularly from respective ends of the base for securing the supporting means to bone in the oral cavity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
