<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298051-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298051</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11208549</doc-number>
<date>20050823</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-157538</doc-number>
<date>20050530</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>40</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257784</main-classification>
<further-classification>257786</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Semiconductor element and manufacturing method thereof</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5739587</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sato</name>
<date>19980400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257758</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5986343</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chittipeddi et al.</name>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257758</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6100589</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tanaka</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257758</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6552438</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lee et al.</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257784</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6791196</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kwon et al.</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257784</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6818540</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Saran et al.</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438612</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-64945</doc-number>
<date>19980300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-358169</doc-number>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-208610</doc-number>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257784</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257786</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060267222</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061130</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Saito</last-name>
<first-name>Hitoshi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kawasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Westerman, Hattori, Daniels &amp; Adrian, LLP.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fujitsu Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kawasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Potter</last-name>
<first-name>Roy Karl</first-name>
<department>2822</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">In a semiconductor element, if a crack is generated inside a bonding pad, the crack does not propagate inside the semiconductor element. The semiconductor element has an electrode on a surface thereof. A wiring layer is formed inside the semiconductor element. A conductive layer is formed separate from the wiring layer so as to form a surface of the electrode. A plurality of pole-like members are formed of a conductive material and extending between the wiring layer and the conductive layer and arranged adjacent to each other. The insulating layer is formed of an insulating material filled between the plurality of pole-like members. A frame member extends between the wiring layer and the conductive layer so as to surround the plurality of pole-like members and the insulating layer together.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="108.29mm" wi="133.94mm" file="US07298051-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="255.52mm" wi="152.15mm" file="US07298051-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="226.40mm" wi="133.86mm" file="US07298051-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="234.95mm" wi="135.38mm" file="US07298051-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="241.55mm" wi="127.25mm" file="US07298051-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="247.73mm" wi="136.57mm" file="US07298051-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="122.17mm" wi="131.91mm" file="US07298051-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention generally relates to a semiconductor element and a manufacturing method thereof and, more particularly, to a semiconductor element having a bonding par or a bump pad or a probing pad that serves as a connection terminal of the semiconductor element in a semiconductor device and a manufacturing method of such a semiconductor element.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Generally, a semiconductor element incorporated in a semiconductor device is provided with a plurality of electrodes for acquiring an electric contact with an external device. For example, if the electrodes serve as connection pads of bonding wires, those electrodes are referred to as bonding pads. If the electrodes serve as connection pads of bumps, those electrodes are referred to as bump pads. Additionally, if the electrodes serve aw connection pads for contacting with probe needles, those electrodes are referred to as probing pads. Hereinafter, the bonding pads are explained below as a representative of the bonding pads, the bump pads and the probing pads.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view showing a part of an integrated circuit package (semiconductor device) in which a semiconductor element having a plurality of bonding pads are incorporated. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the bonding pads <b>6</b><i>a </i>of the semiconductor element <b>6</b> mounted on a die stage <b>4</b> of a lead frame <b>2</b> within the semiconductor device are connected to inner leads <b>2</b><i>a </i>of the lead frame <b>2</b> by bonding wires <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a plan view of the bonding pads shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a line III-III in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, generally, the bonding pads <b>6</b><i>a </i>formed in the semiconductor element have a structure in which many conductive plugs <b>16</b>, which are made of tungsten or the like and arranged in a matrix pattern, are formed on a lower wiring layer <b>14</b> made of aluminum or the like, and an upper conductive layer <b>18</b> made of aluminum or the like is formed on the conductive plugs <b>16</b>. Between the lower wiring layer <b>14</b> and the upper conductive layer <b>18</b>, an insulating layer <b>20</b> is formed around the conductive plug <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It should be noted that the lower wiring layer <b>14</b> is formed on an interlayer insulating film <b>12</b> formed on a semiconductor substrate <b>10</b>, and serves as an internal wiring of the semiconductor element. Additionally, an outer circumferential portion of the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> is covered by a cover film <b>22</b>, and the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> is exposed in openings formed in the cover film <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Here, in a process of forming the semiconductor element, for example, an electric characteristic test is performed by performing an electric test so as to determine whether or not the semiconductor device is good or defective. In this case, is it necessary to bring test probe pins into contact with the bonding pads <b>6</b><i>a </i>(upper conductive layer <b>18</b>). When the test probe pins are pressed onto the upper conductive layer <b>18</b>, a stress is concentrated into the insulating layer, which is hard and brittle as compared to the upper aluminum layer and the conductive plugs <b>16</b>. Due to the stress concentration, there may be a case in which a crack is generated in the insulating layer <b>20</b> between the conductive plugs <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Such a crack does not propagate to the conductive plug <b>16</b>, and ends when the crack reaches the conductive plug <b>16</b>. However, the conductive plugs <b>16</b> are arranged in a matrix pattern, and in the cross-section shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the crack may propagate within the insulating layer <b>20</b> without running into the conductive plugs <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Moreover, a flaw may be formed on the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> by the test probe pins being pressed onto the upper conductive layer <b>18</b>. Such a flaw may propagate within the insulating layer <b>20</b>. Then, if a water component enters the flaw, the water component enters inside the semiconductor element, which may cause a moisture resistance defect.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Thus, in order to solve the above-mentioned problem, there is suggested a bonding pad having a structure in which the conductive plugs and the portions of the insulating layer are exchanged so as to make a grid-like conductive portion <b>16</b>A and island-like insulating layer <b>20</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> (for example, refer to Patent Document 1). It should be noted that <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a plane view of the bonding pad <b>6</b>Aa having the grid-like conductive portion <b>16</b>A, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a line VI-VI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">That is, between the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> and the lower wiring layer <b>14</b>, the grid-like conductive portion <b>16</b>A corresponding to the conductive plugs is formed of tungsten or the like, and an insulating material is filled in each square portion within the grid-like conductive portion <b>16</b>A so as to form the insulating layer <b>20</b>. According to such a structure, the insulating layer <b>20</b>, which tends to generate a crack, is surrounded by wall surfaces of the grid-like conductive portion <b>16</b>A. Accordingly, is a crack is generated in the insulating layer <b>20</b> corresponding to one square portion, the crack does not propagate to the insulating layer <b>20</b> of other square portions or the insulating layer <b>20</b> outside the grid-like conductive portion <b>16</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The following documents relate to the above-mentioned background art of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Patent Document 1: Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 2002-208610</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Patent Document 2: Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 10-64945</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The above-mentioned grid-like conductive portion <b>16</b>A can be formed by forming portions corresponding to openings of the grid pattern (that is, the island-like insulating layer <b>20</b>) and filling tungsten or the like between the island-like insulating layer <b>20</b>. However, since the insulating material forming the insulating layer <b>20</b> has a pole shape, a contact area with the lower wiring layer <b>14</b> is small. Thus, there may be a problem in that the pole-like insulating layer <b>20</b> separate and fall off from the lower wiring layer <b>14</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> when performing etching, ashing, post processing, cleaning, and drying in the forming process of the insulating layer <b>20</b> or when performing cleaning or drying in a subsequent process. It should be noted that, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the island like insulating layer <b>20</b> is indicated not as a square pole but a cylindrical pole. Although the island-like insulating layer <b>20</b> is indicated as a square pole in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, it may be a shape close to cylindrical pole when forming in practice.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In addition, the may happen a problem in that the conductive material cannot be properly filled in a portion indicated by a reference numeral <b>38</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> or a recess is formed when filling the conductive material such as tungsten or the like around the island-like insulating layer <b>20</b>, which cannot acquire a good coverage. It should be noted that the island-like insulating layer <b>20</b> is indicated as a cylindrical pole also in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">It is a general object of the present invention to provide an improved and useful semiconductor element and manufacturing method thereof in which the above-mentioned problems are eliminated.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A more specific object of the present invention is to provide a semiconductor element having a structure in which, if a crack is generated inside a bonding pad, the crack does not propagate inside the semiconductor element.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In order to achieve the above-mentioned objects, there is provided according to one aspect of the present invention a semiconductor element having an electrode on a surface thereof, the semiconductor element comprising: a wiring layer formed inside the semiconductor element; a conductive layer formed separate from the wiring layer so as to form a surface of the electrode; a plurality of pole-like members formed of a conductive material and extending between the wiring layer and the conductive layer and arranged adjacent to each other; an insulating layer formed of an insulating material filled between the plurality of pole-like members; and a frame member extending between the wiring layer and the conductive layer so as to surround the plurality of pole-like members and the insulating layer together.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Additionally, there is provided according to another aspect of the present invention a manufacturing method of a semiconductor element having an electrode on a surface thereof, the manufacturing method comprising: forming a plurality of pole-like members and a frame member on a wiring layer inside the semiconductor element so that the frame member surrounds the plurality of pole-like members; forming an insulating layer by filling an insulating material between the pole-like members; and forming a conductive layer on the plurality of pole-like members, the insulating member and the frame member so as to make a surface of the conductive layer as a surface of the electrode. The frame member may be formed by the same material as the pole-like members.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">According to the present invention, even if a crack is generated in the insulating layer under the electrode due to a stress applied onto the electrode when being contacted by a test probe pin, performing wire-bonding or forming a bump, propagation of the crack is prevented by the frame member and the crack does not propagate inside the semiconductor element. Accordingly, generation of a moisture resistance defect due to a water component entering inside the semiconductor element is prevented. Additionally, since the insulating layer in the electrode structure is in a continuous form connected with each other, a portion of the insulating layer cannot fall off in the manufacturing process.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Additionally, according to the present invention, the pole-like members are not only surrounded by the frame member but also completely surrounded in vertical directions and horizontal directions together with the insulating layer by the wiring layer, the intermediate conductive layer, the conductive layer and the frame member. Thus, even if a crack propagates in vertical directions, the crack cannot propagate outside the bonding pad structure, and the crack is confined within the bonding pad structure.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Other objects features and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a part of an integrated circuit package in which a semiconductor element having a plurality of bonding pads are incorporated;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a plan view of the bonding pads shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a line III-III in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a line IV-IV of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a plane view of a bonding pad having a grid-like conductive portion:</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a line VI-VI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is an illustration showing a state of an insulating layer shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is an illustration showing a art of a grid-like member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a plan view of a bonding pad of a semiconductor element according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a line XI-XI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A description will now be given, with reference to the drawings, of an embodiment according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a plan view of a bonding pad portion according to an embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a line X-X of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along a XI-XI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9 through 11</figref>, parts that are the same as the parts shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> are given the same reference numerals.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In the present embodiment, a bonding pad <b>40</b> has a two-stage structure, and as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, an intermediate conductive layer <b>42</b> is provided between upper and lower conductive plugs <b>16</b>. The conductive plugs are pole-like members formed of a conductive material. In the present embodiment, the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> and the intermediate conductive layer <b>42</b> are electrically connected to each other by the upper conductive plugs <b>16</b>, which are pole-like members formed by a conductive material such as tungsten or the like. Similarly, the intermediate conductive layer <b>42</b> and the lower wiring layer <b>14</b> are electrically connected to each other by the lower conductive plugs <b>16</b>, which are pole-like members formed by a conductive material such as tungsten or the like. An externally exposed surface of the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> serves as a bonding surface to which a bonding wire <b>8</b> is joined.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Although the bonding pad <b>40</b> is configured to be the two-stage structure as mentioned above in the present embodiment, the bonding pad may have a single-stage structure or a multi-stage structure having more than 3 stages. A number of stages of the bonding pad can be determined in accordance with a distance between the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> and the interlayer insulating film <b>12</b> formed on the semiconductor substrate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In the present embodiment, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, an outermost circumferential portion of the conductive plugs <b>16</b> positioned arranged in a matrix form is configured as a frame member <b>44</b>, which is continuous over an entire circumference. In the present embodiment, the frame member <b>44</b> is formed of the same material as the conductive plugs <b>16</b>, such as tungsten or the like, and, thereby, the frame member <b>40</b> can be formed in the same process of forming the tungsten plugs <b>16</b>. Accordingly, similar to the conductive plugs <b>16</b>, the frame member <b>44</b> also serves as a member that electrically connects the lower wiring layer <b>14</b> and the upper conductive layer with each other.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">It should be noted that it is preferable to use tungsten (W), copper (Cu), aluminum (Al) or the like as a conductive material to form the conductive plugs <b>16</b> and the frame member <b>44</b>. Additionally, as an insulating material to form an insulating layer <b>20</b>, there are silicon oxide (SixOy), NSG, Silk, a low-dielectric-constant material (low-k) material, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">A width of the frame member <b>44</b> is preferably set to substantially the same as the width of each conductive plug <b>16</b>. For example, if a 0.35-μm rule is applied as a design rule of the semiconductor device, the width of the frame member <b>44</b> is preferably set to about 0.45 μm. If a 0.18-μm rule is applied as a design rule, the width of the frame member <b>44</b> is preferably set to about 0.25 μm. If a 0.09-μm rule is applied, the width of the frame member <b>44</b> is preferably set to about 0.15 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Additionally, it is preferable that an outline of the frame member <b>44</b> is substantially equal to an outline of the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> forming a bonding surface so that a lot of conductive plugs <b>16</b> can be formed inside the frame member <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In above-mentioned structure, the conductive plugs <b>16</b> and the insulating layer <b>20</b>, which is made of an insulating material, provided between the conductive plugs <b>16</b> are surrounded by the frame member <b>44</b>. Accordingly, even if a crack is generated in the insulating layer provided between the conductive plugs <b>16</b>, the crack cannot propagate outside the frame member <b>44</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>. It can be appreciated that the propagation of the crack <b>30</b> is stopped by the frame member <b>44</b> in the structure according to the present embodiment as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, while the crack <b>30</b> generated in the insulating layer <b>20</b> propagates inside the semiconductor element in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> which shows a conventional structure.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As mentioned above, according to the present embodiment, even if a crack is generated in an insulating layer inside a bonding pad by a mechanical stress applied to the bonding pad when contacting a test probe pin or performing wire-bonding, the crack does not propagate inside the semiconductor element. Thus, generation of a moisture resistance defect due to a water component entering inside the semiconductor element along the crack is. Additionally, since the insulating layer <b>20</b> in the bonding pad structure is not an island-like form but in an interconnected form, a portion of the insulating layer does not fall off.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Moreover, according to the present embodiment, the conductive plugs <b>16</b> are not only surrounded by the frame member <b>44</b> but also completely surrounded in vertical directions and horizontal directions together with the insulating layer <b>20</b> by the lower wiring layer <b>14</b>, the intermediate conductive layer <b>42</b>, the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> and the frame member <b>44</b>. Thus, even if a crack is generated, the crack cannot propagate outside the bonding pad structure, which confines the crack within the bonding pad structure (inside the frame member).</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">It should be noted that the frame member <b>44</b> is formed of the same conductive material as the conductive plugs <b>16</b> in the present embodiment. Since the conductive material is, for example, a metal which is softer than the insulating material forming the insulating layer <b>20</b>, there are advantages in that it is suitable for a material to stop propagation of a crack and the frame member <b>44</b> can be formed in the same process as the process of forming the conductive plugs <b>16</b>. However, it is not always necessary to form the frame member <b>44</b> by a conductive material, and the frame member <b>44</b> may be formed by a relatively flexible insulating material. As such an insulating material, there are, for example, aluminum oxide (AlxOy), titanium aluminum nitride (TixAlyNz), etc.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In order to form the above-mentioned structure of the bonding pad, first, the conductive plugs <b>16</b> and the frame member <b>44</b> are formed on the lower wiring layer <b>14</b> so that the frame member <b>44</b> surrounds the conductive plugs <b>16</b>, and, then, the insulating layer <b>20</b> is formed by filling an insulating material between the conductive plugs <b>16</b>, and, thereafter, the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> is formed on the conductive plugs <b>16</b>, the insulating layer <b>20</b> and the frame member <b>44</b>. Thereby, the surface of the upper conductive layer <b>18</b> can be made as a bonding surface of the bonding pad.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The present invention is not limited to the specifically disclosed embodiments, and variations and modifications may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The present application is based on Japanese priority application No. 2005-157538 filed May 30, 2005, the entire contents of which are hereby incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A semiconductor element having an electrode on a surface thereof, the semiconductor element comprising:
<claim-text>a wiring layer formed inside the semiconductor element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a conductive layer formed separate from the wiring layer so as to form a surface of the electrode;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of pole-like members formed of a conductive material and extending between said wiring layer and the conductive layer and arranged adjacent to each other;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an insulating layer formed of an insulating material filled between the plurality of pole-like members; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a frame member extending between said wiring layer and said conductive layer so as to surround said plurality of pole-like members and said insulating layer together,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein an outer configuration of said conductive layer is equal to or larger than an outer configuration of said frame member, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said insulating layer is entirely and completely enclosed in a space defined by said conductive layer, said wiring layer and said frame member without any openings.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The semiconductor element as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said frame member is formed of said conductive material that forms said pole-like members.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The semiconductor element as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said frame member is formed of a material having a higher flexibility than said insulating material forming said insulating layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A semiconductor element having an electrode on a surface thereof, the semiconductor element comprising:
<claim-text>a wiring layer formed inside the semiconductor element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a conductive layer formed separate from the wiring layer so as to form a surface of the electrode;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of pole-like members formed of a conductive material and extending between said wiring layer and the conductive layer and arranged adjacent to each other;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an insulating layer formed of an insulating material filled between the plurality of pole-like members; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a frame member extending between said wiring layer and said conductive layer so as to surround said plurality of pole-like members and said insulating layer together;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein an outline of said frame member is substantially equal to an outline of said conductive layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The semiconductor element as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said pole-like members are arranged in a matrix form.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The semiconductor element as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein an intermediate conductive layer is provided between said wiring layer and said conductive layer; said pole-like members includes first pole-like members extending between said wiring layer and said intermediate conductive layer and second pole-like layers extending between said intermediate conductive layer and said conductive layer; and said frame member includes a first frame member extending between said wiring layer and said intermediate conductive layer and a second frame member extending between said intermediate conductive layer and said conductive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The semiconductor element as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said first and second frame members are formed of said conductive material that forms said first and second pole-like members.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
