<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298397-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298397</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10202968</doc-number>
<date>20020724</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>833</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>225</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3482071</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Digital transmission system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4584656</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sakai et al.</name>
<date>19860400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348297</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4780761</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Daly et al.</name>
<date>19881000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3752402</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5659776</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chauvel</name>
<date>19970800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>712 22</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6259271</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Couts-Martin et al.</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>326 40</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6381007</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Fabre et al.</name>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348298</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6825876</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Easwar et al.</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348234</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0051065</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Takahashi</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348231</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0054222</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Nitta et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348231</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0126150</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Parry</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345771</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>22</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3482071</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34820711</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34821199</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3482114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34821114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040017478</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040129</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cooper</last-name>
<first-name>Alan Neal</first-name>
<address>
<city>Coppell</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fritz</last-name>
<first-name>Christopher Michael</first-name>
<address>
<city>Dallas</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Exner</last-name>
<first-name>James Walter</first-name>
<address>
<city>Plano</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Jackson Walker LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Klinger</last-name>
<first-name>Robert C.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Freestone Systems, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Addison</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ho</last-name>
<first-name>Tuan</first-name>
<department>2622</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Whipkey</last-name>
<first-name>Jason</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention provides a video transmission system that comprises a camera and a base unit. The camera includes a sensor memory adapted to store video data until each line of the video data is sequentially transmitted, a data buffer adapted to receive and store the sequentially transmitted video data until it is completely received at a base unit memory without errors, a data port adapted to receive from the data buffer and transmit to a camera physical transceiver the data buffered video data, a controller adapted to control data flow between the camera and the base unit, and the camera physical transceiver adapted to transfer the data buffered video data to a physical transceiver of the base unit. The base unit includes the base unit physical transceiver adapted to receive the transferred video data, a base unit data port adapted to receive from the base unit physical transceiver and transmit to a data buffer of the base unit, the transferred video data, a controller adapted to control data flow between the base unit and the camera, the base unit data buffer adapted to store the transferred video data from the base unit data port until it is completely received at the base unit physical transceiver without errors, and the base unit memory adapted to receive and sequentially store each line of the transferred video data.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="82.80mm" wi="136.57mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="110.32mm" wi="165.52mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="92.37mm" wi="137.75mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="98.38mm" wi="147.24mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="111.51mm" wi="150.79mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="109.30mm" wi="117.26mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="186.77mm" wi="141.65mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="148.17mm" wi="114.38mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="214.21mm" wi="151.98mm" file="US07298397-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention is related to patent application Ser. No. 10/202,283 titled DIGITAL OBSERVATION SYSTEM, to patent application Ser. No. 10/202,668 titled DIGITAL CAMERA SYNCHRONIZATION, and to patent application Ser. No. 10/202,257 titled UNIVERSAL SERIAL BUS DISPLAY UNIT. These applications are commonly assigned, commonly filed, and are incorporated by reference herein.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to data transmission systems and, more particularly, to a protocol and transmission system enabling data to be transmitted between a camera and a base unit through a digital lossless process.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">There are requirements to transmit video information from a video source such as a video camera to another unit such as a video display through a lossless process so that the data received is an exact representation of the data transmitted. Conventional solutions exist such as Wide Area Network protocols to address these requirements but they typically are not optimized for the multitude of boundary conditions that are specific to the system and the consideration of a cost of the associated implementation. To overcome this limitation, an improved system that could move data in a format that is native to the source of the data with a high overhead efficiency to minimize the magnitude and cost of the system and to enhance the performance through a streamlined system can be developed. In such a system, a video camera is utilized which outputs a standard National Television Standards Committee (NTSC) square pixel format which has an inherent data rate of 12.5 Mega Pixels per second (Mps). The most typical mode of transmission of this type of data would be to convert the camera Red Green Blue (RGB) color space to a YUV color space. YUV is a format that represents the signal as luminance and chrominance information and is a widely used video format for the transmission of digital video data. The video camera sensor's RGB data however, tends to be approximately 1.5 to 3 times less of a data amount as the YUV format. The reason for this disparity is that the camera sensor data is an efficient method of sampling a scene in which to extract YUV information. By taking advantage of the data in its original form and transmitting it before the color space transformation, a data reduction of 1.5 to 3 times can be achieved. This is a critical issue during NTSC square pixel video signal transmission. The amount of data required to transmit the data in the YUV domain is approximately 150 Mega bits per second (Mbs) which exceeds the capability of Ethernet systems that typically transmit data at 100 Mbs. Therefore, if the data could be transmitted in the camera sensor's original RGB format, the data requirements could be reduced from approximately 150 Mbs to 75 Mbs. As such, the data could be transmitted using the standard, low cost, 100 Mbs transmission method.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Another limitation involves the utilization of the Ethernet protocol for the standard transmission method for 100 Mb data. In such a utilization, the resultant true data output would be far less than 75 Mbs because the Ethernet protocol has multiple operational requirements such as multi-drop operation, error detection, source and destination addressing, and multi-speed operation. In the aforementioned improved system, many of these requirements are not needed. Therefore, these operational requirements can be removed to increase the efficiency of the transmission. However, the video camera data includes unique requirements such as data transmission response latencies to be addressed above normal Ethernet needs. As such, requirements to add additional functions with a minimum penalty to the transmission efficiency exist.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Therefore, it is desirable for the present invention to overcome the conventional limitations associated with transmitting data between a video camera and a base unit.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The present invention achieves technical advantages as a system and method for transmitting video data between a video camera and a base unit via a communication protocol that is compliant with Ethernet physical drivers for transmitting and receiving data at 100 Mbs. The system and protocol can further transmit digital camera data in the camera sensor's original RGB format at the rate of 12.5 Mps or 75 Mbs (using the standard 100 Mbs transmission method). The protocol is designed to handle bi-directional communication channels along with methods for transmission validation and retry of transmissions for lost data packets. The protocol has a reduced overhead designed to maximize data throughput and retain compatibility with standard Ethernet physical drivers.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In an exemplary embodiment, a video transmission system comprises a camera and a base unit. The camera includes a sensor memory adapted to store video data until each line of the video data is sequentially transmitted, a data buffer adapted to receive and store the sequentially transmitted video data until it is completely received at a base unit memory without errors, a data port adapted to receive from the data buffer and transmit to a camera physical transceiver the data buffered video data, a controller adapted to control data flow between the camera and the base unit, and the camera physical transceiver adapted to transfer the data buffered video data to a physical transceiver of the base unit. The base unit includes the base unit physical transceiver adapted to receive the transferred video data, a base unit data port adapted to receive from the base unit physical transceiver and transmit to a data buffer of the base unit, the transferred video data, a controller adapted to control data flow between the base unit and the camera, the base unit data buffer adapted to store the transferred video data from the base unit data port until it is completely received at the base unit physical transceiver without errors, and the base unit memory adapted to receive and sequentially store each line of the transferred video data.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a block diagram of a video transmission system in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a block diagram of a video transmission path between a camera and a base unit each comprising a two video line FIFO memory in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a block diagram of a video transmission path between a camera and a base unit each comprising a RAM module in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>a </i>illustrates a block diagram of a data transmission from a camera to a base unit in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>b </i>illustrates a block diagram of a data transmission from a base unit to a camera in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates a flow chart for video data transmission from a camera to a display in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a flow chart for data transmission error control in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a flow chart for performing certain instructions by a computer readable medium in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a flow chart for video data transmission from a camera to a destination in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a video transmission system <b>10</b> of the present invention is presented. The system <b>10</b> includes at least one camera <b>12</b> and at least one base unit <b>14</b>. The camera <b>12</b> comprises a sensor memory <b>16</b> adapted to store video data until each line of the stored video data is sequentially transmitted and, after some image specific processing such as Correlated Double Sampling and DC Restoration, a data buffer <b>18</b> adapted to receive and store the sequentially transmitted video data until it is completely received at a base unit memory <b>34</b> without errors. The data buffer <b>18</b>, which is operably coupled to the camera sensor <b>36</b> to receive data from the camera sensor memory <b>16</b>, is utilized because the readout of the stored video data from the sensor memory is typically a destructive read. The camera <b>12</b> further comprises a data port <b>20</b>, operably coupled to the data buffer <b>18</b>, that is adapted to simultaneously transmit and receive video and non-video data and transmit the data to the base unit <b>14</b>, and a controller <b>22</b> adapted to control data flow between the camera and the base unit. A camera physical transceiver <b>24</b> is also adapted to simultaneously transmit/transfer (and receive) the video data stored in the data buffer <b>18</b> and the non-video data to a base unit physical transceiver <b>26</b>, where the controller <b>22</b> and the camera physical transceiver <b>24</b> are operably coupled to the data port <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In a preferred embodiment, the data output to the camera physical transceiver <b>24</b> has a peak data rate of 12.5 Mega Bytes per second (MBs) or 100 Mbs. The average data rate is (640 pixels)×(480 lines)×(1 Byte)×(30 Frames per second)=9.216 MBs or 73.728 Mbs. The data output from the camera <b>12</b> during each transmission is equal to one line of the camera sensor <b>36</b> that is 640 pixels long. As such, each data packet sent from the camera <b>12</b> to the base unit <b>14</b> is 640 bytes or 5120 bits of data. The data rate for the transmission is the standard Ethernet 100BaseT rate of 100 Mbs and the transmission time for transmitting the 640 bytes of video data is 51.2 uS which does not include additional data used for error correction, secondary data, and header data. The physical transceivers <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> are Ethernet 100BaseT transceivers and are adapted to transmit and receive data simultaneously. The physical drivers could be other devices dependant on the data speeds required.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The base unit <b>14</b> includes the base unit physical transceiver <b>26</b> which is adapted to simultaneously receive and transmit the video data and the non-video data from the data port <b>20</b> via the camera physical transceiver <b>24</b> (and receive and transmit other data to the camera <b>12</b> from the data buffer <b>32</b> and/or the base unit memory <b>34</b>). The base unit physical transceiver <b>26</b> and the camera physical transceiver <b>24</b> are operably coupled to each other via an Ethernet connection <b>25</b>. The base unit <b>14</b> further includes a data port <b>28</b>, operably coupled to the base unit physical transceiver <b>26</b>, that is adapted to simultaneously transmit and receive video and non-video data and transmit the data to the camera <b>12</b>, a controller <b>30</b> adapted to control data flow between the base unit <b>14</b> and the camera <b>12</b>, and a data buffer <b>32</b> adapted to store the video data from the base unit physical transceiver <b>26</b> and the data port <b>28</b> until it is completely received at the base unit physical transceiver without errors. The data buffer <b>32</b> and the controller <b>30</b> are operably coupled to the data port <b>28</b>. The base unit memory <b>34</b>, operably coupled to the data buffer <b>32</b>, is adapted to sequentially store each line of the video data (i.e. the complete frame of the transmitted video data). The base unit memory <b>34</b> stores the last complete transferred frame of data for the base unit <b>14</b> to display. The image in the memory <b>34</b> will be retained until a new frame of video is received and stored.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In a preferred embodiment, the camera <b>12</b> further comprises a camera sensor <b>36</b>, which comprises the sensor memory <b>16</b>, and an A/D converter (not shown). Initial video data and/or previous video data is sequentially transmitted from the sensor memory <b>16</b> in RGB color space format native to the camera sensor <b>36</b> in, for example, a single serial stream at 12.5 Mps. The A/D converter, which interfaces to the sensor memory <b>16</b> and the camera data buffer <b>18</b>, is adapted to convert the previous video data from RGB analog data to RGB digital data. The RGB digital data is then transmitted to and stored in the camera data buffer <b>18</b>. The camera sensor <b>36</b> may output analog data which is converted to digital data via the A/D converter that is external to the camera sensor <b>36</b>. Additionally, the camera sensor <b>36</b> may internally include the A/D converter and thus directly output digital data. The video data is sent as digital data between the camera <b>12</b> and the base unit <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In an alternate embodiment, the camera <b>12</b> further comprises a programmable logic device (PLD—not shown). The PLD, which interfaces to the A/D converter and the data buffer <b>18</b>, is adapted to convert digital data from one format of color space to another format of color space entirely in the digital domain. As such, the camera sensor <b>16</b> outputs RGB analog data, the A/D converter converts the RGB analog data to RGB digital data, the PLD converts the RGB digital data in RGB color space format to YUV digital data in YUV color space format, which is transferred to the data buffer <b>18</b>. The PLD further controls the timing signals of the camera sensor <b>36</b> and the A/D converter to move the analog data/previous video data out of the camera sensor memory <b>16</b>, through the A/D converter, into the data buffer <b>18</b>, and then to the camera physical transceiver <b>24</b> via the data port <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The base unit physical transceiver <b>26</b> is adapted to transmit an acknowledgement to the camera physical transceiver <b>24</b> after each line of the video data is received without errors from the camera physical transceiver. The base unit controller <b>30</b> is adapted to confirm to the base unit physical transceiver <b>26</b> via the data port <b>28</b> that each line of the video data was received without errors. The sensor memory <b>16</b> is then adapted to increment to a next line of the video data to be transmitted when the acknowledgement is received by the camera controller <b>22</b>. The camera data buffer <b>18</b> is adapted to retransmit the line of the video data when the acknowledgement is not received by the camera controller <b>22</b> within an amount of time.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, a video transmission system comprises a camera including: a sensor memory adapted to store previous video data; a sensor adapted to sequentially transmit the previous video data as RGB analog data, where the camera sensor comprises the sensor memory; an A/D converter adapted to convert the RGB analog data into RGB digital data and transmit the RGB digital data to a data buffer, where the A/D converter interfaces to the sensor and the data buffer; where the data buffer is adapted to receive and store the RGB digital data until it is completely received at a base unit memory without errors, where the data buffer is operably coupled to the sensor memory; and a camera physical transceiver adapted to transmit the stored RGB digital data to a base unit physical transceiver, where the camera physical transceiver is operably coupled to the data buffer via a data port. The video transmission system further comprises the base unit that includes: the base unit physical transceiver adapted to receive the transmitted RGB digital data from the camera physical transceiver, where the base unit physical transceiver is operably coupled to the camera physical transceiver; a data buffer adapted to store the received RGB digital data from the base unit physical transceiver until it is completely received at the base unit physical transceiver without errors, where the data buffer is operably coupled to the base unit physical transceiver via a data port; and the base unit memory adapted to sequentially store each line of the received RGB digital data, where the base unit memory is operably coupled to the data buffer. The sensor memory is further adapted to delete the stored previous video data when each line of the stored previous video data is sequentially transmitted and the camera data buffer is adapted to delete the RGB digital data when it is completely received at the base unit memory without errors.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In another embodiment of the present invention, a video transmission system comprises a destination (such as, for example, the base unit <b>14</b>) and a camera (such as, for example, the camera <b>12</b>) that includes a camera memory that is adapted to: store a frame of video data until each line of the frame is transmitted to and received at the destination, read a next line of the frame when a previous line is received at the destination, and read the next line of the frame upon receiving an acknowledgement of the previous line transmission. The destination includes: a destination memory adapted to store a last complete received frame of the video data from the camera memory, and a display adapted to receive and display the last complete received frame of the video data. The camera memory is further adapted to delete the previous line when the next line is read.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In a further embodiment of the present invention, a video transmission system comprises a camera including a sensor memory adapted to store previous video data, a sensor adapted to sequentially transmit the previous video data in RGB color space format native to the camera sensor, where the camera sensor comprises the sensor memory, and a PLD adapted to convert the sequentially transmitted previous video data into YUV color space format and transmit the YUV data to a data buffer, where the data buffer is adapted to receive and store the YUV data until it is completely received at a base unit memory without errors, and where the data buffer is operably coupled to the sensor memory, and a camera physical transceiver adapted to transmit the stored YUV data to a base unit physical transceiver, where the camera physical transceiver is operably coupled to the data buffer via a data port.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The video transmission system further comprises the base unit that includes the base unit physical transceiver adapted to receive the transmitted YUV data from the camera physical transceiver, where the base unit physical transceiver is operably coupled to the camera physical transceiver, a data buffer adapted to store the received YUV data from the base unit physical transceiver until it is completely received at the base unit physical transceiver without errors, where the data buffer is operably coupled to the base unit physical transceiver via a data port, and the base unit memory adapted to sequentially store each line of the received YUV data, where the base unit memory is operably coupled to the data buffer. The sensor memory is adapted to delete the stored previous video data when each line of the stored previous video data is sequentially transmitted and the camera data buffer is adapted to delete the YUV data when it is completely received at the base unit memory without errors.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, a camera comprises a memory adapted to store previous video data; a first module (such as, for example, the sensor <b>36</b>) adapted to sequentially transmit the previous video data in an analog format, where the first module comprises the memory; a converter adapted to convert the sequentially transmitted previous video data in analog format into a digital format and transmit the digital format data to a second module (such as, for example, the data buffer <b>18</b>), where the converter interfaces to the memory and the second module; where the second module is adapted to receive and store the digital format data until it is completely received at a destination without errors, where the second module is operably coupled to the memory; and a third module (such as, for example, the camera physical transceiver <b>24</b>) adapted to transmit the stored digital format data to the destination, where the third module is operably coupled to the second module via a port.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In another embodiment of the present invention, a camera comprises a sensor memory adapted to store one of a plurality of frames of video data until each line of the one frame is transmitted to and received at a destination, where the sensor memory is adapted to read a next line of the one frame when a previous line is received at the destination, a data buffer adapted to receive the plurality of frames and store them until they are completely received at the destination without errors, where the data buffer is operably coupled to the sensor memory and a data port, and a physical transceiver adapted to transmit the frames to the destination, where the physical transceiver is operably coupled to the data port. The sensor memory is adapted to: delete the previous line when it is received at the destination and to store a next frame of the plurality of frames of video data when each line of the one frame is received at the destination.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In another embodiment of the present invention, a camera comprises a memory adapted to store previous video data, a first module adapted to sequentially transmit the previous video data in a first color space format native to the first module, wherein the first module comprises the memory, a programmable device adapted to convert the sequentially transmitted previous video data into a second color space format and transmit the second color space format data to a second module, wherein the device interfaces to the memory and the second module, where the second module is adapted to receive and store the second color space format data until it is completely received at a destination without errors, and where the second module is operably coupled to the memory, and a third module adapted to transmit the stored second color space format data to the destination, where the third module is operably coupled to the second module via a port.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In a further embodiment of the present invention, a base unit comprises an input adapted to receive each line of a first frame of video data sent from a source, a data port adapted to transmit and receive non-video data to and from the source, where the input is operably coupled to the data port, a data buffer adapted to store the first frame and all subsequently received frames until the frames are completely received at the input without errors, where the data buffer is operably coupled to the data port and a receiver memory, and where the errors occur when the frames are not received within an amount of time, where the receiver memory is adapted to store the frames and the non-video data. The base unit further includes a display adapted to display the frames, where the display is operably coupled to the receiver memory.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a two video line first-in-first-out (FIFO) memory <b>40</b> contained in the data buffers <b>18</b> and <b>32</b> is depicted. The memory <b>40</b> includes an input multiplexer <b>42</b> that receives the video data (in the camera sensor memory <b>16</b>) from the camera sensor <b>16</b>, a first one line FIFO memory <b>44</b>, a second one line FIFO memory <b>46</b>, and an output multiplexer <b>48</b> that outputs the data to the data port <b>20</b>. The input multiplexer <b>42</b> and the output multiplexer <b>48</b> are operably coupled to each other and to the one line FIFO memories <b>44</b> and <b>46</b>. The input multiplexer <b>42</b> selects the appropriate data to be input to each of the memories <b>44</b> and <b>46</b>. The first one line FIFO memory <b>44</b> is adapted to receive and store the video data and the second one line FIFO memory <b>46</b> is adapted to store the line of the video data to be retransmitted (i.e. it receives its own re-circulated output so the data can be resent if the transmission to the base unit <b>14</b> is unsuccessful). The output multiplexer <b>48</b> controls the data output from the memories <b>44</b> and <b>46</b> and selects one of memories' data to output to the physical transceiver <b>24</b> via the data port <b>20</b>. The data output is either the latest line stored or a retransmission of the last unsuccessful transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The receiving data buffer <b>32</b> at the base unit <b>14</b> performs a similar operation in storing the new line being transmitted and outputting the last complete line. When a video line of data is successfully transmitted, the mulitplexers on the receiver will increment to enable the new line of data to be written over the line memory that has already output its data to the base unit memory <b>34</b>, and the other line of data will be transferred to the base unit memory.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In a further embodiment of the present invention, the line memories can be implemented in RAM modules <b>52</b> where the input data multiplexing is controlled by an addresser <b>54</b> performing memory addressing as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The RAM modules <b>52</b> contain enough memory to hold two lines of data. In the camera <b>12</b>, the RAM module's <b>52</b> memory <b>56</b> or <b>58</b> outputs data to the physical receiver <b>24</b> through the multiplexer <b>59</b> and the data port <b>20</b>, while the other memory (opposite of the one outputting) receives new video data from the camera sensor memory <b>16</b>. In the base unit <b>14</b>, one half of the two line RAM memory <b>56</b> or <b>58</b> receives the new video data from the physical receiver <b>26</b> through the multiplexer <b>59</b> and the data port <b>28</b>, while the other half (opposite of the one receiving) is used for transmitting the last completely received line to the base unit memory <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Transmission timing is an important aspect of the video transmission system <b>10</b>. The communication protocol of the system <b>10</b> should allow time for the initial data transmission to reach the base unit <b>14</b>, time for the base unit to check the data and send an acknowledgement, time for the acknowledgement to travel to the camera <b>12</b>, and time for the camera to verify the acknowledgement. The travel time for the transmission of the data and the acknowledgement response time is a variable that is dependant on the length of the connection <b>25</b> and the type of connection. In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the connection <b>25</b> comprises a CAT5 cable and thus the characteristics of the cable are fixed. The maximum travel time is calculated by determining the maximum length of cable allowable and the time period associated with it. As such, the system <b>10</b> utilizes a fixed period of time allowed for the data transmission travel and acknowledgement of the data received before the next line of data is transmitted. The “line time” as described above is 64 uS for the total time which is the period between each line transmission and is the total available time for the transmission and acknowledgement of data from the camera <b>12</b>. The total data packet transmitted is 654 bytes resulting in a 52.32 uS transmission time. The total packet transmitted from the base unit <b>14</b> to the camera <b>12</b> is 14 bytes resulting in a 1.12 uS transmission time. Therefore, the transmission of data takes a total of 52.32+1.12 uS=53.44 uS out of the 64 uS. This leaves 64−53.44=9.56 uS for data travel time and processing time. In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the system operates up to 3000 feet which requires approximately 3000×1.12 ns=6.7 uS for the travel time. This leaves approximately 3 uS for the system <b>10</b> to start and process any transmissions within the 64 uS.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As described above, if the acknowledgement of the transmission is not received at the camera <b>12</b> and processed within one line time, the camera <b>12</b> will retransmit the same line of data. The camera sensor <b>36</b> is a destructive read process—once the data is read from the sensor the data cannot be reconstructed. Since the data may need to be transmitted multiple times, it is required to store the data in the memory <b>40</b>. Furthermore, the timing of the input of the data into the memory <b>40</b> and the output of the data are such that the two memories <b>44</b> and <b>46</b> are required if data from the sensor <b>36</b> is required to be input into the memory <b>40</b> before the old data is read out. This requirement is dependant on the cameras time base design (not shown but described more fully in patent application Ser. No. 10/202,283 titled DIGITAL OBSERVATION SYSTEM which is incorporated by reference herein). In this implementation, the memories <b>44</b> and <b>46</b> are used in an alternating fashion. One memory is used for writing data from the sensor <b>36</b> while the other memory is read out. Each of the memory elements in this implementation was sized at 640×8 bits.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The camera sensor memory <b>16</b> holds one frame of data that is equal to 480 lines of video data and stores the data until each of the lines are successfully transmitted to the base unit <b>14</b>. As described earlier, when the line transmitted is not acknowledged by the base unit <b>14</b>, the camera <b>12</b> will retransmit the same line. In this situation, a new line is not read from the memory <b>16</b> until the line is successfully transmitted to the base unit <b>14</b>. Similarly to the line time, however, a finite time exists for the transmission of all of the data contained in the memory <b>16</b>. In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the system <b>10</b> is designed to transmit 30 frames of the memory 16 per second. This allows 33.33 mS for each frame to be transmitted. Since the memory <b>16</b> holds 480 lines and each line is allocated 64 uS for transmission then the total time for transmission without errors is 480×64 uS=30.72 mS. This leaves approximately 2.6 mS for line retransmissions. Since each retransmission is 64 uS, then 2.6 mS/64 uS=40 lines of data that can be retransmitted. If all of the time leftover is for retransmission, however, other processes are required in the time-base which use some of this allotted time. In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, approximately 20 lines are available for retransmission. This results in the ability to successfully transmit a frame of the camera sensor <b>36</b> with between approximately 5% and 8% of the lines unsuccessfully transmitted.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In addition to retransmissions, error checking and correction are further aspects of the video transmission system <b>10</b>. Error control is achieved through the use of a 16-bit Cyclic Redundancy Check (CRC) which is added to the end of a data transmission between the camera <b>12</b> and the base unit <b>14</b>. This CRC is calculated on all the data transmitted in one line period except for the preamble. If the CRC calculation of the received data at the base unit <b>14</b> is correct, the receiver will send the acknowledgement back to the camera <b>12</b> through a 14-byte transmission that includes the 16-bit CRC. If the camera <b>12</b> receives the 14-byte acknowledgement and the CRC calculation is correct, the camera will increment to send the next line of data at the start of the next line time and will send the line number of the line that is being transmitted to the base unit <b>14</b> to identify the transmitted line. This enables the base unit <b>14</b> to verify that the camera <b>12</b> received its acknowledgement and the next line was transmitted.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">When the data is received by the base unit <b>14</b>, the CRC check is placed at the end of the transmission which requires the base unit to store the full line of transmitted data before it is informed that the data is error free. To make optimal use of time, the data stored from the last successful transmission is transferred into the base unit memory <b>34</b> from the data buffer <b>32</b> at approximately the same time that the next line of data is being transmitted to the base unit <b>14</b>. As such, the base unit <b>14</b> includes two lines of data storage capability to receive data at the same time the last valid line of data is transferred to the base unit memory <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>a</i>, a diagram of a data transmission protocol from the camera <b>12</b> to the base unit <b>14</b> is displayed. To transmit over an Ethernet 100BaseT physical driver, multiple signals are required to control the flow of the data. In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, these signals are generated by the time-base of the camera <b>12</b> and the base unit <b>14</b> accordingly and comply with the physical drivers requirements. The data signal has specific requirements for certain aspects of the start and end of the transmission to allow the physical driver to implement certain control signals in the protocol for signaling the receiving unit the start and stop locations of the data. The data includes a preamble of a specified length with specified values to alert the driver of the location of the data starting position. Beyond this point, the data can be of any form until the driver is notified through control signals that the last of the data has been input into the driver. The CRC data is placed at the end of the data stream so that the error checking verifies all of the data transmitted and for ease of calculation.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The first 8 bytes of data comprise the preamble <b>60</b>, of which the first 7 bytes have a value of “55” in hex and the last byte has a value of “AB” in hex. These values, which are set by the Ethernet standard, let the receiver know when new data is coming and the actual start location of the first byte of data. The next two bytes, “ST<b>1</b>” and “ST<b>0</b>,” are status data <b>62</b> which are reserved for the camera <b>12</b> to send non-video data to the base unit <b>14</b>. This data can be predetermined by the camera <b>12</b> or be requested data by the base unit <b>14</b>. The two bytes following the status data contain the line count <b>64</b>. The most significant of the bytes is designated “LC<b>1</b>” and is transmitted first. The least significant byte is designated “LC<b>0</b>” and is transmitted after “LC<b>1</b>.” In a preferred embodiment, 480 lines are transmitted requiring 9 bits of data. The remaining 7 bits of data not required for the count could also be used for other purposes such as camera status data. Following the line count <b>66</b>, the video data bytes <b>66</b> are transmitted. The video data bytes <b>66</b> are designated as “D<b>0</b>” through “D<b>639</b>” for a total of 640 bytes of video data. Following the video data, two CRC bytes <b>68</b> are transmitted with the most significant byte (“CRC<b>1</b>”) transmitted first and the least significant byte (“CRC<b>0</b>”) transmitted next. The total count of bytes transmitted including the preamble is 654.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>b</i>, a block diagram of a data transmission protocol from the base unit <b>14</b> to the camera <b>12</b> is illustrated. The base unit protocol contains the same 8 bytes of preamble as the camera's <b>12</b> transmission. The two bytes following the base unit protocol's preamble <b>70</b> are the sync bytes <b>72</b> which contain information describing the type of data that is sent. The first byte is “SY<b>1</b>” and has a value of “0F” when acknowledging a line is received, or a value of “A5” to reset the camera <b>12</b> to the start of a new frame. The second byte is “SY<b>0</b>” which contains data to be sent from the base unit <b>14</b> to the camera <b>12</b> that is not required to be received by the camera's registers. Typically this is used for quick data transmissions. Following the sync bytes <b>72</b> are register data bytes <b>74</b> for sending data to the camera registers which are used to change the operation of the camera <b>12</b> or to send data to the camera. The first byte transmitted is an “RA” byte that contains the address of the register to which the data is to be sent. The second byte is the “RD” byte that contains the data that is loaded into the register at the camera <b>12</b>. Following the “RD” byte are the two CRC bytes <b>76</b> that operate in a similar manner as the CRC bytes in the camera transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">This protocol provides a high efficiency of bandwidth and a deterministic time period for each transmission thus enabling the camera <b>12</b> and the base unit <b>14</b> to operate in a fixed time-base of operation. This is very important in video applications where the frame rate of video needs to be consistent for a user to perceive the data as continuous. The system is also robust in that errors are corrected and any failures in transmission do not corrupt the video data to the display.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a method for video data transmission from a camera to a display is presented. The method begins at steps <b>80</b> and <b>82</b>, respectively, with the storing of digital video data in RGB color space format and the transmitting of the digital RGB video with reduced operational overhead and increased operational functionality. The method proceeds to step <b>84</b> with the converting of the transmitted digital RGB video to digital video data in YUV color space format, and, at step <b>86</b>, the displaying of the YUV video data. The operational overhead includes at least one item from a group consisting of: a multi-drop operation, error detection, source addressing, destination addressing, and multi-speed operation, and the operational functionality includes at least one item from a group consisting of: header data, secondary data, and error correction.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a method for data transmission error control is disclosed. The method begins at step <b>90</b> with the adding of a cyclic redundancy check (CRC) to an end of a data transmission comprising a plurality of data bytes from an origination to a destination. Calculating the CRC on all of the transmitted data in a line period excluding a preamble of the data, and transmitting an acknowledgement by the destination when the CRC calculation of the transmitted data in the line period is correct occur, respectively at steps <b>92</b> and <b>94</b>. The acknowledgement includes the CRC located at the end of the acknowledgement. The method proceeds to step <b>96</b>, where the transmitted data in the line period is stored by the destination, and to step <b>98</b> where the origination determines that the CRC calculation of the transmitted data is correct. At step <b>100</b>, transmitting by the origination data in a next line period, and storing by the destination in a memory the transmitted data in the line period contemporaneously occur. The data comprises the CRC at an end of the data transmission of the next line period. The method further includes additional steps such as transmitting a line period number to the destination, determining the reception of the acknowledgement and the transmission of the next line based on the line period number, and storing the transmitted data in the next line period by the destination.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, instructions performed by a computer readable medium are presented. The computer readable medium may be a processor (not shown) or an entity (such as the sensor <b>36</b>) in the camera <b>12</b> and/or the base unit <b>14</b>, and the instructions may be stored in the camera sensor memory <b>16</b>, the camera data buffer <b>18</b>, the base unit data buffer <b>32</b>, the base unit memory <b>34</b> and/or in another memory (not shown). The instructions performed by the computer readable medium include storing data at a first node at step <b>102</b>, sequentially transmitting each line of the stored data at step <b>104</b>, receiving each line of the sequentially transmitted data at a second node at step <b>106</b>, determining that each line of the transmitted data was received without error at step <b>108</b>, storing the errorless data at the second node at step <b>110</b>, and contemporaneously deleting the stored data at the first node, and displaying the errorless data at the second node at step <b>112</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, a method for video data transmission from a camera to a destination is disclosed. The method begins at step <b>120</b> with the transmitting of RGB analog data. Converting the RGB analog data into RGB digital data and transmitting the RGB digital data occurs respectively at steps <b>122</b> and <b>124</b>. The method proceeds at steps <b>126</b> and <b>128</b>, respectively, with the storing of the transmitted RGB digital data in the camera until it is completely received at the destination without errors, and the receiving of the transmitted RGB digital data at the destination. Storing the received RGB digital data in a first destination memory until it is completely received at the destination without errors occurs at step <b>130</b> and storing the received RGB digital data in a second destination memory occurs at step <b>132</b>. The method continues at step <b>134</b> with the deleting of the received RGB digital data in the first destination memory when it is completely received at the second destination memory without errors.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Although an exemplary embodiment of the system and method of the present invention has been illustrated in the accompanied drawings and described in the foregoing detailed description, it will be understood that the invention is not limited to the embodiments disclosed, but is capable of numerous rearrangements, modifications, and substitutions without departing from the spirit of the invention as set forth and defined by the following claims. For example, a plurality of cameras <b>12</b> and base units <b>14</b> may be utilized with the present invention. Further, the camera physical transceiver <b>24</b> and the base unit physical transceiver <b>26</b> may be operably coupled to each other via other connections, including copper, fiber and wireless, if the transceivers were modified to accommodate such other connections. Also, if the camera sensor memory <b>16</b> is not a destructive read then the camera data buffer <b>18</b> may not be required. Still further, the average data rate, the data output, and the transmission time may be altered if different transceivers were used and/or if the resolution of the video differed. Additionally, the connection <b>25</b> may comprise an entity with dynamic characteristics thus altering the maximum travel time, the data transmission travel time, the acknowledgement time, the line time, and the processing time. Also, the system <b>10</b> may operate at a lesser or greater distance than 3000 feet which will alter the travel time and time for the system to start and process any transmissions. Further, the data transmission protocols may comprise different information and/or sizes of the information.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A video transmission system comprising:
<claim-text>a camera including:
<claim-text>a sensor memory adapted to store video data having lines until each said line of the stored video data is sequentially transmitted;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data buffer adapted to receive and store a first said line of the sequentially transmitted video data until the line is completely received at a base unit memory without errors, wherein the data buffer is operably coupled to the sensor memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data port adapted to receive the first line from the data buffer and transmit the first line to a camera physical transceiver, wherein the data port is operably coupled to the data buffer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller adapted to control data flow between the camera and a base unit, wherein the controller is operably coupled to the data port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the camera physical transceiver adapted to transfer the first line to a physical transceiver of the base unit, wherein the camera physical transceiver is operably coupled to the data port; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the base unit includes:
<claim-text>the base unit physical transceiver adapted to receive the transferred first line, wherein the base unit physical transceiver is operably coupled to the camera physical transceiver;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base unit data port adapted to receive the first line from the base unit physical transceiver and transmit the first line to a base unit data buffer, wherein the data port is operably coupled to the base unit physical transceiver;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller adapted to control data flow between the base unit and the camera, wherein the controller is operably coupled to the data port;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the base unit data buffer adapted to store the first line video data from the base unit data port until it is completely received at the base unit physical transceiver without errors, wherein the base unit data buffer is operably coupled to the base unit data port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the base unit memory adapted to receive and sequentially store each said line of the transferred video data, wherein the base unit memory is operably coupled to the data buffer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a camera sensor, wherein the video data is sequentially transmitted from the sensor memory in RGB color space format native to the camera sensor, and wherein the camera sensor comprises the sensor memory.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> further comprising an A/D converter adapted to convert the video data from analog data to digital data, wherein the A/D converter interfaces to the sensor memory and the camera data buffer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> further comprising a programmable logic device (PLD) adapted to control timing signals of the camera sensor, wherein the timing signals are utilized to move the video data out of the camera sensor memory, through the A/D converter, and into the data buffer, and wherein the PLD interfaces to the A/D converter and the camera data buffer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the base unit physical transceiver is adapted to transmit an acknowledgement to the camera physical transceiver after each said line of the transferred video data is received without errors from the camera physical transceiver.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the base unit controller is adapted to confirm, via the data port, that each said line of the transferred video data was received without errors at the base unit physical transceiver.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the sensor memory is adapted to increment to a next said line of the video data to be sequentially transmitted when the acknowledgement is received by the camera controller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the camera data buffer is adapted to retransmit the line of the sequentially transmitted video data when the acknowledgement is not received by the camera controller within an amount of time.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the camera data buffer includes:
<claim-text>an input multiplexer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first one line first-in-first-out (FIFO) memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second one line FIFO memory; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output multiplexer, wherein the input multiplexer and the output multiplexer are operably coupled to the first one line FIFO memory and the second one line FIFO memory, wherein the first one line FIFO memory is adapted to receive and store the video data and wherein the second one line FIFO memory is adapted to store the line of the video data to be retransmitted.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the data ports are further adapted to simultaneously transmit and receive video and non-video data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the physical transceivers are adapted to simultaneously transfer and receive video and non-video data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A video transmission system comprising:
<claim-text>a camera including:
<claim-text>a camera memory adapted to store a frame of video data having lines, and delete a previous said line when a next said line of the frame is read, until each said line of the frame is transmitted to and received at a destination;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the camera memory is adapted to read the next line of the frame when the previous line of the frame is received at the destination; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the next line of the frame is read upon receiving an acknowledgement of the previous line transmission; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the destination includes:
<claim-text>a destination memory adapted to store a last complete received said frame of the video data from the camera memory.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising a display adapted to receive information from the camera memory.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A camera comprising:
<claim-text>a sensor memory adapted to store one of a plurality of frames having lines of video data until each said line of the one frame is transmitted to and received at a destination;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the sensor memory is adapted to read a next said line of the one frame when a previous said line is received at the destination;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data buffer adapted to receive the plurality of frames and store them until they are completely received at the destination without errors, wherein the data buffer is operably coupled to the sensor memory and a data port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a physical transceiver adapted to transmit the frames to the destination, wherein the physical transceiver is operably coupled to the data port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The camera of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the sensor memory is adapted to delete the previous said line when it is received at the destination.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The camera of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the sensor memory is adapted to store a next said frame of the plurality of frames of video data when each said line of the one frame is received at the destination.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The camera of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the data port is adapted to transmit and receive non-video data to and from the destination.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The camera of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a controller adapted to control a flow of data between the camera and the destination, wherein the controller is operably coupled to the data port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the physical transceiver is adapted to receive the data from the destination.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A video transmission system comprising:
<claim-text>a camera including:
<claim-text>a sensor memory adapted to store previous video data and delete the stored previous video data having lines when each said line of the stored previous video data is sequentially transmitted;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sensor adapted to sequentially transmit the previous video data in RGB color space format native to the camera sensor, wherein the camera sensor comprises the sensor memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a programmable logic device (PLD) adapted to convert the sequentially transmitted previous video data into YUV color space format and transmit the YUV data to a data buffer, wherein the PLD interfaces to the sensor memory and the data buffer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the data buffer is adapted to receive and store the YUV data until it is completely received at a base unit memory without errors, wherein the data buffer is operably coupled to the sensor memory; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a camera physical transceiver adapted to transmit the stored YUV data to a base unit physical transceiver, wherein the camera physical transceiver is operably coupled to the data buffer via a data port; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the base unit includes:
<claim-text>the base unit physical transceiver adapted to receive the transmitted YUV data from the camera physical transceiver, wherein the base unit physical transceiver is operably coupled to the camera physical transceiver;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data buffer adapted to store the received YUV data from the base unit physical transceiver until it is completely received at the base unit physical transceiver without errors, wherein the data buffer is operably coupled to the base unit physical transceiver via a data port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the base unit memory adapted to sequentially store each line of the received YUV data, wherein the base unit memory is operably coupled to the data buffer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the camera data buffer is adapted to delete the YUV data when it is completely received at the base unit memory without errors.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A video transmission system comprising:
<claim-text>a camera including:
<claim-text>a sensor memory adapted to store previous video data and delete the stored previous video data when each line of the stored previous video data is sequentially transmitted;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sensor adapted to sequentially transmit the previous video data as RGB analog data, wherein the camera sensor comprises the sensor memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an A/D converter adapted to convert the RGB analog data into RGB digital data and transmit the RGB digital data to a data buffer, wherein the A/D converter interfaces to the sensor and the data buffer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the data buffer is adapted to receive and store the RGB digital data until it is completely received at a base unit memory without errors, wherein the data buffer is operably coupled to the sensor memory; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a camera physical transceiver adapted to transmit the stored RGB digital data to a base unit physical transceiver, wherein the camera physical transceiver is operably coupled to the data buffer via a data port; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the base unit includes:
<claim-text>the base unit physical transceiver adapted to receive the transmitted RGB digital data from the camera physical transceiver, wherein the base unit physical transceiver is operably coupled to the camera physical transceiver;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data buffer adapted to store the received RGB digital data from the base unit physical transceiver until it is completely received at the base unit physical transceiver without errors, wherein the data buffer is operably coupled to the base unit physical transceiver via a data port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the base unit memory adapted to sequentially store each line of the received RGB digital data, wherein the base unit memory is operably coupled to the data buffer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The video transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref>, wherein the camera data buffer is adapted to delete the RGB digital data when it is completely received at the base unit memory without errors.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
