<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299340-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299340</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10774775</doc-number>
<date>20040209</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2003-0008795</doc-number>
<date>20030212</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>320</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>28</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>712 35</main-classification>
<further-classification>712 34</further-classification>
<further-classification>711130</further-classification>
<further-classification>711120</further-classification>
<further-classification>711119</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Data processing device having selective data cache architecture and computer system including the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5686960</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sussman et al.</name>
<date>19971100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3482181</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6170049</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>So</name>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>712 35</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6279489</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Daniel</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>108 92</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6369855</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Chauvel et al.</name>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3484231</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0160637</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Tuli</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>358  115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>25</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040162944</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040819</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kim</last-name>
<first-name>Yun-Hwan</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yongin-shi</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Joong-Eon</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sungnam-shi</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lim</last-name>
<first-name>Kyoung-Mook</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yongin-shi</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>F. Chau &amp; Associates, LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung Electronics., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Peikari</last-name>
<first-name>B. James</first-name>
<department>2189</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The disclosure is a data processing device with selective data cache architecture and a computer system including the data processing device. The data processing device is comprised of a microprocessor, a coprocessor, a microprocessor data cache, an X-data cache, and a Y-data cache. The microprocessor fetches and executes instructions, and the coprocessor carries out digital signal processing functions. The microprocessor data cache stores data provided from the microprocessor. The X-data cache stores a first group of data provided from the coprocessor while the Y-data cache stores a second group of data provided from the coprocessor.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="118.53mm" wi="243.08mm" file="US07299340-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="224.79mm" wi="170.10mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299340-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="245.96mm" wi="141.31mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299340-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="247.23mm" wi="148.76mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299340-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention generally relates to computer systems and, more specifically, to a data processing device with selective data cache architecture in a computer system.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Discussion of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Computer systems perform various functions with sophisticated processors at high speed. The efficiencies in the computer systems are associated with the performance of memories embedded therein. Cache memories employed in the computer systems contribute to managing program information and need to be operable at higher speeds in order to enhance overall performance of the computer systems.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Multiple kinds of cache memories have been proposed with various functional structures to improve performance in correspondence with arising needs of various and complicated functions in computer systems. These cache memories include, for example, cache memories independently assigned to instructions and data, parallel cache memories for accelerating memory access times, and different-sized cache memories with hierarchical structures. Such cache memories typically operate with processing units or execution parts to access other caches.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The trends in constructing the computer systems are rapidly going to system-on-chip (SOC) architecture in which system components, such as processors, cache memories, peripheral devices, and bus interface units, are integrated as a single chip. The SOC architecture is regarded as a small computer system. Typically SOC's have two or more built-in processors: one microprocessor controls overall operations thereof; another microprocessor is a coprocessor, e.g., DSP (digital signal processor) for managing data processing operations. The DSP carries out data multiplication and accumulation, read and write operations for one or more memories, and operations for incrementing address pointer registers.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The microprocessor and the DSP independently access cache memories separately assigned to them according to address locations of external memory data. Such a separate cache system may increase the whole cache memory capacity and the occupation area in the SOC.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">A data processing device manages an efficient cache memory capacity.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A data processing device is capable of being efficiently operable with cache memories in a small chip area.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A computer system comprises a data processing device occupying a small circuit area, wherein the computer system manages an efficient cache memory capacity.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to an embodiment of the present invention, a data processing device comprises a microprocessor (MCU) for fetching and executing an instruction, a coprocessor for storing data managed by the microprocessor, and an MCU data cache for storing data managed by the microprocessor. The data processing device further comprising an X-data cache for storing a first data group managed by the coprocessor, and a Y-data cache for storing a second data group managed by the coprocessor.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The data processing device further comprises an MCU data cache for storing data managed by the microprocessor.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to an embodiment of the present invention, a computer system comprises a system bus, a host processor for receiving, decoding, and executing instructions, an arbiter for controlling priorities for accessing the system bus, a data processing unit for performing digital signal processing operations subject to the host processor, and an external memory for storing data managed by the data processing unit. The data processing unit comprises a microprocessor (MCU) for fetching and executing an instruction, a coprocessor for storing data managed by the microprocessor, an X-data cache for storing a first data group managed by the coprocessor, and a Y-data cache for storing a second data group managed by the coprocessor. The computer system of the invention further comprises an MCU data cache for storing data managed by the microprocessor.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The present invention will be better understood from the following detailed description of exemplary embodiments thereof taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, and its scope will be pointed out in the appended claims.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In the accompanying drawings in like reference characters refer to the same parts throughout the different views. The drawings are not necessarily to scale, emphasis is instead being placed upon illustrating principles of the invention:</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram illustrating a functional structure of a computer system according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating functional structures of the masters shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram illustrating other functional structures of the masters shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">It should be understood that the description of preferred embodiments is merely illustrative and that it should not be taken in a limiting sense. In the following detailed description, several specific details are set forth in order to provide a thorough understanding of the present invention. It will be obvious, however, to one skilled in the art that the present invention may be practiced without these specific details.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a functional structure of a computer system according to an embodiment of the present invention. The computer system comprises a SOC <b>100</b> and an external memory <b>160</b>. The SOC <b>100</b> comprises a host processor <b>110</b>, an arbiter <b>112</b>, a decoder <b>114</b>, masters <b>120</b>, <b>122</b>, and <b>124</b> (<b>120</b>˜<b>124</b>), a bus bridge <b>126</b>, slaves <b>130</b>, <b>132</b>, and <b>134</b> (<b>130</b>˜<b>134</b>), and buses <b>140</b> and <b>150</b>. The host processor <b>110</b> is, for example, a CPU receiving and decoding a sequence of instructions to conduct various operations in accordance with the instructions. The arbiter <b>112</b> monitors bus access requested by the peripheral devices and determines a bus priority order among current bus access, arranging the order of access to the buses <b>140</b> and <b>150</b>. The decoder <b>114</b> maps addresses stored in address registers of the masters and slaves to select the masters <b>120</b>˜<b>124</b> and the slaves <b>130</b>˜<b>134</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The masters <b>120</b>˜<b>124</b> are data processing devices, each comprising a microprocessor (MCU), a coprocessor such a DSP, and cache memories.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The bus bridge <b>126</b> connects the main bus <b>140</b> to the extension bus <b>150</b>. The extension bus <b>150</b> is a fast bus extendible to a substantially infinite range by means of a daisy chain pattern. The slaves <b>130</b>˜<b>134</b> are devices to be added according to the needs of a user, including, for example, a storage extension module, a video control extension module, a multimedia extension module, and a communication extension module. The storage extension module is adaptable to, for example, hard disks, DVDs, and CDs, and the video control extension module is adaptable to LCDs, CRT monitors, and new-generation display devices and the like. The multimedia extension module is adaptable to sound cards, television reception cards, MPEG devices, etc. The communication extension module is adaptable to, for example, networks, modems, and super data-rate communication networks.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the masters <b>120</b>˜<b>124</b> comprise an MCU <b>202</b>, a DSP coprocessor <b>204</b>, an MCU data cache <b>212</b>, an X-data cache <b>214</b>, and Y-data cache <b>216</b>. The MCU <b>202</b> carries out arithmetic functions with integers or with floating points, and Boolean operations, and performs address conversion. The MCU <b>202</b> comprises an instruction fetch unit (IFU), an instruction execution unit (IEU), and a cache control unit.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The instruction fetch unit fetches an instruction, buffers an instruction deferred by the instruction execution unit, and performs an arithmetic operation with a virtual address to be used for fetching the next instruction. The instruction is fetched from an instruction cache of the cache control unit by the instruction fetch unit. The virtual address for the instruction to be fetched is transferred to the instruction cache by way of interpretation to a physical address.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The instruction execution unit stores and searches data of a data cache provided in the cache control unit. The instruction execution unit converts a virtual data address to a physical address adaptable to the cache control unit, which secures a loading/storing operation to be active in a valid order of program stream. The cache control unit determines whether a request defined by a physical address of data is acceptable to the instruction cache or the data cache. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates an example of a data cache in the cache data unit.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The DSP coprocessor <b>204</b> comprises an execution part having at least one arithmetic logic unit (ALU) coupled to a multiplier for executing a mathematically algorithm with pipe-lined. The DSP coprocessor <b>204</b> is mainly assigned to conduct mathematical operations, processes multimedia functions such as video, audio, video capture and play-back, telephone communication, voice identification and synthesis, and communication. Such DSP functions are invoked with micro-coded patterns by the host processor (e.g., the CPU <b>110</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). The micro-coded kernels comprise FIR (finite impulse response) and IIR (infinite impulse response) filters, FFTs (Fourier transforms), correlation functions, matrix multiplication, and Taylor series functions.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The correlation function among the DSP abilities includes X- and Y-vectors. The X-vector is stored in the X-data cache <b>214</b> and the Y-vector is stored in the Y-data cache <b>216</b>. The X- and Y-data caches, <b>214</b> and <b>216</b>, stores predetermined data of an application program without partitioning. The MCU <b>202</b> is accessible to the X-data cache <b>214</b> and the Y-data cache <b>216</b> as well as the MCU data cache <b>212</b>, wherein an amount of accessible cache available to the MCU is increased.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The external memory <b>160</b> is segmented into an MCU field <b>222</b>, an X-data field <b>224</b>, and a Y-data field <b>226</b>. The MCU field <b>222</b> is a memory field accessible to/from the MCU data cache <b>212</b>. The X-data field <b>224</b> is a memory field accessible to/from the X-data cache <b>214</b>. The Y-data field <b>226</b> is a memory field accessible to/from the Y-data cache <b>216</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates masters <b>120</b>′, <b>122</b>′, and <b>124</b>′ (hereinafter, <b>122</b>′˜<b>124</b>′) according to embodiment of the present invention. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the masters <b>120</b>′˜<b>124</b>′ comprises an MCU <b>302</b>, a DSP coprocessor <b>304</b>, an X-data cache <b>312</b>, and a Y-data cache <b>314</b>. The masters <b>120</b>′˜<b>124</b>′ do not include the MCU data cache <b>212</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The MCU <b>302</b> performs data transmission to/from the external memory <b>160</b> alternatively through the X-data cache <b>312</b> and the Y-data cache <b>314</b>. The external memory <b>160</b> comprises an X-data field <b>322</b>, an MCU field <b>323</b>, and a Y-data field <b>324</b>, which are segmented in the external memory <b>160</b>. The DSP coprocessor <b>304</b> also performs data transmission to/from the external memory <b>160</b> alternatively through the X-data cache <b>312</b> and the Y-data cache <b>314</b>. The X-data field <b>322</b>, the MCU field <b>323</b>, and the Y-data field <b>324</b> of the external memory <b>160</b> are accessible to the MCU <b>302</b> and data cache <b>314</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The Y-data cache <b>314</b> is accessible to the MCU <b>302</b> without the MCU data cache <b>212</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The MCU <b>302</b> accesses an alternative one of the X-data cache <b>312</b> and the Y-data cache <b>314</b>, or both the X- and Y-data caches. For example, if an application program operating in the DSP coprocessor <b>304</b> is using the X-data field of the external memory <b>160</b>, the MCU <b>302</b> selects the Y-data cache <b>314</b> and accesses the MCU data field <b>323</b> and the Y-data field of the external memory <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Therefore, the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> has a reduced a circuit area because the MCU data cache <b>212</b> is not employed therein.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Although preferred embodiments of the present invention have been disclosed for illustrative purposes, those skilled in the art will appreciate that various modifications, additions and substitutions are possible, without departing from the scope and spirit of the invention as described in the accompanying claims. For example, the masters may employ various types of caches, as well as the X- and Y-data caches, in accordance with operational characteristics of the DSP application programs.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A data processing device comprising:
<claim-text>a microprocessor for fetching and executing an instruction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coprocessor invoked by the microprocessor for processing data managed by the microprocessor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a microprocessor data cache for storing data managed by the microprocessor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an X-data cache for storing a first data group managed by the coprocessor of the data managed by the microprocessor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Y-data cache for storing a second data group managed by the coprocessor of the data managed by the microprocessor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the microprocessor conducts arithmetic operations for integers and floating points, and Boolean functions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the coprocessor executes a digital signal processor function operable with at least one of video, audio, video capture and play-back, telephone communication, voice identification and synthesis, and multimedia communication.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the digital signal processor function is micro-coded with at least one of finite impulse response and infinite impulse response filters, a Fourier transform, a correlation function, a matrix multiplication, and a Taylor series function.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A data processing device comprising:
<claim-text>a microprocessor for fetching and executing an instruction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coprocessor invoked by the microprocessor for processing data managed by the microprocessor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an X-data cache for storing a first data group managed by the coprocessor of the data managed by the microprocessor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Y-data cache for storing a second data group managed by the coprocessor of the data managed by the microprocessor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the microprocessor selects an alternative one of the X-data cache and the Y-data cache to store data managed by the microprocessor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the microprocessor conducts arithmetic operations for integers and floating points, and Boolean functions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the coprocessor executes a digital signal processor function operable with at least one of video, audio, video capture and play-back, telephone communication, voice identification and synthesis, and multimedia communication.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the digital signal processor function is micro-coded with at least one of finite impulse response and infinite impulse response filters, a Fourier transform, a correlation function, a matrix multiplication, and a Taylor series function.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising an external memory segmented into an X-data field for storing data of the X-data cache, a Y-data field for storing data of the Y-data cache, and a microprocessor data field accessible to the microprocessor via at least one of the X-data cache and the Y-data cache.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A computer system comprising:
<claim-text>a system bus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a host processor for receiving, decoding, and executing an instruction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an arbiter for controlling priorities for system bus access;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data processing unit for performing a digital signal processing operation subject to the host processor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an external memory for storing data managed by the data processing unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the data processing unit comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a microprocessor for fetching and executing an instruction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coprocessor invoked by the microprocessor for processing data managed by the microprocessor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a microprocessor data cache for storing data managed by the microprocessor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an X-data cache for storing a first data group managed by the coprocessor of the data managed by the microprocessor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Y-data cache for storing a second data group managed by the coprocessor of the data managed by the microprocessor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The computer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising a slave in accordance with a need of a user.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The computer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the slave comprises at least one of a storage extension module, a video control extension module, a multimedia extension module, and a communication extension module.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The computer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising a decoder for addressing the data processing unit and the slave.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The computer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the external memory comprises: a microprocessor data field for storing data to and/or from the microprocessor data cache; an X-data field for storing to and/or from the X-data cache; and a Y-data field for storing to and/or from the Y-data cache.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the microprocessor conducts arithmetic operations for integers and floating points, and Boolean functions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the coprocessor executes a digital signal processor function operable with at least one of video, audio, video capture and play-back, telephone communication, voice identification and synthesis, and multimedia communication.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the digital signal processor function is micro-coded with at least one of finite impulse response and infinite impulse response filters, a Fourier transform, a correlation function, a matrix multiplication, and a Taylor series function.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A computer system comprising:
<claim-text>a system bus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a host processor for receiving, decoding, and executing an instruction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an arbiter for controlling priorities for system bus access;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data processing unit for performing a digital signal processing operation subject to the host processor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an external memory for storing data managed by the data processing units;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the data processing unit comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a microprocessor for fetching and executing an instruction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coprocessor invoked by the microprocessor for processing data managed by the microprocessor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an X-data cache for storing a first data group managed by the coprocessor of the data managed by the microprocessor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Y-data cache for storing a second data group managed by the coprocessor of the data managed by the microprocessor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The computer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, further comprising a slave in accordance with a need of a user.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The computer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the slave comprises at least one of a storage extension module, a video control extension module, a multimedia extension module, and a communication extension module.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The computer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, further comprising a decoder for addressing the data processing unit and the slave.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The computer system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the external memory comprises:
<claim-text>a microprocessor data field for storing data to and/or from the microprocessor via at least one of the X-data cache and the Y-data cache;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an X-data field for storing to and/or from the X-data cache; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Y-data field for storing to and/or from the Y-data cache.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the microprocessor conducts arithmetic operations for integers and floating points, and Boolean functions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the coprocessor executes a digital signal processor function operable with at least one of video, audio, video capture and play-back, telephone communication, voice identification and synthesis, and multimedia communication.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The data processing device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref>, wherein the digital signal processor function is micro-coded with at least one of finite impulse response and infinite impulse response filters, a Fourier transform, a correlation function, a matrix multiplication, and a Taylor series function.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
