<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296502-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296502</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11512139</doc-number>
<date>20060830</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>25</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>23</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 811772</main-classification>
<further-classification> 811246</further-classification>
<further-classification> 811801</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Spanner with a bending section</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3832916</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schoeps</name>
<date>19740900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 81464</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4344340</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Erickson</name>
<date>19820800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 811772</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5295423</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mikic</name>
<date>19940300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 81438</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6427563</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Zurbuchen et al.</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 811771</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0160882</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Crow</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 811772</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 811772</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 8117785</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 811243</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 811246</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 81438</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 811761</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 811801</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 81185</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hsieh</last-name>
<first-name>Chih-Ching</first-name>
<address>
<street>235 Chung-Ho Box 8-24</street>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Shakeri</last-name>
<first-name>Hadi</first-name>
<department>3723</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A spanner with a bending section comprises a handle and a driving portion; and a bending connecting portion connected between the handle and the driving portion; the driving portion being installed with an engaging head; a front end of the engaging head having an engaging end; a periphery of the engaging head having a plurality of teeth for engaging the driving portion; a length L of each teeth being longer than a width W of the engaging end. The ratio of L/W is from 2 to 3. Preferably, the ratio is 2.5.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="139.45mm" wi="100.75mm" file="US07296502-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="169.33mm" wi="101.60mm" file="US07296502-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="139.87mm" wi="62.99mm" file="US07296502-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="220.98mm" wi="172.64mm" file="US07296502-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to spanners, in particular to a spanner with a bending section, which has a firm structure so that the driving portion of the spanner can be inserted into a deep place for driving a screw easily and conveniently.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Form the screws locking the tire rim to a wheel disk, the bending spanner is used to drive the screw. This is because the screws are embedded into recesses. The surface of the tire rim is not flat so that the general used spanner is not suitable for driving the screws to lock a tire.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A bending spanner has a handle and a driving portion. A connecting portion serves to connect the handle and the driving portion. The driving portion has an engaging head. The engaging head has an engaging end for receiving a sleeve. The connecting portion cause that the driving portion is inclined to the handle. The engaging head has teeth for engaging the driving portion. In the prior art, the recess for embedding a screw is too deep, the driving portion can not be sufficiently inserted into the recess for driving the screw. As a result, the nut cannot be tightly engaged.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Moreover, in driving the nut, a react force is applied to the spanner and thus the engaging head will be damaged if it is used for a long time. If the engaging head is too long, it is possible that the engaging head will deform or damages so as to affect the lifetime of the product.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Accordingly, the primary object of the present invention is to provide a spanner with a bending section, which has a firm structure so that the driving portion of the spanner can be inserted into a deep place for driving a screw easily and conveniently.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">To achieve above objects, the present invention provides a spanner with a bending section which comprises a handle and a driving portion; and a bending connecting portion connected between the handle and the driving portion; the driving portion being installed with an engaging head; a front end of the engaging head having an engaging end; a periphery of the engaging head having a plurality of teeth for engaging the driving portion; a length L of each teeth being longer than a width W of the engaging end. The ratio of L/W is from 2 to 3. Preferably, the ratio is 2.5.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The various objects and advantages of the present invention will be more readily understood from the following detailed description when read in conjunction with the appended drawing.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic cross sectional view of spanner with a bending section of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic view showing the ratio of the teeth and the engaging end of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic view showing the use of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In order that those skilled in the art can further understand the present invention, a description will be described in the following in details. However, these descriptions and the appended drawings are only used to cause those skilled in the art to understand the objects, features, and characteristics of the present invention, but not to be used to confine the scope and spirit of the present invention defined in the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the structure of the present invention is illustrated. The present invention has the following elements.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A spanner body <b>1</b> has a handle <b>11</b>. One end of the handle <b>11</b> is connected to one end of a bending connecting portion <b>12</b> and another end thereof is connected to a driving portion <b>13</b>. An axial line of the handle <b>11</b> is not parallel to an axial line of the driving portion <b>13</b>. The driving portion <b>13</b> is engaged with an engaging head <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The engaging head <b>14</b> is a long rod which can be received in the driving portion <b>13</b>. A plurality of buckling teeth <b>141</b> are axially formed on the engaging head <b>14</b> for embedding into the driving portion <b>13</b>. A front end of the engaging head <b>14</b> has an engaging end <b>142</b> which is a rectangular block. An elastic buckle <b>143</b> is installed on the engaging end <b>142</b> for positioning a sleeve. A bending angle connected between the handle <b>11</b> and the driving portion <b>13</b> is an obtuse angle. A threaded post protruded from an end portion of the engaging head <b>14</b> for screwing to the handle <b>11</b>; and the teeth <b>141</b> of the engaging end <b>14</b> is at an end near the handle <b>11</b> after assembling the engaging head <b>14</b> of the handle. An elastic buckle <b>143</b> is installed on the engaging end <b>142</b> for positioning a sleeve; and the driving portion <b>13</b> encloses the engaging head <b>14</b>. A front end of the engaging head <b>14</b> has a tapered portion for connecting the engaging end <b>142</b> and a width of the engaging end <b>142</b> is smaller than a width of the engaging head <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a length of a tooth <b>141</b> of the engaging head <b>14</b> is L. A length of a side of the rectangular engaging end <b>142</b> is W. Preferably, the ratio of L/W is from 2 to 3 so as to provide a firm structure, especially in use. A more preferably structure, the ratio of L/W is 2.5.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In the present invention, the length of the teeth <b>141</b> of the engaging end <b>142</b> is related to the structure of the engaging end <b>142</b>. The larger the engaging end <b>142</b>, the greater the nut to be driven. Thus a great driving force is necessary. To increase the length L of the teeth <b>141</b>, the engaging head <b>14</b> will be firm secured to the driving portion <b>13</b>. The above ratio of engaging head <b>14</b> and teeth <b>141</b>, the driving portion <b>13</b> has a firm structure.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the driving portion <b>13</b> with the engaging head <b>14</b> having a set ratio in the structure provides a strong force to screw a nut. Thus the driving portion <b>13</b> will not deform due to the lengths of the engaging head <b>14</b> and the teeth <b>141</b>. Furthermore, the engaging head <b>14</b> can be inserted into a deep place due to a proper length thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The present invention is thus described, it will be obvious that the same may be varied in many ways. Such variations are not to be regarded as a departure from the spirit and scope of the present invention, and all such modifications as would be obvious to one skilled in the art are intended to be included within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A spanner with a bending section comprising a handle and a driving portion; and a bending connecting portion connected between the handle and the driving portion; the driving portion being installed with an engaging head; a front end of the engaging head having an engaging end; a periphery of the engaging head distal from the engaging end having a plurality of teeth for engaging the driving portion; a length L of each teeth being longer than a width W of the engaging end; and
<claim-text>wherein a bending angle connected between the handle and the driving portion is an obtuse angle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein an elastic buckle is installed on the engaging end for positioning a sleeve;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the driving portion encloses the engaging head;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a front end of the engaging head has a tapered portion for connecting the engaging end and a width of the engaging end is smaller than a width of the engaging head; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a threaded post is protruded from an end portion of the engaging head for screwing to the handle; the teeth of the engaging head are at an end near the handle after assembling the engaging head of the handle; and the teeth of the engaging head are axially formed and embedded into the driving portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The spanner with a bending section as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the ratio of L/W is from 2 to 3.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The spanner with a bending section as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the ratio of L/W is 2.5.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
