<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296741-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296741</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11450684</doc-number>
<date>20060609</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235441</main-classification>
<further-classification>235439</further-classification>
<further-classification>235440</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Universal card reader</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5559315</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nair et al.</name>
<date>19960900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>235448</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6234389</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Valliani et al.</name>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>235380</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6738259</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Le et al.</name>
<date>20040500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361737</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6832281</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Jones et al.</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710301</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6835100</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Chen</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439630</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0033722</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Liu et al.</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439630</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0258243</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hsieh</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>235441</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0237539</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chang et al.</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>235441</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235441</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235439</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>12</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kao</last-name>
<first-name>Chuan-Chao</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hsin-Chu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Tung &amp; Associates</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Hsin-Chu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Michael G.</first-name>
<department>2876</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Savusdiphol</last-name>
<first-name>Paultep</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A universal card reader is disclosed. The universal car reader includes a housing having a card slot and a dynamic input area for a memory card provided in the card slot. A controller chip is connected to the dynamic input area for the reading and/or writing of data on the memory card.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="134.70mm" wi="114.98mm" file="US07296741-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="216.07mm" wi="144.70mm" file="US07296741-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="202.27mm" wi="109.98mm" file="US07296741-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="233.68mm" wi="118.87mm" file="US07296741-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="232.83mm" wi="130.39mm" file="US07296741-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="191.77mm" wi="123.87mm" file="US07296741-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="190.84mm" wi="112.44mm" file="US07296741-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to memory cards used to read and/or write data. More particularly, the present invention relates to a universal card reader which is capable of accommodating memory cards of various sizes and configurations and in various positions.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Flash memory provides convenience to the storage of data when data storage needs are single, independent or temporary. Flash memory cards eliminate the need to install a large capacity of memory when such capacity is not needed. Therefore, flash memory cards have recently become a common means of storing and managing data for a particular application.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">There exist multiple types of memory cards for use in various consumer electronic products such as PDAs (personal digital assistants), personal computers, digital cameras and MP3 players, for example. Each type of memory card requires a special card reader due to the various sizes, shapes and electronic interfaces of the cards. Therefore, a user must know the insert direction and orientation of a particular memory card in order to properly and precisely insert the memory card into a card reader.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Accordingly, a universal card reader is needed which is capable of accommodating a memory card of any size or configuration and in any orientation to properly match the memory card specifications to a read/write apparatus in order to read and/or write data on the memory card.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The present invention is generally directed to a universal card reader for a memory card. The universal card reader includes a housing having a card slot and a dynamic input area for a memory card provided in the card slot. A controller chip is connected to the dynamic input area for the reading and/or writing of data on the memory card.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The invention will now be described, by way of example, with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional view of an illustrative embodiment of the universal card reader according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a pin cavity, with a spring-loaded pin provided in the pin cavity, more particularly illustrating an electronic probe for detecting shifting of the pin in the pin cavity;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a pin cavity, with a spring-loaded pin provided in the pin cavity, more particularly illustrating a pressure sensor provided in the pin cavity for detecting shifting of the pin in the pin cavity;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a front view of the universal card reader;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a sectional view of a portion of the universal card reader, illustrating multiple lower vertical pins and multiple lower horizontal pins in top view;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a top view of the lower vertical pins in the universal card reader, illustrating a memory card inserted in the universal card reader and multiple lower vertical pins which together define the size and shape of the memory card displaced in the respective pin cavities and the remaining pins extended from the respective pin cavities;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a top view of the lower vertical pins in the universal card reader, illustrating a memory card inserted in the universal card reader and shown in a shifted configuration;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the universal card reader, illustrating partial insertion of a memory card having terminal electrical contacts into the universal card reader;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the universal card reader, illustrating complete insertion of a memory card having terminal electrical contacts into the universal card reader and further illustrating horizontal pins of the universal card reader disposed in contact with the terminal electrical contacts of the memory card;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the universal card reader, illustrating insertion of a memory card into the universal card reader and further illustrating a lower horizontal pin disposed in electrical contact with a bottom electrical contact provided on the bottom of the memory card; and</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is an enlarged sectional view illustrating the lower horizontal pin disposed in electrical contact with the bottom electrical contact provided on the bottom of the memory card.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Referring to the drawings, an illustrative embodiment of the universal card reader according to the present invention is generally indicated by reference numeral <b>1</b>. As will be hereinafter described, the universal card reader <b>1</b> is designed to accommodate memory cards of various size, configuration and design in any of various orientations to facilitate reading and/or writing data by a read/write apparatus (not shown). The universal card reader <b>1</b> includes a housing <b>2</b> having a card slot <b>3</b>. An array or matrix of multiple lower vertical pins <b>4</b> and multiple upper vertical pins <b>4</b><i>a </i>extend into the card slot <b>3</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref>, the lower vertical pins <b>4</b> and upper vertical pins <b>4</b><i>a </i>are preferably arranged in adjacent relationship to each other in a matrix of intersecting rows and columns.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>, each of the lower vertical pins <b>4</b> and upper vertical pins <b>4</b><i>a </i>is accommodated in a pin cavity <b>5</b> provided in the housing <b>2</b>. A spring <b>6</b> or other bias mechanism is provided in the pin cavity <b>5</b> and normally biases the lower vertical pin <b>4</b> or upper vertical pin <b>4</b><i>a </i>such that the pin extends from the corresponding pin cavity <b>5</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, an electronic probe <b>7</b> may be provided in the side of the pin cavity <b>5</b> and connected to a controller chip <b>15</b> typically by pin wiring <b>13</b> to sense the position of the lower vertical pin <b>4</b> or upper vertical pin <b>4</b><i>a </i>in the corresponding pin cavity <b>5</b>. Alternatively, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a pressure sensor <b>8</b> may be provided in the bottom of the pin cavity <b>5</b> and connected to the controller chip <b>15</b> by pin wiring <b>13</b> to sense the position of the lower vertical pin <b>4</b> or upper vertical pin <b>4</b><i>a </i>in the pin cavity <b>5</b>, depending on the pressure exerted by the spring <b>6</b> against the pressure sensor <b>8</b> as will be hereinafter described.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As further shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, multiple horizontal pins, such as multiple, adjacent lower horizontal pins <b>12</b> and upper horizontal pins <b>12</b><i>a</i>, for example, extend from the wall of the housing <b>2</b>, into the card slot <b>3</b>. Each of the lower horizontal pins <b>12</b> and upper horizontal pins <b>12</b><i>a </i>is typically seated in a corresponding pin cavity <b>5</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>) and extended therefrom by a spring <b>6</b> or other bias mechanism, as was heretofore described with respect to the lower vertical pins <b>4</b> and upper vertical pins <b>4</b><i>a</i>. The pin cavity <b>5</b> may be fitted with an electronic probe <b>7</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) or a pressure sensor <b>8</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) connected to the controller chip <b>15</b> typically by pin wiring <b>13</b>, as was heretofore described. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, a card ejection button <b>18</b> may be provided on the front of the housing <b>2</b> and connected to a card ejection mechanism <b>19</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>), according to the knowledge of those skilled in the art, to facilitate ejecting a memory card from the slot <b>3</b>, as will be hereinafter described. It will be understood that additional rows of horizontal pins, in addition to the lower horizontal pins <b>12</b> and the upper horizontal pins <b>12</b><i>a</i>, may be provided on the housing <b>2</b> and extend into the card slot <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Each of the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b> and <b>12</b><i>a </i>may have a generally cylindrical configuration. Alternatively, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8A</figref>, the tip of each of the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b> and <b>12</b><i>a </i>may have a generally conical configuration. Preferably, each pin <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b> and <b>12</b><i>a </i>has a length of from about 0.1 mm to about 10 mm and a width or diameter of from about 0.01 mm to about 2.0 mm. Each pin may be copper, steel, aluminum or other electrically conductive material.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-11</figref>, the card slot <b>3</b> is designed to accept a memory card <b>24</b> which may be an MMC (Multi-Media Card), an SD (Secure Digital) card, an SM (Smart Media) card, a CF (Compact Flash) card, an XD card or a Macrodrive card, for example. These different types of memory cards <b>24</b> vary in size and configuration, as well as the number and location of the electrical contacts <b>25</b> on the memory card <b>24</b>. For example, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, some types of memory cards <b>24</b> have electrical contacts <b>25</b> which are located on the end of the memory card <b>24</b>, whereas other types of memory cards <b>24</b> have electrical contacts <b>25</b> which are located on the lower surface, the upper surface or both the lower and upper surfaces of the memory card <b>24</b>. As it is pushed into the card slot <b>3</b>, the memory card <b>24</b> pushes the lower vertical pins <b>4</b> and the upper vertical pins <b>4</b><i>a </i>into the respective pin cavities <b>5</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>), against the bias imparted by each spring <b>6</b>. The remaining pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>which are not contacted by the memory card <b>24</b> remain extended from the respective pin cavities <b>5</b>, as indicated by the dark circles in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref>. Therefore, the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>which are pushed into the respective pin cavities <b>5</b> by the memory card <b>24</b> together correspond to the size, configuration and orientation of the memory card <b>24</b> in the card slot <b>3</b>, as indicated by the light-colored circles in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref>. The controller chip <b>15</b> is configured to sense the type of memory card <b>24</b> which is inserted in the card slot <b>3</b> by which of the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>are pressed into the respective pin cavities <b>5</b>. This is carried out by transmission of a signal from the electronic probe <b>7</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) or the pressure sensor <b>8</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) of each pressed pin <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>to the controller chip <b>15</b>. In the foregoing manner, the controller chip <b>15</b> uses the size and shape of the memory card <b>24</b> to determine the card type.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">When the card <b>24</b> is inserted in the card slot <b>3</b>, one or more of the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>contacts the electrical contacts <b>25</b> on the memory card <b>24</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref>, <b>7</b>, <b>10</b> and <b>11</b>. Alternatively, in the event that the electrical contacts <b>25</b> are located on the end of the memory card <b>24</b>, the lower horizontal pins <b>12</b> and/or upper horizontal pins <b>12</b><i>a </i>contact the electrical contacts <b>25</b> on the memory card <b>24</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. Therefore, based on the type of memory card <b>24</b> which was previously determined by the controller chip <b>15</b> to be in the card slot <b>3</b>, as was heretofore described, the controller chip <b>15</b> is capable of determining whichever of the lower vertical pins <b>4</b>, upper vertical pins <b>4</b><i>a</i>, lower horizontal pins <b>12</b> or upper horizontal pins <b>12</b><i>a </i>contacts the electrical contacts <b>25</b> and is to be used to read and/or write data on the memory card <b>24</b>. The controller chip <b>15</b> is further capable of configuring those single or grouped pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>or <b>12</b>, <b>12</b><i>a </i>as the single I/O for the read/write apparatus (not shown). Accordingly, the grouped pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>or <b>12</b>, <b>12</b><i>a </i>form a dynamic input area which contacts the electrical contacts <b>25</b> of the memory card <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">According to a typical mode of operation of the universal card reader <b>1</b>, a memory card <b>24</b> is inserted into the card slot <b>3</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. As it is pushed into the card slot <b>3</b>, the memory card <b>24</b> pushes against some of the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>into their respective pin cavities <b>5</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>) against the bias imparted by the springs <b>6</b> in the pin cavities <b>5</b>. The memory card <b>24</b> is pushed completely into the card slot <b>3</b> until the electrical contacts <b>25</b> on the end of the memory card <b>24</b> contact the respective pins <b>12</b>, <b>12</b><i>a </i>in the end of the card slot <b>3</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. Alternatively, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref>, <b>7</b>, <b>10</b> and <b>11</b>, in the event that the card's electrical contacts <b>25</b> are on one or both surfaces of the memory card <b>24</b>, one or more of the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>contacts the electrical contacts <b>25</b>. The springs <b>6</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>) in the respective pin cavities <b>5</b> push the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>against the respective surfaces of the memory card <b>24</b> to hold the memory card <b>24</b> in the card slot <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Based on the geometrical configuration defined by the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>which are contacted and pushed into their respective pin cavities <b>5</b> by the memory card <b>24</b>, the controller chip <b>15</b> identifies the particular type of memory card <b>24</b> which is inserted in the card slot <b>3</b>. For that particular type of memory card <b>24</b>, the controller chip <b>15</b> then determines which of the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b> and <b>12</b><i>a </i>forms the electronic connection point with the electrical contact or contacts <b>25</b> of the memory card <b>24</b>. Next, the electronic specifications of the memory card <b>24</b> are loaded from the memory card <b>24</b> to the controller chip <b>15</b>, and the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b> and <b>12</b><i>a </i>which form the electronic connection point with the memory card <b>24</b> are enabled to read and/or write data on the memory card <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">After the reading and/or writing of data on the memory card <b>24</b> is completed, the memory card <b>24</b> is ejected from the card slot <b>3</b>. This may be carried out by pushing the card ejection button <b>18</b>, thus causing the card ejection mechanism (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) to push the memory card <b>24</b> from the card slot <b>3</b>. Simultaneously, the springs <b>6</b> push the pins <b>4</b>, <b>4</b><i>a </i>from the respective pin openings <b>5</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, it will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that in the event that the memory card <b>3</b> is rotated or shifts in the card slot <b>3</b>, as in the case of an MMC (Multi-Media Card), the controller chip <b>15</b> is still capable of ascertaining the type of memory card <b>24</b> which is inserted in the card slot <b>3</b>. Furthermore, the universal card reader <b>1</b> need not utilize multiple card slots each of which is configured for a different memory card, since the card slot <b>3</b> is capable of accommodating memory cards of any size, type or configuration. Moreover, for those memory cards having an electrical contact on the upper and/or lower side of the card, a user need not insert the memory card <b>3</b> in the card slot <b>3</b> with the correct side facing up since either the lower vertical pins <b>4</b> or the upper vertical pins <b>4</b><i>a </i>can be used as the I/O for the read/write apparatus (not shown). Additionally, the card slot <b>3</b> may be sized in such a manner that two or more memory cards <b>24</b> may be simultaneously accommodated in the card slot <b>3</b> for the simultaneous reading and/or writing of data on the memory cards <b>24</b>. When incorporated into a notebook computer (not shown), PDA (not shown) or the like, the universal card reader <b>1</b> is capable of saving panel space by eliminating the need for multiple card slots capable of accommodating memory cards of various types. The controller chip <b>15</b> may be provided with the capability to recognize the specifications of various device formats such as USB, PCI, ISA, PCMCIA, FireWire, etc. and to convert signals between such devices and the universal card reader <b>1</b>, and an associated connection interface <b>16</b> for connection to the devices.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">While the preferred embodiments of the invention have been described above, it will be recognized and understood that various modifications can be made in the invention and the appended claims are intended to cover all such modifications which may fall within the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A universal card reader, comprising:
<claim-text>a housing having a card slot adapted to receive at least one memory card;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic input area comprising a plurality of sensors provided in said card slot, said plurality of sensors adapted to sense said at least one memory card within said card slot; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller chip connected to said dynamic input area, said controller chip adapted to determine said geometric shape and size of said memory card in response to said plurality of sensors, said controller chip further adapted to establish communication between said controller chip and said memory card based on said determined geometric shape and size of said memory card.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said controller is further adapted to determine said memory card type using said geometric shape and size of said memory card shape and memory card size, said controller chip further adapted to select a subset of said plurality of sensors to establish said communication.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said plurality of sensors comprises a plurality of biased pins carried by said housing and normally extending into said card slot.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein said plurality of biased pins comprises an electronic probe associated with each of said plurality of plurality of biased pins, said electronic probe adapted to sense movement of said biased pins, said electronic probe connected to said controller chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein said plurality of biased pins comprises a pressure sensor associated with each of said plurality of biased pins, said pressure sensor adapted to sense movement of said biased pins, said pressure sensor connected to said controller chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein each of said plurality of pins has a generally cylindrical shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein each of said plurality of pins has a generally conical shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein each of said plurality of pins has a length of about 0.1 mm to about 10 mm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein each of said plurality of pins has a width of about 0.01 mm to about 2 mm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a card ejection mechanism carried by said housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> further comprising an ejection button carried by said housing and connected to said card ejection mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a device connection interface carried by said controller chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A universal card reader, comprising:
<claim-text>a housing having a card slot adapted to receive at least one memory card;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic input area provided in said card slot, said dynamic input area comprising a plurality of upwardly-biased lower vertical pins and a plurality of downwardly-biased upper vertical pins carried by said housing, said dynamic input area adapted to sense movement of said biased vertical pins in response to said at least one memory card within said card slot; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller chip connected to said dynamic input area, said controller chip adapted to determine said geometric shape and size of said memory card, said controller chip further adapted to select a subset of said plurality of biased vertical pins to establish communication between said controller chip and said memory card.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising a plurality of pin cavities provided in said housing and wherein said plurality of lower vertical pins and said plurality of upper vertical pins are provided in said plurality of pin cavities, respectively.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising an electronic probe associated with each of said plurality of pin cavities, said electronic probe adapted to sense the presence of a compressed pin, said electronic probe connected to said controller chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising a pressure sensor provided in each of said pin cavities, said pressure sensor adapted to sense the presence of a compressed pin, said pressure sensor connected to said controller chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The universal card reader of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising a plurality of biased horizontal pins carried by said housing and extending into said card slot.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method of reading and writing a memory card, comprising:
<claim-text>providing a plurality of biased pins;</claim-text>
<claim-text>compressing multiple ones of said plurality of pins by said memory card;</claim-text>
<claim-text>grouping multiple ones of said plurality of pins into a single input for said memory card;</claim-text>
<claim-text>determining a type of said memory card using a geometric shape and size of compressed ones of said plurality of pins; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>reading and writing said memory card.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein said grouping multiple ones of said plurality of pins into a single input comprises grouping said plurality of pins into a single input on one side of said memory card.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein said grouping multiple ones of said plurality of pins into a single input comprises grouping said plurality of pins into a single input on one end of said memory card.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
