<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296972-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296972</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11293461</doc-number>
<date>20051202</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>67</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>18</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 97R</main-classification>
<further-classification>416 92</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Turbine airfoil with counter-flow serpentine channels</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4753575</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Levengood et al.</name>
<date>19880600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4767268</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Auxier et al.</name>
<date>19880800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5387085</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Thomas, Jr, et al.</name>
<date>19950200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5873695</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Takeishi et al.</name>
<date>19990200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>415115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6099252</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Manning et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6126396</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Doughty et al.</name>
<date>20001000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6164914</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Correia et al.</name>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>416 97 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6220817</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Durgin et al.</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6517312</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Jones et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6672836</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Merry</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>416 97 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6705836</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Bourriaud et al.</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6832889</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lee et al.</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0044278</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Eneau et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0076519</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Halfmann et al.</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0031445</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>McClelland</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>1065343</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00017">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003322003</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 96 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 97 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 92</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070128028</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070607</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Liang</last-name>
<first-name>George</first-name>
<address>
<city>Palm City</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Siemens Power Generation, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Orlando</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Ninh H.</first-name>
<department>3745</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A turbine airfoil usable in a turbine engine and having at least one cooling system. The cooling system may include a pressure side serpentine cooling channel and a suction side serpentine cooling channel. The cooling channels may be nested within each other to optimize heat exchange between the cooling fluids and the materials forming the airfoil, to reduce the amount of cooling fluids required, to reduce the required pressure of the cooling fluids, and to provide other benefits. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel may pass cooling fluids chordwise towards the trailing edge, and the suction side serpentine cooling channel may pass cooling fluids chordwise towards the leading edge.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="209.30mm" wi="141.56mm" file="US07296972-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="142.92mm" wi="146.56mm" file="US07296972-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="197.10mm" wi="109.39mm" file="US07296972-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="228.52mm" wi="155.28mm" file="US07296972-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="219.88mm" wi="143.85mm" file="US07296972-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="153.25mm" wi="156.13mm" file="US07296972-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention is directed generally to turbine airfoils, and more particularly to hollow turbine airfoils having cooling channels for passing fluids, such as air, to cool the airfoils.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Typically, gas turbine engines include a compressor for compressing air, a combustor for mixing the compressed air with fuel and igniting the mixture, and a turbine blade assembly for producing power. Combustors often operate at high temperatures that may exceed 2,500 degrees Fahrenheit. Typical turbine combustor configurations expose turbine vane and blade assemblies to these high temperatures. As a result, turbine vanes and blades must be made of materials capable of withstanding such high temperatures. In addition, turbine vanes and blades often contain cooling systems for prolonging the life of the vanes and blades and reducing the likelihood of failure as a result of excessive temperatures.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Typically, turbine airfoils are formed from an elongated portion having a tip at one end and a root coupled to a platform at an opposite end of the airfoil. The root is configured to be coupled to a disc. The airfoil is ordinarily composed of a leading edge, a trailing edge, a suction side, and a pressure side. The inner aspects of most turbine airfoils typically contain an intricate maze of cooling circuits forming a cooling system. The cooling circuits in the airfoils receive air from the compressor of the turbine engine and pass the air through film cooling channels throughout the airfoil. The cooling circuits often include multiple flow paths that are designed to maintain all aspects of the turbine airfoil at a relatively uniform temperature. At least some of the air passing through these cooling circuits is exhausted through orifices in the leading edge, trailing edge, suction side, and pressure side of the airfoil.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Many conventional turbine airfoils have cooling channels positioned at the leading and trailing edges and the outer walls. The airfoils often have a mid-chord cooling channel that may have a serpentine configuration or other design. Often times, the cooling channel is pressurized with cooling fluids to provide adequate cooling fluids to all portions of the cooling channels forming the cooling system in the airfoil. The walls forming the pressurized mid-chord cooling channel often remain at temperatures much lower than other portions of the airfoil in contact with hot combustion gases, thereby resulting in a large thermal gradient between these regions. The large thermal gradient often results in a reduced mechanical life cycle of airfoil components and poor thermal mechanical fatigue (TMF). Therefore, the inner cooling channel often negatively affects the life cycle of the airfoil. Thus, a need exists for a turbine airfoil having increased cooling efficiency for dissipating heat while reducing the thermal gradient between the cooling channels and the hot combustion gases.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows an external pressure profile for an airfoil. For a conventional five pass serpentine mid-chord cooling channel, cooling fluid is discharged on the pressure and suction sides. The pressure side of the airfoil has a higher external pressure than the suction side, and thereby is used to determine the pressure of the cooling fluid within the cooling system of the airfoil. In order to meet back flow margin criteria, a high cooling supply pressure is needed for this particular design, which results in a large leakage flow of cooling fluids. The second, third, and fourth passes of the serpentine cooling channel typically include film cooling holes for both the pressure and suction sides. In order to meet the back flow margin criteria for the pressure side film cooling holes, the pressure of the cooling fluid within the serpentine cooling channel is approximately ten percent higher than the pressure side external hot gas pressure. This results in over-pressurizing the suction side film cooling holes, which results in tremendous cooling system inefficiencies.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">This invention is directed to a turbine airfoil having a cooling system in inner aspects of the turbine airfoil for use in turbine engines. The cooling system may be used in any turbine blade. The cooling system may include a pressure side serpentine cooling channel nested with a suction side serpentine cooling channel and positioned within a mid-chord region of the airfoil. Nesting the pressure side serpentine cooling channel within the suction side serpentine cooling channel optimizes heat exchange between the cooling fluids and the materials forming the airfoil to reduce the amount of cooling fluids required, to reduce the required pressure of the cooling fluids, and to provide other benefits.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The turbine airfoil may be formed by a generally elongated airfoil formed from an outer wall, a leading edge, a trailing edge, a pressure side, a suction side, a tip at a first end, a root coupled to the airfoil at an end generally opposite to the first end for supporting the airfoil and for coupling the airfoil to a disc, and at least one cavity in the elongated airfoil forming a cooling system in the airfoil.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The cooling system may include a pressure side serpentine cooling channel and a suction side serpentine cooling channel. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel may be formed from a first outboard channel, a first inboard channel coupled to an outboard end of the first outboard channel and extending toward the root, and a second outboard channel coupled to an inboard end of the first inboard channel and extending toward the tip. The suction side serpentine cooling channel may be formed from a first outboard channel and a first inboard channel coupled to an outboard end of the first outboard channel and extending toward the root. The suction side serpentine cooling channel may also include a second outboard channel attached to an inboard end of the first inboard channel and extending toward the tip.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The first outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel may be positioned between the second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and the trailing edge of the airfoil. The first inboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel may be positioned between the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel. The second outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel may be positioned chordwise between the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and the first inboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel. In an alternative embodiment, the first outboard and first inboard channels of the suction side serpentine cooling channel may be positioned between the first outboard channel and the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The pressure side serpentine cooling channel may exhaust cooling fluids through film cooling orifices in the outer wall of the pressure side. The suction side serpentine cooling channel may exhaust cooling fluids through film cooling orifices in the outer wall of the suction side or an orifice extending between an outboard end of the second outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel and an outer surface of the tip, or both.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The cooling system may include at least one leading edge cooling channel extending generally spanwise in close proximity to the leading edge of the elongated airfoil. A plurality of impingement orifices may be positioned in a rib positioned in the at least one leading edge cooling channel. A plurality of trip strips may protrude from inner surfaces of the at least one leading edge cooling channel, and the suction side and pressure side serpentine cooling channels. The cooling system may also include at least one trailing edge cooling chamber extending generally spanwise in close proximity to the trailing edge of the elongated airfoil. The trailing edge cooling chamber may include a plurality of impingement orifices positioned in a first spanwise rib in the at least one trailing edge cooling channel and a plurality of impingement orifices in a second spanwise rib positioned between the first spanwise rib and the trailing edge of the elongated airfoil. The impingement orifices in the second rib may be offset spanwise from the impingement orifices in the first rib. The trailing edge cooling channel may also include a plurality of trip strips protruding from inner surfaces of the at least one leading edge cooling channel, and the suction side and pressure side serpentine cooling channels.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The cooling system may also include a cooling fluid supply chamber in the root of the elongated airfoil. An inboard end of the first outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and an inboard end of the first outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel may be coupled to the cooling fluid supply chamber. The cooling system may also include a central cooling fluid supply channel coupled to an inboard end of the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and an inboard end of the second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel. The central cooling fluid supply channel may separated from the cooling fluid supply channel by a plate that may or may not be removable.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">During use, cooling fluids may be passed into the cooling system in the turbine airfoil. In particular, the cooling fluids may be passed into the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and flow generally back and forth spanwise while flowing chordwise toward the trailing edge. A portion of the cooling fluids may also be passed into the suction side serpentine cooling channel that may pass cooling fluids back and forth spanwise while moving the fluids generally toward the leading edge. In this configuration, the cooling fluids move in a counter-flow relationship. It at least one embodiment, the pressure side and suction side serpentine cooling channels may extend from an inner surface of the pressure side to an inner surface of the suction side. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel may exhaust cooling fluids through the pressure side of the airfoil, and the suction side serpentine cooling channel may exhaust cooling fluids through the suction side of the airfoil.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">An advantage of this invention is that the pressure side serpentine cooling channel is tailored to account for the high temperatures encountered by the pressure side of the airfoil. By initiating the pressure side serpentine cooling channel proximate to the leading edge cooling channel, the pressure of cooling fluid supply may be reduced, which results in an overall reduction in cooling fluid leakage flow in the system.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Another advantage of this invention is that the cooling system is formed from four independent cooling channels, the leading edge and trailing edge cooling channel, and the pressure side and suction side serpentine cooling channels, all of which may be individually tailored for their independent cooling requirements and aerodynamic pressure requirements.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Yet another advantage is that having four independent cooling channels creates flexibility in the system to be adapted for different uses in the future.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Another advantage of this invention is that the separation of the pressure side and suction side serpentine cooling channels eliminates conventional mid-chord cooling fluid flow mal-distribution due to film cooling flow mal-distribution, film cooling hole size, mainstream cooling fluid pressure variation, back-flow margin (BFM), and high blowing ratio for the blade suction side film cooling holes.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Still another advantage of this invention is that the pressure side and suction side serpentine cooling channels eliminate the pressure differential that typically occurs in conventional cooling channel configurations between pressure and suction sides in a single channel.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Another advantage of this invention is that the counter-flow of cooling fluid between the pressure side and suction side serpentine cooling channels yields a more uniform temperature distribution for the airfoil mid-chord section.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">These and other embodiments are described in more detail below.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The accompanying drawings, which are incorporated in and form a part of the specification, illustrate embodiments of the presently disclosed invention and, together with the description, disclose the principles of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a graph of a pressure profile of the external pressure profile of a turbine airfoil having a conventional serpentine mid-chord cooling system.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of a turbine airfoil having features according to the instant invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the turbine airfoil shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> taken along channel line <b>3</b>-<b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic view of the cooling fluid flow through the cooling system of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross-sectional, filleted view of the turbine airfoil shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> taken along channel line <b>5</b>-<b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a graph of the pressure profile of the cooling system of an embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-6</figref>, this invention is directed to a turbine airfoil <b>10</b> having a cooling system <b>12</b> in inner aspects of the turbine airfoil <b>10</b> for use in turbine engines. The cooling system <b>12</b> may be used in any turbine blade. The cooling system <b>12</b> may include a suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> nested within a pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> and positioned within a mid-chord region <b>18</b> of the airfoil <b>10</b>. Nesting the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> within the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> optimizes heat exchange between the cooling fluids and the materials forming the airfoil <b>10</b>, reduces the amount of cooling fluids required, reduces the required pressure of the cooling fluids, and provides other benefits.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the turbine airfoil <b>10</b> may be formed from a generally elongated airfoil <b>20</b> having an outer surface <b>22</b> adapted for use, for example, in an axial flow turbine engine. Outer surface <b>22</b> of the outer wall <b>23</b> may have a generally concave shaped portion forming a pressure side <b>24</b> and a generally convex shaped portion forming a suction side <b>26</b>. The generally elongated airfoil <b>20</b> may be coupled to a root <b>28</b> at a platform <b>30</b>. The turbine airfoil <b>10</b> may be formed from conventional metals or other acceptable materials. The generally elongated airfoil <b>20</b> may extend from the root <b>28</b> to a tip <b>32</b> and include a leading edge <b>34</b> and trailing edge <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The airfoil <b>10</b> may include one or more leading edge cooling channels <b>38</b> extending generally spanwise in close proximity to the leading edge <b>34</b> of the airfoil <b>10</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The leading edge cooling channel <b>38</b> may extend from the root <b>28</b> to a position in close proximity to the tip <b>32</b> of the airfoil <b>10</b>. The leading edge cooling channel <b>38</b> is not limited to a particular configuration but may have any configuration necessary to cool the leading edge <b>34</b> and surrounding areas of the airfoil <b>10</b>. In at least one embodiment, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the leading edge cooling channel <b>38</b> may include a spanwise rib <b>48</b> having a plurality of impingement orifices <b>44</b> positioned to direct cooling fluids onto a back surface <b>46</b> of the leading edge <b>34</b>. A plurality of ribs <b>42</b> extending chordwise may create a plurality of cavities <b>50</b> in the leading edge cooling channel <b>38</b>. In at least one embodiment, the chordwise ribs <b>42</b> may create three cavities <b>50</b> in the leading edge cooling channel <b>38</b>. The leading edge cooling channel <b>38</b> may exhaust cooling fluids through an exhaust orifice <b>52</b> in the tip <b>32</b> and through film cooling orifices <b>54</b> in the leading edge <b>34</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The airfoil <b>10</b> may also include one or more trailing edge cooling channels <b>40</b> extending generally spanwise in close proximity to the trailing edge <b>36</b> of the airfoil <b>10</b>. The trailing edge cooling channel <b>40</b> may extend from the root <b>28</b> to a position in close proximity to the tip <b>32</b> of the airfoil <b>10</b>. The trailing edge cooling channel <b>40</b> is not limited to a particular configuration but may have any configuration necessary to cool the trailing edge <b>36</b> and surrounding areas of the airfoil <b>10</b>. In at least one embodiment, the trailing edge cooling channel <b>40</b> may include one or more spanwise ribs <b>56</b> having a plurality of impingement orifices <b>58</b>. In at least one embodiment, the trailing edge cooling channel <b>40</b> may include a plurality of spanwise ribs <b>56</b>, in which the impingement orifices <b>58</b> may be offset from orifices <b>59</b> in adjacent ribs <b>57</b> This configuration causes cooling fluids flowing through the impingement orifices <b>58</b> to impinge upon a downstream spanwise rib <b>56</b>. The trailing edge cooling channel <b>40</b> may exhaust cooling fluids through an exhaust orifice <b>60</b> in the tip <b>32</b> and through trailing edge exhaust orifices <b>62</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, may be nested with the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b>. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> may be attached to a cooling fluid supply chamber <b>64</b> positioned in the root <b>28</b>. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> may have a first outboard channel <b>66</b> extending generally spanwise from the cooling fluid supply chamber <b>64</b> toward the tip <b>32</b>. In at least one embodiment, the first outboard channel <b>66</b> may extend to within close proximity of the tip <b>32</b> of the airfoil <b>20</b>. The first outboard channel <b>66</b> may not include film cooling orifices <b>54</b>. Rather, the film cooling orifices <b>54</b> may be placed in downstream cooling channels. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> may include a first inboard channel <b>68</b> coupled to an outboard end <b>69</b> of the first outboard channel <b>66</b> and extending generally spanwise toward the root <b>28</b> of the airfoil <b>20</b>. In at least one embodiment, the first inboard channel <b>68</b> may extend into the root <b>28</b> of the airfoil <b>20</b>. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> may also include a second outboard channel <b>70</b> coupled to an inboard end <b>72</b> of the first inboard channel <b>68</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the first inboard channel <b>68</b> and the second outboard channel <b>70</b> may be coupled together at a central cooling fluid supply channel <b>74</b>. The central cooling fluid supply channel <b>74</b> is positioned generally within the root <b>28</b> of the airfoil <b>10</b>. The central cooling fluid supply channel <b>74</b> may be sealed in a closed condition with a plate <b>76</b>, which may or may not be removable. The second outboard channel <b>70</b> may extend generally spanwise toward the tip <b>32</b>. In at least one embodiment, the second outboard channel <b>70</b> may extend to within close proximity of the tip <b>32</b>. Cooling fluids passing through the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> may be exhausted through the film cooling orifices <b>54</b> in the second outboard channel <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The cooling system may also include the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b>. The suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> may include a first outboard channel <b>78</b> extending generally spanwise from the cooling fluid supply channel <b>64</b> toward the tip <b>32</b>. In at least one embodiment, the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> may extend to within close proximity of the tip <b>32</b>. The suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> may also include a first inboard channel <b>80</b> coupled to an outboard end <b>81</b> of the first outboard channel <b>78</b> and extending generally spanwise toward the root <b>30</b>. In at least one embodiment, the first inboard channel <b>80</b> may extend into the root <b>30</b>. The suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> may also include a second outboard channel <b>82</b> coupled to an inboard end <b>84</b> of the first inboard channel <b>80</b> and extending generally spanwise toward the tip <b>32</b>. In at least one embodiment, the second outboard channel <b>82</b> may extend to within close proximity of the tip <b>32</b>. An exhaust orifice <b>88</b> may extend between an outboard end <b>86</b> of the second outboard channel <b>82</b> and the tip <b>32</b> to exhaust cooling fluids from the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b>. Cooling fluids may also be exhausted through film cooling orifices <b>54</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In one embodiment, the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> may be nested with the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. More specifically, the second outboard channel <b>70</b> of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> may be positioned between the first outboard channel <b>78</b> of the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> and the first inboard channel <b>80</b> of the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b>. The suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> may be positioned such that the first inboard channel <b>80</b> and the second outboard channel <b>82</b> are positioned between the second outboard channel <b>70</b> of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> and the first inboard channel <b>68</b> of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b>. In an alternative embodiment, the first outboard and first inboard channels <b>78</b>, <b>80</b> of the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> are positioned between the first outboard channel <b>66</b> and the first inboard channel <b>68</b> of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">By configuring the pressure and suction side serpentine cooling channels <b>14</b>, <b>16</b> in this manner, the cooling fluid flowing through the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> travels in a chordwise direction from the leading edge <b>34</b> toward the trailing edge <b>36</b>. The cooling fluid flowing through the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> travels in a chordwise direction from the trailing edge <b>36</b> to the leading edge <b>34</b>. Thus, the cooling fluid flow through the pressure and suction side serpentine cooling channels <b>14</b>, <b>16</b> is a counter-flow of cooling fluids between the pressure and suction side serpentine cooling channels <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The cooling system <b>12</b> may also include a plurality of turbulence protrusions, such as trip strips <b>90</b>, extending from surfaces of the leading and trailing edge cooling channels <b>38</b>, <b>40</b> and from the pressure and suction side serpentine cooling channels <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>. The trip strips <b>90</b> may be positioned generally orthogonal to a general direction of fluid flow through the cooling channels <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, <b>38</b>, <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In at least one embodiment, the pressure side and suction side serpentine cooling channels <b>14</b>, <b>16</b> may extend from an inner surface of the pressure side <b>24</b> to an inner surface of the suction side <b>26</b>. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> may exhaust cooling fluids through the pressure side <b>24</b> of the airfoil, and the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b> may exhaust cooling fluids through the suction side <b>26</b> of the airfoil <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">During use, cooling fluids may be passed from the cooling fluid supply chamber <b>64</b> into the leading and trailing edge cooling channels <b>38</b>, <b>40</b>, the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b>, and the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b>. The cooling fluids may enter the leading edge cooling channel <b>38</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, pass through the impingement orifices <b>44</b>, and impinge on the back surface <b>46</b> of the leading edge <b>34</b>. The cooling fluids may then pass through exhaust orifice <b>52</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, or film cooling orifice <b>54</b>. Cooling fluids may also pass into the first outboard channel <b>66</b> of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b>, through the first inboard channel <b>68</b>, through the second outboard channel <b>70</b>, and may be exhausted through film cooling orifices <b>54</b>. The cooling fluids may flow generally toward the trailing edge <b>36</b>. Cooling fluids may also pass into the first outboard channel <b>78</b> of the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b>, through the first inboard channel <b>80</b>, through the second outboard channel <b>82</b>, and may be exhausted through film cooling orifices <b>54</b> and the exhaust orifice <b>88</b> in the tip <b>32</b>. The cooling fluids may flow generally toward the leading edge <b>34</b> in the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b>. The cooling fluids may enter the trailing edge cooling channel <b>40</b>, pass through the impingement orifices <b>58</b>, and be exhausted through the trailing edge exhaust orifices <b>62</b> or exhaust orifice <b>60</b> in the tip <b>32</b>. The cooling fluids flowing in this manner flow counter to each other in the pressure and suction side cooling channels <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> displays the pressure profile <b>92</b> of the external hot gases and the pressures of the cooling fluids flowing through the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> and a suction profile <b>94</b> of the cooling fluids flowing through the suction side serpentine cooling channel <b>16</b>. The graph displays how the invention customizes the pressures in the pressure and suction side serpentine cooling channels <b>14</b>, <b>16</b> to maximize the cooling fluid flow efficiencies. The cooling system <b>12</b> is designed based on the mainstream gas pressure distribution. The pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> begins proximate to the leading edge cooling channel <b>38</b>, where the mainstream gas pressure is relatively high. The pressure of the cooling fluids in the pressure side cooling channel <b>14</b> is slightly greater than the outside gas pressure to create a positive outflow margin (OFM). Because the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> does not exhaust cooling fluids from the first outboard channel <b>66</b>, the pressure of the cooling fluids in the first outboard channel <b>66</b> does not need to be as high as conventional pressures, which are about 10 percent greater than the mainstream gas pressure outside the turbine airfoil <b>10</b>. Rather, the pressure of the cooling fluids in the first outboard channel <b>66</b> may be about three percent greater than the mainstream gas pressure outside the turbine airfoil <b>10</b>. As the cooling fluids flow through sections of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel <b>14</b> downstream of the first outboard channel <b>66</b>, such as the first inboard channel <b>68</b> and second outboard channel <b>70</b>, the pressure of the cooling fluids is reduced due to resistance from turns and trips strips. However, the pressure of the mainstream gases outside of the turbine airfoil <b>10</b> are also reduced moving toward the trailing edge <b>36</b>, and thus enables the second outboard channel <b>70</b> to have a back flow margin (BFM) of about 10 percent. In contrast, a conventional serpentine cooling must establish a much higher pressure gradient initially in the first outboard channel in order to maintain a proper BFM in the downstream cooling channels. Thus, conventional designs are less efficient than the instant invention.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The foregoing is provided for purposes of illustrating, explaining, and describing embodiments of this invention. Modifications and adaptations to these embodiments will be apparent to those skilled in the art and may be made without departing from the scope or spirit of this invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A turbine airfoil, comprising:
<claim-text>a generally elongated airfoil formed from an outer wall, a leading edge, a trailing edge, a pressure side, a suction side, a tip at a first end, a root coupled to the airfoil at an end generally opposite the first end for supporting the airfoil and for coupling the airfoil to a disc, and at least one cavity in the elongated airfoil forming a cooling system in the airfoil;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the cooling system comprises a pressure side serpentine cooling channel formed from a first outboard channel, a first inboard channel coupled to an outboard end of the first outboard channel and extending toward the root, and a second outboard channel coupled to an inboard end of the first inboard channel and extending toward the tip;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a suction side serpentine cooling channel formed from a first outboard channel and a first inboard channel coupled to an outboard end of the first outboard channel and extending toward the root;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel is positioned between the second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and the trailing edge of the airfoil, and the first inboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel is positioned between the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein cooling fluids in the pressure side serpentine cooling channel flow in a general direction from the leading edge toward the trailing edge and cooling fluids in the suction side serpentine cooling channel flow in a general direction from the trailing edge toward the leading edge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a second outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel coupled to an inboard end of the first inboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel and extending toward the tip and positioned chordwise between the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and the first inboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising an orifice extending between an outboard end of the second outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel and the tip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising at least one leading edge cooling channel extending generally spanwise in close proximity to the leading edge of the elongated airfoil.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising a rib positioned in the at least one leading edge cooling channel having a plurality of impingement orifices.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising a plurality of trip strips protruding from inner surfaces of the at least one leading edge cooling channel, and the suction side and pressure side serpentine cooling channels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising at least one trailing edge cooling chamber extending generally spanwise in close proximity to the trailing edge of the elongated airfoil.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising a first spanwise rib in the at least one trailing edge cooling channel having a plurality of impingement orifices and a second spanwise rib positioned between the first spanwise rib and the trailing edge of the elongated airfoil having a plurality of impingement orifices, wherein the impingement orifices in the second rib are offset spanwise from the impingement orifices in the first rib.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising a plurality of trip strips protruding from inner surfaces of the at least one leading edge cooling channel, and the suction side and pressure side serpentine cooling channels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a cooling fluid supply chamber in the root of the elongated airfoil and wherein an inboard end of the first outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and an inboard end of the first outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel are coupled to the cooling fluid supply chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a central cooling fluid supply channel coupled to an inboard end of the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and an inboard end of the second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel, wherein the central cooling fluid supply channel is separated from the cooling fluid supply channel by a plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A turbine airfoil, comprising:
<claim-text>a generally elongated airfoil formed from an outer wall, a leading edge, a trailing edge, a pressure side, a suction side, a tip at a first end, a root coupled to the airfoil at an end generally opposite the first end for supporting the airfoil and for coupling the airfoil to a disc, and at least one cavity in the elongated airfoil forming a cooling system in the airfoil;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the cooling system comprises a pressure side serpentine cooling channel formed from a first outboard channel, a first inboard channel coupled to an outboard end of the first outboard channel and extending toward the root, and a second outboard channel coupled to an inboard end of the first inboard channel and extending toward the tip;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a suction side serpentine cooling channel formed from a first outboard channel, a first inboard channel coupled to an outboard end of the first outboard channel and extending toward the root, and a second outboard channel coupled to an inboard end of the first inboard channel and extending toward the tip of the elongated airfoil;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel is positioned between the second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and the trailing edge of the airfoil, and the first inboard channel and the second outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel are positioned between the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein cooling fluids in the pressure side serpentine cooling channel flow in a general direction from the leading edge toward the trailing edge and cooling fluids in the suction side serpentine cooling channel flow in a general direction from the trailing edge toward the leading edge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising an orifice extending between an outboard end of the second outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel and the tip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising at least one leading edge cooling channel extending generally spanwise in close proximity to the leading edge of the elongate airfoil with a plurality of impingement orifices positioned in a spanwise rib positioned in the at least one leading edge cooling channel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising a plurality of trip strips protruding from inner surfaces of the at least one leading edge cooling channel, and the suction side and pressure side serpentine cooling channels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising at least one trailing edge cooling chamber extending generally spanwise in close proximity to the trailing edge of the elongated airfoil having a plurality of impingement orifices positioned in a first spanwise rib in the at least one trailing edge cooling channel and a plurality of impingement orifices in a second spanwise rib positioned between the first spanwise rib and the trailing edge of the elongated airfoil, wherein the impingement orifices in the second rib are offset spanwise from the impingement orifices in the first rib.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, further comprising a plurality of trip strips protruding from inner surfaces of the at least one leading edge cooling channel, and the suction side and pressure side serpentine cooling channels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising a cooling fluid supply chamber in the root of the elongated airfoil and wherein an inboard end of the first outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and an inboard end of the first outboard channel of the suction side serpentine cooling channel are coupled to the cooling fluid supply chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The turbine airfoil of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising a central cooling fluid supply channel coupled to an inboard end of the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel and an inboard end of the second outboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel, wherein the central cooling fluid supply channel is separated from the cooling fluid supply channel by a plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A turbine airfoil, comprising:
<claim-text>a generally elongated airfoil formed from an outer wall, a leading edge, a trailing edge, a pressure side, a suction side, a tip at a first end, a root coupled to the airfoil at an end generally opposite the first end for supporting the airfoil and for coupling the airfoil to a disc, and at least one cavity in the elongated airfoil forming a cooling system in the airfoil;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the cooling system comprises a pressure side serpentine cooling channel formed from a first outboard channel and a first inboard channel coupled to an outboard end of the first outboard channel and extending toward the root;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a suction side serpentine cooling channel formed from a first outboard channel and a first inboard channel coupled to an outboard end of the first outboard channel and extending toward the root;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first outboard and first inboard channels of the suction side serpentine cooling channel are positioned between the first outboard channel and the first inboard channel of the pressure side serpentine cooling channel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein cooling fluids in the pressure side serpentine cooling channel flow in a general direction from the leading edge toward the trailing edge and cooling fluids in the suction side serpentine cooling channel flow in a general direction from the trailing edge toward the leading edge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
