<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296905-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296905</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11122781</doc-number>
<date>20050505</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>25</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>23</main-group>
<subgroup>18</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362119</main-classification>
<further-classification>362190</further-classification>
<further-classification>362287</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Power tool work light</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5541822</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bamber</name>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362190</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6565227</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Davis</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362119</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0157489</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Oomori et al.</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362119</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362109</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362119</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362190</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362253</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362287</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362269</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362648</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60568355</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040505</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060104053</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060518</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Etter</last-name>
<first-name>Mark A.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Humboldt</city>
<state>TN</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Stafford</last-name>
<first-name>Brent</first-name>
<address>
<city>McLemoresville</city>
<state>TN</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jani</last-name>
<first-name>Mehul R.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ayala</last-name>
<first-name>Adan</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yocum</last-name>
<first-name>Chares</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Black &amp; Decker Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Newark</city>
<state>DE</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Alavi</last-name>
<first-name>Ali</first-name>
<department>2875</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Dzierzynski</last-name>
<first-name>Evan</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A work light for a power tool. In an exemplary embodiment, the work light includes a generally cylindrical housing constructed for receiving a light source. The housing includes a pin generally transverse to the housing and unitary with such housing. Further, an electrical coupling is configured to provide electricity to the light source from a power tool electrical source and is integrated with the electrical source. Additionally, a bracket including a flange with a plurality of apertures for receiving a series of fasteners for mounting the bracket to an external surface of the power tool is included. The bracket defines a recessed structure for receiving the pin and includes a pair of recesses spaced apart to retain a first end of the pin and a second end of the pin. The pin included within the housing permits linear positioning of the housing along an axis generally perpendicular to the pin.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="108.71mm" wi="256.71mm" file="US07296905-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="249.09mm" wi="165.86mm" file="US07296905-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="258.15mm" wi="136.23mm" file="US07296905-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="174.24mm" wi="155.70mm" file="US07296905-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="271.19mm" wi="139.78mm" file="US07296905-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application claims the benefit under 35 U.S.C. § 119(e) of U.S. Provisional Application Ser. No. 60/568,355, filed May 5, 2004 which is herein incorporated by reference in its entirety.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to the field of power tools and particularly to a work light for power tools.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Often power tools are operated in areas which do not provide adequate over-head lighting. For example, a do-it-yourself woodworker often converts a portion of a garage into a home machine or woodworking shop. However, a typical garage includes little, if any, over-head lighting which causes the user to operate the machines without adequate lighting or to purchase additional light sources (e.g. halogen work lamps). The operation of machines without the proper lighting may lead to inferior positioning and thus, inferior work product. Further, the purchasing of additional light sources such as halogen work lamps is not only costly, but such sources generate large quantities of heat making the work environment non-conducive for long periods of work. Further, such light sources may not provide the light at a sufficient quantity to the desired area. Thus, additional solutions are necessary to address the need for adequate lighting during power tool operation.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Presently, the need for providing sufficient lighting to a given work area while operating a power tool has been addressed by integrating a work light within the power tool. Although the integration of a work light into a given power tool appeared to solve the problem of inadequate lighting to a specific work area, currently available integrated light systems are inadequate for several reasons. For example, the light source integrated into a drill press is typically recessed in the main body of the head assembly (included in the drill press) behind the drill press bit. Such positioning is disadvantageous for the light source projects light onto the drill bit causing a shadow of the drill bit to be cast upon a portion of the work area in need of illumination. The larger the size of bit, the larger shadow created. Further, such light sources are non-adjustable which prevents the user from directing the light to the desired work area.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Therefore, it would be desirable to provide a power tool with an integrated adjustable light source which supplies unobstructed light to a desired work area.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Accordingly, the present invention is directed to a work light for a power tool. The present work light may be implemented with a variety of power tools including a drill press, a scroll saw, a table saw, a band saw and the like. The work light of the instant invention provides a power tool with an integrated adjustable light source which supplies unobstructed light to a desired work area.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In accordance with a first aspect of the present invention, a work light for a power tool is provided. In an exemplary embodiment, the work light includes a housing constructed for receiving a light source. The housing may include a pin generally transverse to the housing. Further, in the embodiment, an electrical coupling is configured to provide electricity to the light source from a power tool electrical source. The electrical coupling may be configured to integrate with the power tool's electrical system. Additionally, the present embodiment includes a bracket for mounting the housing to an external surface of the power tool. The bracket defines a recessed structure for receiving the pin. Thus, the housing pin permits linear positioning of the housing along an axis generally perpendicular to the pin.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In a further aspect of the present invention, the pin is integral to the housing. In an embodiment, the bracket includes a cross member which contours at least partially for capturing a middle portion of the pin. Moreover, the recessed structure within the bracket may include a pair of recesses spaced apart to retain a first end of the pin and a second end of the pin. In further embodiments, a lens is coupled to the housing generally opposite of the pin for protecting the light source. Additionally, the housing may include an outer surface which is textured for aiding the user in manipulating the housing. For example, the outer surface of the housing may include a series of ribs.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In accordance with an additional aspect of the present invention, a work light for a power tool is provided. In an exemplary embodiment, the work light includes a generally cylindrical housing constructed for receiving a light source. The housing includes a pin generally transverse to the housing. Such pin is unitary with the housing. Further, an electrical coupling is configured to provide electricity to the light source from a power tool electrical source so that the electrical coupling integrates with the power tool electrical source. Additionally, a bracket for mounting the housing to an external surface of the power tool is included. The bracket includes a flange with a plurality of apertures for receiving a series of fasteners for mounting the bracket to the external surface of the power tool. Moreover, the bracket defines a recessed structure for receiving the pin. As such, the recessed structure within the bracket includes a pair of recesses spaced apart to retain a first end of the pin and a second end of the pin. In addition, the housing and bracket may be configured to allow incremental movement of the housing. For example, the pair of recesses as well as the first end and the second end of the pin may include teeth which assist the user in securing the work light housing in a desired orientation.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">It is to be understood that both the foregoing general description and the following detailed description are exemplary and explanatory only and are not necessarily restrictive of the invention as claimed. The accompanying drawings, which are incorporated in and constitute a part of the specification, illustrate an embodiment of the invention and together with the general description, serve to explain the principles of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The numerous advantages of the present invention may be better understood by those skilled in the art by reference to the accompanying figures in which:</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a partial isometric view of a drill press assembly in accordance with the present invention, wherein the drill press assembly includes a head assembly to which a work light is externally mounted;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is an isometric view of a work light in accordance with the present invention, wherein the work light includes a generally cylindrical shaped housing;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a bottom view of a work light in accordance with the present invention, wherein the work light includes an aperture for allowing airflow cooling of the light source;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevational view of a work light in accordance with the present invention, wherein the work light includes a housing pin which permits linear positioning of the housing along an axis generally perpendicular to the pin; and</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an exploded view of the work light illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, wherein the work light includes a bracket for mounting the work light to the drill press assembly.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Reference will now be made in detail to the presently preferred embodiments of the invention, examples of which are illustrated in the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a drill press assembly <b>100</b> including an externally mounted, integral work light in accordance with the present invention is provided. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, in an exemplary embodiment, the drill press assembly <b>100</b> includes a head assembly housing <b>102</b> for substantially enclosing a drill press head assembly. Further, a work light <b>104</b> is mounted to the head assembly housing <b>102</b> for providing light to a desired work area (e.g. a drill press table). In the present embodiment, the work light <b>104</b> is mounted behind the drill bit assembly <b>106</b> to prevent the work light <b>104</b> from interfering with the assembly <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, an exemplary embodiment of the work light <b>104</b> is described. In the present embodiment, the work light <b>104</b> includes a work light housing <b>108</b> constructed for receiving a light bulb <b>136</b> (e.g. an incandescent light bulb, a halogen light bulb, or the like). Alternatively, the work light housing <b>108</b> may be configured for other light emitting devices such as a light emitting diode (LED), multiple LEDS, or a combination of light sources may be utilized. In an embodiment, the work light housing <b>108</b> is generally conical or cylindrically shaped (such as with an enclosed end).</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In further exemplary embodiments, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, an aperture or series of apertures <b>110</b> may be included in the work light housing <b>108</b> adjacent a closed end to allow for airflow cooling of the light source. For example, a cylindrical work light housing may minimize intrusion into the area adjacent the working tool (e.g. a drill bit) while allowing for easy manipulation or positioning of the work light housing. In further embodiments, the work light housing <b>108</b> may include additional light emitting components such as a coherent light source. In the current embodiment, the work light housing <b>108</b> may be formed of a sufficiently rigid plastic, an impregnated plastic/composite material, or the like to prevent damage to the light source while permitting efficient molding or formation.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>, in an embodiment, the outer surface of the work light housing <b>108</b> may include a series of raised ribs <b>112</b>, surface texturing, or a surface coating for aiding a user in manipulating the work light housing <b>108</b>. In addition to assisting a user in manipulating the work light housing <b>108</b>, a gripping surface such as ribs or texturing allows for easy cleaning and minimizes dust collecting on the surface of the work light housing.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In an embodiment, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a pin or rod <b>116</b> is included on one end of the work light housing <b>108</b>. In such embodiment, the pin <b>116</b> is unitary with the work light housing <b>108</b> and extends transverse to the main body of the work light housing <b>108</b>. Forming the pin <b>116</b> unitary with the work light housing <b>108</b> may allow for simplified construction and minimize the number of components. In the foregoing manner, using the pin or rod <b>116</b>, the work light housing <b>108</b> may be swept or positioned at various orientations generally perpendicular to the pin <b>116</b> (when retained in a bracket, i.e., perpendicular to the longitudinal axis), so as to position the work light housing <b>108</b> with respect to the working tool (e.g. drill bit) as well as the desired work area (e.g. a drill press table or the like). See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In an additional embodiment, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 4</figref>, a lens <b>114</b> may be attached to the work light housing <b>108</b> generally opposite to the end of the work light housing <b>108</b> including the pin <b>116</b>. Such attachment may occur via a screw threading, a snap or compression fit, a retaining clip, or the like. The lens <b>114</b> may minimize dust collecting in the work light housing <b>108</b> to prevent the light source from being damaged or may be utilized to focus the projected/emitted light. In addition, a bezel may be included on the end of the work light housing <b>108</b> including the lens <b>114</b> for adjusting the lens allowing the light source to be focused.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, an exemplary embodiment of the work light <b>104</b> including a bracket <b>118</b> for mounting the work light <b>104</b> to the drill press assembly <b>100</b> is provided. In such embodiment, the bracket <b>118</b> is included for mounting the work light <b>104</b> to an external surface of the head assembly housing <b>104</b> of the drill press assembly <b>100</b>. In an embodiment, the bracket <b>118</b> includes a recess (e.g., a partial cylindrical recess or pocket) for capturing an end of the pin <b>116</b>. For example, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the bracket <b>118</b> includes a pair of recess structures denoted generally as <b>120</b> spaced sufficiently apart to retain a first end <b>122</b> and a second end <b>124</b> of the pin <b>116</b>, while providing sufficient distance between the recess/end wall of the recess to allow for insertion of the pin <b>116</b> into the bracket <b>118</b> during manufacturing or replacement (e.g., snap fitting).</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In additional exemplary embodiments, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the bracket <b>118</b> includes a cross member <b>126</b> which forms a contour <b>127</b> for capturing a middle portion <b>128</b> of the pin <b>116</b> (such as by including a corresponding concave structure for the pin). In an embodiment, the cross member <b>126</b> is formed so as to retain the pin <b>116</b> in a snap fit fashion. Further, the cross member <b>126</b> and/or end recess structures <b>120</b> may be configured to frictionally secure the pin <b>116</b> to ensure that the work light housing <b>108</b> is retained in the desired orientation.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In an exemplary embodiment, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the cross member <b>126</b> is unitary with the bracket <b>118</b>. In other embodiments, the cross member <b>126</b> may be retained against a power tool surface via an outer flange recess or the like. For example, in an embodiment, the work light <b>104</b> may be secured or mounted to the power tool via a series of fasteners such as screws extending through apertures <b>130</b> present within a flange <b>132</b> formed as part of the bracket <b>118</b>. Alternatively, the bracket <b>118</b> may be secured via adhesive, or include a magnet for coupling to a magnetically permeable material such as the steel head of a drill.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In the present embodiment, the bracket <b>118</b> is generally circular and may be formed so that the cross member <b>126</b> and end recess structures <b>120</b> are formed with a flat mounting surface. In additional embodiments, an elastomeric strip or corresponding teeth included on the bracket/pin may be utilized to assist in securing the housing in a desired orientation. As provided in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the presence of teeth on the pair of recesses <b>120</b> as well as the first end <b>122</b> and second end <b>124</b> of the pin <b>116</b> may allow a user to incrementally adjust the work light housing <b>108</b> to a desired orientation.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In further embodiments, an electrical coupling is configured to provide electricity to the light source from a drill press electrical source so to integrate the light source of the work light <b>104</b> with the drill press electrical source. For example, to “hard wire” the work light <b>104</b> to the drill press assembly <b>100</b> a stop may be included to prevent a power cord or wiring from becoming crimped or twisted during movement of the work light housing <b>108</b>. Additionally, corresponding contact plates or rings may be utilized to transfer power to the work light <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Although an exemplary embodiment of the present invention integrates the work light with an electrical source disposed within the power tool, it is contemplated that the work light may be powered by a battery such as by disposable batteries, a re-chargeable battery (such as implemented with a cordless power tool) or the like. It is further contemplated that the electricity may be provided to the work light via a standard electrical connection directly to an outlet (such as a wall outlet).</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, an exemplary embodiment of the work light <b>104</b> is provided which illustrates the linear positioning of the housing along an axis generally perpendicular to the pin. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the use of the pin or rod <b>116</b> allows a user to position the work light housing <b>108</b> at various orientations generally perpendicular to the pin <b>116</b> (when retained in a bracket, i.e., perpendicular to the longitudinal axis <b>134</b>). Such feature is advantageous for it allows the work light housing <b>108</b> to be positioned with respect to the working tool (e.g. drill bit) as well as the desired work area (e.g. drill press table <b>106</b> or the like). As previously mentioned, the positioning may be incremental by including teeth on the pair of recesses <b>120</b> as well as the first end <b>122</b> and second end <b>124</b> of the pin <b>116</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In a further exemplary embodiments of the present invention, an inner ring or disk mounting bracket may be utilized to allow for rotation of the work light housing <b>108</b> in addition to the previously described sweeping, linear motion of the work light housing <b>108</b>. For example, an outer ring having a flange or lip for holding the inner ring such that the inner ring may rotate. In such embodiment, a stop may be included to prevent a power cord or wiring from becoming crimped or twisted during movement of the work light housing.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Although the present disclosure focuses upon the use of the instant invention with a drill press, it is contemplated that the disclosed work light may be utilized with a variety of power tools including a scroll saw, a table saw, a band saw and the like without departing from the scope and spirit of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">It is believed that the present invention and many of its attendant advantages will be understood by the foregoing description, and it will be apparent that various changes may be made in the form, construction and arrangement of the components thereof without departing from the scope and spirit of the invention or without sacrificing all of its material advantages. The form herein before described being merely an explanatory embodiment thereof, it is the intention of the following claims to encompass and include such changes.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A work light for a power tool, comprising:
<claim-text>a generally cylindrical housing constructed for receiving a light source, the housing including a pin generally transverse to the housing, the pin being unitary with the housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electrical coupling configured to provide electricity to the light source from a power tool electrical source, the electrical coupling being configured to integrate with the power tool electrical source; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bracket being configured to mount the generally cylindrical housing to an external surface of the power tool, the bracket including a flange with a plurality of apertures for receiving a series of fasteners for mounting the bracket to the external surface of the power tool and the bracket defining a recessed structure for receiving the pin, the recessed structure within the bracket including a pair of spaced apart recesses to retain a first end of the pin and a second end of the pin,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the pin included within the housing permits linear positioning of the housing along an axis generally perpendicular to the pin.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The work light for a power tool as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the bracket includes a cross member which at least partially contours for capturing a middle portion of the pin.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The work light for a power tool as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a lens coupled to the housing generally opposite of the pin included within the housing for protecting the light source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The work light for a power tool as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the housing includes an outer surface which is at least partially textured for aiding the user in manipulating the housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The work light for a power tool as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the housing includes an outer surface defining a series of ribs.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The work light for a power tool as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the housing and bracket are configured to allow incremental movement of the housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The work light for a power tool as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the pair of recesses spaced apart recesses includes teeth; the first end of the pin and the second end of the pin include corresponding teeth which assist the user in securing the work light housing in a desired orientation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A drill press including a work light, comprising:
<claim-text>a head assembly housing for substantially enclosing a drill press head assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a work light mounted to the head assembly housing for providing light to a desired work area, the work area including a drill press table and the work light including:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a generally cylindrical work light housing constructed for receiving a light source, the work light housing including a pin generally transverse to the work light housing, the pin being unitary with the work light housing; an electrical coupling configured to provide electricity to the light source from a drill press electrical source, the electrical coupling being configured to integrate with the drill press electrical source; and a bracket for mounting the work light housing to an external surface of the head assembly housing, the bracket including a flange with a plurality of apertures for receiving a series of fasteners for mounting the bracket to the external surface of the head assembly housing and the bracket defining a recessed structure for receiving the pin, the recessed structure within the bracket including a pair of spaced apart recesses to retain a first end of the pin and a second end of the pin,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the pin included within the work light housing permits linear positioning of the work light housing along an axis generally perpendicular to the pin.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The drill press including a work light as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the bracket includes a cross member which at least partially contours for capturing a middle portion of the pin.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The drill press including a work light as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising a lens coupled to the work light housing generally opposite of the pin included within the work light housing for protecting the light source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The drill press including a work light as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the work light housing includes an outer surface which is at least partially textured for aiding the user in manipulating the work light housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The drill press including a work light as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the work light housing includes an outer surface defining a series of ribs.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The drill press including a work light as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the pair of spaced apart recesses include teeth; the first end of the pin and the second end of the pin include corresponding teeth which assist the user in securing the work light housing in a desired orientation.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
