<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297033-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297033</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11594771</doc-number>
<date>20061109</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-326891</doc-number>
<date>20051111</date>
</priority-claim>
<priority-claim sequence="02" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2006-146215</doc-number>
<date>20060526</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>502</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439701</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e79">Connector</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3701083</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ziegler, Jr.</name>
<date>19721000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439248</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5217386</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ohsumi et al.</name>
<date>19930600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439364</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5651683</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Shimamura et al.</name>
<date>19970700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439 34</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6354855</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Annequin</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439248</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>8-106949</doc-number>
<date>19960400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>2</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439701</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439247</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439248</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>17</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>21</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070111609</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070517</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sakamoto</last-name>
<first-name>Nobuyuki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shizuoka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nagayoshi</last-name>
<first-name>Tomihiko</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shizuoka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Kratz, Quintos &amp; Hanson, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Yazaki Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Dinh</last-name>
<first-name>Phuong</first-name>
<department>2839</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A connector for preventing a load from being applied to terminals, substrates, etc., after sub-connectors are fitted together. The connector has a plurality of first sub-connectors fixed to a substrate and a plurality of second sub-connectors paired with the corresponding first sub-connectors, and includes a male frame having a plurality of accommodating parts in which the second sub-connectors are separately accommodated so as to be freely movable and a female frame to which the male frame fits. The female frame accommodates the plurality of first sub-connectors such that the first sub-connectors are connected to the corresponding second sub-connectors. The connector further includes guide means for guiding each of the second sub-connectors into a connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connector.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="162.31mm" wi="217.93mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="218.69mm" wi="163.41mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297033-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="165.44mm" wi="151.05mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="120.82mm" wi="133.60mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="160.70mm" wi="106.34mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="225.21mm" wi="174.50mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297033-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="185.93mm" wi="145.63mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="102.02mm" wi="132.84mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="165.61mm" wi="161.71mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="149.86mm" wi="131.57mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="134.79mm" wi="161.12mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="197.95mm" wi="159.43mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297033-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="270.68mm" wi="150.54mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00013" num="00013">
<img id="EMI-D00013" he="171.45mm" wi="169.16mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297033-20071120-D00013.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00014" num="00014">
<img id="EMI-D00014" he="200.41mm" wi="177.72mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297033-20071120-D00014.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00015" num="00015">
<img id="EMI-D00015" he="176.11mm" wi="100.58mm" file="US07297033-20071120-D00015.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00016" num="00016">
<img id="EMI-D00016" he="213.78mm" wi="146.98mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297033-20071120-D00016.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00017" num="00017">
<img id="EMI-D00017" he="214.80mm" wi="147.49mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297033-20071120-D00017.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a connector, and in particular, to a connector that has a plurality of first sub-connectors fixed to a substrate and a plurality of second sub-connectors paired with the corresponding first sub-connectors.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">As a multipole connector having, for example, dozens of terminals, a division type connector is used in order to prevent terminal fittings from being inserted into wrong positions in the connector. Such a division type connector is divided into a female connector and a male connector. The female connector and the male connector are further divided into sub-connectors each of which being equipped with terminal fittings. The division type connector incorporates a pair of frames, one female and the other male. Defined in both the female and male frames are accommodating holes to accommodate the corresponding division sub-connectors.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Such sub-connectors are inserted into the accommodating holes of the corresponding frames and locked by a lance so as not to be disconnected from the frames. A lever having an arcuate cam groove is axially supported by one of the frames. A follower pin from which the other frame projects is axially supported in the cam groove. The lever is rotated to pull one frame into the other frame by the action of a lever rule accompanying this rotation, thereby simultaneously fitting the female sub-connectors and the corresponding male sub-connectors into their connections.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The connector described in Japanese Patent Application Laid-Open No. 8-106949 includes groups of female sub-connectors and groups of male sub-connectors paired with the corresponding groups of female sub-connectors. Each group of female sub-connectors and corresponding group of male sub-connectors forming a pair are accommodated in corresponding accommodating holes such that the female sub-connectors and male sub-connectors cannot move in a direction perpendicular to the direction in which both female and male frames are brought into close contact with each other. This makes it possible to fit together the female and male sub-connectors straight, thereby improving the reliability of electrical connections of female and male terminal fittings.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">However, where a positioning structure as in the connector described above uses a displacement spring or the like in order to fit the female and male sub-connectors into their connections, the pressing force of such a displacement spring is applied to the sub-connectors even after their connections. This pressing force results in a load on connection parts of the substrates of the sub-connectors, which is undesirable because the terminals or substrates of the sub-connectors may remain subject to a load even after their connections.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention has been made in view of the drawbacks discussed above. It is therefore an object of the invention to provide a connector that prevents a load from being applied on terminals, substrates, etc., after sub-connectors are fit into their connections.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In order to achieve the above object, according to one aspect of the present invention, there is provided a connector having a plurality of first sub-connectors fixed to a substrate and a plurality of second sub-connectors paired with the corresponding first sub-connectors. The connector includes a male frame having a plurality of accommodating parts in which the second sub-connectors are separately accommodated so as to be freely movable. The connector also includes a female frame to which the male frame fits into its connection, the female frame accommodating the plurality of first sub-connectors such that the first sub-connectors are connected to the corresponding second sub-connectors. The connector further includes guide means for guiding each of the second sub-connectors into a connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connector.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According to the connector, the male frame has the accommodating parts to separately accommodate the plurality of second sub-connectors such that the second sub-connectors are freely movable. The female frame, which fits into its connection to the male frame, accommodates the plurality of first sub-connectors that fit into their connections to the corresponding second sub-connectors. As the male frame and the female frame are fit together, each second sub-connector is guided into the connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connector by the guide means. Accordingly, even if there are variations in the terminals, etc., of each first sub-connector and corresponding second sub-connector, the second sub-connector, which is freely movable, is guided to the connected position relative to the first sub-connector. Thus, the first sub-connector and the second sub-connector are connected and held in position.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In the connector, the guide means includes arms which extend from each of the first sub-connectors toward the corresponding second sub-connector, and enter the male frame so as to come into contact with the second sub-connector. The guide means also includes abutting parts formed on each second sub-connector, each abutting part being adapted such that the corresponding arm can be brought into contact with the abutting part. The guide means further includes tapered parts formed on at least the arms or the abutting parts, each tapered part inclining such that when the male frame and the female frame are fit together, the first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector are guided into the connected position.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Accordingly, as the male frame and the female frame are fit together, the arms of each first sub-connector enter the male frame and come into contact with the abutting parts of the corresponding second sub-connector. Consequently, the first sub-connector and the second sub-connector are guided into the connected position by the tapered parts, so that the first and second sub-connectors are connected and held in position.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Further, the guide means includes a plate-formed guide part which extends from each first sub-connector toward the corresponding second sub-connector and enters the male frame so as to come into contact with the second sub-connector. The guide means also includes a guide hole defined in the corresponding second sub-connector. The guide hole receives the guide such that as the male frame and the female frame are fit together, the first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector are guided into the connected position.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Accordingly, as the male frame and the female frame are fit together, the guide part of each first sub-connector enters the corresponding guide hole of the male frame. Consequently, each first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector are guided to the connected position by the guide and the guide hole so that the first and second sub-connectors are connected and held in position.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In addition, each of the first sub-connectors has a plurality of terminals, and the male frame has through-holes into which the terminals of the first sub-connectors are inserted.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Accordingly, when the terminals of each first sub-connector enter the through-holes of the male frame, the first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector are guided into the connected position by the guide means, so that the first and second sub-connectors are connected and held in position.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In one advantageous arrangement of the connector of the invention, the male frame has the accommodating parts to separately accommodate the plurality of second sub-connectors such that the second sub-connectors are freely movable. The female frame, which fits into its connection to the male frame, accommodates the plurality of first sub-connectors that fit into their connections to the corresponding second sub-connectors. As the male frame and the female frame are fit together, each second sub-connector is guided into the connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connector by the guide means. Accordingly, even if there are variations in the terminals, etc., of each first sub-connector and corresponding second sub-connector, the second sub-connector, which is freely movable, is guided to the connected position relative to the first sub-connector. Thus, the first sub-connector and the second sub-connector are connected and held in position. Additionally, in the case where each first sub-connector or second sub-connector has terminals, the terminals have been formed by mechanical processes, the tolerance of which may result in variations in the leading ends of the terminals and variations in the terminal. However, since each accommodating part of the male frame accommodates the second sub-connector such that the second sub-connector is freely movable, the variations are absorbed such that the second sub-connector can be guided to the connected position. This eliminates the need to provide biasing means, such as a displacement spring, in order to connect and fix each first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector. As a consequence, a load is prevented from being generated on the terminals, substrates, etc. after connection of the first and second sub-connectors.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In another advantageous arrangement of the connector of the invention, the arms of each first sub-connector enter the male frame and come into contact with the abutting parts of the corresponding second sub-connector. Consequently, the first sub-connector and the second sub-connector are guided into the connected position by the tapered parts, so that the first and second sub-connectors are connected and held in position. Accordingly, even if there is an error in the shape of the second sub-connector, the tapered parts accept the error, thus assuring the guide part of the first and second sub-connectors into the connected position.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In another advantageous arrangement of the connector of the invention, as the male frame and the female frame are fit together, the guide part of each first sub-connector enters the corresponding guide hole of the male frame. Consequently, each first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector are guided to the connected position by the guide and the guide hole, so that the first and second sub-connectors are connected and held in position. Accordingly, even if an error occurs in the shape of the second sub-connector, the tapered parts accept the error, thus assuring the guide part of the first and second sub-connectors into the connected position.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In still another advantageous arrangement of the connector of the invention, the male frame has the through-holes into which the terminals of the plurality of first sub-connectors are inserted. This makes it possible to temporarily position the second sub-connectors relative to the corresponding first sub-connectors, thus making it easy to fit the connectors together.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an external view schematically showing an example of an outline of a connector according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded perspective view showing an example of one connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a partially broken view of the one connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an external view showing one example of a first sub-connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an exploded perspective view showing an example of a mating connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an external view showing an example of a second sub-connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a front view of the second sub-connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is an external view showing an example of a fitting part shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a sectional view taken along the line A-A indicated by the arrows in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a sectional view taken along the line B-B indicated by the arrows in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a schematic view for explaining the relations between the first sub-connectors and the second sub-connectors;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12A</figref> is a view for explaining an example of connection of the first sub-connector and the second sub-connector, and shows a state of each tapered part being in contact with an abutting part;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12B</figref> is the view for explaining the example of connection of the first sub-connector and the second sub-connector, and shows each tapered part sliding widthwise;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12C</figref> is the view for explaining the example of connection of the first sub-connector and the second sub-connector, and shows a state of each tapered part after slid;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a perspective view schematically showing an example of a first sub-connector and second sub-connector according to a second embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a view for explaining a state in which one connector and a mating connector according to the second embodiment start fitting together;</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is an enlarged view of an area indicated by P in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16A</figref> is a view for explaining an example of connection of the first sub-connector and second sub-connector being fit together, and schematically shows a state of the connection;</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16B</figref> is the view for explaining the example of connection of the first sub-connector and second sub-connector being fit together, and shows an enlarged view of an area indicated by M in (b);</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17A</figref> is a view for explaining an example of connection of the first sub-connector and second sub-connector fit into their connections, and schematically shows a state of the connection; and</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17B</figref> is the view for explaining the example of connection of the first sub-connector and second sub-connector fit into their connections, and shows an enlarged area indicated by M in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17A</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Now, embodiments of a connector according to the present invention will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 12</figref>.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">A connector <b>1</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> has one connector <b>10</b> (referred to as female connector) serving as a female frame, and a plurality of mating connectors <b>20</b> (referred to as male connector) serving as male frames which fit into their connections to the one female connector <b>10</b>. In the preferred embodiment, two male connectors <b>20</b> can be connected to the one connector <b>10</b>. However, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows only one male connector <b>20</b>, and the other one is not shown.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the female connector <b>10</b> includes: a substantially box-like housing <b>11</b> made of synthetic resin or the like; female fitting parts <b>12</b> which are defined in the housing <b>11</b> and into which the corresponding male connectors <b>20</b> fit; a plurality of first sub-connectors <b>13</b> (the five first sub-connectors <b>13</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) which are accommodated in the housing <b>11</b>; and a substrate <b>14</b> to which the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> are fixed.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The housing <b>11</b> has a fixing part (not shown) to which the substrate <b>14</b> is fixed. By fixing the substrate <b>14</b> to the fixing part, the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> are fixed in predetermined positions in the female fitting part <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> or <b>3</b>, each female fitting part <b>12</b> is made of synthetic resin or the like and extends from the housing <b>11</b>. The female fitting part <b>12</b> includes a peripheral wall <b>12</b>A, a plurality of fitting holes <b>12</b>B defined by the peripheral wall <b>12</b>A; a step <b>12</b>C formed on the internal face of the peripheral wall <b>12</b>A; and guide pieces <b>12</b>D formed in the fitting holes <b>12</b>B.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The peripheral wall <b>12</b>A is made of synthetic resin or the like so as to cover the end of the corresponding male connector <b>20</b> that fits in the female fitting part <b>12</b>. Namely, the peripheral wall <b>12</b>A is shaped to match the corresponding male connector <b>20</b>. Each of the fitting holes <b>12</b>B is shaped to match the outside of each of second sub-connectors (described below) <b>21</b> of the corresponding male connector <b>20</b>. In this preferred embodiment, the shapes of the three fitting holes <b>12</b>B are identical. However, if the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> are shaped differently, the shapes of the first fitting holes <b>12</b>B are also changed so as to match them.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The step <b>12</b>C extends inwards from the internal face of the peripheral wall <b>12</b>A by a predetermined length. By bringing the abutting parts of the male connector <b>20</b> into contact with the step <b>12</b>C, movement of the male connector <b>20</b> is restricted in the direction in which the male connector <b>20</b> is inserted. Each of the guide pieces <b>12</b>D extends between the sidewalls defining each fitting hole <b>12</b>B so as to cross each fitting hole <b>12</b>B widthwise. Each guide piece <b>12</b>D enters the corresponding sub-connector <b>21</b> of the male connector <b>10</b>, thereby blocking vertical movement (direction X in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) of the second sub-connector <b>21</b> and guiding the second sub-connector <b>21</b> in the direction (direction Y in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) of its insertion.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, each first sub-connector <b>13</b> includes: a connector base <b>13</b>A, a plurality of terminals <b>13</b>B extending from the connector base <b>13</b>A toward the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>; a pair of arms <b>13</b>C extending from both ends of the connector base <b>13</b>A toward the second sub-connector <b>21</b>; tapered parts <b>13</b>D formed on the arms <b>13</b>C; and engagement parts <b>13</b>E formed on both sidewalls of the connector base <b>13</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The connector base <b>13</b>A is substantially in the shape of a box and made of synthetic resin or the like. A plurality of terminals <b>13</b>B (described below) are attached to the connector base <b>13</b>A by means of insert molding, press fitting, or the like. Each of the terminals <b>13</b>B is of a metal plate material formed in a predetermined shape by means of punch molding or etching. Examples of the metal plate material include aluminum (Al), copper (Cu), a copper alloy such as Cu—Fe, Cu—Fe—P, Cu—Cr, Cu—Ni—Si, or Cu—Sn, a nickel-iron alloy such as Ni—Fe or Fe—Ni—Co, or a composite member of copper and stainless steel. These metals may be plated with nickel, silver, or gold.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">As for the arrangement of the terminals <b>13</b>B, a predetermined number (e.g., thirteen) of terminals <b>13</b>B are arranged parallel to one another widthwise (direction Z in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) of the connector base <b>13</b>A. Four rows of terminals are arranged vertically (direction X in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>). Arrangement of the terminals <b>13</b>B may be varied according to, for example, the specifications of the connector <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Each terminal <b>13</b>B is substantially L-shaped (not shown) such that its one end extends toward the second sub-connector <b>21</b> as described above and its other end projects from the bottom of the connector base <b>13</b>A toward the substrate <b>14</b>. The other end of each terminal <b>13</b>B is made to pass through the terminal hole of the substrate <b>14</b>, soldered or press-fit, and thereby electrically connected to a wiring pattern formed on the substrate <b>14</b>. Alternatively, surface mounting may be adopted such that the other end of each terminal is directly soldered onto the wiring pattern on the substrate <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The arms <b>13</b>C are formed on both sides of the connector base <b>13</b>A so as to extend further forward than one end of each terminal <b>13</b>B. In this case, taking account of the maximum error of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>, a distance between the pair of arms <b>13</b>C is predetermined so that the arms <b>13</b>C enter the corresponding male connector <b>20</b> and come into contact with the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Even if the maximum error occurs in the second sub-connector <b>21</b>, contact between the pair of arms <b>13</b> and the second sub-connector <b>21</b> is assured.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The internal face of each arm <b>13</b>C has the tapered part <b>13</b>D. When the female connector <b>10</b> and the male connector <b>20</b> are fit together, the tapered parts <b>13</b>D guide the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and second sub-connector <b>21</b> into a predetermined connected position. For example, the tapered parts <b>13</b>D are formed such that the distance between the faces of opposite guides <b>13</b>C<b>1</b> is gradually narrowed as the second sub-connector <b>21</b> is moved in the direction of insertion (direction Y in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>). Thereby, the tapered parts <b>13</b>D guide the second sub-connector <b>21</b> to the connected position while restricting the movement of the second sub-connector <b>21</b> in the direction of insertion of the sub-connector <b>21</b>. In the preferred embodiment, a description will be given in the case where one of the pair of arms <b>13</b>C has the tapered part <b>13</b>D. However, each of the arms <b>13</b>C may have the tapered part <b>13</b>D.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Each engagement part <b>13</b>E is temporarily positioned on a predetermined part of the substrate <b>14</b> by attaching a locking part <b>13</b>F to the connector base <b>13</b>A and inserting or soldering the locking piece <b>13</b>F into or to the substrate. Formed on the substrate <b>14</b> is a wiring pattern (not shown) comprising a circuit by its being connected to each terminal <b>13</b>B, etc., of the first sub-connector <b>13</b>. Terminals, electric wires, etc. (not shown) are externally connected to the substrate <b>14</b>, thereby supplying power or outputting or inputting various signals via the terminals <b>13</b>B.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The female connector <b>10</b> described above is accommodated into the housing <b>11</b> after each first sub-connector <b>13</b> is mounted on the predetermined position of the substrate <b>14</b>. Namely, the terminals <b>13</b>B of each of the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> are arranged in the corresponding female fitting part <b>12</b> so as to extend in the direction of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Thus, the female connector <b>10</b> is completed.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the male connector <b>20</b> includes: a plurality of second sub-connectors <b>21</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, three sub-connectors), each forming a pair with the corresponding first sub-connector <b>13</b>: a fitting part <b>22</b> for accommodating the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>; a holder <b>23</b> for accommodating the fitting part <b>22</b> and the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>; sealing members <b>24</b> provided so as to correspond with the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>; a lever <b>26</b> for receiving and connecting the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> and second sub-connectors <b>21</b> simultaneously; a cover <b>27</b> covering electric wires <b>2</b> connected to the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>; and a waterproof member <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref>, each of the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> includes a plurality of pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A (four in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) and a pressure-welded cover <b>21</b>B covering these pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A. The number of pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A is determined according to the number of terminals of each product, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Each pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A is made of insulating synthetic resin or the like, and has a rectangular plate body <b>211</b> and a plurality of terminal accommodating grooves <b>212</b>. The plate body <b>211</b> includes a bottom wall, pairs of sidewalls <b>211</b><i>a, </i>and an end wall <b>211</b><i>b. </i>The bottom wall is substantially rectangular and almost flat. Each sidewall in a pair <b>211</b><i>a </i>is opposite to and parallel to its corresponding sidewall. The sidewalls <b>211</b><i>a </i>are continuous with the edges of the bottom wall so as to extend upward from the bottom wall.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The end wall <b>211</b><i>b </i>is continuous with the bottom wall and the ends of each pair of sidewalls <b>211</b><i>a. </i>The end wall <b>211</b><i>b </i>extends upward from the bottom wall. The end wall <b>211</b><i>b </i>is continuous with the end of the bottom wall positioned on the frontal side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The end wall <b>211</b><i>a </i>serves as one end described in the specification.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Each of the terminal accommodating groves <b>212</b> is defined by adjacent sidewalls <b>211</b><i>a </i>and the bottom wall. Each terminal accommodating groove <b>212</b> extends from the end wall <b>211</b><i>b </i>to the end of the plate body <b>211</b> opposite to the end wall <b>211</b><i>b. </i>The terminal accommodating grooves <b>212</b> are formed parallel to one another.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">The end wall <b>211</b><i>b </i>has a plurality of parallel insertion holes <b>211</b><i>c </i>into which the terminals <b>13</b>B of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> are inserted. Each of the insertion holes <b>211</b><i>c </i>is a through-hole that is continuous with the corresponding terminal accommodating groove <b>212</b>. Each terminal <b>13</b>B inserted through the corresponding insertion hole <b>211</b><i>c </i>is further inserted into the corresponding terminal accommodating groove <b>212</b> and electrically connected to the pressure-welded terminal <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">Each pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A accommodates the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> in the terminal accommodating groove <b>212</b> selected arbitrarily from among the plurality of terminal accommodating grooves <b>212</b>. The pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A are stacked such that the plate bodies <b>211</b> accommodating the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> are parallel to one another. Each second sub-connector <b>21</b> is constructed in this way.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">In this case, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, electric wires <b>4</b> are pressure-welded to the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> accommodated and held in each pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A with the electric wires <b>4</b> attached thereto are stacked one on another. Each electric wire <b>4</b> has a conductive core wire and a covering, made of insulating synthetic resin, which covers the core wire. When the second-sub-connector <b>21</b> is constructed after the pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A are stacked, the pressure-welded cover <b>21</b>B is arranged so as to cover the top and both sides of the stack of pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">In the-second sub-connector, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, four pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A arranged in a stack have a space <b>21</b>C between the second and third housings <b>21</b>A, that is, the middle of the stack. The aforementioned guide pieces <b>12</b>D of the female fitting part <b>12</b> are inserted into the space <b>21</b>C.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Each pressure-welded cover <b>21</b>B is made of insulating synthetic resin or the like. The pressure-welded cover <b>21</b>B has: a top wall <b>221</b> covering the uppermost pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A; and a pair of sidewall covers <b>222</b> vertically extending from the top wall <b>221</b>. The top wall <b>221</b> is rectangular, which is almost identical in shape to the pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A. Formed on the internal face of the top wall <b>221</b> are projections <b>221</b><i>a </i>which fit in the terminal accommodating groves <b>212</b> of the pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A. The projections <b>221</b><i>a </i>extend from one end of the top wall <b>221</b> to the other end along the terminal accommodating groves <b>212</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Each sidewall cover <b>222</b> is rectangular, which is almost identical in shape to the sides of the stack of pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A. Each sidewall cover <b>222</b> has a sidewall slit <b>222</b><i>a, </i>engagement projections <b>222</b><i>b, </i>and an abutting part <b>222</b><i>c. </i>The sidewall slit <b>222</b><i>a </i>extends from the center of the sidewall cover <b>222</b> to the edge thereof in direction Y as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The sidewall slit <b>222</b><i>a </i>is continuous with the space <b>21</b>C, into which the corresponding guide piece <b>12</b>D of the female fitting part <b>12</b> is inserted to regulate the range of insertion.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The engagement projections <b>222</b><i>b </i>each have a projecting form inclining in direction Y as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The engagement projections <b>222</b><i>b </i>are arranged in a pair such that the sidewall slit <b>222</b><i>a </i>is located therebetween. They are engaged with the long holes (described below) of the fitting part <b>22</b>, thereby positioning the second sub-connector <b>21</b> in the fitting part <b>22</b>. The positions and the number of the engagement projections <b>222</b><i>b </i>can be determined arbitrarily.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">The abutting part <b>222</b><i>c </i>is formed such that the corresponding arm <b>13</b>C of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> comes into contact with this part. The abutting part <b>222</b><i>c </i>projects in a rectangular form from the sidewall cover <b>222</b> and extends in the direction Y along the sidewall slit <b>222</b><i>a. </i>The abutting part <b>222</b><i>c </i>has a tapered part <b>222</b><i>d </i>formed such that when the female connector <b>10</b> and the male connector <b>20</b> are fit together, the abutting part <b>222</b><i>c </i>guides the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the second sub-connector <b>21</b> into their connected position. The tapered part <b>222</b><i>d </i>tapers in the direction Y as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, which is the direction of insertion.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The fitting part <b>22</b> is made of insulating synthetic resin or the like and includes, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, a plurality of accommodating parts <b>22</b>A (three in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) for accommodating the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>, and a case body <b>22</b>B in which the series of accommodating parts <b>22</b>A are defined at predetermined intervals. The number of accommodating parts <b>22</b>A is determined according to the number of the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Each accommodating part <b>22</b>A has a shape corresponding to the outside of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. The height of the accommodating part <b>22</b>A, in direction X in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, is substantially equal to that of the second sub-connector <b>21</b> such that the accommodating part <b>22</b>A can accommodate the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. The width of the accommodating part <b>22</b>A, in direction Z in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, is slightly greater than that of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. The width is designed based on the sidewise movement or the like of the leading ends of the terminals <b>13</b>B, which result from variations in the first sub-connectors <b>13</b>. Guide grooves (not shown) in the second sub-connector <b>21</b> extending widthwise (direction Z in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) are formed in the upper and lower internal faces of the accommodating part <b>22</b>A, so that the projections <b>21</b>D of the second sub-connector <b>21</b> movably fit in them. The accommodating parts <b>22</b>A formed as described above prevent vertical movement of the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> accommodated in the corresponding accommodating parts <b>22</b>A and allow the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> to slide only in the directions indicated by arrow S (that is, widthwise) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Each accommodating part <b>22</b>A includes: through-holes <b>22</b>C into which the terminals of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> are inserted; an accommodating space <b>22</b>D into which the corresponding guide piece <b>12</b>D of the female fitting part <b>12</b> is inserted; entry parts <b>22</b>E into which the arms <b>13</b>C of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> enter; and a plurality of engagement openings <b>22</b>F.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Each of the through-holes <b>22</b>C corresponds to the row of terminals <b>13</b>B of the first sub-connector <b>13</b>. Each of the through-holes <b>22</b>C has the form of a slit so as to correspond to the pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A. The through-holes <b>22</b>C enable the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> to be temporarily positioned in the corresponding first sub-connectors <b>13</b>. Accordingly, the connector <b>1</b> may easily be fit.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">In the preferred embodiment, a description is given in the case where each opening <b>22</b>C has a slit form. However, the through-holes <b>22</b>C may have various shapes corresponding to the terminals <b>13</b>B. The through-holes <b>22</b>C having a slit form can accept variations, which result from manufacturing tolerance in the terminals <b>13</b>B.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Each accommodating space <b>22</b>D has a slit form so as to be continuous with the foregoing space <b>21</b>C. The guide piece <b>12</b>D of the female fitting part <b>12</b>, inserted in the accommodating space <b>22</b>D, is subsequently inserted into the space <b>21</b>C, thereby temporarily positioning the second sub-connector <b>21</b> in the first sub-connector <b>13</b> in a vertical direction (direction X in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">The entry parts <b>22</b>E are defined on both sidewalls of each accommodating part <b>22</b>A. Each entry part <b>22</b>E has the form of an indentation extending in the direction in which the second sub-connector <b>21</b> is inserted (direction Y in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>). As the second sub-connector <b>21</b> is accommodated into the accommodating part <b>22</b>A, the abutting parts <b>222</b><i>c </i>of the second sub-connector <b>21</b> fit into the entry parts <b>22</b>E, and thus, the second sub-connector <b>21</b> is positioned in the accommodating part <b>22</b>A. Arms <b>13</b>C of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> enter the corresponding entry parts <b>22</b>E, thereby coming into contact with the abutting parts <b>222</b><i>c </i>of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. In the preferred embodiment, the entry parts <b>22</b>E have a slit form because a predetermined space is left between the adjacent accommodating parts <b>22</b>A. However, the entry part <b>22</b>E may take any form such as a through-hole.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">The engagement openings <b>22</b>F have an indentation form that is the same as the entry parts <b>22</b>E, and are formed on both sidewalls of each accommodating part <b>22</b>A along the entry parts <b>22</b>E. As the second sub-connector <b>21</b> is accommodated into the accommodating part <b>22</b>A, the engagement projections <b>222</b><i>b </i>of the second sub-connector <b>21</b> fit into the entry parts <b>22</b>E, thereby positioning the second sub-connector <b>21</b> in the accommodating part <b>22</b>A. The engagement openings <b>22</b>F may be formed in both the sidewalls of each accommodating part <b>22</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">The holder <b>23</b> is made of insulating synthetic resin or the like. By covering part of the male fitting part <b>22</b> accommodating the second sub-connectors <b>22</b>, the holder <b>23</b> fixes the male fitting part <b>22</b> in position. The holder <b>23</b> has fixing parts (not shown), which fix the sealing members <b>24</b> to the corresponding second sub-connectors <b>21</b> with a predetermined space L left between them, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9 and 10</figref>. The holder <b>23</b> axially bears the lever <b>26</b> such that the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> and the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> fit into their connections simultaneously. Additionally, the holder <b>23</b> has an axial bearing part (not shown) which axially bears the cover <b>27</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The sealing members <b>24</b> each have a mat seal <b>24</b>A and a mat seal cover <b>24</b>B. The mat seal <b>24</b>A is made of an insulating elastic member and has holes through which the electric wires <b>4</b> are made to pass. The mat seal <b>24</b>A restricts movement of the electric wires <b>4</b>. The mat seal cover <b>24</b>B is made of insulating synthetic resin, and is fixed in the holder <b>23</b> while it holds the mat seal <b>24</b>A. Since the sealing member <b>24</b> formed as describe above absorbs any external force transmitted from the electric wires <b>4</b> connected to the second sub-connector <b>21</b>, transmission of such an external force to the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> is prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">The lever <b>26</b> may be rotated while being axially supported by the holder <b>23</b>. By the action of a lever rule accompanying the rotation, the lever <b>26</b> pulls the female sub-connector <b>10</b> and the male sub-connector <b>20</b>, and fits the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> and the corresponding second sub-connectors <b>21</b> into their connections simultaneously.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">The cover <b>27</b> is made of insulating synthetic resin or the like, and is shaped such as to be continuous with the edges of the holder <b>23</b>. The cover <b>27</b> binds together electric wires <b>4</b> connected to the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> and externally guides the electric wires <b>4</b>. These externally guided electric wires <b>4</b> are bound together by a tie wrap belt <b>20</b>B and fixed to the cover <b>27</b>. Therefore, an external force applied to the electric wires <b>4</b> is absorbed by the cover <b>27</b> fixed by the tie wrap belt <b>20</b>B, and the external force remaining in the cover <b>27</b> is further absorbed by the sealing members <b>24</b>. This reduces the external force applied to the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">The waterproof member <b>28</b> is made of synthetic resin or the like. When the male fitting part <b>22</b> of the male connector <b>20</b> and the female fitting part <b>12</b> of the female connector <b>10</b> are fit into their connections, the waterproof member <b>28</b> is interposed between the fitting parts <b>22</b> and <b>12</b> and seals the gap between them to prevent entry of liquid such as water. This eliminates the need to provide the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and second sub-connector <b>21</b> with waterproofing or the like. This easily meets any demand for an increase in the number of the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> and second sub-connectors <b>21</b> of the waterproof connector <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">The male connector <b>10</b> described above is assembled in a manner as follows. The second sub-connectors <b>21</b> with the electric wires <b>4</b> connected to them are first fit in the corresponding accommodating parts <b>22</b>A so as to be freely movable widthwise. Then, the male fitting part <b>22</b> is fit in the holder <b>23</b>. Subsequently, the sealing members <b>24</b> through which the electric wires <b>4</b> have passed are fit in the holder <b>23</b>. Also, the lever <b>26</b> and the cover <b>27</b> are fit to the holder <b>23</b> so as to be freely rotatable. Thus, the male connector <b>20</b> is completed.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">Referring mainly to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11 and 12</figref>, the connection of the above-mentioned connector <b>1</b> will now be explained.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, the male connector <b>20</b> is aligned to the female connector <b>10</b> such that the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> and the corresponding second sub-connectors <b>21</b> face each other. Then, the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> are moved in the direction of insertion (direction Y in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>). As a result, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12A</figref>, the tapered part <b>13</b>D of the arm <b>13</b>C of each first sub-connector <b>13</b> comes into contact with the tapered part <b>222</b><i>d </i>of the abutting part <b>222</b><i>c </i>of the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">While further moved in the direction of insertion (direction Y), each second sub-connector <b>21</b> slides to the left (direction Z) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> due to the contact of the tapered part <b>13</b>D of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> with the tapered part <b>222</b><i>d </i>of the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>, as shown in FIG. <b>12</b>B. Consequently, the terminal accommodating grooves <b>21</b> of the second sub-connector <b>21</b> slide into a position where the terminals <b>13</b>B of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> can be inserted into the corresponding grooves, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12C</figref>. When each second sub-connector <b>21</b> is further moved in the direction of insertion, the terminals <b>13</b>B of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> are brought into firm contact with the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Thereby, the terminals <b>13</b>B and the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> are electrically connected, and thus, the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b> are connected in the correct connected position. Accordingly, the female connector <b>10</b> and the male connector <b>20</b> are connected to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">According to the above-mentioned connector <b>1</b>, the male fitting part <b>22</b> (male frame) of the male connector <b>20</b> defines accommodating parts <b>22</b>A in which the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> are individually accommodated so as to be freely movable. The female fitting part <b>12</b> (female frame), which fits into its connection to the male fitting part <b>22</b>, accommodates the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> that are connected to the corresponding second sub-connectors <b>22</b>. As the male fitting part <b>22</b> fits into the female fitting part <b>12</b>, each second sub-connector <b>21</b> is guided to the connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connector <b>13</b> by guide means which comprises the arm <b>13</b>C of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the abutting part <b>222</b><i>c </i>of the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Accordingly, even if there are variations in the terminals <b>13</b>B, etc., of each first sub-connector <b>13</b> and corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>, the second sub-connector <b>21</b> designed so as to be freely movable is guided to the connected position relative to the first sub-connector <b>13</b>. Thus, the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the second sub-connector <b>21</b> are connected and held in position. Additionally, in the case where each first sub-connector <b>13</b> has terminals <b>13</b>B, the terminals <b>13</b>B have been formed by mechanical processes, the tolerance of which may result in variations in the leading ends of the terminals <b>13</b>B and variations in the terminal <b>13</b>B. However, since each accommodating part <b>22</b>A of the male fitting part <b>22</b> accommodates the second sub-connector <b>21</b> such that the second sub-connector is freely movable, the variations are absorbed such that the second sub-connector <b>21</b> can be guided to the connected position. This eliminates the need to provide biasing means, such as a displacement spring, in order to connect and fix each first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>, hence preventing a load on the terminals <b>13</b>B, substrates <b>14</b><i>d</i>, etc. after connection of the first and second sub-connectors <b>13</b> and <b>21</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">In the first embodiment, the description has been given in the case where the guide means is realized by the arms <b>13</b>C and tapered parts <b>13</b>D of each of the first sub-connectors <b>13</b>. However, the invention is not limited thereto and may be varied as in the second embodiment. In the second embodiment, the same reference numerals refer to the identical components or corresponding parts used in the first embodiment, and explanations of these are omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">As shown <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a connector <b>1</b> has one connector <b>10</b> (referred to as female connector) serving as a female frame and a plurality of mating connectors <b>20</b> (referred to as male connectors) serving as male frames which fit into its connection to the female connector <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 13</figref>, the female connector <b>10</b> includes: a substantially box-like housing <b>11</b> made of synthetic resin or the like; female fitting parts <b>12</b> which are defined in the housing <b>11</b> and into which the corresponding male connectors <b>20</b> fit; a plurality of first sub-connectors <b>13</b> (the two first sub-connectors <b>13</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>) accommodated in the housing <b>11</b>; and a substrate <b>14</b> to which the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> are fixed.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, the first sub-connector <b>13</b> is composed of two first sub-connectors <b>131</b> and <b>132</b>. Needless to say, the first sub-connector <b>13</b> may be composed of one.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">Each first sub-connector <b>13</b> includes: a connector base <b>13</b><i>a; </i>a plurality of terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>extending from the connector base <b>13</b><i>a </i>toward the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>; guides <b>13</b><i>c </i>extending from the connector base <b>13</b><i>a </i>towards the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>; tapered parts <b>13</b><i>d </i>(refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>) formed on the guides <b>13</b><i>c; </i>and engagement parts <b>13</b><i>e </i>formed on both sidewalls of the first sub-connector <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">The connector base <b>13</b><i>a </i>is substantially in the shape of a box, made of a synthetic resin or the like, and has a peripheral wall <b>13</b><i>a</i><b>1</b>. The peripheral wall <b>13</b><i>a</i><b>1</b> surrounds a plurality of terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>arranged by means of insert molding or the like, and has an opening <b>13</b><i>a</i><b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">As described above, each of the terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>is of a metal plate material or composite member formed in a predetermined shape. In the one first sub-connector <b>131</b>, six lines of six terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>are arranged in the direction X in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>. In the other first sub-connector <b>132</b>, four lines of eight terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>are arranged in the direction X in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>. In the preferred embodiment, the description of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> will be given using the first sub-connector <b>131</b> as the first sub-connector <b>13</b> in order to simplify the description.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">Each terminal <b>13</b><i>b </i>is substantially L-shaped such that its one end extends toward the second sub-connector <b>21</b> as described above and its other end projects from the bottom of the connector base <b>13</b><i>a </i>toward the substrate <b>14</b>. The other end of each terminal <b>13</b><i>b </i>is made to pass through the terminal hole of the substrate <b>14</b>, soldered or press-fit, and thereby electrically connected to a wiring pattern formed on the substrate <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">Each guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>has the form of a plate extending from the connector base <b>13</b><i>a </i>toward the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Specifically, the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>has the shape of a wide flat plate that is narrower than the width along which the six terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>are arranged, and is arranged in the middle of the vertical lines of terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>(i.e., between the third and fourth horizontal lines). In the case of the first sub-connector <b>132</b>, the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>is formed so as to be narrower than the width along which the eight terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>are arranged, and is arranged in the middle of the vertical lines of terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>(i.e., between the second and third horizontal lines). The shape and position of each guide part can be determined according to the dimensions, shape, etc., of the corresponding sub-connector <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">Taking account of the maximum error of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>, the width, thickness, etc., of each guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>are determined such that the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>enters the male connector <b>20</b> and then comes into contact with the guide hole <b>21</b>C of the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>. The guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>extends further forward than one end of each terminal <b>13</b><i>b </i>or extends the distance that is almost equal to the length of each terminal <b>13</b><i>b. </i>Even if the maximum error occurs in the second sub-connector <b>21</b>, the first sub-connector can come into contact with the second sub-connector <b>21</b> by the guide part <b>13</b><i>c. </i></p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16B</figref>, each guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>has tapered parts <b>13</b><i>d </i>near the leafing ends of their sidewalls <b>13</b><i>c</i><b>1</b> in the direction of the guide hole <b>21</b>C of the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Tapered parts <b>13</b><i>d </i>are shaped such that when the female connector <b>10</b> and the male connector <b>20</b> are fit together, the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the second sub-connector <b>21</b> are guided to the predetermined connected position. For example, each tapered part <b>13</b><i>d </i>is shaped such that as the tapered part <b>13</b><i>d </i>is moved in the direction of insertion (direction Y in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>), the tapered part <b>13</b> gradually comes into contact with the sidewall <b>13</b><i>c</i><b>1</b> and the internal wall <b>21</b>C<b>1</b> of the guide hole <b>21</b>C of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Accordingly, when the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>is completely fit into the guide hole <b>21</b>C, movement of the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>is restricted and also the position of the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>is corrected by the faces of the guide hole <b>21</b>C.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">Each engagement part <b>13</b><i>e </i>is temporarily positioned on a predetermined position of the substrate <b>14</b> by its being engaged with a locking piece (not shown) projecting from the surface of the substrate <b>14</b>. Formed on the substrate <b>14</b> is a wiring pattern (not shown) comprising a circuit by its being connected to each terminal <b>13</b><i>b, </i>etc., of the first sub-connector <b>13</b>. Terminals, electric wires, etc. (not shown) are externally connected to the substrate <b>14</b>, thereby supplying power or outputting or inputting various signals via the terminals <b>13</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0100">The female connector <b>10</b> described above is accommodated into the housing <b>11</b> after each first sub-connector <b>13</b> is mounted on the predetermined position of the substrate <b>14</b>. Namely, the terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>of each of the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> are arranged in the corresponding female fitting part <b>12</b> so as to extend in the direction of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Thus, the female connector <b>10</b> is completed.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0101">Just as the foregoing first embodiment, the male connector <b>20</b> includes: a plurality of second sub-connectors <b>21</b>, each forming a pair with the corresponding first sub-connector <b>13</b>: a fitting part <b>22</b> for accommodating the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>; a holder <b>23</b> for accommodating the fitting part <b>22</b> and the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>; sealing members <b>24</b> provided so as to correspond with the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>; a lever <b>26</b> for receiving and connecting the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> and second sub-connectors <b>21</b> simultaneously; a cover <b>27</b> covering electric wires <b>2</b> connected to the second sub-connectors <b>21</b>; and a waterproof member <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0102">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, each second sub-connector <b>21</b> includes a plurality of pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A, and a pressure-welded cover <b>21</b>B covering the pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A. The second sub-connector <b>21</b> incorporates pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A (six pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>) arranged in a stack. Defined between the third and fourth pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A is the aforementioned guide hole <b>21</b>C into which the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>fits. The guide hole <b>21</b>C has the form of a slit shaped to match the guide part <b>13</b><i>c. </i>Specifically, the upper face or lower face of the plate body <b>211</b> of an arbitrary pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A has a recess to define the guide hole <b>21</b>C.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0103">Each pressure-welded housing <b>21</b>A accommodates the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> in the terminal accommodating grooves <b>212</b> selected arbitrarily from among the plurality of terminal accommodating grooves <b>212</b>. The pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A are stacked such that the plate bodies <b>211</b> accommodating the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> are parallel to one another. Each second sub-connector <b>21</b> is constructed in this way. In addition, a fitting part <b>22</b> is formed near the middle of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. After the pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A are arranged in a stack to compose the second sub-connector <b>21</b>, the top and both sides of the stack of pressure-welded housings <b>21</b>A are covered with the pressure-welded cover <b>21</b>B, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0104">The male connector <b>20</b> described above is assembled in a manner as follows. The second sub-connectors <b>21</b> with the electric wires <b>4</b> connected thereto are first fit in the corresponding accommodating parts <b>22</b>A so as to be freely movable widthwise. Then, the fitting part <b>22</b> is fit in the holder <b>23</b>. Subsequently, the sealing members <b>24</b> through which the electric wires <b>4</b> have passed are fit in the holder <b>23</b>. Also, the lever <b>26</b> and the cover <b>27</b> are fit to the holder <b>23</b> so as to be freely rotatable. Thus, the male connector <b>20</b> is completed.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0105">Additionally, the female connector <b>10</b> according to the second embodiment includes a temporary position control part <b>15</b> that controls the temporary position of the female connector <b>10</b> relative to the male connector <b>20</b> by its abutting on the sidewalls <b>22</b>G of the fitting part <b>22</b> of the male connector <b>20</b>. The temporary position control part <b>15</b> makes it possible to correctly position the female connector <b>10</b> relative to the male connector <b>20</b> when the connectors <b>10</b> and <b>20</b> are fit together.</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0106">An example of fitting the above-described connector <b>1</b> according to the second embodiment will now be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 14 to 16</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0107">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 14 and 15</figref>, when the temporary position control part <b>15</b> brings the female connector <b>10</b> and male connector <b>20</b> into the connected position, the second sub-connector <b>20</b> is moved in the direction of insertion (direction Y in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>). Consequently, the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> is brought into contact with the end <b>21</b>C<b>2</b> of the guide hole <b>21</b>C of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0108">While further moved in the direction of insertion (direction Y), each second sub-connector <b>21</b> slides to the left (direction Z) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> due to the contact of the tapered part <b>13</b><i>d </i>of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> with the end <b>21</b>C<b>2</b> of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>. Consequently, the terminal accommodating grooves <b>212</b> of the second sub-connector <b>21</b> slide into a position where the terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> can be inserted into the corresponding grooves. When each second sub-connector <b>21</b> is further moved in the direction of insertion, the terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> are brought into firm contact with the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> of the second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Thereby, the terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>and the pressure-welded terminals <b>29</b> are electrically connected, and thus, the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b> are connected in the correct connected position. Accordingly, the female connector <b>10</b> and the male connector <b>20</b> are fitted together.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0109">According to the above-mentioned connector <b>1</b>, the fitting part <b>22</b> (male frame) of the male connector <b>20</b> defines accommodating parts <b>22</b>A in which the second sub-connectors <b>21</b> are individually accommodated so as to be freely movable. The female fitting part <b>10</b> (female frame), which fits into its connection to the male fitting part <b>22</b>, accommodates the first sub-connectors <b>13</b> that are connected to the corresponding second sub-connectors <b>22</b>. As the male fitting part <b>22</b> fits into the female fitting part <b>12</b>, each second sub-connector <b>21</b> is guided to the connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connector <b>13</b> by guide means which comprises the guide part <b>13</b><i>c </i>of the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the guide hole <b>21</b>C of the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>. Accordingly, even if there are variations in the terminals <b>13</b><i>b, </i>etc., of each first sub-connector <b>13</b> and corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>, the second sub-connector <b>21</b> designed so as to be freely movable is guided to the connected position relative to the first sub-connector <b>13</b>. Thus, the first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the second sub-connector <b>21</b> are connected and held in position. Additionally, in the case where each first sub-connector <b>13</b> has the terminals <b>13</b><i>b, </i>the terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>have been formed by mechanical processes, the tolerance of which may result in variations in the leading ends of the terminals <b>13</b><i>b </i>and variations in the terminal <b>13</b><i>b. </i>However, since each accommodating part <b>22</b>A of the fitting part <b>22</b> accommodates the second sub-connector <b>21</b> such that the second sub-connector <b>21</b> is freely movable, the variations are absorbed such that the second sub-connector <b>21</b> can be guided to the connected position.</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0110">This eliminates the need to provide biasing means, such as a displacement spring, in order to connect and fix each first sub-connector <b>13</b> and the corresponding second sub-connector <b>21</b>. As a consequence, a load is prevented from being generated on the terminals <b>13</b><i>b, </i>substrates <b>14</b><i>d, </i>etc. during and after connection of the first and second sub-connectors <b>13</b> and <b>21</b>. Additionally, each first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector, which are the smallest unit, are positioned relative to each other. This further reduces the load applied on the terminals <b>13</b><i>b. </i>Moreover, this assures fitting accuracy without demanding high precision in mounting the substrate <b>14</b> of the female connector <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0111">In the preferred embodiments, the descriptions have been given in the case where the first sub-connector <b>13</b> is a male connector and the second sub-connector <b>21</b> is a female connector. However, the invention is not limited thereto, and the first sub-connector <b>13</b> may be a female connector and the second sub-connector may be a male connector.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A connector including a plurality of first sub-connectors fixed to a substrate and a plurality of second sub-connectors paired with the corresponding first sub-connectors, comprising:
<claim-text>a male frame having a plurality of accommodating parts in which the second sub-connectors are separately accommodated so as to be freely movable</claim-text>
<claim-text>a female frame into which the male frame fits, the female frame being adapted to accommodate the plurality of first sub-connectors such that the first sub-connectors are connected to the corresponding second sub-connectors; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means for guiding each of the second sub-connectors into a connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connectors, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the guide means comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>arms which extend from each of the first sub-connectors toward the corresponding second sub-connector, and enter the male frame so as to come into contact with the second sub-connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>abutting parts formed on each second sub-connector, each abutting part being adapted such that the corresponding arm can be brought into contact with the abutting part; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>tapered parts formed on at least the arms or the abutting parts, each tapered part inclining such that when the male frame and the female frame are fit together, the first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector are guided into the connected position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A connector including a plurality of first sub-connectors fixed to a substrate and a plurality of second sub-connectors paired with the corresponding first sub-connectors, comprising:
<claim-text>a male frame having a plurality of accommodating parts in which the second sub-connectors are separately accommodated so as to be freely movable;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a female frame into which the male frame fits, the female frame being adapted to accommodate the plurality of first sub-connectors such that the first sub-connectors are connected to the corresponding second sub-connectors; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means for guiding each of the second sub-connectors into a connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connectors, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the guide means comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plate-formed guide part which extends from each first sub-connector toward the corresponding second sub-connector and enters the male frame so as to come into contact with the second sub-connector; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a guide hole defined in the corresponding second sub-connector, the guide hole being adapted to receive the guide part such that as the male frame and the female frame are fit together, the first sub-connector and the corresponding second sub-connector are guided into the connected position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A connector including a plurality of first sub-connectors fixed to a substrate and a plurality of second sub-connectors paired with the corresponding first sub-connectors, comprising:
<claim-text>a male frame having a plurality of accommodating parts in which the second sub-connectors are separately accommodated so as to be freely movable;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a female frame into which the male frame fits, the female frame being adapted to accommodate the plurality of first sub-connectors such that the first sub-connectors are connected to the corresponding second sub-connectors; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means for guiding each of the second sub-connectors into a connected position relative to the corresponding first sub-connectors, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>each of the first sub-connectors has a plurality of terminals, and the male frame has through-holes into which the terminals of the first sub-connectors are inserted.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
