<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296917-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296917</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11471497</doc-number>
<date>20060621</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>60</class>
<subclass>Q</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362464</main-classification>
<further-classification>362512</further-classification>
<further-classification>362111</further-classification>
<further-classification>34082569</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Wireless remote-controlled searchlight with improved manipulator</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4930057</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Williams</name>
<date>19900500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362272</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5438325</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nishigaki et al.</name>
<date>19950800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>34082524</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6582105</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Christensen</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362385</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7057494</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Fitzgibbon</name>
<date>20060600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340  57</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0198336</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Jancic et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>455420</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0248930</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Naval et al.</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362 85</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362464</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362512</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362111</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362276</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34082569</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340 105</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chiu</last-name>
<first-name>Shin-Yung</first-name>
<address>
<street>1F., No. 5, Lane 35, Sec. 2, Baoyuan Rd.</street>
<city>Sindian City, Taipei County</city>
<postcode>231</postcode>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Bacon &amp; Thomas, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Sember</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas M.</first-name>
<department>2885</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Shallenberger</last-name>
<first-name>Julie A.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A wireless remote-controlled searchlight adapted to manual remotely control and wireless remotely control comprises a hand-held manipulator having a hand controlled circuit to manual remotely control the searchlight while a four-way directional control switches and an on/off switch being selectively pressed by hand, a RF receiver particularly installed inside to receive controlled RF signals transmitted from a separated potable wireless transmitter, and a MCU adapted to control a relay actuated circuit and a motor actuated circuit by according to the input corresponding received RF signals from the RF receiver to execute wireless remotely control the searchlight; and the hand-held manipulator is assembled on the position outside and away from the searchlight to get an advantage of being easy to wireless remotely control with great precision.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="251.54mm" wi="179.58mm" file="US07296917-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="199.39mm" wi="133.27mm" file="US07296917-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="252.39mm" wi="180.42mm" file="US07296917-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="225.38mm" wi="173.14mm" file="US07296917-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Present Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention relates to a wireless remote-controlled searchlight, and more particularly to a wireless remote-controlled searchlight has a hand-held manipulator with a wireless receiver installed inside for having the receiver's assembling position outside and away from the searchlight.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of Prior Act</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">An example of a remote-controlled searchlight as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is known from U.S. Pat. No. 4,930,057 to J. L. Williams, which is disclosed the remote-controlled searchlight permanently mounted to a supporting surface, such as the roof of a car or the deck of a boat, and a remote-control box capably being placed inside of a vehicle to permit the vehicle operator to switch the searchlight on and off as well as to undergo sweeping movement in both vertical and horizontal directions.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In this patent there is described a searchlight <b>10</b> which comprises a lamp housing <b>20</b> constituted by an upper housing <b>21</b> and a lower housing <b>22</b> with an integrally formed ring gear <b>25</b>; a base means <b>30</b> for mounting the lamp housing <b>20</b>, which has a flange <b>31</b> with several holes <b>32</b> formed for permanently mounting the base <b>30</b> by means of screws to a supporting surface for the searchlight <b>10</b>; a lamp means <b>40</b> mounted in the lamp housing <b>20</b> for vertical movement, which includes a bulb housing <b>41</b> with a bearing means for mounting in the lamp housing <b>20</b> and a vertical gear member <b>43</b> integrally formed on back of the bulb housing <b>41</b>; a vertical drive means <b>50</b> mounted in the lamp housing <b>20</b> for vertically driving the lamp means <b>40</b>, which includes a reversible gear motor <b>51</b> having an output shaft with pinion means <b>52</b> for engaging the vertical gear member <b>43</b> of the lamp means <b>40</b>; a horizontal drive means <b>60</b> mounted in the base means <b>30</b> for driving the lamp means <b>40</b> and lamp housing <b>20</b> in a horizontal plane less than 360 degrees, which includes a reversible gear motor <b>61</b> having an output shaft with a pinion means <b>62</b> for engaging the ring gear <b>25</b> of the lamp housing <b>20</b>; and an electrical cable <b>70</b> with leads <b>71</b>, <b>72</b> and <b>73</b> as power source extended from the lamp housing <b>20</b> and the base means <b>30</b> into a remote-control box placed inside of a vehicle, so that a bulb installed in the bulb housing <b>41</b> is connected by leads <b>71</b> to a 12-volt DC power source, the reversible gear motor <b>51</b> is connected by leads <b>72</b> to a 12-volt DC power source and the reversible gear motor <b>61</b> is connected by leads <b>73</b> to a 12-volt DC power source.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The remote-controlled searchlight <b>10</b> mentioned above is very convenient in use, but the remote-controlled searchlight <b>10</b> can not be remotely operated by wireless remote control, and the remote-controlled searchlight <b>10</b> is short of a waterproof cover to prevent rain water from seeping into the interior of the remote-controlled searchlight <b>10</b> through a gap <b>28</b> is existed in between the lamp means <b>40</b> and the lamp housing <b>20</b>, so that the remote-controlled searchlight <b>10</b> is easily happened to break down under stress of weather.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Another example of a “wireless remote-controlled searchlight” is known from U.S. Pat. No. 5,673,989 to Gohl et al. Although most mechanical structures of the wireless remote-controlled searchlight are similar to that of U.S. Pat. No. 4,930,057 mentioned above, the remote control for the searchlight is preferably provided by a hand-held multi-channel radio transmitter and a locally mounted receiver contained within a lamp housing of the searchlight. The transmitter and receiver circuits control the reversible gear motor in the lamp housing for vertical and horizontal rotational movement of the lamp and the power to the lamp filament.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, due to the receiver mounted inside the lamp housing of the searchlight and closed to the reversible gear motor, the RF transmitted from the transmitter is easily jammed by interference from the reversible gear motor, resulted in the wireless remote-controlled searchlight is frequently hard to remotely control by wireless control.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">For improving the “wireless remote-controlled searchlight” mentioned above, the applicant had been filed an U.S. application Ser. No. 11/205,070 which invented and disclosed to a “searchlight improvement structure” comprising an electrical cable with four leads to supply power source for the searchlight, a RF receiver with an antenna inside which is assembled on the electrical cable to have its assembling position outside and away from the lamp housing and the base means, and two separated wireless transmitters each having an on/off switch and a four-way directional control switch, wherein one of the wireless transmitters is connected by leads of the electrical cable and the other wireless transmitter is powered by a replaceable internal power supply. Due to the RF receiver installed outside and away from the lamp housing and the base means to prevent from radio interference caused from the vertical and horizontal drive means of the searchlight, the advantage of the invented “searchlight improvement structure” is then easy to wireless remotely control with great precision.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">With the instant invention, it is a further advanced improvement to the “searchlight improvement structure” of the U.S. application Ser. No. 11/205,070 mentioned above.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Therefore, the main object of the present invention is to provide a wireless remote-controlled searchlight permanently positioned on the roof of a vehicle or the deck of a boat, which comprises a hand-held manipulator having a RF receiver installed inside is placed inside of the vehicle or the boat so that the manipulator has both manually remote-controlled function and wireless remote-controlled function to the operator in use, and the manipulator is further to have the receiver's assembling position outside and away from the searchlight to enable the wireless remote-controlled searchlight of the invention to get the advantage of being easy to wireless remotely control with great precision.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The whole structure of the wireless remote-controlled searchlight comprises a lamp means mounted in a lamp housing having a vertical drive means for tilting the lamp means in a vertical direction and a horizontal drive means for rotating the lamp means in a horizontal direction, a hand-held manipulator with a RF receiver installed inside being adapted to switch the searchlight on and off as well as to undergo sweeping movement in both vertical and horizontal directions by manual remotely control, and a separated portable wireless transmitters via the RF receiver installed inside the hand-held manipulator being adapted to be wireless remotely operated from a distance to switch the searchlight on and off as well as to undergo sweeping movement in both vertical and horizontal directions by wireless remotely control.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Another object of this present invention is to provide a waterproof cover to prevent rain water from seeping into the interior of the searchlight, so that the searchlight of the invention shall be always kept in normal use under stress of weather.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Other features and advantages of the present invention will become apparent in the following detailed description of the preferred embodiments with reference to the accompanying drawings, of which:</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a partial cross sectional side view of the remote-controlled searchlight according to U.S. Pat. No. 4,930,057; and</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a partial cross sectional side view of the invented searchlight according to the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic circuit diagram of the hand-held manipulator and the separated portable wireless transmitter according to the present invention for depicting the relation between components and the position of each component.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Before the present invention is described in greater detail, it should be noted that like elements are denoted by the same reference numerals throughout the disclosure.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>, the preferred embodiment of a wireless remote-controlled searchlight <b>15</b> of the present invention is permanently positioned on the roof of a vehicle or the deck of a boat, which comprises a lamp housing <b>20</b>, a base means <b>30</b>, a lamp means <b>40</b>, a vertical drive means <b>50</b>, a horizontal drive means <b>60</b>, an electrical cable <b>70</b> with a plug <b>75</b> and three leads <b>71</b>, <b>72</b>, and <b>73</b> as power source for the searchlight <b>15</b>, a hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> with a RF receiver <b>81</b> assembled on the electrical cable <b>70</b> to have its assembling position outside and away from the lamp housing <b>20</b> and the base means <b>30</b>, and a separated portable wireless transmitter <b>90</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The lamp housing <b>20</b> is constituted by an upper housing <b>21</b> and a lower housing <b>22</b> provided with an integrally formed ring gear <b>25</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The base means <b>30</b> for mounting the lamp housing <b>20</b> has a flange <b>31</b> extended from its bottom and plural fasten holes <b>32</b> formed on the flange <b>31</b> applied for permanently mounting the base <b>30</b> by means of screws to the roof of a vehicle or the deck of a boat.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The lamp means <b>40</b> with a bulb is pivotedly mounted in the lamp housing <b>20</b> for vertical movement, which includes a bulb housing <b>41</b> with a bearing means for mounting in the lamp housing <b>20</b> and a vertical gear member <b>43</b> integrally formed on back of the bulb housing <b>41</b>. And, the bulb of the lamp means <b>40</b> is connected by leads <b>71</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> to a 12-volt DC power source.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The vertical drive means <b>50</b> is mounted in the lamp housing <b>20</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> for vertically driving the lamp means <b>40</b>, which includes a reversible gear motor <b>51</b> having an output shaft with pinion means <b>52</b> for engaging the vertical gear member <b>43</b> of the lamp means <b>40</b>. And, the reversible gear motor <b>51</b> is connected by leads <b>72</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> to a 12-volt DC power source.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The horizontal drive means <b>60</b> is mounted in the base means <b>30</b> for driving the lamp means <b>40</b> and lamp housing <b>20</b> in a horizontal plane less than 360 degrees, which includes a reversible gear motor <b>61</b> having an output shaft with a pinion means <b>62</b> for engaging the ring gear <b>25</b> of the lamp housing <b>20</b>. And, the reversible gear motor <b>61</b> is connected by leads <b>73</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> to a 12-volt DC power source.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The separated portable wireless transmitter <b>90</b> includes a four-way directional control switch SW<b>1</b>, SW<b>2</b>, SW<b>3</b> and SW<b>4</b>, an on/off switch SW<b>5</b>, an encoder <b>91</b> and a signal transmitting unit <b>92</b>, and the power for the wireless transmitter <b>90</b> is supplied by a replaceable internal power supply, e.g. a 9-volt battery.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">When any one of switches of SW<b>1</b>, SW<b>2</b>, SW<b>3</b>, SW<b>4</b> and SW<b>5</b> of the wireless transmitter <b>90</b> is pressed, an identification code with corresponding RF (radio frequency) signal information is generated from the encoder <b>91</b> and further transmitted out through the signal transmitting unit <b>92</b> by surface acoustic waves (SAW). It is meant the wireless transmitter <b>90</b> is capable of sending out the RF control signals including a Power On/Off controlled RF signal by pressing the switch SW<b>5</b>, a lamp tilting in vertical direction controlled RF signal by pressing the switch SW<b>3</b> or SW<b>4</b>, and a lamp rotating in a horizontal direction controlled RF signal by pressing the switch SW<b>1</b> or SW<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Therefore, while the vehicle or the boat is parked, the wireless transmitter <b>90</b> shall be portable to a distance away from the vehicle or the boat to operate the searchlight <b>15</b> of the invention by wireless remotely control.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> is assembled on the electrical cable <b>70</b> with its assembling position outside and away from the lamp housing <b>20</b> and the base means <b>30</b>, which is particularly designed to have two useful purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">For the first useful purpose of the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> is to control the leads <b>71</b>, <b>72</b> or <b>73</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> to be in open circuit or close circuit so that the wireless remote-controlled searchlight <b>15</b> shall be operated by manual remotely control, while the electrical cable <b>70</b> is supplied a 12-volt DC power source from the vehicle through the plug <b>75</b> or from the boat battery.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">For the second useful purpose of the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> is used to install a RF receiver <b>81</b> to receive the RF control signals transmitted from the separated portable wireless transmitter <b>90</b> including the Power On/Off controlled RF signal, the lamp tilting in vertical direction controlled RF signal or the lamp rotating in a horizontal direction controlled RF signal. And, due to the RF receiver <b>81</b> installed inside the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b>, the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> is also capable of controlling the leads <b>71</b>, <b>72</b> or <b>73</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> to be in open circuit or close circuit by wireless remotely control from the separated portable wireless transmitter <b>90</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">To achieve the two useful purposes mentioned above, the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> is designed to have a four-way directional control switch SW<b>1</b>, SW<b>2</b>, SW<b>3</b> and SW<b>4</b>, an on/off switch SW<b>5</b>, a RF receiver <b>81</b>, a microcontroller (MCU) <b>82</b> with ROM or EEPROM, a hand controlled circuit <b>83</b>, a relay actuated circuit <b>84</b> and a motor actuated circuit <b>85</b>. In addition, a current voltage regulator is adapted to convert 12-volt DC power source into a 5-volt DC current power which is required by the RF receiver <b>81</b>, the MCU <b>82</b>, the ROM or EEPROM, and the hand controlled circuit <b>83</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The RF receiver <b>81</b> is installed inside the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b>, and which function is to receive the identification code and the RF signal transmitted from the wireless transmitter <b>90</b> and subsequently send the received identification code and RF signal to the input port of the MCU <b>82</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The MCU <b>82</b> is an IC component that independently carries out specific control functions and integrates related circuits for the central processing unit (CPU), read-on memory (ROM) or electrically erasable programmable read-on memory (EEPROM), random access memory, I/O control circuit and CTC timer on a single chip.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Since the ROM or EEPROM of the MCU <b>82</b> contains the information of the identification code and the corresponding decoding for the received RF control signals transmitted from the wireless transmitter <b>90</b>, therefore, after the identification code received by the receiver <b>81</b> is confirmed, the MCU <b>82</b> will base on the input corresponding received RF signals and the decoded corresponding control signals to output a corresponding controlling signal to the relay actuated circuit <b>84</b> or the motor actuated circuit <b>85</b>, or both.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The relay actuated circuit <b>84</b> is functioned to have the leads <b>71</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> normally kept in open circuit, and the leads <b>71</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> is to become either in open circuit or in close circuit only if a related power on/off controlling signal had output from the MCU <b>82</b> to control the relay actuated circuit <b>84</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">By wireless remotely control, while the receiver <b>81</b> is received the Power On/Off controlled RF signal transmitted from the wireless transmitter <b>90</b>, it is meant the bulb of the lamp means <b>40</b> shall be illuminated for searchlight according to the fact that the relay actuated circuit <b>84</b> is controlled by the MCU <b>82</b> to be in close circuit. Otherwise, the bulb of the lamp means <b>40</b> is not illuminated when the relay actuated circuit <b>84</b> is further controlled by the MCU <b>82</b> to be in open circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Similarly, the motor actuated circuit <b>85</b> is functioned to have the leads <b>72</b> and <b>73</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> normally kept in open circuit, and the lead <b>72</b> or the lead <b>73</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> is to become either in open circuit or in close circuit only if a related tilting controlled signal or rotating controlled signal had output from the MCU <b>82</b> to actuate the motor actuated circuit <b>85</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">By wireless remotely control, while the receiver <b>81</b> is received the lamp tilting in vertical direction or rotating in a horizontal direction controlled RF signal transmitted from the wireless transmitter <b>90</b>, it is meant either the reversible gear motor <b>51</b> of vertical drive means <b>50</b> shall be actuated for vertically driving the lamp means <b>40</b> or the reversible gear motor <b>61</b> of horizontal drive means <b>60</b> shall be actuated for horizontal driving the lamp means <b>40</b>, according to the fact that the motor actuated circuit <b>85</b> is to have the lead <b>72</b> or the lead <b>73</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> become in close circuit until to be in open circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">By manual remotely control, the hand controlled circuit <b>83</b> is adapted to actuate the relay actuated circuit <b>84</b> and/or the motor actuated circuit <b>85</b>. While one of the four-way directional control switch SW<b>1</b>, SW<b>2</b>, SW<b>3</b> and SW<b>4</b> of the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> is selectively pressed, the motor actuated circuit <b>85</b> is to have the lead <b>72</b> or the lead <b>73</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> become in close circuit to execute either tilting or rotating the lamp means <b>40</b> by hand.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">And, while the on/off switch SW<b>5</b> of the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> is pressed, an executed signal to have the bulb of the lamp means <b>40</b> in illumination is send to the input port of the MCU <b>82</b>, and then a related power on/off controlling signal shall output from the MCU <b>82</b> to control the relay actuated circuit <b>84</b> to have the leads <b>71</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> to become in close circuit. While the on/off switch SW<b>5</b> of the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> is pressed again, the MCU <b>82</b> shall further control the relay actuated circuit <b>84</b> to have the leads <b>71</b> of the electrical cable <b>70</b> to become in open circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In the meantime, the microcontroller MCU <b>82</b> may add a learning circuit with a learning function, so that if the wireless transmitter <b>90</b> is missing or lost, then the identification code can be inputted for a new wireless transmitter <b>90</b> to replace the original one.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Another preferred embodiment of wireless remote-controlled searchlight <b>15</b> of this present invention is further provided with a waterproof cover <b>29</b> which is securely assembled on the lamp housing <b>20</b> and positioned in front of the lamp means <b>40</b> to cover the gap existed due to the lamp means <b>40</b> installed inside the lamp housing <b>20</b> with vertical rotational movement.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">With the waterproof cover <b>29</b>, the wireless remote-controlled searchlight <b>15</b> of this present invention has function of preventing rain water from seeping into the interior of the searchlight <b>15</b>, so that the searchlight <b>15</b> of the invention shall be always kept in normal use under stress of weather.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Due to the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> assembled on the electrical cable <b>70</b> with a assembling position outside and away from the lamp housing <b>20</b> and the base means <b>30</b>, the RF receiver <b>81</b> installed inside the hand-held manipulator <b>80</b> shall be prevented from radio interference caused from the vertical drive means <b>50</b> and horizontal drive means <b>60</b>, so that this present invention has the advantage of being easy to wireless remotely control with great precision.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A wireless remote-controlled searchlight comprising:
<claim-text>an electric cable with a plug and three leads to supply power source to the searchlight;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lamp housing constituted by an upper housing and a lower housing with an integrally formed ring gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base means for mounting the lamp housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lamp means for pivotedly mounting in the lamp housing for vertical movement, which includes a bulb housing with a bulb connected by leads of the electric cable and a vertical gear member integrally formed on the back of the bulb housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a vertical drive means mounted in the lamp housing for vertically driving the lamp means, which includes a reversible gear motor connected by leads of the electric cable having an output shaft with a pinion means for engaging the vertical gear member of the lamp means;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a horizontal drive means mounted in the base means for driving the lamp means and lamp housing in a horizontal plane, which includes a reversible gear motor connected by leads of the electric cable having an output shaft with a pinion means for engaging the ring gear of the lamp housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a separated portable wireless transmitter adapted to transmit a Power On/Off controlled RF signal, a lamp tilting in vertical direction controlled RF signal or a lamp rotating in a horizontal direction controlled RF signal, the wireless transmitter comprising an on/off switch, a four-way directional control switch, an encoder and a signal transmitting unit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a hand-held manipulator connected to the electrical cable and positioned outside and away from the lamp housing and the base means, the hand-held manipulator comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>a hand controlled circuit adapted to manually and remotely control tilting or rotating the lamp means or power on/off to the bulb of the lamp means;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a four-way directional control switch SW<b>1</b>, SW<b>2</b>, SW<b>3</b> and SW<b>4</b> configured to, when pressed by hand through the hand controlled circuit, execute either tilting or rotating the lamp means;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an on/off switch SW<b>5</b> configured to, when pressed by hand through the hand controlled circuit, have the bulb of the lamp means to be illuminated for searchlight or not;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a RF receiver installed inside the handheld manipulator to receive the controlled RF signals transmitted from the separate portable wireless transmitter;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a MCU to output a power on/off controlling signal, a tilting controlled signal or a rotating controlled signal according to the input corresponding received RF signals from the RF receiver or an executed signal sent from the hand controlled circuit while the on/off switch SW<b>5</b> being processed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a relay actuated circuit configured such that the leads of the electrical cable connected to the bulb of the lamp means are normally kept in an open circuit state and are put in a closed circuit state only if the power on/off controlling signal is output from the MCU to control the relay actuated circuit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a motor actuated circuit configured such that the leads of the electrical cable respectively connected to the reversible gear motor of the vertical drive means or the horizontal drive means are normally kept in an open circuit state and are put in a closed circuit state only if either the tilting controlled signal or the rotating controlled signal is output from the MCU or while one of the switches SW<b>1</b>, SW<b>2</b>, SW<b>3</b> and SW<b>4</b> is pressed to have the hand controlled circuit to actuate the motor actuated circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The wireless remote-controlled searchlight as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a waterproof cover is securely assembled on the lamp housing and positioned in front of the lamp means to prevent water from seeping into the interior of the searchlight.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The wireless remote-controlled searchlight as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the MCU has a learning circuit with a learning function.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
