<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297369-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297369</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10814571</doc-number>
<date>20040331</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>360</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>427358</main-classification>
<further-classification>427356</further-classification>
<further-classification>427164</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Process for micro-grooving a polymer alignment layer for a liquid crystal display</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3919377</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dow et al.</name>
<date>19751100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>264147</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5705096</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kano et al.</name>
<date>19980100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2522994</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0035231</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Epstein et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359834</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0150141</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chao et al.</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0050187</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hirai et al.</name>
<date>20060300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349  5</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>57192926</doc-number>
<date>19821100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>58-100121</doc-number>
<date>19830600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>58100121</doc-number>
<date>19830600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>04372931</doc-number>
<date>19921200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>6034975</doc-number>
<date>19940200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/US2005/010774</doc-number>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>Lee, E. S. et al., “Control of the LC Alignment Using a Stamped Morphology Method and Its Application to LCD's”, May 16, 1993, SID International Symposium—Digest of Technical Papers, pp. 957-960.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>17</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>427358</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>427356</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>427164</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>18</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050221009</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051006</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Clemons</last-name>
<first-name>Gregory S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chandler</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Blakely, Sokoloff, Taylor &amp; Zafman LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Intel Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Santa Clara</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Parker</last-name>
<first-name>Fred J.</first-name>
<department>1762</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A process is disclosed for imprinting microgrooves in a polymer layer to create an alignment layer for a liquid crystal display. In one embodiment, the process comprises providing a transparent substrate having a polymer film applied on one side thereof, providing a tool having a contact surface, the contact surface having a plurality of microgrooves formed thereon, and pressing the contact surface against the polymer film. Additional embodiments are also disclosed and claimed.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="111.00mm" wi="164.76mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="262.30mm" wi="196.17mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="247.99mm" wi="197.44mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="215.39mm" wi="181.78mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="240.20mm" wi="168.40mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="259.50mm" wi="179.49mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="208.70mm" wi="183.39mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="257.47mm" wi="177.63mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="224.03mm" wi="193.63mm" file="US07297369-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to liquid crystal displays and in particular, but not exclusively, to the formation of microgrooves in an alignment layer of a liquid crystal display.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Liquid crystal cells are commonly used as part of liquid crystal displays associated with electronic devices such as televisions, watches, calculators, computer displays, and mobile telephones. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref> illustrate, respectively, a side elevation and a plan view of an embodiment of a liquid crystal (LC) display cell <b>100</b>. The LC display cell <b>100</b> comprises a die <b>102</b> having a dam <b>106</b> formed on a surface <b>104</b> thereof. The dam <b>106</b> forms a sealed perimeter around a portion of the surface <b>104</b>. A transparent cover <b>108</b> having surfaces <b>112</b> and <b>113</b> is attached and sealed around its perimeter to the dam <b>106</b> such that a small portion of the cover <b>108</b> overhangs the dam. The surface <b>104</b> of the die <b>102</b>, the dam <b>106</b>, and the transparent cover <b>108</b> define a sealed volume <b>116</b> of depth d that is then filled with liquid crystals to complete the liquid crystal cell. In one embodiment the volume <b>116</b> has a depth d of approximately one micron, although the distance d can range from a distance on the order of millimeters to a distance on the order of micrometers. In the embodiment shown, the LC cell <b>100</b> is attached to a substrate <b>103</b>, which in one embodiment is a ceramic substrate but in other embodiments may be something different. The ceramic substrate <b>103</b> can include other components not shown here, such as heat sinks, electronic circuits and/or components, and the like. The die <b>102</b> is electrically connected to the substrate <b>103</b> via bond pads <b>120</b> and wire bonds <b>124</b>. The overhanging portion of the transparent cover <b>108</b> is electrically connected to the ceramic substrate, or to some circuitry thereon, by a crossover ground <b>126</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref> illustrates the structure of the transparent cover <b>108</b> of the LC cell <b>100</b>. The cover <b>108</b> includes a transparent substrate <b>110</b> with an alignment layer <b>117</b>. The alignment layer is applied to a surface <b>115</b> of the substrate <b>110</b>. Although not shown, a transparent electrically conductive layer is usually applied to the substrate; the conductive layer is commonly applied to the surface <b>115</b> of the substrate (i.e., it is sandwiched between the substrate <b>110</b> and the alignment layer <b>117</b>), but in other embodiments can also be applied to the outer surface <b>113</b> of the substrate. The electrically conductive layer functions as an electrode, so that an electric field can be applied to the liquid crystals within the volume <b>116</b> to cause the liquid crystals to alter their orientation and thus alter the display. In one embodiment, the electrical signal is routed through the die via traces connected to the bond pads <b>120</b> and flows through the liquid crystal distance d to the electrically conductive layer as it aligns the liquid crystals to display the image. The electrically conductive layer is grounded back to the substrate <b>103</b> via a cross over ground connection <b>126</b>. The side of the alignment layer <b>112</b> that is in contact with the liquid crystals in the volume <b>116</b> usually includes a plurality of microgrooves <b>118</b> therein. The purpose of the microgrooves <b>118</b> is to provide an initial alignment to the liquid crystals within the volume <b>116</b>; in most cases, the initial alignment of the liquid crystals is parallel to the microgrooves. It is preferable that the initial alignment of the liquid crystal has a substantial penetration depth—that is, the alignment layer should cause the liquid crystals in the volume <b>116</b> to become initially aligned in the desired direction throughout the entire depth d of the liquid crystal (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Currently, the microgrooves <b>114</b> in the alignment layer are formed by hand-rubbing the layer <b>108</b> with some sort of abrasive material such as rayon pile cloth with a 600 μm fiber length, 15 μm fiber diameter and a thread count of 32,000 thread per square centimeter. In addition to the less-than-ideal quality of the resulting microgrooves, the hand-rubbing method for forming the microgrooves has several other disadvantages. Among other things, it does not result in a uniform and consistent groove pattern, which can affect the penetration depth of the alignment. Hand rubbing is also time intensive and labor intensive, which leads to increased costs for liquid crystal displays. The hand-rubbing method is difficult to adapt to a manufacturing environment, and also makes it difficult or impossible to realize economies of scale in the manufacturing of the liquid crystal displays.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Non-limiting and non-exhaustive embodiments of the present invention are described with reference to the following figures, wherein like reference numerals refer to like parts throughout the various views unless otherwise specified.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref> are a side elevation and a plan view, respectively, of an embodiment of a liquid crystal display.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref> is an enlarged side elevation of an embodiment of a transparent cover for a liquid crystal display, the cover having an alignment layer thereon.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is an enlarged side elevation of an embodiment of a microtool having a pattern of microgrooves therein.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is an enlarged plan view of an embodiment of a contact surface of a tool like the one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-3D</figref> are enlarged cross-sections of various embodiments of microgrooves that could be used with an embodiment of a tool such as the one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A-2B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A-4F</figref> illustrate an embodiment of a process for imprinting microgrooves on a polymer film applied to a glass substrate such as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref> using a tool such as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A-2B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref> illustrate an alternative embodiment of a process for imprinting microgrooves on a polymer film applied to a glass substrate such as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> using a tool such as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE ILLUSTRATED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Embodiments of a process for imprinting microgrooves in a polymer layer to create an alignment layer such as those used in liquid crystal displays are described herein. In the following description, numerous specific details are described to provide a thorough understanding of embodiments of the invention. One skilled in the relevant art will recognize, however, that the invention can be practiced without one or more of the specific details, or with other methods, components, materials, etc. In other instances, well-known structures, materials, or operations are not shown or described in detail to avoid obscuring aspects of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Reference throughout this specification to “one embodiment” or “an embodiment” means that a particular feature, structure, or characteristic described in connection with the embodiment is included in at least one embodiment of the present invention. Thus, appearances of the phrases “in one embodiment” or “in an embodiment” in this specification do not necessarily all refer to the same embodiment. Furthermore, the particular features, structures, or characteristics may be combined in any suitable manner in one or more embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A-2B</figref> illustrate an embodiment of a microtool <b>200</b> for imprinting a plurality of microgrooves in an alignment layer. The tool <b>200</b> is referred to as a “microtool” because of the small dimensions of the features it will be used to pattern; the tool itself is not necessarily small, although it can be. FIG. <b>2</b>A is a side elevation illustrating the basic construction of the tool <b>200</b>, which includes a contact surface <b>202</b> having a plurality of microgrooves <b>204</b> formed therein. In one embodiment, the tool <b>200</b> is made using Nickel (Ni), although in other embodiments different materials or combinations of materials can be used. In one embodiment, the microgrooves <b>204</b> can be etched or otherwise put on the contact surface <b>202</b> using conventional means such as lithography. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a plan view of the contact surface <b>202</b> of the tool <b>200</b>. The contact surface <b>202</b> of the tool <b>200</b> includes a pattern <b>208</b> having a plurality of microgrooves therein. The pattern has a breadth B and depth H that will, in one embodiment, correspond to the size of the dam in the LC cell for which the tool will be used to create microgrooves in the alignment layer.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-3D</figref> are enlargements of the circular area <b>206</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> illustrating various embodiments of cross-sectional profiles that the microgrooves <b>204</b> can take. The cross-sectional profiles of the microgrooves created in the polymer film will, of course, correspond to the cross-sectional profile of the microgrooves <b>204</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> illustrates microgrooves having a cross-sectional profile that is a triangular or “sawtooth” pattern. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> illustrates microgrooves with a cross-sectional profile that is square. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3C and 3D</figref> illustrate two variations of microgrooves, both with a cross-sectional profile that can be described as a “spaced triangular profile” or “spaced sawtooth profile.” In one embodiment, the widths W of individual grooves can be on the order of nanometers, while the separation P of the individual grooves (also known as the “pitch”) can also be on the order of nanometers. In one particular embodiment, for example, the grooves can have a width W of 100 nm and a pitch P of 150 nm. Substantially larger and/or smaller groove widths and pitches are, of course, possible in other embodiments; both the widths and pitches of the microgrooves can vary from distances on the order of millimeters to distances on the order of angstroms, depending on the application.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In each embodiment of the cross-sectional profiles shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-3D</figref>, the microgrooves <b>204</b> have depth A. In most cases, the depth A will be less than or equal to the thickness t of the polymer film <b>410</b> in which the alignment layer will be created (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>). In other cases, however, a depth A greater than the polymer film thickness t can be used to create a desired profile. For example, microgrooves having a cross-sectional profile similar to that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3D</figref> can be created using a tool <b>200</b> with microgrooves having the cross-sectional profile shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> if the depth A is greater than the thickness t of the polymer film <b>410</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Although only a small number of microgroove cross-sectional profiles are shown herein, the cross-sectional profile of the microgrooves may take other forms that are not shown here. Additionally, all microgrooves <b>204</b> in the tool—and thus all the corresponding microgrooves formed in the alignment layer—need not have the same cross-sectional profile, but can include combinations of different cross-sectional profiles and/or different depths A. Also, the microgrooves <b>204</b> need not have a regular, constant depth; microgroove patterns in which the depths of individual grooves vary from each other are entirely possible.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A-4F</figref> illustrate an embodiment of a process for imprinting microgrooves in a polymer layer. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref> illustrate the application of a polymer layer <b>410</b> onto a surface <b>406</b> of a transparent substrate <b>402</b>. In one embodiment, the transparent substrate <b>402</b> can be glass, but in other embodiments different types of transparent substrate may be used. Also in one embodiment the polymer film is a polyimide (PI); an example of a commercially available polyimide is Nissan RN1332, which is available from the Nissan Corporation of Tokyo, Japan. In other embodiments the polymer film can be something else, such as a polyvinylalcohol (PVOH); examples of commercially available PVOHs include Nissan SE150 and SE12710, both of which are also available from the Nissan Corporation of Tokyo, Japan. In still other embodiments, other polymers not listed or mentioned here can be used. In the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>, a spray unit <b>404</b> sprays a suitable polymer onto the surface <b>406</b> until the desired film thickness t is achieved, at which time the spraying stops. In other embodiments, the film <b>410</b> can be applied to the surface <b>406</b> by other means, such as spin coating. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> illustrates the result of applying the polymer film to the surface of the transparent substrate <b>402</b>, which is the substrate with a polymer film <b>410</b> thereon. The polymer layer is preferably of uniform thickness t. The transparent substrate <b>402</b> generally has a thickness on the order of millimeters, while the polymer film <b>410</b> has a thickness in the micrometer or nanometer range. In one particular embodiment, for example, the substrate <b>402</b> has a thickness of about 0.5 mm, while the polymer film has a thickness t of about 50 nm.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> illustrates conditioning the polymer film <b>410</b> to better receive an imprint of microgrooves from an imprinting tool. The type of conditioning required will depend mostly on the polymer chosen for the polymer film <b>410</b>. In the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>, the transparent substrate <b>402</b> and polymer film <b>410</b> are inserted into an oven or autoclave <b>412</b>, so that the temperature of the polymer film <b>410</b> can be increased. By increasing the polymer film's temperature, it can become more receptive to imprinting of microgrooves by a tool. In other embodiments, however, conditioning the polymer film may require something different. For example, the polymer film may require partial or complete curing before the microgrooves can be imprinted; this would be the case if the polymer is liquid upon application to the surface <b>406</b> and prior to curing, or if the polymer film otherwise has very low viscosity. In still other embodiments, it can be possible to imprint the microgrooves in the polymer film without doing anything further to the polymer film after its application to the substrate; in such cases, conditioning the polymer film amounts to doing nothing. Thus, conditioning the polymer film prior to imprinting is optional, depending on the exact polymer chosen for the polymer film.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4D-4F</figref> illustrate an embodiment of a process for imprinting microgrooves in a polymer layer <b>410</b> to form an alignment layer. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4D</figref>, a tool <b>414</b> having a contact surface <b>416</b> with a pattern therein comprising a plurality of microgrooves <b>418</b> is brought down onto the polymer film <b>410</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4E</figref>, the contact surface <b>416</b> of the tool, and thus the microgrooves <b>418</b> in the tool, are brought in contact with the polymer film <b>410</b> and, if necessary, a force F is applied to the tool to press the microgrooves <b>418</b> of the tool into the polymer film, creating a corresponding pattern of microgrooves <b>420</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4F</figref>) in the polymer film and turning the polymer layer into an alignment layer. The magnitude of the force F needed to imprint the microgrooves in the polymer layer will vary depending on the polymer used and its physical state at the time of imprinting; in some cases little or no force will need to be applied, while in others considerable force may need to be applied. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4F</figref>, the contact surface of the tool is removed from the polymer layer, leaving the microgrooves <b>420</b> behind in the polymer layer <b>410</b>. In some embodiments of the process, the polymer layer <b>410</b> may require further processing after imprinting. For example, if the microgrooves were imprinted after a partial curing of the polymer layer, then further curing will be necessary to further harden the polymer layer <b>410</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref> illustrate an alternative embodiment of a process for imprinting microgrooves in a polymer layer. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5B</figref> depict parts of the process similar to those shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4D-4E</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, a tool <b>414</b> having a contact surface <b>416</b> with a pattern therein comprising a plurality of microgrooves <b>418</b> is brought down onto the polymer film <b>410</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>, the contact surface <b>416</b> of the tool, and thus the microgrooves <b>418</b> in the tool, are brought in contact with the polymer film <b>410</b> and a force F is applied to the tool if necessary to press the microgrooves <b>418</b> of the tool into the polymer film, creating a corresponding pattern of microgrooves <b>420</b> in the polymer film and turning the polymer layer into an alignment layer.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref> is a top plan view of what is shown in elevation view in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>. The contact surface <b>416</b> of the tool <b>414</b> is in contact with the polymer film <b>410</b>, so that the microgrooves <b>418</b> on the contact surface of the tool <b>414</b> create microgrooves <b>20</b> in the polymer film. In this embodiment, however, while the contact surface <b>416</b> remains in contact with the polymer film, the entire tool is oscillated, either along the microgrooves in the direction of the arrows <b>422</b> or perpendicular to the microgrooves in the direction of the arrows <b>424</b>. The amplitude of the tool's oscillation will likely be very small, the intent being to better form the microgrooves in the polymer layer by, for example, polishing the microgrooves through the oscillation of the tool or removing polymer material displaced during imprinting. In an alternative embodiment, an abrasive substance may be applied to the microgrooves <b>318</b> of the tool, so that there will be more polishing and/or forming action when the tool is oscillated. The abrasiveness of the substance applied in the microgrooves will depend on such factors as the hardness of the polymer film <b>310</b> and the amount of forming and/or polishing required.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The above description of illustrated embodiments of the invention, including what is described in the Abstract, is not intended to be exhaustive or to limit the invention to the precise forms disclosed. While specific embodiments of, and examples for, the invention are described herein for illustrative purposes, those skilled in the relevant art will recognize that various equivalent modifications are possible within the scope of the invention. These modifications can be made to the invention in light of the above detailed description.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The terms used in the following claims should not be construed to limit the invention to the specific embodiments disclosed in the specification and the claims. Rather, the scope of the invention is to be determined entirely by the following claims, which are to be construed in accordance with established doctrines of claim interpretation.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A process comprising:
<claim-text>applying a polymer film to a transparent substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>optionally conditioning the polymer film; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>imprinting a plurality of microgrooves in the polymer film by pressing a contact surface of a tool against the polymer film and oscillating the contact surface in the plane of the polymer film, the contact surface having a pattern formed therein including a plurality of microgrooves.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the polymer film comprises a polyimide (PI) or a polyvinylalcohol (PVOH).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the transparent substrate comprises glass.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein applying the polymer film to the transparent substrate comprises spraying or spin-coating the polymer film onto the transparent substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the plurality of microgrooves in the pattern have a selected profile.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the selected profile is a square profile, a triangular profile, a spaced triangular profile, or a combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein conditioning the polymer film comprises raising the temperature of the polymer film.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein conditioning the polymer film comprises at least partially curing the polymer film.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the microgrooves have an abrasive material embedded therein.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A process comprising:
<claim-text>providing a transparent substrate having a polymer film applied on one side thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a tool having a contact surface, the contact surface having a plurality of microgrooves formed thereon;</claim-text>
<claim-text>pressing the contact surface against the polymer film; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>oscillating the contact surface in a plane of the polymer film.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the polymer film comprises a polyimide (PI) or a polyvinylalcohol (PVOH).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the transparent substrate comprises glass.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the plurality of microgrooves have a selected profile.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the selected profile is a square profile, a triangular profile, a spaced triangular profile, or a combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising optionally conditioning the polymer film.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein conditioning the polymer film comprises raising the temperature of the polymer film.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein conditioning the polymer film comprises at least partially curing the polymer film.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
