<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297638-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297638</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10783940</doc-number>
<date>20040220</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2003-0011110</doc-number>
<date>20030221</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>135</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>461</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>302</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438717</main-classification>
<further-classification>438720</further-classification>
<further-classification>438721</further-classification>
<further-classification>438724</further-classification>
<further-classification>438725</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Method for manufacturing a semiconductor device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5637151</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schulz</name>
<date>19970600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>134  2</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5759746</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Azuma et al.</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>430313</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6159860</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yang et al.</name>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438706</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6383723</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Iyer et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>430327</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6686668</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Nesbit et al.</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257300</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6753247</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Okoroanyanwu et al.</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438623</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>12</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>15</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050032371</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050210</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>An</last-name>
<first-name>Ju-Jin</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yongin</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Soo-Woong</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suwon</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>F. Chau &amp; Associates, LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung Electronics Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Suwon-Si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Deo</last-name>
<first-name>Duy-Vu N</first-name>
<department>1765</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device comprises: forming a conductive film on a substrate; forming an anti-reflective layer on the conductive film; cleaning oxide residues on the anti-reflective layer using a first cleaning solution; cleaning the oxide residues on the anti-reflective layer using a second cleaning solution; forming a photoresist pattern on the anti-reflective layer; and patterning the conductive film using the photoresist pattern.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="58.84mm" wi="122.94mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="223.69mm" wi="121.33mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="106.60mm" wi="120.99mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="223.52mm" wi="124.21mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="107.78mm" wi="96.10mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="224.03mm" wi="124.54mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="218.52mm" wi="131.91mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="236.47mm" wi="137.67mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="198.71mm" wi="135.81mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="243.84mm" wi="132.67mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="231.82mm" wi="143.17mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="233.34mm" wi="134.28mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="243.84mm" wi="136.99mm" file="US07297638-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a method for manufacturing a semiconductor device; more specifically, a method of forming patterns in semiconductor device.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Generally, semiconductor memory devices comprise a volatile memory device and a non-volatile memory device. The volatile memory devices comprise a dynamic random access memory (DRAM) device and a static random access memory device (SRAM). The non-volatile memory devices comprise an erasable programmable read only memory (EPROM) and an electrically erasable programmable ROM (EEPROM).</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The volatile memory device usually has one transistor and one capacitor. Thus, for example, a 16M-DRAM device has about 16,000,000 transistors and about 16,000,000 capacitors per unit chip. A capacitor of the DRAM device includes a storage node, a cell plate, and a dielectric layer.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The non-volatile memory device has a vertically stacked (multi-layered) gate structure including a floating gate formed on a semiconductor substrate. The vertically stacked gate structure of the non-volatile memory device typically comprises at least one tunnel oxide film or at least one interlayer dielectrics (ILD), and a control gate formed over the floating gate or near the floating gate.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Recently, widths of wirings and distances between the wirings have been greatly reduced, and minute and more intricate patterns are warranted as the volatile and non-volatile memory devices became more highly integrated. To form the minute patterns, minute photoresist patterns needed to be formed using an anti-reflective layer (ARL) because the ARL minimizes interference that may be caused by underlying films. Generally, conductive patterns of the memory device have been formed using minute photoresist patterns.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Methods for forming patterns of a volatile memory device or a non-volatile memory device using an anti-reflective layer are disclosed in Korean Patent Laid Open Publication No. 2002-34772, U.S. Pat. Nos. 6,174,816 and 6,380,611 (issued to Zhiping Yin et. al.), and U.S. Pat. No. 5,948,703 (issued to Lewis Shen et. al.).</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A to 1C</figref> are cross-sectional views illustrating a conventional method of forming patterns of a semiconductor device.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, and <b>1</b>C, after an insulation film <b>15</b> mainly including oxide is formed on a semiconductor substrate <b>10</b>, a conductive film <b>20</b> including polysilicon, metal or metal compound is formed on the insulation film <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">An anti-reflective layer (ARL) <b>25</b> is formed on the conductive film <b>20</b>. The ARL <b>25</b> includes silicon oxide, silicon nitride or silicon oxynitride.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">After a photoresist film (not shown) is formed on the ARL <b>25</b>, the photoresist film is patterned to form photoresist patterns <b>30</b> for the formation of conductive patterns <b>35</b> using a photo process.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The ARL <b>25</b> is etched using the photoresist pattern <b>30</b> as an etching mask to form an ARL pattern <b>40</b>. The conductive film <b>20</b> is successively etched to form the conductive patterns <b>35</b> on the insulation film <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The photoresist patterns <b>30</b> and the ARL pattern <b>40</b> are removed from the conductive patterns <b>35</b>, thereby completing the conductive pattern <b>35</b>. The conductive patterns <b>35</b> serve as a bit line or a word line of a semiconductor device.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">However, in the above-described method of forming the pattern, oxide residues are generated from a purge gas containing nitrogen oxide that is used during a purge process for forming the ARL. Because the oxide residues may not be completely removed from the ARL through a pre-treating process of forming the photoresist pattern, the photoresist patterns may be lifted from the ARL or the photoresist patterns may cling to each other. Thus, the conductive patterns may be lifted or connected to each other in accordance with the lifted or clung photoresist patterns. The conductive patterns lifted or connected cause failures in the semiconductor device. This problem will be more apparent by viewing <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A</figref>, <b>2</b>B and <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> are cross-sectional views of a conventional method for forming patterns in semiconductor device. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an electron microscopic picture showing conductive patterns formed according to the conventional method.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, a purge gas generally including nitrogen oxide is introduced to purge the ARL <b>25</b> during a formation of the ARL <b>25</b>. Then, oxide residues <b>45</b> are generated on the ARL <b>25</b> due to the purge gas. When the photoresist patterns <b>30</b> are formed on the ARL <b>25</b> on which the oxide residues <b>45</b> exist, an adhesion strength between the photoresist pattern <b>30</b> and the ARL <b>25</b> may be reduced. As a result, the photoresist patterns <b>30</b> may be lifted from the ARL <b>30</b> or adjacent photoresist patterns <b>30</b> may cling to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2B and 3</figref>, the conductive patterns <b>35</b> are formed by etching the conductive film <b>20</b> using the lifted or clung photoresist patterns <b>30</b> as an etching mask. The conductive patterns <b>35</b> may not have desired shapes and dimensions because the conductive patterns <b>35</b> may not be formed or adjacent conductive patterns <b>35</b> may cling to each other. These conductive patterns <b>35</b> cause the failure of the semiconductor device, and manufacturing yield is reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">A need therefore exists to provide a method of forming patterns in semiconductor device that prevents the lifting and clinging of conductive patterns.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">According to one embodiment of the invention, a method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device comprises: forming a conductive film on a substrate; forming an anti-reflective layer on the conductive film; cleaning oxide residues on the anti-reflective layer using a first cleaning solution; cleaning the oxide residues on the anti-reflective layer using a second cleaning solution; forming a photoresist pattern on the anti-reflective layer; and patterning the conductive film using the photoresist pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Preferably, cleaning oxide residues on the anti-reflective layer using a first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid is performed at a temperature of about 70° C. for about 3 to about 10 minutes. Cleaning the oxide residues on the anti-reflective layer using a second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b> is performed at a temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 5 to about 15 minutes.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">According to another embodiment of the invention, a method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device comprises: forming an insulation film on a substrate; forming a conductive film on the insulation film; forming a hard mask layer on the conductive film; cleaning oxide residues on the hard mask layer using a first cleaning solution; cleaning the oxide residues on the hard mask layer using a second cleaning solution; forming a photoresist pattern on the hard mask layer; forming a hard mask by patterning the hard mask layer using the photoresist pattern; and patterning the conductive film using the hard mask.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">According to another embodiment of the invention, a method of manufacturing a non-volatile memory device comprises: forming a tunnel oxide film on a semiconductor substrate; forming a first conductive film on the tunnel oxide film, the first conductive film being a floating gate of the non-volatile memory device; forming an ONO film on the first conductive film; forming a second conductive film on the ONO film, the second conductive film being a control gate of the non-volatile memory device; forming a metal silicide layer on the second conductive film; forming a hard mask layer on the metal silicide layer; cleaning oxide residues on the hard mask layer using a first cleaning solution; cleaning the oxide residues on the hard mask layer using a second cleaning solution; forming a photoresist pattern on the hard mask layer; forming a hard mask by patterning the hard mask layer using the photoresist pattern; and patterning the metal silicide layer, the second conductive film, the ONO film and the first conductive film using the hard mask.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Preferably, a thickness ratio among the first anti-reflective layer, the third oxide film and the second anti-reflective layer is about 1:10:2.5.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">According to another embodiment of the invention, a method of manufacturing a volatile memory device comprises: forming a transistor structure and a pad on a semiconductor substrate; forming an insulation film on the transistor structure and the pad; forming an anti-reflective layer on the insulation film; cleaning oxide residues on the anti-reflective layer using a first cleaning solution; cleaning the oxide residues on the anti-reflective layer using a second cleaning solution; forming photoresist pattern on the anti-reflection film; forming a contact hole exposing the pad by etching the anti-reflective layer and the insulation film using the photoresist pattern; and forming a contact plug electrically connected to the pad in the contact hole.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The above and other advantages of the present invention will become more apparently by describing in detail exemplary embodiments thereof with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A to 1C</figref> illustrate a conventional method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> are cross-sectional views illustrating a conventional method of forming the patterns in a semiconductor device;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an electron microscopic picture showing conductive patterns formed according to the conventional method of forming patterns of the semiconductor device;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A to 4D</figref> illustrate a method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A to 5D</figref> illustrate a method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device according to another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A to 6D</figref> illustrate a method of manufacturing a semiconductor device according to still another embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A to 7D</figref> illustrate a method of manufacturing a semiconductor device according to another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The invention now will be described more fully hereinafter with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which preferred embodiments of the invention are shown. This may, however, be embodied in many different forms and should not be construed as limited to the embodiments set forth herein.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In the drawings, the thickness of layers and regions are exaggerated for clarity. Like numerals refer to like elements throughout. It will be understood that when an element such as a layer, film, region, or substrate is referred to as being “on” another element, it can be directly on the other element or intervening elements may also be present. In contrast, when an element is referred to as being “directly on” another element, there are no intervening elements present.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The semiconductor device according to the invention will be described with reference to the drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A to 4D</figref> illustrate a method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>, an insulation film <b>105</b> including oxide or nitride is formed on a semiconductor substrate <b>100</b> using a chemical vapor deposition (CVD) process or an atomic layer deposition (ALD) process. The insulation film <b>105</b> includes an interlayer dielectric (ILD) (not shown) that is interposed between metal wirings of a semiconductor device. Additionally, the insulation film <b>105</b> includes an oxide film of a transistor (not shown) formed on the semiconductor substrate <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">After a conductive film <b>110</b> is formed on the insulation film <b>105</b>, an anti-reflective layer (ARL) <b>115</b> is formed on the conductive film <b>110</b>. The conductive film <b>110</b> will be patterned to form wiring patterns, electrode patterns or pad patterns in a semiconductor device. The conductive film <b>110</b> includes polysilicon, doped polysilicon, metal or metal silicide. The metal includes tungsten (W), aluminum (Al) or cobalt (Co). The metal silicide includes tungsten silicide (WSi<sub>x</sub>) or cobalt silicide (CoSi<sub>x</sub>). The ARL <b>115</b> includes silicon nitride, silicon oxide or silicon oxynitride.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">To form a photoresist film (not shown) on the ARL <b>115</b>, the semiconductor oxide residues from the hard mask layer using the second cleaning solution including SC substrate <b>100</b> having the ARL <b>115</b> formed thereon is purged in-situ using a purge gas containing nitrogen oxide such as nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O). As a result, oxide residues <b>120</b> are generated from the purge gas including nitrogen oxide, and the oxide residues <b>120</b> are formed on the ARL <b>115</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>, the oxide residues <b>120</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>) are removed from the ARL <b>115</b> using a first cleaning process and a second cleaning process. After the oxide residues <b>120</b> are removed from the ARL <b>115</b>, a photoresist film (not shown) is formed on the ARL <b>115</b>. The photoresist film is patterned to form photoresist patterns <b>125</b>. The photoresist patterns <b>125</b> are stably formed on the ARL <b>115</b> because there are no oxide residues on the ARL <b>115</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the first cleaning process, the oxide residues <b>120</b> are cleaned using a first cleaning solution at a low temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 3 to about 10 minutes. Preferably, the first cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 50° C. for about 5 minutes.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The first cleaning solution preferably includes sulfuric acid (H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). Then, the oxide residues <b>120</b> are removed from the ARL <b>115</b> using a second cleaning process. In the second cleaning process, the oxide residues <b>120</b> are completely removed from the ARL <b>115</b> using a second cleaning solution at a low temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 5 to about 15 minutes. Preferably, the second cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 50° C. for about 10 minutes. The second cleaning solution includes standard cleaning solution <b>1</b> (referred to as SC <b>1</b>) that includes ammonium hydroxide (NH<sub>4</sub>OH), hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) and deionized water (H<sub>2</sub>O) by a volume ratio of about 1:1:5. The first and second cleaning processes are performed in-situ. Compositions of the first and second cleaning solutions can be varied in accordance with a composition of the ARL <b>115</b> or the purge gas. Alternatively, the first cleaning solution may have an identical or similar composition to the second cleaning solution.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">In the conventional method of forming a pattern of a semiconductor device, oxide residues formed on an anti-reflective layer may not be removed because a pre-treating process for forming a photoresist pattern is merely performed for about 5 minutes. The remaining oxide residues may reduce a structural stability of the photoresist patterns formed thereon, thereby causing a lifting of the photoresist patterns or a clinging of the photoresist patterns. In the present invention, primary and secondary cleaning processes are performed in-situ to completely remove the oxide residues <b>120</b> on the ARL <b>115</b>. Thus, photoresist patterns can be stably formed on the ARL <b>115</b>. Therefore, conductive patterns having desired dimensions can be formed by the photoresist patterns that have improved structural stabilities because the lifting or the clinging of the photoresist patterns can be effectively prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Oxides may be formed on the ARL <b>115</b> by a nitrogen oxide used as a purge gas for forming the ARL <b>115</b>. The oxides may reduce the adhesion strength between the photoresist pattern <b>125</b> and the ARL <b>115</b>, thereby causing the lifting of the photoresist pattern <b>125</b> from the surface of the ARL <b>115</b>. To prevent the lifting of the photoresist pattern <b>125</b> and to improve the adhesion strength between the photoresist pattern <b>125</b> and the ARL <b>115</b>, the oxide residues <b>120</b> should be completely removed from the ARL <b>115</b>. Then, the photoresist pattern <b>125</b> can be stably formed on the ARL <b>125</b> due to the improved adhesion strength between the photoresist pattern <b>125</b> and the ARL <b>115</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>, the ARL <b>115</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>) and the conductive film <b>110</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>) are patterned using the photoresist patterns <b>125</b> as etching masks to form ARL patterns <b>135</b> and conductive patterns <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4D</figref>, the photoresist patterns <b>125</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>) and the ARL patterns <b>135</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>) are removed using an ashing process and a stripping process to complete the conductive patterns <b>130</b> on the substrate <b>100</b> including the insulation film <b>105</b> formed thereon. The conductive patterns <b>130</b> include wiring patterns, electrode patterns or pad patterns of the semiconductor device (all not shown). Alternatively, after the photoresist patterns <b>125</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>) are removed from the ARL patterns <b>135</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>), the conductive film <b>110</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>) is etched using the ARL patterns <b>135</b> as hard masks to form the conductive patterns <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A to 5D</figref> illustrate a method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device according to another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, a first oxide film <b>205</b> is formed on a semiconductor substrate <b>200</b> using a thermal oxidation process, a CVD process or an ALD process. The first oxide film <b>205</b> includes a gate oxide film of a transistor or a field oxide film defining an active region on the semiconductor substrate <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">After a conductive film <b>210</b> is formed on the first oxide film <b>205</b>, a first ARL <b>215</b> is formed on the conductive film <b>210</b>. The conductive film <b>210</b> will be patterned to form conductive patterns used as wiring patterns, gate electrode patterns or pad patterns of a semiconductor device. The conductive film <b>210</b> includes polysilicon, polysilicon doped with impurities, metal or metal silicide. The metal includes tungsten, aluminum or cobalt. The metal silicide includes tungsten silicide or cobalt silicide. The first ARL <b>215</b> includes silicon nitride, silicon oxide or silicon oxynitride.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">A second oxide film <b>220</b> and a second ARL <b>225</b> are successively formed on the first ARL <b>215</b>. The second oxide film <b>220</b> including oxide is formed using a CVD process. The second ARL <b>225</b> includes material identical to that of the first ARL <b>215</b> such as silicon nitride, silicon oxide or silicon oxynitride. The first ARL <b>215</b>, the second oxide film <b>220</b> and the second ARL <b>220</b> form together a hard mask layer <b>250</b> for etching the conductive film <b>210</b>. A thickness ratio among the first ARL <b>215</b>, the second oxide film <b>220</b> and the second ARL <b>220</b> is about 1:10:2.5. Interference effects caused by an underlying layer can be minimized during a photo process for forming photoresist patterns because double anti-reflective layers <b>215</b> and <b>225</b> are formed beneath and on the second oxide film <b>220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">To form a photoresist film (not shown) on the second ARL <b>225</b>, a purge process is performed in-situ forming the second ARL <b>225</b> using a purge gas including nitrogen oxide such as nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O). Oxide residues <b>230</b> are generated from the purge gas during the purge process and formed on the second ARL <b>225</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>, a first cleaning process is performed on the hard mask layer <b>250</b> having the oxide residues <b>230</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>) formed thereon using a first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid. The first cleaning process removes the oxide residues <b>230</b> from the second ARL <b>225</b>. The first cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 3 to about 10 minutes. Preferably, the first cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 50° C. for about 5 minutes.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Subsequently, a second cleaning process is performed in-situ on the hard mask layer <b>250</b> using a second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b>. The second cleaning process removes the oxide residues <b>230</b> from the second ARL <b>225</b>. The second cleaning process is performed in-situ at a low temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 5 to about 15 minutes. Preferable, the second cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 50° C. for about 10 minutes. A composition of the first cleaning solution and the second cleaning solution may vary in accordance with the composition of the second ARL <b>225</b> and the purge gas.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">After a photoresist film (not shown) is formed on the second ARL <b>225</b> using a spin coating process, the photoresist film is patterned to form photoresist patterns <b>235</b>. Conductive patterns <b>245</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>) are formed using the photoresist patterns <b>235</b>. The photoresist patterns <b>235</b> are stably formed on the second ARL <b>225</b> due to improved adhesion strength between the photoresist patterns <b>235</b> and the second ARL <b>225</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5B and 5C</figref>, the second ARL <b>225</b>, the second oxide film <b>220</b> and the first ARL <b>215</b> are successively etched using the photoresist patterns <b>235</b> as etching masks, thereby forming a hard mask <b>270</b> including a first ARL pattern <b>255</b>, a second oxide film pattern <b>260</b> and a second ARL pattern <b>265</b>. The photoresist patterns <b>235</b> are removed using an ashing and a stripping processes.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">The conductive film <b>210</b> is etched using the hard mask <b>270</b> as an etching mask to form conductive patterns <b>245</b>. The conductive patterns <b>245</b> are used as wiring or gate electrodes of the semiconductor device. The first oxide film <b>205</b> can be etched with the conductive film <b>210</b> to form first oxide film patterns <b>240</b> beneath the conductive patterns <b>245</b> as occasion demands.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5D</figref>, after the hard mask <b>270</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>) is removed from the conductive patterns <b>245</b>, a cleaning process is performed concerning the semiconductor substrate <b>200</b> to complete the first oxide film patterns <b>240</b> and the conductive patterns <b>245</b> on the semiconductor substrate <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A to 6D</figref> illustrate a method of manufacturing a NAND flash memory device according to an embodiment of the present invention. One skilled in the art appreciates that, although a method of manufacturing a NAND flash memory device is herein described, the invention may not be limited to this type of memory device.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Generally, a semiconductor substrate includes an active region and a field region. The two regions are defined by an isolation process such as a shallow trench isolation (STI) process. After a trench having a predetermined depth is formed in the semiconductor substrate by partially etching the semiconductor substrate using a photolithography process, an oxide film is formed on the semiconductor substrate to fill up the trench using a CVD process. The trench defines the active region in the semiconductor substrate. The oxide film is etched using a chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) process or an etch back process to form a filed oxide film in the trench only. Thus, the field oxide film defines the active region and the field region in the semiconductor substrate. Alternatively, the active region and field region can be defined using local oxidation of silicon (LOCOS) process. In addition, the active region can be defined using a self-aligned STI (SA-STI) process that simultaneously forms the active region and a floating gate of a non-volatile memory device.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, after a tunnel oxide film <b>305</b> is formed on the semiconductor substrate <b>300</b> using a thermal oxidation process, a first conductive film <b>310</b> is formed on the tunnel oxide film <b>305</b>. The tunnel oxide film <b>305</b> functions as a gate oxide film of the non-volatile memory device. The first conductive film <b>310</b> corresponds to a floating gate (not shown) of the non-volatile memory device. The tunnel oxide film <b>305</b> includes silicon oxide or silicon oxynitride. The first conductive film <b>310</b> includes polysilicon or amorphous silicon. The first conductive film <b>310</b> has a thickness of about 1,200 to about 1,600 Å. The first conductive film <b>310</b> is doped with N type impurities using a POCl<sub>3 </sub>diffusion process, an ion implantation process or an in-situ doping process. Then, portions of the first conductive film <b>310</b> on the field region are removed through a photolithography process to isolate floating gates of adjacent memory cells.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">An oxide/nitride/oxide (ONO) film <b>315</b> is formed on the first conductive film <b>310</b> by successively forming a first oxide film, a nitride film and a second oxide film (all not shown) on the first conductive film <b>310</b>. The ONO film <b>315</b> includes two oxide films and one nitride film interposed the two oxide films. The ONO film <b>315</b> is formed using a thermal oxidation process or a CVD process, and has a thickness of about 200 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">After a second conductive film <b>320</b> is formed on the ONO film <b>315</b>, a metal silicide layer <b>325</b> is formed on the second conductive film <b>320</b>. The second conductive film <b>320</b> functions as a control gate of the non-volatile memory device. The second conductive film <b>320</b> has a thickness of about 800 Å, and includes polysilicon or amorphous silicon. Preferably, the second conductive film <b>320</b> is formed using a silane (SiH<sub>4</sub>) gas and a phosphine (PH<sub>3</sub>) gas while the second conductive film <b>320</b> is doped with impurities in-situ. The metal silicide layer <b>325</b> includes tungsten silicide (WSi<sub>x</sub>), titanium silicide (TiSi<sub>x</sub>) or tantalum silicide (TaSi<sub>x</sub>). Preferably, the metal silicide layer <b>325</b> includes tungsten silicide and has a thickness of about 1,200 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">A first ARL <b>330</b>, a third oxide film <b>335</b> and a second ARL <b>340</b> are successively formed on the metal silicide layer <b>325</b> to form a hard mask layer <b>345</b> including the first ARL <b>330</b>, the third oxide film <b>335</b> and the second ARL <b>340</b>. That is, the hard mask layer <b>345</b> has two anti-reflective layers <b>330</b> and <b>340</b>, and one oxide film <b>335</b> interposed between the two anti-reflective layers <b>330</b> and <b>340</b>. The first and second anti-reflective layers <b>330</b> and <b>340</b>, including silicon nitride, silicon oxide or silicon oxynitride, are formed using a CVD process. The third oxide film <b>335</b>, including silicon oxide, is formed using a plasma enhanced CVD (PECVD) process. The hard mask layer <b>345</b> has the first ARL <b>330</b>, the third oxide film <b>335</b> and the second ARL <b>340</b>. The hard mask layer <b>345</b> minimizes the interference caused by underlying films during the configuration of photoresist patterns. In addition, the hard mask layer <b>345</b> assists in forming stable control and floating gates in the non-volatile memory device. The third oxide film <b>335</b> has a thickness of about 2,400 to about 2,600 Å. The first ARL <b>330</b> has a thickness of about 240 to 280 Å and the second ARL <b>340</b> has a thickness of about 640 to 680 Å. Thus, a thickness ratio among the first ARL <b>330</b>, the third oxide film <b>335</b> and the second ARL <b>340</b> is about 1:10:2.5.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">When the second ARL <b>340</b> is formed, a purge process is performed in-situ on the third oxide film <b>335</b> using a purge gas including nitrous oxide. Oxide residues <b>350</b> are generated from the purge gas containing nitrous oxide. The oxide residues <b>350</b> are formed on the second ARL <b>340</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">A first cleaning process is performed concerning the hard mask layer <b>345</b> using a first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid. The first cleaning process removes the oxide residues <b>350</b> formed on the second ARL <b>340</b>. The first cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 30 to about 70° C., preferably about 50° C., for about 3 to about 10 minutes, preferably about 5 minutes.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Then, a second cleaning process is performed in-situ concerning the hard mask layer <b>345</b> using a second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b>. The second cleaning process removes the oxide residues <b>350</b> from the second ARL <b>340</b>. The second cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 30 to about 70° C., preferably about 50° C., for about 5 to about 15 minutes, preferably about 10 minutes.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, after the photoresist film (not shown) is formed on the cleaned second ARL <b>340</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>), the photoresist film is patterned to form photoresist patterns <b>355</b>. The second ARL <b>340</b>, the third oxide film <b>335</b>, and the first ARL <b>330</b> (all shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>) are successively etched using the photoresist patterns <b>355</b> as etching masks, thereby forming a hard mask <b>380</b>. The hard mask <b>380</b> includes first ARL patterns <b>360</b>, third oxide film patterns <b>365</b> and second ARL patterns <b>370</b>. The hard mask <b>380</b> is used for forming control and floating gates of the non-volatile memory device.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, the oxide residues <b>350</b> caused by purge gas containing nitrous gas are formed on a surface of the hard mask layer <b>345</b> after the second ARL <b>340</b> is formed. When the oxide residues <b>350</b> exist between the hard mask layer <b>345</b> and the photoresist film, the adhesion strength between the second ARL <b>340</b> and the photoresist film may be deteriorated. Hence, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, the photoresist patterns <b>355</b> may be lifted from the second ARL patterns <b>370</b> after the photoresist patterns <b>355</b> are formed. The photoresist patterns <b>355</b> were lifted in more than 30 chips among 150 chips formed on an entire wafer when scanned by a scanning electron microscope (SEM).</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">However, in the present invention, after the hard mask layer <b>345</b> was cleaned using the first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid for about 5 minutes, the wafer was measured using Stealth Measurement Apparatus (SMA). The SMA detected about 677 defects among entire defects of about 1228 as real defects. When the defects were identified by the SEM, the photoresist patterns <b>355</b> were lifted in about 25 chips on the wafer. Then, after the hard mask layer <b>345</b> was cleaned using the second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b> for about 10 minutes, the wafer was measured again using the SMA. The SMA detected about 434 defects among entire defects of about 585 as real defects. When the defects were identified by the SEM, the photoresist patterns <b>355</b> were lifted in about 2 chips on the wafer.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Therefore, the first and the second cleaning processes performed on the wafer may completely remove the oxide residues <b>350</b> on the hard mask layer <b>345</b>. Then, the adhesion strength between the photoresist pattern <b>355</b> and the second ARL <b>340</b> can be greatly improved. This improved adhesion strength minimizes the lifting of the photoresist pattern <b>355</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref>, after the photoresist patterns <b>355</b> are removed using an ashing and stripping processes, the metal suicide layer <b>325</b>, the second conductive film <b>320</b>, the ONO film <b>315</b>, the first conductive film <b>310</b> and the tunnel oxide film <b>305</b> (all shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>) are successively etched using the hard mask <b>380</b> having the second ARL pattern <b>370</b>, the third oxide film pattern <b>365</b>, and the first ARL pattern <b>360</b>. Thus, there are formed gate structures having gate oxide film patterns <b>390</b>, floating gates <b>395</b>, ONO film patterns <b>400</b>, control gates <b>405</b> and metal suicide patterns <b>410</b>. Preferably, the hard mask <b>380</b> remains on the gate structure <b>420</b> by a thickness of about 900 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref>, impurities are implanted into predetermined portions of the semiconductor substrate <b>300</b> between the gate structures <b>420</b> using an ion implantation process. Then, the impurities are thermally treated to form source/drain regions <b>385</b> between the gate structures <b>420</b>. After the remaining hard mask <b>380</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref>) is removed, a cleaning process and drying process are performed on the semiconductor substrate <b>300</b> including the resultant structure formed thereon, thereby completing the non-volatile memory device.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A to 7D</figref> illustrate a method of manufacturing a DRAM device according to an embodiment of the present invention. One skilled in the art appreciates that, although a method of manufacturing a DRAM device is herein described, the present invention may not be limited to this type of memory device.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref>, with an isolation process such as a LOCOS process or an STI process, a field oxide film <b>455</b> is formed on a semiconductor substrate <b>450</b> to define an active region and a field region in the semiconductor substrate <b>450</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">Metal Oxide Semiconductor (MOS) structures <b>470</b> are formed on the semiconductor substrate <b>450</b>. Each of the MOS structures <b>470</b> includes gate structure <b>460</b> and source/drain region <b>465</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">The gate structure <b>460</b> includes a gate oxide film <b>475</b>, a gate electrode <b>480</b>, a capping layer <b>485</b> and a spacer <b>490</b>. The gate oxide film <b>460</b>, the gate electrode <b>480</b>, and the capping layer <b>485</b> are successively formed on the semiconductor substrate <b>450</b>. The spacer <b>490</b> is formed on a sidewall of the gate electrode <b>480</b>. The gate electrode <b>480</b> includes polysilicon or polysilicon/silicide. The capping layer <b>485</b> mainly includes oxide. The spacer <b>490</b> includes silicon oxide or silicon nitride. The source/drain regions <b>465</b> of each of the MOS structures <b>470</b> are formed on the semiconductor substrate <b>450</b> using an ion implantation process. The source/drain region <b>465</b> is disposed between the gate structures <b>460</b> by doping impurities into the substrate <b>450</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">After a first conductive film (not shown) is formed on the substrate <b>450</b> having the resultant structure formed thereon, an upper portion of the first conductive film is planarized using a CMP process or an etch back process until the gate structures <b>460</b> are exposed. As a result, pads <b>495</b> for capacitors and bit lines are formed between the gate structures <b>460</b>. The first conductive film includes a conductive material such as tungsten, titanium, titanium silicide or polysilicon.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref>, a first insulation film <b>500</b> and a second insulation film <b>505</b> are successively formed on the pads <b>495</b> and the gate structures <b>460</b> using CVD processes. The first and second insulation films <b>500</b> and <b>505</b> include silicon oxides.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">An ARL <b>510</b> is formed on the second insulation film <b>505</b> using silicon oxide, silicon nitride or silicon oxynitride. At the same time, the ARL is purged in-situ using a purge gas including nitrogen oxide. In this case, oxide residues <b>515</b> caused by the purge gas are generated on the ARL <b>510</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">A first cleaning process is performed on the ARL <b>510</b> using a first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid. The first cleaning process removes the oxide residues <b>515</b> from the ARL <b>510</b>. The first cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 30 to about 70° C., preferably 50° C., for about 3 to 10 minutes, preferably about 5 minutes. A second cleaning process is performed in-situ on the ARL <b>510</b> using a second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b> to remove the oxide residues <b>515</b> from the ARL <b>510</b>. The second cleaning process is performed at a low temperature of about 30 to about 70° C., preferably 50° C., for about 5 to 15 minutes, preferably about 10 minutes. Then, the oxide residues <b>515</b> may be completely remove from the ARL <b>510</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7C and 7D</figref>, after the photoresist film (not shown) is formed on the cleaned ARL <b>510</b>, the photoresist patterns <b>520</b> are formed on the ARL <b>510</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">The ARL <b>510</b>, the second insulation film <b>505</b> and the first insulation film <b>500</b> are successively etched using the photoresist patterns <b>520</b> as etching masks, thereby forming storage node contact holes <b>530</b> exposing the pads <b>495</b> formed on the substrate <b>450</b>. The photoresist patterns <b>520</b> and the ARL <b>510</b> are removed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7D</figref>. To form contact plugs <b>535</b> using a self-aligned process, spacers <b>525</b> including silicon nitride are formed on sidewalls of the storage node contact holes <b>530</b> formed through the first and second insulation films <b>500</b> and <b>505</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">After a second conductive film (not shown) is formed on the second insulation film <b>505</b> to fill up the storage node contact holes <b>530</b> including spacers <b>525</b>, the second conductive film is etched using a CMP process or an etch back process to form storage node contact plugs <b>535</b> in the storage node contact holes <b>530</b>. The second conductive film includes tungsten, titanium, titanium silicide or polysilicon.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">A dielectric layer (not shown) and a top electrode (not shown) are successively formed on second insulation film <b>505</b> having the storage node contact plugs <b>535</b> formed therein in accordance with general processes for forming a capacitor, thereby completing a DRAM device.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">According to embodiments of the invention, oxide residues formed during a formation of an anti-reflective layer are completely removed from the anti-reflective layer by enhanced cleaning processes before a photoresist film is formed on the anti-reflective layer. Adhesion strength between a photoresist pattern and the anti-reflective layer is improved and lifting of a photoresist pattern and clinging of photoresist patterns are prevented, forming photoresist patterns having precise shapes and dimensions.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">While the present invention has been described in detail with reference to the preferred embodiments, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited to the disclosed embodiments, but, on the contrary, is intended to cover various modifications and equivalent arrangements included within the spirit and scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of forming patterns in a semiconductor device comprising:
<claim-text>forming an insulation film on a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a conductive film on the insulation film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a hard mask layer on the conductive film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cleaning oxide residues generated in forming the hard mask layer from the hard mask layer using a first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cleaning the oxide residues from the hard mask layer using a second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b>;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a photoresist pattern on the hard mask layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a hard mask by patterning the hard mask layer using the photoresist pattern; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>patterning the conductive film using the hard mask, wherein forming the hard mask layer further comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first anti-reflective layer on the conductive film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming an oxide film on the first anti-reflective layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second anti-reflective layer on the oxide film.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the oxide residues are generated by purging the second anti-reflective layers using a purge gas including nitrogen oxide in forming the second anti-reflective layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first and second anti-reflective layers include silicon oxide, silicon nitride or silicon oxynitride.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a thickness ratio among the first anti-reflective layer, the oxide film and the second anti-reflective layer is about 1:10:2.5.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein cleaning oxide residues from the hard mask layer using the first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid is performed at a temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 3 to about 10 minutes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein cleaning the oxide residues from the hard mask layer using the second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b> is performed at a temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 5 to about 15 minutes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A method of manufacturing a non-volatile memory device comprising:
<claim-text>forming a tunnel oxide film on a semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first conductive film on the tunnel oxide film, the first conductive film being a floating gate of the non-volatile memory device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming an oxide/nitride/oxide film on the first conductive film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second conductive film on the oxide/nitride/oxide film, the second conductive film being a control gate of the non-volatile memory device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a metal suicide layer on the second conductive film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a hard mask layer on the metal silicide layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cleaning oxide residues generated in forming the hard mask layer from the hard mask layer using a first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cleaning the oxide residues from the hard mask layer using a second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b>;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a photoresist pattern on the hard mask layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a hard mask by patterning the hard mask layer using the photoresist pattern; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>patterning the metal silicide layer, the second conductive film, and the oxide/nitride/oxide film and the first conductive film using the hard mask, wherein forming the hard mask layer further comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first anti-reflective layer on the metal silicide layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming an oxide film on the first anti-reflective layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second anti-reflective layer on the oxide film.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein a thickness ratio among the first anti-reflective layer, the third oxide film and the second anti-reflective layer is about 1:10:2.5.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the first and the second anti-reflective layers include silicon oxide, silicon nitride or silicon oxynitride, and the oxide residues are generated by purging the second anti-reflective layer using a purge gas including nitrogen oxide in forming the second anti-reflective layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein cleaning oxide residues from the hard mask layer using the first cleaning solution including sulfuric acid is performed at a temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 3 to about 10 minutes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein cleaning the oxide residues from the hard mask layer using the second cleaning solution including SC <b>1</b> is performed at a temperature of about 30 to about 70° C. for about 5 to about 15 minutes.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
