<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298723-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298723</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10782595</doc-number>
<date>20040218</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>658</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>Q</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>24</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370335</main-classification>
<further-classification>370350</further-classification>
<further-classification>455574</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Method for reduced access delay in multiple access attempt exchanges</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0065117</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Suda</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>455574</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0026324</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Li et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>375141</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0232621</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Brooks</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>455424</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>44</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050180362</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050818</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chin</last-name>
<first-name>Tom</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Diego</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Pilkington</last-name>
<first-name>John Randall</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Diego</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Rouse</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Seo</last-name>
<first-name>Howard</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zhu</last-name>
<first-name>Peng</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Qualcomm Incorporated</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>San Diego</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Gary</last-name>
<first-name>Erika A.</first-name>
<department>2617</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A system and method for reducing access delay associated with multiple access attempt exchanges in a communications network is provided. A system of the present invention may include a mobile station and a base station system for sending and receiving signals; an air interface link for carrying the signals; and a set of timing modules for governing the transmission of the signals, whereby the set of timing modules controls activation periods of the battery's current flow to the transmit clock according to a predetermined time interval. Control of activation periods minimizes delay during access attempts and conserves power resources.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="236.90mm" wi="178.56mm" file="US07298723-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="254.00mm" wi="172.89mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298723-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="243.84mm" wi="165.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298723-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="240.20mm" wi="180.68mm" file="US07298723-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention generally relates to wireless communication networks and, more particularly, to a system and method to reduce access delay associated with multiple access attempt exchanges between devices associated with such a network.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Generally, wireless communications supply users with numerous services via a variety of devices, including mobile telephones, pagers, and handheld devices, gaming devices and servers. Such services may include voice, paging, video, and messaging; i.e., sending and receiving text messages via mobile devices such as mobile telephones. Advanced messaging features may include group paging, pre-programmed messages, on-call groups, scheduled messages, and repeating messages. Integrated services provide two or more services via the same device. For example, one such integrated service, push-to-talk (PTT), delivers audio messaging services in real-time, combining the flexibility of messaging with the ease-of-use of voice. PTT permits users to connect directly, in seconds, to another PTT user by pushing a button on a mobile telephone (not unlike the communication exchange between “walkie-talkies”). PTT services often include group-calling, in which icons appear directly on the user's handset, indicating which users are available to participate. This eliminates the need for the user to waste valuable time attempting to identify which of the contacts are available. Group calling further provides the advantage of providing voice services between many users at the same time, as opposed to one-on-one conversations.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The Code Division Multiple Access (CDMA) system is widely employed in many of the aforementioned services. It allows numerous signals to occupy a common frequency band, optimizing the use of available bandwidth. CDMA employs analog-to-digital conversion (ADC) in combination with spread spectrum technology. ADC facilitates the conversion of audio input from the sending device to binary elements. The binary elements are then transmitted to the receiving device. The stream of binary elements from one mobile sending device is distinguished from the binary elements of another mobile sending device by means of Pseudonoise (PN) sequences. There are trillions of possible codes generated from the Pseudonoise sequence, thus minimizing interference.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The varied code pattern employed in CDMA applications is calculated according to a specific, complex algorithm that is a function of time. To receive signals transmitted according to this scheme, the sending device and receiving device must “know” both the code generating function and its current position in the sequence. Therefore the sending device and the receiving device must initially synchronize respective time clocks to ensure simultaneous starting time points. Synchronization of the respective time clocks typically includes turning on the transmit clock at the correct frequency and loading the correct state into the long code generator and I-channel and Q-channel PN sequence generators at the correct time to ensure that codes output by the long code generator and the I-channel and Q-channel PN sequence generators have the proper sequence at the proper time; i.e., synchronized to CDMA system time. References to “PN generators,” as used herein, refer to both the long code generator and the I-channel and Q-channel PN sequence generators, which are clocked by the transmit clock. According to the CDMA IS2000 standard, the CDMA long code generator is the CDMA system time PN sequence generator. This long code is used to channelize the mobile to decrease interference and eliminate cross-talk. If the sending device and receiving device have their long codes aligned differently in time, then communication will fail. The I-channel and Q-channel PN sequence is used for the transmit time reference.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">As a precursor to many CDMA applications, an initial access process consisting of several asynchronous access attempt messages, or multiple access attempt exchange (MAAE), may be executed between the sending device and an initial receiving device, such as a base station system, or equipment designed to initially receive signals transmitted from the sending device. For example, in PTT applications, once the user invokes the PTT service by pushing a button on the mobile telephone, the MAAE commences. An MAAE of the prior art typically entails drawing current from a battery of the sending device to provide power to a transmit clock associated with the sending device; synchronizing the transmit clock, with its associated long code and I-channel and Q-channel PN codes, with a CDMA time source associated with the communication network; attempting to access the receiving device via the communication network to establish a link; i.e., sending a series of coded signals or probes; then removing current flow from the battery to the transmit clock (which results in stoppage of the transmit clock) to conserve energy and prolong the life of the battery. The foregoing steps are iteratively repeated in rapid succession, as more than one access attempt is generally required during a single MAAE before successful establishment of a link occurs. A classic example of an MAAE occurs each time a user presses the button of a mobile telephone to initiate a push-to-talk session.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Users of mobile communication services, such as PTT, expect a seamless, near-instantaneous communication connection between their device, such as a mobile telephone, and another device, such as the mobile telephone of another user. Despite such expectations, mobile communication services of the prior art typically incur significant delays, particularly during the initial connect phase, or the MAAE. Such delays are compounded by the time lost each time the battery current is reapplied to the transmit clock and the sending device must synchronize its transmit clock and associated PN generators with the CDMA time source.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">One alternative to reduce transitional delay during MAAE is to permit the battery current flow to the transmit clock to remain activated for the entire time the sending device is powered on whether or not an MAAE is in progress, thus eliminating the need for subsequent synchronization processes after the initial time synchronization. This alternative quickly expends power resources and adversely impacts battery life.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is apparent from the foregoing that a need exists for an improved system and method for minimizing delay during the MAAE phase in wireless communication applications. There is a further need to provide such a system and method that conserves energy resources and prolongs battery life.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">An aspect includes steps of determining if a transmit clock is stopped; if the transmit clock is stopped, activating a current flow from a power device to the transmit clock, powering the transmit clock via the power device, and starting the transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators; sending one or more access probes from the sending device to the receiving device via the link; and deactivating the current flow from the power device to the transmit clock after lapse of a predetermined time interval measured by a control device.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Another aspect includes steps of (a) activating current flow from the battery to the transmit clock; (b) starting the transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with a system time associated with the communication network via the air interface link; (c) sending a series of access probes from the mobile station to the base station system via the air interface link; (d) setting a timer for a predetermined time interval; if a successive access is to be attempted, (e) determining if the timer has expired; if the timer has expired, repeating preceding steps starting from step (a); and if the timer has not expired, stopping the timer; and repeating the preceding steps starting from step (c).</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Still another aspect includes a sending device, the sending device transmitting signals to the receiving device via the link. The sending device includes a power device, the power device providing a power source; a transmit clock, the transmit clock receiving the power source; and a control device, the control device controlling activation periods of the current flow from the power device to the transmit clock and controlling periods in which the sending device transmits signals according to a predetermined time interval.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Yet another aspect includes a mobile station having a battery, the mobile station sending and receiving signals to and from the base station system via the air interface link. The mobile station includes a battery, the battery providing a power source; a transmit clock, the transmit clock receiving the power source; and a timer, the timer controlling activation periods of the power device to the transmit clock and controlling periods in which the sending device transmits signals according to a predetermined time interval, such as a range of one to five seconds.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A further aspect includes a sending device, the sending device transmitting signals to the receiving device via the link, the sending device having a transmit clock, the transmit clock receiving the power source; and a set of timing modules, the set of timing modules governing periods for transmission of the signals and controlling activation periods of the current flow from the battery to the transmit clock according to a predetermined time interval.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A still further aspect includes means for activating a battery's current flow to the transmit clock; means for starting a transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with a system time associated with a communication network via an air interface link; means for sending a series of access probes from the mobile station to the base station system via the air interface link; means for setting a timer for a predetermined time interval; means for deactivating the current flow from the battery to the transmit clock and stopping the transmit clock after expiration of the timer; means for determining if a successive access is to be attempted; means for determining if the predetermined time interval has expired; and means for stopping the timer if the timer has not expired.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Yet a further aspect includes steps of: a step for sending and receiving signals between a mobile station having a battery and a base station system via an air interface link; and a step for governing the transmission of the signals by controlling activation periods of the battery's current flow to the transmit clock according to a predetermined time interval.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Still another aspect includes a set of timing modules, the set of timing modules governing transmission of signals by controlling activation of a battery's current flow to the transmit clock according to a predetermined time interval.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">A further aspect includes a control device for governing an optimal time interval that limits the activation of the power device and permits transmission of signals from the sending device to the receiving device via the link.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">These and other features, aspects and advantages of the present invention will become better understood with reference to the following drawings, description and claims.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a system schematic for multiple access attempt exchanges in a wireless communication network, according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a timeline diagram of a multiple access attempt exchange according to an embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flow diagram of a method according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The following detailed description is of the best currently contemplated modes of carrying out the invention. The description is not to be taken in a limiting sense, but is made merely for the purpose of illustrating the general principles of the invention, since the scope of the invention is best defined by the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Broadly, an embodiment of the present invention provides a system and method for optimizing a multiple access attempt exchange (MAAE) in a wireless communication network. More specifically, and in contrast to the prior art, various embodiments of the present invention may minimize the delay normally incurred during multiple synchronization operations in a single MAAE. In contrast to the prior art, various embodiments may conserve power resources associated with various devices. The MAAE is a process executed between a sending device such as a mobile station or mobile telephone and a receiving device such as a base station system via a link such as an air interface link. During MAAE, a mobile station's power source to the transmit clock, such as a battery, can be activated and the timing of the mobile station's transmit clock and associated PN generators can be synchronized to a CDMA system time through an alignment of the transmit clock timing to the timing received from the base station. Once synchronization is accomplished, a set of access probes (signals) may be sent from the mobile station to the base station system. After transmission of an initial set of probes, a control device, such as a timer associated with the mobile station, can be used to control one or more periods during the multiple access attempt exchange by, for example, performing a predetermined action. For example, the timer can be set for a predetermined time interval. The predetermined time interval may be an optimal time interval as determined by selecting a maximum time period for sending signals without resynchronization of the transmit clock and associated PN generators (thus minimizing delay), wherein the maximum time period may be limited by a determination of the maximum time period in which the power device may be permitted activation to the transmit clock (thus conserving power resources). Once the timer is set, the transmit clock may remain started and the transmit clock and associated PN generators may remain synchronized, thus successive access attempts may be made during such a period without incurring the delay associated with re-starting the transmit clock and re-synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with CDMA system time. The control device, such as the timer, can also control one or more periods in which the battery's current flow to the transmit clock is deactivated, thus conserving power resources. Deactivation of the battery's current flow to the transmit clock can result in inactivation or stoppage of the transmit clock. For example, in various embodiments the timer may be set according to a predetermined time interval. In this example, expiration of the timer may result in deactivation of current flow from the battery to the transmit clock, which may stop the transmit clock. Before each set of successive probes is sent, the timer can be checked. If the timer has not expired, then a successive set of probes may be sent. The timer may be reset. If, however, the timer has expired (resulting in deactivation of the battery's current flow to the transmit clock and stoppage of the transmit clock), then the battery's current flow to the transmit clock can be reactivated and the transmit clock can be restarted and the transmit clock and associated PN generators can be re-synchronized prior to transmission of the successive set of probes. Limiting redundant synchronization processes coupled with limiting periods of battery current flow to the transmit clock can result in an optimized MAAE process. In contrast to processes of the prior art, embodiments of the present invention can reduce the communication exchange delays experienced by users of mobile devices without significant depletion of power reserves of the mobile devices. As a skilled artisan will note, embodiments of the present invention are applicable to various wireless communication services, including push-to-talk, gaming, data calling, and video messaging.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Turning now to the drawings, wherein like items are referenced with the same numerals, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> generally shows an exemplary system <b>10</b> for multiple access attempt exchanges that may have a mobile station (MS) <b>12</b> sending and receiving signals via an air interface link <b>14</b> to and from a base station system (BSS) <b>16</b>, and a set of timing modules <b>18</b> governing transmissions between the MS <b>12</b> and the BSS <b>16</b>, as shown encompassed in the phantom oval. The MS <b>12</b>, such as a mobile telephone or other device, may include mobile equipment (ME) <b>12</b><i>a</i>. The ME <b>12</b><i>a </i>can typically comprise hardware elements such as a battery <b>12</b><i>b</i>, a transmit clock with associated PN generators; i.e., long code generator and I-channel and Q-channel PN sequence generators <b>12</b><i>c</i>, a timer <b>12</b><i>d</i>, a screen, processor, circuit boards, transmitter, and receiver.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The BSS <b>16</b> may include a Base Station Controller (BSC) <b>20</b> and one or more Base Transceiver Stations (BTS) <b>22</b>. The BSS <b>16</b> may provide the functionality that enables the MS <b>12</b> to access various network services over the air interface link <b>14</b>, such as by signal transmission. The signal information may then be converted to various communication formats and may be forwarded to destination media. For example, the signal may be transmitted to a mobile switching center (MSC) <b>24</b>, for onward transmission of the associated information to one or more destination devices <b>26</b> via, for example, a publicly switched telephone network (PSTN) <b>28</b>, the Internet <b>30</b>, a communication link <b>32</b>, or a combination thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The communication link <b>32</b> may comprise and utilize any medium, method, or a combination thereof for communication transfer, including short wave radio, analog lines, digital networks, and so forth. The set of timing modules <b>18</b> may include an activation module <b>18</b><i>a</i>, a start and synchronization module <b>18</b><i>b</i>, a probe module <b>18</b><i>c</i>, a start timer module <b>18</b><i>d</i>, and a stop timer module <b>18</b><i>e</i>. The set of timing modules <b>18</b> may include any combination of modules necessary to carry out the function described herein. Furthermore, the modules may be embodied as hardware, software, or a combination thereof. The modules <b>18</b> may be integral components of the MS <b>12</b>, the BSS <b>16</b>, or both. Furthermore, the modules <b>18</b> may be remotely embodied elsewhere and accessible to the MS <b>12</b>, to the BSS <b>16</b>, or to both.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In various applications such as push-to-talk (PTT), the MS <b>12</b> initially may attempt to contact the BSS <b>16</b> by transmission of a series of signals. In an MAAE, as heretofore described, the activation module <b>18</b><i>a </i>may activate the current flow from the battery <b>12</b><i>b </i>to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c</i>, which provides an energy source for the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c</i>. After activation, the start and synchronization module <b>18</b><i>b </i>may start the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>and synchronize the transmit clock and associated PN generators <b>12</b><i>c </i>with CDMA system time by matching the frequency of the transmit clock and the states of the long code generator and I-channel and Q-channel PN sequence generators to the timing received from the BSS <b>16</b>. The probe module <b>18</b><i>c </i>may direct the MS <b>12</b> to send access probes (not shown) via the air interface link <b>14</b> to the BSS <b>16</b>, and the initial access attempt completes. After transmission of an initial set of access probes, the current flow from the battery <b>12</b><i>b </i>to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>may remain activated and the start timer module <b>18</b><i>d </i>may set the timer <b>12</b><i>d </i>for a predetermined time interval. Upon expiration of the set time, the current flow from the battery <b>12</b><i>b </i>to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>may be deactivated, thus eliminating the power source to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>and stopping it. The predetermined time interval may include a range of one to five seconds, a two-second period, or other time limitations. The predetermined time interval of an embodiment of the present invention may vary according to specific application and objectives. For example, a gaming device may utilize an embodiment of the present invention having one precise time interval, and a mobile telephone offering PTT services may utilize a second precise time interval. Discrete time intervals exemplified herein are for illustrative purposes only.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">If subsequent access attempts are to be made and the predetermined timer interval on the timer <b>12</b><i>d </i>has not yet expired, then the stop timer module <b>18</b><i>e </i>may stop the timer <b>12</b><i>d</i>, and repeat the procedure starting with the transmission of probes; i.e., the probe module <b>18</b><i>c </i>may then direct the MS <b>12</b> to send a series of probes via the air interface link <b>14</b> to the BSS <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">If subsequent access attempts are to be made and the predetermined timer interval on the timer <b>12</b><i>d </i>has expired, then the access attempts may be accomplished according to the procedure set out above for an initial access attempt; i.e., the activation module <b>18</b><i>a </i>may again activate the current flow from the battery <b>12</b><i>b </i>to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c</i>, and so forth.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">If no further access attempts are to be made, then the MAAE may complete. Significantly, the subsequent access attempts during an MAAE in an embodiment do not require the start and synchronization process, thus do not incur the considerable delay inherent in prior art processes that synchronize the transmit clock and associated PN generators <b>12</b><i>c </i>after each access attempt in a single MAAE. Furthermore, deactivation of the current flow from the battery <b>12</b><i>b </i>to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>after expiration of the predetermined time interval conserves energy and prolongs battery life.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">With reference now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, there is shown a timeline diagram of a multiple access attempt exchange according to an embodiment of the present invention. A timeline <b>34</b> starting at <b>36</b> identifies periods of time during which the transmit clock is off, periods of time in which the transmit clock is on and the transmit clock and associated PN generators are synchronizing, and periods of time in which the transmit clock is on and the transmit clock and associated PN generators are synchronized. After an arbitrary point in time <b>38</b> on the timeline <b>34</b>, and while the transmit clock is turned off, the battery's current flow to the transmit clock may be activated at <b>40</b> and may provide power to the transmit clock at <b>42</b>, after which a sequence of long codes and I-channel and Q-channel PN sequences may be aligned to CDMA system time at <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Upon completion of the synchronization step <b>44</b>, the transmit clock is on and the transmit clock and PN generators are synchronized with CDMA system time at <b>46</b>. Access probes <b>48</b> may be sent during a first access attempt at <b>50</b>, immediately after which the timer may be started at <b>52</b> and set for a predetermined time interval, depicted in this example as a two-second interval <b>54</b> (or a portion thereof). Access probes may be sent during a successive access attempt within the two-second interval <b>54</b> (or a portion thereof). For example, access probes <b>48</b> from a second access attempt are sent at <b>56</b>, and the timer is stopped at <b>58</b>. Immediately following a transmission of access probes, the timer may be reset for a two-second interval, as shown at <b>60</b>. If the delay between access attempts exceeds two seconds, as shown at <b>62</b>, the timer may continue to run down, expiring at the two-second setpoint, as shown at <b>64</b>. Upon expiration of the two-second period at <b>64</b>, the current flow from the battery to the transmit clock may be deactivated, thus stopping the transmit clock at <b>66</b>. Further access attempts may require activation of the battery's current flow to the transmit clock, as shown at point <b>68</b>, whereafter the synchronization step <b>44</b> may be performed. After synchronization, the transmit clock and associated PN generators are accurate with CDMA system time at <b>70</b>, access probes <b>48</b> may be sent at <b>72</b>, after which the timer may be started at time <b>74</b>, and the MAAE may continue as described until MAAE is completed.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Turning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (and with continuing reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), there is shown generally at <b>76</b> a flow diagram of a method for reducing delay during a multiple access attempt exchange in a communications network, including activating the current flow from the battery <b>12</b><i>b </i>to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>at step <b>78</b>; for example, activating the battery's <b>12</b><i>b </i>current to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>and long code generator and I-channel and Q-channel PN sequence generators. At step <b>80</b>, the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>and associated PN generators may be synchronized with CDMA system time associated with the communication network <b>10</b>; for example, synchronizing the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>and long code and I-channel and Q-channel PN sequence generators (not shown) with CDMA system time. Once the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>is accurate with CDMA system time, the MS <b>12</b> may send a series of probes to the BSS <b>16</b> via the air interface link <b>14</b>, as shown in step <b>82</b>. Upon completion of step <b>82</b>, the timer may be set to the predetermined time interval at step <b>84</b>. Continuation of the current MAAE may be checked and determined at <b>86</b>. For example, the program may wait for either timer expiration or a successive access attempt, after which various logic paths may be taken, shown, for example, at <b>88</b> and <b>90</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">If one or more successive access attempts are to be performed, then the state of the transmit clock may be checked to ensure that the transmit clock is started and the transmit clock and associated PN generators are synchronized prior to transmission of the access probes of the successive access attempt. If the transmit clock has been stopped and a successive attempt is to be performed, then the battery's current flow to the transmit clock may need to be reactivated to power the transmit clock, and the transmit clock may need to be restarted and the transmit clock and associated PN generators may need to be re-synchronized. For example, expiration of the timer <b>12</b><i>d </i>may trigger deactivation of the current flow from the battery <b>12</b><i>b </i>to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c </i>and stoppage of the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c</i>, thus ensuring that the expenditure of power resources is limited. A step may be taken to determine if the transmit clock is started. For example, in various embodiments, this step may include checking the state of the battery's current flow to the transmit clock or state of the transmit clock, or checking the status of the timer <b>12</b><i>d</i>, as shown at branch <b>98</b>. Because the expiration of the timer may result in deactivation of the battery's current flow to the transmit clock and stoppage of the transmit clock, once the status of the timer is determined an inference may be drawn regarding the states of the battery and transmit clock. For example, if the timer is checked, and it is determined that the timer had expired at branch <b>88</b>, then it may be inferred that the battery's current flow to the transmit clock had been deactivated and the transmit clock stopped, as shown at <b>89</b>. In such circumstances, successive access attempts may commence by iteratively repeating steps of the multiple access attempt exchange starting with the step <b>78</b> for activating the current flow from the battery <b>12</b><i>b </i>to the transmit clock <b>12</b><i>c</i>, as shown at branch <b>94</b>. If the timer <b>12</b><i>d </i>is checked, and it is determined that the timer had not expired at <b>90</b>, it may then be inferred that the battery's current flow to the transmit clock remains activated, the transmit clock remains started and the transmit clock and associated PN generators remain synchronized. In such circumstances, the timer <b>12</b><i>d </i>had been stopped at <b>96</b>. Successive access attempts may commence at branch <b>98</b> by iteratively repeating steps of the multiple access attempt exchange starting with the step <b>82</b> of sending the probes.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">It should be understood, of course, that the foregoing relates to preferred embodiments of the invention and that modifications may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as set forth in the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for reducing delay during a multiple access attempt exchange in a sending device with a power device, a transmit clock, and a control device; and a link, the method comprising steps of:
<claim-text>a. determining if the transmit clock is stopped;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b. only if the transmit clock is stopped after lapse of a predetermined time interval in which no access attempt has been made, activating the power device; powering the transmit clock via the power device; and starting the transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with system time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c. sending one or more access probes from the sending device to a receiving device via the link; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>d. deactivating the power device to stop the transmit clock after lapse of the predetermined time interval in which no access attempt has been made, measured by the control device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the sending device operates in a CDMA wireless communication network.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the sending device further comprises a mobile telephone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the receiving device further comprises a base station system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the control device further comprises a timer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the link further comprises an air interface link.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A method for reducing delay during a multiple access attempt exchange in a communication network having a base station system, an air interface link, and a mobile station with a battery, a transmit clock, and a timer, the method comprising steps of:
<claim-text>a. activating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock to start the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b. synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with system time associated with the communication network via the air interface link;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c. attempting an access by sending a series of access probes from the mobile station to the base station system via the air interface link;</claim-text>
<claim-text>d. setting a timer for a predetermined time interval;</claim-text>
<claim-text>e. if a successive access is attempted, before the timer determines that the predetermined time interval has expired, stopping the timer, leaving the transmit clock on and repeating steps c, d, e, and f and</claim-text>
<claim-text>f. if the timer determines that the predetermined time interval has expired before the successive access is attempted, stopping the timer, deactivating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock to stop the transmit clock and, in response to the successive access attempt, repeating steps a, b, c, d, e, and f.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval is selected from a range of one second to five seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the range further comprises two seconds to four seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the range further comprises two seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method for multiple access attempts in a communication network, the method comprising steps of:
<claim-text>a step for synchronizing a transmit clock of a mobile stations, having a battery, to a base station system via an air interface link; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a step for controlling activation periods of the battery's current flow to the transmit clock by leaving the transmit clock on unless no subsequent access attempt occurs within a predetermined time interval.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the step of governing the transmission of signals further comprises steps of:
<claim-text>a step for activating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a step for starting the transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with system time after the battery's current flow to the transmit clock has been activated;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a step for sending a series of access probes from the mobile station to the base station system after the transmit clock has been started;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a step for setting the timer according to the predetermined time interval after the series of probes have been sent; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a step for stopping the timer if successive access attempts are to be initiated and the timer has not expired.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising a step of selecting the predetermined timer interval from a range of one second to five seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A mobile station with a sending device having a power device, the mobile station comprising:
<claim-text>a control device that controls activation periods of the power device, the mobile station being synchronized with a base station system during an initial access attempt of one activation period of the activation periods so that the one activation period continues through subsequent access attempts and is not stopped unless no subsequent access attempt occurs within to a predetermined time interval.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The mobile station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the mobile station operates in a CDMA wireless network.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The mobile station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the base station system further comprises a receiving device receiving the signals from the sending device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The mobile station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the link farther comprises an air interface link.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The mobile station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the mobile station further comprises a mobile telephone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The mobile station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the mobile station further includes a transmit clock.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The mobile station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the control device further includes a timer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The mobile station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval ranges from one second to five seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A wireless communication network having a mobile station with a sending device; a base station system; and an air interface link, the sending device sending and receiving signals to and from the base station system, the wireless communication network comprising:
<claim-text>a battery for providing a power source;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transmit clock for receiving the power source; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a timer for controlling activation periods of the power source to the transmit clock, the timer stopping timing of a predetermined time interval, leaving the transmit clock on in response to a subsequent access attempt within the predetermined time interval; and the timer stopping the timing of the predetermined time interval, turning the transmit clock off in response to no subsequent access attempt within the predetermined time interval.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The wireless communication network of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval further comprises two seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A wireless communication network having a mobile station with a sending device, a power device, a link, and a base station system having a receiving device, the sending device transmitting signals to the receiving device via the link, the wireless communication network comprising:
<claim-text>a set of timing modules that synchronize the mobile station to a base station system during an initial access attempt in an activation period and that control the activation period of the power device so that the activation period continues through subsequent access attempts and is not stopped unless no subsequent access attempt occurs within a predetermined time interval.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The wireless communication network of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref>, wherein the mobile station further comprises a transmit clock and a timer and the power device further comprises a battery.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The wireless communication network of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, wherein the set of timing modules further comprises:
<claim-text>an activation module for activating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start and synchronization module for starting the transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with CDMA system time after the activation module has activated the battery's current flow to the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a probe module for sending a series of access probes from the mobile station to the base station system after the start and synchronization module has started the transmit clock and synchronized the transmit clock and associated PN generators with CDMA system time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start timer module for setting the timer according to the predetermined time interval after the probe module has sent the series of access probes; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a stop timer module for stopping the timer, deactivating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock, and stopping the transmit clock after the start timer module has started the timer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The wireless communication network of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00026">claim 26</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval further comprises a discrete time element selected from a group including all discrete time elements in a range of one second to five seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. A wireless communication network comprising:
<claim-text>a mobile station for sending and receiving signals, the mobile station having mobile equipment comprising:
<claim-text>a battery;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transmit clock; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a timer;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base station system for sending and receiving the signals to and from the mobile station;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an air interface link for carrying the signals to and from the mobile station and the base station system; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a set of timing modules for governing the transmission of the signals, the set of timing modules comprising:
<claim-text>an activation module for activating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start and synchronization module for starting the transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with CDMA system time after the activation module has activated the battery's current flow to the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a probe module for sending a series of access probes from the mobile station to the base station system after the start and synchronization module has staffed the transmit clock and synchronized the transmit clock and associated PN generators with CDMA system time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start timer for setting the timer for a period of two seconds after the probe module has sent the series of probes and, upon expiration of the period of two seconds without a successive access attempt, deactivating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock and stopping the transmit clock; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a stop timer for stopping the timer and not deactivating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock if the successive access attempt is initiated before the period of two seconds has expired.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. A system for reducing delay during a multiple access attempt exchange in a mobile station with a battery, a transmit clock, and a timer, the system comprising:
<claim-text>means for activating the battery's current flow to start the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for starting the transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with a system time associated with a communication network associated with the mobile station via an air interface link;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for attempting an access by sending a series of access probes from the mobile station to a base station system via the air interface link;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for setting a timer for a predetermined time interval;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for determining if a successive access is attempted before the predetermined time interval has expired, and, if so, stopping the timer, leaving the transmit clock on; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for determining if the predetermined time interval has expired before the successive access is attempted, and, if so, stopping the timer and deactivating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock to stop the transmit clock.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00029">claim 29</claim-ref>, wherein the means for setting a timer further comprises means for setting a timer according to a predetermined time interval in the range of one to five seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00029">claim 29</claim-ref>, wherein means for setting a timer further comprises means for setting a timer for a time period of two seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00029">claim 29</claim-ref>, wherein the communications network further comprises a wireless communication network.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00033" num="00033">
<claim-text>33. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00032">claim 32</claim-ref>, wherein the wireless communications network further comprises a CDMA wireless communications network.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00034" num="00034">
<claim-text>34. A system for multiple access attempts in a communication network having a mobile station with a battery; a transmit clock; and a timer; a base station system; and an air interface link, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a set of timing modules that control activation of a battery's current flow to the transmit clock so that the mobile station synchronizes to the base station system during an initial access attempt, and the transmit clock continues without resynchronization through subsequent access attempts and is not stopped unless no subsequent access attempt occurs within a predetermined time interval.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00035" num="00035">
<claim-text>35. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00034">claim 34</claim-ref>, wherein the set of timing modules further comprises:
<claim-text>an activation module for activating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start and synchronization module for starting the transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators with CDMA system time after the activation module has activated the battery's current flow to the transmit clock;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a probe module for sending a series of access probes from the mobile station to the base station system after the start and synchronization module has started the transmit clock and synchronized the transmit clock and associated PN generators with system time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start timer module for setting the timer according to the predetermined time interval after the probe module has sent a series of probes and deactivating the battery's current flow to the transmit clock and stopping the transmit clock upon expiration of the time interval; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a stop timer module for stopping the timer if successive access attempts are to be initiated and the timer set by the start timer module has not expired.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00036" num="00036">
<claim-text>36. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00035">claim 35</claim-ref>, wherein the communications network further comprises a wireless communications network.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00037" num="00037">
<claim-text>37. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00036">claim 36</claim-ref>, wherein the wireless communications network utilizes CDMA protocol.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00038" num="00038">
<claim-text>38. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00036">claim 36</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval further comprises a discrete time element selected from a range of one to five seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00039" num="00039">
<claim-text>39. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00036">claim 36</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval further comprises two seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00040" num="00040">
<claim-text>40. A set of timing modules in a mobile station, the set of timing modules comprising:
<claim-text>an activation module for activating a power device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start and synchronization module for staffing a transmit clock and synchronizing the transmit clock and associated PN generators after the activation module has activated the power device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a probe module for sending a series of access probes from a sending device to a receiving device after the staff and synchronization module has started the transmit clock and synchronized the transmit clock and associated PN generators with a system time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start timer module for staffing timing of a predetermined time interval after the probe module has sent the series of access probes; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a stop timer module for stopping the timing of the predetermined time interval, leaving the transmit clock on in response to a subsequent access attempt within the predetermined time interval; and for stopping the timing of the predetermined time interval, turning the transmit clock off in response to no subsequent access attempt within the predetermined time interval.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00041" num="00041">
<claim-text>41. The set of timer modules of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00040">claim 40</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval comprises a time unit in the range of one second to five seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00042" num="00042">
<claim-text>42. The set of timer modules of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00041">claim 41</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval further comprises a time unit in the range of two seconds to four seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00043" num="00043">
<claim-text>43. The set of timer modules of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00042">claim 42</claim-ref>, wherein the predetermined time interval further comprises two seconds.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00044" num="00044">
<claim-text>44. A system in a wireless communication network having a sending device with a power device, a receiving device, and a link, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a control device that limits the activation of the power device so that the sending device is synchronized to the receiving device via the link during an initial access attempt and the activation continues through subsequent access attempts, and is stopped after no subsequent access attempt occurs within an optimal time interval.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
