<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299077-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299077</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10795332</doc-number>
<date>20040309</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>92203933 U</doc-number>
<date>20030314</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>793</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>M</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4555753</main-classification>
<further-classification>4555751</further-classification>
<further-classification>4555501</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Exchangeable decor panel for portable cellular phone</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0109560</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Nuovo et al.</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>379440</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>411017794</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>8</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4555751</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4555501</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4555753</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>379450</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>379440</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>D14248</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>D14138</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040180706</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040916</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Pan</last-name>
<first-name>Long-Jyh</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Troxell Law Office, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>BENQ Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>TaoYuan</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ramakrishnaiah</last-name>
<first-name>Melur</first-name>
<department>2614</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A structure of exchangeable décor panel for portable cellular phone that is applied to the folding portable cellular phone having a continuing groove located on a proper position of flip cover and base portion thereof for accommodating a décor panel made of flexible material, wherein said flexible décor panel is installed in its inner side with two rigid plates whose outer rims conform exactly to the outer rims of said décor panel, moreover, there is at least one retainer extending outwards from the outer rim of said rigid plate for clipping on the corresponding retainer holes installed inside said continuing groove to form a compact structure, thus, said décor panel can be changed at will to enable said cellular phone to have different appearance.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="128.10mm" wi="165.10mm" file="US07299077-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="158.67mm" wi="121.24mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299077-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="165.61mm" wi="134.62mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299077-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="157.73mm" wi="136.14mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299077-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="136.06mm" wi="141.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299077-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="136.57mm" wi="142.41mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299077-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="122.34mm" wi="97.20mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299077-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="169.93mm" wi="127.85mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299077-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">(a). Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a portable cellular phone with exchangeable décor panel, more specifically to an exterior décor panel design for the folding portable cellular phone.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">(b). Description of the Prior Arts</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Today, telecommunication industry is becoming more and more important for human life. There are products from the early telephone, fax machine and intercom and so on, to the Global Positioning System (GPS), pager, wireless communication and fixed network etc. of the modem world. The advances in the telecommunication industry are making it possible to rapidly transmit the voice, image and graphic via a wireless means. The result is the fast development and prosperity of the global economy and industry. Consequently, the computer industry and the telecommunication industry are destined to become the two leading industry which can progress in the speed beyond human imagination and bring a vast change to human life.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Due to the development of GSM cellular phone, portable cellular phones have come into wide use in Taiwan for connecting friends, relatives and clients with great efficiency. Moreover, the global roaming capability of the GSM cellular phone enables the user to be able to use his portable cellular phone everywhere in the world that, in consequence, provides a favorable condition for the prevalence of cellular phone. Besides, in addition to the common answering incoming calls and issuing outgoing calls, modem cellular phones have many additional functions (such as recording, calendar, games, MP3, WAP, etc.). Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a schematic drawing is presented illustrating a structure of exchangeable décor panel for portable cellular phone. In order to pander to people's liking for novelty, some cellular phone manufacturers design a product with exchangeable décor panel that can be changed by consumers (e.g. Nokia 3310, 8810, etc.). The kind of cellular phone is composed of a body A<b>2</b>, a front cover A<b>1</b> and a back cover A<b>3</b>. Through changing the front cover A<b>1</b> and back cover A<b>3</b> with different pattern and color, the consumer's craving for novelty can be fulfilled.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">While changing the décor panel of the portable cellular phone using the aforementioned method, in order to prevent the décor panel from falling off by outside influences, the locking clasps between the front and back cover are designed to be rigidly precise. Therefore, the method for changing the décor panel of the portable cellular phone can still present a daunting task for many users. The method will require many practices to be able to master and is not acceptable for most consumers.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">As to the folding portable cellular phone, it is common that no structure with exchangeable décor panel is installed. Therefore, the appearance of the kind of cellular phone is usually too stale to stir up the craving of young cellular phone consumers. In view of the above drawback, the present invention is related to a structure of exchangeable décor panel for the folding portable cellular phone.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In view of the above drawback of the prior art, the present invention is a portable cellular phone with exchangeable décor panel. The primary object of the present invention is to provide a folding portable cellular phone having a continuing groove located at a proper position of the flip cover and the base portion thereof for accommodating a décor panel made of flexible material. The flexible décor panel is installed in its inner side with two rigid plates whose outer rims conform exactly to the outer rims of the décor panel. There is at least one retainer extending outwards from the outer rim of the rigid plate for clipping on the corresponding retainer holes installed inside the continuing groove to form a compact structure. Thus, the décor panel can be changed at will to enable the cellular phone to have different appearance.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Another object of the present invention is to enable users of the portable cellular phone to take off and change the décor panel by themselves without the help of any auxiliary tools, so that the décor panel of the cellular phone can be changed with ease and convenience.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The third object of the present invention is to provide an opening installed at the proper position of the décor panel and the rigid plate to cooperate with a second screen of the cellular phone for displaying.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Yet another object of the present invention is to provide the cellular phone with a better protection while subjecting to an impact by employing the flexible décor panel as a buffer.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Other and further features, advantages and benefits of the invention will become apparent in the following description taken in conjunction with the following drawings. It is to be understood that the foregoing general description and following detailed description are exemplary and explanatory but are not to be restrictive of the invention. The accompanying drawings are incorporated in and constitute a part of this application and, together with the description, serve to explain the principles of the invention in general terms. Like numerals refer to like parts throughout the disclosure.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The objects, spirits and advantages of the preferred embodiments of the present invention will be readily understood by the accompanying drawings and detailed descriptions, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic drawing showing a structure of exchangeable décor panel for portable cellular phone according to prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is the first three dimensional schematic representation depicting the main body of the cellular phone according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is the second three dimensional schematic representation depicting the main body of the cellular phone according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is the first three dimensional schematic representation depicting the décor panel of the cellular phone according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is the second three dimensional schematic representation depicting the décor panel of the cellular phone according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a sectional side view schematically showing a compact structure formed by fitting a bump protruding outwards from the décor panel to the retainer holes of the main body according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a three dimensional schematic representation depicting the formation of the main body of cellular phone and the décor panel according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The following embodiments will illustrate the device and the method for processing the digital image of the present invention in detail.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the portable cellular phone, as shown, is a folding cellular phone <b>1</b> having a continuing groove located at a proper position of the flip cover <b>11</b> and the base portion <b>12</b> thereof, wherein the groove <b>12</b> located on the flip cover <b>11</b> is installed with a first retainer hole <b>131</b>, a second retainer hole <b>132</b>, a third retainer hole <b>133</b> and a fourth retainer hole <b>134</b>; and the groove <b>12</b> located on the base portion <b>12</b> is installed with a fifth retainer hole <b>135</b>, a sixth retainer hole <b>136</b>, a seventh retainer hole <b>137</b> and a eighth retainer hole <b>138</b>, moreover, the groove <b>12</b> can accommodate a flexible décor panel <b>2</b> made of rubber. The surface of the décor panel <b>2</b> can be painted with all kinds of patterns and colors for the attraction of consumer's attendance. The two inner sides of the flexible décor panel <b>2</b> are installed with a first rigid plate <b>3</b> and a second rigid plate <b>4</b>. The two rigid plates (<b>3</b>, <b>4</b>) are made of a metal or rigid plastic, and the outer rims thereof conform exactly to the outer rims of the décor panel <b>2</b>, wherein a first retainer <b>31</b>, a second retainer <b>32</b> and a third retainer <b>33</b> are protruding outwards from the outer rim of the first rigid plate <b>3</b>, and further, a first bump <b>35</b> is installed at a proper position in the inner side of the first rigid plate <b>3</b>; correspondingly, a fourth retainer <b>41</b>, a fifth retainer <b>42</b> and a sixth retainer <b>43</b> are protruding outwards from the outer rim of the second rigid plate <b>4</b>, and further a second bump <b>44</b> is installed at a proper position in the inner side of the second rigid plate <b>4</b>. A hinge <b>15</b> connecting the flip cover <b>11</b> and the base portion <b>12</b> of the folding cellular phone <b>1</b> is covered by the décor panel <b>2</b>, so that it can be a simple and practical structure without the need for beautification to save the cost for designing the hinge <b>15</b>. An antenna <b>16</b> is installed at a proper position of the cellular phone <b>1</b> for receiving and transmitting signals.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Besides the foregoing décor panel structure for the cellular phone, in response to the most popular folding cellular phone design these days is a cellular with double screens, where a second screen <b>14</b> is installed on the outer side of the flip cover <b>11</b> in addition to the first screen (not shown) installed on the inner side of the flip cover <b>11</b>. The second screen <b>14</b> can display information, such as time, caller ID, signal strength, etc., which otherwise can not be read using the conventional folding cellular phone <b>1</b> before opening its flip cover. Therefore, according to the present invention, the décor panel of the folding cellular phone with double screens is installed with an opening (<b>21</b>, <b>34</b>) to cooperate with the second screen <b>14</b> of the cellular phone for displaying information.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, in order to combine the cellular phone <b>1</b> with the décor panel <b>2</b>, the first retainer <b>31</b>, the second retainer <b>32</b> and the third retainer <b>33</b> protruding outwards from the outer rim of the décor panel <b>2</b> are clipped on the corresponding first retainer hole <b>131</b>, the second retainer hole <b>132</b> and the hird retainer hole <b>133</b>, and, the same time that the first bump <b>35</b> located on the first rigid plate <b>3</b> slips into the fourth retainer hole <b>134</b>, so that a structure with décor panel <b>2</b> fixed on the flip cover <b>11</b> is complete, furthermore, the fourth retainer <b>41</b>, the fifth retainer <b>42</b> and the sixth retainer <b>43</b> of the décor panel <b>2</b> are clipped on the corresponding fifth retainer hole <b>135</b>, the sixth retainer hole <b>162</b> and the seventh retainer hole <b>137</b>, and, the same time that the second bump <b>44</b> located on the second rigid plate <b>4</b> slips into the eighth retainer hole <b>138</b>, so that a structure with décor panel <b>2</b> fixed on the base portion <b>12</b> is complete</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">As shown in the aforementioned <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the present invention indeed can be applied to the folding portable cellular phone with functions that can not be accomplished by the prior art. That is, the present invention having a continuing groove for accommodating a flexible décor panel, wherein the flexible décor panel contains in its inner side two rigid plates with at least one set of protruding retainer for clipping on the continuing groove to form a compact structure. Thus, the décor panel can be changed at will to enable the cellular phone to have different appearance. Besides, the present invention provides the cellular phone with a better protection while subjecting to an impact by employing the flexible décor panel as a buffer. Moreover, A hinge connecting the flip cover and the base portion of the folding cellular phone is covered by the décor panel, so that it can be a simple and practical structure without the need for beautification.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">While the present invention has been shown and described with reference to a preferred embodiment thereof, and in terms of the illustrative drawings, it should be not considered as limited thereby. Various possible modification, omission, and alterations could be conceived of by one skilled in the art to the form and the content of any particular embodiment, without departing from the scope and the sprit of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A structure of exchangeable décor panel for portable cellular phone that is applied to a folding portable cellular phone having a continuing groove located its flip cover and base portion for accommodating a décor panel made of flexible material, wherein the inner side of said flexible décor panel is installed with two rigid plates whose outer rims conform exactly to the outer rims of said décor panel, moreover, there is at least one retainer extending outwards from the outer rim of said rigid plate for clipping onto a corresponding retainer hole installed inside said continuing groove to form a compact structure, thus, said décor panel can be changed at will for enabling said cellular phone to have different appearance.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said décor panel is made of rubber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said décor panel is made of leather.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said décor panel is made of a metal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said rigid plate is made of a rigid plastic.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein an opening is installed on said décor panel and said rigid plate to cooperate with a second screen of said cellular phone for displaying.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein at least one bump is installed respectively in the inner side of both said rigid plates for fitting into a retainer hole located on said groove of said cellular phone so as to form a structure for fixing said décor panel onto the exterior of said cellular phone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said retainer holes located on said groove include a first retainer hole, a second retainer hole, a third retainer hole, a fourth retainer hole, a fifth retainer hole, a sixth retainer hole, a seventh retainer hole, and an eighth retainer hole, which corresponding to a first retainer, a second retainer, a third retainer, a fourth retainer, a fifth retainer, a sixth retainer, a seventh retainer, and an eighth retainer of said second rigid plate for fixing said décor panel onto said cellular phone.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
