<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298613-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298613</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10948447</doc-number>
<date>20040923</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>35</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361686</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Portable computer docking station</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5627450</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ryan et al.</name>
<date>19970500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5859762</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Clark et al.</name>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361686</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6076787</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Troyer</name>
<date>20000600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6185094</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ruch et al.</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6208508</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ruch et al.</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6256193</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Janik et al.</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6480376</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Nguyen et al.</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6583985</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Nguyen et al.</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0103328</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hillis et al.</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0057893</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Homer et al.</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361683</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0057896</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Homer</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361686</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>22</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361679</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361683</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361686</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361687</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060061961</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060323</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yin</last-name>
<first-name>Memphis-Zhihong</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tomball</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Doczy</last-name>
<first-name>Paul J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Cypress</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wolff</last-name>
<first-name>Stacy L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Cypress</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hewlett-Packard Development Company, L.P.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Houston</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chang</last-name>
<first-name>Yean-Hsi</first-name>
<department>2835</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A portable computer docking station comprising a base and a panel rotatably connected to the base. An angle is formed between the base and the panel. A mounting point is disposed on the panel and provides a releasable connection to an interface assembly that is operable to releasably connect to a portable computer. An adjusting system controls the angle of the panel relative to the base.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="132.25mm" wi="148.00mm" file="US07298613-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="230.12mm" wi="165.78mm" file="US07298613-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="244.52mm" wi="152.23mm" file="US07298613-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="212.51mm" wi="177.29mm" file="US07298613-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="214.21mm" wi="153.33mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298613-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Portable computers are compact, lightweight computing devices and may comprise any portable electronic device, for example, notebook computers, personal digital assistants, tablet personal computers, and laptop computers. Although designed for portability and mobile uses, many people use portable computers in desktop environments. The use of portable computers in desktop environments has always created challenges with ergonomics and ease of use. Many of the features that make portable computers useful mobile tools, such as compact size and integrated components, can be limitations when used in a desktop environment.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Portable computer docking stations have been developed to ease the use of a portable computer in a desktop environment. Many of these docking stations provide interfaces with peripheral equipment, for example, input devices, networks, printers, and additional display devices, that allows the portable computer to be more easily used as a desktop system. Certain pieces of peripheral equipment, such as additional displays and input devices, enable more ergonomic use of a portable computer but are redundant to components integral to the portable computer. These redundant components not only increase hardware investment but also often occupy a large amount of desktop space.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Therefore, as can be appreciated, there is a need for a portable computer docking station that enables ergonomic use of a portable computer while limiting the use of desktop space. The problems noted above are solved in large part by a portable computer docking station comprising a base and a panel rotatably connected to the base. An angle is formed between the base and the panel. A mounting point is disposed on the panel and provides a releasable connection to an interface assembly that is operable to releasably connect to a portable computer. An adjusting system controls the angle of the panel relative to the base.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">For a detailed description of exemplary embodiments of the invention, reference will now be made to the accompanying drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a front perspective view of a portable computer docking station in accordance with embodiments of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a rear view of the portable computer docking station of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a front perspective view of a portable computer installed on a portable computer docking station in accordance with embodiments of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a side view of a portable computer installed on a portable computer docking station in accordance with embodiments of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates an adjustment system in accordance with embodiments of the invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a front perspective view of a portable computer docking station in accordance with embodiments of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">NOTATION AND NOMENCLATURE</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Certain terms are used throughout the following description and claims to refer to particular system components. As one skilled in the art will appreciate, computer companies may refer to a component by different names. This document does not intend to distinguish between components that differ in name but not function. In the following discussion and in the claims, the terms “including” and “comprising” are used in an open-ended fashion, and thus should be interpreted to mean “including, but not limited to . . . . ” Also, the term “couple” or “couples” is intended to mean either an indirect or a direct electrical connection. Thus, if a first device couples to a second device, that connection may be through a direct electrical connection, or through an indirect electrical connection via other devices and connections.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, portable computer docking station <b>10</b> comprises base <b>12</b>, panel <b>14</b>, hinge <b>16</b>, and adjustment system <b>18</b>. Computer docking station <b>10</b> is shown with portable computer interface assembly <b>20</b> removably connected to panel <b>14</b> at mounting point <b>38</b>. Base <b>12</b> comprises a substantially planar main body <b>22</b> having a front edge <b>24</b> and a rear edge <b>26</b>. Front edge <b>24</b> comprises outer hinge mounts <b>28</b> that interface with hinge <b>16</b>. Rear edge <b>26</b> comprises cable slot <b>30</b> that runs along body <b>22</b> towards front edge <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Panel <b>14</b> comprises front surface <b>32</b>, rear surface <b>34</b>, and lower edge <b>36</b>. Panel <b>14</b> also comprises mounting points <b>38</b> that engage portable computer interface <b>20</b>, and protruding shoulders <b>40</b> that support an installed portable computer (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). Adjustment system <b>18</b> is housed within panel <b>14</b> and can be actuated by handles <b>42</b>, which are mounted on rear surface <b>34</b>. Cable tray <b>44</b> is disposed on rear surface <b>34</b> and may be aligned with cable slot <b>30</b> in base <b>12</b>. Lower edge <b>36</b> comprises inner hinge mount <b>46</b> that interfaces with hinge <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Interface assembly <b>20</b> can be releasably connected to panel <b>14</b> and comprises an electronic interface <b>48</b> that detachably couples to a portable computer system (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). Assembly <b>20</b> may releasably connect to panel <b>14</b> using any effective releasable connector. Assembly <b>20</b> is shown as having slots <b>50</b> that releasably engage mounting points <b>38</b>. Mounting points <b>38</b> are preferably compatible with a variety of interface assemblies allowing a single docking station to be used with more than one interface assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Interface assembly <b>20</b> may be a port replicator (PR), an advanced port replicator (APR), or the like, that provides fixed attachment points for cables for network connections, peripheral equipment, and other components. Assembly <b>20</b> also comprises input/output ports <b>52</b> that provide communication between the portable computer system and peripheral systems plugged into the ports. Ports <b>52</b> may comprise serial, parallel, universal serial bus (USB), and other electronic data transfer and communication ports.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, portable computer <b>54</b> is shown installed on computer docking station <b>10</b>. Computer <b>54</b> is coupled to interface assembly <b>20</b> by interface <b>48</b> and supported by shoulders <b>40</b> on panel <b>14</b>. Connecting cables <b>56</b> can be routed through cable slot <b>30</b> and tray <b>44</b> to couple to ports <b>52</b> on assembly <b>20</b>. Adjustment mechanism <b>18</b> can be actuated by pulling on one, or both, of handles <b>42</b> such that panel <b>14</b> can be rotated about hinge <b>16</b> to a desired working elevation. Although shown as configured for a notebook computer system, computer docking station <b>10</b> may also be configured for use as a docking station for a variety of portable computer systems.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, adjustment mechanism <b>18</b> is shown comprising handles <b>42</b>, actuation cables <b>58</b>, and latch <b>60</b>. Latch <b>60</b> comprises actuation arms <b>66</b>, engaging arm <b>68</b>, and biasing spring <b>70</b>. Handles <b>42</b> comprise cable attachment bar <b>72</b> and springs <b>74</b>. Adjustment mechanism <b>18</b> is used to limit the rotation of panel <b>14</b> about hinge <b>16</b>. Hinge <b>16</b> comprises shaft <b>62</b> that has ends <b>64</b> retained in outer hinge mounts <b>28</b>. Shaft <b>62</b> also has splined section <b>64</b> that is aligned with latch <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Biasing spring <b>70</b> urges engaging arm <b>68</b> against splined section <b>64</b> by rotating latch <b>60</b> about pivot <b>76</b>. Engaging arm <b>68</b> has teeth <b>78</b> that engage splined section <b>64</b> and prevent rotation of shaft <b>62</b>. When one, or both, of handles <b>42</b> are pulled outward, springs <b>74</b> compress and tension is applied to actuation cables <b>58</b>. Actuation cables <b>58</b> transfer this tension to actuation arms <b>66</b>, which, when pulled, cause latch <b>60</b> to rotate. As latch <b>60</b> rotates, biasing spring <b>70</b> is compressed and teeth <b>78</b> disengage splined section <b>64</b>, enabling panel <b>14</b> to rotate relative to shaft <b>62</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Panel <b>14</b> can be rotated to any desired position. Once panel <b>14</b> is positioned, handles <b>42</b> are released and adjustment system <b>18</b> maintains the position of panel <b>14</b>. The release of handles <b>42</b> enables springs <b>74</b> to retract the handles and relieve tension from actuating cables <b>58</b>. Without the tension from actuating cables <b>58</b>, biasing spring <b>70</b> rotates latch <b>60</b> back towards its initial position and engaging arm <b>68</b> engages shaft <b>72</b>. The interface between teeth <b>78</b> and splined section <b>64</b> prevents rotation of shaft <b>72</b> relative to panel <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Adjustment system <b>18</b> is one embodiment of a system for angular adjustment of panel <b>14</b> relative to base <b>12</b>. Other one-hand and two-hand actuated systems may be used. Adjustment system <b>18</b> facilitates movement of panel <b>14</b> from substantially parallel to base <b>12</b> to an incline of between 0 and approximately 45 degrees, or more. Other ranges of inclination are also possible.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, portable computer docking station <b>10</b> is shown with an alternate computer interface assembly <b>80</b> installed. Computer interface assembly is illustrated as an advanced port replicator that provides increased functionality over the port replicator as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>. Interface assembly <b>80</b> also comprises an electronic interface <b>48</b> that couples to a portable computer. Assembly <b>80</b> may mount to panel <b>14</b> using any effective connector and is shown as having slots <b>82</b> that engage mounting points <b>38</b>. In this manner, mounting points <b>38</b> can be used to support a variety docking stations, port replicators, and other interface assemblies as desired, thus providing flexibility in the use of computer docking station <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The above discussion is meant to be illustrative of the principles and various embodiments of the present invention. Numerous variations and modifications will become apparent to those skilled in the art once the above disclosure is fully appreciated. For example, an adjustable computer docking station may be configured for use with a variety of portable computers, for example, other types of notebook systems, notepad systems, personal digital assistants, and other equipment.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A portable computer docking station comprising: a base;
<claim-text>a panel comprising a front surface and a rear surface, wherein said panel is rotatably connected to said base so that the rear surface faces said base and forms an angle between said base and the rear surface of said panel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a mounting point disposed on the front surface of said panel, wherein said mounting point provides a releasable connection to an interface assembly, wherein the interface assembly is operable to releasably connect to a portable computer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjusting system that controls the angle of said panel relative to said base.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the angle of said panel relative to said base is adjustable between substantially 0° and 45° or more.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the interface assembly comprises at least one port that couples to peripheral devices.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a cable slot disposed on said base.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a cable tray disposed on said panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said adjusting system is constructed so as to be operable with one hand.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A portable computer docking station comprising:
<claim-text>a base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a panel rotatably connected to said base so as to form an angle between said base and said panel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a mounting point disposed on said panel, wherein said mounting point provides a releasable connection to an interface assembly, wherein the interface assembly is operable to releasably connect to a portable computer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjusting system that controls the angle of said panel relative to said base, wherein said adjusting system comprises:
<claim-text>a latch having an engaged position that prevents movement of said panel relative to said base and a disengaged position that enables movement of said panel relative to said base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cable connected to said latch; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a handle connected to said cable such that actuation of said handle applies tension to said cable so as to move said latch from the engaged position to the disengaged position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further comprising a spring that urges said latch to the engaged position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A portable computer docking station comprising:
<claim-text>a panel comprising a front surface, a back surface, and a lower edge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a hinge connected to the lower edge of said panel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base connected to said hinge so that the back surface faces said base, wherein said base is disposed at an angle to said panel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjusting system interfaced with said hinge, wherein said adjusting system varies the angle between said base and said panel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface assembly removably attached to the front surface of said panel, wherein said interface assembly is operable to releasably connect to a portable computer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said hinge comprises:
<claim-text>outer hinge mounts disposed on said base; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shaft comprising ends retained by said outer hinge mounts.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the said panel can be disposed at an angle to said base between substantially 0° and 45° or more.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said adjusting system is constructed so as to enable one-handed operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A portable computer docking station comprising:
<claim-text>a panel comprising a front surface, a back surface, and a lower edge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a hinge connected to the lower edge of said panel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base connected to said hinge, wherein said base is disposed at an angle to said panel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjusting system interfaced with said hinge, wherein said adjusting system varies the angle between said base and said panel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface assembly removably attached to the front surface of said panel, wherein said interface assembly is operable to releasably connect to a portable computer, wherein said adjusting system comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a latch attached to said panel, wherein said latch has a first position engaged with said shaft and a second position disengaged from said shaft; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a handle that moves said latch from the first position to the second position, wherein the first position prevents movement of said panel relative to said base.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising a cable connected to said handle to said latch.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising a spring that urges said latch to the first position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method comprising:
<claim-text>mounting an interface assembly to a front surface of a panel that is movably connected to a base by a hinge so that a back surface of the panel faces the base, wherein the panel is disposed at an angle to the base and the interface assembly is operably to releasably connect to a portable computer system; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>using an adjusting system to change the angle between the panel and the base and maintain the angle between the panel and the base, wherein the adjusting system comprises:
<claim-text>a latch having a first position that fixes the position of the panel relative to the base and a second position that enables movement of the panel relative to the base; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a handle that moves the latch from the first position to the second position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> wherein the latch is moved from the first position to the second position by actuating a handle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> the latch is moved from the second position to the first position when the handle is released.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> further comprising coupling a portable computer to the interface assembly, wherein the interface assembly provides an electrical connection between the portable computer and peripheral equipment communicatively connected to the interface assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A portable computer docking station comprising:
<claim-text>means for removably attaching an interface assembly to a front surface of a panel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for releasably connecting a portable computer to the interface assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for supporting the panel at an angle to a base, wherein a back surface of the panel faces the base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for adjusting the angle between the panel and the base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for biasing a tooth surface against a corresponding locking surface to prevent movement of the panel relative to the base.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref>, wherein the means for supporting the panel supports a portable computer coupled to the interface assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The portable computer docking station of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref> wherein said means for adjusting the angle can be operated with a single hand.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
