<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298603-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298603</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11493093</doc-number>
<date>20060725</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-215860</doc-number>
<date>20050726</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>4</main-group>
<subgroup>005</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>4</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361303</main-classification>
<further-classification>361311</further-classification>
<further-classification> 29 2542</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Multilayer ceramic capacitor and manufacturing method of the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4477858</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Steiner</name>
<date>19841000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361273</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6661640</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Togashi</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3613063</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6768630</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Togashi</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3613061</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6912115</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kobayashi et al.</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3613063</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0285271</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lee et al.</name>
<date>20061200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361303</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>8-124785</doc-number>
<date>19960500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-22930</doc-number>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361303-305</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361311</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29 2542</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070025055</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070201</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mizuno</last-name>
<first-name>Youichi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Gunma</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nishikawa</last-name>
<first-name>Jun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Gunma</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kawamura</last-name>
<first-name>Chie</first-name>
<address>
<city>Gunma</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Knobbe Martens Olson &amp; Bear LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Taiyo Yuden Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Thomas</last-name>
<first-name>Eric</first-name>
<department>2831</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">In one inventive aspect, a multilayer ceramic capacitor is provided, in which occurrence of cracks can be prevented even when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased. Non-flat portions are formed in both sides in a width direction of each of inner electrode layers. In addition, the non-flat portions comprise regions substantially changed into oxide regions, therefore a thermal expansion coefficient of the non-flat portions can be decreased so that stress due to difference in thermal expansion coefficient to non-flat portions can be reduced, and the stress can be dispersed in accordance with curvature or inclination of the non-flat portions. That is, stress generated when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased is decreased and dispersed, thereby occurrence of cracks due to the stress can be prevented in side margins of the ceramic chip.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="83.57mm" wi="77.81mm" file="US07298603-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="195.33mm" wi="130.64mm" file="US07298603-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="214.71mm" wi="153.25mm" file="US07298603-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="163.32mm" wi="118.96mm" file="US07298603-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a multilayer ceramic capacitor, and a method of manufacturing the multilayer ceramic capacitor.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Technology</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The multilayer ceramic capacitor has a ceramic chip in a rectangular prism shape having a structure where a plurality of inner electrode layers are stacked via ceramic portions, and an edge of each of the inner electrode layers is alternately exposed on either end face in a length direction, and a pair of outer electrodes formed at both ends in the length direction of the ceramic chip. The ceramic portions include a dielectric such as BaTiO<sub>3</sub>, and the inner electrode layers and the outer electrodes includes a metal such as Ni.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The multilayer ceramic capacitor is manufactured through a step of stacking and pressing non-baked ceramic layers having non-baked inner electrode layers formed therein to obtain a non-baked ceramic chip, a step of forming non-baked outer electrodes at both ends in a length direction of the non-baked ceramic chip, and a step of baking the non-baked ceramic chip having the non-baked outer electrodes formed therein. When the metal configuring the inner electrode layers is a base metal, a step of reoxidation of the ceramic chip after baking is performed for controlling characteristics as necessary.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Certain background information may be found in Japanese Patent Documents JP-A-8-124785 and JP-A-2003-22930, each of which is incorporated by reference in it entirety.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The multilayer ceramic capacitor is generally mounted on various substrates by soldering, and when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased in soldering or voltage application after mounting, cracks may occur in the ceramic chip. The cracks occur mainly due to a fact that a thermal expansion coefficient of the inner electrode layers is higher than that of ceramic portions, that is, inner electrodes being thermally expanded cause stress mainly in side margin portions of the ceramic chip, and the stress causes occurrence of the cracks in the margin portions. Since the cracks in the ceramic chip may be a factor of significant change in capacitor characteristics, a measure is necessary, the measure being for preventing the cracks in the ceramic chip even when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">A capacitor in size 0603 (a reference value in a length direction is 0.6 mm and reference values in width and height directions are 0.3 mm) or size 0402 (a reference value in a length direction is 0.4 mm and reference values in width and height directions are 0.2 mm) is put into practical use with recent requirement of increase in capacity and size reduction, and the occurrence of cracks tends to be more significant with reduction in size of the multilayer ceramic capacitor, therefore the measure for preventing the cracks is now an extremely important technical development subject.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">It is desirable to provide a multilayer ceramic capacitor in which occurrence of cracks in a ceramic chip can be prevented even when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased, and a method of manufacturing a multilayer ceramic capacitor by which the multilayer ceramic capacitor can be preferably manufactured.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF CERTAIN INVENTIVE ASPECTS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A multilayer ceramic capacitor according to one inventive aspect has a ceramic chip in a shape of a rectangular prism having a structure where a plurality of inner electrode layers are stacked via ceramic portions, wherein the plurality of inner electrode layers are in a rectangular shape having predetermined width, length and thickness, and at least part of the plurality of inner electrode layers have flat portions in centers in a width direction and non-flat portions at both sides in the width direction, and the non-flat portions comprise substantially oxidized regions.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to the multilayer ceramic capacitor, the non-flat portions are formed in both sides in the width direction of the inner electrode layers, in addition, the non-flat portions comprise substantially oxidized regions, therefore a thermal expansion coefficient of the non-flat portions can be decreased so that stress due to difference in thermal expansion coefficient to the non-flat portions can be reduced, and the stress can be dispersed in accordance with curvature or inclination of the non-flat portions. That is, stress generated when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased is decreased and dispersed, thereby occurrence of cracks due to the stress can be prevented in the side margins of the ceramic chip.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A method of manufacturing a multilayer ceramic capacitor according to one inventive aspect, has a step of stacking and pressing a plurality of non-baked ceramic layers having non-baked inner electrode layers formed therein such that at least part of the plurality of non-baked inner electrode layers are made to be non-flat at both sides in a width direction, so that a non-baked ceramic chip is obtained; and a step of baking the non-baked ceramic chip in a condition that a substantially oxidized region is formed in the non-flat portions at both the sides in the width direction of at least the part of the plurality of non-baked inner electrode layers, so that the ceramic chip is obtained.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to the method of manufacturing the multilayer ceramic capacitor, the multilayer ceramic capacitor can be manufactured preferably and precisely.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to one inventive aspect, a multilayer ceramic capacitor having a ceramic chip in which cracks do not occur even when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased, and a method of preferably manufacturing the multilayer ceramic capacitor can be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Configurations, operations and effects of the embodiment of certain inventive aspects will be made clear according to the following description and attached drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a multilayer ceramic capacitor;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross section view along a line a-a of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross section view along a line b-b of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view showing an example of a method of manufacturing the multilayer ceramic capacitor shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a view showing the example of the method of manufacturing the tacked ceramic capacitor shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 3</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a view showing the example of the method of manufacturing the tacked ceramic capacitor shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 3</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF CERTAIN ILLUSTRATIVE EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a multilayer ceramic capacitor, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross section view along a line a-a of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross section view along a line b-b of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The multilayer ceramic capacitor <b>10</b> has a ceramic chip <b>11</b> in a shape of a rectangular prism having a predetermined length, width, and height, and a pair of outer electrodes <b>12</b> provided at both ends in a length direction of the ceramic chip <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The ceramic chip <b>11</b> has a structure in which a plurality of inner electrode layers <b>13</b> including a base metal such as Ni, Cu or Sn are stacked via ceramic portions <b>14</b> including a dielectric such as BaTiO<sub>3</sub>. An edge of each of the inner electrode layers <b>13</b> is exposed alternately on either end face in a length direction of the ceramic chip <b>11</b>. Each of outer electrodes <b>12</b> includes a base metal such as Ni, Cu or Sn, and is conducted to each of the exposed edges of the inner electrode layers <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The plurality of inner electrode layers <b>13</b> are formed in a rectangular shape having predetermined width, length and thickness, and as known from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, each inner electrode layer <b>13</b> has a flat portion <b>13</b><i>a </i>in the center in a width direction and non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>in both sides in the width direction. While curved portions (portions bent in an arcuate form) are shown as the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>may be inclined portions with respect to the flat portion <b>13</b><i>a </i>(slant portions by being inclined), or mixed portions of curved and inclined portions. Moreover, while <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a chip where the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>are directed to the center in a height direction of the ceramic chip <b>11</b>, the portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>may be directed to a lower side in the height direction of the ceramic chip <b>11</b>, or directed to an upper side in the direction of the ceramic chip <b>11</b>, or may be randomly directed.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Moreover, the non-flat portion <b>13</b><i>b </i>of each inner electrode layer <b>13</b> includes a region substantially changed into an oxide region. In other words, the non-flat portion <b>13</b><i>b </i>of each inner electrode layer <b>13</b> as a whole is substantially changed into the oxide region, or part of the portion <b>13</b><i>b </i>is substantially changed into the oxide region. That is, capacitance of the multilayer ceramic capacitor <b>10</b> is mainly determined by the flat portions <b>13</b><i>a </i>of the plurality of inner electrode layers <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, W indicates total lateral size of the inner electrode layer <b>13</b>, Wa indicates lateral size of the flat portion <b>13</b><i>a</i>, Wb indicates lateral size of the non-flat portion <b>13</b><i>b</i>, and MG indicates a space of a side margin portion of the ceramic chip <b>11</b> (space between a side edge of the non-flat portion <b>13</b><i>b </i>and a side face of the ceramic chip <b>11</b> facing the side edge).</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Again in the multilayer ceramic capacitor <b>10</b>, when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased in soldering or voltage application after mounting, thermal expansion occurs in each of the inner electrode layers <b>13</b> and each of the ceramic portions <b>14</b>, however, the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>are provided at both the sides in the width direction of each inner electrode layer <b>13</b>, in addition, the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>include a region substantially changed into the oxide region, therefore the thermal expansion coefficient of the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>is reduced so that stress due to difference in thermal expansion coefficient to the ceramic portions <b>14</b> can be reduced, and the stress can be dispersed in accordance with curvature and inclination of the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b</i>. That is, the stress generated when temperature of the capacitor itself is increased is reduced and dispersed, thereby occurrence of cracks due to the stress can be prevented in the side margin portions and the like of the ceramic chip <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">To more effectively reduce the stress generated in the side margin portions of the ceramic chip <b>11</b>, the lateral size Wb of the non-flat portion <b>14</b><i>a </i>can be within a range of 0.1 to 10% of the total lateral size W of the inner electrode layers <b>13</b>, and preferably within a range of 1 to 5%. When the lateral size is less than 0.1%, the effect of preventing the occurrence of cracks is hardly obtained, and when it exceeds 10%, capacitance is significantly decreased. Moreover, the space MG of the side margin portion of the ceramic chip <b>11</b> is made within a range of 1 to 20% of the lateral size (W+2MG) of the ceramic chip, and preferably within a range of 2 to 15%. When it is less than 1%, oxidation may proceed to the flat portion <b>13</b><i>a </i>of the inner electrode layer <b>13</b>, and when it exceeds 20%, the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>tend to be insufficiently changed into oxidized regions.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 to 6</figref> show an example of a method of manufacturing the multilayer ceramic capacitor <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">First, non-baked ceramic layers CL<b>1</b> to CL<b>3</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> are stacked and subjected to thermal compression bond in an order as shown in the figure to obtain a non-baked ceramic chip CC (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The non-baked ceramic layer CL<b>1</b> includes a green sheet formed by coating slurry containing dielectric powder of BaTiO<sub>3 </sub>and the like, organic binder and organic solvent on a film and then drying it. The non-baked ceramic layers CL<b>2</b> and CL<b>3</b> are prepared by forming non-baked inner electrode layers EL<b>1</b> and EL<b>2</b> by printing conductive paste in a rectangular pattern having predetermined width, length and thickness on a surface of a green sheet similar to that of the non-baked ceramic layer CL<b>1</b>, the paste containing powder of a base metal of Ni, Cu or Sn, organic binder and organic solvent, and then drying it.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">While <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the non-baked ceramic layers CL<b>1</b> to CL<b>3</b> having a size corresponding to a single component, actually, the non-baked ceramic layers have a size corresponding to multi components taken at a time, and the non-baked inner electrode layers are formed multiply in predetermined arrangement. The non-baked ceramic chip CC is prepared by dividing a stacked body, which was obtained by stacking the non-baked ceramic layers and performing thermal compression bond to the layers, into a unit size.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the non-baked ceramic chip CC has a structure where a plurality of the non-baked inner electrode layers EL<b>1</b> and EL<b>2</b> are stacked via non-baked ceramic portions CP, and non-flat portions BP are formed at both sides in a width direction of each of the non-baked inner electrode layers EL<b>1</b> and EL<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Levels of curvature and inclination of the non-flat portions BP can be controlled by controlling thickness of the non-baked inner electrode layers. That is, when the thickness of the non-baked inner electrode layers is increased, a vertical deformation level of the side margin portions of the non-baked ceramic layers is increased during stacking and pressing to be able to increase the levels of curvature and inclination of the portions at both the sides in the width direction of the non-baked inner electrode layers associated with the vertical deformation.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, conductive paste like the above is coated on both ends in a length direction of the non-baked ceramic chip CC using a method such as dipping method and then dried it to form non-baked outer electrodes EE.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Next, the non-baked ceramic chip CC after the non-baked outer electrodes EE have been formed is baked at a condition of forming a region where the non-flat portions BP at both the sides in the width direction of each of the non-baked inner electrode layers EL<b>1</b> and EL<b>2</b> are substantially changed into oxide regions, specifically, at an atmosphere having an oxygen partial pressure corresponding to the oxidation equilibrium oxygen partial pressure of a metal contained in the non-baked inner electrodes EL<b>1</b> and EL<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">For example, when the metal contained in the non-baked inner electrode layers EL<b>1</b>, EL<b>2</b> and the non-baked outer electrodes EE is Ni, a reducing atmosphere having an oxygen partial pressure (=10<sup>−8 </sup>atm ≅10<sup>−3 </sup>Pa) corresponding to the equilibrium oxygen partial pressure of Ni—NiO is employed and baking is carried out in the atmosphere at about 1,200° C.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">While the non-flat portions BP can be sufficiently changed into oxidized regions according to a baking process as above, a reoxidation may be performed after a baking step at an atmosphere (including air) having higher oxygen partial pressure than that in the baking atmosphere, thereby the non-flat portions BP can be accurately changed into the oxidized regions. Moreover, the non-flat portions BP can be acceleratingly changed into the oxidized regions by controlling heating rate or cooling rate in the baking step, or increasing oxygen partial pressure during cooling.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">According to the manufacturing method, the multilayer ceramic capacitor <b>10</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 3</figref> can be manufactured preferably and accurately.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">While the capacitor in which the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>are provided at both the sides in the width direction of all the inner electrode layers <b>13</b>, in the case that the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>are provided at both the sides in the width direction of part of the inner electrode layers <b>13</b>, for example, in the case that the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>are not present at both the sides in the width direction of several sheets of the inner electrode layers <b>13</b> of the plurality of inner electrode layers <b>13</b>, presence of the non-flat portions <b>13</b><i>b </i>including the regions substantially changed into the oxide regions provides the operations similar to those in the above, so that occurrence of cracks can be prevented. In some embodiments, the non-flat portions are not present at both the sides in the width direction of one or more of the inner electrode layers.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">While the above detailed description has shown, described, and pointed out novel features of the invention as applied to various embodiments, it will be understood that various omissions, substitutions, and changes in the form and details of the device or process illustrated may be made by those skilled in the technology without departing from the spirit of the invention. The scope of the invention is indicated by the appended claims rather than by the foregoing description. All changes which come within the meaning and range of equivalency of the claims are to be embraced within their scope.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A multilayer ceramic capacitor comprising:
<claim-text>a ceramic chip in a shape of a rectangular prism, the ceramic chip comprising a plurality of inner electrode layers stacked via ceramic portions,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein one or more of the plurality of inner electrode layers comprise flat portions in centers in a width direction and non-flat portions at both sides in the width direction, and wherein the non-flat portions comprise substantially oxidized regions.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The multilayer ceramic capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the lateral size of each of the non-flat portions is within a range of about 0.1% to 10% of the total lateral size of the respective inner electrode layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The multilayer ceramic capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the lateral size of each of the non-flat portions is within a range of about 1% to 5% of the total lateral size of the respective inner electrode layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The multilayer ceramic capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a space between each of the non-flat portions and a side face of the ceramic chip facing the side edge of the non-flat portion is within a range of approximately 1% to 20% of lateral size of the ceramic chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The multilayer ceramic capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each non-flat portion comprises a curved or inclined portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The multilayer ceramic capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein capacitance of the multilayer ceramic capacitor depends mainly on the flat portions of the plurality of the inner electrode layers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The multilayer ceramic capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the thermal expansion coefficients of the non-flat portions is substantially lower than the flat portions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A method of manufacturing a multilayer ceramic capacitor comprising a ceramic chip in a shape of a rectangular prism, the ceramic chip comprising a plurality of inner electrode layers stacked via ceramic portions, the method comprising:
<claim-text>stacking and pressing a plurality of non-baked ceramic layers each comprising non-baked inner electrode layers such that at least one of the plurality of non-baked inner electrode layers comprise non-flat portions at both sides in a width direction; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>baking the layers in a condition such that one or more regions of each non-flat portion is substantially oxidized.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the layers are baked in a baking atmosphere of an oxygen partial pressure corresponding to the oxidation equilibrium oxygen partial pressure of a metal comprised in the non-baked inner electrode layers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising re-oxidizing the ceramic chip in an atmosphere of higher oxygen partial pressure than the baking atmosphere.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the lateral size of each of the non-flat portions is within a range of about 0.1% to 10% of the total lateral size of the respective inner electrode layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the lateral size of each of the non-flat portions is within a range of about 1% to 5% of the total lateral size of the respective inner electrode layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein a space between each of the non-flat portions and a side face of the ceramic chip facing the side edge of the non-flat portion is within a range of approximately 1% to 20% of lateral size of the ceramic chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein each non-flat portion comprises a curved or inclined portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
