<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296935-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296935</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11673152</doc-number>
<date>20070209</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>6</main-group>
<subgroup>38</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 55</main-classification>
<further-classification>385 59</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 60</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 78</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Ferrule adapter and ferrule adapter assembly</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7048447</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Patel et al.</name>
<date>20060500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 59</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 55</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 59</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 60</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 72</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 78</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 81</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Childers</last-name>
<first-name>Darrell R</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hickory</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Granger</last-name>
<first-name>Russell J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hickory</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Howard</last-name>
<first-name>Joseph P</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hickory</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yount</last-name>
<first-name>Myron W</first-name>
<address>
<city>Conover</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Leetzow, P.A.</last-name>
<first-name>Michael L.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>US Conec, Ltd.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Hickory</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Sanghavi</last-name>
<first-name>Hemang</first-name>
<department>2874</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An adapter for holding a multi-fiber ferrule in position to mate with a fiber optic connector includes an adapter body having a first side and a second side, with a first opening disposed in the first side that is configured to receive the multi-fiber ferrule. A second opening is disposed in the second side of the adapter end is configured to receive a fiber optic connector. An engagement member, which preferably rotates about an axis transverse to the opening, is disposed adjacent the first opening to engage and hold the multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="209.55mm" wi="126.07mm" file="US07296935-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="229.11mm" wi="132.84mm" file="US07296935-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="179.75mm" wi="152.57mm" file="US07296935-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="238.00mm" wi="120.90mm" file="US07296935-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="232.24mm" wi="158.83mm" file="US07296935-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="228.43mm" wi="144.95mm" file="US07296935-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="237.24mm" wi="157.31mm" file="US07296935-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="220.90mm" wi="155.70mm" file="US07296935-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to an adapter for mechanically and optically connecting a fiber optic connector and ferrule, and particularly to an adapter for mating an MT ferrule with an MTP connector in a box or panel.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Fiber optic ribbons are widely used today to transmit a large amount of data rapidly and efficiently. Systems using fiber-optic ribbons typically have multiple connection points, or interfaces, where the light signals must be transmitted from one set of optical fibers to another set of optical fibers. These connection points or interfaces usually involve two optical ferrules that are mechanically and optically aligned to allow the light to traverse the connection points. This is achieved by either spring clipping together the optical ferrules or incorporating them into push-pull connectors and mating connectors in an adapter.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The use of push-pull connectors may significantly increase the cost of the system. There are two reasons that the connectors increase the cost: the out-of-pocket expenses for the connectors and the time required to assemble the connectors. Additionally, one of the connectors is usually disposed behind a fiber-optic panel or enclosed in a box and is never removed or accessed after the initial installation. Thus, the use of a push-pull connector in these situations causes unwarranted expense and time. However, adapters that are currently available allow for only connector to connector mating or ferrule to ferrule mating.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">It would be desirable therefore to provide an adapter that is easily installed, reliable, allows for faster connection of the system, and is more cost-effective by allowing a connector to ferrule configuration.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Disclosed herein is adapter for holding a multi-fiber ferrule in position to mate with a fiber optic connector that includes an adapter body, the adapter body having a first side and a second side, a first opening disposed in the first side of the adapter body and configured to receive the multi-fiber ferrule, a second opening being disposed in the second side of the adapter body and in communication with the first opening, the second opening configured to removably receive the fiber optic connector and the first and second openings configured to position the fiber optic connector and multi-fiber ferrule to optically and mechanically engage one another, and an engagement member connected to the adapter and disposed adjacent the first opening to engage and hold the multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In some embodiments, the engagement member rotates between a first position and a second position in about an axis traverse to the openings.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In some embodiments, the adapter includes a flange disposed between the two sides and is configured to engage a fiber optic panel when the adapter is inserted through a hole in the fiber-optic panel.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In some embodiments, the adapter body has two body halves, a first body half corresponding to the first side of the adapter body and a second body half corresponding to the second side of the adapter body.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In another aspect, an adapter for removably receiving one optical fiber connector and a multi-fiber ferrule in an operative coupled relationship is disclosed, the adapter includes a first body half having a free end to removably receive the optical fiber connector and a mating end opposite thereto and defining an opening therethrough from the free end to the mating end, a second body half having a free end to receive the multi-fiber ferrule and a mating end opposite thereto, the first body half having an opening therethrough from the free end to the mating end and joined to the second body half at the mating ends so as to align the openings along a common longitudinal axis, and an engagement member connected to the second body half, the engagement member disposed adjacent the free end and the opening therein to engage and hold the multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In yet another aspect, an adapter and fiber optic assembly is disclosed that includes an optical fiber connector, the optical fiber connector having a ferrule that contains at least one optical fiber that terminates at an end face of the ferrule, a multi-fiber ferrule, the multi-fiber ferrule having at least one optical fiber that terminates at an end face of the multi-fiber ferrule, an adapter body, the adapter body having a first side and a second side, a first opening disposed in the first side of the adapter body and configured to receive the multi-fiber ferrule, a second opening being disposed in the second side of the adapter body and in communication with the first opening, the second opening configured to removably receive the fiber optic connector and the first and second openings configured to position the fiber optic connector and multi-fiber ferrule to optically and mechanically engage one another, and an engagement member connected to the adapter and disposed adjacent the first opening to engage and hold the multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Additional features and advantages of the invention will be set forth in the detailed description which follows, and in part will be readily apparent to those skilled in the art from that description or recognized by practicing the invention as described herein, including the detailed description which follows, the claims, as well as the appended drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">It is to be understood that both the foregoing general description and the following detailed description of the present embodiments of the invention, and are intended to provide an overview or framework for understanding the nature and character of the invention as it is claimed. The accompanying drawings are included to provide a further understanding of the invention, and are incorporated into and constitute a part of this specification. The drawings illustrate various embodiments of the invention, and together with the description serve to explain the principles and operations of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an exploded perspective view of an adapter according to the present invention with a multi-fiber connector and multi-fiber ferrule shown therewith;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of the assembled adapter with the multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a partial cross section view of the adapter with the engagement member in a first position;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a partial cross-section view of the adapter with the engagement member rotated to a second position;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a front view of an alternative embodiment of a portion of an adapter according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is a cross section view of the portion of the adapter in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> is a front view of an alternative embodiment of a portion of an adapter according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> is a cross section view of the portion of the adapter in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref> is a front view of an alternative embodiment of a portion of an adapter according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref> is a cross section view of the portion of the adapter in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a top view of the adapter of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with a fiber optic connector and multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter installed in a fiber optic panel or box.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Reference will now be made in detail to the present preferred embodiment(s) of the invention, examples of which are illustrated in the accompanying drawings. Whenever possible, the same reference numerals will be used throughout the drawings to refer to the same or like parts.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, adapter <b>10</b> has an adapter body <b>12</b> having two sides, which are illustrated as two body halves <b>14</b>,<b>16</b>. The first body half <b>14</b> is configured to receive the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> in an opening <b>20</b> that extends between a free end <b>22</b> and the mating end <b>24</b>. The second body half <b>16</b> also has an opening <b>26</b> is configured to receive a fiber optic connector <b>28</b>, preferably an MTP connector, but any fiber optic connector that will mate with the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> is within the scope of the present invention. The second body half <b>16</b> also has a free end <b>30</b>, into which the multi-fiber connector <b>28</b> is inserted, and a mating end <b>32</b>. The openings <b>20</b>,<b>26</b> are aligned with one another such that the end face of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> and the end face of ferrule in the fiber optic connector <b>28</b> will be in mechanical and optical alignment with each other. While the adapter body <b>12</b> is illustrated as having two halves <b>14</b>,<b>16</b>, it may be made as a single, unitary piece.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The first body half <b>14</b> has a base <b>34</b> at the mating end <b>24</b> and three walls <b>36</b>,<b>38</b>,<b>40</b> extending away from the mating end <b>24</b> and towards the free end <b>22</b> to provide protection to the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> when inserted into the opening <b>20</b>. The first body half <b>14</b> also has an open side <b>42</b> that allows easy access to the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> and opening <b>20</b>. The first body half <b>14</b> also has central pedestal <b>44</b> in which the opening <b>20</b> is formed. The central pedestal <b>44</b> is preferably attached to wall <b>38</b>, but not attached to walls <b>36</b>,<b>40</b> to allow for connection and rotation of engagement member <b>46</b>. As best seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, the engagement member <b>46</b> is rotatably attached to the central pedestal <b>44</b> and rotates about an axis A that is transverse to the longitudinal axis through the opening <b>20</b>. The engagement member <b>46</b> is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref> as a rotating latch with two prongs <b>46</b><i>a</i>,<b>46</b><i>b </i>that engage opposite sides of the rear face of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> in a first position (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>), but are also flexible enough to allow for the use of a pin clamp plate <b>48</b> with the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> if the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> is required to have guide pins <b>50</b> inserted therein. An open area <b>52</b> around the central pedestal <b>44</b> allows the engagement member <b>46</b> to rotate from the first position, engaging the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>), to a second position where the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> can be removed from the adapter <b>10</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, opening <b>20</b> is disposed in pedestal <b>44</b>, which has an upper surface <b>45</b> that is dimensioned to engage the shoulder portion of multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b>. The opening <b>20</b> is preferably slightly larger than the front portion of multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b>, which allows some lateral movement of multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> within opening <b>20</b>. However, the opening <b>20</b> is not so large as to allow significant movement of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> in the opening <b>20</b>. In fact, the opening <b>20</b> is dimensioned such that the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> will engage the guide pins <b>50</b> on the multi-fiber connector <b>28</b> (or the guide pins <b>50</b> will engage the multi-fiber connector <b>28</b>) without any further alignment. The dimensioning of the opening <b>20</b> also reduces the amount to dirt and unwanted particles that can become lodged therein and affect the mechanical and optical engagement of the multi-fiber connector <b>28</b> and the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b>. In the unmated configuration, the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> only engages the upper surface <b>45</b> of pedestal <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Optical fibers are not illustrated as being in secured in the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b>, but one of ordinary skill in the art would be able to properly secure and protect optical fibers in the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The mating ends <b>24</b>,<b>32</b> of the two body halves <b>14</b>,<b>16</b> are preferably flat so that they may be attached to one another to make up the adapter body <b>12</b>. However, the mating ends <b>24</b>,<b>32</b> may also have projections <b>54</b> and recesses <b>56</b> (corresponding to and accepting the respective projections <b>54</b> on the mating body half) to provide more strength to the adapter <b>10</b> when the two body halves <b>14</b>,<b>16</b> are joined together. The two body halves <b>14</b>,<b>16</b> may be joined in any appropriate manner, including with adhesives, by ultrasonic welding, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The outer surface of walls <b>36</b>,<b>38</b>,<b>40</b> on body half <b>14</b> preferably has a recessed portion <b>58</b> to accept and maintain a spring clip <b>60</b>. Spring clip <b>60</b> is used to engage a fiber-optic panel or box into which the adapter <b>10</b> is installed. The spring clip <b>60</b> is well-known in the art and may be of any appropriate size, configuration and type.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The second body half <b>16</b> is configured as a standard connector adapter half, and, in particular is illustrated as an adapter half that will accept an MTP® connector <b>28</b>, available from the assignee of the present application, U.S. Conec Ltd. As noted above, the connector <b>28</b> can be of any form factor or configuration and still be within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Both body halves <b>14</b>,<b>16</b> also preferably have flanges <b>80</b> adjacent the base <b>34</b> that extend outward away from openings <b>20</b>, <b>26</b> to engage a fiber-optic panel or box into which the adapter <b>10</b> is installed and prevent the adapter <b>10</b> from being pulled through the opening in the fiber-optic panel or box. Additionally, flanges <b>80</b> preferably have at least one screw-sized hole <b>82</b> therein that correspond to an appropriate opening or hole in the fiber-optic panel or box, allowing the adapter <b>10</b> to be secured to the fiber-optic panel or box with a screw, bolt, rivet, or other appropriate securing member. While the flanges <b>80</b> are illustrated on both body halves <b>14</b>,<b>16</b>, either body half may or may not have the flanges <b>80</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">An alternative embodiment according to the present invention is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref>. In this embodiment only the first body half <b>114</b> is illustrated and it is to be understood that the second body half would be the same as described above. First body half <b>114</b> is configured to receive the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> in an opening <b>120</b> that extends between a free end <b>122</b> and the mating end <b>124</b>. The opening <b>120</b> would be aligned with the other opening in the second body half so that the end face of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> and the end face of ferrule in the fiber optic connector <b>28</b> will be in mechanical and optical alignment with each other. Again, first body half <b>114</b> may be made as a single, unitary piece with the second body half.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The first body half <b>114</b> has a base <b>134</b> at the mating end <b>124</b> and three walls <b>136</b>,<b>138</b>,<b>140</b> extending away from the mating end <b>124</b> and towards the free end <b>122</b> to provide protection to the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> when inserted into the opening <b>120</b>. The first body half <b>114</b> also has an open side <b>142</b> that allows easy access to the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> and opening <b>120</b>. The opening <b>120</b> has a chamfered portion <b>126</b> to allow the ferrule <b>18</b> to be inserted as described in more detail below. The first body half <b>114</b> also has central portion <b>144</b> in which the opening <b>120</b> is formed. The central portion <b>144</b> is preferably attached to all three walls <b>136</b>,<b>138</b>,<b>140</b> because engagement member <b>146</b> is embedded into the first body half <b>114</b>. As best seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>, the engagement member <b>146</b> is preferably a fixed spring latch that includes two elastic members that extend upward and out of the central portion <b>144</b> between the opening <b>120</b> and the wall <b>138</b> and forcibly pushes downward on the rear face of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> (preferably with a force of about 2 lbs.) to keep multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> in the first body half <b>114</b>. The engagement member <b>146</b> is flexed toward wall <b>138</b> to allow access to the opening <b>120</b> and multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> is inserted into opening <b>120</b>. The engagement member <b>146</b> may prevent the upright insertion of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b>, so the chamfered portion <b>126</b> may be needed to allow the insertion of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> at an angle to prevent damage to the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> or first body half <b>114</b>. The engagement member <b>146</b> is also flexible enough to allow for the use of a pin clamp plate with the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> if the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> is required to have guide pins as discussed above. The first body half <b>114</b> may also have two projections <b>154</b> and two recesses (not shown) as discussed above.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Another embodiment of the present invention is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref>. The first body half <b>114</b>′ is similar to the one in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref>, with a different engagement member <b>146</b>′. Engagement member <b>146</b>′ is preferably a one piece (although it could be any number of pieces) fixed spring latch that is disposed on at least two sides of opening <b>120</b> and is at least partially embedded into the central portion <b>144</b>′ of the first body half <b>114</b>′. Engagement member <b>146</b>′ has a first spring portion <b>148</b>′ on a first side of opening <b>120</b> that extends upward from the central portion <b>144</b>′ and towards opening <b>120</b> and then continues to extend upward but away from opening <b>120</b>. Engagement member <b>146</b>′ has a second spring portion <b>150</b>′ on an opposite side of opening <b>120</b> that extends upward from the central portion <b>144</b>′ and towards opening <b>120</b> and first spring portion <b>148</b>′ and then continues to extend upward but away from opening <b>120</b>. As illustrated best in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, the spring two portions <b>148</b>′ and <b>150</b>′ of the engagement member <b>146</b>′ provide a funnel-like opening therein to receive the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> and, because of the elastic characteristics of the spring portions <b>148</b>′,<b>150</b>′ of engagement member <b>146</b>′, will move away from one another to allow the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> to be inserted into opening <b>120</b>. Once the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> is inserted completely into opening <b>120</b>, the two spring portions <b>148</b>′ and <b>150</b>′ of the engagement member <b>146</b>′ will return to engage a rear portion of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> to keep multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> in the first body half <b>114</b>′. While the engagement member <b>146</b>′ is illustrated along the two long sides of the opening <b>120</b>, it could be oriented such that it is oriented along the short sides and still fall within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Another embodiment according to the present invention is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A and 7B</figref>. In this embodiment, the first body half <b>114</b>″ has an engagement member <b>146</b>″ that is a fixed, nonflexible member. The engagement member <b>146</b>″ is preferably made from a plastic material with prongs that engage openings in central portion <b>144</b>″ and engages the rear face of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> along at least two sides and more preferably along three sides. The engagement member <b>146</b>″ engages the rear face of multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> with shoulders <b>148</b>″ and has an opening <b>150</b>″ that allows the optical fibers (not shown) to exit the rear of the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b>. Engagement member <b>146</b>″ rigidly holds multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> in the opening <b>120</b>″ and does not allow the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> to float relative to the first body half <b>114</b>″ as in the prior embodiments. Therefore, it is imperative that the connector or ferrule that mates with the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> in this embodiment have a spring in order to mate with each other correctly.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates adapter <b>10</b> having a connector <b>28</b> installed on the second side and a multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> installed on the first side. The adapter <b>10</b> is installed into a fiber-optic panel or box <b>100</b>. As is known in the art, the spring clip <b>60</b> engages the inside or rear portion <b>102</b> of the fiber-optic panel or box <b>100</b>, preventing it from being pulled out of the fiber-optic panel or box <b>100</b>. Since the first body half <b>14</b> of adapter <b>10</b> is behind the fiber-optic panel or box <b>100</b> and not readily accessible to the user or tradesman, there is no need for the protective components of the connector <b>28</b> and only a ferrule is need to optically and mechanically connect the multi-fiber ferrule <b>18</b> to the connector <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Similar engagement members for a different adapter are disclosed in a co-pending application Ser. No. 11/673,191, entitled “Ferrule-to-Ferrule Adapter And Ferrule Adapter Assembly”, filed on the same date, the contents of which are expressly incorporated in their entirety by reference herein.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">It will be apparent to those skilled in the art that various modifications and variations can be made to the present invention without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. Thus it is intended that the present invention cover the modifications and variations of this invention provided they come within the scope of the appended claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An adapter for holding a multi-fiber ferrule in position to mate with a fiber optic connector comprising:
<claim-text>an adapter body, the adapter body having a first side and a second side;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first opening disposed in the first side of the adapter body and configured to receive the multi-fiber ferrule;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second opening being disposed in the second side of the adapter body and in communication with the first opening, the second opening configured to removably receive the fiber optic connector and the first and second openings configured to position the fiber optic connector and multi-fiber ferrule to optically and mechanically engage one another; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an engagement member connected to the adapter and disposed adjacent the first opening to engage and hold the multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the engagement member rotates between a first position and a second position and about an axis transverse to the openings, the engagement member engaging the multi-fiber ferrule in the first position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the adapter body only engages a front portion of the multi-fiber ferrule disposed therein.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a flange disposed between the first and second sides, the flange configured to engage a fiber optic panel when the first side of the adapter is inserted through a hole in the fiber optic panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising at least one screw-sized hole disposed in the flange to correspond to at least one screw-sized hole in the fiber optic panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a spring clip disposed on an outside surface of the adapter body to engage a fiber optic panel, thereby retaining the adapter in the fiber optic panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the engagement member is a fixed spring latch.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the fixed spring latch is at least partially embedded in the main body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the fixed spring latch is disposed on two sides of the opening on the first side of the main body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the engagement member is configured to accommodate a pin clamp plate associated with the multi-fiber ferrule.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the adapter body has a two body halves, a first body half corresponding to the first side of the adapter body and a second body half corresponding to the second side of the adapter body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An adapter for removably receiving one optical fiber connector and a multi-fiber ferrule in an operative coupled relationship, the adapter comprising:
<claim-text>a first body half having a free end to removably receive the optical fiber connector and a mating end opposite thereto and defining an opening therethrough from the free end to the mating end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second body half having a free end to receive the multi-fiber ferrule and a mating end opposite thereto, the first body half having an opening therethrough from the free end to the mating end and joined to the second body half at the mating ends so as to align the openings along a common longitudinal axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an engagement member connected to the second body half, the engagement member disposed adjacent the free end and the opening therein to engage and hold the multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the engagement member rotates between a first position and a second position and about an axis transverse to the openings, the engagement member engaging the multi-fiber ferrule in the first position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the adapter body only engages a front portion of the multi-fiber ferrule disposed therein.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising a flange disposed between the first and second sides, the flange configured to engage a fiber optic panel when the first side of the adapter is inserted through a hole in the fiber optic panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further comprising at least one screw-sized hole disposed in the flange to correspond to at least one screw-sized hole in the fiber optic panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising a spring clip disposed on an outside surface of the adapter body to engage a fiber optic panel, thereby retaining the adapter in the fiber optic panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the engagement member is a fixed spring latch.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The adapter according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the engagement member is configured to accommodate a pin clamp plate associated with the multi-fiber ferrule.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. An adapter and fiber optic assembly, comprising:
<claim-text>an optical fiber connector, the optical fiber connector having a ferrule that contains at least one optical fiber that terminates at an end face of the ferrule;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a multi-fiber ferrule, the multi-fiber ferrule having at least one optical fiber that terminates at an end face of the multi-fiber ferrule;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adapter body, the adapter body having a first side and a second side;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first opening disposed in the first side of the adapter body and configured to receive the multi-fiber ferrule;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second opening being disposed in the second side of the adapter body and in communication with the first opening, the second opening configured to removably receive the fiber optic connector and the first and second openings configured to position the fiber optic connector and multi-fiber ferrule to optically and mechanically engage one another; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an engagement member connected to the adapter and disposed adjacent the first opening to engage and hold the multi-fiber ferrule in the adapter.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
