<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298080-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298080</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10929602</doc-number>
<date>20040831</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-354490</doc-number>
<date>20031015</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>494</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>63</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>62</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313495</main-classification>
<further-classification>313496</further-classification>
<further-classification>313497</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Display device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5477105</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Curtin et al.</name>
<date>19951200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313422</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5650690</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Haven</name>
<date>19970700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313422</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6653777</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Onishi</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313495</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0013113</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Onishi et al.</name>
<date>20020100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>445  6</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>07-282743</doc-number>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-101965</doc-number>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313495-497</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313293-304</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313309</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313310</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313336</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313346 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050093421</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050505</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kodera</last-name>
<first-name>Yoshie</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chigasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sagawa</last-name>
<first-name>Masakazu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Inagi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kusunoki</last-name>
<first-name>Toshiaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokorozawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ohishi</last-name>
<first-name>Tetsu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hiratsuka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sawai</last-name>
<first-name>Yuichi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hitachi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Antonelli, Terry, Stout &amp; Kraus, LLP.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hitachi, Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Santiago</last-name>
<first-name>Mariceli</first-name>
<department>2879</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Hines</last-name>
<first-name>Anne M</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A flat type display device is provided which is capable of accurately and easily assembling a spacer when arranging the spacer while reducing the danger of damaging the metal back. In the display device, a plurality of fine holes each having a fluorescent materials are formed on a light transparency substrate and a metal sheet is arranged by a black oxide film formed on the surface of the light transparency substrate side so as to obtain a light absorbing layer. A plurality of concave portions are provided on a surface of the metal sheet of the rear substrate side. A metal back having an openings corresponding to predetermined areas containing each of the concave portions is superimposed on the metal sheet, thereby constituting an acceleration electrode of two-layer structure. The spacer is inserted into the concave portion on the metal sheet exposed in the opening of the metal back.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="112.86mm" wi="156.38mm" file="US07298080-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="218.69mm" wi="158.83mm" file="US07298080-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="223.10mm" wi="176.87mm" file="US07298080-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="274.57mm" wi="183.73mm" file="US07298080-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="204.89mm" wi="173.14mm" file="US07298080-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="142.58mm" wi="157.31mm" file="US07298080-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="165.18mm" wi="173.82mm" file="US07298080-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">INCORPORATION BY REFERENCE</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority from Japanese application JP2003-354490 filed on Oct. 15, 2003, the content of which is hereby incorporated by reference into this application.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to a display device such as a field emission display (hereinafter, referred to as FED) containing in an air tight vessel an electronic source formed of electronic emission elements arranged in a matrix.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The FED constitutes an air tight vessel by opposing a rear panel where electronic emission elements are arranged in a matrix and a display panel including a light transparent substrate having fluorescent materials of three primary colors (R, G, B) which emit light by collision of electrons from the electron emission elements. Since inside the air tight vessel, a vacuum atmosphere is present, in order that the vacuum vessel is not destroyed by the pressure difference between the inside and the outside, a plurality of support members (hereinafter, referred to as spacers) are arranged between the display panel and the rear panel. On the other hand, a conductive thin film called metal back is formed on the rear panel side of the fluorescent materials formed on the light transparent substrate to which acceleration voltage (anode voltage) for accelerating the electrons from the electron emission elements is applied. Such an FED configuration is disclosed, for example, in JP-A-2001-101965 (document 1), FIG. 21.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In the afore-mentioned FED configuration, when arranging the spacers, the metal back may be peeled off by the interference (physical contact) between the spacers and the metal back. The conventional technique for preventing this is disclosed, for example, in JP-A-7-282743 (document 2), FIG. 4, FIG. 6 and FIG. 7. According to this disclosure, on the areas where spacers are to be arranged, metal back is removed to expose the black stripes (black light absorbing layer) arranged between the fluorescent materials, so that the spacers are fixed on the black stripes.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The metal back which has been peeled off by the interference between the spacers and the metal back (spacer positioning shift and spacer deformation) is scattered to the electron emission elements, wiring circuit and the like and there is a danger of short-circuiting them. The afore-mentioned document 2 discloses a technique that the spacers are not in direct contact with the metal back, thereby preventing the short-circuiting due to the interference between the spacers and the metal back.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">When the spacers are charged, an orbit of electrons from the electron emission element is changed and the electron does not collide into the fluorescent material preferably. Accordingly, it is necessary to prevent or reduce charging of spacers by electrically contacting the spacers with the metal back. In the document 1, the light absorbing layer where the spacers are fixed is made from an insulative material such as graphite or black color glass (see the document 1, paragraph 0030). For this, in order to prevent charging of the spacers, the spacers are electrically connected to the metal back with a conductive layer or a conductive flit glass, thereby assuring electric conductivity between them.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">That is, the document 2 discloses a technique to prevent interference between the spacers and metal back but in addition to the step of fixing the spacers onto the light absorbing layer, a new step of connecting spacers to the metal back is required. That is, two independent steps are required: a step of fixing spacers to the light absorbing layer and the step of electrically connecting the spacers to the metal back, thereby complicating the manufacturing procedure.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Moreover, it is difficult to accurately arrange in the light absorbing layer area of about 100 μm wide. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows an example of arrangement (partial) of fluorescent materials in a flat-type display device having a 30-inch display range, 1280×720 pixels (one pixels consists of a set of R, G, B pixels), and aspect ratio 16:9. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the fluorescent materials <b>111</b>R, <b>111</b>G, <b>111</b>B are arranged at 0.173 mm pitch in Y direction so as to sandwich the black stripes <b>150</b><i>a </i>which are the black light absorbing layers of width of 0.05 mm. Moreover, the fluorescent materials <b>111</b>R, <b>111</b>G, and <b>111</b>B are separated in X direction by black stripes <b>150</b><i>b </i>which are black light absorbing layers of about 0.1 mm wide. In order to prevent spacers from affecting the image, the spacers should be positioned in the light absorbing layers and should be 100 μm or below of the width of the black stripes <b>150</b><i>b</i>. Furthermore, considering the spacer attachment error and spacer thickness direction manufacturing error, the spacer thickness should be substantially 90 μm. It is difficult to arrange and position a flat spacer having a thickness of about 90 μm or below along the area of the narrow light absorbing layer having a width of about 100 μm, when clearance in the thickness direction is considered. Additionally, there is a danger that the spacer side wall may scratch the metal back.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Accordingly, in the FED, when arranging spacers on the display panel, it is necessary to prevent charging of the spacers, assemble the spacers accurately in one step, and reduce the danger of damaging the metal back. When this is achieved, it is possible to improve the reliability of the flat-type display device such as the FED. Furthermore, this can improve the productivity of the display device.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">It is therefore an object of this invention to provide a display device having an improved reliability.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In order to achieve the afore-mentioned object, the display device according to this invention includes a conductive sheet (hereinafter, referred to a metal sheet) having a plurality of holding holes (hereinafter, referred to as fine holes) formed in a matrix for containing and holding a plurality of fluorescent materials on a surface of the light transparent substrate of the rear panel side and a metal back arranged on the surface of the metal sheet of the rear panel side so as to be brought into electrical contact with the conductive sheet. An opening is formed at an area opposing to an area between fine holes of the conductive sheet and a spacer is attached to the metal sheet exposed from this opening.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">With the configuration, the spacer is attached to the metal sheet in the opening where the metal back is removed. Thus, the spacer can be attached without interfering (direct contact) with the metal back and it is possible to prevent peeling off of the metal back. Furthermore, the spacer is attached to the metal sheet which is electrical contact with the metal back and it is possible to apply a small current from the metal back via the metal sheet to the spacer. Accordingly, without electrically connecting the spacer to the metal back (without performing a new work for this), it is possible to prevent charging of the spacer.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Moreover, in an aspect of this invention, a concave portion is provided in the metal sheet for inserting the spacer and the spacer is inserted into the concave portion exposed from the opening of the metal back. Thus, while preventing the interference with the metal back, it is possible to accurately and easily assemble the spacer with one connection by using the concave portion, thereby improving the productivity.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Moreover, according to this invention, the surface of the metal sheet of the light transparent substrate side is made substantially black to form a light absorbing layer. In this invention, the spacer is arranged between the fine holes of the metal sheet, i.e., on the area of the light absorbing layer. Accordingly, the spacer does not affect the image.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Other objects, features and advantages of the invention will become apparent from the following description of the embodiments of the invention taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a brief configuration of a flat-type display device according to a first embodiment of this invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top view of the metal sheet viewed from the rear panel side.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a top view of the metal back according to the first embodiment viewed from the rear panel side.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the metal back according to a second embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref> show metal backs according to a third, fourth and fifth embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> show metal backs according to a sixth and seventh embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows equilibrium oxygen partial pressure when Fe, Ni, and their oxides maintain the state of equilibrium in a closed system.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows an example of arrangement of fluorescent materials in a flat-type display device.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Description will now be directed to a flat-type display device according to the embodiments of this invention with reference to the attached drawings. The flat-type display device according to this invention includes: a rear panel (first panel) where a plurality of cold cathode elements are arranged as electron emission elements; a display panel (second panel) having a light transparent substrate arranged to oppose to the rear panel; and spacers for supporting the rear panel and the display panel. Furthermore, the display device according to this invention includes: a conductive sheet on which a plurality of holding holes are formed in a matrix shape for holding a plurality of fluorescent materials corresponding to the plurality of cold cathode elements; and a metal back arranged on the rear panel side of the conductive sheet (metal sheet) in such a manner that it is in electric contact with the metal sheet, to which metal back acceleration electrode is applied for accelerating the electrons emitted from the cold cathode elements. Openings are formed on the metal back at the area opposing to the area between the plurality of holding holes in the metal sheet, so that the spacers are brought into abutment with the conductive sheet exposed from the openings of the metal back. Thus, it is possible to support the display panel and the rear panel by the spacers while preventing interference with the metal back. The flat-type display device according to this invention is characterized by the afore-mentioned configuration. Moreover, this invention is characterized in that concave portions are formed at predetermined positions between the plurality of fine holes for holding the spacers and the spacers are inserted into the concave portions so as to support the rear panel and the display panel. Hereinafter, the characteristic will be detailed.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Firstly, explanation will be given on a first embodiment. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a brief configuration of the float-type display device according to the first embodiment of this invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a display panel <b>101</b> includes: a light transparent substrate <b>110</b> such as glass transmitting light; a thin metal sheet <b>120</b> having a plenty of fine holes <b>122</b> arranged in a matrix shape (two-dimensional state); a fixation layer <b>112</b> having a low melting point for fixing the metal sheet <b>120</b> onto the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>; fluorescent material <b>111</b> applied inside the fine holes <b>122</b> of the metal sheet <b>120</b>; and a metal back <b>130</b> made of metal (such as aluminum (Al)) formed on the metal sheet <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The metal sheet <b>120</b> is configured similarly as the shadow mask used in the Braun tube (CRT). That is, the metal sheet <b>120</b> has a plenty of fine holes <b>120</b> formed in a matrix shape and the fluorescent material <b>111</b> is painted to each of the fine holes <b>122</b>. That is, the fine holes <b>122</b> are used as holes for holding the fluorescent material <b>111</b>. Moreover, the metal sheet <b>120</b> has a surface of the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> side as a light absorbing layer <b>121</b> of substantially black color preventing reflection of the outer light and preventing lowering of contrast. Furthermore, the metal sheet <b>120</b> has the other surface of the rear panel <b>1</b> side where concave portions <b>123</b> are formed at predetermined positions between the plurality of fine holes <b>122</b>. The concave portions <b>123</b> are indentations or grooves for inserting spacers <b>30</b>. As has been described above, the spacers <b>30</b> are arranged vertically between the rear panel <b>1</b> and the display panel <b>101</b> and support the rear panel <b>1</b> and the display panel <b>101</b> so as to support the interval between them. The spacers <b>30</b> are inserted into the concave portions <b>123</b>, for example, via flit glass (not depicted) and fixed there.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">To the metal back <b>130</b>, acceleration voltage (anode voltage) is applied for accelerating electrons from the cold cathode elements toward the fluorescent material <b>111</b>. The metal back is formed at the rear panel <b>1</b> side of the metal sheet <b>120</b> excluding the concave portions <b>123</b> where the spacers <b>30</b> are inserted and a predetermined area in the vicinity of the spacers. That is, the metal back <b>130</b> has a plurality of openings <b>131</b> including concave portions <b>123</b> in the openings. Explanation will be given on why the concave portions where the spacers <b>30</b> are inserted and a predetermined area in the vicinity of the spacers are made as openings <b>131</b> and metal back is not provided. In case metal back is formed on the concave portion <b>123</b>, when inserting the spacers <b>30</b> into the concave portion <b>123</b>, the spacers <b>30</b> and the metal back interfere each other and the spacers <b>30</b> scratches the metal back. Then, the metal back is peeled off and its fine powder is scattered, which may short-circuit the electron emission element on the rear panel <b>1</b>. In order to prevent this, no metal back is provided at predetermined area including the concave portion <b>123</b> where the spacer <b>30</b> is arranged. Moreover, the metal back <b>30</b> is electrically connected to the metal sheet <b>120</b> and the spacer <b>30</b> is electrically connected to the metal back <b>130</b> via the metal sheet <b>1120</b>. Furthermore, the metal back <b>130</b> has the function to protect the fluorescent material from deterioration by electron beam irradiation, the function to reflect the light directed toward the rear panel <b>1</b> side among the light emission of the fluorescent material against the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>, thereby improving light emission luminance, and the function to conduct charge of the fluorescent material and prevent charging of the fluorescent material.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The method for forming the metal back is detailed, for example, in JP-A-5-36355. Here, only brief explanation will be given on this. Firstly, on the fluorescent material <b>111</b>, for example, a filming film of organic film is formed by the emulsion method or lacquer method. On the filming film, aluminum is vapor-deposited about 80 to 100 nm thick. After this, baking is performed at 450 degrees C. or above so as to decompose and remove the filming film of the organic film.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The rear panel <b>1</b> includes, for example, an insulative substrate <b>10</b> composed of glass and an electron emission element formation layer <b>19</b> of the cold cathode having a plenty of electron emission elements formed as an electron source on the insulative substrate <b>10</b>. The electron emission element used is, for example, a so-called MIM type in which an insulator is sandwiched between an upper electrode and a lower electrode. Scan (selection) voltage is applied to the lower electrode constituting the electron emission element while a drive signal from a drive signal generation circuit (not depicted) is applied to the upper electrode. The drive signal is generated by processing a video signal input to tan input section (not depicted) and the level is changed according to the intensity of the video signal. When the scan is applied to the lower electrode and the drive voltage is applied to the upper electrode, an electron appears according to the potential difference. The electron is pulled by the acceleration electrode applied to the metal back <b>130</b> and collides into the fluorescent material <b>111</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In the flat-type display device, the display panel <b>101</b> and the rear panel <b>1</b> are supported by the spacers <b>30</b> and the periphery of the display panel <b>101</b> and the rear panel <b>1</b> is air-tightly attached by using flit glass <b>115</b>. The pressure inside is about 10<sup>−5 </sup>to 10<sup>−7 </sup>torr.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As has been described above, the metal sheet <b>120</b> is configured in the same way as the shadow mask used as a color selection mask for irradiating an electron beam to a predetermined fluorescent material in the cathode ray tube (CRT) for a color television. Firstly, in an extremely low carbon steel thin plate of an Fe—Ni-based alloy, a plenty of fine hold <b>122</b> are formed in a matrix shape by etching. At temperature of 450 to 470 degrees C. which is equal to or lower than the steel re-crystallization temperature, thermal treatment is performed in a oxidization atmosphere for 10 to 20 minutes so that the surface becomes black. Thus, when producing the metal sheet, the conventional facility for producing the shadow mask can be used as it is.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The thickness of the metal sheet <b>120</b> is about 20 to 250 μm. The lower limit of the thickness is decided as this because almost no commercial demand is present for a steel plate having a thickness lower than this and as will be detailed later, the layer of the fluorescent material <b>111</b> is about 10 to 20 μm, which should be exceeded. Moreover, the extremely low carbon steel thin plate of Fe—Ni-based alloy is expensive and the upper limit is preferably 250 μm because little commercial demand is present for the thickness exceeding this.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The fluorescent material <b>111</b> in the fine holes <b>122</b> is excited by the electronic beam from the electron emission elements on the rear panel <b>1</b> and the secondary electron generated from the fluorescent material may leak into the adjacent fine hole <b>122</b> to excite the fluorescent material there and emit light. In order to prevent this, in this embodiment, the height of the fine hole <b>122</b>, that is, the thickness of the metal sheet is greater than the thickness of the fluorescent material. Thus, the secondary electron generated is absorbed by the inner wall of the fine hole <b>122</b> (the black oxide film of the inner wall is removed and the inner wall conducts electricity, which will be detailed later) and the metal back <b>130</b> and not leak into the adjacent fine hole <b>122</b>. Accordingly, it is possible to reduce the charge of the fluorescent material.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Since the surface of the metal sheet <b>120</b> is subjected to blackening processing and black oxide film is formed on the surface, the surface of the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> side can be used as the light absorbing layer <b>121</b>. On the other hand, since the inner surface of the fine hole <b>122</b> and the black oxide film of surface of the rear panel <b>1</b> side remove electric charge from the fluorescent material and gives conductivity with the metal back, they are removed, for example by the sand blast. Thus, the inner surface of the fine hole <b>122</b> and the surface of the rear panel <b>1</b> side conduct electricity.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Accordingly, the metal sheet <b>120</b> is electrically connected with the metal back <b>130</b> formed on it and the acceleration voltage applied to the metal back is also applied inevitably to the metal sheet <b>120</b>. That is, the acceleration electrode (not depicted) for accelerating electrons emitted from the rear panel <b>1</b> has the two-layer structure consisting of the metal sheet <b>120</b> and the metal back <b>130</b> arranged on it.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">On the other hand, the spacers <b>30</b> are emitted by the electrons from the electron emission elements and in the vicinity of the spacers <b>30</b>, the orbit of electrons emitted from the rear panel <b>1</b> is curved and there arises a phenomenon that the image is distorted. In order to prevent this, as is disclosed in JP-A-57-118355 and JP-A-61-124031, it is necessary to apply small current to the spacer surface by providing on the spacer surface a film of tin oxide having a high resistance, or mixed thin film of tin oxide and indium oxide, or a conductive film of a metal film.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In this invention, the spacers are arranged in the concave portions <b>123</b> where no metal back of the metal sheet <b>120</b> is formed but the afore-mentioned acceleration voltage is applied to the metal sheet <b>120</b>. Accordingly, it is possible to apply a small current from the metal back <b>130</b> to the spacers <b>30</b> via the metal sheet <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The metal sheet <b>120</b> thus processed is fixed to the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> by a fixing layer <b>112</b> of a low melting point (500 degrees C. or below). The fixing member of the fixing layer <b>112</b> is, for example, flit glass which is a glass having a low melting point. The flit glass is applied to the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>, to which the metal sheet <b>120</b> is attached. This is subjected to thermal treatment with 450 to 470 degrees for sintering. The fixing member may also be polycylazan which is liquid glass precursor. By using this, sintering and fixing may be made with a temperature of more than 120° C.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">It should be noted that the optical characteristic of the fixing layer is not limited to the light transparency of about 100%. For example, in the CRT, a glass whose transparency is limited to a predetermined value is conventionally used as the front panel material so as to improve the contrast. Accordingly, in this invention also, even though the light transparent substrate is transparent (light transparency is almost 100%), the fixing layer can be formed by a glass layer whose light transparency is limited to a predetermined value, so as to obtain the effect of contrast improvement like in the CRT. The glass whose transparency is limited can easily be manufactured in the same way as the one used in the CRT conventionally.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The metal sheet <b>120</b> is fixed to the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> via the fixing layer <b>112</b>. For this, in order to reduce the thermal distortion caused by difference in thermal expansion between the metal sheet <b>120</b> and the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>, the metal sheet <b>1120</b> preferably has the same coefficient of thermal expansion as the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>. When glass is used as the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>, the coefficient of thermal expansion of the glass is about 38 to 90×10<sup>−7</sup>/degrees C. (30-300 degrees C.). The coefficient of thermal expansion of the metal sheet <b>120</b> made of an Fe—Ni-based alloy can be made the same by changing the content of nickel (Ni). For example, when the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> is made of boron-silicated glass having a coefficient of thermal expansion 48×10<sup>−7</sup>/degrees C. and the metal sheet <b>120</b> is made of an Fe-42% Ni alloy, for example, their thermal expansions may be made substantially same.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">From the same point of view, the fixing layer <b>112</b> also preferably has the same coefficient of thermal expansion as the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>. For this, the fixing member is made of, for example, flit glass having the same coefficient of the thermal expansion as the light transparent substrate made of the glass material.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">It should be noted that it is preferable that the metal sheet <b>120</b> have the same coefficient of thermal expansion as the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> so as to reduce the thermal distortion but the light transparent substrate made of glass and the fixing layer have weak tensile stress. For this, the coefficient of thermal expansion of the metal sheet <b>120</b> may be slightly greater than that of the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> and the fixing layer <b>112</b>, so that compressive stress is applied to the light transparent substrate and the fixing layer when actually used.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Here, according to the afore-mentioned embodiment, the metal sheet <b>120</b> has a plenty of fine holes, a surface is subjected blackening processing, and it is fixed to the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> by the after-fixing layer. However, the invention is not limited to this process. For example, the metal sheet may be subjected in an oxidization atmosphere and the surface is subjected to blackening processing in advance. The metal sheet is fixed to the light transparent substrate by the fixing layer, after which a plenty of fine holes are formed by etching. By this process, the same function as the afore-mentioned embodiment can be obtained and since fines holes are absent when fixing the metal sheet <b>120</b> to the light transparent substrate, handling becomes easy and fixation efficiency is improved.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">After the metal sheet <b>120</b> is fixed to the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> by the fixing layer <b>112</b> which is a glass layer, fluorescent materials <b>111</b>R, <b>111</b>G and <b>111</b>B of red color (R), green color (G) and blue color (B) are pained in the fine holes <b>122</b> by about 10 to 20 μm. Filming is performed on it. After this, the metal back <b>130</b> is used by using a metal mask by performing vacuum deposition of aluminum by 30-200 nm. The metal back <b>130</b> should sufficiently pass electrons from the electron emission elements so that electrons collide into the fluorescent material <b>111</b>. From this view-point, the metal back has a thickness set within the afore-mentioned range and preferably substantially 100 nm.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Moreover, as has been described above, from the inside of the fine holes <b>122</b> of the metal sheet <b>120</b> and the rear panel side of the metal sheet <b>120</b>, the insulative black oxide film is removed by sand blast, for example. For this, electric charge charged to the fluorescent material <b>111</b> and secondary electrons generated in the fluorescent material move to the metal sheet <b>120</b> and the metal back <b>114</b>, thereby preventing charging of the fluorescent material.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Furthermore, the metal sheet <b>120</b> has a thickness of 20 μm or above which is greater than the thickness of the fluorescent material <b>111</b> and fine jaggy is formed on the inner surface of the fine holes <b>122</b> by the sand blast. For this, when painting the fluorescent material <b>111</b>, the fine jaggy provides a preferable wettability and when viewed from the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> side, the fluorescent material <b>111</b> has a substantially U-shaped form (the bottom is about 100 μm and the side is about 20 μm). Accordingly, the metal back <b>130</b> can be preferably formed in the fine holes <b>122</b> also, and it is not peeled off easily, i.e., the adhesiveness is improved.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top view of the metal sheet viewed from the rear panel side. Here, for easiness of viewing, the screen consists of 4 lines×5 pixels (each pixel consists of three color pixels: R light, G light, B light) and four concave portions <b>123</b> for spacers are depicted. Actually, however, on the entire metal sheet, a plenty of concave portions <b>123</b> are provided for arranging a plenty of spacers sufficient to resist the atmosphere.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the metal sheet <b>120</b> has a plenty of fine holes <b>122</b> arranged in a matrix (two-dimensional way). The fluorescent material pained in the fine holes <b>122</b> emits light and forms a pixel. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an example of the rectangular form of the fine holes. Since fluorescent material is pained inside the fine holes <b>122</b>, the pixel shape matches with hole shape of the fine holes <b>122</b>. However, in the same way as the Braun tube, the pixel form, i.e., the form of the fine holes <b>122</b> is not limited to this. For example, it may be a circle, ellipse or a rectangle whose four angles are rounded. In each fine hole <b>122</b>, R fluorescent material <b>111</b>R, G fluorescent material <b>111</b>G and B fluorescent material B exist and these three color pixels of fluorescent materials <b>111</b>R, <b>111</b>G, <b>111</b>B form a set of pixels performing color display. A plurality of concave portions <b>123</b> are arranged at predetermined positions between the pixels on the surface opposite to the surface where the light absorbing layer is provided.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">As is clear from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the concave portion <b>123</b> is in the range of the light absorbing layer <b>121</b> when viewed from the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>. Accordingly, when the spacer <b>30</b> is inserted and arranged into the concave portion, this will not affect the orbit of the electron beam from the rear panel <b>1</b> to the fluorescent material <b>111</b>. In this invention, the depth of the concave portion <b>123</b> is set to substantially ½ of the metal sheet, i.e., about 10 to 125 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a top view of the metal back formed on the metal sheet according to the first embodiment viewed from the rear panel side. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the metal back <b>130</b>A is arranged on the metal sheet <b>1210</b>, but the metal back is not formed in the opening <b>131</b>A surrounding a predetermined area around the concave portion <b>123</b>. In the opening <b>131</b>A, the concave portion <b>123</b> and the metal sheet <b>120</b> are exposed. That is, the acceleration electrode according to this embodiment has a two-layered structure consisting of the metal sheet <b>120</b> having the concave portion <b>123</b> and the metal back <b>130</b>A having the opening <b>131</b>A and formed thereon. Assembling is facilitated by inserting the spacer <b>30</b> into the concave portion <b>123</b> in the opening <b>131</b>A. That is, since the spacer <b>30</b> is inserted into the concave portion <b>123</b>, very small current can be applied to the spacer <b>30</b> and prevent changing of the spacer. Moreover, the spacer positioning is easy and the spacer can easily be arranged with a high arrangement accuracy. The arrangement accuracy of the spacer is determined by the formation accuracy of the concave portion <b>123</b>. The concave portion is formed by etching in the same way as the fine holes. Accordingly, the concave portion can be formed with a high accuracy and the spacer <b>30</b> can be arranged at a predetermined position with a high accuracy with respect to the display panel <b>101</b>. In this invention, the concave portion is not directly connected to the metal back <b>130</b>A but indirectly, i.e., electrically connected. Unlike the above mentioned document, the connection of the spacer <b>30</b> to the display panel can be performed at once. It is noted that the shape of the concave portion <b>123</b> is similar to the end surface shape of the spacer <b>30</b> inserted.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the prolonged rectangular concave portion <b>123</b> are arranged in the horizontal direction of the drawing sheet for arranging the flat spacers <b>30</b>. Since a plurality of spacers are required for resisting against the atmosphere applied to the flat-type display device, a plurality of concave portions <b>123</b> are arranged for inserting the spacers. Corresponding to it, the same number of openings <b>131</b>A are arranged. It is quite natural that the openings and the concave portions may be arranged in the vertical direction of the drawing sheet. It should be noted that the depth of the concave portion <b>123</b> is substantially ½ of the metal sheet and the depth is set considering the engagement with the spacer.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">As described above, according to this embodiment, the metal back is not formed in the region of the display panel including the portion which is brought into abutment with the spacer <b>30</b> (i.e., the concave portion <b>123</b> formed on the metal sheet <b>120</b>). That is, in the metal back according to this embodiment, the portion corresponding to the afore-mentioned region is the opening <b>131</b>. Accordingly, when arranging the spacer, the spacer <b>30</b> does not interfere with the metal back <b>130</b> and it is possible to prevent scratching of the metal back by the spacer <b>30</b> and scattering of the fine powder. Moreover, even when the spacer <b>30</b> scratches the metal sheet <b>120</b>, the metal sheet <b>120</b> is made of an extremely low carbon steel thin plate of Fe—Ni-based alloy and there is no danger of generation of the metal fine powder.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Moreover, since the metal sheet <b>120</b> according to this embodiment is an Fe—Ni-based alloy, it has the getter function to react with the oxygen and vapor in the impurities gas emitted from the display panel and the rear panel contained in the FED which is an air tight vessel and to acquire it as oxide. (This will be detailed later). In this embodiment, as described above, the metal sheet <b>120</b> is exposed in the opening <b>131</b>A of the metal back and the exposed surface of the metal sheet <b>120</b> acquires oxygen and vapor as impurities gas, thereby maintaining a preferable air tight state in the FED. This effect becomes greater as the area of the exposed surface of the metal sheet <b>120</b> increases. Accordingly, as compared to the afore-mentioned first embodiment, the embodiments shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> have a greater effect.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Hereinafter, explanation will be given on the getter function of the Fe—Ni-based alloy. Fe, Ni, Fe—Ni alloy and other metals in general are oxidized in an atmosphere containing oxygen. In other words, they function as the oxygen getter. For example, when the reaction of Equation 1 maintains equilibrium in a closed system, the equilibrium oxygen partial pressure of the system is given by Equation 2. When oxygen exceeding this exists in the system, it reacts with Fe and becomes Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3 </sub>or Fe oxide.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?> 4/3Fe+O<sub>2</sub>=⅔Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>  (Equation 1)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>log <i>P</i><sub>O2</sub><i>=ΔG</i><sup>o</sup><i>/RT </i>ln 10  (Equation 2)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0055">(wherein ΔG<sup>o </sup>is a Gibs free energy change of the reaction)</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0056">The equilibrium oxygen partial pressure is a function of temperature. The equilibrium oxygen partial pressure (unit: atmosphere) when the Fe and Fe oxide are in the equilibrium state, for example, at the room temperature is very low as shown in Equation 3.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>log <i>P</i><sub>O2</sub>=−80 to −85  (Equation 3)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0057">Ni also absorbs oxygen of the system by the completely same reason. Accordingly, when the total oxygen amount is sufficiently small in the air tight system, the Fe═Ni-based alloy of the metal spacers are not all oxidized and the Fe—Ni-based alloy function as the oxygen getter. This function in the same way when the system contains vapor. In the reaction of Equation 4, the absolute amount of oxygen maintaining equilibrium with the vapor becomes small and the vapor partial pressure is also lowered.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>2H<sub>2</sub>+O<sub>2</sub>=2H<sub>2</sub>O  (Equation 4)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0058"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows an equilibrium oxygen partial pressure when Fe, Ni, and their oxides maintain the equilibrium state in the closed system. The equilibrium oxygen partial pressure increase as the temperature increases but it is sufficiently a low value as compared to the oxygen amount in the vacuum part of the FED.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0059">As described above, when no metal back is present in the concave portion <b>123</b>, the spacer <b>30</b> inserted into the concave portion <b>123</b> does not interfere with the metal back. There are methods for not forming the metal back in the concave portion <b>123</b> and the vicinity other than this embodiment. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the other embodiments will be explained.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0060"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a metal back according to a second embodiment. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> the metal back <b>130</b>B has an opening <b>131</b>B extending in the entire row direction instead of forming openings for each concave portion <b>123</b>. Like in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, no metal back is present in the concave portion <b>123</b>, the spacer <b>30</b> inserted into the concave portion <b>123</b> does not interfere with the metal back.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0061"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows metal backs according to other embodiments. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref>, the metal back is formed on the area where the fluorescent material of the metal sheet is present. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> shows a metal back according to a third embodiment. The metal back <b>130</b>C is formed in a comb-tooth shape on the area where the fluorescent material of the metal sheet <b>120</b> is present.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0062">By the way, as described above, the acceleration electrode has a two-layered structure consisting of the metal sheet <b>120</b> and the metal back <b>130</b> and the resistance is as follows. When the conductivity of copper is assumed to be 100, the aluminum as the material of the metal back <b>130</b> has % conductivity <b>62</b> while the Fe—Ni-base alloy as the material of the metal sheet has % conductivity as low as 3 (Denki Densi Zairyo Handbook (Electric and electronic material handbook), pp. 597-602, 1987, first edition, Asakura publisher). However, as compared to the metal back <b>130</b> having a thickness substantially 100 nm, the metal sheet <b>120</b> has thickness as large as 20 μm, i.e., more than 100 times thicker. Accordingly, the area resistance of the metal sheet <b>120</b> is smaller than 1/about 4.8 (=300/62) of the metal back <b>130</b>. Consequently, when the metal back is connected in parallel to the metal sheet, it is possible to reduce the resistance loss of the acceleration voltage. This is approved for DC and low-frequency current.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0063">However, when abnormal emission is caused by some reason, the emission current flows instantaneously. Accordingly, the emission current contains a high-frequency component and it is necessary to consider the skin effect. The high-frequency current flows in the vicinity of conductor surface and not in the center of the conductor. Accordingly, it flows the metal back side having a large % conductivity. Consequently, the emission current which is the high-frequency current flows through the metal back <b>130</b> having a thickness of substantially 100 nm and small resistance rather than the metal sheet <b>120</b> having a thickness of 20 μm or above and a large high-frequency resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0064">Here, as compared to the metal back in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> where the metal back is arranged over almost entire range of the metal sheet, the metal back arranged on the area where the fluorescent material of the metal sheet is present as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> reduces the width of current flow (width of conductive path), which in turn increases the resistance and inductance. As a result, it is possible to reduce the emission current flowing in the metal back <b>130</b> when abnormal emission is caused. Thus, it is possible to minimize damage of electronic emission elements by the excessive current flowing upon abnormal discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0065">It should be noted that the opening <b>131</b>C<sub>2 </sub>may not be present. However, in order to minimize damage of the electronic emission elements and the like upon abnormal emission, it is preferable that the opening <b>131</b>C<sub>2 </sub>be present.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0066"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> shows a fourth embodiment. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>, the metal back <b>130</b>D is formed only in the area where the fluorescent material of the metal sheet <b>120</b> is present. It should be noted that the opening <b>131</b>D<sub>2 </sub>may not be present. However, when the reduction of damage of the electron emission elements upon abnormal emission is considered, the opening <b>131</b>D<sub>2 </sub>is preferably present.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0067"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref> shows a fifth embodiment. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>, the metal back <b>130</b>E is formed continuously, i.e., unicursally only in the area where the fluorescent material of the metal sheet <b>120</b> is present. Accordingly, as compared to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref>, the resistance and inductance become greater and it is possible to further reduce damage of the electron emission element or the like upon abnormal emission. It should be noted that the opening <b>131</b>E<sub>2 </sub>may not be present. However, when the reduction of damage of the electron emission elements upon abnormal emission is considered, the opening <b>131</b>E<sub>2 </sub>is preferably present.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0068">Moreover, like <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref>, no metal back is present in the concave portion <b>123</b>. Accordingly, even when the spacers <b>130</b> are inserted in to the concave portions <b>123</b>, the spacers <b>30</b> to not interfere with the metal back and there is no danger of scattering of the metal back fine powder.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0069"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref> are top views of metal backs according to the other embodiments. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref>, the metal back is formed in color pixel unit or pixel unit separately. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> shows a sixth embodiment in which the metal back <b>130</b>F is separated in color pixel unit. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> shows a seventh embodiment in which the metal back <b>130</b>G is separated in a set of pixels for performing color display by three color pixels of fluorescent materials <b>111</b>R, <b>111</b>G and <b>111</b>B. Thus, when the metal back is formed separately in color pixel unit or pixel unit, between the metal backs, there exist a plurality of metal sheets whose high-frequency resistance value is high. As a result, it is possible to reduce the emission current upon abnormal emission as compared to the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref> and accordingly, it is possible to further reduce damage of the electron emission elements or the like. Moreover, in like <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref>, no metal back is present in the concave portions <b>123</b>. Accordingly, even when the spacers <b>30</b> are inserted in the concave portions <b>123</b>, there is no danger of scattering of metal back fine powder. It should be noted that <b>131</b>F and <b>131</b>G are openings surrounded by a plurality of separate metal backs <b>130</b>F and <b>130</b>G where the metal sheet <b>120</b> is exposed.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0070">The metal back <b>130</b> described in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref> can easily be formed by the conventional vacuum deposition (known technique) of aluminum (Al) by using a metal mask. Moreover, it is also possible to form the metal back <b>130</b> by the printing method using metal paste (such as silver paste). It should be noted that after the fluorescent material is painted, filming processing is performed, and then the metal back is formed by the aluminum vacuum deposition or silver paste printing.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0071">As described above, according to this embodiments, the metal sheet <b>120</b> used has a plurality of fine holes <b>122</b> having the fluorescent material <b>111</b> and the black oxide film formed as the light absorbing layer <b>121</b> on the side of the light transparent substrate <b>111</b>. The metal sheet also has a plurality of concave portions <b>123</b> formed on the side of the rear panel <b>1</b>. The metal back <b>130</b> having an opening corresponding to a predetermined area surrounding the concave portions <b>123</b> is superimposed on the metal sheet <b>120</b>, thereby constituting an acceleration electrode of two-layer structure. By inserting spacers <b>30</b> into the concave portions <b>123</b> of the metal sheet <b>120</b> exposed in the openings <b>131</b> of the metal back <b>130</b>, it is possible to prevent charging of the spacers <b>30</b> without lowering the contrast. Furthermore, it is possible to easily assemble the spacers <b>30</b> with a high accuracy al at once while suppressing the positioning shift. Moreover, since no metal back is formed in the area surrounding the concave portions <b>123</b> of the metal sheet <b>120</b>, even when the spacers <b>30</b> are inserted into the concave portions <b>123</b>, there is no danger of scratching the metal back. Accordingly, it is possible to prevent scattering of metal back fine powder caused by friction and there is no danger of shortcircuit of the electron emission elements and a wiring circuit of the rear panel <b>1</b>. It should be noted that even when the spacer <b>30</b> scratches the metal sheet <b>120</b>, the metal sheet <b>120</b> is made of extremely low carbon steel thin plate of Fe—Ni-based alloy and there is no danger of generation of metal fine powder.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0072">In this embodiments thus described, fixing member is applied to the light transparent substrate <b>110</b> when fixing the metal sheet <b>120</b> obtained by blackening the extremely low carbon steel thin plate of Fe—Ni-based alloy to the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>. However, this invention is not limited to this. For example it is possible to paint a fixing member mixed with black pigment so as to be black onto the metal sheet <b>120</b> not subjected to the blackening processing and fix the light transparent substrate <b>110</b>. That is, glass paste and black pigment paste containing black pigment are printed on the metal sheet <b>120</b> excluding the fine holes <b>122</b> and the light transparent substrate is fixed. Here, the light absorbing layer is simultaneously formed. In this case, since the metal sheet <b>120</b> is not subjected to the blackening processing, it is possible to skip the step of removing the black oxide film from the inner wall of the fine holes <b>122</b> of the metal sheet <b>120</b> and the surface where the metal back is to be formed (such as sand blast). It is noted that fine irregularities should be formed on the inner wall of the fine holes <b>122</b> for improving wettability.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0073">Thus, according to this invention, it is possible to prevent interference (friction) between the spacers and the metal back when attaching the spacers to the display panel. Accordingly, it is possible to prevent shortcircuit of the electron emission elements and a wiring circuit of the rear panel. Moreover, the spacers are not brought into direct contact with the metal back and it is possible to suppress charge of spacers. Furthermore, according to this invention, it is possible to attach the spacers with a high accuracy while suppressing positioning shift. The spacers can be easily attached at once. As a result, according to this invention, it is possible to improve the reliability and/or productivity of the flat-type display device such as the FED.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0074">It should be further understood by those skilled in the art that although the foregoing description has been made on embodiments of the invention, the invention is not limited thereto and various changes and modifications may be made without departing from the spirit of the invention and the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A display device comprising:
<claim-text>(a) a rear substrate including an insulative substrate on which a plurality of cold cathode elements for emitting electrons are formed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) a display substrate including:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light transparent substrate arranged to oppose to said rear substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a metal sheet including a plurality of fine holes arranged in a matrix and each having a plurality of fluorescent materials excited by an electron beam from the cold cathode element so as to emit light;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a metal back arranged at the side of the rear substrate of the metal sheet, to which metal back acceleration voltage is applied for accelerating the electron beam from the cold cathode element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) a plurality of support members arranged vertically between said rear substrate and said display substrate so as to maintain the interval between them; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(d) a frame member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a space surrounded by said rear substrate, said display substrate and said frame member is a vacuum atmosphere;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said metal sheet includes a light absorbing layer for absorbing external light formed on a surface of the light transparent substrate side a plurality of concave portions for holding said support members on the surface of said rear substrate side;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said metal back has an opening formed to exposes a predetermined area at least around the concave portion of said metal sheet; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said display substrate has a fixation layer for fixing said metal sheet to the light transparent substrate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said metal back is separately formed only on the area including at least one fine hole of said metal sheet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each of the fine holes emits light of one of three light primary colors, three of the fine holes emitting the colors constitute one pixel, and said metal back is separately formed only on the area containing at least one of the pixels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said metal sheet is fixed to the light transparent substrate by the fixation layer, after which the fine holes are formed on said metal sheet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the fixation layer is a glass layer having a low melting point.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the fixation layer is a glass layer having a light transparency limited to a predetermined value.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said metal sheet, the light transparent substrate and the glass layer have substantially same thermal expansion coefficient.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said metal sheet has a thickness of 20 μm to 250 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said metal sheet has a composition of Fe—Ni-based alloy.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said metal sheet has a substantially black surface on the light transparent substrate side.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the side wall of the fine holes formed on said metal sheet is electrically conductive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A display device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the fluorescent materials in the fine holes of said metal sheet has a substantially U-shaped cross sectional view.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
