<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299118-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299118</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10656193</doc-number>
<date>20030908</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-309146</doc-number>
<date>20021024</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>397</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>62</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>35</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701 45</main-classification>
<further-classification>297480</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Vehicle occupant protection apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6374168</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Fujii</name>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>701 45</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6758495</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Brambilla et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0068354</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Tabe</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>701 45</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>44 17 064</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19950700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>100 05 010</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 6-286581</doc-number>
<date>19941000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>B2 2715528</doc-number>
<date>19971100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2000-190815</doc-number>
<date>20000700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2000-211475</doc-number>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 200-247210</doc-number>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2001-39268</doc-number>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2001-39269</doc-number>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2001-55105</doc-number>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2002-19555</doc-number>
<date>20020100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>6</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701 45</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040080204</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040429</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Enomoto</last-name>
<first-name>Takaaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Anjo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kato</last-name>
<first-name>Hideki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nishin</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Oliff &amp; Berridge, PLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Toyota Jidosha Kabushiki Kaisha</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Toyota</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Thu V.</first-name>
<department>3661</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An occupant protection apparatus appropriately protects occupants of a vehicle, when a vehicle crush occurs, without requiring a troublesome task to the occupants. The occupant protection apparatus is provided with a steering angle sensor, a distance sensor and a brake depressing amount sensor. An electronic control unit predicts a vehicle crash based on the detection signals of each sensor so as to set a tension applied to a driver seat seatbelt to be smaller than a tension applied to passenger seat seatbelts. Additionally, the electronic control unit increases the tension applied to the seatbelts when a temperature detected by an outside-temperature detection sensor and/or an inside-temperature detection sensor is low.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="244.86mm" wi="106.93mm" file="US07299118-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="253.58mm" wi="178.99mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299118-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="245.62mm" wi="111.00mm" file="US07299118-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="202.18mm" wi="126.58mm" file="US07299118-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="159.94mm" wi="135.97mm" file="US07299118-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="170.18mm" wi="133.35mm" file="US07299118-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="251.88mm" wi="192.79mm" file="US07299118-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="261.96mm" wi="186.61mm" file="US07299118-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention generally relates to occupant protection apparatuses and, more particularly, to an occupant protection apparatus for appropriately protecting occupants of a vehicle by increasing a tension applied to a seatbelt.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Conventionally, as disclosed, for example, in Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 2000-55105 (pages 5-7 and FIG. 5), a protection apparatus of this kind protects an occupant of a vehicle by increasing a tension of the seatbelt according to the occupant's physical feature when it is judged that there is a possible crash or impact of the vehicle. In this protection apparatus, the occupant's physical feature is previously stored in a database so that data of each occupant is read out using a fingerprint sensor, an ID card, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, in the above-mentioned conventional occupant protection apparatus, a large strain may be imposed on an occupant since the occupant is required to input data to the apparatus so as to store the physical feature of the occupant. Moreover, in order to retrieve each occupant's data, it is necessary for each occupant to make a fingerprint check each time or use an ID card, which may be a problem in that each occupant is enforced to do a complicated procedure.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">It is a general object of the present invention to provide an improved and useful occupant protection apparatus in which the above-mentioned problems are eliminated.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A more specific object of the present invention is to provide an occupant protection apparatus which appropriately protect occupants, when a vehicle crush occurs, without requiring a troublesome task to the occupants.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In order to achieve the above-mentioned objects, there is provided according to one aspect of the present invention an occupant protection apparatus for a vehicle, comprising: driver-seat seatbelt tension changing means for changing a tension applied to a driver-seat seatbelt provided to a driver seat of the vehicle; passenger-seat seatbelt tension changing means for changing a tension applied to a passenger-seat seatbelt provided to a seat other than the driver seat; crash predicting means for predicting a crash of the vehicle; and belt tension controlling means for controlling the driver-seat seatbelt tension changing means and said passenger-seat seatbelt tension changing means so as to increase the tension applied to each of the driver-seat seatbelt and the passenger-seat seatbelt when the crash predicting means determines that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash, and set the tension applied to the driver-seat seatbelt to be smaller than the tension applied to the passenger-seat seatbelt.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In the above-mentioned invention, the crash predicting means may be constituted by time predicting means for predicting a time period until the vehicle crashes into an object (vehicle, etc) moving ahead and determining means for determining a possibility of a vehicle crash when the predicted time period is equal to or less than a predetermined short time. Additionally, the crash predicting means may be constituted by distance detecting means for detecting a distance from a front end of a vehicle to an object (vehicle, etc) moving ahead of the vehicle and determining means for predicting a front crash of the vehicle when the detected distance is equal to or smaller than a predetermined short distance.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Moreover, the crash predicting means may be constituted by brake depressing amount detecting means for detecting an amount of depression or travel of a brake pedal and determining means for predicting a front crash of a vehicle when a brake depressing velocity calculated based on the detected amount of depression is equal to or greater than a predetermined velocity. Furthermore, the crash predicting means may be constituted by steering angle detecting means for detecting a steering angle of a steering wheel and determining means for predicting a front crash of a vehicle when a steering angular velocity calculated based on the detected steering angle is equal to or greater than a predetermined angular velocity.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to the above-mentioned invention, the occupants including the driver and the passenger can be protected from a vehicle crash since the tension applied to each of the seatbelt of the driver seat and seatbelts of the passenger seats is increased when it is determined by the crash predicting means that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash. Additionally, an influence to a driving operation of a driver can be reduced since the tension of the seatbelt of the driver seat is set smaller than the tension of the seatbelts of the passenger seats, thereby permitting the driver to continuously performing the driving operation. Therefore, an attempt can be made to provide an appropriate protection corresponding to each occupant without imposing a procedural burden to each occupant as compared to the conventional technique.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Additionally, there is provided according to another aspect of the present invention an occupant protection apparatus for a vehicle, comprising: occupant belt tension changing means for changing a tension applied to an occupant seatbelt provided to the vehicle; outside-temperature detecting means for detecting a temperature outside the vehicle; crash predicting means for predicting a crash of the vehicle; and belt tension controlling means for controlling the occupant belt tension changing means so as to increase the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt when the crash predicting means determines that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash, and set the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt, when the outside temperature detected by the outside-temperature detection means is a first temperature, to be larger than the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt when the detected outside temperature is a second temperature higher than the first temperature.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to the above-mentioned invention, in addition to the protection of occupants when a vehicle crash occurs, the tension applied to the seatbelts when the outside temperature is low is increased (the first temperature) as compared to the tension when the outside temperature is high (the second temperature) in accordance with the outside temperature detected by the outside-temperature detecting means. In a case where an occupant wears winter clothes, a time period for removing a slack of the seatbelt is longer than usual due to a compression of the clothes even if the seatbelt tension is increased. For this reason, there is a possibility that a slack of the seatbelt may no be sufficiently removed if the seatbelt tension is increased with the same condition as the case where the occupant does not wear winter clothes. Thus, according to the detected outside temperature, it is assumed that the occupant wears wither clothes when the outside temperature is low and the tension applied to the seatbelts is increased. Therefore, the tension applied to the seatbelts can be increased while sufficiently removing a slack of the seatbelts, which results in appropriate protection of occupants while the thickness of clothes is also taken into consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Additionally, there is provided according to another aspect of the present invention an occupant protection apparatus for a vehicle, comprising: occupant belt tension changing means for changing a tension applied to an occupant seatbelt provided to the vehicle; inside-temperature detecting means for detecting a temperature inside the vehicle; crash predicting means for predicting a crash of the vehicle; and belt tension controlling means for controlling said occupant belt tension changing means so as to increase the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt when the crash predicting means determines that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash, and set the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt, when the inside temperature detected by the inside-temperature detection means is a first temperature, to be larger than the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt when the detected inside temperature is a second temperature higher than the first temperature.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to the above-mentioned invention, the tension of the seatbelts when the inside temperature is low (the first temperature) is increased as compared to that of a case where the inside temperature is high (second temperature) in accordance with the inside temperature detected by the inside-temperature detecting means. Although it differs from the assumption based on the outside temperature with respect to the assumption that an occupant wears winter clothes when the inside temperature is low, the present is the same as the aforementioned invention in that tension of the seatbelts when the inside temperature is low is increased as compared to that of a case where the inside temperature is high in accordance with the detected inside temperature, and the tension of the seatbelts when the assumption is made that the occupant wears winter clothes when the inside temperature is low is increased as compared to that of a case where the occupant does not wear winter clothes. Therefore, also in the present invention, each occupant is appropriately protected while the thickness of clothes is also taken into consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The occupant protection apparatus according to the present invention may further comprise physique detecting means for detecting physique of an occupant, and wherein the belt tension controlling means further controls the occupant belt tension changing means based on the physique detected by the physique detecting means so that the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt is set to be smaller as the detected physique is larger.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Accordingly, in addition to the protection of occupants which also considers the thickness of clothes, the tension applied to the seatbelts is decreased as compared to a case where the physique is large in accordance with the detected physique. That is, it is considered that a force required to constrain an occupant to each of the seats with the corresponding seatbelts is proportional to the physique of the occupant. Accordingly, when an occupant is a child and if the tension applied to each of the seatbelts is uniformly increased in the same manner as a case where the occupant is an adult, there is a possibility that too much binding load is applied to the child, which may result in insufficient protection to the child. Thus, the tension of the seatbelts is decreased when the weight of the occupant is small in response to the detected physique. Thereby, each occupant can be appropriately protected in accordance with their physique.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Additionally, there is provided according to another aspect of the present invention an occupant protection apparatus for a vehicle, comprising: occupant belt tension changing means for changing a tension applied to an occupant seatbelt provided to the vehicle; belt wear detecting means for detecting wear of the occupant seatbelt; crash predicting means for predicting a crash of the vehicle; and belt tension controlling means for controlling the occupant belt tension changing means, when it is judged by the crash predicting means that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash and also when wear of the occupant seatbelt is detected by the belt wear detecting means, so as to increase the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">According to the above-mentioned invention, the tension applied to the seatbelts is increased on the condition that it is determined that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash and also wear of the seatbelts is detected. Therefore, when the seatbelts are not worn, the tension control of the seatbelts is prohibited. For this reason, generation of abnormal noise is prevented, which may occur in the control of the seatbelts that are not worn, and failure and deterioration in the occupant belt tension changing means can be avoided.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Additionally, there is provided according to another aspect of the present invention an occupant protection apparatus for a vehicle, comprising: occupant belt tension changing means for changing a tension applied to an occupant seatbelt provided to the vehicle; belt wear detecting means for detecting wear of the occupant seatbelt; child seat detecting means for detecting attachment of a child seat to a passenger seat of the vehicle; crash predicting means for predicting a crash of the vehicle; and belt tension controlling means for controlling the occupant belt tension changing means, when it is judged by the crash predicting means that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash and when wear of the occupant seatbelt is detected by the belt wear detecting means and also when attachment of the child seat is not detected by child seat detecting means, so as to increase the tension applied to the occupant seatbelt.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">According to the above-mentioned invention, the tension applied to the seatbelts is increased on the condition that it is determined that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash, wear of the seatbelts is detected and also attachment of a child seat is not detected. Therefore, when the seatbelts are not worn, the tension control of the seatbelts is prohibited. Accordingly, generation of abnormal noise is prevented, which may occur in the control of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>b</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>that are not worn, and failure and deterioration in the occupant belt tension changing means can be avoided. On the other hand, when a child seat is attached, an execution of the tension control of the seatbelts to which a child seat is not attached is prohibited. Thus, the tension control of the seatbelts that do not require the control is prohibited, and failure and deterioration in the belt tension changing means can be avoided.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of an occupant protection apparatus according to first to third embodiments of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a flowchart of a seatbelt tension change control program executed by an electronic control unit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> according to the first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flowchart of a crash time detection program which is one of crash prediction processes performed by the seatbelt tension change control program;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flowchart of an emergency-braking detection program which is one of crash prediction processes performed by the seatbelt tension change control program;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flowchart of an emergency-steeling detection program which is one of crash prediction processes performed by the seatbelt tension change control program;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a flowchart of a seatbelt tension change control program executed by the electronic control unit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> according to the second embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flowchart of a seatbelt tension change control program executed by the electronic control unit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> according to the third embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">A description will now be given, with reference to the drawings, of a first embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram showing a vehicle occupant protection apparatus according to the first embodiment of the present invention. The occupant protection apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> increases a tension applied to a seat belt of each occupant at the time of a vehicle crash. The occupant protection apparatus comprises a driver's seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A, a front passenger seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>B, a rear right seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>C, and a rear left seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>D that are provided to respective occupant seats S<b>1</b>, S<b>2</b>, S<b>3</b> and S<b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">A description will be given of a specific structure of the driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A as an example of each of the seatbelt apparatuses <b>10</b>A, <b>10</b>B, <b>10</b>C and <b>10</b>D. The driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A is equipped with driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a</i>, a buckle <b>12</b><i>a </i>and a belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a</i>. One end of the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>is fixed to a vehicle body at a position near a side of the driver seat, and the other end of the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>enters the belt take-up motor <b>13</b><i>a</i>. A tongue plate <b>14</b><i>a </i>is attached to an intermediate portion of the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a</i>. The buckle <b>12</b><i>a </i>is attached to a side of the drive seat S<b>1</b>, and the tongue plate <b>14</b><i>a </i>can be removably connected to the buckle <b>12</b><i>a</i>. The belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a</i>, which constitutes a driver seat seatbelt tension changing means of the present invention, is attached to the vehicle body at a side of the driver seat S<b>1</b>. The belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>comprises an electric motor and a roll-up mechanism for winding the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>by being driven by the electric motor.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">A buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>a </i>is incorporated into the buckle <b>12</b><i>a</i>. The buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>a</i>, which functions as a belt wear detecting means, is in an OFF state when a driver do not wear the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>and in an ON state when a driver wears the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a</i>. Additionally, a belt tension sensor <b>22</b><i>a </i>is incorporated into the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a</i>. The belt tension sensor <b>22</b><i>a </i>detects the rolling-up torque of the electric motor of the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>so as to output a signal indicating the tension of the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a</i>. Moreover, an occupant physique (load) sensor <b>23</b><i>a </i>is provided to a seat frame of the drive seat S<b>1</b>. The occupant physique (load) sensor <b>23</b><i>a </i>functions as a physique detecting means to detect a physique such as a driver's weight.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">A structure of each of the front passenger seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>B, the rear right seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>C and the rear left seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>D is substantially the same as the structure of the driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A, and reference numerals with different alphabet signs are given to the corresponding parts and description thereof will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Next, a description will be given in detail of an electric control apparatus of the occupant protection apparatus. The electric control apparatus comprises a steering angle sensor <b>24</b>, a distance sensor <b>25</b>, a brake depressing amount sensor <b>26</b> and a vehicle speed sensor <b>27</b> in addition to the buckle-signal detection switches <b>21</b><i>a</i>-<b>21</b><i>d</i>, the belt tension sensors <b>22</b><i>a</i>-<b>22</b><i>d </i>and the occupant physique (load) sensors <b>23</b><i>a</i>-<b>23</b><i>d</i>. The steering angle sensor <b>24</b> detects a steering angle of a steering wheel. The steering angle of the steering wheel indicates a neutral state of the steering wheel at “0”, a steering amount in a left-hand direction by a negative value, and a steering amount of the steering wheel by a positive value. The distance sensor <b>25</b> detects a distance L from a front end of the vehicle to an object (mainly a vehicle) ahead of the vehicle equipped with the distance sensor <b>25</b>. The brake depressing amount sensor <b>26</b> detects an amount of travel of a brake pedal. The vehicle speed sensor <b>27</b> detects a speed V of the vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The buckle-signal detection switches <b>21</b><i>a</i>-<b>21</b><i>d</i>, the belt tension sensors <b>22</b><i>a</i>-<b>22</b><i>d</i>, the occupant physique (load) sensors <b>23</b><i>a</i>-<b>23</b><i>d</i>, the steering angle sensor <b>24</b>, the distance sensor <b>25</b>, the brake depressing amount sensor <b>26</b> and the vehicle speed sensor <b>27</b> are connected to an electronic control unit <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The electronic control unit <b>30</b> uses as a main structural component part a microcomputer, which comprises a CPU, a ROM, a RAM, a timer, etc. The electronic control unit <b>30</b> controls the tension applied to each of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>in the driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A, the front passenger seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>B, the rear right seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>C and the rear left seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>D by executing a seatbelt tension change control program shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> for each predetermined short time. Drive circuits <b>31</b><i>a</i>-<b>31</b><i>d </i>are connected to the electronic control unit <b>30</b>. The drive circuits <b>31</b><i>a</i>-<b>31</b><i>d </i>operate the electric motors of the belt take-up devices <b>13</b><i>a</i>-<b>13</b><i>d </i>in response to control signals from the electronic control unit <b>30</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A description will now be given of an operation of the occupant protection apparatus according to the first embodiment of the present invention. Upon turning on of an ignition switch, which is not shown in the figures, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> starts to repeatedly execute the seatbelt tension change control program shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> for each predetermined short period of time. The execution of the seatbelt tension change control program is started in step <b>100</b>, and a crash prediction process is performed in step <b>102</b>. In the crash prediction process, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 to 5</figref>, a crash time detection program, an emergency braking detection program and an emergency steering detection program are performed, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Execution of the crash time detection program is started in step <b>200</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. A vehicle speed V is input in step <b>202</b>, and it is determined whether or not the vehicle is moving by determining whether or not the vehicle speed is equal to or greater than a predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>. If the vehicle is almost in an idle state where the vehicle speed V is less than the predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>202</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>218</b>. In step <b>218</b>, a crash prediction flag PRF<b>1</b> is set to “0”, and the execution of the crash time detection program at this time is ended in step <b>220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">On the other hand, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>202</b>, that is, if it is determined that the vehicle speed V is equal to or greater than the predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> performed a process after step <b>204</b>. In step <b>204</b>, a distance L from the front end of the vehicle to an object ahead of the vehicle that is detected by the distance sensor <b>25</b> is input so as to set the distance L as a current distance Lnew, which represents a distance input by the execution of program at this time.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Next, a relative velocity Vab (=(Lold−Lnew)/Δt) with respect to a front object is calculated by dividing a subtraction value (Lold−Lnew), which is obtained by subtracting the current Lnew from the distance L (hereinafter referred to as a previous distance Lold) input at the last time of execution of the program, by an execution time interval Δt of the crash time detection program.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">It should be noted that, last distance Lold has been set as “0” by an initialization setting process which is not illustrated. In this case, the relative velocity Vab calculated at the first time becomes a negative value, and it is judged, in step <b>210</b> mentioned later, to be “No”, and the routine proceeds to step <b>218</b> where the crash prediction flag PRF<b>1</b> is set as “0”. Then, in step <b>220</b>, the execution of the crash time detection program at this time is ended. For this reason, there is no problem even if the relative velocity Vab calculated at the first time is inappropriate.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">After the calculation of the relative velocity Vab, the last distance Lold is updated, in step <b>208</b>, to the current distance Lnew for a next calculation of the relative velocity Vab. Next, it is determined, in step <b>210</b>, whether or not the relative velocity Vab is a positive value. If the relative velocity Vab is not a positive value, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>210</b> as mentioned above. Then, the crash prediction flag PRF<b>1</b> is set as “0” in step <b>218</b>, and the execution of the crash time detection program is ended in step <b>220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">On the other hand, if the relative velocity Vab is a positive value, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>210</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>212</b>. In step <b>212</b>, a time Ts (=Lnew/Vab) is calculated by dividing the current distance Lnew by the relative velocity Vab, the time Ts representing a period of time until a front end of the vehicle reaches the object moving ahead if the vehicle continuously moves at the current relative velocity Vab. Hereinafter, the time Ts is referred to as a front-end impact time. Next, it is determined, in step <b>214</b>, whether or not the front-end impact time Ts is equal to or smaller than a predetermined time Ts<b>1</b>. The predetermined time Ts<b>1</b> is set to a value at which there is a certain possibility that the front end of the vehicle reaches the object moving ahead.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">If the front-end impact time Ts is greater than the predetermined time Ts<b>1</b>, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>214</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>218</b>. In step <b>218</b>, as mentioned above, the crash prediction flag PRF<b>1</b> is set as “0”, and the execution of the crash time prediction program is once ended in step <b>220</b>. On the other hand, if the front-end impact time Ts is equal to or smaller than the predetermined time Ts<b>1</b>, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>214</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>216</b>. In step <b>216</b>, the crash prediction flag PRF<b>1</b> is set as “1”, and the execution of the crash time prediction program is ended.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The execution of the emergency braking detection program is started in step <b>300</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. In step <b>302</b>, a vehicle speed V detected by the vehicle speed sensor <b>27</b> is input, and it is determined whether or not the vehicle speed V is equal to or greater than a predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>, that is, whether or not the vehicle is in a running state. If the vehicle is in almost stopped state and when the vehicle speed V is smaller than the predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>302</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>314</b>. A crash prediction flag PRF<b>2</b> is set as “0” in step <b>314</b>, and the execution of the emergency braking detection program is once ended in step <b>316</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">On the other hand, when the vehicle starts to run and if an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>302</b>, that is, if it determined that the vehicle speed V is greater than the predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> performs a process after step <b>304</b>. In step <b>304</b>, a brake depressing amount B detected by the brake depressing amount sensor <b>26</b> is input so as to be set as a current depressing amount Bnew which represents an input depressing amount by the current execution of the emergency braking detection program. Next, in step <b>306</b>, a brake depressing velocity Bv (=(Bnew−Bold)/Δt) is calculated by dividing a subtraction value (Bnew−Bold) by a time interval Δt of execution of the braking detection program, the subtraction value being obtained by subtracting the depressing amount B (hereinafter referred to as a last depressing amount Bold) input in the last execution of the program from the current depressing amount Bnew. After the calculation of the brake depressing velocity Bv, the last depressing amount Bold is updated, in step <b>308</b>, to the current depressing amount Bnew for the next calculation of the brake depressing velocity Bv.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Then, if a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>310</b>, that is, if the brake depressing velocity Bv is smaller than a predetermined value B1, the routine proceeds to step <b>314</b>. In step <b>314</b>, the crash prediction flag PRF<b>2</b> is set as “0”, and the execution of the emergency braking detection program is once ended. On the other hand, if the brake depressing velocity Bv is equal to or greater than the predetermined value B1, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>310</b>. Then, the crash prediction flag PRF<b>2</b> is set as “1”, and the execution of the emergency braking detection program is ended in step <b>316</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The execution of the emergency steering detection program is started in step <b>400</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. In step <b>402</b>, a vehicle speed V detected by the vehicle speed sensor <b>27</b> is input, and it is determined whether or not the vehicle speed V is equal to or greater than a predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>, that is, whether or not the vehicle is in a running state. If the vehicle is in almost stopped state and when the vehicle speed V is smaller than the predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>402</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>414</b>. A crash prediction flag PRF<b>3</b> is set as “0” in step <b>314</b>, and the execution of the emergency steering detection program is once ended in step <b>416</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">On the other hand, when the vehicle starts to run and if an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>402</b>, that is, if it determined that the vehicle speed V is greater than the predetermined small value V<sub>0</sub>, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> performs a process after step <b>404</b>. In step <b>404</b>, a steering angle θ detected by the steering angle sensor <b>24</b> is input so as to be set as a current steering angle θnew which represents an input steering angle by the current execution of the emergency steering detection program. Next, in step <b>406</b>, a steering angular velocity θv (=(θnew−θold)/Δt) is calculated by dividing a subtraction value (θnew−θold) by a time interval Δt of execution of the steering angle detection program, the subtraction value being obtained by subtracting the steering angle θ (hereinafter referred to as a last steering angle θold) input in the last execution of the program from the current steering angle θnew. After the calculation of the steering angular velocity θv, the last steering angle θold is updated, in step <b>408</b>, to the current steering angle θnew for the next calculation of the steering angular velocity θv.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Then, if a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>410</b>, that is, if the steering angular velocity θv is smaller than a predetermined value θ1, the routine proceeds to step <b>414</b>. In step <b>414</b>, the crash prediction flag PRF<b>3</b> is set as “0”, and the execution of the emergency steering detection program is once ended. On the other hand, if the steering angular velocity θv is equal to or greater than the predetermined value θ1, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>410</b>. Then, the crash prediction flag PRF<b>3</b> is set as “1”, and the execution of the emergency braking detection program is ended in step <b>416</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Returning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, it is determined, in step <b>104</b>, whether or not at least one of the crash prediction flags PRF<b>1</b> through PRF<b>3</b> has been set to “1”. If all of the crash prediction flags PRF<b>1</b> through PRF<b>3</b> have been set to “0” according to the above-mentioned crash prediction process, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>104</b>, and the execution of the seatbelt tension change control program is once ended in step <b>122</b>. On the other hand, when at least one of the crash prediction flags PRF<b>1</b> through PRF<b>3</b> has been set to “1”, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>104</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Then, it is determined, in step <b>106</b>, whether or not the buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A is an ON state. If the buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>a </i>is an OFF state (not worn), a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>106</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>110</b>. On the other hand, if the buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>a </i>is an ON state (worn), an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>106</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>108</b>. In step <b>108</b>, the electric motor of the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>is driven so that the tension of the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>is set to T<b>1</b>. That is, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> controls the rotation of the electric motor of the belt take-up apparatus <b>13</b><i>a </i>through the drive circuit <b>31</b><i>a </i>so as to operate the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>so that a belt tension based on a torque detected by the belt tension sensor <b>22</b><i>a </i>is set to T<b>1</b>. Thereby, driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>is rolled up, and the driver is constricted to the driver seat S<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">After the control of the driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A has ended, the front passenger seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b><i>b</i>, the rear right passenger seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>C and the rear left passenger seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>D are controlled sequentially by the process of steps <b>110</b> through <b>120</b>. However, in order to control each of the seatbelt apparatuses <b>10</b>B, <b>10</b>C and <b>10</b>D on an individual seatbelt apparatus basis, the seatbelt apparatuses <b>10</b>B, <b>10</b>C and <b>10</b>D are sequentially controlled by sequentially incrementing the parameter “m” by the process of steps <b>110</b>, <b>118</b> and <b>112</b> using the parameter “m”.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">First, it is determined, in step <b>112</b>, whether or not the buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>b </i>is an ON state with respect to the front passenger seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>B which is provided with the parameter “m”=1. If the buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>b </i>is an OFF state, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>112</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>118</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">On the other hand, it the buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>b </i>is an ON state, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>112</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>114</b>. It is determined, in step <b>114</b>, whether the front passenger seat S<b>2</b> is attached with a child seat. The child seat is attached to the front passenger seat S<b>2</b> by being constrained with the seat belt <b>11</b><i>b </i>of the front passenger seat S<b>2</b> with its back part or bottom part being pressed against the front passenger seat S<b>2</b>. In order to determine whether or not a child seat is attached, a belt tension T based on the torque detected by the belt tension sensor <b>22</b><i>b </i>and a weight W detected by the occupant physique (load) sensor <b>23</b><i>b </i>are input. If the belt tension T is equal to or greater than a predetermined tension T<b>0</b> and the weight W is equal to or smaller than a predetermined weight W<b>0</b>, it is determined that a child seat is attached. Otherwise, it is determined that a child seat is not attached. Consequently, if a child seat it attached, an affirmative determination is made in step <b>114</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>118</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">On the other hand, if a child seat is not attached, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>114</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>116</b>. In step <b>116</b>, the electric motor of the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>b </i>is driven so that the tension of the seat belt <b>11</b><i>b </i>of the front passenger seat is TZ. That is, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> controls the rotation of the belt roll-up motor <b>13</b><i>b </i>through the drive circuit <b>31</b><i>b </i>so as to operate the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>b </i>so that the belt tension based on a torque detected by the belt tension sensor <b>22</b><i>b</i>. Thereby, the passenger seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>b </i>is rolled up, thereby constraining an occupant to the front passenger seat S<b>2</b>. In this case, the tension T<b>1</b> of the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat is smaller by a predetermined value than the tension T<b>2</b> of the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>b </i>of the front passenger seat S<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Similarly, the rear right seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>C and the rear left seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>D are controlled while changing the parameter “m” as “m”=2 and “m”=3. Thereafter, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>118</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>122</b> where the execution of the seatbelt tension change control program is ended.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">As mentioned above, in the first embodiment of the present invention, when it is determined in the process of step <b>102</b> and <b>104</b> that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash, a tension applied to each of the driver seat seatbelt and the passenger seat seatbelts is increased, thereby protecting all occupants from a vehicle crash. Additionally, since the tension T<b>1</b> of the driver seat seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>is set to be smaller than the tension T<b>2</b> of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>b</i>-<b>11</b><i>d</i>, an influence to a driving operation of the driver is reduced so that it is easy for the driver to continuously perform the driving operation.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Moreover, according to the above-mentioned first embodiment, the tension applied to the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is increased on the condition that it is determined that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash in the process of steps <b>102</b> and <b>104</b> and also wear of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is detected. Therefore, when the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>are not worn, the tension control of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is prohibited by the process of steps <b>106</b> and <b>112</b>. For this reason, the belt take-up devices <b>13</b><i>a</i>-<b>13</b><i>d </i>are prevented from generating abnormal noise, which may occur in the control of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>that are not worn, and a failure in the belt take-up devices <b>13</b><i>a</i>-<b>13</b><i>d </i>and a deterioration in a motor contact point can be avoided. Moreover, since the electric motor is prevented from being supplied with a motor-lock current, there is obtained an effect of reduction in power consumption.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Further, in the above-mentioned first embodiment of the present invention, a tension applied to the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>b</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is increased on the condition that it is determined that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash in the process of steps <b>102</b> and <b>104</b>, wear of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>b</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is detected in the process of step <b>112</b> and also attachment of a child seat is not detected in the process of step <b>114</b>. Therefore, when the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>are not worn, the belt take-up devices <b>13</b><i>b</i>-<b>13</b><i>d </i>are prevented from generating abnormal noise, which may occur in the control of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>b</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>that are not worn, and a failure in the belt take-up devices <b>13</b><i>b</i>-<b>13</b><i>d </i>and a deterioration in a motor contact point can be avoided. Moreover, since the electric motor is prevented from being supplied with a motor-lock current, there is obtained an effect of reduction in power consumption.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">On the other hand, when a child seat is attached, an execution of the tension control of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>b</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>to which a child seat is not attached is prohibited in the process of step <b>114</b>. Thus, the tension control of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>that do not require the control is prohibited, and a failure in the belt take-up devices <b>13</b><i>b</i>-<b>13</b><i>d </i>and a deterioration in a motor contact point can be avoided. Moreover, since the electric motor is prevented from being supplied with a motor-lock current, there is obtained an effect of reduction in power consumption. As mentioned above, the belt tension sensors <b>22</b><i>b</i>-<b>22</b><i>d</i>, the occupant physique (load) sensors <b>23</b><i>b</i>-<b>23</b><i>d </i>and the process of step <b>114</b> correspond to the child seat detecting means of the present invention.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Next, a second embodiment of the present invention will be explained. The occupant protection apparatus according to the second embodiment of the present invention comprises an outside-temperature detection sensor <b>28</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> by dotted lines. The outside-temperature detection sensor <b>28</b> functions as outside-temperature detecting means attached to the exterior of the vehicle for detecting an outside temperature of the vehicle, and is connected to the electronic control unit <b>30</b>. Additionally, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> according to the second embodiment stores a seatbelt tension change control program of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> instead of the seatbelt tension change control program of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, and repeatedly executes the program for every predetermined short time. Other parts of the present embodiment are the same as the above-mentioned first embodiment, and descriptions thereof will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">A description will be given below of an operation of the occupant protection apparatus according to the second embodiment of the present invention. Also in the occupant protection apparatus of the present embodiment, upon turning on of the ignition switch, which is not shown in the figures, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> starts to repeatedly execute the seatbelt tension change control program shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> for each predetermined short period of time. The execution of the seatbelt tension change control program is started in step <b>130</b>, and the electronic control unit <b>30</b> performs, similar to the above-mentioned first embodiment, a crash prediction process of step <b>102</b>. If all of the crash prediction flags PRF<b>1</b> through PRF<b>3</b> have been set to “0” according to the crash prediction process, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>104</b>, and the execution of the seatbelt tension change control program is once ended in step <b>158</b>. On the other hand, when at least one of the crash prediction flags PRF<b>1</b> through PRF<b>3</b> has been set to “1”, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>104</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>132</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">In step <b>132</b>, in order to control the seatbelt apparatuses <b>10</b>A, <b>10</b>B, <b>10</b>C and <b>10</b>D on an individual apparatus basis, each of the seatbelt apparatuses <b>10</b>A, <b>10</b>B, <b>10</b>C and <b>10</b>D is controlled in the process of step <b>132</b>, <b>154</b> and <b>156</b> using the parameter “m” while incrementing the parameter “m” from 1 to 4. First, it is determined, in step <b>134</b>, whether the buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>a </i>is an ON state with respect to the driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A which corresponds to “m”=1. If the buckle-signal detection pilot-switch <b>21</b><i>a </i>is an OFF state, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>134</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>154</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">On the other hand, if the buckle-signal detection switch <b>21</b><i>a </i>is an ON state, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>134</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>136</b>. In step <b>136</b>, it is determined whether a child seat is attached to the driver seat S<b>1</b>. Since a child seat is never attached to the driver seat S<b>1</b>, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>136</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>138</b>. In step <b>138</b>, an outside temperature tout detected by the outside-temperature detection sensor <b>28</b> is input. Next, a weight W of the driver detected by the occupant physique (load) sensor <b>23</b><i>a </i>is input in step <b>140</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Then, it is determined, in step <b>142</b>, whether or not the outside temperature tout is equal to or lower than a predetermined temperature tout<b>1</b>. If the outside temperature tout is equal to or lower than the predetermined temperature tout<b>1</b>, it is assumed that the driver wears winter clothes (wear a lot of clothes). In this case, in order to sufficiently remove the slack of the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat, the tension applied to the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat is increased. It is considered that a force required for the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>to constrain a driver to the driver seat S<b>1</b> is proportional to the weight of the driver. Therefore, if, the weight W of the driver is equal to or greater than a predetermined weight W, the electric motor of the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>is driven through the drive circuit <b>31</b><i>a </i>in the process of steps <b>144</b> and <b>146</b> so that the tension of the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat is set to T<b>3</b> (large).</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">On the other hand, if the weight W of the driver is smaller than the predetermined weight W<b>1</b>, in order to prevent an excessive binding load to the driver, the electric motor of the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>is driven through the drive circuit <b>31</b><i>a </i>in the process of steps <b>144</b> and <b>150</b> so that the tension applied to the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat is set to T<b>4</b> (middle).</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">If the outside temperature tout is higher than the predetermined temperature tout1 in step <b>142</b>, it is assumed that the driver does not wear winter clothes (not wear a lot of clothes) and the tension applied to the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat is increased. In this case, however, since there is no need to remove a slack of the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a</i>, the tension applied to the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>is smaller than the seatbelt tension T<b>3</b>. Since it is considered that a force to constrain the driver to the driver seat by the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat is proportional to the weight of the driver, if the weight W of the driver is equal to or larger than the predetermined weight W<b>1</b>, the electric motor of the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>is driven through the drive circuit <b>31</b><i>a </i>in the process of steps <b>148</b> and <b>150</b> so that the tension applied to the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat is set to T<b>4</b> (middle).</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">On the other hand, if it is determined in step <b>148</b> that the weight W of the driver is smaller than the predetermined weight W<b>1</b>, in order to prevent an excessive binding load to the driver, the electric motor of the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>is driven through the drive circuit <b>31</b><i>a </i>in the process of steps <b>148</b> and <b>152</b> so that the tension applied to the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the driver seat is set to T<b>5</b> (small).</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">In the above-mentioned case, the seatbelt tension T<b>4</b> is smaller than the seatbelt tension T<b>3</b> by a predetermined amount, and the seatbelt tension T<b>5</b> is smaller than the seatbelt tension T<b>4</b> by a predetermined amount. That is, an electric current value supplied to the electric motor of the belt take-up device <b>13</b><i>a </i>decreases in turn as the seatbelt tension decreases as T<b>3</b>, T<b>4</b>, T<b>5</b> in turn.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">After controlling the seatbelt apparatuses <b>10</b>B <b>10</b>C, and <b>10</b>D while changing “m”=2, 3, 4 in the same manner, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>154</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>158</b> so as to end the execution of the seatbelt tension change control program. However, in the process of step <b>136</b> for each of the seatbelt apparatuses <b>10</b>B, <b>10</b>C and <b>10</b>D, similar to the process of step <b>114</b> explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, it is determined that a child seat is attached if the belt tension T is equal to or larger than a predetermined tension T<b>0</b> and also the weight W is equal to or smaller than a predetermined weight W<b>0</b>. In other cases, it is determined that a child seat is not attached. Then, if a child seat is attached, an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in step <b>136</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>154</b>. That is, it is determined in step <b>136</b> whether or not a child seat is attached on the condition that it is determined whether or not it is a process for the driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A and a determination is made that the process is not for the driver seat seatbelt apparatus <b>10</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">As mentioned above, according to the second embodiment of the present invention, in addition to the protection of occupants when a vehicle crash occurs and the effect acquired by the prohibition of the seatbelt tension control by the process of steps <b>134</b> and <b>136</b>, the tension applied to the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>when the outside temperature tout is high is increased as compared to the tension when the outside temperature tout is low by the process of steps <b>142</b>, <b>146</b> and <b>150</b> in accordance with the outside temperature tout detected by the outside-temperature detection sensor <b>28</b>. In a case where an occupant wears winter clothes, a time period for removing a slack of the seatbelt is longer than usual due to a compression of the clothes even if the seatbelt tension is increased. For this reason, there is a possibility that a slack of the seatbelt may no be sufficiently removed if the seatbelt tension is increased with the same condition as the case where the occupant does not wear winter clothes. Thus, according to the detected outside temperature tout, it is assumed that the occupant wears wither clothes when the outside temperature tout is low and the tension applied to the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is increased. Therefore, the tension applied to the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>can be increased while sufficiently removing a slack of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d</i>, which results in appropriate protection of occupants while the thickness of clothes is also taken into consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Additionally, according to the second embodiment of the present invention, in addition to the protection of occupants which also considers the thickness of clothes, the tension applied to the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>when the weight W of an occupant is small is decreased as compared to a case where the weight W is large by the process of steps <b>144</b>, <b>146</b>, <b>148</b>, <b>150</b> and <b>152</b> in accordance with the detected weight W (detected physique). That is, it is considered that a force required to constrain an occupant to each of the seats S<b>1</b>-S<b>4</b> with the corresponding seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is proportional to the weight of the occupant. Accordingly, when an occupant is a child and if the tension applied to each of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is uniformly increased in the same manner as a case where the occupant is an adult, there is a possibility that too much binding load is applied to the child, which may result in insufficient protection to the child. Thus, the tension of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is decreased when the weight of the occupant is small in response to the detected weight W. Thereby, each occupant can be appropriately protected in accordance with their weight.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Third Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">Next, a third embodiment of the present invention will be explained. The occupant protection apparatus according to the second embodiment of the present invention comprises an inside-temperature detection sensor <b>29</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> by dotted lines instead of the outside-temperature detection sensor <b>28</b>. The inside-temperature detection sensor <b>29</b> functions as inside-temperature detecting means attached to the interior of the vehicle for detecting an inside temperature of the vehicle, and is connected to the electronic control unit <b>30</b>. Additionally, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> according to the third embodiment stores a seatbelt tension change control program of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> instead of the seatbelt tension change control program of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, and repeatedly executes the program for every predetermined short time. The seatbelt tension change control program of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> executes the process of steps <b>172</b> and <b>174</b> instead of the process of steps <b>138</b> and <b>142</b> of the seatbelt tension change control program according to the above-mentioned second embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">A description will be given below of an operation of the occupant protection apparatus according to the third embodiment of the present invention. Also in the occupant protection apparatus of the present embodiment, upon turning on of the ignition switch, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> starts to repeatedly execute the seatbelt tension change control program shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> for each predetermined short period of time. The execution of the seatbelt tension change control program is started in step <b>170</b>, and the electronic control unit <b>30</b> performs the process of steps <b>102</b> through <b>136</b> that is the same as the above-mentioned second embodiment. If it is determined, in step <b>136</b>, that the a child seat is not attached, a negative determination “No” is made in step <b>136</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>172</b>. In step <b>172</b>, the inside temperature tin detected by the inside-temperature detection sensor <b>29</b> is input. Then, the occupant's weight W is input in step <b>140</b>, and the routine proceeds to step <b>174</b>. It is determined, in step <b>174</b>, whether or not the inside temperature tin is equal to or lower than a predetermined temperature tin<b>1</b>. If the inside temperature tin is equal to or lower than the predetermined temperature tin<b>1</b>, the routine proceeds to step <b>144</b>. On the other hand, if the internal temperature tin is higher than the predetermined temperature tin<b>1</b>, the routine proceeds to step <b>148</b>. The process of subsequent steps <b>144</b>-<b>158</b> is the same as that of the second embodiment, and descriptions thereof will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">According to the third embodiment of the present invention, the tension of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>when the inside temperature is high is increased as compared to that of a case where the inside temperature tin is low by the process of steps <b>174</b>, <b>146</b>, <b>150</b> in accordance with the inside temperature tin detected by the inside-temperature detection sensor <b>29</b>. Although it differs from the assumption based on the outside temperature tout as is in the process of step <b>142</b> according to the second embodiment with respect to the assumption in the process of step <b>174</b> that an occupant wears winter clothes when the inside temperature tin is low, the present embodiment is the same as the second embodiment in that tension of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>when the inside temperature tin is low is increased as compared to that of a case where the inside temperature tin is high by the process of steps <b>146</b> and <b>150</b> in accordance with the detected inside temperature tin, and the tension of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>when the assumption is made that the occupant wears winter clothes when the inside temperature tin is low is increased as compared to that of a case where the occupant does not wear winter clothes. Therefore, also in the present embodiment, each occupant is appropriately protected while the thickness of clothes is also taken into consideration. Moreover, the present embodiment is the same as the second embodiment in that each occupant can be appropriately protected in response to their weight by decreasing the tension of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>when the weight W is small is decreased as compared to that of a case where the weight W is large by the process of the steps <b>144</b>, <b>146</b>, <b>148</b>, <b>150</b> and <b>152</b> in accordance with the detected weight W.</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">Other Embodiments</heading>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">The occupant protection apparatuses according to the first through third embodiments were explained above. However, the occupant protection apparatus according to the present invention is not limited to the first through third embodiments, and various variations may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">For example, in the second embodiment, the description was give of the occupant protection apparatus that uses the outside-temperature detection sensor <b>28</b> as the outside-temperature detecting means, and the tension of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is increased in accordance with the detected outside temperature tout alone when the outside temperature tout is equal to or lower than the predetermined temperature tout<b>1</b>. Additionally, in the third embodiment, the description was given to the occupant protection apparatus that uses the inside-temperature detection sensor <b>29</b> as inside temperature detecting means, and the tension of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>is increased in accordance with the detected inside temperature tin alone when the inside temperature tin is equal to or lower than the predetermined temperature tin<b>1</b>. However, the occupant protection apparatus according to the present invention may use both the outside-temperature detection sensor <b>28</b> and the inside-temperature detection sensor <b>29</b> simultaneously so as to increase the tension of the seatbelt <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>when an affirmative determination “Yes” is made in the process of determining whether or not the outside temperature tout is equal to or lower than the predetermined temperature tout<b>1</b> and whether or not the inside temperature tin is equal to or lower than the predetermined temperature tin<b>1</b>. In this case, the probability in the assumption that an occupant wears wither clothes (wears a lot of clothes) can be increased, and, thus, protection of the occupant can be surely attempted while the thickness of the clothes is taken into consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">Additionally, in the second and third embodiments, descriptions were given as to the occupant protection apparatuses that increase the tension of the seatbelts <b>11</b><i>a</i>-<b>11</b><i>d </i>when the outside temperature tout is equal to or lower than the predetermined temperature tout<b>1</b> or the inside temperature tin is equal to or lower than the predetermined temperature tin<b>1</b>. However, the present invention is not limited to the apparatus performing such a process, and the seatbelt tension T may be determined in response to the outside temperature tout or the inside temperature tin. Specifically, a seatbelt tension table is prepared and stored in the electronic control unit <b>30</b>. The seatbelt tension table represents a relationship between the outside temperature tout (inside temperature tin) and the seatbelt tension T wherein the seatbelt tension T increases as the outside temperature tout (inside temperature tin) decreases. Then, the electronic control unit <b>30</b> determines the seat belt tension T corresponding to the outside temperature tout (inside temperature tin) by referring to the seat belt tension table. According to this embodiment, the tension of the seatbelts is increased in accordance with the outside temperature tout (inside temperature tin) when the outside temperature tout (inside temperature tin) is low as compared to that of a case where the outside temperature tout (inside temperature tin) is high. Therefore, also in this case, appropriate protection to each occupant can be attempted while the thickness of clothes is taken into consideration.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Moreover, although in the above-mentioned first through third embodiments, the occupant physique (load) sensors <b>23</b><i>a</i>-<b>23</b><i>d </i>are used as the physique detecting means, the present invention is not limited to such a sensor, and, for example, any one of the followings may be used: assuming a physique by detecting a weight of an occupant from a pressure inside a bag which is filled with a liquid and placed inside a seating surface of a seat; assuming a physique of an occupant from a surface pressure distribution when the occupant seats by inserting a film provided with a lot of pressure sensors into inside of the seat; assuming a physique of an occupant from changes in an electrostatic capacity by arranging a cloth-like antenna in a seat; assuming a physique of an occupant in a front seat from a position of the seat along a front-to-rear direction; and assuming a physique by an image take by a camera.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">Further, although the belt tension sensors <b>22</b><i>b</i>-<b>22</b><i>d </i>and the occupant physique (load) sensors <b>23</b><i>b</i>-<b>23</b><i>d </i>are used as an example of the child seat detecting means in the first through third embodiments, the preset invention is not limited to such a sensor and any one of the followings may be used: detecting a child seat from a surface pressure distribution obtained by many pressure sensors; assuming an existence of a child seat by measuring changes in an electrostatic capacity; and detecting a child seat by an image taken by a camera.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">The present invention is not limited to the specifically disclosed embodiments, and variations and modifications may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">The present application is based on Japanese priority application No. 2002-309146 filed Oct. 24, 2002, the entire contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An occupant protection apparatus for a vehicle, comprising:
<claim-text>driver-seat seatbelt tension changing means for changing a tension applied to a driver-seat seatbelt provided to a driver seat of the vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>passenger-seat seatbelt tension changing means for changing a tension applied to a passenger-seat seatbelt provided to a seat other than said driver seat;</claim-text>
<claim-text>crash predicting means for predicting a crash of said vehicle; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>belt tension controlling means for controlling said driver-seat seatbelt tension changing means and said passenger-seat seatbelt tension changing means so as to increase the tension applied to each of said driver-seat seatbelt and said passenger-seat seatbelt when said crash predicting means determines that there is a possibility of a vehicle crash, and set the tension applied to said driver-seat seatbelt to always be smaller than the tension applied to said passenger-seat seatbelt.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The occupant protection apparatus as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising belt wear detecting means for detecting wear of each of said driver-seat seatbelt and said passenger-seat seatbelt, and wherein said belt tension controlling means further controls said driver-seat seatbelt tension changing means and said passenger-seat seatbelt tension changing means, when said crash predicting means judges that there is a possibility of vehicle crash and also when said belt wear detecting means detects wear of each of said driver-seat seatbelt and said passenger-seat seatbelt, so as to increase the tension applied to each of the driver-seat seatbelt and the passenger-seat seatbelt.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The occupant protection apparatus as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising physique detecting means for detecting physique of an occupant, and wherein said belt tension controlling means further controls said driver-seat seatbelt tension changing means and said passenger-seat seatbelt tension changing means based on the physique detected by said physique detecting means so that the tension applied to each of said driver-seat seatbelt and passenger-seat seatbelt is set to be smaller as the detected physique is larger.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The occupant protection apparatus as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising belt wear detecting means for detecting wear of each of said driver-seat seatbelt and said passenger-seat seatbelt and child seat detecting means for detecting attachment of a child seat to said seat other than said driver seat, and wherein said belt tension controlling means further controls said driver-seat seatbelt tension changing means and said passenger-seat seatbelt tension changing means, when said crash predicting means judges that there is a possibility of vehicle crash and also when said belt wear detecting means detects wear of each of said driver-seat seatbelt and said passenger-seat seatbelt and further when said child seat detecting means does not detect attachment of said child seat, so as to increase the tension applied to each of the driver-seat seatbelt and the passenger-seat seatbelt.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A seatbelt tension control method of controlling a tension applied to seatbelts of a vehicle, the method comprising:
<claim-text>predicting a crash of said vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>judging whether a driver-seat seatbelt provided to a driver seat is worn;</claim-text>
<claim-text>increasing the tension applied to said driver-seat seatbelt when there is a possibility of a vehicle crash and also when said driver-seat seatbelt is worn;</claim-text>
<claim-text>judging whether a seatbelt provided to a seat other than said driver seat is worn; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>increasing the tension applied to said seatbelt provided to said seat other than said driver-seat seatbelt when there is a possibility of a vehicle crash and also when said seatbelt provided to said seat other than said driver-seat seatbelt is worn, and set the tension applied to said driver-seat seatbelt to always be smaller than the tension applied to said passenger-seat seatbelt.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The seatbelt tension control method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>detecting attachment of a child seat to said seat other than said driver seat; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>prohibiting an increase in the tension applied to said seatbelt provided to said seat other than said driver-seat.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
