<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298471-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298471</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11410944</doc-number>
<date>20060426</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-366255</doc-number>
<date>20031027</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3562375</main-classification>
<further-classification>3562372</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Surface inspection apparatus and surface inspection method</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5046847</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nakata et al.</name>
<date>19910900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5777744</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yoshii et al.</name>
<date>19980700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5835220</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kazama et al.</name>
<date>19981100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>356369</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6594012</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Takeuchi et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0010363</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Watanabe et al.</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0013935</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Watanabe et al.</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0026365</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hirosawa</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>356369</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 1-117024</doc-number>
<date>19890500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2-12002</doc-number>
<date>19900100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 6-3278</doc-number>
<date>19940100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 10-232122</doc-number>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 11-295231</doc-number>
<date>19991000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2002-116011</doc-number>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>11</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>17</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>PCT/JP2004/015925</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20041027</date>
</document-id>
<parent-status>PENDING</parent-status>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11410944</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060192953</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060831</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fukazawa</last-name>
<first-name>Kazuhiko</first-name>
<address>
<city>Misato</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Komatsu</last-name>
<first-name>Koichiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Oomori</last-name>
<first-name>Takeo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sagamihara</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Oliff &amp; Berridge PLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nikon Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Stafira</last-name>
<first-name>Michael P.</first-name>
<department>2886</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A surface inspection apparatus and a surface inspection method aim to securely deal with finer repetition pitch without shortening the wavelength of illumination light. To this end, the apparatus includes a unit illuminating repetitive pattern(s) formed on the substrate surface to be inspected with linearly polarized light, a unit setting to an oblique angle an angle between the direction of an intersecting line of a vibration plane of the linearly polarized light on the substrate surface and the repetition direction of repetitive pattern(s), a unit extracting a polarized light component perpendicular to the vibration plane of the linearly polarized light, from light having been emitted from the repetitive pattern(s) in a specular direction, and a unit detecting a defect of the repetitive pattern(s) according to the light intensity of the polarized light component.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="166.71mm" wi="150.37mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="182.80mm" wi="150.88mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="204.22mm" wi="100.41mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="223.27mm" wi="159.43mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="232.58mm" wi="121.75mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="213.19mm" wi="128.61mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="230.38mm" wi="177.29mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="232.66mm" wi="117.01mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="203.79mm" wi="136.14mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="234.53mm" wi="160.70mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="116.16mm" wi="167.64mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="176.28mm" wi="145.03mm" file="US07298471-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation application of International Application PCT/JP 2004/015925, filed on Oct. 27, 2004, and claims the benefit of priority from Japanese Patent Application No. 2003-366255, filed on Oct. 27, 2003, designating the U.S.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION </heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a surface inspection apparatus and a surface inspection method for the surface of a semiconductor wafer or a liquid crystal substrate.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE RELATED ART </heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In the production process of a semiconductor circuit device and a liquid crystal display device, a defect inspection is performed on a repetitive pattern (pattern of lines and space such as an interconnection pattern) formed on the surface of a semiconductor wafer or a liquid crystal substrate (generally referred to as a substrate). An automated surface inspection apparatus has a substrate mounted on a tiltable stage, irradiates the surface of the substrate with illumination light (unpolarized light) for inspection, to capture the image of the substrate according to the diffracted light (for example, the first order diffracted light) that is emitted from the repetitive pattern on the substrate, and identify a defective portion of the repetitive pattern based on the contrast of the image (for example, refer to Japanese Unexamined Patent Application Publication No. 10-232122). Further, it is also possible for the conventional surface inspection apparatus to perform a defect inspection of repetitive pattern on a substrate, the repetitive pitch of which is different, by adjusting the tilt of a stage.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">However, with the above-mentioned conventional surface inspection apparatus, in principle, when the pitch of repetitive pattern is less than a predetermined value (=(diffraction order)×(wavelength of illumination light)÷2), the diffracted light is not emitted from the repetitive pattern, therefore, a defect inspection cannot be performed. Further, if the repetitive pitch is in the vicinity of the predetermined value, it is difficult to realize a defect inspection with diffracted light by the restriction of the mechanical arrangement of an illumination system and a light detecting system in an apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">There is one way to deal with finer repetition pitch (that is, reduction of the lines and space of such as ab interconnection pattern), and that is to reduce the above-mentioned predetermined value by shortening the wavelength of the illumination light. However, this is not preferable because it leads to limiting the kinds of light source to bulky and expensive ones as well as limiting the material for optical elements constituting the illumination system or the light detecting system to expensive ones.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">An object of the present invention is to provide a surface inspection apparatus and a surface inspection method for securely dealing with finer repetitive pitch without the need to reduce the wavelength of illumination light.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A surface inspection apparatus of the present invention includes an illumination unit which illuminates with linearly polarized light repetitive pattern(s) formed on the surface of a substrate to be inspected, a setting unit which sets, to an oblique angle, an angle between a direction of a vibration plane of the linearly polarized light on the substrate surface and a repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s), and an extraction unit which extracts a polarized light component from light that has been emitted from the repetitive pattern(s) in a specular direction. The polarized light component is perpendicular to the vibration plane of the linearly polarized light</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is preferable that the surface inspection apparatus include a detection unit which detects a defect of the repetitive pattern(s) according to a light intensity of the polarized light component extracted by the extraction unit.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">It is also preferable that the surface inspection apparatus include an image formation unit which forms an image of the substrate to be inspected, using the light extracted by the extraction unit and a detection unit which detects a defect of the repetitive pattern(s).</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">It is also preferable that the setting unit set the angle to an arbitrary value between 30 degrees and 60 degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">It is also preferable that the setting unit set the angle to 45 degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">It is also preferable that the surface inspection apparatus include a substrate support unit which supports the substrate to be inspected and rotates, within the surface, the repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s), and that the detection unit detect a defect of the repetitive pattern(s) according to a state in which the substrate is before and after the substrate support unit rotates the repetition direction by 180 degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Further, the surface inspection method of the present invention includes the steps of illuminating, with linearly polarized light, repetitive pattern(s) formed on the substrate surface to be inspected in a state in which a direction of a vibration plane of the linearly polarized light on the substrate is inclined with respect to a repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s), and detecting a defect of the repetitive pattern(s) according to a light intensity of a polarized light component from the light that has been emitted from the repetitive pattern(s) in the specular direction, the polarized light component being perpendicular to the vibration plane of the linearly polarized light.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">It is preferable that the method include the steps of illuminating, with linearly polarized light, repetitive pattern(s) formed on a surface of a substrate to be inspected in a state in which a direction of a vibration plane of the linearly polarized light on the surface is inclined with respect to a repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s), extracting a polarized light component perpendicular to the vibration plane from light that has been emitted from the repetitive pattern(s) in the specular direction, forming an image of the substrate to be inspected using extracted light, and detecting a defect of the repetitive pattern(s) according to the formed image.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">It is also preferable that the direction of the vibration plane of the linearly polarized light on the substrate surface be inclined at an arbitrary angle between 30 degrees and 60 degrees with respect to a repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s).</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">It is also preferable that the direction of the vibration plane of the linearly polarized light on the substrate surface be inclined at 45 degrees with respect to the repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s).</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">It is also preferable that a defect of the repetitive pattern(s) be detected in a state in which the substrate to be inspected is in before and after the repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s) is rotated by 180 degrees within the surface.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS </heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The nature, principle, and utility of the invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings in which like parts are designated by identical reference numbers, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows an entire configuration of a surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in a first embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an external view of a surface of a semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view showing a corrugation structure of a repetitive pattern <b>22</b>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a diagram showing an inclined state of an incidence plane (<b>3</b>A) of linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5(</figref><i>a</i>) to <b>5</b>(<i>c</i>) are diagrams showing the direction of vibration of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b>;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a diagram showing an inclined state of the direction of vibration plane (V direction) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a diagram showing how light is divided into a polarized light component V<sub>X </sub>parallel to the repetition direction (X direction) and a polarized light component V<sub>Y </sub>perpendicular thereto;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a diagram showing a relationship between the magnitude of a polarized light component L<b>3</b> and a line width D<sub>A </sub>of a line portion <b>2</b>A of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>9</b>(<i>b</i>) are diagrams showing an example of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> where a pitch P is different and the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and a space portion <b>2</b>B is the same;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a diagram showing repetitive patterns <b>25</b> and <b>26</b> whose repetition directions are different;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>11</b>(<i>b</i>) are diagrams showing a relationship between the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> with asymmetric edge shape and the incidence direction of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>12</b>(<i>b</i>) are diagrams showing an entire configuration of a surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> in a second embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 13(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>13</b>(<i>b</i>) are diagrams showing the plane of vibration of a linearly polarized light L<b>5</b> and L<b>6</b>, respectively, and the repetition direction of layers in the form birefringence for a perpendicular incidence;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a diagram showing components parallel to and components perpendicular to the repetition direction of layers;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 15(</figref><i>a</i>) to <b>15</b>(<i>c</i>) are diagrams showing a relationship between refractive index (a), amplitude reflectivity (<i>b</i>), and difference in amplitude reflectivity (<i>c</i>) and thickness t<b>1</b> of a material <b>1</b>;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> is a diagram showing a relationship between a light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> (∝ brightness value of a reflected image) and the inclination angle φ (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>) of the plane of vibration of linearly polarized light; and</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> is a diagram showing an entire configuration of a surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b><i>a </i>in a third embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Embodiments of the present invention are described below in detail with reference to drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">First Embodiment </heading>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in a first embodiment includes, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a stage <b>11</b> that supports a semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> which is a substrate to be inspected, an alignment system <b>12</b>, an illumination system <b>13</b>, a light detecting system <b>14</b>, and an image processing device <b>15</b>. The surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> is an apparatus that automatically performs inspection of the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> during the production process of a semiconductor circuit element. After the resist film on the uppermost layer is exposed and developed, the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is conveyed from a wafer cassette or a development apparatus, not shown, by a conveyer system, also not shown, and adsorbed to the stage <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a plurality of chip regions <b>21</b> is arranged in the X and Y directions on the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> and repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is formed in each chip region <b>21</b>. The repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is a resist pattern (for example, an interconnection pattern) in which a plurality of line portions <b>2</b>A is arranged at a constant pitch P along the width direction as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. A space between neighboring line portions <b>2</b>A is a space portion <b>2</b>B. The direction of arrangement of the line portion <b>2</b>A (X direction) is referred to as “the repetition direction of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>”.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Here, it is assumed that the designed value of a line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is ½ of the pitch P. When the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is formed in accordance with the designed value, the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A becomes equal to a line width D<sub>B </sub>of the space portion <b>2</b>B and the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B is almost 1:1. In contrast to this, if the exposure focus during the process of forming the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> deviates from an proper value, the pitch P remains the same, however, the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A comes to differ from the designed value and therefore, also comes to differ from the line width D<sub>B </sub>of the space portion <b>2</b>B, and the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B deviates from almost 1:1.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment performs a defect inspection of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> by utilizing the change in the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B of the above-mentioned repetitive pattern <b>22</b>. For simplicity of explanation, it is assumed that an ideal volume ratio (designed value) is 1:1. The change in the volume ratio results from the deviation of the exposure focus from a proper value and appears in each shot region of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>. Here, the volume ratio can be referred to in other words as an area ratio of a section shape.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Moreover, in the first embodiment, it is assumed that the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is sufficiently small compared to the wavelength of illumination light (to be described later) for the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>. Because of this, it is unlikely that diffracted light is emitted from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>, therefore, it is not possible to perform a defect inspection of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> using the diffracted light. The principle of the defect inspection in the first embodiment is explained below in order together with the configuration of the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The stage <b>11</b> of the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> mounts the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> on its upper surface and fixes and holds it by, for example, vacuum adsorption. Further, the stage <b>11</b> can be rotated around the normal line <b>1</b>A at the center of the upper surface as an axis. By means of this rotation mechanism, it is possible to rotate the repetition direction (X direction in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> in the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>. Here, the upper surface of the stage <b>11</b> is a horizontal plane and the stage <b>11</b> does not have a tilt mechanism. Because of this, it is possible to keep the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> in a horizontal state at all times.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">When the stage <b>11</b> is rotating, the alignment system <b>12</b> illuminates the outer edge portion of the semiconductor waver <b>20</b>, detects the position in the rotation direction of an outline reference (for example, a notch) provided on the outer edge portion, and stops the stage <b>11</b> at a predetermined position. As a result, it is possible to set the repetition direction of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> (X direction in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> at an inclined angle of 45 degrees with respect to an incident plane <b>3</b>A of illumination light to be described later (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The illumination system <b>13</b> is an eccentric optical system including a light source <b>31</b>, a wavelength selection filter <b>32</b>, a light guide fiber <b>33</b>, a polarization filter <b>34</b>, and a concave reflection mirror <b>35</b>, and the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> on the stage <b>11</b> is illuminated with linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>. The linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> is an illumination light for the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>. The entire surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is irradiated with the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The propagating direction of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> (direction of the main ray of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> that reaches an arbitrary point on the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>) is almost parallel to an optical axis O<b>1</b> of the concave reflection mirror <b>35</b>. The optical axis O<b>1</b> passes through the center of the stage <b>11</b> and is inclined at predetermined angles θ with respect to the normal line <b>1</b>A of the stage <b>11</b>. Incidentally, the plane including the propagating direction of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and parallel to the normal line <b>1</b>A of the stage <b>11</b> is the incident plane of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>. The incident plane <b>3</b>A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an incident plane at the center of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Moreover, in the first embodiment, the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> is the p polarized light. In other words, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>a</i>), the plane including the propagating direction of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and the direction of the vibration of the electric (or magnetic) vector (the plane of vibration of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>) is included in the incident plane (<b>3</b>A) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>. The plane of vibration of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> is defined by the transmission axis of the polarization filter <b>34</b> arranged on the front stage of the concave reflection mirror <b>35</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">By the way, the light source <b>31</b> of the illumination system <b>13</b> is an inexpensive discharge light source such as a metal halide lamp and a mercury lamp. The wavelength selection filter <b>32</b> allows a bright line spectrum having a predetermined wavelength among light from the light source <b>31</b> to pass through selectively. The light guide fiber <b>33</b> transmits light from the wavelength selection filter <b>32</b>. The polarization filter <b>34</b> is arranged in the vicinity of the outgoing end of the light guide fiber <b>33</b> and its transmission axis is set to a predetermined orientation, making light from the light guide fiber <b>33</b> linearly polarized in accordance with this transmission axis. The concave reflection mirror <b>35</b> is a reflection mirror whose reflection surface is an inner surface of a sphere and arranged so that its front focus almost coincides with the outgoing end of the light guide fiber <b>33</b> and its rear focus positions almost coincides with the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>, and guides a light from the polarization filter <b>34</b> to the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>. The illumination system <b>13</b> is a telecentric optical system for the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> side.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In the above-mentioned illumination system <b>13</b>, the light from the light source <b>31</b> passes through the wavelength selection filter <b>32</b>, the light guide fiber <b>33</b>, the polarization filter <b>34</b>, and the concave reflection mirror <b>35</b>, turns into the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> with the p polarization (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>a</i>)) and is incident on the entire surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>. The respective incidence angles of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> at respective points of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> are equal to each other, corresponding to an angle θ formed by the optical axis O<b>1</b> and the normal line <b>1</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In the first embodiment, since the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> incident on the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is the p polarized light (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>a</i>)), when the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is set to 45 degrees with respect to the incident plane (<b>3</b>A) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the angle between the direction (V direction in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6)</figref> of the intersecting line of the plane of vibration and of the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> and the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is also set to 45 degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">In other words, the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> enters the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> in such a manner as to obliquely transverse the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> in a state in which the direction (V direction in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) of the intersecting line of the plane of vibration and of the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is inclined at 45 degrees with respect to the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Such a state of the angle between the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is uniform on the entire surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>. Here, even if 45 degrees are replaced with any one of 135 degrees, 225 degrees, and 315 degrees, the state of the angle between the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> remains the same. Further, the angle formed by the direction of the plane of vibration in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> (V direction) and the repetition direction (X direction) is set to 45 degrees because the sensitivity of the defect inspection of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is made maximum.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Then, when the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is illuminated with the above-mentioned linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>, elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> is emitted from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> in the specular direction (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>b</i>)). In this case, the propagating direction of the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> coincides with the specular direction. The specular direction is a direction included in the incident plane (<b>3</b>A) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and inclined at the angle θ with respect to the normal <b>1</b>A of the stage <b>11</b> (an angle equal to the incidence angle θ of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>). Here, since the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is sufficiently small compared to the illumination wavelength, it is unlikely that diffracted light is emitted from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Here, the reason why the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> turns into an elliptic polarization by the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> and the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> is emitted from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is explained briefly. When the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> is incident on the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>, the direction of the plane of vibration (V direction in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) is divided into two polarized light components V<sub>X </sub>and V<sub>Y </sub>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The polarized light component V<sub>X</sub>, on one hand, is a component parallel to the repetition direction (X repetition). The polarized light component V<sub>Y</sub>, on the other hand, is a component perpendicular to the repetition direction (X direction). Then, the two polarized light components V<sub>X </sub>and V<sub>Y </sub>are subjected to the different amplitude changes and phase changes independently of each other. The amplitude change and the phase change are different because the complex reflectivity (that is, the amplitude reflectivity of a complex number) is different resulting from the anisotropy of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> and is referred to as the form birefringence. As a result, the reflected lights of the two polarized light components V<sub>X </sub>and V<sub>Y </sub>differ in amplitude and phase from each other and the reflected light, which is a combination of the components, becomes the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>b</i>)).</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Further, it is assumed that the degree of ellipseness due to the anisotropy of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is equal to a polarized light component L<b>3</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>c</i>)) perpendicular to the plane of vibration (identical to the incident plane (<b>3</b>A) in the first embodiment) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>a</i>) among the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>b</i>). Then, the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b> depends on the material and the shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> and the angle between the direction of the plane of vibration (V direction) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> and the repetition direction (X direction). Because of this, to keep the angle between the V direction and the X direction to a constant value (45 degrees in the first embodiment), as the shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> changes, the degree of ellipseness (the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b>) changes accordingly even when the material of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is constant.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The relationship between the shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> and the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b> is described below. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the repetitive patterns <b>22</b> have a corrugation shape, in which the line portions <b>2</b>A and the space portions <b>2</b>B are arranged alternately along the X direction and if they are formed in accordance with the designed values with a proper exposure focus, the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A is equal to the line width D<sub>B </sub>of the space portion <b>2</b>B and the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B is almost 1:1. In such a case of the ideal shape, the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b> becomes maximum. In contrast to this, if the exposure focus deviates from the proper value, the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A and the line width D<sub>B </sub>of the space portion <b>2</b>B become different and the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B deviates from almost 1:1. In this case, the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b> becomes smaller compared to that in the ideal case. The change in the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b> is schematically shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. The horizontal axis in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> represents the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">As described above, if the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is illuminated using the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> in a state in which the direction (V direction) of the plane of vibration in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is inclined at 45 degrees with respect to the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>, the degree of ellipseness (the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>c</i>)) of the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>b</i>)) that has been emitted in the specular direction depends on the shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> (the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B) (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8)</figref>. The propagating direction of the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> is included in the incident plane (<b>3</b>A) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and inclined at the angle θ (an angle equal to the incidence angle θ of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>) with respect to the normal line <b>1</b>A of the stage <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Next, the light detecting system <b>14</b> is described. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the light detecting system <b>14</b> is an eccentric optical system including a concave reflection mirror <b>36</b>, an image formation lens <b>37</b>, a polarization filter <b>38</b>, and an image pickup device <b>39</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The concave reflection mirror <b>36</b> is the same reflection mirror as the concave reflection mirror <b>35</b> in the above-mentioned illumination system <b>13</b>, with its optical axis O<b>2</b> passing through the center of the stage <b>11</b> and is arranged so as to be inclined at the angle θ with respect to the normal line <b>1</b>A of the stage <b>11</b>. Therefore, the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> propagates along the optical axis O<b>2</b> of the concave reflection mirror <b>36</b> as a result. The concave reflection mirror <b>36</b> reflects the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> and guides it toward the image formation lens <b>37</b> and condenses it on the image pickup plane of the image pickup device <b>39</b> in cooperation with the image formation lens <b>37</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">However, between the image formation lens <b>37</b> and the concave reflection mirror <b>36</b>, the polarization filter <b>38</b> is arranged. The orientation of the transmission axis of the polarization filter <b>38</b> is set so as to be perpendicular to the transmission axis of the polarization filter <b>34</b> in the above-mentioned illumination system <b>13</b> (the cross Nicol state). Therefore, it is possible for the polarization filter <b>38</b> to extract only a polarized light component L<b>4</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) corresponding to the polarized light component L<b>3</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>c</i>) of the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> and guide it to the image pickup device <b>39</b>. As a result, on the image pickup plane of the image pickup device <b>39</b>, the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> by the polarized light component L<b>4</b> is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The image pickup device <b>39</b> is, for example, a CCD image pickup device, and opto-electrically converts the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> formed on the image pickup plane and outputs an image signal to the image processing device <b>15</b>. The contrast of the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is almost in proportion to the light intensity of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> (the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>c</i>)) and changes in accordance with the shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> (the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B) (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8)</figref>. The reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is brightest when the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> have the ideal shape (the volume ratio is 1:1). Here, the contrast of the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> appears in each shot region.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The image processing device <b>15</b> captures the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> based on the image signal output from the image pickup device <b>39</b>. Incidentally, the image processing device <b>15</b> stores the reflected image of the conforming wafer in advance for comparison. The conforming wafer has the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> of ideal shape (the volume ratio is 1:1) formed on the entire surface. The brightness information of the reflected image of the conforming wafer shows the highest brightness value.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Therefore, after capturing the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>, which is a substrate to be inspected, the image processing device <b>15</b> compares its brightness information with the brightness information of the reflected image of the conforming wafer. Then, based on the amount of drop in the brightness value at a dark portion of the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> (∝ the amount of drop Δ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>), the image processing device <b>15</b> detects defects of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> (the change in the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B). For example, it is only necessary to judge that it is “defective” when the amount of drop in the brightness value is larger than a predetermined threshold value (allowable value) and “normal” when it is smaller than the threshold value.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">By the way, in addition to the configuration in which the reflected image of the conforming wafer is stored in advance as described above, the image processing device <b>15</b> may have a configuration in which arrangement data and the threshold value of the brightness value in the shot region of the wafer are stored in advance.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">In this case, the position of each shot region in the captured reflected image of the wafer is known based on the arrangement data of the shot region, the brightness value in each shot region is found. Then, by comparing the brightness value and the stored threshold value, defects of the patterns are detected. It is only necessary to judge a shot region the brightness value of which is smaller than the threshold value as a defect.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">As described above, according to the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment, the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is illuminated using the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> in a state in which the direction of the plane of vibration (V direction) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is inclined with respect to the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> and at the same time, defects of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> are detected based on the light intensity of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> (the magnitude of the polarized light component L<b>3</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>c</i>)) among the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> that has been emitted in the specular direction, therefore, even if the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is sufficiently small compared to the illumination wavelength, it is possible to securely perform a defect inspection. In other words, it is possible to securely cope with reduction of the repetition pitch without the need to shorten the wavelength of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>, which is the illumination light.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Further, in the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment, the angle formed by the direction (V direction) of the plane of vibration in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> and the repetition direction (X direction) is set to 45 degrees, therefore, it is possible to extract the amount of drop in the brightness value (∝ the amount of drop Δ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>) of the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> with good sensitivity, therefore, it is possible to perform a highly sensitive defect inspection of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Moreover, in the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment, performing the defect inspection of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is not limited to the case where the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is sufficiently small compared to the wavelength of the illumination light, but it is also possible when the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is about the same as the wavelength of the illumination light and even when it is greater than the wavelength of the illumination light. In other words, regardless of the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>, it is possible to perform the defect inspection without fail. This is because the turning into an elliptic polarization of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> due to the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> results from the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> but does not depend on the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Further, in the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment, if the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is the same, the amount of drop in the brightness value (∝ the amount of drop Δ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>) of the reflected image becomes the same. Because of this, regardless of the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>, the detection can be performed with the same sensitivity as long as the amount of change in the volume ratio is the same. For example, as the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9(</figref><i>a</i>) and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9(</figref><i>b</i>), when the pitch P is different and the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B is the same, it is possible to perform a defect inspection with the same sensitivity. As can be seen from the comparison in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9(</figref><i>a</i>) and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9(</figref><i>b</i>), the smaller the pitch P is; the smaller change in shape (the amount of deviation δ of the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A from the designed value) can be detected securely.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">In the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment, even when the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is different, it is possible to perform inspection while maintaining the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> in a horizontal state (without performing the conventional tilt adjustment of the stage), it is possible to securely reduce the preparation time before a defect inspection actually begins (that is, the time until the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is captured) and therefore improve the operation efficiency.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Further, in the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment, the stage <b>11</b> does not have the tilt mechanism, therefore, the device configuration can be simplified. In addition, an inexpensive discharge light source can be used as the light source <b>31</b> of the illumination system <b>13</b>, therefore, the total configuration of the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> becomes inexpensive and simple.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Moreover, for the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment, it is possible to easily perform a defect inspection of all of the repetitive patterns, even when a plurality of kinds of repetitive patterns is formed on the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> and the repetitive patterns different in the pitch P or the repetition direction (X direction) are present mixedly, by capturing the reflected image of the entire surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> and investigating the amount of drop in the brightness value at each portion. Note that, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the repetitive patterns different in the repetition direction are repetitive patterns <b>25</b> in the zero-degree direction and repetitive patterns <b>26</b> in the 90-degree direction. These repetitive patterns <b>25</b> and <b>26</b> differ 90 degrees from each other in the repetition direction (X direction). However, the angle formed by the repetition direction (X direction) and the direction of the plane of vibration (V direction) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> is 45 degrees, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Furthermore, for the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in the first embodiment, it is also possible to obtain defect information relating to the asymmetry of the edge shape of the line portion <b>2</b>A of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> (for example, the directivity of collapse of the edge shape) because the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> is made incident obliquely with respect to the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). To this end, it becomes necessary to rotate by 180 degrees the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> by the stage <b>11</b>, capture the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> in the states before and after the rotation, and investigate the difference in the brightness at the same portion.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> schematically shows the relationship between the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> the edge shape of which is asymmetric and the incidence direction of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>. For example, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11(</figref><i>a</i>) shows a state before the 180-degree rotation and the illumination light is made incident through the edge (E<sub>1</sub>) side that has collapsed between the edges E<sub>1 </sub>and E<sub>2 </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11(</figref><i>b</i>) shows a state after the 180-degree rotation and the illumination light is made to enter through the edge (E<sub>2</sub>) side that has not collapsed between the two edges E<sub>1 </sub>and E<sub>2</sub>. Then, the brightness value of the reflected image captured in each state reflects the edge shape of the edges E<sub>1 </sub>and E<sub>2 </sub>in the incidence direction and in this example, the brightness value of the reflected image is larger in the case shown in FIG. <b>11</b>(<i>a</i>). Therefore, by investigating the difference in the brightness of the reflected image before and after rotated by 180 degrees, the asymmetry of the edge shape of the line portion <b>2</b>A is known. It may also be possible to perform a defect inspection by combining the reflected images before and after 180-degree rotation.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">Note that as in the first embodiment, when the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> is made incident obliquely with respect to the surface of the semiconductor waver <b>20</b> (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the incidence angle θ), to be strict, the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>b</i>)) that is emitted from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> rotates slightly with its propagating direction as an axis. Because of this, it is preferable to fine-adjust the orientation of the transmission axis of the polarization filter <b>38</b> in the light detecting system <b>14</b> taking this rotation angle into consideration. In the state after fine adjustment, the orientation of the transmission axis of the polarization filters <b>34</b> and <b>38</b> is no longer 90 degrees accurately, however, such an angle also belongs to the category of “perpendicular (or orthogonal)” and the state can be said as the cross Nicol state. It is possible to improve the inspection precision by fine-adjusting the orientation of the transmission axis of the polarization filter <b>38</b>. As one example of the fine adjustment method is to capture an image by reflecting the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> on the surface without repetitive patterns and to rotate the orientation of the transmission axis of the polarization filter <b>38</b> so that the brightness value of the image is to be minimum.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Moreover, in the above-mentioned first embodiment, an example in which the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> is the p polarized light is described, however, the present invention is not limited to this. Instead of the p polarized light, an s polarized light may be used. The s polarized light is linearly polarized light whose plane of vibration is perpendicular to the incident plane. Because of this, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, when the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is set to an angle of 45 degrees with respect to the incident plane (<b>3</b>A) of the s polarized light, which is the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>, the angle between the direction of the intersecting line of the plane of vibration of the s polarized light and of the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> and the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is also set to 45 degrees. Incidentally, the p polarized light has an advantage in acquiring defect information relating to the edge shape of the line portion <b>2</b>A of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>. The s polarized light efficiently extracts defect information about the surface of the semiconductor waver <b>20</b> and is advantageous in improving the SN ratio.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">Furthermore, not limited to the p polarized light or s polarized light, but linearly polarized light whose plane of vibration has an arbitrary inclination with respect to the incident plane may be accepted. In this case, it is preferable to set the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> to an angle other than 45 degrees with respect to the incident plane of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and set the angle between the direction of the intersecting line of the plane of vibration of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and of the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> and the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern 22 to 45 degrees.</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">Second Embodiment </heading>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">Here, a surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> including an illumination system (<b>41</b> to <b>46</b>) and a light detecting system (<b>45</b> to <b>49</b>) shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12(</figref><i>a</i>) instead of the illumination system <b>13</b> and the light detecting system <b>14</b> of the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1)</figref> in the first embodiment is described. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12(</figref><i>a</i>), the stage <b>11</b>, the alignment system <b>12</b>, and the image processing device <b>15</b> similar to those in the first embodiment are not shown schematically. The surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> is also an apparatus that automatically performs inspection of the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> in the production process of a semiconductor circuit device.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">The illumination system (<b>41</b> to <b>46</b>) and the light detecting system (<b>45</b> to <b>49</b>) of the surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> in the second embodiment are described. The illumination system (<b>41</b> to <b>46</b>) includes a light source <b>41</b>, a wavelength selection filter <b>42</b>, a relay lens <b>43</b>, an aperture diaphragm <b>44</b>, a polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b>, and a lens <b>46</b>. Among these, the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> and the lens <b>46</b> function also as a part of the light detecting system (<b>45</b> to <b>49</b>). The light detecting system (<b>45</b> to <b>49</b>) includes an aperture diaphragm <b>47</b>, an image formation lens <b>48</b>, and an image pickup device <b>49</b>, in addition to the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> and the lens <b>46</b>. An optical axis O<b>3</b> of the lens <b>46</b> coincides with the normal line <b>1</b>A of the stage <b>11</b> (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> is one provided with the lens <b>46</b> instead of the concave reflection mirrors <b>35</b> and <b>36</b> of the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, which has both the functions thereof, and with the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> instead of the polarization filters <b>34</b> and <b>38</b> of the surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b>, which has both the functions thereof. As described above, the optical elements (<b>45</b>, <b>46</b>) of the illumination system (<b>41</b> to <b>46</b>) and the light detecting system (<b>45</b> to <b>49</b>) are made common, therefore, the number of parts can be reduced and the configuration can be simplified.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Here, the light source <b>41</b>, the wavelength selection filter <b>42</b>, the image formation lens <b>48</b>, and the image pickup device <b>49</b> are the same as the above-mentioned light source <b>31</b>, the wavelength selection filter <b>32</b>, the image formation lens <b>37</b>, and the image pickup device <b>39</b>. The aperture diaphragms <b>44</b> and <b>47</b> are arranged in the vicinity of the focus of the lens <b>46</b>. The aperture diaphragm <b>47</b> is an optical element for shielding stray light. The polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> reflects only linearly polarized light whose plane of vibration is perpendicular to the surface of the paper and allows only linearly polarized light whose plane of vibration is parallel to the surface of the paper to pass through. In other words, the reflection axis and the transmission axis of the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> are perpendicular to each other with respect to the orientation (the cross Nicol state).</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">In the illumination system (<b>41</b> to <b>46</b>), light from the light source <b>41</b> enters the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> via the wavelength selection filter <b>42</b>, the relay lens <b>43</b>, and the aperture diaphragm <b>44</b> and the light reflected therefrom (that is, the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> whose plane of vibration is perpendicular to the surface of the paper) is guided to the lens <b>46</b>. Then, after passing through the lens <b>46</b>, the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> from the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> incidents perpendicularly on the entire surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>. In the case of perpendicular incidence, the incident plane of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> cannot be defined. The direction of an intersecting line of a plane of vibration of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and of the surface of the semiconductor waver <b>20</b> is shown as “V direction” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12(</figref><i>b</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">The semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is set so that the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is inclined at 45 degrees with respect to the direction of the plane of vibration of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> (V direction) by the stage <b>11</b> and the alignment system <b>12</b> as those in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The angle formed by the V direction and the X direction is set to 45 degrees in an attempt to maximize the sensitivity of the defect inspection of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>. Such a state of the angle between the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> and the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is uniform on the entire surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">Then, when the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is illuminated with the above-mentioned linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>, an elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> is emitted from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> in the specular direction (in the direction of the optical axis O<b>3</b>). The reason for turning into an elliptic polarization is the same as that in the first embodiment and in the case of perpendicular incidence, the phase change is the same between the polarized light component V<sub>X </sub>parallel to the repetition direction (X direction) and the polarized light component V<sub>Y </sub>(<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>) perpendicular thereto. In other words, the polarized light components V<sub>X </sub>and V<sub>Y </sub>are subjected to different amplitude changes independently of each other. Because of this, the reflected light of the polarized light components V<sub>X </sub>and V<sub>Y </sub>differ in amplitude and the reflected light, which is a combination of these components, becomes the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b>. Incidentally, the form birefringence in the case of perpendicular incidence corresponds to the fact that the amplitude reflectivity differs resulting from the anisotropy of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">The elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is condensed again by the lens <b>46</b> and after passing through the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b>, the aperture diaphragm <b>47</b>, and the image formation lens <b>48</b>, it is condensed on the image pickup plane of the image pickup device <b>49</b>. The polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> extracts only the polarized light component L<b>4</b> perpendicular to the plane of vibration (parallel to the surface of the paper) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> among the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> and guides it to the image pickup device <b>49</b>. On the image pickup plane of the image pickup device <b>49</b>, a reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> by the polarized light component L<b>4</b> is formed. The contrast of the reflected image is almost proportional to the light intensity of the polarized light component L<b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">The light intensity of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> changes in accordance with the shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> (the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B) (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>). However, it is assumed that angle between the direction of the plane of vibration of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> (V direction) and the repetition direction (X direction) is kept to a constant value (45 degrees in the second embodiment) and the material property of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is constant. The light intensity of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> is maximum when the shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is ideal (the volume ratio is 1:1).</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">Here, the form birefringence (the difference in the amplitude reflectivity resulting from the anisotropy of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>) in the case of perpendicular incidence is described and the relationship between the shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> and the light intensity of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> is described. For this description, the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is modeled. In other words, it is assumed that a plurality of layers composed of a substance <b>1</b> with thickness t<sub>1 </sub>and dielectric constant ∈<sub>1 </sub>and a substance <b>2</b> with thickness t<sub>2 </sub>and dielectric constant ∈<sub>2 </sub>are arranged on a plane with a sufficiently short repetition period compared to the illumination wavelength.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13(</figref><i>a</i>), when the layer is irradiated with linearly polarized light L<b>5</b> whose plane of vibration is parallel to the repetition direction of the layer, an electric field is applied so as to traverse the layer, and then small polarization occurs in accordance with the electric field. In other words, each layer generates polarization in series for the electric field. The apparent dielectric constant ∈<sub>X </sub>in this case can be expressed by the following expression (1). Then, in the case of perpendicular incidence, the amplitude reflectivity r<sub>X </sub>in the substance with dielectric constant ∈<sub>X </sub>can be expressed by the following expression (2).</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>ɛ</mi>
          <mi>X</mi>
        </msub>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mfrac>
          <mrow>
            <mrow>
              <mo>(</mo>
              <mrow>
                <msub>
                  <mi>t</mi>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </msub>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <msub>
                  <mi>t</mi>
                  <mn>2</mn>
                </msub>
              </mrow>
              <mo>)</mo>
            </mrow>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <msub>
              <mi>ɛ</mi>
              <mn>1</mn>
            </msub>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <msub>
              <mi>ɛ</mi>
              <mn>2</mn>
            </msub>
          </mrow>
          <mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>t</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>⁢</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>ɛ</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
            <mo>+</mo>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>t</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>⁢</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>ɛ</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
          </mrow>
        </mfrac>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>r</mi>
          <mi>X</mi>
        </msub>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow>
              <msqrt>
                <msub>
                  <mi>ɛ</mi>
                  <mi>X</mi>
                </msub>
              </msqrt>
              <mo>-</mo>
              <mn>1</mn>
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msqrt>
                <msub>
                  <mi>ɛ</mi>
                  <mi>X</mi>
                </msub>
              </msqrt>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <mn>1</mn>
            </mrow>
          </mfrac>
          <mo>=</mo>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow>
              <msqrt>
                <mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <mo>(</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>t</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </msub>
                      <mo>+</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>t</mi>
                        <mn>2</mn>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>)</mo>
                  </mrow>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>ɛ</mi>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </msub>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>ɛ</mi>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
              </msqrt>
              <mo>-</mo>
              <msqrt>
                <mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>t</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>ɛ</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>t</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>ɛ</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
              </msqrt>
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msqrt>
                <mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <mo>(</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>t</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                      </msub>
                      <mo>+</mo>
                      <msub>
                        <mi>t</mi>
                        <mn>2</mn>
                      </msub>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>)</mo>
                  </mrow>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>ɛ</mi>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </msub>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>ɛ</mi>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
              </msqrt>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msqrt>
                <mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>t</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>ɛ</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>t</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>ɛ</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
              </msqrt>
            </mrow>
          </mfrac>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>2</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13(</figref><i>b</i>), when the layer is irradiated with linearly polarized light L<b>6</b> whose plane of vibration is perpendicular to the repetition direction of the layer, an electric field is applied along the lengthwise direction of the layer, and then polarization occurs in accordance with the electric field. When viewed from the electric field, the polarization in each layer is arranged in parallel. The apparent dielectric constant ∈<sub>Y </sub>in this case is a weighted average of the layer thickness (t<sub>1</sub>+t<sub>2</sub>) and can be expressed by the following expression (3). Then, in the case of perpendicular incidence, the amplitude reflectivity r<sub>Y </sub>in the substance with dielectric constant ∈<sub>Y </sub>can be expressed by the following expression (4).</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">
<maths id="MATH-US-00002" num="00002">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>ɛ</mi>
          <mi>Y</mi>
        </msub>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mfrac>
          <mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>t</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>⁢</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>ɛ</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
            <mo>+</mo>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>t</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>⁢</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>ɛ</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
          </mrow>
          <mrow>
            <msub>
              <mi>t</mi>
              <mn>1</mn>
            </msub>
            <mo>+</mo>
            <msub>
              <mi>t</mi>
              <mn>2</mn>
            </msub>
          </mrow>
        </mfrac>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>3</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>r</mi>
          <mi>Y</mi>
        </msub>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow>
              <msqrt>
                <msub>
                  <mi>ɛ</mi>
                  <mi>Y</mi>
                </msub>
              </msqrt>
              <mo>-</mo>
              <mn>1</mn>
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msqrt>
                <msub>
                  <mi>ɛ</mi>
                  <mi>Y</mi>
                </msub>
              </msqrt>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <mn>1</mn>
            </mrow>
          </mfrac>
          <mo>=</mo>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow>
              <msqrt>
                <mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>t</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>ɛ</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>t</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>ɛ</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
              </msqrt>
              <mo>-</mo>
              <msqrt>
                <mrow>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>t</mi>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </msub>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>t</mi>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
              </msqrt>
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msqrt>
                <mrow>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>t</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>ɛ</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>t</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>ɛ</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                  </mrow>
                </mrow>
              </msqrt>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msqrt>
                <mrow>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>t</mi>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </msub>
                  <mo>+</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>t</mi>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
              </msqrt>
            </mrow>
          </mfrac>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>4</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">As described above, when the directions of the plane of vibration of the linearly polarized lights L<b>5</b> and L<b>6</b> that enter perpendicularly (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>) are different, the apparent dielectric constants ∈<sub>X </sub>and ∈<sub>Y </sub>differ (expressions (1) and (3)), therefore, as a result, the amplitude reflectivities r<sub>X </sub>and r<sub>Y </sub>also differ (expressions (2) and (4)). The difference (r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>Y</sub>) between the amplitude reflectivities r<sub>X </sub>and r<sub>Y </sub>is considered as the form birefringence in the case of perpendicular incidence.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>, a case is considered where the plane of vibration of linearly polarized light is inclined at an angle φ with respect to the repetition direction of the layer. It is assumed that the amplitude of the linearly polarized light when it is incident on the layer is E. The linearly polarized light incident on the layer is divided into a component parallel to the repetition direction of the layer (the amplitude is E cos φ) and a component perpendicular to the repetition direction (the amplitude is E sin φ) and they are respectively subjected to the amplitude change in accordance with the above-mentioned amplitude reflectivities r<sub>X </sub>and r<sub>Y </sub>independently of each other. Because of this, the amplitude E<sub>X </sub>of the reflected light of the component parallel to the repetition direction and the amplitude E<sub>Y </sub>of the reflected light of the component perpendicular to the repetition direction are expressed by the following expressions (5) and (6). Then, the reflected light, which is a combination of the respective components whose amplitude are E<sub>X </sub>and E<sub>Y</sub>, becomes the elliptically polarized light.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>E</i><sub>X</sub><i>=r</i><sub>X</sub><i>E </i>cosφ  (5)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>E</i><sub>Y</sub><i>=r</i><sub>Y</sub><i>E </i>sinφ  (6)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">Then, among the elliptically polarized light, the component perpendicular to the plane of vibration of the incident light passes through the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12(</figref><i>a</i>) and becomes the polarized light component L<b>4</b> directed toward the image pickup device <b>49</b>. The amplitude E<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> is expressed as the following expression (7) using the amplitudes E<sub>X </sub>and E<sub>Y </sub>in the expressions (5) and (6). By the way, the amplitude E<sub>C </sub>of the component parallel to the plane of vibration of the incident light (the component cut by the polarized light beam splitter <b>45</b>) is expressed by the following expression (8).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>E</i><sub>L4</sub><i>=E</i><sub>X </sub>sinφ+<i>E</i><sub>Y </sub>cosφ=0.5 <i>E </i>(<i>r</i><sub>X</sub><i>−r</i><sub>Y</sub>) sin 2φ  (7)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>E</i><sub>C</sub><i>=E</i><sub>X </sub>cosφ+<i>E</i><sub>Y </sub>sinφ=<i>E </i>(<i>r</i><sub>X </sub>cos<sup>2</sup><i>φ+r</i><sub>Y </sub>sin<sup>2</sup>φ)   (8)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">Further, the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> having the amplitude E<sub>L4 </sub>in the expression (7) can be expressed by the following expression (9). As can be seen from the expression (9), the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> is the product of the component relating to the form birefringence (the difference (r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>Y</sub>) in the amplitude reflectivity) in the case of perpendicular incidence and the component relating to the inclination angle φ (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>) with respect to the repetition direction of the plane of vibration of the linearly polarized light. Further, when the inclination angle φ of the plane of vibration is constant, the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> depends only on the component relating to the form birefringence (the difference (r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>Y</sub>) in the amplitude reflectivity).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>I</i><sub>L4</sub>=(<i>E</i><sub>L4</sub>)<sup>2</sup>=0.25<i>E</i><sup>2</sup>(<i>r</i><sub>X</sub><i>−r</i><sub>Y</sub>)<sup>2 </sup>sin<sup>2</sup>2φ  (9)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">Next, an evaluation on the form birefringence (the difference (r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>Y</sub>) in the amplitude reflectivity) in the expression (9) is described. For this evaluation, it is assumed that the substance <b>1</b> is a resist (dielectric constant ∈<sub>1</sub>=2.43), the substance <b>2</b> is air (dielectric constant ∈<sub>2</sub>=1), and the thickness (t<sub>1</sub>+t<sub>2</sub>) of the layers is 100 nm.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">In this case, the substance <b>1</b> corresponds to the line portion <b>2</b>A of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> and the thickness t<sub>1 </sub>of the substance <b>1</b> corresponds to the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). The substance <b>2</b> corresponds to the space portion <b>2</b>B and the thickness t<sub>2 </sub>of the substance <b>2</b> corresponds to the line width D<sub>B </sub>of the space portion <b>2</b>B. Also, the thickness (t<sub>1</sub>+t<sub>2</sub>) of the layers corresponds to the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">The dependence of the apparent refractive index n<sub>X</sub>=√∈<sub>X </sub>of the polarized light component parallel to the repetition direction of the layer and the apparent refractive index n<sub>Y</sub>=√∈<sub>Y </sub>of the polarized light component perpendicular to the repetition direction on the thickness t<sub>1 </sub>of the substance <b>1</b> (the line width D<sub>A</sub>) are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15(</figref><i>a</i>). Further, the dependence of the amplitude reflectivity r<sub>X </sub>of the parallel polarized light component and amplitude reflectivity r<sub>Y </sub>of the perpendicular polarized light component on the thickness t<sub>1 </sub>of the substance <b>1</b> (the line width D<sub>A</sub>) are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15(</figref><i>b</i>). Furthermore, the relationship between the form birefringence (the difference (r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>Y</sub>) in the amplitude reflectivity) and the thickness t<sub>1 </sub>of the substance <b>1</b> (the line width D<sub>A</sub>) is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15(</figref><i>c</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">As can be seen from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15(</figref><i>c</i>), when the thickness t<sub>1 </sub>of the substance <b>1</b> is 50 nm, that is, the thickness t<sub>1 </sub>of the substance <b>1</b> is equal to the thickness t<sub>2 </sub>of the substance <b>2</b>, the absolute value of the form birefringence (the difference (r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>Y</sub>) in the amplitude reflectivity) becomes maximum. Then, as can be seen from the expression (9), when the inclination angle φ of the plane of vibration is constant (45 degrees in the second embodiment), the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> becomes maximum when the form birefringence is maximum, that is, the thickness t<sub>1 </sub>of the substance <b>1</b> is equal to the thickness t<sub>2 </sub>of the substance <b>2</b>. Further, when the thickness t<sub>1 </sub>of the substance <b>1</b> changes and the magnitude of the form birefringence in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15(</figref><i>c</i>) changes, the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> also changes accordingly (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8)</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">Therefore, in the surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> in the second embodiment, when the image processing device <b>15</b> not shown captures the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> based on the image signal from the image pickup device <b>49</b>, it compares the brightness information (∝ the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b>) with the brightness information of the reflected image of the conforming wafer. Then, based on the amount of drop in the brightness value (∝ the amount of drop Δ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>) at a dark portion of the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>, defects of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> (the change in the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B) are detected. For example, it is only necessary to judge that it is “defective” when the amount of drop in the brightness value is larger than a predetermined threshold value and “normal” when it is smaller than the threshold value.</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0100">As described above, according to the surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> in the second embodiment, the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is illuminated using the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> in a state in which the direction of the plane of vibration (V direction) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is inclined with respect to the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> and at the same time, defects of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is detected based on the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> among the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> that has been emitted in the specular direction, therefore, even if the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is sufficiently small compared to the illumination wavelength, it is possible to securely perform a defect inspection. In other words, it is possible to securely cope with reduction of the repetition pitch without the need to shorten the wavelength of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>, which is the illumination light.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0101">Further, in the surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> in the second embodiment, the angle formed by the direction (V direction) of the plane of vibration in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> and the repetition direction (X direction) is set to 45 degrees, therefore, it is possible to perform a defect inspection of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> with high sensitivity. This point is apparent also from the above-mentioned expression (9). Here, the relationship between the light intensity I<sub>L4</sub>(∝ brightness value of the reflected image) and the inclination angle φ (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>) of the plane of vibration of linearly polarized light in the expression (9) is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>. It is assumed that the form birefringence (r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>Y</sub>) is the constant value of the conforming patterns. As can be seen from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>, the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>of the polarized light component L<b>4</b> takes the maximum value (=0.25 E<sup>2 </sup>(r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>Y</sub>)<sup>2</sup>) when the inclination angle φ is 45 degrees. Because of this, it is possible to extract the amount of drop in the brightness value of the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> (∝ the amount of drop Δ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>) with good sensitivity and a highly sensitive defect inspection becomes possible. Here, the vertical axis in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> assumes that the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>when the inclination angle φ is 45 degrees (maximum value) is 100%.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0102">Here, the allowable error of the inclination angle φ is considered. In order to detect without fail a line width change of 10% of the line portion <b>2</b>A of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>, it is necessary for the error Δφ of the inclination angle φ to satisfy the following expression (10). The expression (10) is the condition that the amount of change in the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>(Δ(r<sub>X</sub>−r<sub>1</sub>)<sup>2</sup>, the amount of drop in the brightness value of the reflected image) resulting from the line width change of 10% exceeds the amount of change in the light intensity I<sub>L4 </sub>(sin<sup>2 </sup>2Δφ) resulting from the error Δφ of the inclination angle φ. For example, when the dielectric constant of the resist of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is 2.43 and the pitch P is 100 nm, in order to detect the line width change of 10% (that is, 5 nm) of the line portion <b>2</b>A, it is only necessary to suppress the error Δφ of the inclination angle φ below 3.37 degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0103">
<maths id="MATH-US-00003" num="00003">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mfrac>
          <msup>
            <mrow>
              <mi>Δ</mi>
              <mo>⁡</mo>
              <mrow>
                <mo>(</mo>
                <mrow>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>r</mi>
                    <mi>X</mi>
                  </msub>
                  <mo>-</mo>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>r</mi>
                    <mi>Y</mi>
                  </msub>
                </mrow>
                <mo>)</mo>
              </mrow>
            </mrow>
            <mn>2</mn>
          </msup>
          <msup>
            <mrow>
              <mo>(</mo>
              <mrow>
                <msub>
                  <mi>r</mi>
                  <mi>X</mi>
                </msub>
                <mo>-</mo>
                <msub>
                  <mi>r</mi>
                  <mi>Y</mi>
                </msub>
              </mrow>
              <mo>)</mo>
            </mrow>
            <mn>2</mn>
          </msup>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>≧</mo>
        <mfrac>
          <mrow>
            <mn>1</mn>
            <mo>-</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mi>cos</mi>
              <mo>⁡</mo>
              <mrow>
                <mo>(</mo>
                <mrow>
                  <mn>4</mn>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <mi>Δ</mi>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <mstyle>
                    <mspace width="0.3em" height="0.3ex"/>
                  </mstyle>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <mi>ϕ</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mo>)</mo>
              </mrow>
            </mrow>
          </mrow>
          <mn>2</mn>
        </mfrac>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>10</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0104">Moreover, from the surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> in the second embodiment, the following effects [1], [2], and [3] can be obtained, which are the same as those in the above-mentioned first embodiment. [1] Regardless of the pitch P of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>, a defect inspection can be performed securely. [2] For example, when the pitches P are different and the volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B is the same, as in the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9(</figref><i>a</i>) and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9(</figref><i>b</i>), a defect inspection can be performed with the same sensitivity. [3] The smaller the pitch P is, the finer change in shape (the amount of deviation δ from the designed value of the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A) can be detected securely. These points are apparent from the expression obtained by substituting the expressions (2) and (4) in the above-mentioned expression (9).</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0105">Furthermore, from the surface inspection apparatus <b>40</b> in the second embodiment, the following effects [4] to [6] can be obtained same as from the above-mentioned first embodiment. [4] The preparation time before a defect inspection actually begins (that is, the time until the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is captured) can be reduced securely and therefore the operation efficiency is improved. [5] The stage <b>11</b> does not have the tilt mechanism and the light source <b>41</b> is an inexpensive discharge light source, therefore, the apparatus configuration is simplified. [6] Even when repetitive patterns different in the pitch P and in the repetition direction (X direction) are present mixedly, a defect inspection of all of the repetitive patterns can be performed totally and simply.</p>
<heading id="h-0009" level="1">Third Embodiment </heading>
<p id="p-0107" num="0106">In the configuration in the first embodiment, the light detecting system <b>14</b> obtains the image signal by condensing the reflected light from the wafer <b>20</b> into an image on the image pickup plane of the image pickup device <b>39</b> thereby a defect inspection is performed, however, in the present embodiment, an observer performs an inspection visually by seeing the reflected light from the wafer <b>20</b> with his/her eyes.</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0107"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> is a diagram showing the configuration of a surface inspection apparatus <b>10</b><i>a </i>according to the third embodiment. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>, the members with the same symbols as those in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> are the same members as those in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In other words, the configuration of the stage <b>11</b> and the illumination system <b>13</b> is the same as that in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (the first embodiment). Then, as in the first embodiment, the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is set to an angle of 45 degrees with respect to the incident plane (<b>3</b>A) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0108">A polarization filter <b>50</b> is arranged on the optical path of the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b> from the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> on the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b>. The orientation of the transmission axis of the polarization filter <b>50</b> is set so as to be perpendicular to the transmission axis of the polarization filter <b>34</b> in the illumination system <b>13</b> (the cross Nicol state), as in the polarization filter <b>38</b> in the first embodiment. Therefore, it is possible to extract only the polarized light component L<b>4</b> corresponding to the polarized light component L<b>3</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5(</figref><i>c</i>) of the elliptically polarized light L<b>2</b>. The polarized light component L<b>4</b> thus extracted enters eyes <b>51</b> of an observer and is observed by the observer.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0109">Incidentally, it is preferable for the polarization filter <b>50</b> to have a size with which the entire image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> can be seen through the polarization filter <b>50</b> by the observer.</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0110">The observer checks the brightness at each portion of the image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> through the polarization filter <b>50</b> and detects defects of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> based on the amount of drop in the brightness.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0111">According to the third embodiment described above, the same effects as those described in the first embodiment can be obtained.</p>
<heading id="h-0010" level="1">MODIFICATION EXAMPLES </heading>
<p id="p-0113" num="0112">By the way, in the embodiments described above, the angle (the inclination angle φ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>) formed by the direction of the plane of vibration (V direction) of the linearly polarized light L<b>1</b> on the surface of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> and the repetition direction (X direction) of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is set to 45 degrees, however, the present invention is not limited to this. As can be seen from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> already described, when the inclination angle φ is set to 45 degrees±15 degrees, the brightness drops by about 70% and when 45 degrees±20 degrees, the brightness drops by about 55%. In other words, when the inclination angle φ is in a range from 30 degrees to 60 degrees, more than 70% of the brightness value when the angle is set to 45 degrees can be secured, therefore, it is possible to perform the same defect inspection as that described above. Further, the rate of drop in the brightness value due to the change in shape at the time of defocus (for example, 50% etc.) is constant regardless of the inclination angle φ. Therefore, the amount of drop in the brightness value at the time of defocus (the difference in the brightness from that at the time of focus) becomes smaller as the inclination angle φ further deviates from 45 degrees. However, if the inclination angle φ is in a range from 30 degrees to 60 degrees, an inspection can be performed sufficiently. In an actual operation, it is much preferable for the inclination angle φ to be in a range from 35 degrees to 55 degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0113">Moreover, the embodiments above has described a case in which the amount of drop in the brightness value of the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is obtained using the brightness value of the reflected image of the conforming wafer as a reference, to detect a detect of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>, however, the present invention is not limited thereto. Since the arrangement of the repetitive patterns in each chip region <b>21</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is the same, it may also be possible to identify the chip region of the conforming product or the shot region of the conforming product and perform a defect inspection with the brightness value as a reference. In this case, it is no longer necessary to manufacture a dedicated wafer the entire surface of which is conforming. In addition, it may also be possible to compare with the brightness value of a limit sample. Further, it may also be possible to determine the reference of the brightness value by simulation and perform a defect detection of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> by comparison with the reference value.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0114">Furthermore the embodiments above has described a case where the designed value of the line width D<sub>A </sub>of the line portion <b>2</b>A of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b> is set to ½ of the pitch P (the ideal volume ratio between the line portion <b>2</b>A and the space portion <b>2</b>B is set to 1:1), however, the present invention is not limited thereto. The present invention is applicable when the ideal volume ratio is not 1:1. In this case, the brightness value of the reflected image of the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> may increase depending on the change in shape of the repetitive pattern <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0116" num="0115">In addition, the embodiments above has described a case where the semiconductor wafer <b>20</b> is a substrate to be inspected, however, the present invention is not limited thereto. The present invention can be applied to defect inspection on a liquid crystal substrate (a substrate to be inspected) in the production process of a liquid crystal display device. Further, the same effects is obtainable not only in defect detection processing by the image processing device <b>15</b> of the surface inspection apparatus, but also in that by an external computer connected to the surface inspection apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0117" num="0116">Further, the embodiments above have employed a two-dimensional sensor such as a CCD as the image pickup device <b>39</b>, however, a one-dimensional sensor may be used. In this case, the entire image of a semiconductor wafer (or a liquid crystal substrate) may be captured by relatively moving the one-dimensional sensor an image pickup device and a stage that mounts thereon the semiconductor wafer (or the liquid crystal substrate) as a substrate to be inspected, and causing the one-dimensional sensor to scan the entire surface of the semiconductor wafer (or the liquid crystal substrate).</p>
<p id="p-0118" num="0117">The invention is not limited to the above embodiments and various modifications may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. Any improvement may be made in part or all of the components.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07298471-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="16.26mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298471-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00002" nb-file="US07298471-20071120-M00002.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00002" he="15.92mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298471-20071120-M00002.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00003" nb-file="US07298471-20071120-M00003.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00003" he="7.45mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298471-20071120-M00003.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is: </us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A surface inspection apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>an illumination unit which illuminates a surface of a substrate to be inspected with linearly polarized light;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a setting unit which sets a direction of a vibration plane of said linearly polarized light on the surface of the substrate to be inspected such that the direction of the vibration plane is neither parallel to nor orthogonal to a repetition direction of repetitive pattern(s) formed on said surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an imaging unit which captures an image of the surface of the substrate to be inspected, using a polarized light component of light that has been reflected from said repetitive pattern(s), to generate image data for two different directions, the polarized light component being perpendicular to the vibration plane of said linearly polarized light; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detection unit which detects a defect of said repetitive pattern(s) according to said image data.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The surface inspection apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>a detection unit detects a defect of said repetitive pattern(s) by comparing image data on a conforming substrate stored in advance and the image data generated by said imaging unit, the conforming substrate having ideal repetitive patterns formed thereon.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The surface inspection apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>a detection unit determines a region of said image data as a defect when a brightness value of the region is smaller than a predetermined threshold value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The surface inspection apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said setting unit sets an angle between the direction of the vibration plane of said linearly polarized light on the surface of the substrate to be inspected and the repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s) formed on said surface to an arbitrary value between 30 degrees and 60 degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The surface inspection apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said setting unit sets the angle between the direction of the vibration plane of said linearly polarized light on the surface of the substrate to be inspected and the repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s) formed on said surface to 45 degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The surface inspection apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said setting unit sets the direction of the vibration plane of said linearly polarized light on the surface of the substrate to be inspected and the repetition direction of the repetitive pattern(s) formed on said surface to be diagonal, by supporting said substrate to be inspected and rotating said substrate to be inspected within said surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said detection unit detects a defect of said repetitive pattern(s) according to a state in which said substrate is before and after said setting unit rotates the repetition direction by 180 degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A surface inspection method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>illuminating, with linearly polarized light, repetitive pattern(s) formed on a surface of a substrate to be inspected in a state in which a direction of a vibration plane of the linearly polarized light on the surface is neither parallel to nor orthogonal to a repetition direction of said repetitive pattern(s);</claim-text>
<claim-text>capturing an image of the surface of the substrate to be inspected using a polarized light component of light that has been reflected from said repetitive pattern(s), to generate image data for two different directions, the polarized light component being perpendicular to the vibration plane of said linearly polarized light; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>detecting a defect of said repetitive pattern(s) according to the image data.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The surface inspection method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the direction of the vibration plane of said linearly polarized light on said surface is inclined at an arbitrary angle between 30 degrees and 60 degrees with respect to a repetition direction of said repetitive pattern(s).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The surface inspection method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the direction of the vibration plane of said linearly polarized light on said surface is inclined at 45 degrees with respect to a repetition direction of said repetitive pattern(s).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The surface inspection method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>a defect of said repetitive pattern(s) is detected in a state in which said substrate to be inspected is in before and after the repetition direction of said repetitive pattern(s) is rotated by 180 degrees within said surface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The surface inspection method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the defect of said repetitive pattern(s) is detected by comparing image data on a conforming substrate stored in advance and the generated image data, the conforming substrate having ideal repetitive patterns formed thereon.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The surface inspection method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the detection of the defect of said repetitive pattern(s) is performed by determining a region of said image data as the defect when a brightness value of the region is smaller than a predetermined threshold value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The surface inspection method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the defect of said repetitive pattern(s) is detected according to a drop in the brightness value of the image data relative to that of the image data on the conforming substrate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The surface inspection apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said detection unit detects the defect of said repetitive pattern(s) according to a drop in the brightness value of the image data relative to that of the image data on the conforming substrate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
