<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297412-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297412</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11386208</doc-number>
<date>20060322</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<disclaimer>
<text>This patent is subject to a terminal disclaimer.</text>
</disclaimer>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>32</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>21</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>39</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>428621</main-classification>
<further-classification>428 411</further-classification>
<further-classification>428 417</further-classification>
<further-classification>438976</further-classification>
<further-classification>156249</further-classification>
<further-classification>156299</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e51">Fabrication of stacked microelectronic devices</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7022418</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Connell et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>428621</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7037751</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Connell et al.</name>
<date>20060500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438106</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00003">
<othercit>AI Technology, UV Releasing Tape, “Dicing &amp; Lapping Tapes for Wafer and Substrate,” 3 pages, Nov. 12, 2001, &lt;http://www.aitechnology.com/dicingtape/prod03<sub>—</sub>uv<sub>—</sub>release<sub>—</sub>dice.htm&gt;.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00004">
<othercit>Lintec-USA, UV Curable Adhesive, 3 pages, Nov. 12, 2001 &lt;http://www.lintec-usa.com/Contents/Products/Tape/Uvad.htm&gt;.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>22</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438 33</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438109</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438113</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438464</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438976</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156249</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156299</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>428621</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>428 414</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>428 423</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>428 401</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>428 417</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>12</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10933794</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040902</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7022418</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20060404</date>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11386208</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10051890</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20020116</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6896760</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20050524</date>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10933794</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060159947</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060720</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Connell</last-name>
<first-name>Michael E.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jiang</last-name>
<first-name>Tongbi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Perkins Coie LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Micron Technology, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Osele</last-name>
<first-name>Mark A.</first-name>
<department>1734</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Manufacture of stacked microelectronic devices is facilitated by producing subassemblies wherein adhesive pads are applied to the back surfaces of a plurality of microelectronic components in a batch fashion. In one embodiment, an adhesive payer is applied on a rear surface of a wafer. A plurality of spaced-apart adhesive pads are defined within the adhesive layer. Each adhesive pad may cover less than the entire back surface area of the component to which it is attached. A mounting member (e.g., dicing tape) may be attached to the adhesive layer and, in some embodiments, the adhesive layer may be treated so that the mounting member is less adherent to the adhesive pads than to other parts of the adhesive layer, easing removal of the adhesive pads with the microelectronic components.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="85.34mm" wi="158.75mm" file="US07297412-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="101.43mm" wi="148.25mm" file="US07297412-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="202.78mm" wi="151.98mm" file="US07297412-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="217.42mm" wi="163.58mm" file="US07297412-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="234.61mm" wi="167.05mm" file="US07297412-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="235.80mm" wi="163.66mm" file="US07297412-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="220.30mm" wi="160.70mm" file="US07297412-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="185.59mm" wi="158.92mm" file="US07297412-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/933,794, filed Sep. 2, 2004, now U.S. Pat. No. 7,022,418, issued Apr. 4, 2006, which is a divisional of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/051,890, filed Jan. 16, 2002, now U.S. Pat. No. 6,896,760, issued May 24, 2005, both of which are incorporated herein by reference in their entireties.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to methods and apparatus for increasing microelectronic component density. The invention has particular utility in connection with producing vertically superimposed, multi-component microelectronic devices in which at least one of the components is wire-bonded to a substrate.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Higher performance, lower cost, increased miniaturization of components, and greater packing density of integrated circuits are ongoing goals of the computer industry. Greater integrated circuit density is primarily limited by the space or “real estate” available for mounting microelectronic component on a substrate such as a printed circuit board. The microelectronic component may be electrically connected to circuitry on the circuit board via flip chip attachments, wire bonding, tape automated bonding (TAB), or a variety of other techniques.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Increasingly, microelectronic components are being vertically stacked atop one another to conserve valuable substrate real estate. In such a vertically stacked assembly, a first microelectronic component is attached directly to the substrate and a second microelectronic component may be physically attached to the first microelectronic component (e.g., stacked on the first microelectronic component). If the first microelectronic component is electrically connected to the substrate via flip chip attachments or TAB, the active surface of the microelectronic component (i.e., the surface bearing the electrical contacts for connection to the circuitry of the microelectronic component) faces toward the substrate. Commonly, the bare backside surface of the first microelectronic component is exposed and faces away from the substrate, and the second microelectronic component is attached directly to the backside surface.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">If the first microelectronic component is electrically connected to the substrate by wire bonding, however, attachment of the second microelectronic component to the first microelectronic component can be more problematic. In wire-bonding techniques, the backside of the first microelectronic component is mounted to the substrate and the active surface of a wire bonded microelectronic component defines the outer surface which faces away from the substrate. The contacts on the active surface are then electrically coupled to the contacts on the substrate by small conductive “bonding” wires that extend from the active surface to the substrate. The wires that electrically connect the active surface of the microelectronic component to the substrate accordingly interfere with attaching the second microelectronic component directly on the active surface.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> schematically illustrates one current stacked microelectronic device in which the first and second microelectronic components are wire-bonded to the substrate. The stacked microelectronic device <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> includes a substrate <b>120</b> carrying a pair of microelectronic components <b>130</b> and <b>140</b>. The substrate <b>120</b>, which may be a circuit board or the like, has a contact surface <b>124</b> bearing a plurality of electrical contacts <b>126</b><i>a</i>-<b>126</b><i>d</i>. A first microelectronic component <b>130</b> is attached to the component surface <b>124</b> of the substrate <b>120</b> by means of an adhesive <b>135</b>. The adhesive <b>135</b> may cover the entire mounting face <b>132</b> of the first microelectronic component <b>130</b>. The active surface <b>134</b> of the first microelectronic component <b>130</b> includes a plurality of electrical contacts <b>136</b><i>a</i>-<b>136</b><i>b</i>. A first bonding wire <b>138</b><i>a </i>electrically connects the first electrical contact <b>136</b><i>a </i>of the first microelectronic component <b>130</b> to the first electrical contact <b>126</b><i>a </i>of the substrate <b>120</b>, and a second bonding wire <b>138</b><i>b </i>electrically connects a second electrical contact <b>136</b><i>b </i>of the first microelectronic component <b>130</b> to a second electrical contact <b>126</b><i>b </i>of the substrate <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The second microelectronic component <b>140</b> is carried by the first microelectronic component <b>130</b>. In some conventional stacked microelectronic devices, a facing surface <b>142</b> of the second microelectronic component is attached to the active surface <b>134</b> of the first microelectronic component <b>130</b> via an adhesive layer <b>145</b>. This adhesive layer <b>145</b> conventionally has a thickness which is greater than the height to which the bonding wires <b>138</b> extend above the active surface <b>134</b> so the second microelectronic component <b>140</b> does not directly contact or rest against the bonding wires <b>138</b>. Such a structure is shown in U.S. Pat. No. 5,323,060 (Fogal et al.), the entirety of which is incorporated herein by reference. Once the second microelectronic component <b>140</b> is in place, a first electrical contact <b>146</b><i>a </i>on the outer surface <b>144</b> of the second microelectronic component <b>140</b> can be electrically connected to a third electrical contact <b>126</b><i>c </i>carried by the substrate <b>120</b>. Similarly, a second electrical contact <b>146</b><i>b </i>on the outer surface <b>144</b> can be electrically connected to a fourth electrical contact <b>126</b><i>d </i>carried by the substrate <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The stacked microelectronic device of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> includes two microelectronic components <b>130</b> and <b>140</b>. The same approach can be employed to stack three or more microelectronic components in a single microelectronic device. For example, a third microelectronic component (not shown) may be attached to the outer surface <b>144</b> of the second microelectronic component <b>140</b> using another adhesive layer similar to adhesive layer <b>145</b>. The third microelectronic component can be joined to other electrical contacts carried by the substrate <b>120</b> (e.g., contacts <b>126</b><i>e </i>and <b>126</b><i>f</i>) or one of the other microelectronic components (e.g., contacts <b>146</b>) via wire bonding.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The system proposed by Fogal et al. provides a relatively simple structure which enables stacking of microelectronic components to increase component density in a microelectronic device. However, a stacked microelectronic device such as that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> can present some manufacturing difficulties. For example, rapidly and precisely positioning the adhesive layer <b>145</b> and the second microelectronic component <b>140</b> can be a challenge. For this structure to work reliably, the adhesive layer <b>145</b> must be positioned within a central area of the first component's active surface <b>134</b> inside of the electrical contacts <b>136</b> of the first microelectronic component. If the adhesive layer <b>145</b> overlaps the electrical contacts <b>136</b>, this can damage or interfere with the connection between the electrical contacts <b>136</b> and the associated bonding wires <b>138</b>. Many microelectronic components, such as semiconductor dies, are fairly small. It can be difficult to consistently and unerringly position the adhesive layers <b>145</b> on previously mounted microelectronic components <b>130</b> in a rapid fashion to facilitate mass production of stacked microelectronic devices <b>100</b>. After the adhesive layer <b>145</b> is applied, the next microelectronic component <b>140</b> must be accurately positioned on the adhesive layer <b>145</b>. As the number of microelectronic components stacked atop one another in the microelectronic device increases, the chances for error increase concomitantly as one error in alignment or position of any layer of the stacked device can render the entire device unacceptable.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Embodiments of the present invention provide methods of preparing microelectronic components and of manufacturing stacked microelectronic devices. Other embodiments provide microelectronic subassemblies, which subassemblies may be useful in manufacturing stacked microelectronic devices.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">One embodiment of the invention provides a method of preparing microelectronic components. In accordance with this method, an adhesive layer is applied on at least a portion of a rear surface of a microelectronic wafer. The adhesive layer has a first surface in contact with the rear surface of the wafer and a second surface oriented away from the wafer. A plurality of separable, spaced-apart adhesive pads are defined within the adhesive layer. The second surface of the adhesive layer is contacted with a mounting member. The wafer is diced into a plurality of microelectronic components, with each microelectronic component having a back surface to which at least one of the adhesive pads is attached. The microelectronic components and their attached adhesive pads are separated from the mounting member, leaving a remainder of the adhesive layer. In one adaptation of this embodiment, the adhesive layer may be selectively treated to yield a first adherence between the mounting member and the second surfaces of the adhesive pads and a second, greater adherence between the remainder of the adhesive layer and the mounting member.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In another embodiment, the invention provides a method of applying adhesive pads to a plurality of microelectronic components. This method includes applying an adhesive layer on at least a portion of a rear surface of a microelectronic wafer. The microelectronic wafer comprises a plurality of microelectronic components, each of which has a back surface. A plurality of separable, spaced-apart adhesive pads are defined within the adhesive layer. Each of the microelectronic components has an adhesive pad attached to its back surface, with the adhesive pad covering less than the entire back surface of the microelectronic component. The microelectronic components are singulated. If so desired, the adhesive layer may contact a mounting member prior to singulating the microelectronic components.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Other embodiments of the invention provide microelectronic subassemblies. One such subassembly includes a microelectronic wafer having an active surface and a rear surface. The wafer comprises a plurality of microelectronic components, each of which has a back surface. The wafer also includes a plurality of streets defining peripheries of the microelectronic components. An adhesive layer has a first surface in contact with the rear surface of the wafer and covering the back surfaces of the plurality of microelectronic components. The adhesive layer includes an array of separable adhesive pads separated by adhesive boundaries, each adhesive pad being in contact with the back surface of one of the microelectronic components. Each adhesive boundary is aligned with at least one of the streets of the wafer. If so desired, each adhesive pad may cover less than the entire back surface of the microelectronic component to which it is adhered.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A microelectronic subassembly in accordance with a different embodiment of the invention includes a microelectronic wafer comprising a plurality of microelectronic components. A mounting member has a mounting surface oriented toward a rear face of the wafer. An adhesive layer has a first surface adhered to the rear surface of the wafer and a second surface adhered to the mounting surface of the mounting member. The adhesive layer includes a plurality of adhesive pads separated by adhesive boundaries. Each of the adhesive pads is adhered to one of the microelectronic components. The mounting member is less adherent to the adhesive pads than to the adhesive boundaries.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic view of one conventional stacked microelectronic device employing a spacer between the microelectronic components.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> are rear and side elevational views, respectively, of a microelectronic wafer.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> are rear and side elevational views, respectively, of the microelectronic wafer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> bearing an adhesive layer.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref> are rear and side elevational views, respectively, of the wafer and adhesive layer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> bearing a compound mounting member in accordance with one embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref> are rear and side elevational views, respectively, of the wafer and adhesive layer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> further including a mounting member and a mask in accordance with another embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref> are rear and side elevational views, respectively, of the subassembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> schematically representing the adhesive layer after treatment through the mask.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a side elevational view schematically illustrating a stage in processing a microelectronic component in accordance with a further embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Various embodiments of the present invention provide methods of manufacturing stacked microelectronic devices and subassemblies useful in such manufacture. The following description provides specific details of certain embodiments of the invention illustrated in the drawings to provide a thorough understanding of those embodiments. It should be recognized, however, that the present invention can be reflected in additional embodiments and the invention may be practiced without some of the details in the following description.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> illustrates a microelectronic wafer <b>10</b> having an active surface <b>12</b> and a rear surface <b>14</b>. The wafer <b>10</b> may comprise a plurality of microelectronic components <b>20</b>. For example, the wafer <b>10</b> may comprise a semiconductor wafer and each of the microelectronic components <b>20</b> may comprise a semiconductor die. Such semiconductor wafers are commonly manufactured as 200 mm or 300 mm discs with a plurality of semiconductor dies arranged in an array on the disc. The microelectronic components <b>20</b> may be positioned near one another. Commonly, adjacent semiconductor dies are spaced from one another a distance sufficient to accommodate the width of a saw used to cut the wafer <b>10</b> into individual microelectronic components <b>20</b>. These spaces are commonly aligned with one another to facilitate cutting with a wafer saw, defining so-called “streets” <b>22</b> between the microelectronic components <b>20</b>. Such microelectronic wafers <b>10</b> and their methods of manufacture are well known in the art and need not be detailed here.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-B</figref> are rear and side elevational views, respectively, of the wafer <b>10</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> with an adhesive layer <b>30</b> applied on the rear surface <b>14</b> of the wafer <b>10</b>. The adhesive layer <b>30</b> has a first surface <b>32</b> which may be in direct contact with the rear surface <b>14</b> of the wafer <b>10</b> and a second surface <b>34</b> which is oriented away from the wafer <b>10</b>. The adhesive layer <b>30</b> desirably covers the back surfaces of at least two adjacent microelectronic components <b>20</b> and the street <b>22</b> disposed therebetween. In one embodiment, the adhesive layer <b>30</b> covers the entire back surface of all of the microelectronic components <b>20</b> of the wafer <b>10</b>, but need not cover areas of the rear surface <b>14</b> of the wafer <b>10</b> which do not comprise a back surface of a microelectronic component <b>20</b>. In the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-B</figref>, the adhesive layer <b>30</b> covers the entire rear surface <b>14</b> of the wafer <b>10</b>. The adhesive layer first surface <b>32</b> may be coextensive with the wafer rear surface <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The adhesive layer <b>30</b> comprises a plurality of separable adhesive pads <b>40</b> spaced from one another in a predetermined array. Adhesive pads <b>40</b> are spaced from one another by boundaries <b>44</b> of a predetermined width. The boundaries <b>44</b> may be discrete from one another. In the illustrated embodiment, the adhesive boundaries <b>44</b> are joined in a continuous structure defining a grid between the adhesive pads <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">For reasons explained below, the adhesive pads <b>40</b> should be fairly readily separable from the rest of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. In one embodiment, this is accomplished by forming the adhesive pads <b>40</b> of a different material than the remainder of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. In the illustrated embodiment, the adhesive pads <b>40</b> have peripheries defined by cuts <b>42</b> in the adhesive layer. In one embodiment, these cuts extend through substantially the entire thickness of the adhesive layer, extending from the first surface <b>32</b> to the second surface <b>34</b> of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. The cuts <b>42</b> may be continuous, providing an essentially complete separation between the pads <b>40</b> and the adjacent boundaries <b>44</b>. In other embodiments, the cuts <b>42</b> may extend through less than the entire thickness of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. In still other embodiments, the cuts <b>42</b> may be discontinuous, defining the peripheries of the pads <b>40</b> as a series of perforations along which the adhesive layer <b>30</b> may be readily broken to remove the pads <b>40</b> from the remainder of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The array of separable, spaced-apart adhesive pads <b>40</b> can be defined in any desired fashion. In one embodiment, the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is applied to the rear surface <b>14</b> of the wafer <b>10</b> as a monolithic, continuous layer. After the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is applied to the wafer rear surface <b>14</b>, the adhesive pads <b>40</b> can be formed in the adhesive layer <b>30</b>, such as by cutting the adhesive layer <b>30</b> to define the peripheral cuts <b>42</b>. This can be accomplished in any known fashion, such as by using lasers or photochemical processes. If the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is cut with a wafer saw, the cuts <b>42</b> may comprise a series of parallel chords (not shown) which intersect one another to define the peripheries of the adhesive pads <b>40</b>. This will also cut the remainder of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> into a series of discrete boundaries <b>44</b> rather than the continuous, grid-like arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In an alternative embodiment, the adhesive pads <b>40</b> are defined in the adhesive layer <b>30</b> before the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is applied to the wafer rear surface <b>14</b>. This permits mass production of adhesive material having pre-formed adhesive pads <b>40</b> defined therein, minimizing the chances of damage to the wafer <b>10</b> in the process of forming the cuts <b>42</b> after application of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> to the wafer <b>10</b>. If the cuts <b>42</b> are continuous and extend through the entire thickness of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>, it may desirable to carry the adhesive layer <b>30</b> on a liner (not shown). The liner may be attached to the second surface <b>34</b> of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> to hold the adhesive pads <b>40</b> in place with respect to the remainder of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. If the cuts <b>42</b> comprise discontinuous perforations, such a liner may be unnecessary.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As suggested in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, the adhesive pads <b>40</b> are arranged in an array which is modeled after the arrangement of the microelectronic components <b>20</b> on the wafer <b>10</b>. In particular, each adhesive pad <b>40</b> may be in contact with the back surface of one of the microelectronic components <b>20</b>. In one embodiment, none of the adhesive pads <b>40</b> are in contact with the back surfaces of more than one microelectronic component <b>20</b>. The adhesive boundaries <b>44</b> between adjacent adhesive pads <b>40</b> may be generally aligned with the streets <b>22</b> of the wafer <b>10</b>. In the illustrated embodiment, each of the boundaries <b>44</b> is wider than the street <b>22</b> with which it is aligned. As a consequence, each of the adhesive pads <b>40</b> has a periphery which is spaced inwardly from the periphery of the microelectronic component <b>20</b> to which it is attached. Since the adhesive pads <b>40</b> do not cover the entire back surface of the microelectronic components <b>20</b> to which they are attached, each microelectronic component <b>20</b> has a back surface area which is greater than the contact area between the adhesive pad <b>40</b> and the back surface of the microelectronic component <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The widths of the boundaries <b>44</b> and, hence, the distance which the microelectronic component <b>20</b> extends outwardly beyond the periphery of the associated adhesive pad <b>40</b>, will vary depending on the particular application. In one embodiment, the size of the adhesive pad <b>40</b> is chosen to permit it to be attached to the active surface of another microelectronic component without interfering with the electrical contacts on that active surface. For example, in the context of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the adhesive pad <b>40</b> may be used instead of the adhesive layer <b>145</b> between the two microelectronic components. In this context, the boundaries of the adhesive pad <b>40</b> will be selected so that the adhesive pad <b>40</b> could be attached to the active surface <b>134</b> of the first microelectronic component <b>130</b> without covering the electrical contacts <b>136</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The adhesive pads <b>40</b> may serve as an adhesive layer to connect one of the microelectronic components <b>20</b> to another microelectronic component (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-B</figref>) in a stacked microelectronic device. As such, the material of the adhesive pad <b>40</b> should be compatible with the microelectronic components <b>20</b> of the wafer <b>10</b> and the other microelectronic components to which the pads will be attached. The adhesive material should also be mechanically and chemically stable under the anticipated conditions of use, though some adhesive materials known in the art may require thermal or other curing processes to yield the final desired characteristics. In one embodiment particularly useful in connection with the process outlined below in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-7</figref>, for example, the adhesive layer <b>30</b> (and the adhesive pads <b>40</b> defined therein) are formed of a material which is curable by radiation and may also require a secondary thermal cure to yield the final desired adhesive pad <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The adhesive layer <b>30</b> can be applied at any suitable thickness. As noted above and explained more fully below, the adhesive pads <b>40</b> may serve as a spacer between microelectronic components in a stacked microelectronic device. The thickness of the adhesive pads <b>40</b> may be selected to ensure adequate clearance between the active surface of the underlying microelectronic component (e.g., surface <b>134</b> of the first microelectronic component in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) and the back surface of the microelectronic component to which it is attached to avoid interference between the microelectronic component <b>20</b> and bonding wires (e.g., <b>138</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) attached to the underlying microelectronic component. The thickness will depend on the loop height of those bonding wires. In one embodiment, the adhesive layer <b>30</b> has a thickness of about 6 mils.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a mounting member <b>50</b> may be brought into contact with the second surface <b>34</b> of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. In one embodiment, the second surface <b>34</b> of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is adhered to a mounting surface <b>52</b> of the mounting member <b>50</b>, effectively connecting the wafer <b>10</b> to the mounting member <b>50</b>. The mounting member <b>50</b> may comprise a conventional, commercially available dicing tape. In conventional microelectronic component manufacture, a wafer may be attached to a dicing tape before the wafer is cut to “singulate” individual microelectronic components. Such dicing tapes typically comprise flexible polymeric films.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>, the mounting member <b>50</b> comprises a backing layer <b>58</b> which defines the exterior surface <b>54</b> of the mounting member <b>50</b> and a release layer <b>56</b> which defines the mounting surface <b>52</b>. The release layer <b>56</b> is selected to control the adherence between the adhesive layer <b>30</b> and the mounting member <b>50</b>. In particular, the adherence between the adhesive layer <b>30</b> and the release layer <b>56</b> should be sufficient to enable the wafer <b>10</b> to be handled and diced using conventional equipment, but should allow singulated microelectronic components <b>20</b>, with the adhesive pad <b>40</b> attached thereto, to be lifted away from the mounting member <b>50</b> with conventional handling equipment, such as that mentioned below in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A-B</figref>, the wafer <b>10</b> may be diced after the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is attached to the mounting member <b>50</b>. The wafer <b>10</b> may be diced in a conventional fashion, such as by scribing cuts <b>22</b><i>a </i>in the wafer using a conventional wafer saw. The cuts <b>22</b><i>a </i>may follow along the path of the streets (<b>22</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>) between adjacent microelectronic components, as is conventional in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The cuts <b>22</b><i>a </i>desirably pass through substantially the entire thickness of the wafer <b>10</b>, but are spaced from the mounting member <b>50</b>. In the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>, the cuts <b>22</b><i>a </i>extend through the thickness of the wafer <b>10</b>, but do not extend appreciably into the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. Because the boundaries <b>44</b> between adjacent adhesive pads <b>40</b> are aligned with the wafer streets (<b>22</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>), cutting to a depth spaced from the mounting member <b>50</b> will leave the boundaries <b>44</b> between adjacent adhesive pads <b>40</b> largely intact. This facilitates removal of the adhesive pads <b>40</b> with the microelectronic components <b>20</b> to which they are attached while leaving the remainder of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> (including the boundaries <b>44</b>) attached to the mounting member <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-6B</figref> illustrate an alternative embodiment of the invention. In accordance with this embodiment, the second surface <b>34</b> of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is brought into contact with a different mounting member <b>60</b>. Whereas the mounting member <b>50</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>) has a multi-layer structure, the mounting member <b>60</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>) may have a single monolithic layer which extends from the mounting surface <b>62</b> to the exterior surface <b>64</b>. The mounting member <b>60</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> may have a relatively high transmissivity of a selected treatment radiation, e.g., ultraviolet (UV) radiation, and is relatively stable under exposure to that radiation.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In accordance with the process outlined in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-6B</figref>, a mask <b>70</b> is positioned between the mounting member <b>60</b> and a radiation source <b>75</b>. The mask <b>70</b> has a body <b>72</b> and a plurality of orifices or windows <b>74</b> therethrough. These windows <b>74</b> are arranged to align with the either the adhesive pads <b>40</b> or the boundaries <b>44</b> of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. In the illustrated embodiment, the windows <b>74</b> are arranged to align with the adhesive pads <b>40</b> and the body <b>72</b> of the mask <b>70</b> is designed to align with the boundaries <b>44</b> between the adhesive pads <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The windows <b>74</b> are adapted to transmit radiation from the radiation source <b>75</b> while the body <b>72</b> limits passage of that radiation. This permits the areas of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> aligned with the windows <b>74</b> to be selectively exposed to the radiation from the radiation source <b>75</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The material of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> may be selected to change properties in response to exposure to radiation from the radiation source <b>75</b>. This may be done, for example, to alter the properties of the adhesive pads <b>40</b> to better bond the adhesive pads to the wafer rear surface <b>14</b> or to facilitate defining the adhesive pads <b>40</b> or their removal from the remainder of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In one particular embodiment of the invention, adhesion between the adhesive layer <b>30</b> and the mounting member <b>60</b> is altered by exposure to radiation from the radiation source <b>75</b>. By positioning the mask <b>70</b> between the radiation source <b>75</b> and the adhesive layer <b>30</b>, the adhesive layer <b>30</b> may be selectively exposed to yield a first adherence between the mounting member <b>60</b> and the second surfaces <b>34</b> of the adhesive pads <b>40</b>, and a second, greater adherence between the second surface <b>34</b> of the remainder of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> and the mounting member <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In one embodiment, the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is a UV- or visible light-curable adhesive material and the radiation source <b>75</b> emits radiation of a wavelength adapted to cure the adhesive <b>30</b>. A variety of suitable adhesive materials are commercially available. These adhesive materials are commonly employed to provide a high level of adhesion between a wafer and a backing tape, for example, during ordinary handling, yet permit ready removal of the backing tape by exposure to an appropriate wavelength of radiation. Adhesives expected to be suitable for this purpose include ABLELUX “UV/visible curable” or “UV/visible/secondary thermal curable” adhesives, sold by Ablestik Laboratories of Rancho Dominguez, Calif., USA; UV200 and UV500 adhesives available from AI Technology of Princeton Junction, N.J., USA; and D-SERIES adhesives available from Lintec Corporation of Tokyo, Japan.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A-B</figref> schematically illustrate the subassembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-B</figref> after exposure by the radiation source <b>75</b> through the mask <b>70</b>. The adhesive pads in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A-B</figref> are designated by reference number <b>40</b><i>a </i>and are crosshatched to schematically signify the change induced by exposure to the radiation source <b>75</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A-6B</figref> illustrate the wafer <b>10</b> wherein the microelectronic components <b>20</b> have been separated by cuts <b>22</b><i>a </i>along the streets (<b>22</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>) of the wafer <b>10</b>. As with the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>, the cuts <b>22</b><i>a </i>used to dice the wafer <b>10</b> stop short of cutting through the entire thickness of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>. In the illustrated embodiment, the cuts <b>22</b><i>a </i>extend through the thickness of the wafer without cutting into the adhesive layer <b>30</b> at all.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> schematically illustrates removal of an individual microelectronic component <b>20</b> and its associated adhesive pad <b>40</b><i>a </i>from the diced wafer <b>10</b>. As is known in the art, the active surface <b>26</b> of a microelectronic component <b>20</b> may be contacted with a vacuum tip <b>90</b> to sucktorially grasp an individual microelectronic component <b>20</b>. As the microelectronic component <b>20</b> is lifted away from the mounting member <b>60</b>, the adhesive pad <b>40</b><i>a </i>attached to the back surface <b>24</b> of the microelectronic component <b>20</b> will be lifted with the microelectronic component <b>20</b>. In the illustrated embodiment, selectively exposing the adhesive pads <b>40</b> to the radiation source <b>75</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>) renders the mounting member <b>60</b> less adherent to the adhesive pads <b>40</b><i>a </i>than to the boundaries <b>44</b> between the adhesive pads <b>40</b><i>a</i>. This facilitates removal of the microelectronic component <b>20</b> with the adhesive pads <b>40</b><i>a </i>while leaving the boundary areas <b>44</b> of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> attached to the mounting member <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">It is not necessary to expose the adhesive layer <b>30</b> to radiation or otherwise treat the adhesive layer <b>30</b> to render the adhesive pads <b>40</b> relatively less adherent to the mounting member <b>60</b>. If a multi-layer mounting member <b>50</b> with a release liner <b>56</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>) is employed, for example, it may be possible to simply lift the diced microelectronic component <b>20</b> with the untreated adhesive pad <b>40</b> attached, leaving the rest of the adhesive layer <b>30</b> in place. If so desired, a plunger <b>92</b> may be urged upwardly against the exterior surface <b>64</b> of the mounting member <b>60</b> (or exterior surface <b>54</b> of the mounting member <b>50</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>) to locally deform the mounting member <b>60</b> and facilitate selective detachment of the adhesive pad <b>40</b> from the mounting member <b>60</b>. Such a plunger <b>92</b> can also be used in connection with embodiments of the invention wherein the adhesive layer <b>30</b> is selectively exposed to reduce adherence of the adhesive pads <b>40</b><i>a </i>to the mounting member <b>60</b> as suggested in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">This process may be continued for each of the diced microelectronic components <b>20</b>. At the end of process, each of the adhesive pads <b>40</b><i>a </i>will be removed with the microelectronic components <b>20</b> to which they are attached. This will leave a remainder of the adhesive layer <b>30</b>, including the boundaries <b>44</b> which separated the spaced-apart adhesive pads <b>40</b><i>a</i>, attached to the mounting member <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the vacuum tip <b>90</b> can remove a single microelectronic component <b>20</b> with an attached adhesive pad <b>40</b><i>a</i>. This adhesive pad <b>40</b> may have a periphery spaced inwardly from the periphery of the microelectronic component <b>20</b>. This is an excellent expedient for the manufacture of stacked microelectronic devices. As noted above in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, current techniques require high-precision placement of a small adhesive layer <b>145</b> on the active surface <b>134</b> of an individual microelectronic component <b>130</b>. The process of applying these individual adhesive layers <b>145</b> can be a manufacturing bottleneck and can increase product losses due to relatively small errors in adhesive layer placement.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Embodiments of the present invention greatly streamline the process of applying and positioning an adhesive which can be used to stack microelectronic components. By applying the adhesive layer <b>30</b> to the wafer <b>10</b> before the individual microelectronic component <b>20</b> are singulated, adhesive pads <b>40</b> can be attached in a batch process to a large number of microelectronic components <b>20</b>. This yields a stackable component subassembly (<b>220</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>) which includes a microelectronic component <b>20</b> and the attached adhesive pad <b>40</b>. This subassembly <b>220</b> can be positioned with respect to another microelectronic component (e.g., <b>130</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) of a stacked microelectronic device. The adhesive pad <b>40</b> can then be used to join the microelectronic component <b>20</b> to the underlying microelectronic component and as a spacer to avoid damage to any bonding wires (<b>138</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) attached to the underlying microelectronic component (<b>130</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">From the foregoing, it will be appreciated that specific embodiments of the invention have been described herein for purposes of illustration, but that various modifications may be made without deviating from the spirit and scope of the invention. Accordingly, the invention is not limited except as by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A microelectronic subassembly, comprising:
<claim-text>a microfeature workpiece having an active surface and a rear surface, the workpiece comprising a plurality of microelectronic components, each of which has a back surface, and a plurality of streets between the microelectronic components;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adhesive layer having a first surface in contact with the rear surface of the workpiece and covering the back surfaces of the plurality of microelectronic components, the adhesive layer comprising an array of separable adhesive pads spaced by adhesive boundaries, each adhesive pad being in contact with the back surface of one of the microelectronic components and each adhesive boundary being aligned with at least one of the streets of the workpiece.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive pads have peripheries defined by cuts in the adhesive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the cuts extend through substantially an entire thickness of the adhesive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the cuts define perforations between the adhesive pads and the adhesive boundaries.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive boundaries are joined in a continuous structure defining a grid between the adhesive pads.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive pads and the adhesive boundaries comprise the same material applied as a continuous adhesive layer and subsequently cut to define the adhesive pads and the adhesive boundaries.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein each of the microelectronic components has a back surface, each adhesive pad covering less than the entire back surface of the microelectronic component to which it is adhered.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive layer has a second surface oriented away from the workpiece, further comprising a support member in contact with the second surface of the adhesive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the support member comprises a backing tape and a release liner, the release liner being carried between the backing tape and the adhesive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the support member is less adherent to the adhesive pads than to the adhesive boundaries.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive layer comprises a radiation-sensitive material adapted to change adherence to the support member in response to exposure to radiation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive layer comprises a radiation-sensitive material which reduces adherence to the support member in response to exposure to radiation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the microfeature workpiece comprises a semiconductor substrate including a plurality of microelectronic dies.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A microelectronic subassembly, comprising:
<claim-text>a microfeature workpiece comprising a plurality of microelectronic components, the workpiece having a rear surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a support member having a mounting surface oriented toward the rear surface of the workpiece; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adhesive layer having a first surface adhered to the rear surface of the workpiece and a second surface adhered to the mounting surface of the support member, the adhesive layer comprising a plurality of adhesive pads separated by adhesive boundaries, each of the adhesive pads being adhered to one of the microelectronic components, the support member being less adherent to the adhesive pads than to the adhesive boundaries.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive pads have peripheries defined by cuts in the adhesive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the cuts extend through substantially an entire thickness of the adhesive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the cuts define perforations between the adhesive pads and the adhesive boundaries.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive boundaries are joined in a continuous structure defining a grid between the adhesive pads.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive pads and the adhesive boundaries comprise the same material applied as a continuous adhesive layer and subsequently cut to define the adhesive pads and the adhesive boundaries.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the support member comprises a backing tape and a release liner, the release liner being carried between the backing tape and the adhesive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the adhesive layer comprises a radiation-sensitive material adapted to change adherence to the support member in response to exposure to radiation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The microelectronic subassembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the microfeature workpiece comprises a semiconductor substrate including a plurality of microelectronic dies.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
