<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298825-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298825</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11164438</doc-number>
<date>20051122</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>36</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378116</main-classification>
<further-classification>378207</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Portable digital detector system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5265149</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Varisco</name>
<date>19931100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5687717</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Halpern et al.</name>
<date>19971100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6007243</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ergun et al.</name>
<date>19991200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6550964</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Guerit et al.</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6702459</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Barnes et al.</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0150214</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Spahn</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>378189</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0176535</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Dixon et al.</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>378 62</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378189-190</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378115-117</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378102</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378207</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378204</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378210</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378 988</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070116180</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070524</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Omernick</last-name>
<first-name>Jon C.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wauwatosa</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kump</last-name>
<first-name>Kenneth S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Waukesha</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zaman</last-name>
<first-name>Sabih Q.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Elm Grove</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>General Electric Co.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Schenectady</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Song</last-name>
<first-name>Hoon</first-name>
<department>2882</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A detector for a portable imaging system includes a flash memory including a full set of configuration parameters and calibration files. The detector also includes a transmit and receive unit for communicating with the portable imaging system. The detector still further includes a detector controller responding to a request for identification of the detector received through the transmit and receive unit. The detector transmits calibration data and configuration data from the flash memory to the portable imaging system and boots the detector.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="61.64mm" wi="110.49mm" file="US07298825-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="165.61mm" wi="127.00mm" file="US07298825-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="143.51mm" wi="103.97mm" file="US07298825-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to imaging systems and more particularly to mobile radiography.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In the hospital setting, mobile radiographic exams are performed on patients incapable of being moved or difficult to move. Also, in tertiary care medical centers, mobile radiographic exams represent a significant percentage of the radiographic exams performed.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">When a portable digital detector is used in the mobile radiology (RAD) clinical environments, it is critical that the system be reliable and available to the user (i.e. maximization of uptime). Due to the harsh environment in which this type of detector is used, (detector being dropped, banged against objects, etc.) it is inevitable that the detector may need to be replaced on a clinical site. It is desirable that the time to replace the detector and return the system back to the customer be as short as possible. With current remote diagnostic capabilities, it is possible to determine which component has failed and to provide the proper part to the site.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">If, however, once the detector has been replaced, a long configuration, calibration process is required, as is often the case, time for the user to receive the unit and restart patient procedures may be significantly impacted. As the cost of the system requires high productivity and low downtime, it is critical to reduce or eliminate this effort.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In addition, if any change to the detector design occurs during production it would be highly beneficial for the detector itself to include any configuration parameters that would be affected without requiring the customer to reload new software on the system prior to using the detector.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Also, if multiple detectors are available to the customer and the detector is capable of quickly switching through wireless or quick disconnect connections, the capability quickly to configure the system to work optimally with that detector may add to time saving.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The disadvantages associated with current, portable digital detectors for mobile radiography units have made it apparent that a new technique for installing detectors and configuring portable detector information would be beneficial. The present invention is directed to these ends.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In accordance with one aspect of the present invention, a detector for a portable imaging system includes a flash memory including a full set of configuration parameters and calibration files. The detector also includes a transmit and receive unit for communicating with the portable imaging system. The detector still further includes a detector controller responding to a request for identification of the detector received through the transmit and receive unit. The detector transmits calibration data and configuration data from the flash memory to the portable imaging system and boots the detector.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In accordance with another embodiment of the present invention, a method for auto-configuring an imaging system having a portable detector and an imaging computer includes installing the portable detector in the imaging system. The imaging system checks the detector for identification information and requests configuration data from the detector in response to a difference between imaging system identification information for the detector and detector identification information. Detector calibration and configuration data is then loaded from the detector to the imaging system.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">This invention provides a robust system and method for quickly switching detectors after component failure or system usage and configuring the system to allow it to be returned to customer operation.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Additional advantages and features of the present invention will become apparent from the description that follows and may be realized by the instrumentalities and combinations particularly pointed out in the appended claims, taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">For a more complete understanding of the invention, there will now be described some embodiments thereof, given by way of example, reference being made to the accompanying drawings, in which.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram of a scanning system, in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram of a scanning system, in accordance with another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a logic flow diagram of a method for auto-configuring a portable detector, in accordance with another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The present invention is illustrated with respect to a mobile radiology scanning system <b>10</b>, particularly suited to the medical field. The present invention is, however, applicable to various other uses that may require x-ray scanning, as will be understood by one skilled in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In one embodiment, the present invention describes a system including an x-ray source assembly, a controller, and a detector attached to a mobile radiographic system.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Through the device and method of the present invention, the process of installing a detector is illustrated.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, a mobile radiography or x-ray scanning system <b>10</b> includes a wheeled base <b>12</b>, an operator console <b>14</b>, and an x-ray source assembly <b>15</b>. The x-ray source assembly <b>15</b> includes an x-ray tube housing <b>22</b> containing an x-ray source, the tube housing <b>22</b> having an x-ray emission aperture (not shown), and a collimator <b>24</b> attached to the tube housing <b>22</b> and aligned with the x-ray emission aperture. The scanning system <b>10</b> is embodied for scanning an object <b>29</b> to be imaged, illustrated on a table <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The mobile system <b>10</b> further includes a controller <b>27</b> (imaging computer) and a removeable detector <b>26</b> in communication with the controller <b>27</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The controller <b>27</b> includes logic checking for at least one of a serial number and MAC address from the detector. In response to at least one of the serial number and the MAC address not found in the imaging computer, the controller <b>27</b> receives data from the detector <b>26</b> configuring and calibrating the controller <b>27</b> such that the controller <b>27</b> recognizes the detector and operates with the detector <b>26</b>. In other words, if the controller <b>27</b> does not include configuration data for or does not recognize the detector <b>26</b>, the detector transmits information required to run that particular detector.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates the controller <b>27</b> communicating wirelessly with the detector <b>26</b> as the detector <b>26</b> is activated and brought in a vicinity of the controller <b>27</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates the detector <b>26</b> coupled to the imaging system <b>10</b> through a wire <b>37</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The detector <b>26</b> attaches to the system <b>10</b>, on, for example, a collimator <b>24</b>. The detector <b>26</b> includes a flash memory <b>31</b>, a detector controller <b>33</b>, and a transmit/receive unit <b>35</b>. The detector <b>26</b> is positioned to produce an image of a target array <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In accordance with one embodiment of the present invention, a detector platform, such as the Geode portable detector platform, includes flash memory <b>31</b>, which is loaded from the vendor with a full set of configuration parameters and calibration files. This data is uploaded to the system controller <b>27</b> based on the MAC address or serial number on system boot after the detector <b>26</b> is re-connected. The data included in the flash data includes all calibration data, model information and component configuration data.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In accordance with another embodiment of the present invention, if during system operation, calibration is required either due to changes of the detector <b>26</b> or for image quality (IQ) requirements, this new calibration data will be transferred back to the detector <b>26</b> from the controller <b>27</b> for ensuring that the data on the detector <b>26</b> is refreshed.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The detector <b>26</b> includes the transmit/receive unit <b>35</b> for communicating with the controller <b>27</b>. The transmit/receive unit <b>35</b> may be wireless or may include wires connecting to the controller <b>27</b> or to another part of the imaging system <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The detector <b>26</b> further includes the detector controller <b>33</b> receiving and processing signals from the controller <b>27</b> and controlling boot functions of the detector <b>26</b>, including configuring the detector <b>26</b> for use with the particular imaging system <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">While it is preferred that the detector <b>26</b> be affixable to the collimator housing <b>24</b>, it is appreciated that the detector <b>26</b>, according to the present invention, can be mounted in a variety of positions on the mobile x-ray system <b>10</b>. It is further recognized that other detectors and numerous numbers thereof, in addition to a digital detector, are operative herein. These additional detectors may be optical in nature, or be based on other principles such as magnetic interactions, ultrasound, or inertial navigation.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a logic flow diagram <b>100</b> of one embodiment of the operations of the present invention is illustrated.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In operation block <b>102</b>, the controller or system boot activates, and in operation block <b>104</b>, the detector boot activates.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In operation block <b>106</b>, serial numbers and MAC addressed are checked between the system boot and the detector boot. This is conducted in either the system controller or the detector or both.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In inquiry block <b>108</b>, a check is made whether the serial numbers and MAC addresses are different. For a negative response the boot completes.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Otherwise, in operation block <b>112</b> the detector requests configuration data from the system boot, or the system boot automatically updates the detector.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In operation block <b>114</b>, configuration data, detector parameters, and calibration data is received in the system boot in response to system boot request or automatic detector signal.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In operation, a method for auto-configuring an imaging system having a portable detector and an imaging computer includes installing the portable detector in the imaging system. The imaging system checks the detector for identification information and requests configuration data from the detector in response to a difference between imaging system identification information for the detector and detector identification information. Detector calibration and configuration data is then loaded from the detector to the imaging system.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">From the foregoing, it can be seen that there has been brought to the art a scanning system <b>10</b> and method. It is to be understood that the preceding description of the preferred embodiment is merely illustrative of some of the many specific embodiments that represent applications of the principles of the present invention. Numerous and other arrangements would be evident to those skilled in the art without departing from the scope of the invention as defined by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A detector for a portable imaging system comprising:
<claim-text>a flash memory comprising a full set of calibration data and configuration data;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transmit and receive unit for communicating with the portable imaging system; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detector controller responding to a request for identification of said detector received through said transmit and receive unit and transmitting calibration data and configuration data from said flash memory to the portable imaging system and booting the detector.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said transmit and receive unit comprises at least one of a wireless unit or an electrical connection.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said detector controller comprises detector serial number data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said detector controller comprises detector Media Access Control (MAC) address data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A method for auto-configuring an imaging system having a portable detector and an imaging computer, the method comprising:
<claim-text>installing the portable detector in the imaging system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the imaging system checking the detector for identification information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the imaging system requesting calibration and configuration data from the detector in response to a difference between imaging system identification information for the detector and detector identification information; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>loading detector calibration and configuration data from the detector to the imaging system.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said step of installing comprises the detector communicating wirelessly with the imaging system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> further comprising booting the detector and the imaging system as a function of said detector calibration and configuration data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein loading detector calibration and configuration data further comprises loading detector model information.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising in response to a calibration requirement occurring during imaging system operation, transmitting new calibration data to the detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein loading detector calibration and configuration data comprises uploading a full set of configuration parameters and calibration files based on at least one of a MAC address and a serial number on an image system boot after the detector is installed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising the imaging system completing a boot in response to consistency between said imaging system identification information for the detector and said detector identification information.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A portable scanning system comprising:
<claim-text>an x-ray source coupled to an imaging computer and adapted to generate an x-ray exposure in response to imaging computer signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detector comprising a memory loaded with configuration parameters and calibration files, said detector communicating with said imaging computer and adapted to receive said x-ray exposure and generate therefrom a detector signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an imaging computer comprising logic checking for at least one of a serial number and MAC address from said detector, in response to said at least one of said serial number and said MAC address not found in said imaging computer, said imaging computer receiving data from said detector configuring and calibrating said imaging computer such that said imaging computer recognizes said detector and operates with said detector.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said memory of said detector comprises a flash memory loaded.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said flash memory is preloaded by a vendor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising a wireless communication system for transmitting data between said detector and said imaging computer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said memory further comprises detector model information.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said imaging computer comprises logic activating in response to a calibration requirement occurring during system operation and transmitting new calibration data to said detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein data on said detector refreshes in response to said new calibration data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said detector further comprises a detector controller responding to a request for identification of said detector by sending requested identification data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said detector and said imaging computer boot as a function of said imaging computer recognizing said detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
