<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296873-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296873</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10774373</doc-number>
<date>20040210</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-349427</doc-number>
<date>20031008</date>
</priority-claim>
<priority-claim sequence="02" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-349428</doc-number>
<date>20031008</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>266</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>41</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>2</main-group>
<subgroup>165</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347 23</main-classification>
<further-classification>347 19</further-classification>
<further-classification>347  7</further-classification>
<further-classification>347 14</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e89">Printing device, printing method, printing program and computer-readable recording medium on which the program is recorded</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5530461</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sakuma</name>
<date>19960600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347 23</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6158837</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hilton et al.</name>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6312072</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hough</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347  7</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6318828</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Barbour et al.</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347  9</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6808255</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Haines et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347 86</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6817693</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Phillips et al.</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347 19</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>09-269709</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19971000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-69139</doc-number>
<date>19980300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-221840</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-100530</doc-number>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-125462</doc-number>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-341703</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-162187</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-195705</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>30</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347  7</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347 23</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>10</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050078165</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050414</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Harada</last-name>
<first-name>Seiji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hachioji</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Morita</last-name>
<first-name>Kenichi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hino</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Morrison &amp; Foerster LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Konica Minolta Business Technologies, Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Luu</last-name>
<first-name>Matthew</first-name>
<department>2861</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Goldberg</last-name>
<first-name>Brian J.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The printer reads a capacity number of printed sheets and a accumulated number of printed sheets of a toner cartridge stored in a cartridge memory of toner cartridge and compares them to determine whether toner cartridge's service life has expired. Similarly, it reads toner cartridge's product information stored in the cartridge memory, and compares it with an authorized product's product information to determine whether the toner cartridge is an authorized product. If it is determined that toner cartridge's life has expired or the toner cartridge is not an authorized product, the printer executes printing process in the safety mode with an increased frequency compared to that of the standard mode. Thus, the printer allows continuation of printing without deteriorating printing quality and without halting instantly even when a toner cartridge, whose service life has expired, or an unauthorized product is used.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="203.62mm" wi="153.84mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="225.89mm" wi="142.92mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="100.50mm" wi="142.58mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="221.74mm" wi="166.45mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="173.74mm" wi="147.83mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="102.70mm" wi="143.43mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="188.55mm" wi="153.08mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="203.71mm" wi="147.32mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="190.58mm" wi="161.80mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="102.79mm" wi="142.66mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="185.08mm" wi="163.41mm" file="US07296873-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is based on Japanese Patent Application No. 2003-349427 filed on Oct. 8, 2003, and Japanese Patent Application No. 2003-349428 filed on Oct. 8, 2003 the contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The invention related to a printing device. More specifically, it relates to a printing device that allows the printing process to be continued without deteriorating printing quality or without halting the printing operation instantly even when a developing agent cartridge, whose service life has expired or which is not an authorized product, is used.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The toner cartridge of a printing device such as a printer is a consumable item and it is necessary to replace it with a new cartridge when the toner material stored inside the cartridge is used up. If the used up cartridge is replaced with a cartridge authorized by the manufacturer of said printer (“authorized product”), the printing quality and reliability are guaranteed. However, refilled cartridges that are manufactured by using used-up cartridge bodies of authorized products and refilling them with unauthorized toners or toners of other manufacturers (“refilled product”) or cartridges made by other manufacturers in imitation of authorized products (“unauthorized product”) are available on the market, and they sometimes caused deterioration of printing quality or reliability or even printer problems. Also, each component of the cartridge has a specific service life, so that even an authorized product is used, it may cause similar troubles when a service life of a part of its components has expired even if its toner has still remained.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In the meanwhile, there are printing device inventions that are capable of judging whether a cartridge is an authorized one depending on the data stored in the cartridge memory (e.g., JP-10-69139A), judging whether a cartridge is a refilled product by detecting increase of the toner quantity recorded on the cartridge memory (e.g., JP-2001-100530A), judging whether a cartridge is a refilled product by detecting damages on the cartridge body making the body impossible to open it without damaging a certain part of it (e.g., Patent Application 2001-125462), and others.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">However, in any of these prior arts, it is designed to stop or prohibit printing if the loaded cartridge is found to be a refilled product and the like, so that it has a problem that a user can use a product by mistake without noticing that it is a refilled product, or an authorized product but its service life has expired, or an unauthorized product, in which case the user has no choice to stop printing if a replacement authorized product is not available on the spot.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention is made under the consideration of such a problem of the prior art, and is intended to provide a printing device that is capable of continuing the printing process without causing such troubles as deterioration of printing quality and reliability or printer malfunctions, etc., even when a refilled product, a cartridge whose service life has expired, or an unauthorized product is used.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Said objective of the present invention can be accomplished by the following means:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">(1) A printing device comprising: a judging unit for judging whether a service life of a developing agent cartridge has expired; and an operation mode setting unit for setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment unit determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">(2) A printing device comprising: a judging unit for judging whether a service life of a developing agent cartridge has expired; and an operation mode setting unit for setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in which a printing process is executed with an increased cleaning frequency compared to that of a standard mode when said judging unit determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">(3) A printing method comprising: a judging step of judging whether a service life of a developing agent cartridge has expired; and an operation mode setting step of setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment step determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">(4) A printing method comprising: a judging step of judging whether a service life of a developing agent cartridge has expired; and an operation mode setting step of setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in which a printing process is executed with an increased cleaning frequency compared to that of a standard mode when said judging step determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">(5) A printing program for causing a printing device to execute: a judging step of judging whether a service life of a developing agent cartridge has expired; and an operation mode setting step of setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment step determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">(6) A computer-readable recording medium on which the printing program described in (5) is recorded.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">(7) A printing device comprising: a judging unit for judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and an operation mode setting unit for setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment unit determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">(8) A printing device comprising: a judging unit for judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and an operation mode setting unit for setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in which a printing process is executed with an increased cleaning frequency compared to that of a standard mode when said judgment unit determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">(9) A printing method comprising: a judging step of judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and an operation mode setting step of setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment step determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">(10) A printing method comprising: a judging step of judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and an operation mode setting step of setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in which a printing process is executed with an increased cleaning frequency compared to that of a standard mode when said judgment step determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">(11) A printing program for causing a printing device to execute: a judging step of judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0021">an operation mode setting step of setting up its own operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment step determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0022">(12) A computer-readable recording medium on which the printing program described in (11) is recorded.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram showing the entire constitution of a printing system including a printing device according to a first embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram showing the constitution of a printer <b>1</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a drawing showing the structure of a printing unit <b>15</b> of printer <b>1</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of the standard mode printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a drawing showing an example of dialog to be displayed on a display of a PC <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of the safety mode printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of printing process of a printer <b>1</b>B concerning a second embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a flowchart-showing the sequence of the standard mode printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>B.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a drawing showing an example of dialog to be displayed on a display of a PC <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of the safety mode printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>B.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0034" num="0034">The preferred embodiments of the invention will be described in detail below with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram showing the entire constitution of a printing system including a printing device according to a first embodiment of the present invention. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the printing system according to this embodiment is equipped with a printer <b>1</b>A as a printing device and a PC (personal computer) <b>2</b> as a printing job transmission device, which are connected via a network <b>3</b> to communicate with each other. The types and the number of equipment to be connected to network <b>3</b> are not limited to those shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram showing the constitution of printer <b>1</b>A according to the present embodiment. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, printer <b>1</b>A contains a CPU <b>11</b>, a ROM <b>12</b>, a RAM <b>13</b>, an operating panel unit <b>14</b>, a printing unit <b>15</b>, and a network interface <b>16</b>, all of which are interconnected by a bus <b>17</b> for exchanging signals.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0037">CPU <b>11</b> controls various parts indicated above and executes various arithmetic processes according to a program. ROM <b>12</b> stores various programs and parameters for controlling basic operations of printer <b>1</b>A. RAM <b>13</b> stores programs and data temporarily as a working area.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0038">Operating panel unit <b>14</b> consists of a display panel, fixed keys, indicator lamps and others used for various inputting and displaying purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0039">Printing unit <b>15</b> prints image data on printing paper by means of the electronic photograph method. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a drawing showing the structure of a printing unit <b>15</b> of printer <b>1</b>A. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, printing unit <b>15</b> is equipped with a sensitizing drum <b>151</b>, a charging roller <b>152</b>, a toner cartridge <b>153</b>, a developing roller <b>154</b>, a transfer roller <b>155</b>, a paper feeding tray <b>156</b>, a fixing roller <b>157</b>, and a paper discharge tray <b>158</b>. When image data is received, printing unit <b>15</b> uniformly charges the surface of sensitizing drum <b>151</b> by means of charging roller <b>152</b>, and attaches toner supplied from toner cartridge <b>153</b> by means of developing roller <b>154</b> to the electrostatic latent images on it, after exposing it with lights on the basis of the received image data. Next, the toner is transferred by transfer roller <b>155</b> to a sheet of printing paper transferred from paper feeding tray <b>156</b>, fixing roller <b>157</b> fixes the toner on the paper, and the paper with an image formed on it is discharged to paper discharge tray <b>158</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0040">In the present embodiment, printing unit <b>15</b> is using the cleaner-less method which enables the system to do development and cleaning simultaneously in the developing unit by optimizing the conditions of developing bias potential (JP-9-269709A). Printing unit <b>15</b> is capable of executing a cleaning sequence independent of the printing sequence, adjusting the development bias to the optimum level, and rotating sensitizing drum <b>151</b> one revolution, to cause the cycle of collecting the toner on sensitizing drum <b>151</b>, sensitizing drum <b>152</b>, and transfer roller <b>155</b> on the toner cartridge twice in a row, thus achieving the cleaning without fail.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0041">In the present embodiment, toner cartridge <b>153</b> is equipped with a cartridge memory <b>153</b>A with read and write capabilities, and printer <b>1</b>A is capable of judging whether the service life of the currently loaded toner cartridge has expired or not by accessing a cartridge memory <b>153</b>A. In other words, the information about the number of sheets that can be printed with said cartridge while maintaining the guaranteed quality, i.e., the service life information that represents the service life of said cartridge, is recorded in a certain area of cartridge memory <b>153</b>A when it is shipped by the manufacturers plant. Another area of cartridge memory <b>153</b>A holds the information about the accumulated number of sheets printed using said cartridge up until that time, i.e., the consumption information that represents the amount of usage of said cartridge memory at the present time.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0042">Cartridge memory <b>153</b>A is connected with bus <b>17</b> by signal lines in order to allow printer <b>1</b>A to access said specified area of cartridge memory <b>153</b>A to read the capacity number of printed sheets and the accumulated number of printed sheets, and to calculate the consumption rate (consumption rate=capacity number of printed sheets/accumulated number of printed sheets×100). It makes a judgment as to whether the consumption rate has exceeded the threshold value, and determines that the currently loaded toner cartridge's service life has not expired if the consumption rate is lower than the threshold value and that the currently loaded toner cartridge's service life has expired if the consumption rate exceeds the threshold value.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0043">As it is described later, the accumulated number of printed sheets is increased one each time when a page is printed and is never reduced. This way, the consumption rate never returns to zero even when the cartridge is refilled with toner by someone who is not the manufacturer of printer <b>1</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0044">Network interface <b>16</b> is an interface to connect with a network for communicating with other devices on the network using standards such as Ethernet®, Token Ring, FDDI, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0045">The printer driver for printer <b>1</b>A is installed on the operation system (OS) of PC<b>2</b> in order to generate the printing job from the application data and transmit it to printer <b>1</b>A, monitor the current status of the printing process, or control various settings of printer <b>1</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0046">Network <b>3</b> can be a LAN connecting computers and network equipment according to standards such as Ethernet®, Token Ring, and FDDI, or a WAN that consists of several LANs connected by a dedicated line.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0047">Next, the outline of the printing system according to this embodiment will be described below. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>A in the present embodiment. The algorithm indicated by the flowchart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is stored as a control program on ROM <b>12</b> of printer <b>1</b>A, read out by RAM <b>13</b>, and is executed by CPU <b>11</b> when the operation starts.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0048">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, printer <b>1</b>A waits until it receives the printing job from PC<b>2</b> (S<b>101</b>: No), accesses the specified area of cartridge memory <b>153</b>A of toner cartridge <b>153</b> of printing unit <b>15</b> to read the accumulated number of printed sheets and the capacity number of printed sheets of said toner cartridge onto RAM <b>13</b> (S<b>102</b>) when the printing job is received from PC<b>2</b> via network <b>3</b> and network interface <b>16</b> (S<b>101</b>: Yes), and calculates the consumption rate from these data (S<b>103</b>). The consumption rate thus obtained is compared with the predetermined threshold value to make a judgment whether said toner cartridge's service life has expired (S<b>104</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0049">If it is judged that the toner cartridge's service life has not expired (S<b>104</b>: No), the standard mode printing process is executed (S<b>105</b>). <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of the standard mode printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>A in the present embodiment. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, printer <b>1</b>A executes the cleaning process before and after of each printing job as well as during the recovery time when jamming occurs in the standard mode printing.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0050">In other words, printer <b>1</b>A conducts the cleaning process prior to the printing process for the printing job received in step S<b>101</b> (S<b>201</b>). Next, the data of the first page of the printing job is rasterized, and the image data obtained is printed and discharged (S<b>202</b> and S<b>203</b>). If a judgment is made as to whether any jam has occurred (S<b>204</b>) and it is judged that no jam has occurred (S<b>204</b>: No), another judgment is made as to whether the printing process for the printing job is completed (S<b>205</b>), and if it is determined that the printing process has not been completed (S<b>205</b>: No), the printing process of the next page is performed (S<b>206</b> and S<b>203</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0051">When it is judged that a jam has occurred in step S<b>204</b> (S<b>204</b>: Yes), it waits until the jam is recovered (S<b>207</b>), and executes the cleaning process (S<b>208</b>) when the jam is recovered with the jammed paper having been removed (S<b>207</b>: Yes), and then executes the same printing process for the same page again (S<b>203</b>). When the entire printing process of the printing job is completed (S<b>205</b>: Yes), executes the cleaning process (S<b>209</b>) to end the standard mode printing process.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0052">On the other hand, if it is determined that the toner cartridge's service life has expired in step S<b>104</b> (S<b>104</b>: Yes), a service life expiration notice is transmitted to PC <b>2</b> via network interface <b>16</b> and network <b>3</b> (S<b>106</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0053">The printer driver of PC <b>2</b> that received the service life expiration notice from printer <b>1</b>A, displays a dialog as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> to notify the user that the loaded toner cartridge's service life has expired to check if the safety mode printing is desired. It waits until the user's instruction is received, and transmits the user's instruction for the printing to be continued or cancelled to printer <b>1</b>A via network <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0054">When printer <b>1</b>A receives a printing cancellation order from PC <b>2</b> via network <b>3</b> and network interface <b>16</b> (S<b>107</b>: No), it cancels the printing job being processed (S<b>108</b>) to end the printing process.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0055">On the other hand, if it receives from PC <b>2</b> an order for continuing the printing process in step S<b>107</b> (S<b>107</b>: Yes), it executes the safety mode printing process. (S<b>109</b>). The safety mode here means an operating mode for preventing printing troubles, in other words, an operating mode for printing while enhancing the countermeasures against the deterioration of printing quality and reliability, printer malfunctions and the like, which also means increasing the frequencies of cleaning, calibration, and communication with the control center as well as lowering the printing speed in comparison with the standard mode.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0056"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of safety mode printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>A in the present embodiment. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, printer <b>1</b>A executes the cleaning process after printing each page as well as prior to each printing job and during the recovery time when jamming occurs in the safety mode printing.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0057">In other words, printer <b>1</b>A conducts the cleaning process prior to the printing process for the printing job received in step S<b>101</b> (S<b>301</b>). Next, the data of the first page of the printing job is rasterized, and the image data obtained is printed and discharged (S<b>302</b> and S<b>303</b>). Next, the accumulated number of printed sheets is incremented by one and is stored in the specified area of the cartridge memory <b>153</b>A of toner cartridge <b>153</b> (S<b>304</b>). If a judgment is made as to whether any jam has occurred (S<b>305</b>) and it is judged that no jam has occurred (S<b>305</b>: No), another judgment is made as to whether the printing process for the printing job is completed (S<b>307</b>) after the cleaning process (S<b>306</b>), and if it is determined that the printing process has not been completed (S<b>307</b>: No), the printing process of the next page is performed (S<b>308</b> and S<b>303</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0058">On the other hand, if it is judged that a jam has occurred in step S<b>305</b> (S<b>305</b>: Yes), it waits until the jam is recovered (S<b>309</b>), executes the cleaning process (S<b>310</b>) after the jam is recovered with the jammed paper having been removed (S<b>309</b>: Yes), and then executed the printing process for the same page again (S<b>303</b>). When the printing process of the printing job is all completed (S<b>307</b>: yes), the safety mode printing process is terminated.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0059">Next, the outline of the actions of a printing system equipped with a printing device according to the second embodiment of the present invention will be described. Similar to the printing system according to the first embodiment, the printing system according to this embodiment is equipped with a printer <b>1</b>B as a printing device and a PC <b>2</b> as a printing job transmission device, which are connected via a network <b>3</b> to communicate with each other (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). Printer <b>1</b>B has a similar constitution as printer <b>1</b>A according to said first embodiment (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0060">However, toner cartridge <b>153</b> of printer <b>1</b>B is equipped with a cartridge memory <b>153</b>B capable of reading and writing in place of cartridge memory <b>153</b>A, so that printer <b>1</b>B is capable of making a judgment on whether the loaded toner cartridge is a product authorized by the manufacturer of printer <b>1</b>B by accessing cartridge memory <b>153</b>B. More specifically, cartridge memory <b>153</b>B is connected to bus <b>17</b> via electrical signal lines and printer <b>1</b>B determines that the currently loaded toner cartridge is an unauthorized product when it detects that the loaded toner cartridge does not have a cartridge memory by detecting that said electrical signal lines are not communicating (inactive).</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0061">The product information that identifies said printer or said toner cartridge is written in a specified area of cartridge memory <b>153</b>B upon shipment from the manufacturer. When said signal lines are capable of transmission (active), printer <b>1</b>B accesses said specified area of cartridge memory <b>153</b>B to read out the product information, compares the currently read product information with the product information of the authorized product stored in ROM <b>12</b>, and determines that a toner cartridge of the authorized product is loaded if the current product information matches with that of the authorized product, or determines that a toner cartridge of the unauthorized product is loaded if the current product information does not match with that of the authorized product.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0062"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>B in the present embodiment. The algorithm indicated by the flowchart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is stored as a control program on ROM <b>12</b> of printer <b>1</b>B, read out by RAM <b>13</b>, and is executed by CPU <b>11</b> when the operation starts.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0063">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, printer <b>1</b>B waits until it receives the printing job from PC<b>2</b> (S<b>401</b>: No), accesses the specified area of cartridge memory <b>153</b>B of toner cartridge <b>153</b> of printing unit <b>15</b> to read the product information onto RAM <b>13</b> (S<b>402</b>) when the printing job is received from PC<b>2</b> via network <b>3</b> and network interface <b>16</b> (S<b>401</b>: Yes), and compares said product information with that of the authorized product to determine if said toner cartridge is an authorized product (S<b>403</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0064">If it is judged that the loaded toner cartridge is an authorized product (S<b>403</b>: Yes), the standard mode printing process is executed (S<b>404</b>). <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a flowchart showing the sequence of the standard mode printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>B in the present embodiment. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, printer <b>1</b>B executes the cleaning process before and after of each printing job as well as during the recovery time when jamming occurs in the standard mode printing.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0065">In other words, printer <b>1</b>B conducts the cleaning process prior to the printing process for the printing job received in step S<b>401</b> (S<b>501</b>) Next, the data of the first page of the printing job is rasterized, and the image data obtained is printed and discharged (S<b>502</b> and S<b>503</b>). If a judgment is made as to whether any jam has occurred (S<b>504</b>) and it is judged that no jam has occurred (S<b>504</b>: No), another judgment is made as to whether the printing process for the printing job is completed (S<b>505</b>), and if it is determined that the printing process has not been completed (S<b>505</b>: No), the printing process of the next page is performed (S<b>506</b> and S<b>503</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0066">When it is judged that a jam occurred in step S<b>504</b> (S<b>504</b>: Yes), it waits until the jam is recovered (S<b>507</b>), executes the cleaning process (S<b>508</b>) when the jam is recovered with the jammed paper having been removed (S<b>507</b>: Yes), and then executes the same printing process for the same page again (S<b>503</b>) When the entire printing process of the printing job is completed (S<b>505</b>: Yes), executes the cleaning process. (S<b>509</b>) to end the standard mode printing process.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0067">On the other hand, if it is determined that the toner cartridge is not an authorized product in step S<b>403</b> (S<b>403</b>: No), an unauthorized product notice is transmitted to PC <b>2</b> via network interface <b>16</b> and network <b>3</b> (S<b>405</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0068">The printer driver of PC <b>2</b> that received the unauthorized product notice from printer <b>1</b>B, displays a dialog as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> to notify the user that the loaded toner cartridge is not an authorized product to check if the safety mode printing is desired. It waits until the user's instruction is received, and transmits the user's instruction for the printing to be continued or cancelled to printer <b>1</b>B via network <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0069">When printer <b>1</b>B receives the printing cancellation order from PC <b>2</b> via network <b>3</b> and network interface <b>16</b> (S<b>406</b>: No), it cancels the printing job being processed (S<b>407</b>) to end the printing process.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0070">On the other hand, if it receives an order for continuing the printing process in step S<b>406</b> (S<b>406</b>: Yes), it executes the safety mode printing process (S<b>408</b>). FIG. <b>11</b> is a flowchart showing the sequence of the safety mode printing process by means of printer <b>1</b>B in the present embodiment. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, printer <b>1</b>B executes the cleaning process after printing each page as well as prior to each printing job and during the recovery time when jamming occurs in the safety mode printing.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0071">In other words, printer <b>1</b>B conducts the cleaning process prior to the printing process for the printing job received in step S<b>401</b> (S<b>601</b>). Next, the data of the first page of the printing job is rasterized, and the image data obtained is printed and discharged (S<b>602</b> and S<b>603</b>). If a judgment is made as to whether any jam has occurred (S<b>604</b>) and it is judged that no jam has occurred (S<b>604</b>: No), another judgment is made as to whether the printing process for the printing job is completed (S<b>606</b>) after the cleaning process (S<b>605</b>), and if it is determined that the printing process has not been completed (S<b>606</b>: No), the printing process of the next page is performed (S<b>607</b> and S<b>603</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0072">On the other hand, if it is judged that a jam has occurred in step S<b>604</b> (S<b>604</b>: Yes), it waits until the jam is recovered (S<b>608</b>), executes the cleaning process (S<b>609</b>) after the jam is recovered with the jammed paper having been removed (S<b>608</b>: Yes), and then executes the printing process of the same page again (S<b>603</b>). When the printing process of the printing job is all completed (S<b>606</b>: yes), the safety mode printing process is terminated.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0073">The present invention is not limited by the formats of the embodiments presented above, and can be improved or modified in designs without deviating from the gist of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0074">For example, the printer can be directly connected with PC (locally connected) by means of serial interfaces such as IEEE 1394 and USB, parallel interfaces such as IEEE 1284, or wireless telecommunication standard such as Bluetooth® IEEE 802.11, IrDA, without going through networks.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0075">The printer can be either a monochromatic or color printer. In case of a CMYK four color toner printer, the system can be so constituted to switch to the safety mode printing when one toner cartridge's service life has expired or it is an unauthorized product, or when all four color cartridges' service lives have expired or they are all unauthorized products.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0076">The printer can be of the electronic photograph type or the ink jet type, where, in case of the latter, a judgment is made on whether an ink cartridge's service life has expired or it is an authorized product.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0077">Also, a printer's judgment as to whether a toner cartridge's service life has expired or whether it is an authorized product can be made either when the toner cartridge is loaded, when the electric power is turned on, or at the start of printing, or can be executed multiple times.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0078">The system can also be constituted in such a way that the dialog displayed on the PC, when the toner cartridge's service life has expired or it is an unauthorized product, can include something that were not described in the above embodiments, for example, the choice of the standard mode printing and the safety mode printing.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0079">The dialog display on the PC can be made for each printing instruction or can be made only once. It can also be constituted in such a way that the user can choose whether it should be displayed or not afterwards.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0080">Although the service life information and the consumption information were described in the above embodiments that they were based on the number of sheets to be printed by the printer, they can also be based on the number of effective pixels (number of pixels other than white pixels) used in forming images, or the amount of toner consumed.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0081">Although the service life information was described in the above embodiments that it is read from the cartridge memory of the toner cartridge, it can be the service life information stored preliminarily in the ROM of the printer, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0082">Moreover, in the above embodiments, the safety mode was described as a mode in which printing is executed with an increased frequency of cleaning processes as compared to those of a standard mode, but it can also be a process of printing by increasing the frequency of calibration for compensating the image quality or the frequency of data transmission process for controlling the printing device status to the control center, or a process of printing at a lower speed for reducing the possibility of causing troubles such as jamming. Since a better quality of printing can be achieved by using only the authorized products, it can also have functions of displaying a warning that the present cartridge is an unauthorized or information about stores where the authorized products can be purchased.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0083">Although the printing device was described as a printer in the description of the embodiments, the present invention is not limited to it, and can be an MFP with a printing capability such as a digital copying machine and a facsimile device.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0084">The printing device and the method according to this invention can be realized by a dedicated hardware circuit for executing the abovementioned steps, or by causing a CPU to execute a program where said steps are described. If the present invention is to be materialized by the latter means, said programs for operating the printing device can be provided by computer-readable recording media such as a floppy® disk and CD-ROM, or can be provided on-line via a network such as the Internet. In this case, the program recorded on the computer-readable recording medium is normally transferred to and stored in a memory device such as ROM and a hard disk. The program can also be provided as independent application software or can be built into the software of the printing device as a part of its function.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0085">As can be seen from the above description, the printing device according to the present invention is capable of continuing the printing job without causing such troubles as deterioration of printing quality and reliability or printer malfunctions, when a developing agent cartridge whose service life has expired or a developing agent cartridge of unauthorized product is used.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller, comprising:
<claim-text>a judgment unit for judging whether a service life of a loaded developing agent cartridge has expired by accessing a memory unit built into said developing agent cartridge, said memory unit storing information concerning the service life of the developing agent cartridge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting unit for setting an operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment unit determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said safety mode is to execute a printing process with an increased cleaning frequency, an increased calibration frequency or an increased communication frequency with a control center compared to those of a standard mode,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A printing device described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a consumption information reading unit for reading consumption information that represents a consumption rate of said developing agent cartridge at a printed time stored in a memory unit of said developing agent cartridge, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said judgment unit determines whether the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired by comparing the consumption information of said developing agent cartridge read by said consumption information reading unit with preset service life information that represents the service life of said developing agent cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A printing device described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said consumption information and service life information are based on a number of printed sheets, a number of effective pixels used in forming images, or an amount of consumed developing agent.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A printing device described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said developing agent cartridge is either a toner cartridge or an ink cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller, comprising:
<claim-text>a judgment unit for judging whether a service life of a loaded developing agent cartridge has expired by accessing a memory unit built into said developing agent cartridge, said memory unit storing information concerning the service life of the developing agent cartridge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting unit for setting an operation mode to a safety mode in which a printing process is executed with an increased cleaning frequency compared to that of a standard mode when said judgment unit determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A printing device described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said cleaning frequency is such that cleaning is executed in every page of image formation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A printing method for printing with a printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller, comprising:
<claim-text>a judgment step of judging whether a service life of a loaded developing agent cartridge has expired by accessing a memory unit built into said developing agent cartridge, said memory unit storing information concerning the service life of the developing agent cartridge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting step of setting an operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment step determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said safety mode is to execute a printing process with an increased cleaning frequency, an increased calibration frequency or an increased communication frequency with a control center compared to those of a standard mode,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A printing method described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a consumption information reading step of reading consumption information that represents consumption rate of said developing agent cartridge at a printed time stored in a memory unit of said developing agent cartridge, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said judgment step determines whether the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired by comparing the consumption information of said developing agent cartridge read by said consumption information reading step with preset service life information that represents the service life of said developing agent cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A printing method described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said consumption information and service life information are based on a number of printed sheets, a number of effective pixels used in forming images, or an amount of consumed developing agent.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A printing method described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claims 7</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said developing agent cartridge is either a toner cartridge or an ink cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A printing method for printing with a printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller, comprising:
<claim-text>a judgment step of judging whether a service life of a loaded developing agent cartridge has expired by accessing a memory unit built into said developing agent cartridge, said memory unit storing information concerning the service life of the developing agent cartridge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting step of setting an operation mode to a safety mode in which a printing process is executed with an increased cleaning frequency compared to that of a standard mode when said judgment step determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A printing program for causing a printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller to execute:
<claim-text>a judgment step of judging whether a service life of a loaded developing agent cartridge has expired by accessing a memory unit built into said developing agent cartridge, said memory unit storing information concerning the service life of the developing agent cartridge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting step of setting an operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment step determines that the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A printing program described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further causing a printing device to execute:
<claim-text>a consumption information reading step of reading consumption information that represents a consumption rate of said developing agent cartridge at a printed time stored in a memory unit of said developing agent cartridge, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said judgment step determines whether the service life of said developing agent cartridge has expired by comparing the consumption information of said developing agent cartridge read by said consumption information reading step with preset service life information that represents the service life of said developing agent cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A printing program described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said consumption information and service life information are based on a number of printed sheets, a number of effective pixels used in forming images, or an amount of consumed developing agent.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A printing program described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said safety mode is to execute a printing process with an increased cleaning frequency, an increased calibration frequency or an increased communication frequency with a control center, or a reduced printing speed compared to those of a standard mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A printing program described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said developing agent cartridge is either a toner cartridge or an ink cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A computer-readable recording medium on which the printing program described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> is recorded.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller, comprising:
<claim-text>a judgment unit for judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting unit for setting an operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment unit determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said safety mode is to execute a printing process with an increased cleaning frequency, an increased calibration frequency or an increased communication frequency with a control center compared to those of a standard mode,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A printing device described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a product information reading unit for reading product information for identifying a product of said printing device or said developing agent cartridge stored in a memory unit of said developing agent cartridge, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said judgment unit determines whether said developing agent cartridge is an authorized product or not by comparing the product information read by said product information reading unit with a product information of an authorized product.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A printing device described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said developing agent cartridge is either a toner cartridge or an ink cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller, comprising:
<claim-text>a judgment unit for judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting unit for setting an operation mode to a safety mode in which a printing process is executed with an increased cleaning frequency compared to that of a standard mode when said judgment unit determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A printing device described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said cleaning frequency is such that cleaning is executed in every page of image formation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. A printing method for printing with a printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller, comprising:
<claim-text>a judgment step of judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting step of setting an operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment step determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said safety mode is to execute a printing process with an increased cleaning frequency, an increased calibration frequency or an increased communication frequency with a control center compared to those of a standard mode,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A printing method described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a product information reading step of reading product information for identifying a product of said printing device or said developing agent cartridge stored in a memory unit of said developing agent cartridge, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said judgment step determines whether said developing agent cartridge is an authorized product or not by comparing the product information read by said product information reading step with a product information of an authorized product.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. A printing method described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said developing agent cartridge is either a toner cartridge or an ink cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. A printing method for printing with a printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller, comprising:
<claim-text>a judgment step of judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting step of setting an operation mode to a safety mode in which a printing process is executed with an increased cleaning frequency compared to that of a standard mode when said judgment step determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. A printing method described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00026">claim 26</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said cleaning frequency is such that cleaning is executed in every page of image formation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. A computer-readable medium storing a printing program for causing a printing device having a sensitizing drum and a developing roller to execute:
<claim-text>a judgment step of judging whether a loaded developing agent cartridge is an authorized product; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operation mode setting step of setting an operation mode to a safety mode in order to prevent printing troubles when said judgment step determines that said developing agent cartridge is not an authorized product,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said safety mode is to execute a printing process with an increased cleaning frequency, an increased calibration frequency or an increased communication frequency with a control center compared to those of a standard mode,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the printing device prints by an electronic photograph method and collects toner remaining on the sensitizing drum by using the developing roller while rotating the sensitizing drum as a sequence independent of a printing sequence to clean the sensitizing drum, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the printing device increases cleaning frequency in the safety mode compared to the standard mode, the printing device executes a cleaning process per printing job in the standard mode and executes a cleaning process per printing page in the safety mode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. A printing program described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00028">claim 28</claim-ref> further causing a printing device to execute:
<claim-text>a product information reading step of reading product information for identifying a product of said printing device or said developing agent cartridge stored in a memory unit of said developing agent cartridge, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said judgment step determines whether said developing agent cartridge is an authorized product or not by comparing the product information read by said product information reading step with a product information of an authorized product.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. A printing program described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00028">claim 28</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>said developing agent cartridge is either a toner cartridge or an ink cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
