<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299208-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299208</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10117319</doc-number>
<date>20020405</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>Q</subclass>
<main-group>40</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>705 37</main-classification>
<further-classification>705 35</further-classification>
<further-classification>705 36 R</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Apparatus and system for defining an automated spread trading parameter</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5812987</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Luskin et al.</name>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>705 36 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6408282</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Buist</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>705 36 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6493682</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Horrigan et al.</name>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>705 36 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6519574</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wilton et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>705 35</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO 02/059711</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>31</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>705 10- 42</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>11</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bailon</last-name>
<first-name>Leoncio H.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Livingston</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zhang</last-name>
<first-name>Chengteng</first-name>
<address>
<city>Jersey City</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Buckley, Maschoff &amp; Talwalkar LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Goldman Sachs &amp; Co.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>New York</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Poinvil</last-name>
<first-name>Frantzy</first-name>
<department>3692</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">According to one embodiment, an apparatus includes a communication device adapted to communicate with a trader device via a temporary communication channel (e.g., via a Web site). The apparatus may receive from the trader device a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments and store the parameter for subsequent use (e.g., to automatically generate orders in accordance with a spread trading strategy).</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="93.98mm" wi="99.40mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="173.23mm" wi="161.37mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="175.68mm" wi="172.55mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="137.75mm" wi="101.52mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="183.64mm" wi="172.55mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="192.45mm" wi="176.36mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="204.39mm" wi="115.49mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="168.91mm" wi="173.99mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="170.69mm" wi="165.18mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="175.43mm" wi="171.53mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="210.65mm" wi="97.11mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="160.36mm" wi="161.04mm" file="US07299208-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is related to U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/117,715 entitled “Apparatus and System for Providing Automated Spread Trading Transaction Information” and filed concurrently herewith.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">COPYRIGHT AUTHORIZATION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A portion of the disclosure of the patent document contains material which is subject to copyright protection. The copyright owner has no objection to the facsimile reproduction by anyone of the patent document or the patent disclosure, as it appears in the Patent and Trademark Office patent file or records, but otherwise reserves all copyright rights whatsoever.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to spread trading. In particular, the present invention relates to an apparatus and system for defining an automated spread trading parameter.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">According to certain types of investment strategies, a trader simultaneously (or nearly simultaneously) purchases and sells associated investment instruments, such as stocks or bonds. In particular, the trader attempts to take advantage of a difference, or “spread,” between the prices of the associated instruments. For example, a trader might note that: (i) a first instrument can currently be purchased in a first market for $8.25, and (ii) a second instrument—which is expected to be priced the same as the first instrument—can currently be sold in a second market for $8.27. In this case, the trader would simultaneously purchase the first instrument and sell the second instrument to take advantage of the $0.02 price difference.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">There are a number of different types of spread trading strategies. For example, arbitrage trading is associated with differences in price when the same security, currency, or commodity is traded on two or more markets. As another example, index arbitrage trading exploits price differences between stock index futures and underlying stocks.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As still another example, risk arbitrage trading involves a purchase of stock in a company being acquired, referred to as a “target,” and a sale of stock in a proposed “acquirer” (e.g., a trader may attempt to profit on an expected rise in the price of the target's shares and drop in the price of the acquirer's shares).</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In general, the size of investments that are purchased and sold during spreading trading can be significant (e.g., because the price discrepancies tend to be relatively small). Moreover, spread trading investment strategies are time sensitive (e.g., markets can be expected to quickly correct any price discrepancies). As a result, it may not be practical for a trader to manually monitor investments and place orders based on his or her observations. Instead, a trader establishes a number of trading parameters (e.g., a price difference at which orders should be generated) and have an automated system monitor investments and generate orders as appropriate.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">For example, a trader might place a telephone call to an operator associated with an automated trading platform. The trader asks to have the platform monitor particular investments and generate orders based on trading parameters he or she verbally provides to the operator. Such an approach, however, may be inefficient for the trader (as well as for the trading platform), especially if the trader frequently adjusts the trading parameters (e.g., based on market conditions). Moreover, such an approach may lead to mistakes (e.g., the operator may incorrectly enter one or more parameters into the trading platform system).</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">As another approach, a trader might install a hard-wired computer communication channel to the automated trading platform (e.g., by leasing a dedicated access T1 line). A dedicated communication channel, however, can be expensive to install and maintain. As a result, this approach may not be feasible for traders who perform a only a limited amount of spread trading. In addition, the automated trading platform will only be able to accommodate a limited number of traders (e.g., based on a maximum number of dedicated lines that can be received by the platform).</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">To alleviate problems inherent in the prior art, the present invention introduces an apparatus and system for defining an automated spread trading parameter.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to one embodiment, a processor is coupled to a communication device adapted to communicate with a trader device via a temporary computer communication channel. A storage device in communication with the processor stores instructions adapted to be executed by the processor to (i) receive from the trader device a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments and (ii) store the received trading parameter for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to another embodiment, a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments is received from a trader device via a temporary computer communication channel. The received trading parameter is then stored for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to another embodiment, a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments is received from a trader device via a communication channel potentially accessible by a plurality of unrelated trader devices. The received trading parameter is then stored for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to another embodiment, a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments is received via a public computer communication network. The received trading parameter is then stored for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to still another embodiment, a trader identifier is received via a Web site and verified. The following information is then received via the Web site: an acquirer stock identifier, a target stock identifier, a selected risk arbitrage trading strategy, and an authorization to automatically generate orders in accordance with the strategy. The received information is then stored for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">According to yet another embodiment, a temporary computer communication channel is established with an automated spread trading system. A trading parameter for a pair of associated investments is then transmitted via the communication channel.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">One embodiment comprises: means for receiving from a trader device a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments, the receiving being performed via a temporary computer communication channel; and means for storing the received trading parameter for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Another embodiment comprises: means for receiving from a trader device a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments, the receiving being performed via a communication channel potentially accessible by a plurality of unrelated trader devices; and means for storing the received trading parameters for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Another embodiment comprises: means for receiving from a trader device a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments, the receiving being performed via a public computer communication network; and means for storing the received trading parameters for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Still another embodiment comprises: means for receiving a trader identifier via a Web site; means for verifying the trader identifier; means for receiving via the Web site an acquirer stock identifier, a target stock identifier, a selected risk arbitrage trading strategy, and an authorization to automatically generate orders in accordance with the strategy; and means for storing the received information for use by an automated spread trading system.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Yet another embodiment comprises: means for establishing a temporary computer communication channel with an automated spread trading system; and means for transmitting via the communication channel a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">With these and other advantages and features of the invention that will become hereinafter apparent, the invention may be more clearly understood by reference to the following detailed description of the invention, the appended claims, and the drawings attached herein.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram overview of a trading environment according to some embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram overview of an automated spread trading system according to some embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flow chart of a method according to some embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a deal dictionary display according to some embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates a deals display according to some embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a block diagram of an automated spread trading system according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a tabular representation of a portion of a client database according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a tabular representation of a portion of a trader database according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a tabular representation of a portion of a deal definition database according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a flow chart of a computer-implemented method of facilitating risk arbitrage trading according to some embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> illustrates a client, trader, and account hierarchy according to some embodiments of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a trading environment <b>100</b> according to some embodiments of the present invention. The trading environment <b>100</b> includes an automated spread trading system <b>600</b> in communication with a number of trader devices <b>10</b> and an order processing system <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The automated spread trading system <b>600</b>, the trader devices <b>10</b>, and the order processing system <b>30</b> may comprise any devices capable of performing the various functions described herein. For example, a trader device <b>10</b> may be a Personal Computer (PC) associated with a “trader.” As used herein, the term “trader” may refer to, for example, an individual or other entity that buys and sells investments (e.g., securities, stocks, bonds, options, or commodities). A trader device <b>10</b> may also comprise a portable computing device such as a laptop computer, a Personal Digital Assistant (PDA), a wired or wireless telephone, or any other appropriate storage and/or communication device.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may be, for example, a Web server adapted to exchange information with trader devices <b>10</b> and/or the order processing system <b>30</b>. As used herein, devices (e.g., the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> and the trader devices <b>10</b>) may communicate, for example, via a communication network <b>20</b>, such as an Internet Protocol (IP) network (e.g., the Internet). Note that the communication network <b>20</b> can also include a number of different networks, such as an intranet, a Local Area Network (LAN), a Metropolitan Area Network (MAN), a Wide Area Network (WAN), a proprietary network, a Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN), and/or a wireless network.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">According to some embodiments of the present invention, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> communicates with the trader device <b>10</b> via a temporary computer communication channel (e.g., a path through which information can be exchanged). In other words, the communication channel between the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> and a trader device <b>10</b> may be established and discontinued as appropriate. Note that an established communication channel does not need to be associated with a particular physical path. For example, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may exchange information with a trader device <b>10</b> via a Web site, in which case packets of information may be transmitted via various physical paths.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">According to other embodiments, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> communicates with the trader device <b>10</b> via a public computer communication network. That is, at least a portion of the communication network may be accessed by devices other than the automated trading system <b>600</b> and the trader device <b>10</b>. Note, however, that the information exchanged between the automated trading system <b>600</b> and the trader device <b>10</b> could be encrypted or otherwise protected to prevent a third party from accessing (i.e., understanding) the information.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">According to still other embodiments, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> communicates with the trader device <b>10</b> via a computer communication channel that is potentially accessible by a plurality of unrelated trader devices <b>10</b>. For example, a single port or line associated with the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> might communicate with a first trader device <b>10</b> for a period of time and then with a second, unrelated trader device <b>10</b> (i.e., the first and second trader devices <b>10</b> may be associated with different traders or clients).</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Although a single automated spread trading system <b>600</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, any number of these devices may be included in the trading environment <b>100</b>. Similarly, any number of trader devices <b>10</b>, order processing systems <b>30</b>, or any other device described herein may be included in the trading environment <b>100</b> according to embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The order processing system <b>30</b> may be, for example, a trade platform that arranges for orders to be executed based on information received from the automated spread trading system <b>600</b>. For example, the order processing system <b>30</b> may arrange for buy and sell orders to be executed via a market center or public exchange (e.g., the New York Stock Exchange). The order processing system <b>30</b> may be associated with, for example, a Web server or third-party order processing service.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Note that some of devices illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> may actually be incorporated in a single device. For example, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may also act as an order processing system <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">According to an embodiment of the present invention, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> receives from a trader device <b>10</b> one or more trading parameters for a pair of associated investments. For example, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> might receive stock identifiers associated with an acquirer and a target (e.g., “GE” and “HON”). The automated spread trading system <b>600</b> might also receive an indication of a trading strategy (e.g., associated with a particular risk arbitrage trading strategy). The automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may then store the received trading parameters.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram overview of the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> according to some embodiments of the present invention. As can be seen, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> includes a deal dictionary tool <b>602</b> (e.g., an investment pair setup tool). The deal dictionary tool <b>602</b> may comprise, for example, an application or engine that exchanges information with a trader device <b>10</b>. The deal dictionary tool <b>602</b> helps a trader set up one or more deals (e.g., each deal being associated with a pair of investments). In particular, the deal dictionary tool <b>602</b> may let the trader establish trading parameters for the deal. Note that some or all of the functions described with respect to the deal dictionary tool <b>602</b> may instead be performed at a trader device <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">According to one embodiment, a trader selects one or more trading strategies associated with a risk arbitrage deal. For example, a trader might select limits, distribution, dollar-to-dollar, share-to-share, and/or order-for-order trading strategies. According to another embodiment, the trader selects a strategy for a deal associated with fixed income investments (e.g., government, corporate, or municipal bonds). For example, the trader might define a spread between two treasury investments (e.g., treasury bills, notes, or bonds) at which buy and sell orders should be automatically generated. According to another embodiment, the trader selects a strategy associated with two baskets of investment instruments (e.g., two mutual funds) that are somehow statistically related.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In the case of a risk arbitrage deal, the trading parameters defined via the deal dictionary tool <b>602</b> might include information about a potential acquirer, such as a stock name, a dividend amount, a sell action (e.g., “sell long only,” “sell short only” or a “mixed” sell action indicating that the action type should be determined by an actual position share number in an account), and/or an indication that orders should only be generated in “round lots” (i.e., generally accepted units of trading). Other information may indicate whether the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> should initiate orders of a target stock. Similar information about a potential target may also be defined via the deal dictionary tool <b>602</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Other trading parameters for the deal might include a ratio value (e.g., a value indicating a share converting ratio), a spread ration (e.g., a dollar spread discussed below), a cash value (e.g., a value indicating a converting cash amount), a cash balance, a hedge type (e.g., options of hedge for dollar and hedge for share), and a hedge ratio (e.g., which may default to a spread ration for dollar hedge but not for share hedge). Similarly, the trader may define a maximum position, such as a maximum target position share amount that will limit the trader's stake in the deal. The trader may also define a percent per tick value reflecting a percent of maximum target position shares per “tick” (e.g., an upward or downward price movement) to be applied on pair initiate orders.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">According to some embodiments, the trading parameters may include a setup limit (e.g., a sell spread limit dollar or percentage amount) and a setup position, such as a maximum setup target position associated with selling an acquirer investment and purchasing a target investment (e.g., a dollar value for a dollar hedge or a share value for a share hedge). Similarly, the trading parameters may include a setup position per order (e.g., an initiating order share number or dollar value depending on the associated hedge type).</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Moreover, the trading parameters might include an unwind limit (e.g., a buy spread limit dollar or percentage amount) and an unwind position, such as a maximum unwind target position associated with selling a target investment and purchasing an acquirer investment (e.g., a dollar value for a dollar hedge or a share value for a share hedge). Similarly, the trading parameters may include an unwind position per order (e.g., an initiating order share number or dollar value depending on the associated hedge type).</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The deal dictionary tool <b>602</b> may also be used to establish a quote range (e.g., in dollars), an order time interval (e.g., a time constraint between consecutive orders that are initiated), and/or a sell short constraint which may be applicable for trading strategies that allow both sell and buy initiate orders (e.g., dollar-to-dollar limits).</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Moreover, the deal dictionary tool <b>602</b> may be used to define a strategy (e.g., a limit or distribution strategy), a spread type (e.g., a dollar, yield, or yield close spread type), a cancel/replace increment (e.g., when the limit price of an initiate order moves above a dollar amount the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may send a cancel/replace order with a new limit price), a liquidity constraint (e.g., in terms of percentage of current open size of other side), a short tick allowance (e.g., adjustment of spread limits for setup and unwind if the price type of balance order is sell short), a balance buy type (e.g., price type of balance buy order), a balance sell type (e.g., a price type of balance sell order), a buy offset (e.g., an adjustment of limit price of balance buy order), a sell offset (e.g., an adjustment of limit price of balance sell order), a balance order unit, and/or a balance order multiplier.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In the case of a dollar spread, an upper limit (e.g. a sell spread limit in dollars) and a lower limit (e.g., a buy spread limit in dollars) may be defined. For example, a “bid spread” may be defined as:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>BB</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>bid</sub><i>−A</i><sub>div</sub>)*ratio+cash−(<i>T</i><sub>bid</sub><i>−T</i><sub>div</sub>)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
where A<sub>bid </sub>is associated with an acquirer bid, A<sub>div </sub>is associated with an acquirer dividend, T<sub>bid </sub>is associated with a target bid, and T<sub>div </sub>is associated with a target dividend. Similarly, an “ask spread” may be defined as:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>AA</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>ask</sub><i>−A</i><sub>div</sub>)*ratio+cash−(<i>T</i><sub>ask</sub><i>−T</i><sub>div</sub>)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Moreover, a “bid-ask spread” and an “ask-bid spread” may be defined as, respectively:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>BA</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>bid</sub><i>−A</i><sub>div</sub>)*ratio+cash−(<i>T</i><sub>ask</sub><i>−T</i><sub>div</sub>)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>AB</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>ask</sub><i>−A</i><sub>div</sub>)*ratio+cash−(<i>T</i><sub>bid</sub><i>−T</i><sub>div</sub>)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
and a “last spread” may be defined as:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>LL</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>last</sub><i>−A</i><sub>div</sub>)*ratio+cash−(<i>T</i><sub>last</sub><i>—T</i><sub>div</sub>)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In the case of a yield spread, these values may instead be defined as follows:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>BB</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>bid</sub><i>/T</i><sub>bid</sub>)*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>AA</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>ask</sub><i>/T</i><sub>ask</sub>)*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>BA</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>bid</sub><i>/T</i><sub>ask</sub>)*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>AB</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>ask</sub><i>/T</i><sub>bid</sub>)*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>LL</i>=(<i>A</i><sub>last</sub><i>/T</i><sub>last</sub>)*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In the case of a yield close spread, the values may be defined as:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>BB</i>=((<i>A</i><sub>bid</sub><i>/A</i><sub>close</sub>)−(<i>T</i><sub>bid</sub><i>/T</i><sub>close</sub>))*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>AA</i>=((<i>A</i><sub>ask</sub><i>/A</i><sub>close</sub>)−(<i>T</i><sub>ask</sub><i>/T</i><sub>close</sub>))*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>BA</i>=((<i>A</i><sub>bid</sub><i>/A</i><sub>close</sub>)−(<i>T</i><sub>ask</sub><i>/T</i><sub>close</sub>))*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>AB</i>=((<i>A</i><sub>ask</sub><i>/A</i><sub>close</sub>)−(<i>T</i><sub>bid</sub><i>/T</i><sub>close</sub>))*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>spread-<i>LL</i>=((<i>A</i><sub>last</sub><i>/A</i><sub>close</sub>)−(<i>T</i><sub>last</sub><i>/T</i><sub>close</sub>))*100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The automated spread trading system <b>600</b> also includes an automated trading strategy component <b>604</b>. The automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> may comprise, for example, one or more agents that use trading parameters associated with a deal and market information to determine if buy and/or sell orders should be automatically generated. That is, following a trading strategy selected by the trader, the automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> may control the initial order process and manage existing open orders. Note that the automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> may receive market data and trading information (e.g., associated with open orders and positions) in substantially real-time and process the data to issue subsequent orders based on trading parameters. The order messages may then be transmitted to the order processing system <b>30</b> for eventual execution.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In the case of a limits trading strategy, sell orders may be triggered when pre-determined offer prices (e.g., calculated using spread limits and ask prices of the opposite side in the deal) are above, at, or lower than the current ask price as appropriate. In particular, the pre-determined offer prices for selling the acquirer stock and selling the target stock may be defined as, respectively:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>A</i><sub>offer</sub>=((<i>T</i><sub>ask</sub><i>−T</i><sub>div</sub>)+Upper Limit−cash)/ratio and<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>T</i><sub>offer</sub>=(<i>A</i><sub>ask</sub><i>−T</i><sub>div</sub>)*ratio+cash−Lower Limit.<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Note that the calculated prices may be rounded-off as desired. When A<sub>offer </sub>is less than or equal to (A<sub>ask</sub>+Quote Range) or B<sub>offer </sub>is less than or equal to (T<sub>ask</sub>+Quote Range), a sell order is generated by the automated trading strategy component <b>604</b>. Note that ambiguous sale decisions could result if the separation between spread limits is defined as less than 2*Quote Range.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">According to one embodiment, the automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> generates a “cancel” request (e.g., indicating that an outstanding order should be cancelled) when the selling condition described above fails. Moreover, when the A<sub>offer</sub>/T<sub>offer </sub>price moves away from the last order price, a “cancel and replace” order may be generated to take advantage of the new price.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">According to some embodiments of the present invention, the current position balance is monitored. When a sell order on one side is partially filled, the automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> can then place a market buy order for a corresponding amount on the opposite side.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The number of shares for each sell order may be set, for example, as the lesser of (i) a trader-defined percentage of a maximum position and (ii) a percentage (e.g., a liquidate constraint) of a current ask size for the balance side.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">According to some embodiments, the automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> imposes a time delay: (i) between two orders on the same investment instrument and/or (ii) between a balancing order and a subsequent initiating order. By way of example, the time delay could be twenty four seconds or another value defined by a trader via the deal dictionary tool <b>602</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Consider now a “distribution” trading strategy to be used when a trader wants to maintain positions at different spreads for a particular deal. For example, such a strategy might utilize a distribution file that can be modified by the trader in substantially real time. Table I illustrates values for a such a distribution file:</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="1">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="217pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="1" rowsep="1">TABLE I</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="1" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Distribution File Illustration</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="4">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="14pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="63pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="77pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="63pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Deal Identifier</entry>
<entry>Desired Acquire Position</entry>
<entry>Spread</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="3" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="4">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="14pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="63pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="77pt" align="char" char="."/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="63pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>AOL_TWX</entry>
<entry>−5,000</entry>
<entry>above 3.0</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>AOL_TWX</entry>
<entry>−3,000</entry>
<entry>2.5 to 3.0</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>AOL_TWX</entry>
<entry>−1,000</entry>
<entry>2.0 to 2.5</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>AOL_TWX</entry>
<entry>0</entry>
<entry>1.5 to 2.0</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>AOL_TWX</entry>
<entry>2,000</entry>
<entry>1.0 to 1.5</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>AOL_TWX</entry>
<entry>5,000</entry>
<entry>below 1.0</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="3" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
<br/>
Now assume that (i) the current ask-spread (e.g., the difference between the last ask prices of “AOL” shares and “TWX” shares) is 1.7 and (ii) the trader does not have any position in the account. Since the spread is currently between 1.5 and 2.0, the target position is “0” shares.
</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">When the current ask-spread moves above 2.0, the desired position now becomes “−1,000.” The automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> sells spread (i.e., sells AOL shares and buys TWX shares) until the desired position is reached (i.e., “−1,000” shares).</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">When the current ask-spread moves back below 2.0, the desired position again becomes “0.” The automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> buys spread (i.e., sells TWX shares and buys AOL shares) until the desired position is reached (i.e., “0” shares).</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> also includes a system risk control tool <b>606</b>. The system risk control tool <b>606</b> may, for example, let a trader, a client, and/or an operator associated with the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> establish various trading activity constraints. For example, the system risk control tool <b>606</b> might halt trading for a specific deal or an entire account when a constraint is exceeded. Similarly, an order might only be generated when time, size, dollar, liquidity, and/or system availability parameters are met.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The constraint parameters monitored by the system risk control tool <b>606</b> may include, for example, a maximum share amount or dollar position for each deal, a maximum open order share amount or dollar amount for each deal, and/or a maximum number of open orders for each deal. Similarly, the system risk control tool <b>606</b> might monitor these parameters on an account basis (e.g., reflecting a number of different deals). As another example, the system risk control tool <b>606</b> might ensure that a limit order price is within a predetermined range of a current market price.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">According to one embodiment, a risk parameters is automatically determined based on trader information. For example, all traders associated with a particular client may be assigned a particular risk parameter (e.g., a $10,000 trading limit). According to another embodiment, a system operator provides the risk parameter which is then stored for use by the system risk control tool <b>606</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">According to another embodiment, the system risk control tool <b>600</b> also verifies system information. For example, if a component crashes or improper messages are detected, the system risk control tool <b>606</b> could automatically halt trading for investments that might be associated with the problem.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Trading System Method</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flow chart of a method that may be performed by the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> according to some embodiments of the present invention. The flow charts described herein do not imply a fixed order to the steps, and embodiments of the present invention may be practiced in any order that is practicable.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">At <b>302</b>, a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments is received from a trader device <b>10</b> via a temporary computer communication channel. For example, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may receive the trading parameter via a Web site. The pair of investments may be associated, for example, because they have been selected by the trader and/or because of an underlying statistical relationship (or perceived statistical relationship). According to some embodiments, a trading parameter may be associated with more than two investments (e.g., a trader might define a deal associated with three or more investments). The information received by the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> might include, for example, a trader identifier, a trader device identifier, a client identifier, and/or an account identifier.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">According to one embodiment, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> receives a trading parameter associated with risk arbitrage trading, and the pair of associated investments comprise an acquirer stock and a target stock. According to another embodiment, at least one of the investments is associated with a plurality of investments (e.g., one investment might be a mutual fund). According to still another embodiment, the received trading parameter is associated a fixed income trading strategy.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a deal dictionary display <b>400</b> (e.g., displayed via a trader device <b>10</b>) according to some embodiments of the present invention. In particular, the display <b>400</b> comprises a Graphical User Interface (GUI) that a trader can use to define stock pairs and other trading parameters for a risk arbitrage deal. The display <b>400</b> may be generated by, for example, a JAVA™ applet transmitted from the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> to the trader device <b>10</b>. According to another embodiment, the trader instead defines one or more trading parameters by exporting or otherwise providing information from another application (e.g., a MICROSOFT EXCEL® spreadsheet).</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">As can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the trading parameter defined via the display <b>400</b> can include one or more investment identifiers (e.g., stock identifies associated with the acquirer and the target). According to some embodiments, the trader may also define a deal identifier (e.g., “GE_HON” not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>). The information may also include a service and/or an exchange associated with the deal (e.g., “NYX” and “NYSE,” respectively).</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">For each of the acquirer and target investments, the trader may further define a dividend value, a sell action (e.g., “mixed”), a round lot indication (e.g., indicating that orders should only be generated for round lots, and/or an order initiation indication. Other trading parameters that may be established via the display <b>400</b> include a lower limit, an upper limit, a ratio, and/or a cash value.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">The trader may also define a trading strategy associated with the pair of investments, such as a follow spread strategy, a distribution strategy, a dollar-to-dollar strategy, a share-to-share strategy, and/or an order-for-order strategy.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">As can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the display <b>400</b> may also be used to establish one or more of the following trading parameters: a Minimum Price Variation (MPV), a maximum position, a percent per tick, a liquidate constraint, a quote range, a time interval, a sell short constraint, a balance buy type, a balance sell type, an over balance multiple, a per spread above bid, a per spread below offer, and/or an over balance spread.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The trader may also activate areas on the display to indicate that the deal should executed, reset (e.g., returned to default values), deleted, or dismissed.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates a deals display <b>500</b> according to some embodiments of the present invention. In particular, the display <b>500</b> is providing information about a single risk arbitration deal (i.e., having an identifier of “GE_HON”). Note that the deals display <b>500</b> could provide information about a number of different deals defined by a trader.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">For each deal, the deals display indicates whether or not orders are being automatically generated (i.e., as indicated by a check mark). The trader may activate this area to select and de-select this indication to authorize the automatic generation of orders in accordance with the strategy he or she selected via the deal dictionary tool <b>602</b>. According to one embodiment, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> automatically cancels any outstanding orders associated with a deal when this indication is deselected.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">For each deal, the deal display <b>500</b> displays a target and acquirer asking price, a lower limit, an ask spread, a target bid, and an acquirer bid. Moreover, other information about each deal could be displayed. For example, for each deal some or all of the following information might be provided: a target bid, an acquirer bid, a last target value, and a last acquirer value.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">The lower portion of the display <b>500</b> may provide information about all orders (e.g., including orders that have been executed), open orders, or rejected orders as selected by the trader. In particular, for each order the following information is provided: an account identifier, a stock symbol, the side of the order (e.g., buy or sell), the number of shares associated with the order, a price associated with the order (e.g., a limit price and average price), and a time associated with the order (e.g., the time the order was created and the time the transaction was executed). Moreover, other information about each order could be displayed, such as: an order dollar amount, an order lot size, a number of shares that have been filled, and/or a number of shares that remain open. The trader may also select to clear the order portion of the display <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">The information on the deals display <b>500</b> may be updated in substantially real time (e.g., once every second). Note that different portions of the deals display <b>500</b> may be updated at different rates. Moreover, the deals display <b>500</b> might provide information on an account, a trader, a client, and/or a system basis.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">In addition to the trading parameters described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, other information could be defined for a deal (e.g., via the deal dictionary tool <b>602</b>), such as: a date, a time (e.g., indicating that orders should be automatically generated until 2:00 PM), a duration (e.g., indicating that orders should be automatically generated for the next three hours), start information, and/or end information (e.g., a trigger that will halt the automatic generation of orders). According to another embodiment, the trader may define an alternate communication address independent of the temporary computer communication channel. For example, the trader might provide a telephone number or an electronic mail address that should be used to contact the trader when a defined trigger is satisfied.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">At <b>304</b>, the received trading parameter is stored for use by the automated spread trading system <b>600</b>. For example, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may locally store the trading parameter in a database. The trading parameter may be stored in association with, for example, a particular trader, a client associated with a plurality of traders, and/or one of a plurality of accounts associated with a trader. Note that the trading parameter may still be stored after the temporary computer communication channel is discontinued. For example, a set of trading parameters might be stored even after a trader leaves a Web site. In this way, orders can be automatically generated when the trader is not currently in communication with the automated spread trading system <b>600</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">Automated Spread Trading System</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates an automated spread trading system <b>600</b> that is descriptive of the device shown, for example, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> according to an embodiment of the present invention. The automated spread trading system <b>600</b> comprises a processor <b>610</b>, such as one or more INTEL® Pentium® processors, coupled to a communication device <b>620</b> configured to communicate via, for example, (i) a temporary computer communication channel, (ii) a computer communication channel potentially accessible by a number of unrelated trader devices <b>10</b>, (iii) a public computer communication network, and/or (iv) any other type communication channel or network. The communication device <b>620</b> may be used to communicate, for example, with one or more trader devices <b>10</b> and order processing systems <b>30</b>. According to one embodiment, the communication device <b>620</b> is also used to communicate with other automated spread trading systems.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">The processor <b>610</b> is also in communication with a storage device <b>630</b>. The storage device <b>630</b> may comprise any appropriate information storage device, including combinations of magnetic storage devices (e.g., magnetic tape and hard disk drives), optical storage devices, and/or semiconductor memory devices such as Random Access Memory (RAM) devices and Read Only Memory (ROM) devices.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">The storage device <b>630</b> stores a program <b>615</b> for controlling the processor <b>610</b>. The processor <b>610</b> performs instructions of the program <b>615</b>, and thereby operates in accordance with the present invention. For example, the processor <b>610</b> may receive from a trader device <b>10</b> a trading parameter for a pair of associated investments. The processor <b>610</b> may then store the received trading parameter for subsequent use.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">According to one embodiment, the processor <b>610</b> receives a trader identifier via a Web site and verifies the trader identifier. The processor <b>610</b> then receives the following information via the Web site: an acquirer stock identifier, a target stock identifier, a selected risk arbitrage trading strategy, and an authorization to automatically generate orders in accordance with the strategy. This information is then stored by the processor <b>610</b> for subsequent use.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">As used herein, information may be “received” by or “transmitted” to, for example: (i) the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> from a trader device <b>10</b> or an order processing system <b>30</b>; or (ii) a software application or module within the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> from another software application, module, or any other source.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the storage device <b>630</b> also stores: a client database <b>700</b> (described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>); a trader database <b>800</b> (described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>); and a deal definition database <b>900</b> (described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>). Examples of databases that may be used in connection with the trading environment <b>100</b> will now be described in detail with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 through 9</figref>. The illustrations and accompanying descriptions of the databases presented herein are exemplary, and any number of other database arrangements could be employed besides those suggested by the figures.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">Client Database</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a table represents the client database <b>700</b> that may be stored at the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention. The table includes entries identifying clients that may define deals via the trading environment <b>100</b>. The table also defines fields <b>702</b>, <b>704</b>, <b>706</b>, <b>708</b>, <b>710</b>, <b>712</b> for each of the entries. The fields specify: a client identifier <b>702</b>, a name <b>704</b>, an address <b>706</b>, a payment identifier <b>708</b>, a limit <b>710</b>, and a current amount <b>712</b>. The information in the client database <b>700</b> may be created and updated, for example, based on information received from trader devices <b>10</b> and/or an operator associated with the automatic spread trading system <b>600</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">The client identifier <b>702</b> may be an alphanumeric code associated with a particular client. The name <b>704</b> and address <b>706</b> indicate the name and address of the client, respectively, and the payment identifier <b>708</b> may be, for example, a credit card or bank account number used to exchange payments with the client. The limit <b>710</b> may be a maximum dollar position associated with the client, and the current amount <b>712</b> may indicate the client's current dollar position.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">Trader Database</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, a table represents the trader database <b>800</b> that may be stored at the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention. The table includes entries identifying traders that may define deals via the trading environment <b>100</b>. The table also defines fields <b>802</b>, <b>804</b>, <b>806</b>, <b>808</b>, <b>810</b> for each of the entries. The fields specify: a trader identifier <b>802</b>, a client identifier <b>804</b>, accounts <b>806</b>, a limit <b>808</b>, and a current amount <b>810</b>. The information in the trader database <b>800</b> may be created and updated, for example, based on information received from trader devices <b>10</b> and/or an operator associated with the automatic spread trading system <b>600</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">The trader identifier <b>802</b> may be an alphanumeric code associated with a particular trader (e.g., a user name and/or password). The client identifier <b>804</b> indicates a client associated with the trader and may be based on, or associated with, the client identifier <b>702</b> stored in the client database <b>700</b>. For example, as illustrated by the first two entries in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the trader identified as “Jones” and the trader identified as “Greene” are both associated with a single client (i.e., identified as “ABC”).</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0100">The accounts <b>806</b> indicate one or more accounts associated with that trader. The limit <b>808</b> may be a maximum dollar position associated with the trader, and the current amount <b>810</b> may indicate the trader's current dollar position.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0101">Deal Definition Database</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0102">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, a table represents the deal database <b>900</b> that may be stored at the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention. The table includes entries identifying deals that have been defined by traders. The table also defines fields <b>902</b>, <b>904</b>, <b>906</b>, <b>908</b>, <b>910</b>, <b>912</b> for each of the entries. The fields specify: a deal identifier <b>902</b>, a trader identifier <b>904</b>, an acquirer <b>906</b>, a target <b>908</b>, a strategy <b>910</b>, and orders <b>912</b>. The information in the deal database <b>900</b> may be created and updated, for example, based on information received from trader devices <b>10</b> and/or an order processing system <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0103">The deal identifier <b>902</b> may be an alphanumeric code associated with a deal that has been defined by a trader. The trader identifier <b>904</b> may indicate the trader who defined the deal and may be based on, or associated with, the trader identifier <b>802</b> stored in the trader database <b>800</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0104">The acquirer <b>906</b> and the target <b>908</b> indicate a pair of investments associated with the deal. The acquirer <b>906</b> and the target <b>908</b> may comprise, for example, identifiers associated with a pair of stocks. The strategy <b>910</b> may indicate a trading strategy that should be used to automatically generate orders for the deal (e.g., a limits or distribution trading strategy). The orders <b>912</b> represent orders that have been automatically generated in accordance with the strategy <b>910</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0105">Risk Arbitrage Method</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0106"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a flow chart of a computer-implemented method of facilitating risk arbitrage trading according to some embodiments of the present invention. The method may be performed, for example, by the automated spread trading system <b>600</b>. At <b>1002</b>, a trader identifier is received via a Web site. For example, a trader may use a trader device <b>10</b> to provide a user name and password to a Web site associated with the automated spread trading system <b>600</b>. At <b>1004</b>, the trader identifier is verified. For example, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may verify the trader identifier using information stored in the client database <b>700</b> and/or the trader database <b>800</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0107">An acquirer stock identifier is received at <b>1006</b>, a target stock identifier is received at <b>1008</b>, and a selected risk arbitrage trading strategy is received at <b>1010</b>. For example, the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may receive this information from a trader device <b>10</b> via the Web site. An authorization to automatically generate orders in accordance with the strategy is received at <b>1012</b>. For example, the trader may activate the deal via the deals display <b>500</b> described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0108">The received information is then stored at <b>1014</b> for use by the automated spread trading system <b>600</b>. For example, the acquirer <b>906</b>, the target <b>908</b>, and the strategy <b>910</b> in the deal definition database <b>900</b> may be updated as appropriate.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0109">Clients, Traders, and Accounts</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0110"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> illustrates clients, traders, and accounts according to some embodiments of the present invention. In particular, a hierarchy <b>1100</b> illustrates how the automated spread trading system <b>600</b> may organize a number of clients, traders, and accounts. Note that a single client may be associated with a number of different traders—and that a single trader may be associated with a number of different accounts.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0111">One or more trading parameters may be stored on a client basis. For example, all deals defined for a client may be associated with a default “limits” trading strategy. Similarly, a trading parameter could be stored on a trader or account basis. Note that the system risk control tool <b>606</b> may monitor trading activity on one or more of a client, trader, and/or account level.</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">ADDITIONAL EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0113" num="0112">The following illustrates various additional embodiments of the present invention. These do not constitute a definition of all possible embodiments, and those skilled in the art will understand that the present invention is applicable to many other embodiments. Further, although the following embodiments are briefly described for clarity, those skilled in the art will understand how to make any changes, if necessary, to the above-described apparatus and methods to accommodate these and other embodiments and applications.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0113">Although embodiments of the present invention have been described with respect to trading parameters stored at the automated spread trading system <b>600</b>, according to other embodiments some or all of the trading parameters are instead stored at the trader device <b>10</b>. For example, default trading parameters may be stored at the trader device <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0114">Moreover, according to one embodiment the automated trading strategy component <b>604</b> is incorporated into the trader device <b>10</b> (e.g., the trader device <b>10</b> may receive market information and automatically generate orders based on a trading strategy).</p>
<p id="p-0116" num="0115">The present invention has been described in terms of several embodiments solely for the purpose of illustration. Persons skilled in the art will recognize from this description that the invention is not limited to the embodiments described, but may be practiced with modifications and alterations limited only by the spirit and scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An apparatus, comprising:
<claim-text>a processor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a communication device coupled to said processor and adapted to communicate with a trader device via a temporary computer communication channel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a storage device in communication with said processor and storing instructions adapted to be executed by said processor to:
<claim-text>receive via the communication device an indication of a first investment from said trader device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receive via the communication device an indication of a second investment from the trader device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>store an association between the first investment and the second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receive from the trader device a trading parameter to be associated with both the first and second investments, said receiving the trading parameter being performed via the communication device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>store the received trading parameter, in association with both the first and second investments, for use by an automated spread trading system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>retrieve the stored trading parameter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmit the stored trading parameter, via the communication device, to the trader device for display to a trader.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said storage device further stores at least one of: (i) a client database, (ii) a trader database, or (iii) a deal definition database.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said communication device is adapted to communicate with at least one of: (i) the trader device, (ii) an order processing system, (iii) an automated spread trading system, (iv) a deal dictionary tool, (v) an automated trading strategy component, or (vi) a system risk control tool.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A method to facilitate spread trading, comprising:
<claim-text>receiving from a trader device an indication of a first investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving from the trader device an indication of a second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing an association between the first investment and the second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving from the trader device a trading parameter to be associated with both the first and second investments, said receiving the trading parameter being performed via a temporary computer communication channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing the received trading parameter, in association with both the first and second investments, for use by an automated spread trading system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>retrieving the stored trading parameter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the stored trading parameter, via the temporary computer communication channel, to the trader device for display to a trader.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the communication channel is associated with a Web site.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trader device is associated with at least one of: (i) the trader, or (ii) a client associated with a plurality of traders.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the automated spread trading system is associated with a risk arbitrage trading strategy.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the first investment comprises an acquirer stock and the second investment comprises a target stock.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein at least one of the investments are associated with a plurality of investments.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the automated spread trading system is associated with a fixed income strategy.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter comprises at least one of: (i) a trader identifier, (ii) a trader device identifier, (iii) a client identifier, or (iv) an account identifier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter comprises at least one of: (i) an investment identifier, (ii) a stock identifier, or (iii) a deal identifier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter comprises at least one of: (i) a service, or (ii) an exchange.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter comprises at least one of: (i) a dividend value, (ii) a sell action, (iii) a round lot indication, or (iv) an order initiation indication.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter comprises at least one of: (i) a lower limit, (ii) an upper limit, (iii) a ratio, or (iv) a cash value.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter comprises a strategy associated with the first and second investments.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the strategy comprises at least one of: (i) a follow spread strategy, (ii) a distribution strategy, (iii) a dollar-to-dollar strategy, (iv) a share-to-share strategy, or (v) an order-for-order strategy.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter comprises an authorization to automatically generate orders in accordance with the strategy.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter comprises at least one of: (i) a date, (ii) a time, (iii) a duration, (iv) start information, (v) end information, or (vi) a communication address independent of the temporary computer communication channel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said storing comprises storing the information in association with at least one of: (i) one of a plurality of traders, (ii) a client associated with a plurality of traders, or (iii) one of a plurality of accounts associated with a trader.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>receiving a trader identifier; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>verifying the trader identifier.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>determining risk control information.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein the risk control information comprises at least one of: (i) a maximum share position for the pair of investments, (ii) a maximum dollar position for the pair of investments, (iii) a maximum share position for an account, (iv) a maximum dollar position for an account, (v) a maximum open order shares amount for the pair of investments, (vi) a maximum open dollar amount for the pair of investments, (vii) a maximum number of open orders for the pair of investments, (viii) a maximum open order shares amount for an account, (ix) a maximum open dollar amount for an account, (x) a maximum number of open orders for an account, or (xi) a range around market price.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein said determining is based on at least one of: (i) trader information, or (ii) information received from an operator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>storing the risk control information for use by the automated spread trading system.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the trading parameter is still stored after a termination of the temporary computer communication channel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the temporary computer communication channel is associated with a Web site.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. A computer-readable medium storing instructions adapted to be executed by a processor to perform a method to facilitate spread trading, said method comprising:
<claim-text>receiving from a trader device an indication of a first investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving from the trader device an indication of a second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing an association between the first investment and the second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving from the trader device a trading parameter to be associated with both the first and second investments, said receiving the trading parameter being performed via a temporary computer communication channel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing the received trading parameter, in association with both the first and second investments, for use by an automated spread trading system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>retrieving the stored trading parameter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the stored trading parameter, via the temporary computer communication channel, to the trader device for display to a trader.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. A method to facilitate spread trading, comprising:
<claim-text>receiving from a trader device an indication of a first investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving from the trader device an indication of a second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing an association between the first investment and the second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving from the trader device a trading parameter to be associated with both the first and second investments, said receiving the trading parameter being performed via a computer communication channel potentially accessible by a plurality of unrelated trader devices;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing the received trading parameter, in association with both the first and second investments, for use by an automated spread trading system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>retrieving the stored trading parameter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the stored trading parameter, via the temporary computer communication channel, to the trader device for display to a trader.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. A method to facilitate spread trading, comprising:
<claim-text>receiving from a trader device an indication of a first investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving from the trader device an indication of a second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing an association between the first investment and the second investment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving from the trader device a trading parameter to be associated with both the first and second investments, said receiving the trading parameter being performed via a public computer communication network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing the received trading parameter, in association with both the first and second investments, for use by an automated spread trading system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>retrieving the stored trading parameter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the stored trading parameter, via the temporary computer communication channel to the trader device for display to a trader.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. A computer-implemented method to facilitate risk arbitrage trading, comprising:
<claim-text>receiving a trader identifier via a Web site;</claim-text>
<claim-text>verifying the trader identifier;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving via the Web site the following information:
<claim-text>an acquirer stock identifier,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a target stock identifier,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a selected risk arbitrage trading strategy, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an authorization to automatically generate orders in accordance with the strategy;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing the received acquirer stock identifier in association with the received target stock identifier;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing the received selected risk arbitrage trading strategy, in association with both the received acquirer stock identifier and received target stock identifier, for use by an automated spread trading system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>retrieving the stored selected risk arbitrage trading strategy; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting an indication of the selected risk arbitrage trading strategy via a communication network to a device associated with the trader identifier.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
