<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297951-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297951</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11190688</doc-number>
<date>20050727</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>202</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>25033902</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Two F-number, two-color sensor system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4996427</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Noble et al.</name>
<date>19910200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5075553</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Noble et al.</name>
<date>19911200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>250352</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5113076</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schulte</name>
<date>19920500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5258618</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Noble et al.</name>
<date>19931100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5343542</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kash et al.</name>
<date>19940800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5457331</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kosai et al.</name>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5751473</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Runciman</name>
<date>19980500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359356</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5959339</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chapman et al.</name>
<date>19990900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6034372</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>LeVan et al.</name>
<date>20000300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6618199</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Cook</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6700706</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chang et al.</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7157706</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Gat et al.</name>
<date>20070100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2503381</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0211907</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wellman et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0238741</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Gat et al.</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2503381</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0255275</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Garman et al.</name>
<date>20061100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2503381</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0274431</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wood et al.</name>
<date>20061200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359722</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>26</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>25033902</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070023663</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070201</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Chungte W.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Irvine</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Anderson</last-name>
<first-name>John S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Santa Monica</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Alkov</last-name>
<first-name>Leonard A.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Raytheon Company</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Waltham</city>
<state>MA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Porta</last-name>
<first-name>David</first-name>
<department>2884</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Webb</last-name>
<first-name>Christopher</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A sensor system senses a scene and includes a dual-band imaging infrared detector lying on a beam path, wherein the infrared detector detects infrared images in a first infrared wavelength band and in a second infrared wavelength band; and a two-color cold-shield filter lying on the beam path between the infrared detector and the scene. The cold-shield filter defines a first aperture size for infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band, and a second aperture size larger than the first aperture size for infrared light of the second infrared wavelength band. The first infrared wavelength band has wavelengths less than wavelengths of the second infrared wavelength band.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="179.66mm" wi="258.57mm" file="US07297951-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="261.54mm" wi="183.47mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297951-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="224.28mm" wi="181.02mm" file="US07297951-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="271.02mm" wi="176.78mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297951-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates to a sensor system and, more particularly, to an imaging infrared sensor system that senses a scene in two different infrared wavelength bands.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Imaging infrared sensors image the light from a scene in the infrared wavelength range of about 0.9 micrometers to about 12 micrometers and in some cases to even longer infrared wavelengths. By contrast, visible-light sensors operate in shorter wavelengths below about 0.9 micrometers. Infrared sensor are preferred to visible-light sensors for many applications, because the infrared sensor can often image a scene through clouds, dust, and other obstructions that obscure the visible-light scene.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In a further refinement, more-recent infrared sensors include the capability to image a scene in two different infrared wavelength bands. For example, the scene may be simultaneously imaged in the medium-wavelength infrared (MWIR) band and the long-wavelength infrared (LWIR) band. The simultaneous images in two different infrared wavelength bands may be used to determine the nature of some types of features, whose characters cannot be determined either by visible light or by imaging in a single infrared wavelength band.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Complications arise when the scene is imaged in two different infrared wavelength bands. Diffraction of the light is wavelength dependent, so that the point spread function is wavelength dependent. If MWIR and LWIR wavelengths are imaged through the same aperture, the point spread function is significantly larger for the LWIR wavelengths than for the MWIR wavelengths, with the result that the MWIR image is “sharper” than the LWIR image. This difference in the images makes it difficult to compare the two images by digital analysis techniques. On the other hand, it is known to split the input beam into beams of the two different wavelength ranges, pass the two beams through different apertures, and separately image the two beams onto different infrared detectors. While operable, this technique significantly increases the cost of the sensor system by requiring two infrared detectors, and by requiring that the cooling system be substantially larger than would otherwise be the case.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">There is a need to improve dual-band infrared imaging to achieve satisfactory image quality while reducing the cost of the sensor system and the envelope size of the sensor system. The present invention fulfills this need, and further provides related advantages.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The present invention provides an imaging sensor system that images two different wavelength bands with a single dual-band imaging detector. The two different wavelength bands may include two wavelength bands in the visible, two wavelength bands in the infrared (the preferred case), or one wavelength band in the visible and one wavelength band in the infrared. The optical system compensates for the wavelength-dependent diffraction effects so that the images obtained at the two different wavelengths are comparable. The performance for the longer-wavelength image is significantly improved over what it would otherwise be. The improved performance is obtained with a less-costly, more compact structure that requires less cooling power than alternative approaches.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In accordance with the invention, a sensor system for sensing a scene comprises a dual-band imaging detector lying on a beam path from the scene, wherein the detector detects images in a first wavelength band and in a second wavelength band, and a two-color cold-shield filter lying on the beam path between the detector and the scene. A first filter portion of the cold-shield filter passes light of the first wavelength band and the second wavelength band, and a second filter portion of the cold-shield filter does not pass light of the first wavelength band but passes light of the second wavelength band. Preferably, at least one, and more preferably both, of the wavelength bands imaged by the detector are in the infrared.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Desirably, the first filter portion is a circle centered on the beam path, and the second filter portion is a circular annulus centered on the beam path. Most preferably, an outer diameter of the circle is an inner diameter of the annulus. The outer diameter of the circle thereby defines a first aperture of a first F-number for the first wavelength, and the outer diameter of the annulus defines a second aperture of a second F-number for the second wavelength. The first wavelength band comprises wavelengths less than wavelengths of the second wavelength band. In a case of most interest, the first wavelength band is in the infrared and from about 3 to about 5 micrometers wavelength (the Medium Wavelength Infrared or MWIR wavelength band), and the second wavelength band is in the infrared from about 8 to about 12 micrometers wavelength (the Long Wavelength Infrared or LWIR wavelength band).</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In a practical application, a cooler housing such as a cryogenic cooler housing encloses the detector and the cold-shield filter. The cooler housing includes a window to admit the beam path to an interior of the cooler housing. A telescope and an imager lie on the beam path outside of the cooler housing. The telescope and the imager image the scene through the cold-shield filter and onto the detector that is within the cooler housing.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The cold-shield filter may be conveniently formed by depositing one or more thin-film filters onto a substrate. In one embodiment, the cold-shield filter comprises a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion, a first multilayer bandpass coating overlying the first substrate portion, and a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion. In another embodiment, the cold-shield filter comprises a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion, and a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">There may additionally be an aberration corrector for the cold-shield filter, wherein the aberration corrector lies in the beam path. The aberration corrector may conveniently be affixed to the cold-shield filter, as for example a Schmidt Corrector affixed to one of the faces of the cold-shield filter.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In an embodiment of particular interest, a sensor system for sensing a scene comprises a dual-band imaging infrared detector lying on a beam path from the scene, wherein the infrared detector detects infrared images in the first infrared wavelength band and in a second infrared wavelength band, and a two-color cold-shield filter lying on the beam path between the infrared detector and the scene. A circular first filter portion of the cold-shield filter passes infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band and the second infrared wavelength band. The first infrared wavelength band comprises wavelengths less than wavelengths of the second infrared wavelength band. An annular second filter portion of the cold-shield filter does not pass infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band and passes infrared light of the second infrared wavelength band. An outer diameter of the circle is an inner diameter of the annulus. A cooler housing encloses the infrared detector and the cold-shield filter. The cooler housing includes a window to admit the beam path to an interior of the cooler housing. Other operable features discussed herein may be used with this embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">More generally, a sensor system for sensing a scene comprises a dual-band imaging infrared detector lying on a beam path. The infrared detector detects infrared images in a first infrared wavelength band and in a second infrared wavelength band. A two-color cold-shield filter lies on the beam path between the infrared detector and the scene. The cold-shield filter defines a first aperture size for infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band, and a second aperture size larger than the first aperture size for infrared light of the second infrared wavelength band. The first infrared wavelength band comprises wavelengths less than wavelengths of the second infrared wavelength band.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">By defining a relatively smaller aperture (larger F-number) for the shorter wavelength band and a relatively larger aperture (smaller F-number) for the longer wavelength band, the point spread function of the longer wavelength band is reduced in size to be comparable with that of the shorter wavelength band. The result is that the two images from the two wavelength bands are made more nearly comparable, and the quality of the image associated with the longer wavelength band is improved.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The present detector structure is simple to fabricate and to keep in alignment. There are only two parts in the detector structure, the detector and the cold-shield filter, and no moving parts. There is no beamsplitter and no multiple detectors that must be fabricated and maintained in alignment during service.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Other features and advantages of the present invention will be apparent from the following more detailed description of the preferred embodiment, taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, which illustrate, by way of example, the principles of the invention. The scope of the invention is not, however, limited to this preferred embodiment.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic elevational view of an infrared sensor system;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic elevational interior view of a cooler housing, showing the cold-shield filter and the imaging infrared detector;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view of the cold-shield filter;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A-4E</figref> are a series of elevational views illustrating the steps in a process for fabricating a first embodiment of the cold-shield filter; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5E</figref> are a series of elevational views illustrating the steps in a process for fabricating a second embodiment of the cold-shield filter.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> depicts a preferred embodiment of a sensor system <b>20</b> for sensing and imaging a scene <b>22</b>. The most-preferred embodiment is designed for use in the infrared, and the following description is directed to this most-preferred embodiment. The illustrated infrared sensor system <b>20</b> includes a telescope <b>24</b>, in this case formed by a series of mirrors, and an imager <b>26</b>, in this case a series of lenses, lying on a beam path <b>28</b>. (The telescope <b>24</b> may instead be refractive, and the imager <b>26</b> may be reflective, or each of these components may use a mix of reflective and refractive optics.) The telescope <b>24</b> and the imager <b>26</b> image the scene <b>22</b> to a detector structure <b>30</b> that also lies on the beam path <b>28</b>. For infrared applications, an interior of the detector structure <b>30</b> is typically cooled to a reduced temperature, such as a cryogenic temperature near the temperature of liquid nitrogen, by a refrigerator <b>32</b>, such as a Joule-Thomson refrigerator. Any operable telescope <b>24</b>, imager <b>26</b>, and refrigerator <b>32</b> may be used.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The detector structure <b>30</b> is shown in greater detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The detector structure <b>30</b>, and thence the sensor system <b>20</b>, includes a dual-band imaging infrared detector <b>34</b> lying on the beam path <b>28</b> from the scene <b>22</b>. The single infrared detector <b>34</b> detects infrared images in two different infrared wavelength bands, specifically a first infrared wavelength band and a second infrared wavelength band. Because infrared light is light, comparable terminology to that used in discussing visible light is used in some instances. For example, the two different wavelength bands are often referred to as two different “color” bands. In a case of most interest, the detector <b>34</b> images in the medium-wavelength infrared (MWIR) band of from about 3 to about 5 micrometers wavelength, and in the long-wavelength infrared (LWIR) band of from about 8 to about 12 micrometers wavelength. Dual-band imaging infrared detectors <b>34</b> are known in the art, see for example U.S. Pat. Nos. 5,959,339; 5,113,076; and 5,457,331, whose disclosures are incorporated by reference.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The scene <b>22</b> is imaged through an aperture structure <b>36</b> onto the detector <b>34</b> by the telescope <b>24</b> and the imager <b>26</b>. If a single-size aperture structure is used for the two different wavelength bands (a structure that is not within the scope of the present invention), the longer-wavelength band has a point spread function on the infrared detector <b>34</b> that is larger than the point spread function of the shorter-wavelength band. The larger point spread function of the longer-wavelength band causes the images of the two different wavelength bands to be different, and also reduces the resolution of the image formed by the light of the longer-wavelength band. One possible approach to improving upon this situation is to split the beam incoming to the detector structure into two beams of the different wavelength bands, and to pass these two subbeams through differently sized apertures and onto two different single-wavelength band detectors. This alternative approach, which is not within the scope of the present invention, is significantly more costly to implement due to the need for two detectors, and also increases the size of the detector structure and the volume that must be cooled.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In the present approach, a two-color cold-shield filter <b>38</b> lies on the beam path <b>28</b> between the infrared detector <b>34</b> and the scene <b>22</b>, most preferably within the cooled interior <b>52</b> of a cooler housing <b>48</b>. The cold-shield filter <b>38</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and in greater detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, is structured such that a first filter portion <b>40</b> of the cold-shield filter <b>38</b> passes infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band and also the second infrared wavelength band (the same two wavelength bands imaged by the detector <b>34</b>). A second filter portion <b>42</b> of the cold-shield filter <b>38</b> does not pass infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band but passes infrared light of the second infrared wavelength band. Preferably, the first filter portion <b>40</b> is a circle centered on the beam path <b>28</b>, and the second filter portion <b>42</b> is a circular annulus centered on the beam path <b>28</b>, as may be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Most preferably, an outer diameter of the circle of the first filter portion <b>40</b> is an inner diameter of the annulus of the second filter portion <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The first filter portion <b>40</b> defines a first aperture <b>44</b> having a diameter D<b>1</b> (and an associated larger F-number), and the second filter portion defines a second aperture <b>46</b> having a diameter D<b>2</b> (and an associated smaller F-number). The first aperture <b>44</b> serves as an aperture for the first (shorter or MWIR) infrared wavelength band, because the second filter portion <b>42</b> does not pass light of the first infrared wavelength band. The second aperture <b>46</b> serves as an aperture for the second (longer or LWIR) infrared wavelength band, because both the first filter portion <b>40</b> and the second filter portion <b>42</b> of the cold-shield filter <b>38</b> pass light of the second infrared wavelength band. Thus, the cold-shield filter <b>38</b> having a single integral structure and no moving parts provides the functionality of two apertures for the different wavelength bands and two F-numbers.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The preferred detector structure <b>30</b> includes the cooler housing <b>48</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) enclosing the infrared detector <b>34</b> and the cold-shield filter <b>38</b>. This arrangement keeps the cold-shield filter <b>38</b> cool, to reduce background thermal radiation that is within the field of view of the infrared detector <b>34</b>. The cooler housing <b>48</b> includes a window <b>50</b> to admit the beam path <b>28</b> to the interior <b>52</b> of the cooler housing <b>48</b>, so that the beam path <b>28</b> may pass through the cold-shield filter <b>38</b> and be incident upon the infrared detector <b>34</b>. The cooler housing <b>48</b> and its interior <b>52</b>, and thence the infrared detector <b>34</b> and the cold-shield filter <b>38</b>, are cooled by the refrigerator <b>32</b>. The cooler housing <b>48</b> may be a vacuum housing, in which case the interior <b>52</b> of the cooler housing <b>48</b> is evacuated. The cooler housing <b>48</b> serves the dual functions of maintaining the temperature of the infrared detector <b>34</b> and the cold-shield filter <b>38</b>, and also protecting them against contamination from external sources.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> illustrate manufacturing sequences for two different embodiments of the structures of the cold-shield filter <b>38</b>. In the first embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A-E</figref>, the cold-shield filter <b>38</b> comprises a substrate <b>60</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>) having a first substrate portion <b>62</b> corresponding to the first filter portion <b>40</b> and a second substrate portion <b>64</b> corresponding to the second filter portion <b>42</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>). A first multilayer bandpass coating <b>66</b> is deposited to overlie the first substrate portion <b>62</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>), and a second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b> overlies the second substrate portion <b>64</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>). The bandpass filters may be designed to pass only a specific range of wavelengths, or they may be designed as edge filters to pass all light above or below a certain edge wavelength. The multilayer bandpass coatings <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> are multilayer structures designed to pass only certain wavelengths of light and to reflect or absorb other wavelengths of light. Such multilayer bandpass coatings are known in the art for other applications, such as for Fabry-Perot filters. See, for example, U.S. Pat. Nos. 5,343,542; 6,618,199; and 6,700,706, whose disclosures are incorporated by reference. In the present case, the first multilayer bandpass coating <b>66</b> is designed to pass the first infrared wavelength band and the second infrared wavelength band. The second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b> is designed to pass the second infrared wavelength band but to reflect or absorb (but not pass) the first infrared wavelength band.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A-4E</figref> depict a sequence for fabricating this first embodiment. The substrate <b>60</b> is first provided, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>. For the present application wherein the first infrared wavelength band is the MWIR band and the second infrared wavelength band is the LWIR band, the substrate <b>60</b> is preferably made of germanium about 2 millimeters thick. The first multilayer bandpass coating <b>66</b> is deposited overlying the first substrate portion <b>60</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>. For the present application, the first multilayer bandpass coating <b>66</b> is preferably made of alternating layers of zinc sulfide and germanium. The second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b> is deposited overlying the second substrate portion <b>62</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>. For the present application, the second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b> is also preferably made of alternating layers of zinc sulfide and germanium, of different thicknesses than those of the first multilayer bandpass coating <b>66</b>. (The order of the process steps of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4B and 4C</figref> may be reversed, so that the second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b> is first deposited, followed by the second multilayer bandpass coating <b>66</b>. Optionally, an antireflection coating <b>70</b> is deposited overlying both the first multilayer bandpass coating <b>66</b> and the second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4D</figref> Multilayer antireflection coatings are known in the art for other applications, and operate on much the same principles as the multilayer bandpass coatings <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> except reflect all relevant wavelengths. Optionally, an optical corrector <b>72</b> may be affixed or deposited upon the structure, preferably on the side of the substrate <b>70</b> away from the anti-reflection coating <b>70</b> to lie in the beam path <b>28</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4E</figref>. The optical corrector <b>72</b>, such as a Schmidt corrector, acts as a lens to reduce aberrations in the light beam incident upon the multilayer bandpass coatings <b>66</b> and <b>68</b>, and thence reaching the infrared detector <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5</figref> depicts a second embodiment of the cold-shield filter <b>38</b>. Features similar to those of the first embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref> are assigned the same callout numbers, and the prior description is incorporated here. In this embodiment, no first multilayer bandpass coating is used, and only the second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b> is present to overlie the second substrate portion <b>64</b>. This embodiment has the advantage that it is not necessary to deposit the first multilayer bandpass coating, saving fabrication costs. However, this embodiment permits all wavelengths of light to reach the infrared detector <b>34</b> through the first substrate portion <b>62</b>, a disadvantage in some applications.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5E</figref> depict a sequence for fabricating this second embodiment. The substrate <b>60</b> is first provided, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>. The substrate <b>60</b> is etched to remove a portion of the thickness thereof in the second substrate portion <b>64</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>. The second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b> is deposited overlying the second substrate portion <b>64</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>. Optionally, the antireflection coating <b>70</b> is deposited, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5D</figref>, and the optical corrector is affixed or deposited, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5E</figref>. The antireflection coating <b>70</b>, where used, is deposited over the unetched first substrate portion <b>62</b> and the second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b>. For this reason, the depth of the etching in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is preferably exactly the optical thickness of the second multilayer bandpass coating <b>68</b>, so that the antireflection coating <b>70</b> may be deposited upon a substantially flat surface.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Although a particular embodiment of the invention has been described in detail for purposes of illustration, various modifications and enhancements may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. Accordingly, the invention is not to be limited except as by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A sensor system for sensing a scene, the sensor system comprising:
<claim-text>a dual-band imaging detector lying on a beam path from the scene, wherein the detector detects images in a first wavelength band and in a second wavelength band;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a two-color cold-shield filter lying on the beam path between the detector and the scene, wherein
<claim-text>a first filter portion of the cold-shield filter passes light of the first wavelength band and the second wavelength band, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second filter portion of the cold-shield filter does not pass light of the first wavelength band and passes light of the second wavelength band; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a telescope and an imager lying on the bean, path, wherein the telescope and the imager image the scene through the cold-shield filter and onto the detector.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first filter portion is a circle centered on the beam path, and the second filter portion is a circular annulus centered on the beam path.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first filter portion is a circle centered on the beam path, and the second filter portion is a circular annulus centered on the beam path, and wherein an outer diameter of the circle is an inner diameter of the annulus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first wavelength band comprises wavelengths less than wavelengths of the second wavelength band.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first wavelength band is from about 3 to about 5 micrometers wavelength, and the second wavelength band is from about 8 to about 12 micrometers wavelength.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further including a cooler housing enclosing the detector and the cold-shield filter, wherein the cooler housing includes a window to admit the beam path to an interior of the cooler housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter comprises
<claim-text>a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first multilayer bandpass coating overlying the first substrate portion, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter comprises
<claim-text>a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further including
<claim-text>an optical aberration corrector for the cold-shield filter, wherein the optical aberration corrector lies in the beam path.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A sensor system for sensing a scene, the sensor system comprising:
<claim-text>a dual-band imaging infrared detector lying on a beam path from the scene, wherein the infrared detector detects infrared images in a first infrared wavelength band and in a second infrared wavelength band;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a two-color cold-shield filter lying on the beam path between the infrared detector and the scene, wherein
<claim-text>a circular first filter portion of the cold-shield filter passes infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band and the second infrared wavelength band, wherein the first infrared wavelength band comprises wavelengths less than wavelengths of the second infrared wavelength band, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an annular second filter portion of the cold-shield filter does not pass infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band and passes infrared light of the second infrared wavelength band, and wherein an outer diameter of the circle is an inner diameter of the annulus;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cooler housing enclosing the infrared detector and the cold-shield filter, wherein the cooler housing includes a window to admit the beam path to an interior of the cooler housing; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a telescope and an imager lying on the beam path, wherein the telescope and the imager image the scene onto the infrared detector.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the first infrared wavelength band is from about 3 to about 5 micrometers wavelength, and the second infrared wavelength band is from about 8 to about 12 micrometers wavelength.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter comprises
<claim-text>a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter comprises
<claim-text>a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first multilayer bandpass coating overlying the first substrate portion, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter has an optical aberration corrector affixed thereto overlying at least the second portion of the cold-shield filter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A sensor system for sensing a scene, the sensor system comprising:
<claim-text>a dual-band imaging detector lying on a beam path from the scene, wherein the detector detects images in a first wavelength band and in a second wavelength band;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a two-color cold-shield filter lying on the beam path between the detector and the scene, wherein
<claim-text>a first filter portion of the cold-shield filter passes light of the first wavelength band and the second wavelength band, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second filter portion of the cold-shield filter does not pass light of the first wavelength band and passes light of the second wavelength band; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>an optical aberration corrector for the cold-shield filter, wherein the optical aberration corrector lies in the beam path.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the first filter portion is a circle centered on the beam path, and the second filter portion is a circular annulus centered on the beam path.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the first filter portion, is a circle centered on the beam path, and the second filter portion is a circular annulus centered on the beam path, and wherein an outer diameter of the circle is an inner diameter of the annulus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the first wavelength band comprises wavelengths less than wavelengths of the second wavelength band.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the first wavelength band is from about 3 to about 5 micrometers wavelength, and the second wavelength band is from about 8 to about 12 micrometers wavelength.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further including:
<claim-text>a cooler housing enclosing the detector and the cold-shield filter, wherein the cooler housing includes a window to admit the beam path to an interior of the cooler housing.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter comprises;
<claim-text>a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first multilayer bandpass coating overlying the first substrate portion, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter comprises:
<claim-text>a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. A sensor system for sending a scene, the sensor system comprising:
<claim-text>a dual-band imaging infrared detector lying on a beam path from the scene, wherein the infrared detector detects infrared images in a first infrared wavelength band and in a second infrared wavelength band;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a two-color cold-shield filter lying on the beam path between the infrared detector and the scene, wherein
<claim-text>a circular first filter portion of the cold-shield filter passes infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band and the second infrared wavelength band, wherein the first infrared wavelength band comprises wavelengths less than wavelengths of the second infrared wavelength band,</claim-text>
<claim-text>an annular second filter portion of the cold-shield filter does not pass infrared light of the first infrared wavelength band and passes infrared light of the second infrared wavelength band, and wherein an outer diameter of the circle is an inner diameter of the annulus, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the cold-shield filter has an optical aberration corrector affixed thereto overlying at least the second portion of the cold-shield filter; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cooler housing enclosing the infrared detector and the cold-shield filter, wherein the cooler housing includes a window to admit the beam path to an interior of the cooler housing.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref>, wherein the first infrared wavelength band is from about 3 to about 5 micrometers wavelength, and the second infrared wavelength band is from about 8 to about 12 micrometers wavelength.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter comprises:
<claim-text>a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The sensor system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref>, wherein the cold-shield filter comprises:
<claim-text>a substrate having a first substrate portion corresponding to the first filter portion and a second substrate portion corresponding to the second filter portion,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first multilayer bandpass coating overlying the first substrate portion, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second multilayer bandpass coating overlying the second substrate portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
