<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298987-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298987</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10824349</doc-number>
<date>20040415</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-112698</doc-number>
<date>20030417</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>414</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399107</main-classification>
<further-classification>399411</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">External cover, and image forming device and control system including the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-133443</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19980500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-270133</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-182441</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399107</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399411</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040208669</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20041021</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tokishige</last-name>
<first-name>Kiyoshi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kyoto</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Okada</last-name>
<first-name>Naofumi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tenri</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nagata</last-name>
<first-name>Jinichi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Osaka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ohgita</last-name>
<first-name>Toshiki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nara</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nanba</last-name>
<first-name>Toyoaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Higashiosaka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Birch, Stewart, Kolasch &amp; Birch, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sharp Kabushiki Kaisha</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Osaka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Gray</last-name>
<first-name>David M.</first-name>
<department>2852</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Walsh</last-name>
<first-name>Ryan D.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A connector cover of the present invention serves a function as a cover for a connector when a postprocessing device is not fitted to a main unit of an image forming device. Further, when the postprocessing device is fitted to the main unit of the image forming device, the connector cover is secured at the other position while maintaining the function as a cover for the connector, and serves a function as a shock-absorbing member with respect to the actuator which is provided in the postprocessing device. This makes it possible to secure a good appearance of the image forming device and make effective use of resources.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="157.06mm" wi="231.22mm" file="US07298987-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="272.12mm" wi="160.78mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298987-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="266.95mm" wi="160.70mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298987-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="218.69mm" wi="181.44mm" file="US07298987-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="249.34mm" wi="185.34mm" file="US07298987-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="237.15mm" wi="146.47mm" file="US07298987-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="270.68mm" wi="162.81mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298987-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This Nonprovisional application claims priority under 35 U.S.C. § 119(a) on Patent Application No. 2003/112698 filed in Japan on Apr. 17, 2003, the entire contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an external cover included in a main unit of an image forming device or the like including printer, facsimile, and copier, and when an option device or the like is not fitted to the main unit, covering a connecting part (attaching part) between the main unit and the option device, e.g. paper-receiving port, and relates to an image forming device including the external cover.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Conventionally, a peripheral device such as postprocessing device and large-capacity paper feeder (hereinafter referred to as option device) would be fitted to a main unit of an image forming device in response to user's demand.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Because of this, the main unit of the image forming device includes a communication part with the option device, e.g. a paper-receiving port for guiding sheets of paper received from the option device and a paper-feeding port for guiding sheets of paper to the option device. Also, the image forming device includes electrically connecting section and other sections relating to communication and power supply between the option device and the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, in the case where the option device is not fitted to the image forming device, it is necessary to improve the appearance of the image forming device and to prevent accidents at the communication part and other part. Therefore, the attaching section, such as the communication part and the electrically connecting section (a connecting part between the main unit of the device and the option device), is covered with an external cover for covering, a cover provided as an outer surface of the image forming device, or the like so that the attaching section is invisible or the attaching section is not usable.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In such an image forming device, after detaching the external cover for covering, or cutting off a portion of a cover provided as an outer surface of the image forming device as disclosed in Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 10-133443/1998 (Tokukaihei 10-133443; published on May 22, 1998), the option device is fitted to the main unit of the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 10-133443/1998, the cut-off portion, which serves another function, is reused without being thrown away. With this arrangement, effective use of resources is attempted.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, in an image forming device as described in Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 10-133443/1998, the following problem arises when the image forming device is used independently from the option device: when a portion of the cover provided as the outer surface of the image forming device is cut off, the outer surface of the image forming device is kept exposed with its original form lost, degrading appearance of the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Further, when the cover provided as the outer surface of the image forming device is replaced with a new one, the problem that maintenance cost occurs arises.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 2002-182441 (Tokukai 2002-182441; published on Jun. 26, 2002) discloses that parts removed from a main unit of a device before the option device is fitted to the main unit are made usable as a functioning component of the option device. In addition, Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 2002-182441 discloses that the parts removed from the main unit of the device can be reattached to the main unit of the device after the option device is separated from the main unit of the device. Note that, as a usage example of the parts removed from the main unit of the device as the functioning component of the option device, given is a paper stopper for a paper feed tray. However, although the parts removed from the main unit of the device can be used as a functioning component of the option device, the removed parts are a supplementary component of the option device, not essential component for the option device. Therefore, some users might not use the parts removed from the main unit of the device as a functioning component of the option device. On this account, there is the possibility that the parts removed from the main unit of the device would be lost when the option device is fitted to the main unit of the device.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Further, Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application No. 2000-270133 (Tokukai 2000-270133; published on Sep. 29, 2000) discloses that in the image forming device, an external cover corresponding to the part where an additional option device is fitted is a partial cover being attachable/detachable to/from the external cover, and the partial cover can be attached in an inverted position in the vertical direction or horizontal direction, depending on whether or not the option device is fitted to the image forming device. However, the partial cover has only the function as a cover when the option device is attached or is not fitted to the image forming device. Further, in the image forming device, when the part where the additional option device is fitted is located between the image forming device and the additional option device, the attaching part is covered by the option device. This eliminates the necessity to cause the partial cover to function as a cover when the option device is fitted, and the partial cover might not be attached to the image forming device, depending on a user. Because of this, there is the possibility that the partial cover would be lost.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present invention has been attained in view of the above problem, and a feature of the present invention is to provide an external cover capable of securing its good appearance and effective use of resources and being less likely to be lost than a conventional external cover, and an image forming device and a control system including the external cover.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In accordance with the above feature, an external cover of the present invention is an external cover covering an attaching section which is provided in a main unit of a first device to fit a second device to the main unit of the first device, the external cover, when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device, serves a first function as a cover for the attaching section, and the external cover, when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, serves a second function which is different from the first function while maintaining the first function, such that the external cover is provided to the first device or the second device in a state different from a state when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to the above arrangement, the external cover has a first function of covering an attaching section (a part connecting between the main unit of the first device and the second device) provided in the main unit of the first device. To realize system expansion by fitting the second device to the main unit of the first device, the external cover having been provided as a cover for the attaching section is reused, serving a new function (second function) while maintaining the first function as a cover. Therefore, even when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, the external cover is necessary for the first device or the second device. This eliminates loss of the external cover. In the case where the second device is separated from the first device so as to get back to a state where the first device is independent from the second device, the external cover can be reattached to the main unit of the first device, functioning as a cover for the attaching section. This makes it possible to secure a good appearance of the first device, to make effective use of resources, and to provide an external cover with no risk of being lost.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">For a fuller understanding of the nature and advantages of the invention, reference should be made to the ensuing detailed description taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an outside and perspective view illustrating an external cover according to one embodiment of the present invention, an image forming device, and a postprocessing device, when the postprocessing device is fitted to the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional view illustrating an external cover according to one embodiment of the present invention, an image forming device, and a postprocessing device, when the postprocessing device is fitted to the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view illustrating an external cover according to another embodiment of the present invention, an image forming device, and an option device, when the option device is not fitted to the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view illustrating an external cover according to another embodiment of the present invention, an image forming device, and an option device, when the option device is fitted to the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an outside and perspective view of the external cover according to another embodiment when viewed from the front side thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an outside and perspective view of the external cover according to another embodiment when viewed from the back side thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross-sectional view illustrating the external cover according to another embodiment of the present invention, the image forming device, and the postprocessing device, when the postprocessing device is fitted to the image forming device.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The following will describe one embodiment according to the present invention with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an outside and perspective view illustrating an image forming device, a postprocessing device as option device, and an external cover when the postprocessing device is fitted to the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a postprocessing device having stapling function, punching function, and other functions (second device) <b>50</b> is fitted to an image forming device (first device) <b>1</b> on the paper ejection side (the side shown in the left-hand part of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). A postprocessing device (second device) <b>50</b> is a device for extending a system of the image forming device <b>1</b>. Further, a large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is fitted to the other side of the image forming device <b>1</b> (the side shown in the right-hand part of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). The large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> will be described later in the Second Embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the image forming device <b>1</b> of the present embodiment includes a printer section (image forming section) <b>2</b> and a paper feed unit <b>3</b> placed under the printer section <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">To the side surface of the paper feed unit <b>3</b> facing the postprocessing device <b>50</b> (the side shown in the left-hand part of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), a connector (attaching section) <b>23</b> and a connector cover (external cover) <b>40</b> for covering the connector <b>23</b> are provided. Further, to the side surface of the printer section <b>2</b> facing the postprocessing device <b>50</b>, a positioning boss <b>24</b> is provided.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The postprocessing device <b>50</b> has a cable <b>52</b> including a connector <b>51</b> at its end, on the side surface facing the postprocessing device <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Connection between the connector <b>23</b> and the connector <b>51</b> allows the postprocessing device <b>50</b> to communicate with the image forming device <b>1</b> and to receive a power supply from the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Further, the connector cover <b>40</b> is an external cover which is secured with a screw or the like to the image forming device <b>1</b> so as to cover the connector <b>23</b> while the option device such as the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is not fitted to the image forming device. At this moment, the connector cover <b>40</b> serves a function as a cover for the connector <b>23</b> that is the attaching section (a connecting part between the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b>) (first function). That is, the connector cover <b>40</b> forms a portion of an outer surface of the image forming device <b>1</b>. This arrangement enhances the appearance of the image forming device <b>1</b>. Moreover, the connector cover <b>40</b> protects the connector <b>23</b> from externally given physical shocks.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In the case where the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> is detached from the paper feed unit <b>3</b>, and the connector <b>23</b> is exposed. The detached connector cover <b>40</b> is secured with a screw to the side surface of the printer section <b>2</b> facing the postprocessing device <b>50</b>, which is apart from the connector <b>23</b>. Here, the connector cover <b>40</b> is arranged so as to be reattached to cover the connector <b>23</b>, without losing the function as a cover for the connector <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The positioning boss <b>24</b> is one for constantly maintaining relative positions between the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b> when the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>. Constant relative positions are positions where the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b> can perform normal operation as a series of devices. More specifically, constant relative positions are positions where a paper transport path of the image forming device <b>1</b> is connected to a paper transport path of the postprocessing device <b>50</b> so that paper delivery is possible between the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b>. The relative positions are described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional diagram of the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b> when they are cable-connected with the connectors <b>23</b> and <b>51</b>. Note that, the image forming device <b>1</b> is fitted to the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> on the right side of the image forming device <b>1</b>. The large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> will be described in the Second Embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">On the side of the postprocessing device <b>50</b> facing the image forming device <b>1</b> provided are a paper-receiving port <b>56</b> for receiving a sheet of paper from the image forming device <b>1</b>, and a detector <b>54</b> including an actuator <b>53</b>. A sheet of paper entering the paper-receiving port <b>56</b> is guided by a transport path <b>55</b> and is subjected to a predetermined process.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Further, as indicated by an arrow in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is moved toward the image forming device <b>1</b>, and the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>. While the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> is secured with a screw to a predetermined position of the printer section <b>2</b> so that the actuator <b>53</b> strikes the connector cover <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Inside the printer section <b>2</b> provided is a transport path <b>22</b>. The transport path <b>22</b> is one for transporting a sheet of paper including an image formed thereon to the postprocessing device <b>50</b>, and is directly connected to a paper-feeding port.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">When the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b> so that they maintain the constant relative positions in accordance with the positioning boss <b>24</b> provided to the image forming device <b>1</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), the transport path <b>22</b> of the printer section <b>2</b> is connected to the transport path <b>55</b> of the postprocessing device <b>50</b>. At the same time, the actuator <b>53</b> strikes the connector cover <b>40</b> secured with a screw to a predetermined position of the printer section <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">When the actuator <b>53</b> strikes the connector cover <b>40</b> secured with a screw to a predetermined position of the printer section <b>2</b>, the detector <b>54</b> recognizes that the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is properly fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>. That is, the detector <b>54</b> and the actuator <b>53</b> are one of object determination means for determining whether or not an object exists at the end part of the actuator <b>53</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Further, the present embodiment has a control system including a control circuit (not shown) for controlling operations of the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In the present control system, when the detector <b>54</b> determines that there exists any object at the end part of the actuator <b>53</b>, the control circuit is set so as to operate the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b> in response to a signal from the detector <b>54</b>. On the other hand, in the present control system, when the detector <b>54</b> determines that no object exists at the end part of the actuator <b>53</b>, the control circuit is set so as not to operate the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Therefore, when the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b> without the connector cover <b>40</b>, having been detached from the connector <b>23</b>, attached to a predetermined position to cause the connector cover <b>40</b> to function as an shock-absorbing member with respect to the actuator <b>53</b>, the detector <b>54</b> determines that no object exists at the end part of the actuator <b>53</b>. That is, the detector <b>54</b> determines that the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is separated from the printer section <b>2</b>. At this moment, in the control system, the control circuit causes the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b> not to operate.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Thus, in the case where the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> detached from the connector <b>23</b> is not thrown away and lost mistakenly because the connector cover <b>40</b> is an essential component.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Further, when a paper jam occurs in the transport path <b>32</b> inside the printer section <b>2</b>, a part located in the vicinity of the transport path <b>32</b> on the side surface of the printer section <b>2</b> facing the postprocessing device (a part shown in the left-hand part of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) must be open to clear a paper jam. Because of this, the postprocessing device <b>50</b> must be separated from the image forming device <b>1</b>, and the actuator <b>53</b> does not strike the connector cover <b>40</b> at the same time. At this moment, the present control system causes the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b> not to operate, which can prevent user's hands and other parts from getting caught in the image forming device <b>1</b> and prevent other troubles.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Further, in the case where the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is separated from the image processing device <b>1</b> due to the unnecessity of the postprocessing device <b>50</b> as option device, the connector cover <b>40</b> having functioned as a shock-absorbing member with respect to the actuator <b>53</b> is reattached so as to cover the connector <b>23</b>, as a cover for the connector <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">With this arrangement, after the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is separated from the image forming device <b>1</b>, it is possible to return the appearance of the image forming device <b>1</b> to its good appearance without exposure of the connector <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Further, since the connector cover <b>40</b> functions as a shock-absorbing member with respect to the actuator <b>53</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> also has a function of protecting the side surface of the image forming device <b>1</b> from damage caused by the actuator <b>53</b>. Thus, the side surface of the image forming device <b>1</b> is protected by the connector cover <b>40</b> without being disfigured its appearance. Therefore, after the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is separated from the image forming device <b>1</b>, the side surface of the image forming device <b>1</b> is hardly degraded its appearance.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Thus, while the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> is attached, as a shock-absorbing member with respect to the actuator <b>53</b>, to the printer section <b>2</b>. On the other hand, while the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is not fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> is attached as a cover for the connector <b>23</b>. That is, it is possible to freely change between the functions of the connector cover <b>40</b>, depending on whether or not the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">More specifically, the connector cover <b>40</b>, which is one of the embodiments in the present invention, serves a function as a cover for the connector <b>23</b> (first function), which is an attaching section (a connecting part between the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b>), while the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>. Further, the connector cover <b>40</b> serves a function as a shock-absorbing member with respect to the actuator <b>53</b> (second function) included in the detector <b>54</b> while the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Next, the following will describe the printer section <b>2</b>, the paper feed unit <b>3</b> placed under the printer section <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Substantially at the central position of the printer section <b>2</b> located is a xerographic process section centrally having a photoconductive drum <b>4</b>. More specifically, the xerographic process section includes a charging unit <b>5</b>, a light scanning unit <b>6</b>, a development unit <b>7</b>, a transfer unit <b>8</b>, and a cleaning unit <b>9</b> located around the photoconductive drum <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The charging unit <b>5</b> is one for electrically charging the photoconductive drum <b>4</b> evenly. The light scanning unit <b>6</b> is one for scanning an optical image and writing an electrostatic latent image on the photoconductive drum <b>4</b> electrically charged evenly. The development unit <b>7</b> is one for developing the electrostatic latent image written by the light scanning unit <b>6</b> with a developer.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The transfer unit <b>8</b> is one for transferring an image recorded and reproduced on the photoconductive drum <b>4</b> onto a recording medium. The cleaning unit <b>9</b> is one for removing the residual developer remaining on the photoconductive drum <b>4</b> so that a new image can be recorded on the photoconductive drum <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Note that, the residual developer removed by the cleaning unit <b>9</b> is collected and reused by a developer supplying section <b>10</b> of the developement unit <b>7</b>. Note that, an image forming device of the present invention, not limited to an image forming device including such a process of reusing the residual developer, includes an image forming device collecting and disposing of the residual developer.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Next, the following will describe the paper feed unit <b>3</b>. The paper feed unit <b>3</b> includes a plurality of paper feed trays (recording media supplying section) <b>11</b>, <b>12</b>, <b>13</b>, and <b>14</b>. Inclusion of these paper feed trays <b>11</b>, <b>12</b>, <b>13</b>, and <b>14</b> allows the paper feed unit <b>3</b> to contain various sheet of papers, as recording media, divided for each size.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The image forming device <b>1</b> selects one tray from among the paper feed trays <b>11</b>, <b>12</b>, <b>13</b>, and <b>14</b>. Then, the image forming device <b>1</b> takes one sheet each from sheets of paper in the selected tray and supplies between the photoconductive drum <b>4</b> and the transfer unit <b>8</b>. Subsequently, the transfer unit <b>8</b> transfers an image recorded and reproduced on the photoconductive drum <b>4</b> onto a supplied paper.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Now, the following will describe the paper feed trays <b>11</b> through <b>14</b> in details. The paper feed tray (first recording media supplying section) <b>11</b> and the paper feed tray (second recording media supplying section) <b>12</b> are placed parallel to each other. The paper feed tray <b>13</b> is placed under the paper feed trays <b>11</b> and <b>12</b>, and further the paper feed tray <b>14</b> is placed under the paper feed trays <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Further, the capacity of the paper feed tray <b>13</b> is substantially as large as that of the paper feed tray <b>14</b>. Moreover, the capacity of the paper feed trays <b>11</b> and <b>12</b> are set to be larger than that of the paper feed tray <b>13</b> or <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Then, the paper feed unit <b>3</b> includes transport paths <b>15</b> and <b>16</b> for transporting sheets of paper contained in the paper feed trays <b>11</b>, <b>12</b>, <b>13</b>, and <b>14</b> toward the printer section <b>2</b>. Note that, the transport path <b>15</b> is one for transporting sheets of paper contained in the paper feed trays <b>11</b>, <b>13</b>, and <b>14</b> toward the printer section <b>2</b>, and the transport path <b>16</b> is one for transporting sheets of paper contained in the paper feed tray <b>12</b> toward the printer section <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Further, the transport path <b>15</b> extends in the perpendicular direction along a frame <b>17</b> of the paper feed unit <b>3</b>. On the other hand, the transport path <b>16</b> extends in the horizontal direction along the frame <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Therefore, the paper feed trays <b>11</b> through <b>14</b> and the transport paths <b>15</b> and <b>16</b> are efficiently placed inside the paper feed unit <b>3</b>, which realizes saving in space of the paper feed unit <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Note that, to load sheets of paper in the paper feed tray <b>11</b>, <b>12</b>, <b>13</b>, or <b>14</b>, a target paper feed tray selected from among the paper feed trays <b>11</b>, <b>12</b>, <b>13</b>, and <b>14</b> is pulled out in the front direction of the main unit of the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">When a paper jam occurs in the transport path <b>15</b>, a sheet of paper jammed in the transport path <b>15</b> is cleared by moving a guide <b>15</b><i>a </i>(the diagonally shaded areas in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), which constitutes the transport path <b>15</b>, toward the user with respect to the back of the paper feed unit <b>3</b> as a supporting point. Note that, such paper-removing operation is performed using a working space previously secured between the transport path <b>15</b> and the frame <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">Also, when a paper jam occurs in the transport path <b>16</b>, a sheet of paper jammed in the transport path <b>16</b> is cleared by moving a guide <b>16</b><i>a </i>(the diagonally shaded areas in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), which constitutes the transport path <b>16</b>, toward the user with respect to the back of the paper feed unit <b>3</b> as a supporting point. Note that, such paper-removing operation is performed in a circumstance where a working space is secured under the transport path <b>16</b> by pulling out the paper feed trays <b>11</b> and <b>12</b> placed in parallel to each other toward the user.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Note that, the image forming device <b>1</b> of the present embodiment has an arrangement such that the paper feed trays <b>11</b> and <b>12</b> can be simultaneously pulled out. However, the present invention is not limited to this arrangement. The image forming device <b>1</b> of the present embodiment may have an arrangement such that the paper feed trays <b>11</b> and <b>12</b> can be independently pulled out. In this case, it is safe that a working space where a sheet of paper jammed in the transport path <b>16</b> is cleared is secured under the transport path <b>16</b> by pulling out the paper feed tray <b>11</b> toward the user.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">A manual paper feed unit (third recording media supplying section) <b>18</b> where a relatively small amount of sheets of paper is loaded is provided on the downstream side of the transport path <b>16</b>. There is a high possibility that special sheets of paper would be loaded in the manual paper feed unit <b>18</b>. This is because replacing with another type of sheet of paper or loading sheets of paper can be easily performed with respect to the manual paper feed unit <b>18</b>. It is arranged such that a sheet of paper is supplied from the manual paper feed unit <b>18</b> to the transport path <b>16</b> via a transport path <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The above description has been given based on the connector cover <b>40</b> as external cover according to the First Embodiment. However, the connector cover <b>40</b> can be altered as follows.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">A way of securing the connector cover <b>40</b> to the image forming device <b>1</b>, not limited to a way of securing with screws, may be any ways provided that the connector cover <b>40</b> is secured to the image forming device <b>1</b>. The connector cover <b>40</b> may be secured to the image forming device <b>1</b> by hook connection or by using a magnet.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">In the present embodiment, when the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> is secured on the side surface of the image forming device <b>1</b>. However, the place where the connector cover <b>40</b> is secured is not limited to the side surface. For example, under a circumstance where the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, in the case where a protrusion with the actuator <b>53</b> provided to the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is located on the back surface of the image forming device <b>1</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> is attached to the back surface of the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Further, in the above arrangement, when the actuator <b>53</b> provided to the postprocessing device <b>50</b> comes into contact with the connector cover <b>40</b> attached to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the detector <b>54</b> recognizes that the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is properly fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>. However, the present invention is not limited to this arrangement, and may have any arrangement provided that constant relative positions maintained between two devices can be determined.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Further, in the above arrangement, the connector cover <b>40</b> comes into contact with both of the devices (the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b>). However, it is not necessarily required that the connector cover <b>40</b> comes into contact with both of the devices. For example, the present invention may be arranged so that the postprocessing device <b>50</b> has a distance measuring device for measuring a distance from an object by means of light, and a reflection mirror is provided to a part of the connector cover <b>40</b>. The distance measuring device is one of object determination means since the distance measuring device determines in accordance with an obtained measured value whether or not there is any object at a predetermined distance. At this moment, light emitted in a predetermined direction from the distance measuring device is reflected by a reflection mirror of the connector cover <b>40</b>. The distance measuring device can detect the reflected light measure a distance between the postprocessing device <b>50</b> and the image forming device <b>1</b>. The distance measuring device determines from the obtained measurement value whether or not the postprocessing device <b>50</b> and the image forming device <b>1</b> exist at predetermined relative positions.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Still further, in the present embodiment, when the postprocessing device <b>50</b> including the actuator <b>53</b> and the detector <b>54</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> is attached to a predetermined position of the image forming device <b>1</b>. However, instead of the above arrangement, the present invention may have an arrangement such that when the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b> including the actuator <b>53</b> and the detector <b>54</b>, the connector cover <b>40</b> is attached to a predetermined position of the postprocessing device <b>50</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>). This arrangement can attain the same effects as the arrangement of the present embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Further, in the above control system, when the detector <b>54</b> determines that the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is not properly fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the control circuit controls the postprocessing device <b>50</b> and the image forming device <b>1</b> not to operate. However, the control circuit may control only the image forming device <b>1</b> not to operate. This is because, also in this case, the connector cover <b>40</b> is necessary when the postprocessing device <b>50</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, which eliminates mistaken disposal and loss of the connector cover <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Further, the foregoing control system is working with the control circuit. However, the present system is not limited to this arrangement, and hence there is an alternative arrangement such that a program for carrying out the above-mentioned processes is recorded in a recording medium, and an information processing device which can read out the program and a digital signal output device operating under the control of the information processing device are used in place of the control circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">In this arrangement, an arithmetic unit (such as CPU and MPU) of the information processing device reads out the program recorded in the recording medium, and execute the processes. Thus, it is possible to consider that the processes are realized by the program itself.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">As the above-mentioned information processing device, feature expansion boards and units attached to a computer can be adopted, apart from typical computers (such as work stations and personal computers).</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">The above-mentioned program is a program code of a software realizing the operations of the image forming device <b>1</b> and the postprocessing device <b>50</b> (e.g. an execute form program, intermediate code program, source program). The program may be self-contained, or used in combination with another program (e.g. an operating system).</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">After being read out from the recording medium, the program may be stored temporarily in a memory (such as a RAM) in the device, and then read out again and executed.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">The recording medium in which the program is recorded may be easily detachable from the information processing device, or may be fixed (attached) to the device. Alternatively, the recording medium may be an external memory unit connected to the device.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">As such a recording medium, the followings may be adopted: magnetic tapes such as a vide tape and cassette tape, magnetic disks such as a Floppy® disk and hard disk, optical disks such as a CD-ROM, MO, MD, DVD, and CD-R, memory cards such as an IC card and optical card, and semiconductor memories such as a mask ROM, EPROM, EEPROM, and flash ROM.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Also, a recording medium connected to the information processing device via a network (e.g. intranet and the Internet) may be adopted. In this case, the information processing device downloads the program via the network. That is to say, the program may be obtained through a transmission medium (a medium fluidly carrying the program) on a network (connected to a wired/wireless line). Note that, a program for downloading is preferably stored in the information processing device (or in the image forming device) in advance.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">The following will describe another embodiment according to the present invention with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 through 6</figref>. Note that, for the purpose of explanation, members having the same functions as those described in the First Embodiment are given the same reference numerals and explanations thereof are omitted here.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the paper feed unit <b>3</b> of the image forming device (first device) <b>1</b> is fitted (connected) to the large-capacity paper feeder (second device) <b>60</b> as a fourth recording medium supplying section. The capacity of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is set to be larger than those of other paper feed trays <b>11</b> through <b>14</b>. A sheet of paper fed from the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> passes through a transport path <b>20</b> and is guided to the printer section <b>2</b> through the transport path <b>19</b> and the transport <b>16</b>. Note that, the transport path <b>20</b> is a transport path, provided to the paper feed unit <b>3</b>, for first receiving a transporting target such as paper and overhead transparency from the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b>. Therefore, the transport path <b>20</b> is located in the vicinity of the side surface of the image forming device <b>1</b> facing the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view illustrating the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> and the image forming device <b>1</b> before the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>. In the image forming device <b>1</b>, a cover member (external cover) <b>41</b> is secured with screws to a cover support member <b>25</b> of the paper feed unit <b>3</b> so as to close the transport path <b>20</b> of the paper feed unit <b>3</b>. The cover member <b>41</b> is a member having a rectangular board as a base taking the shape of an opening of the transport path <b>20</b> (paper receiving port <b>30</b> described later), and has a front surface of the base (front side) and a back surface of the base (back side) of respectively different shapes. Note that, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a view illustrating a state where the cover member <b>41</b> is attached to the image forming device <b>1</b> so that the front surface of the base of the cover member <b>41</b> faces the outside of the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a perspective view of the cover member <b>41</b> when the cover member <b>41</b> is viewed from its front surface of the base. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the front surface of the base is a smooth surface and includes two recessed sections <b>42</b> provided on the both ends in the width direction of a transported sheet and through which the cover member <b>41</b> is attached with screws.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a depth H<b>1</b> of the recessed section <b>42</b> is set so that when the cover member <b>41</b> is fixed to the cover support member <b>25</b> in such a direction that the front surface of the base of the cover member <b>41</b> faces outside, the front surface is flush with a right-side surface <b>26</b> of the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">Further, the front surface of the base is shaped to close the opening of the transport path <b>20</b>, and when the cover member <b>41</b> is attached to the paper feed unit <b>3</b> in such a direction that the front surface of the base is exposed to the outside of the image forming device <b>1</b>, the front surface of the base functions as a cover for the opening of the transport path <b>20</b> (paper receiving port <b>30</b> described later). This makes it possible to maintain a good appearance of the image forming device <b>1</b> without exposing the opening of the transport path <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a perspective view of the cover member <b>41</b> when the cover member <b>41</b> is viewed from the back side of the base. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the base is provided with a plurality of trapezoidal ribs <b>43</b> on its back surface, and the trapezoidal ribs <b>43</b> are arranged in parallel in the wide direction of the base. Further, a series of oblique lines of the ribs <b>43</b> form a slope with a predetermined angle with respect to the surface of the base.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">Further, the base is provided on its back surface with two raised sections <b>44</b> through which the cover member <b>41</b> is attached with screws. Note that, the raised section <b>44</b> corresponds to the recessed section <b>42</b> provided on the front surface of the cover member <b>41</b> and through which the cover member <b>41</b> is attached with screws.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">Here, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a distance from the base surface to the leading end of the rib <b>43</b> is denoted as H<b>3</b>, and a distance from the base surface to the top of the raised section <b>44</b> is denoted as H<b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the cover member <b>41</b>, the image forming device <b>1</b>, and the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> when the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is fitted to the paper feed unit <b>3</b> of the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">To fit the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> to the paper feed unit <b>3</b> of the image forming device <b>1</b>, the cover member <b>41</b> having been attached to the cover support member <b>25</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) with the screws <b>45</b> is detached therefrom. Thereafter, the cover member <b>41</b> is positioned in such a direction that its back surface is exposed to the outside of the image forming device <b>1</b> (in a direction opposite to such a direction that the front surface is exposed to the outside of the image forming device <b>1</b> in the present embodiment), and the cover member <b>41</b> is attached to the cover support member <b>25</b> with the screws <b>45</b> again. With this arrangement, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the paper receiving port (attaching section) <b>30</b> of the transport path <b>20</b> becomes open, and a sheet of paper fed from a paper-feeding port <b>61</b> of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is guided to the transport path <b>20</b> of the paper feed unit <b>3</b>. That is, the paper receiving port <b>30</b> of the paper feed unit <b>3</b> is coupled to the paper-feeding port <b>61</b> of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b>. This connects the image forming device <b>1</b> and the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b>. At this moment, the slope formed with the ribs <b>43</b> on the back surface of the base of the cover member <b>41</b> functions as a guide surface for guiding a lower side of a transporting target such as a sheet of paper.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">Under the circumstance where the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is fitted to the paper feed unit <b>3</b>, if the cover member <b>41</b> is not attached to the cover support member <b>25</b>, the guide surface does not exist in the paper feed unit <b>3</b>. In this case, the transporting target is not fed from the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> to the paper feed unit <b>3</b> because the transporting target is jammed in a section where the screw <b>45</b> is inserted or other section. Therefore, whenever the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is fitted to the paper feed unit <b>3</b>, the cover member <b>41</b> is attached to the cover support member <b>25</b>, which prevents loss of the cover member <b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">Note that, the transporting target is generally a medium on which images are formed by an image forming device, and more specifically the transporting target is a sheet such as paper and overhead transparency.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">Here, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, when a distance from the top of the raised section <b>44</b> to the leading end of the rib <b>43</b> is denoted as H<b>2</b>, H<b>2</b> is expressed, using H<b>3</b> and H<b>4</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, by the following equation: H<b>2</b>=H<b>3</b>−H<b>4</b>. Note that, the cover member <b>41</b> is formed so that H<b>2</b>&gt;H<b>1</b> is satisfied. With this arrangement, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, when the cover member <b>41</b> is attached to the cover support member <b>25</b> so that the back surface of the base of the cover member <b>41</b> faces the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b>, a part of the cover member <b>41</b> (vicinity of the leading end of the rib <b>43</b>) is in a state of being projected over the right-side surface <b>26</b> of the paper feed unit <b>3</b>. The projected part is located at the lower side of a guide member <b>64</b> forming the paper-feeding port <b>61</b> of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b>. Note that, the guide member <b>64</b> has a function of guiding a transporting target at the paper-feeding port <b>61</b> of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">More specifically, the cover member <b>41</b> provided to the image forming device <b>1</b> and the guide member <b>64</b> provided to the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> overlap each other in the perpendicular direction. With this arrangement, the guide surface of the cover member <b>41</b> and the guide member <b>64</b> are continuously connected to each other without being disconnected, thus reliably guiding a transporting target such as a sheet of paper fed from the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> to the paper feed unit <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">As described previously, when the large-capacity paper feeder (second device) <b>60</b> is not fitted to the image forming device (first device) <b>1</b>, the cover member <b>41</b> is attached to the image forming device <b>1</b> in such a direction that the front surface of the base of the cover member <b>41</b> is exposed to the outside of the image forming device <b>1</b>. This makes the cover member <b>41</b> to function as a cover for the paper receiving port (attaching section) <b>30</b> (first function).</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">On the other hand, when the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>, the cover member <b>41</b> is attached to the image forming device <b>1</b> in such a direction that the ribs <b>43</b> formed on the back surface of the base of the cover member <b>41</b> are exposed to the outside of the image forming device <b>1</b> (i.e. in a direction opposite to the foregoing direction). This makes the cover member <b>41</b> to function as a guide of a transporting target fed from the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> (second function).</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">Note that, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, on the right-side surface <b>26</b> of the image forming device <b>1</b> provided are a hook section <b>29</b> in the lower position and an eye section <b>28</b> in the upper position. Further, on the left-side surface of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> provided are a hook support member <b>63</b> in the lower position and a hook section <b>62</b> in the upper position.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">The hook section <b>29</b> of the paper feed unit <b>3</b> is hooked on the hook support member <b>63</b> of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b>. Next, the upper part of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is rotated toward the paper feed unit <b>3</b> upon the hook support member <b>63</b>. With this arrangement, the hook section <b>62</b> of the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is engaged in the eye section <b>28</b> of the paper feed unit <b>3</b>. As a result of this, the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is attached and secured to the paper feed unit <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0100">When the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is unnecessary, the hook section <b>62</b> and the eye section <b>28</b> are unhooked from each other, and the hook support member <b>63</b> and the hook section <b>29</b> are unhooked from each other. This separates the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> from the image forming device <b>1</b>. Thereafter, the cover member <b>41</b> is attached to the cover support member <b>25</b> again so that the front surface of the base faces outside.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0101">Thus, the function of the cover member <b>41</b> is freely changed between a cover and a sheet guide member, depending on whether or not the large-capacity paper feeder <b>60</b> is fitted to the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0102">Note that, the cover member <b>41</b> as external cover according to the Second Embodiment can be altered as follows.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0103">The above arrangement has assumed that the cover member <b>41</b> is secured to the cover support member <b>25</b> with the screws <b>45</b>. However, a way of securing the cover member <b>41</b> is not limited to a way of securing with screws. For example, the cover member <b>41</b> may be secured to the cover support member <b>25</b> by hook connection or by using a magnet.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0104">Further, the following arrangement may be adopted: the cover member <b>41</b> includes a support axis, and the cover member <b>41</b> is rotatably secured to the cover support member <b>25</b> about the support axis. With this arrangement, it is possible to change between the surfaces respectively having functions, without detaching the cover member <b>41</b> from the image forming device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0105">As described above, in an external cover of an embodiment of the present invention is an external cover covering an attaching section which is provided in a main unit of a first device to fit a second device to the main unit of the first device, the external cover, when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device, serves a first function as a cover for the attaching section, and the external cover, when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, serves a second function which is different from the first function while maintaining the first function, such that the external cover is provided to the first device or the second device in a state different from a state when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device.</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0106">According to the above arrangement, the external cover has a first function of covering an attaching section (a part connecting between the main unit of the first device and the second device) provided in the main unit of the first device. To realize system expansion by fitting the second device to the main unit of the first device, the external cover having been provided as a cover for the attaching section is reused, serving a new function while maintaining the first function as a cover. Therefore, even when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, the external cover is necessary for the first device or the second device. This eliminates loss of the external cover. In the case where the second device is separated from the first device so as to get back to a state where the first device is independent from the second device, the external cover can be reattached to the main unit of the first device, functioning as a cover for the attaching section. This makes it possible to secure a good appearance of the first device, to make effective use of resources, and to provide an external cover with no risk of being lost.</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0107">Further, in addition to the above arrangement, an external cover of an embodiment of the present invention preferably has an arrangement such that one of the first device and the second device is provided with object determination means which determines whether or not there exists any object at a predetermined position, prior to fitting the second device to the main unit of the first device, the external cover is detached from the attaching section, and while the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, the external cover exists at the position thus determined by the object determination means, and is attached to an device which is not provided with the object determination means of the first device and the second device.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0108">Here, the object determination means provided in the device is means for determining whether or not there exists any object at a predetermined position relative to the device. The predetermined position relative to the device can be expressed by a specific coordinate in the X-Y-Z coordinate system having the center of the device as an origin point.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0109">According to the above arrangement, to fit the second device to the first device, the external cover is detached from the attaching section of the first device, and attached to another position of the first device, or any position of the second device. That is, this means that the external cover, which is an object, exists at a place where no object originally exists. Here, the position where the external cover is attached is set so as to correspond to a position at which the object determination means provided in the second device (or the first device) determines whether or not there exists any object, when the second device is properly fitted to the main unit of the first device. Therefore, on the basis of determination result obtained by the object determination means, the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, so that it is possible to determine whether or not relative positions between the first device and the second device are proper.</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0110">Further, in addition to the above arrangement, an external cover of an embodiment of the present invention preferably has an arrangement such that the external cover includes a plurality of surfaces, and when the external cover is attached to the first device, a function of the external cover is changed between the first function and the second function depending on which surface of the plurality of surfaces is exposed to outside of the first device.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0111">According to the above arrangement, a surface of the external cover exposed to outside of the first device is different depending on whether or not the second device is fitted to the first device. Therefore, when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device, one surface of the external cover exposed to outside the first device can serve a function as a cover for the attaching section (first function). When the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, the external cover can serve another function (second function) by causing the other surface to provide a shape having the second function and exposing the other surface of the external cover to outside of the first device. This makes it possible to allow the external cover to have a plurality of functions, and to avoid waste of resources without disposal of the external cover. In this case, a position where the external cover is attached to the main unit of the first device can be one and the same position regardless of whether or not the second device is fitted to the first device.</p>
<p id="p-0113" num="0112">Still further, in addition to the above arrangement, an external cover of the present invention preferably has an arrangement such that while the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, a transporting target can be delivered between the main unit of the first device and the second device, and a surface of the external cover exposed to outside of the main unit of the first device serves the second function by guiding the transporting target to be transported.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0113">According to the above arrangement, a transporting target which is delivered between the first device and the second device when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device can be guided (transported) smoothly.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0114">Yet further, in addition to the above arrangement, an external cover of the present invention preferably has an arrangement such that the second device has a guide member which guides the transporting target to be transported, and when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, the guide member and a surface of the external cover exposed to outside of the first device overlap each other.</p>
<p id="p-0116" num="0115">According to the above arrangement, the first device and a part functioning as a guide member included in the second device overlap each other, thereby more reliably performing delivery of the transporting target between the first device and the second device.</p>
<p id="p-0117" num="0116">Further, in addition to the above arrangement, an external cover of the present invention preferably has an arrangement such that the second function is a function associated with the second device.</p>
<p id="p-0118" num="0117">According to the above arrangement, when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device to realize system expansion, the external cover is reused, serving a function associated with the second device having being fitted. On this account, the external cover is always necessary when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, and is reused without being disposed, so that it is always possible to make effective use of resources.</p>
<p id="p-0119" num="0118">Further, an image forming device of an embodiment of the present invention includes the external cover.</p>
<p id="p-0120" num="0119">That is, an image forming device of an embodiment of the present invention is an image forming device including: an attaching section for fitting other device thereto; and an external cover covering the attaching section, when the other device is not fitted to the image forming device, the external cover serves a first function as a cover for the attaching section, and when the other device is fitted to the image forming device, the external cover serves a second function which is different from the first function while maintaining the first function, such that the external cover is provided to the image forming device or the other device in a state different from a state when the other device is not fitted to the image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0121" num="0120">This makes it possible to realize an image forming device allowing another second device (other device) to be fitted thereto, eliminating degradation its appearance when the other device is separated from the image forming device, facilitating effective use of resources in an economical way, and avoiding loss of the external cover.</p>
<p id="p-0122" num="0121">Further, a control system of the present invention includes the first device, the second device, and the external cover, and is arranged such that if the external cover does not serve the second function when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, at least the main unit of the first device, of the main unit of the first device and the second device, is caused not to operate.</p>
<p id="p-0123" num="0122">More specifically, a control system of an embodiment of the present invention includes: a first device; a second device; and an external cover covering an attaching section which is provided in a main unit of the first device to fit a second device to the main unit of the first device, wherein: the external cover, when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device, serves a first function as a cover for the attaching section, the external cover, when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, serves a second function which is different from the first function while maintaining the first function, such that the external cover is provided to the first device or the second device in a state different from a state when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device, and if the external cover does not serve the second function when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, at least the main unit of the first device, of the main unit of the first device and the second device, is caused not to operate.</p>
<p id="p-0124" num="0123">According to the above arrangement, if the external cover does not serve the second function when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, at least the main unit of the first device does not operate. Because of this, the external cover is not mistakenly thrown away or lost. With this arrangement, after the second device is separated from the main unit of the first device, the external cover is reliably reattached as a cover for the attaching section to the first device. This makes it possible to avoid degradation in appearance of the main unit of the first device and to make effective use of resources.</p>
<p id="p-0125" num="0124">The invention being thus described, it will be obvious that the same way may be varied in many ways. Such variations are not to be regarded as a departure from the spirit and scope of the invention, and all such modifications as would be obvious to one skilled in the art are intended to be included within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A device which is a first device for fitting a second device thereto, the device, comprising:
<claim-text>an attaching section to which the second device is fitted; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a removable cover that can be entirely detached from a main unit of the first device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device, the removable cover serving a first function as a cover for the attaching section, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>one of the first device and the second device is provided with object determination means which determines whether or not there exists any object at a predetermined position,</claim-text>
<claim-text>prior to fitting the second device to the main unit of the first device, the removable cover is entirely detached from the attaching section,</claim-text>
<claim-text>while the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, the removable cover exists at the position determined by the object determination means, and is attached to a device which is not provided with the object determination means of the first device and the second device, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, the removable cover serving a second function which is different from the first function, such that the removable cover is entirely detached from the first device at a location at which the removable cover serves as a cover for the attaching section and then reattached to one of either the first device and the second device in a state different from a state when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the object determination means is an actuator, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second function is a function as a shock-absorbing member with respect to the actuator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the second function is a function associated with the second device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A control system comprising:
<claim-text>a first device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a removable cover covering an attaching section which is provided in a main unit of the first device to fit the second device to the main unit of the first device, wherein:</claim-text>
<claim-text>the removable cover, when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device, serves a first function as a cover for the attaching section,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the removable cover, when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, serves a second function which is different from the first function, such that the removable cover is provided to the first device in a state different from a state when the second device is not fitted to the main unit of the first device, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>if the removable cover does not serve the second function when the second device is fitted to the main unit of the first device, at least one of the main unit of the first device, and the main unit of the first device and the second device, is caused not to operate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An image forming device comprising:
<claim-text>an attachment section at which said image forming device is connectable to an auxiliary device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a removable cover attachable to said image forming device in a first manner to cover said attachment section and in a second manner to enable said image forming device and the auxiliary device to function together when the auxiliary device is connected to said image forming device, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said cover is adapted to engage an actuator on the auxiliary device when said cover is secured to said image forming device in the second manner and is to function as a shock absorbing device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A method of selectively rendering operable an image forming device connected to an auxiliary device comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>providing an image forming device having an attachment section for attachment to an auxiliary device and an enablement section for supporting an element for enabling the joint operation of the image forming device and the auxiliary device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>attaching a removable cover at the attachment section;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing an auxiliary device attachable to the image forming device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing the removable cover;</claim-text>
<claim-text>repositioning the removable cover and reattaching the removable cover at the enablement section; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>attaching the auxiliary device to the imaging forming device such that the removable cover enables the joint operation of the image forming device and the auxiliary device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said step of repositioning the removable cover and reattaching the removable cover at the enablement section comprises the steps of reattaching the removable cover at a location spaced from the attachment section.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said step of repositioning the removable cover and reattaching the removable cover at the enablement section comprises the steps of reattaching the removable cover at a location at least partially overlying the attachment section.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. In an image forming device including an attachment section at which an auxiliary device is attachable to the image forming device and a removable cover for covering the attachment section when no auxiliary device is attached to the attachment section, a method of preventing loss of the removable cover comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>configuring the auxiliary device or the image forming device so as to be inoperable when the auxiliary device is connected to the image forming device unless an enabling device is connected to the image forming device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>configuring the removable cover as the enabling device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said step of configuring the removable cover as the enabling device comprises the step of configuring the removable cover as a shock absorbing element for engaging an actuator on the auxiliary device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said step of configuring the removable cover as the enabling device comprises the step of configuring the removable cover as a reflective surface for reflecting a distance measuring light of the auxiliary device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said step of configuring the removable cover as the enabling device comprises the step of configuring the removable cover as a portion of a paper guide path between a paper source in the auxiliary device and a photoconductive drum in the image forming device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. In an image forming device including an attachment section at which an auxiliary device is attachable to the image forming device and a removable cover for covering the attachment section when no auxiliary device is attached to the attachment section, a method of using an enabling device to connect the auxiliary device to the image forming device comprising:
<claim-text>configuring the auxiliary device or the image forming device so as to be inoperable when the auxiliary device is connected to the image forming device unless the enabling device is connected to the image forming device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>using the removable cover as the enabling device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said step of using the removable cover as the enabling device comprises the step of configuring the removable cover as a shock absorbing element for engaging an actuator on the auxiliary device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said step of using the removable cover as the enabling device comprises the step of configuring the removable cover as a reflective surface for reflecting a distance measuring light of the auxiliary device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said step of using the removable cover as the enabling device comprises the step of configuring the removable cover as a portion of a paper guide path between a paper source in the auxiliary device and a photoconductive drum in the image forming device.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
