<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296918-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296918</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11181199</doc-number>
<date>20050715</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>40</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>60</class>
<subclass>Q</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362500</main-classification>
<further-classification>362473</further-classification>
<further-classification>362485</further-classification>
<further-classification>362487</further-classification>
<further-classification>362565</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Illuminated tire rim apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2949869</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Leeuwrik</name>
<date>19600800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>432152</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>D245775</doc-number>
<kind>S</kind>
<name>Muth</name>
<date>19770900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5497302</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>O'Donnel</name>
<date>19960300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5634707</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bailey</name>
<date>19970600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5683164</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chien</name>
<date>19971100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5800035</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Aichele</name>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>D420639</doc-number>
<kind>S</kind>
<name>Roesianto</name>
<date>20000200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6045244</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dixon et al.</name>
<date>20000400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6168301</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Martinez et al.</name>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6220733</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Gordon</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>D461153</doc-number>
<kind>S</kind>
<name>Koyama</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0130905</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Olds et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362487</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>4</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362500</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362487</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362473</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362485</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362565</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Davydyuk</last-name>
<first-name>Dmitriy</first-name>
<address>
<street>10730 Coloma Rd. #14</street>
<city>Rancho Cordova</city>
<state>CA</state>
<postcode>95670</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Davydyuk</last-name>
<first-name>Valentina</first-name>
<address>
<street>10730 Coloma Rd. #14</street>
<city>Rancho Cordova</city>
<state>CA</state>
<postcode>95670</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>O'Shea</last-name>
<first-name>Sandra</first-name>
<department>2875</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Tsidulko</last-name>
<first-name>Mark</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An illuminated tire rim apparatus includes a hub that has a central aperture therein for receiving a free end of an axle of a vehicle. The hub has a plurality of bolt receiving openings therein positioned between the aperture and an outer edge of the hub. A plurality of spokes is attached to the outer edge of the hub and radially extends outwardly therefrom. Each of the spokes is comprised of a substantially translucent material and each of the spokes has an outer end. A rim has a generally cylindrical shape and has an inner surface and an outer surface. Each of the outer ends of the spokes is attached to the rim. Each of a plurality of light emitters is mounted in one of the spokes so that the spokes are illuminated when the light emitters are turned on. A power supply is electrically coupled to the light emitters.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="134.20mm" wi="170.77mm" file="US07296918-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="229.95mm" wi="180.85mm" file="US07296918-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="239.35mm" wi="168.99mm" file="US07296918-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="224.28mm" wi="161.37mm" file="US07296918-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to illuminated tire devices and more particularly pertains to a new illuminated tire device for providing an illuminated rim having a plurality of translucent spokes.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The use of illuminated tire devices is known in the prior art. U.S. Pat. No. 5,497,302 describes a hubcap device that is attachable to a rim and which is selectively illuminated. Another type of illuminated tire device is U.S. Pat. No. 5,634,707 having a structure adapted for being attached to a wheel and which can be selectively turned on for illuminating the wheel. Yet another such device is found in U.S. Pat. No. 5,683,164 which again includes an assembly adapted for being attached to and illuminating a wheel.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">While these devices fulfill their respective, particular objectives and requirements, the need remains for a device which includes integral components of a rim which are selectively illuminated. This can be accomplished with spokes of a rim that are translucent or transparent. This will also give the affect of having no spokes when the spoke are not illuminated and the rim is being rotated.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The present invention meets the needs presented above by generally comprising a hub that has a central aperture therein for receiving a free end of an axle of a vehicle. The hub has a plurality of bolt receiving openings therein positioned between the aperture and an outer edge of the hub. A plurality of spokes is attached to the outer edge of the hub and radially extends outwardly therefrom. Each of the spokes is comprised of a substantially translucent material and each of the spokes has an outer end. A rim has a generally cylindrical shape and has an inner surface and an outer surface. Each of the outer ends of the spokes is attached to the rim. Each of a plurality of light emitters is mounted in one of the spokes so that the spokes are illuminated when the light emitters are turned on. A power supply is electrically coupled to the light emitters.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">There has thus been outlined, rather broadly, the more important features of the invention in order that the detailed description thereof that follows may be better understood, and in order that the present contribution to the art may be better appreciated. There are additional features of the invention that will be described hereinafter and which will form the subject matter of the claims appended hereto.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The objects of the invention, along with the various features of novelty which characterize the invention, are pointed out with particularity in the claims annexed to and forming a part of this disclosure.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The invention will be better understood and objects other than those set forth above will become apparent when consideration is given to the following detailed description thereof. Such description makes reference to the annexed drawings wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a front view of an illuminated tire rim apparatus according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a front view of the present invention having support rods therein.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along line <b>4</b>-<b>4</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an expanded view of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a schematic view of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">With reference now to the drawings, and in particular to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 through 6</figref> thereof, a new illuminated tire device embodying the principles and concepts of the present invention and generally designated by the reference numeral <b>10</b> will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">As best illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 through 6</figref>, the illuminated tire rim apparatus <b>10</b> generally comprises a hub <b>12</b> that has a central aperture <b>14</b> therein for receiving a free end of an axle of a vehicle. The hub <b>12</b> has a plurality of bolt receiving openings <b>16</b> therein positioned between the aperture and an outer edge of the hub <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Each of a plurality of spokes <b>18</b> is attached to the outer edge of the hub <b>12</b> and radially extends outwardly therefrom. Each of the spokes <b>18</b> is comprised of a substantially translucent material. The translucent material is preferable a thermoplastic such a Plexiglas. It should be understood that translucent includes slightly opaque to completely transparent. Each of the spokes <b>18</b> has an outer end <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">A rim <b>22</b> has a generally cylindrical shape and has an inner surface <b>24</b> and an outer surface <b>26</b>. Each of the outer ends <b>20</b> of the spokes <b>18</b> is attached to the rim <b>22</b>. The spokes <b>18</b> may be attached to rim <b>22</b> and hub <b>12</b> in a number of ways. One preferred way is to include an inner ring of translucent material, which forms the hub <b>12</b>, and which is integrally attached to the spokes <b>18</b>. An outer ring <b>28</b> of translucent material is attached to the outer ends <b>20</b> of the spokes <b>18</b> and the outer ring <b>28</b> is secured to the rim <b>22</b> with a plurality of fasteners <b>30</b>. The rim <b>22</b> is comprised of a metallic material. A stabilizing ring <b>32</b> may be attached to the inner ring, or hub <b>12</b>, to add strength to the hub <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A plurality of stabilizing rods <b>34</b> may be included. Each of the rods <b>34</b> has a first end <b>36</b> and a second end <b>38</b>. Each of the first ends <b>36</b> is attached to the hub <b>12</b> and each of the second ends <b>38</b> is attached to the rim <b>22</b>. The rods <b>34</b> are each positioned in one of the spokes <b>18</b> so that each of the spokes <b>18</b> has at least one rod <b>34</b> positioned therein. The rods <b>34</b> ensure that the spokes <b>18</b> are strong enough to hold the weight of a vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">A plurality of light emitters <b>40</b> is provided. Each of the light emitters <b>40</b> is mounted in one of the spokes <b>18</b> so that the spokes <b>18</b> are illuminated when the light emitters <b>40</b> are turned on. Each of the light emitters <b>40</b> is positioned adjacent to the hub <b>12</b> and is directed toward the rim <b>22</b>. This position aids in hiding the light emitters <b>40</b> from a person viewing the spokes <b>18</b>. A cap <b>42</b> and cover <b>44</b> may be positioned over the hub <b>12</b> to aid in hiding the light emitters <b>40</b>. A power supply <b>46</b> is electrically coupled to the light emitters <b>40</b>. The power supply <b>46</b> may either be electrically coupled directly to a vehicle's power supply or at least one battery mounted in the hub <b>12</b>. An actuator <b>48</b> is electrically coupled to the power supply <b>46</b> for selectively turning the light emitters <b>40</b> on or off. The actuator <b>48</b> may be a button positioned on the hub <b>12</b> or in the vehicle if the vehicle's power supply is being used. Alternatively, the actuator may include a switch that is actuated by centrifugal force so that the light emitters <b>40</b> are turned on when the hub <b>12</b> is rotated.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In use, the apparatus <b>10</b> is used as conventional rim on which a tire mounted. The rim is then mounted on a vehicle's axle. The spokes <b>18</b> provide the illusion that the rims are floating around the hubs <b>12</b> while the light emitters <b>40</b> add an ornamental affect.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">With respect to the above description then, it is to be realized that the optimum dimensional relationships for the parts of the invention, to include variations in size, materials, shape, form, function and manner of operation, assembly and use, are deemed readily apparent and obvious to one skilled in the art, and all equivalent relationships to those illustrated in the drawings and described in the specification are intended to be encompassed by the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Therefore, the foregoing is considered as illustrative only of the principles of the invention. Further, since numerous modifications and changes will readily occur to those skilled in the art, it is not desired to limit the invention to the exact construction and operation shown and described, and accordingly, all suitable modifications and equivalents may be resorted to, falling within the scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An illuminated tire mounting assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a hub having a central aperture therein for receiving a free end of an axle of a vehicle, said hub having a plurality of bolt receiving openings therein positioned between said aperture and an outer edge of said hub;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of spokes being attached to said outer edge of said hub and radially extending outwardly therefrom, each of said spokes consisting of a substantially translucent material, each of said spokes having an outer end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rim having a generally cylindrical shape and having an inner surface and an outer surface, each of said outer ends of said spokes being attached to said rim;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of light emitters, each of said light emitters being mounted in one of said spokes such that said spokes are illuminated when said light emitters are turned on; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply being electrically coupled to said light emitters.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further including a plurality of stabilizing rods, each of said rods having a first end and a second end, each of said first ends being attached to said hub and each of said second ends being attached to said rim, each of said rods being positioned in one of said spokes such that each of said spokes has at least one rod positioned therein.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The assembly according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each of said light emitters is positioned adjacent to said hub and being directed toward said rim.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. An illuminated tire mounting assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a hub having a central aperture therein for receiving a free end of an axle of a vehicle, said hub having a plurality of bolt receiving openings therein positioned between said aperture and an outer edge of said hub;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of spokes being attached to said outer edge of said hub and radially extending outwardly therefrom, each of said spokes consisting of a substantially translucent material, each of said spokes having an outer end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rim having a generally cylindrical shape and having an inner surface and an outer surface, each of said outer ends of said spokes being attached to said rim;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of stabilizing rods, each of said rods having a first end and a second end, each of said first ends being attached to said hub and each of said second ends being attached to said rim, each of said rods being positioned in one of said spokes such that each of said spokes has at least one rod positioned therein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of light emitters, each of said light emitters being mounted in one of said spokes such that said spokes are illuminated when said light emitters are turned on, each of said light emitters being positioned adjacent to said hub and being directed toward said rim;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply being electrically coupled to said light emitters, said power supply comprising at least one battery; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an actuator being electrically coupled to said power supply for selectively turning said light emitters on or off.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
