<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298082-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298082</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10959975</doc-number>
<date>20041008</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2003-0070337</doc-number>
<date>20031009</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>400</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>62</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>63</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313504</main-classification>
<further-classification>313498</further-classification>
<further-classification>313506</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Organic electroluminescent display device with projecting structure layer</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6489638</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Seo et al.</name>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257 98</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7128632</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Nakamura</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>445 25</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0026125</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Yamazaki et al.</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313505</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0035713</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kimura</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313501</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0048072</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ishihara et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313506</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0127974</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Miyazawa</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313504</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0040762</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kurihara</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>313512</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2002-055411</doc-number>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313504</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313498</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313506</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313512</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>313292</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050077819</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050414</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Park</last-name>
<first-name>Jin-Woo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yongin-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>H.C. Park &amp; Associates, PLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung SDI Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Suwon</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Patel</last-name>
<first-name>Nimeshkumar D.</first-name>
<department>2879</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Quarterman</last-name>
<first-name>Kevin</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention relates to an organic electroluminescent display device in which luminance and emission efficiency may be improved by forming light emitting elements of the organic electroluminescent display device in a projecting structure and provides an organic electroluminescent display device comprising a projecting structure layer formed on an insulating substrate; first electrode formed in a projecting structure on the substrate including the projecting structure layer; an organic layer formed on the first electrode; and second electrode formed on the insulating substrate, wherein the second electrode may be formed in a projected shape by the projecting structure layer so that the second electrode surrounds the organic layer.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="128.19mm" wi="218.19mm" file="US07298082-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="225.13mm" wi="159.77mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298082-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="219.29mm" wi="147.57mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298082-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the benefit of Korean Patent Application No. 2003-70337, filed on Oct. 9, 2003, the disclosure of which is hereby incorporated herein by reference in its entirety.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to an organic electroluminescent display device (and method for fabricating the same), and more particularly to a rear emitting type organic electroluminescent display device having improved luminance and emission efficiency. These advantages may be obtained by forming light emitting elements in a projecting structure in such a way that a second electrode surrounds an organic layer.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Organic electroluminescent display devices have received recent attention because of their merits with regard to thinness, width of viewing angle, weight, size, response speed and power consumption in comparison to cathode ray tube (CRT) and liquid crystal display (LCD) devices. Particularly, organic electroluminescent display devices may have the advantage of being easily fabricated through a simple fabrication process. The simplified fabrication process may arise from the simple structure of an organic electroluminescent display device: anode electrode, organic material film, and cathode electrode.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A brief description of a rear emitting type organic electroluminescent display follows with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross sectional view for showing a conventional rear emitting type organic electroluminescent display device.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, first electrode <b>150</b> may be electrically connected to the thin film transistor and may function as an anode electrode. First electrode <b>150</b> may be formed on a lower insulating substrate <b>100</b> equipped an inter-insulating layer <b>140</b> on the thin film transistor T including activation layer <b>110</b>, gate electrode <b>120</b>, and source/drain electrodes <b>131</b> and <b>135</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">An opening part <b>165</b> for exposing a part of first electrode <b>150</b> may be formed by creating a pixel defined layer <b>160</b> on the front side of the lower insulating substrate <b>100</b> and using a photolithography technique on pixel defined layer <b>160</b> after forming first electrode <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">An organic layer <b>170</b> may be formed on an upper part of an opening part <b>165</b> after forming opening part <b>165</b>. Open part <b>165</b> may expose a part of first electrode <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">An organic emitting device E including first electrode <b>150</b>, organic layer <b>170</b>, and a second electrode <b>180</b> may be formed by creating second electrode <b>180</b> on the front side of the lower insulating substrate <b>100</b> after forming the organic layer <b>170</b>. Second electrode <b>180</b> may function as a cathode electrode.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The lower insulating substrate <b>100</b> including the thin film transistor T and organic emitting device E may be sealed using a sealing substrate as an upper insulating substrate. The sealing substrate has been omitted from the drawings, but may be formed after forming the organic emitting device E.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Unfortunately, only about 20% of light actually generated from the organic layer <b>170</b> may be extracted to the outside since the light may be lost by being absorbed by several films of a lower part of the organic layer <b>170</b> in the process of being emitted from the organic layer <b>170</b>. A particularly large amount of light may be lost at one side from the first electrode <b>150</b> functioning as an anode electrode. The loss may be through total reflection. For example, a conventional rear emitting type organic electroluminescent display device may have problems with low emission efficiency and luminance because a large amount of light emitted from the organic layer <b>170</b> may be lost.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Therefore, in order to solve the foregoing problems of the conventional art, it may be one aspect of the present invention to provide a rear emitting type organic electroluminescent display device in which emission efficiency and luminance may be improved by forming an organic emitting device in a projecting structure, thereby reflecting light getting out to the side by total reflection at each interlayer boundary surface so that the reflected light may be extracted in a rear direction.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In order to achieve the foregoing object, the present invention provides an organic electroluminescent display device comprising a projecting structure layer formed on an insulating substrate; first electrode formed in a projecting structure on the substrate including the projecting structure layer; an organic layer formed on the first electrode; and second electrode formed on the insulating substrate, wherein the second electrode formed in a projected shape by the projecting structure layer so that the second electrode surrounds the organic layer.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In embodiments of the present invention, a part of the second electrode may be positioned under the lower surface of flat region of the first electrode. Furthermore, it may be desirable that the projecting structure layer formed of a material having a small refractive index difference between the projecting structure layer and the first electrode, and it more that the projecting structure layer formed of a material having a refractive index of 1.0 to 1.7.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Furthermore, it may be desirable that the projecting structure layer formed of any one material selected from the group consisting of an organic material of BCB, acryl based curing resin, phenol based curing resin or polyimide, an inorganic material of silicon oxide or silicon nitride, and an organic and inorganic composite material ormocer, aerosol or porous silicon dioxide.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Furthermore, it may be desirable that the projecting structure layer has a thickness of 300 nm to <b>10</b> μm and a gradient of 15 degrees to 70 degrees. Furthermore, it may be desirable that the organic layer formed on an upper part of the first electrode a part of which exposed by a pixel defined layer and the pixel defined layer thinner than the projecting structure layer.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The above and other features and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art by describing in detail several embodiments thereof with reference to the attached drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross sectional view for showing an organic electroluminescent display device; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross sectional view for showing an organic electroluminescent display device according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The present invention will now be described in detail in connection with several embodiments with reference to the accompanying drawings. For reference, like reference characters designate corresponding parts throughout several views.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross sectional view showing a rear emitting type organic electroluminescent display device according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">An organic electroluminescent display device according to an embodiment of the present invention as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> includes a projecting structure layer <b>240</b> formed on an inter-insulating layer <b>238</b> on an insulating substrate <b>200</b>; first electrode <b>250</b> formed on the insulating substrate <b>200</b> including the projecting structure layer <b>240</b>; an organic layer <b>270</b> formed in a projecting structure on the first electrode <b>250</b>; and second electrode <b>280</b> formed on the front side of the insulating substrate <b>200</b>, wherein the second electrode <b>280</b> may be formed in a projected shape by the projecting structure layer <b>240</b> so that the second electrode <b>280</b> surrounds the organic layer <b>270</b>. Such a projecting structure <b>240</b> formed in a projecting shape may serve as an elevating structure.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">A part of the second electrode <b>280</b> may be positioned under the lower surface of flat region of the first electrode <b>250</b> by the projecting structure layer <b>240</b> so that light emitted from the organic layer <b>270</b> may be reflected to the rear side, and the reflected light may be extracted to the rear side by reflecting light getting out to the side by total reflection without transmission of the first electrode <b>250</b> and projecting structure layer <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a projecting structure layer <b>240</b> may be formed by depositing an organic material having low refractive index on a lower insulating substrate <b>200</b> equipped with a thin film transistor T including activation layer <b>210</b>, gate electrode <b>220</b> and source/drain electrodes <b>231</b>, <b>235</b> and patterning the organic material. The projecting structure layer <b>240</b> plays a role of forming an organic emitting device E in a projected structure for the front direction. The lower insulating substrate <b>200</b> together with thin film transistor T, and including its various layers below first electrode <b>250</b>, may be an example of the control portion of the device.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">It may be desirable that the projecting structure layer <b>240</b> may be formed in such a way that the projecting structure layer may have a thickness of 300 nm to 10 μm, and the side of the projecting structure layer <b>240</b> may have a gradient of 15 degrees to 70 degrees. Such a projecting structure <b>240</b> may result in a convex shape being supplied to layers deposited or otherwise formed on projecting structure <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Furthermore, the projecting structure layer <b>240</b> may be preferably formed of a material having a small refractive index difference between the projecting structure layer and first electrode to be formed afterward, and more preferably formed of a material having a refractive index of 1.0 to 1.7 so that total reflection generated at the boundary surface between the first electrode and the projecting structure layer <b>240</b> may be minimized.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Furthermore, it may be desirable that the projecting structure layer <b>240</b> may be formed of an organic material such as BCB, acryl based curing resin, phenol based curing resin and polyimide, an inorganic material such as silicon oxide and silicon nitride, or an organic and inorganic composite material such as ormocer, aerosol and porous silica.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">First electrode <b>250</b> operated as an anode electrode, electrically connected to the thin film transistor T and formed in a projected structure by the projecting structure layer may be formed by depositing a transparent conductive material formed of ITO and IZO on the projecting structure layer <b>240</b> and patterning the transparent conductive material after forming the projecting structure layer <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">A part of the first electrode <b>250</b> may be exposed by forming a pixel defined layer <b>260</b> on the front side of the lower insulating substrate <b>200</b> and photolithographing the pixel defined layer <b>260</b> after forming the first electrode <b>250</b>, wherein the pixel defined layer <b>260</b> may be preferably formed in such a way that the pixel defined layer <b>260</b> may be thinner than the projecting structure layer <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">An organic layer <b>270</b> may be formed on an exposed part of the first electrode <b>250</b> after forming the pixel defined layer <b>260</b>. The organic layer <b>270</b> can be formed of several layers according to function of the organic layer <b>270</b> and may be generally formed in a multilayer structure including at least one or more layers selected from hole injection layer (HIL), hole transfer layer (HTL), emitting layer, hole blocking layer (HBL), electron transport layer (ETL) and electron injection layer (EIL). The organic layer <b>270</b> and accompanying layers such as the pixel defined layer <b>260</b> and the second electrode <b>280</b> may be an example of the electroluminescent portion of the device.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">An organic emitting device E having projecting structure layer <b>240</b>, first electrode <b>250</b>, pixel defined layer <b>260</b>, organic layer <b>270</b>, and second electrode <b>280</b> formed in a projected structure for the front side may be formed by forming second electrode <b>280</b>, operated as a cathode electrode and formed in a projected structure on the front side of the lower insulating substrate <b>200</b>, after forming the organic layer <b>270</b>, wherein the second electrode <b>280</b> may be formed in a projected structure by the projecting structure layer <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Furthermore, a material of Mg, Ag, Ca, Al or Ba having superior reflectivity and lower work function than a material used as the first electrode <b>250</b> may be preferably used as the second electrode <b>280</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Furthermore, it may be desirable that a part of the second electrode <b>280</b> may be positioned under the lower surface of flat region of the first electrode <b>250</b> so that the second electrode <b>280</b> surrounds the organic layer <b>270</b> to extract the reflected light to the rear side by reflecting light getting out to the side by total reflection without transmission of the first electrode <b>250</b> and projecting structure layer <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">A lower insulating substrate <b>200</b> including light emitting element E and thin film transistor T may be sealed using a sealing substrate used as an upper insulating substrate although the sealing substrate is not illustrated on drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">If voltage is impressed to an organic electroluminescent display device formed through the foregoing processes, holes injected through anode electrode may be combined with electrons injected through cathode electrode in organic layer so that the organic layer may be emitted, and light emitted from the organic layer <b>270</b> comes out in a direction of the first electrode <b>250</b>, wherein light loss may be increased accordingly since total reflection may be increased if a refractive index difference between the first electrode <b>250</b> and lower film may be large.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The total reflection may be generated at the boundary surface between the dense medium and the sparse medium if a refractive index between the dense medium and the sparse medium may be large if light proceeds from dense medium to sparse medium.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The total reflection may be generated if an incidence angle of light may be larger than an incidence angle at which total reflection may be generated, and critical angle of the total reflection may be sin θ=1/n<sub>1,2</sub>=n<sub>1</sub>/n<sub>2</sub>, wherein n<sub>1,2 </sub>may be a refractive index of the dense medium to the sparse medium, n<sub>1 </sub>may be a refractive index of the sparse medium, and n<sub>2 </sub>may be a refractive index of the dense medium.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">For example, the total reflection may be further increased since the larger a refractive index difference between the sparse medium and the dense medium may be, the smaller the critical angle of the total reflection becomes.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Therefore, an organic electroluminescent display device including a projecting structure type organic emitting device E according to an embodiment of the present invention reduces total reflection by forming the first electrode <b>250</b> and projecting structure layer <b>240</b> using a material having the similar refractive index and theoretically increases 100% or more of light extracting ratio by reflecting light lost to the side by the total reflection at the second electrode <b>280</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">As described in the above, the present invention may be capable of providing an organic electroluminescent display device with superior luminance and emission efficiency by forming light emitting element of the organic electroluminescent display device in a projected structure, thereby collecting light emitted from organic layer at reflective second electrode and reflecting light getting out to the side by total reflection at first electrode so that the reflected light may be collected.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Furthermore, the present invention may be capable of providing an organic electroluminescent display device whose power consumption and life time may be improved by improving luminance and emission efficiency.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">While the invention has been particularly shown and described with reference to several embodiments thereof, it will be understood by those skilled in the art that the foregoing and other changes in form and details may be made therein without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An organic electroluminescent display device, comprising:
<claim-text>a projecting structure layer formed on an insulating substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first electrode disposed on the projecting structure layer such that the first electrode has a projected shape in a perpendicular direction to the insulating substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an organic layer formed on the first electrode; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second electrode formed on the insulating substrate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second electrode is formed in a projected shape by the projecting structure layer so that the second electrode surrounds the organic layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein a part of the second electrode is positioned under the lower surface of a flat region of the first electrode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the projecting structure layer is formed of a material having substantially the same refractive index as that of the first electrode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the projecting structure layer is formed of a material having a refractive index of 1.0 to 1.7.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the projecting structure layer is formed of an organic material selected from the group consisting of BOB, acryl based curing resin, phenol based curing resin and polyimide.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the projecting structure layer is formed of silicon oxide or silicon nitride.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the projecting structure layer is formed of an organic and inorganic composite material of ormocer, aerosol or porous silicon dioxide.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the projecting structure layer has a thickness of 300 nm to 10 μm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the projecting structure layer has a gradient of 15 degrees to 70 degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The organic electroluminescent display device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the organic layer is formed on an upper part of the first electrode a part of which is exposed by a pixel defined layer, and the pixel defined layer is thinner than the projecting structure layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
