<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298888-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298888</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10689799</doc-number>
<date>20031021</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>792</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>382151</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Electronic level sensor</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2252727</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Pepper</name>
<date>19410800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3324564</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wright et al.</name>
<date>19670600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4382680</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hamar</name>
<date>19830500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4468119</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hamar</name>
<date>19840800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4566202</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hamar</name>
<date>19860100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4666299</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tamaki et al.</name>
<date>19870500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4714344</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hamar</name>
<date>19871200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5307368</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hamar</name>
<date>19940400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5317810</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Isono et al.</name>
<date>19940600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5322441</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lewis et al.</name>
<date>19940600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5371951</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Piske</name>
<date>19941200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5704130</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Augustin et al.</name>
<date>19980100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 3336612</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6115928</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dauerer</name>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 33348</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6248989</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ohishi</name>
<date>20010600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6320653</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Feist</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6343422</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Takahashi</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00017">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6410932</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Johnson</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00018">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6568021</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wood</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 152354</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00019">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0218469</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Brazell et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324637</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>15</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>382151</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60420804</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20021023</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040083616</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040506</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hamar</last-name>
<first-name>Martin R.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wilton</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hespos</last-name>
<first-name>Gerald E.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Casella</last-name>
<first-name>Anthony J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hamar Laser Instruments, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Danbury</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Bali</last-name>
<first-name>Vikkram</first-name>
<department>2624</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electro-optical level includes a bubble level having a tube with a liquid therein and a bubble formed by the liquid in the tube. A substantially linear light source is directed toward and through the tube. A linear lens array focuses light passing through the bubble tube onto a linear lens array for producing an image of the bubble in the bubble level. The lens array employs the focused light to identify precisely end points of the bubble in the tube and then employs locational data for the end points to assess levelness. The electro-optical level further includes an out put display that is pivotally mounted into an optimal alignment for easy viewing by a user.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="106.93mm" wi="122.09mm" file="US07298888-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="242.82mm" wi="138.68mm" file="US07298888-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="134.28mm" wi="168.57mm" file="US07298888-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="223.01mm" wi="165.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298888-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="191.94mm" wi="111.17mm" file="US07298888-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority on U.S. Provisional Patent Appl. No. 60/420,804, filed Oct. 23, 2002.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The invention relates to a bubble level that employs electro-optical components for achieving high precision.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A typical carpenter's level is an elongated generally rectangular structure having opposed first and second ends. Planar top and bottom faces are aligned parallel to one another and extend between the ends. The top and bottom faces are the portions of the prior art level that will be placed against another surface for assessing horizontal or vertical alignment.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A typical prior art level includes a glass tube partly filled with a liquid spirit. The portion of the tube that is not filled by the liquid forms a bubble. Movement of the level will cause the liquid to shift within the tube, and hence will cause a repositioning of the bubble. The tube includes a pair of lines that are spaced apart by a distance approximately equal to the length of the bubble. When the tube is aligned horizontally, the liquid will be disposed symmetrically in the tube, and the bubble will be positioned precisely between the lines.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The prior art level can be used by placing the top or bottom face of the level on a substantially horizontal surface. The relative position of the bubble in the tube provides an indication of the closeness of the level to a horizontal alignment. The surface on which the level is supported may be adjusted to position the bubble between the lines of the tube, and hence to achieve a fairly exact horizontal alignment of the surface on which the level is supported.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The precision that can be obtained with the prior art level is dependent upon the eyesight of the user and the ability of the user to determine the positions of the ends of the bubble relative to the lines on the glass tube. This ability will depend at least partly upon the optical alignment of the user of the level relative to the bubble tube. Precision can be fairly good if the user has good eyesight and if the user can be positioned so that the line of sight is perpendicular to the axis of the tube. However, the realities of a construction or manufacturing site often do not permit the user of a level to be positioned perfectly relative to the bubble tube. Thus, the level may be positioned at a location significantly above the head of the user or at a position where the line of sight is at an acute angle to the axis of the bubble tube. Either of these fairly common uses of a level significantly reduce accuracies that can be obtained by the level.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The boundary between the gas and the liquid in the bubble tube is fairly precise. However, the bubble is an elliptoid with curved boundaries. A viewer necessarily sees the curved boundaries between the gas and the liquid in the bubble tube, and hence the boundary between the bubble and the liquid appears as a fairly dark broad line. The apparent width of the line that defines the bubble can lead to a lack of precision by the user. In particular, accuracy will vary depending upon which part of the apparently broad boundary of the bubble aligns with the positioning indicia on the glass tube.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The prior art includes the use of electro-optical devices that attempt to determine the position of a bubble in a level. These devices have taken several forms, but rely primarily on attempts to identify an end or midpoint of the bubble or to identify an angle of the surface of the liquid. The known electro-optical devices used with a bubble level do not provide the desired degree of precision.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In view of the above, an object of the subject invention is to provide a bubble level with significantly increased accuracy.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Another object of the subject invention is to provide a bubble level where accuracy is not dependent upon the angle of viewing.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The subject invention is directed to a level that includes electronic and optical components for providing a high degree of accuracy independent of the angle of viewing and independent of the eyesight of the viewer.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The apparatus of the subject invention includes a bubble tube partly filled with a liquid so that a generally elliptoid bubble remains in the tube. The apparatus further includes a light source in proximity to the bubble tube and operative to direct light toward and through the bubble tube. The apparatus further includes a light sensor on a side of the bubble tube substantially diametrically opposite the light source and aligned for receiving light emitted from the light source and passing through the bubble. The light sensor is operative to generate electrical signals indicative of centers of energy impinging thereon. The apparatus also includes a focusing means between the bubble and the light sensor for focusing light passing through the bubble tube onto the sensor. The focusing means is operative to effectively image the bubble and adjacent areas of the bubble tube onto the sensor. The apparatus also may include a display for providing a clear visual indication of the output of the light sensor. The display may be a screen with a graph for identifying energy levels. Alternatively, the display may be a precise graphic depiction of a bubble tube. Still further, the display may provide a numerical quantification of the degree of levelness. The display may be mounted to the apparatus for pivoting or swiveling into an alignment that facilitates observation by a user. Thus, in contrast to prior art levels, accuracy and readability are entirely independent of the relevant positions of the level and the user.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The light source may comprise a substantially linear light source, such as a cold cathode illuminator, aligned parallel to the bubble tube.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The focusing means may include a lens array extending substantially linearly and parallel to the bubble tube. Alternatively, the focusing means may include a conventional cylindrical lens aligned substantially parallel to the axis of the bubble tube.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The light sensor may be a CCD array aligned substantially parallel to the bubble tube. The light sensor preferably is spaced approximately 1/16-⅛″ from the focusing means.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In operation, the transmission of the light through the bubble tube will vary depending upon whether the light is being transmitted through the bubble or through the liquid and is significantly differently at the boundaries between the liquid and the bubble. In particular, light will be reflected or refracted differently by the bubble than by the liquid. These differences result in inverted peaks or “divots” in the output signals of the light sensor at locations substantially aligned with the ends of the bubble. The divots will be substantially identical and at known positions when the bubble is centered in the bubble tube. However, the divots will shift and/or change in size when the bubble moves in the tube.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The apparatus may be used with a differential screw adjusting means for moving the position of the level relative to the object that is being assessed. Hence, the differential screw adjuster may be moved until the light sensor and any output means associated therewith produce signals to indicate a level state for the level. Thus, amounts of adjustments can be measured.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The apparatus has several significant advantages over more complex electronic levels. In particular, the apparatus is very rugged and very compact. Furthermore, the apparatus can be packaged within a version of a conventional carpenter's level that is familiar to skilled technicians.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a front elevational view of a level apparatus in accordance with the subject invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a front elevational view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, but showing the display in a different orientation.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an exploded schematic view of the bubble level and the electronic and optical components used therewith.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic illustration of the output of the level apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a graphic depiction of a portion of the readout for precisely identifying a position of an end of the bubble.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">A level apparatus in accordance with the subject invention is identified generally by the numeral <b>10</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>. The apparatus <b>10</b> includes an elongate rectangular housing <b>12</b>, an electro-optical level sensor <b>14</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) and an output display <b>16</b>. The output display <b>16</b> is mounted pivotally to the housing <b>12</b> to achieve an optimum viewing angle for a user. The pivotal connection permits 360° of rotation of the display <b>16</b> relative to the housing <b>12</b>. The display <b>16</b> incorporates a carrying handle <b>17</b> configured and dimensioned to be gripped by hand for carrying and positioning the apparatus <b>10</b>. The apparatus <b>10</b> further includes a base <b>18</b> removably mounted to the housing <b>12</b> at a side substantially opposite the display <b>16</b>. A plurality of differently configured bases <b>18</b> can be provided in accordance with the size and shape of the surface on which the apparatus <b>10</b> will be supported for measuring levelness.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The electro-optical level sensor <b>14</b> includes a bubble level <b>20</b> having an elongate tube <b>22</b> with a central axis <b>24</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The tube <b>22</b> may be curved convexly up or may be ground or otherwise formed to have an internal curve with a central high point, so that the interior of the level is generally barrel-shaped. The tube <b>22</b> is filled partly with a liquid <b>26</b>, and portions of the tube <b>22</b> that are not filled with the liquid <b>26</b> define a bubble <b>28</b>. The bubble <b>28</b> will move longitudinally within the tube <b>22</b> depending upon the orientation of the axis <b>24</b> relative to the gravitational axis. In particular, the bubble <b>28</b> will be centrally disposed in the tube <b>22</b> when the axis <b>24</b> of the tube <b>22</b> is normal to the gravitational axis. However, the bubble <b>28</b> will shift toward the high end of the tube <b>22</b> when the axis <b>24</b> of the tube <b>22</b> is not perpendicular to the gravitational axis. The amount of shifting of the bubble <b>28</b> will depend upon the angle between the axis <b>24</b> of the tube <b>22</b> and the gravitational axis.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The electro-optical level sensor <b>14</b> further includes a substantially linear light source <b>30</b> aligned substantially parallel to the axis <b>24</b> of the tube <b>22</b> and operative to emit light toward and through the tube <b>22</b>. The light source <b>30</b> preferably is a cold cathode illuminator.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The electro-optical level sensor <b>14</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> further includes a lens <b>32</b> disposed on a side of the bubble level <b>20</b> opposite the light source <b>30</b>. The lens <b>32</b> may be a cylindrical lens, a single spherical lens or a multiple lens array of cylindrical or spherical lenses arranged linearly, such as lens arrays sold under the trademark SELFOC® by NSG America, Inc. The lens array <b>32</b> focuses light that has been emitted from the light source <b>30</b> and passed through the tube <b>22</b> substantially along the axis of the tube.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The electro-optical level sensor <b>14</b> further includes a light sensitive receiver <b>34</b> aligned substantially parallel to the axis <b>24</b> of the tube <b>22</b> and disposed on a side of the lens array <b>32</b> opposite to the tube <b>22</b>. Thus, the lens array <b>32</b> focuses an image of the liquid <b>26</b> and the bubble <b>28</b> onto the light sensitive receiver <b>34</b>. The light sensitive receiver <b>34</b> may be a CCD array or other receiver that is operative to identify the location and magnitude of peaks of light energy impinging thereon. The light sensitive receiver <b>34</b> preferably defines a length in excess of the length of the bubble <b>28</b>. However, the light receiver <b>34</b> need not extend the entire length of the tube <b>22</b>. The light sensitive receiver <b>34</b> is connected operatively to a processor <b>36</b> that is in the housing <b>12</b> connected to the display <b>16</b>. Thus, the display <b>16</b> is operative to produce an output indicative of energy peaks identified by the CCD array or other such light sensitive receiver <b>34</b>. The apparatus <b>10</b> may further include an aperture plate between the tube <b>22</b> and the light sensitive receiver <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The liquid <b>26</b> and the bubble <b>28</b> in the tube <b>22</b> alter the level of energy of illumination passing through the tube <b>22</b> and focused by the lens array <b>32</b> onto the CCD array or other such light sensitive receiver <b>34</b>. The variation in output voltage is measured by variations in voltage level outputted from the light sensitive receiver <b>34</b>. The variation in illumination is most prominent at the edges of the bubble <b>28</b>. Thus, the bubble <b>28</b> takes the uniform illumination produced by the light source <b>30</b> and focused by the lens <b>32</b> and couples energy from the position of the bubble <b>28</b> and beyond the ends of the bubble <b>28</b> to produce an energy distribution as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The energy distribution shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> depicts two substantially equal inverse peaks or “divots” indicative of a bubble <b>28</b> that is centrally disposed relative to the light sensitive receiver <b>34</b> and hence indicating a horizontal alignment of the axis <b>24</b>. The bubble <b>28</b> shifts to the left or right if the axis <b>24</b> is not perfectly horizontal. As a result, the divots also shift, and one of the divots may become larger and the other may become smaller in proportion. The divots are read by the CCD array <b>34</b> and associated electronics. More particularly, the input current is adjusted by the processor <b>36</b> to achieve a brightness or output voltage for each pixel of the CCD array <b>34</b> that is in a readable range. The output voltage of each pixel in the CCD array <b>34</b> then is read by the processor <b>36</b> of the electro-optical sensor <b>14</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the array output includes a first set of pixel output voltages <b>50</b> on a first side of the bubble <b>28</b>, a second set of pixel output voltages <b>52</b> on a second side of the bubble <b>28</b> and an array of pixel output voltages <b>54</b> corresponding to the bubble <b>28</b>. A divot <b>56</b> is defined between the first array of pixel output voltages <b>50</b> to the left of the bubble <b>28</b> and the array of pixel output voltages <b>54</b> aligned with the bubble. The divot <b>56</b> has a slope <b>58</b> extending from the first array of pixel output voltages <b>50</b> to the divot <b>56</b> and a slope <b>60</b> extending from the divot <b>56</b> to the array of pixel output voltages <b>54</b> corresponding to bubble <b>28</b>. The slope <b>58</b> is longer and steeper than the slope <b>60</b>. The array output further includes a divot <b>66</b> corresponding to the right end of the bubble <b>28</b>. A slope <b>68</b> extends from the divot <b>66</b> to the array of pixel output voltages <b>52</b> and a slope <b>70</b> extending from the array of pixel output voltages <b>54</b> corresponding to the bubble <b>28</b> to the divot <b>66</b>. The slope <b>68</b> is steeper and longer than the slope <b>70</b>. The processor <b>36</b> of the apparatus <b>10</b> establishes a threshold voltage, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, at a position that is known to intersect the slopes <b>58</b> and <b>68</b> approximately at their midpoint. The controller then identifies voltage levels for specific pixel positions on the respective slopes <b>58</b> and <b>68</b> and through a simple algebraic linear regression calculation identifies relative pixel positions <b>62</b> and <b>72</b> where the respective slopes <b>58</b> and <b>68</b> intersect the threshold voltage, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The positions <b>62</b> and <b>72</b> are symmetrically disposed with great precision relative to opposite ends of the bubble <b>28</b>. Hence, the center of the bubble <b>28</b> can be defined with great precision as the midpoint between the respective threshold intersections <b>62</b> and <b>72</b> respectively. The longer steeper slopes <b>58</b> and <b>68</b> provide more precision.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a bubble length of 189 pixels in this example. That bubble length will remain substantially constant for a broad array of angular orientations of the level <b>20</b> and can be determined during a calibration of the apparatus <b>10</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the divots <b>56</b> and <b>66</b> have nearly identical output levels. However, as the level <b>20</b> is tilted more, the optics associated with the bubble <b>28</b> will cause the output voltages of the respective peaks to vary significantly from one another. Within a range of angular alignments normally encountered, the above-described algorithm can be applied with great accuracy despite the different output voltage levels for the respective divots <b>56</b> and <b>66</b>. However, at a certain angle for the level, one or the other of the divots <b>56</b> or <b>66</b> may move above the threshold voltage. Thus, the above described algebraic procedure cannot be used for identifying the two intersections <b>62</b> and <b>72</b> of the threshold voltage. However, one intersection <b>62</b> or <b>72</b> can be identified. Additionally, the bubble length will remain constant. As a result, the one intersection <b>62</b> or <b>72</b> for slope <b>58</b> or <b>68</b> with the threshold voltage can be used with the knowledge of the bubble length to identify the center of the bubble <b>28</b>. Thus, in this situation, at least two and preferably three pixel readings along the slope <b>58</b> or <b>68</b> will be identified so that the readings bridge the threshold voltage. An algebraic linear regression equation is used to identify the precise intersection with the threshold voltage and one-half of the bubble length is added to or subtracted from pixel position for the intersection <b>62</b> or <b>72</b> of the threshold voltage to identify the precise pixel position for the center of the bubble <b>28</b> relative to the CCD array <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The apparatus <b>10</b> is used by placing the base <b>18</b> on a surface that is to be tested for levelness. The apparatus <b>10</b> then may be powered on by using a control switch <b>74</b> connected to an internal power source <b>76</b>, such as a rechargeable lithium-ion battery. The display <b>16</b> is pivoted relative to the base <b>18</b> to be readily visually observable to a user. The bubble <b>28</b> will move in the tube <b>22</b> depending upon the alignment of the surface. The apparatus <b>10</b> functions by directing light from the light source <b>30</b> through the bubble level <b>20</b>. The lens array <b>32</b> focuses the light onto the CCD array or other sensor <b>34</b>, and hence produces an image of the bubble <b>28</b> on the CCD array <b>34</b>. The processor <b>36</b> of the apparatus <b>10</b> then identifies at least one of the divots <b>56</b> and <b>66</b> corresponding to the ends of the bubble <b>28</b> and calculates the intersection <b>62</b> and/or <b>72</b> of at least one of the slopes <b>58</b> and <b>68</b>. The pixel positions for the intersections of the slopes <b>58</b> and/or <b>68</b> with the threshold voltage are determined with great precision and the midpoint of the bubble <b>28</b> then is determined based on those calculated pixel positions. More particularly, the midpoint of the bubble <b>28</b> is midway between the threshold intersections <b>62</b> and <b>72</b> in those situations where both slopes <b>58</b> and <b>68</b> intersect the threshold voltage. Alternatively, the midpoint of the bubble <b>28</b> can be determined by adding a previously calibrated bubble length to the intersection <b>62</b> or <b>72</b> of the threshold voltage with one of the slopes <b>58</b> or <b>68</b>. As noted above, the level <b>12</b> can be used with differential screw adjusters to alter the relative vertical position of either end of the level <b>12</b>. Thus, the user can observe the changes in the peaks on the display <b>16</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> as the differential screw adjusters are being turned. As a result, real-time adjustments and calibration can be carried out. The display <b>16</b> can output information on levelness in terms of arc seconds or distance (inches or millimeters) based on trigonometric calculations performed by the processor <b>36</b>. The display <b>16</b> also can indicate whether the output data is positive or negative relative to the “+” and “−” indicia applied to the housing <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The level <b>20</b> is described herein as a bubble tube <b>22</b>. However the level also can be a bulls eye level where the bubble can move relative to two axes to measure levelness in plural directions. With this embodiment, it is necessary to focus the image onto two perpendicularly arranged linear arrays of sensors or onto a two axis sensor.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electro-optical level comprising:
<claim-text>a bubble level having a liquid and a gas bubble therein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light source in proximity to the bubble level for directing light toward and through the bubble level;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light sensor disposed on a side of the bubble level opposite the light source and operative for identifying characteristics of light impinging thereon;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lens disposed between the bubble level and the light sensor for focusing an image of the bubble onto the light sensor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a display for displaying output readings of said light sensor indicative of levelness; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller connected to the light sensor and the display, the controller being operative to identified display output data indicative of at least one end of the bubble.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the liquid and the bubble are disposed in a bubble tube, the light sensor comprises a CCD linear array aligned substantially parallel to the bubble tube and having a length exceeding a length of the bubble in the bubble tube.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the lens is an elongate lens aligned substantially parallel to the bubble level and wherein the light sensor is an elongate sensor aligned substantially parallel to the lens.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the lens is a cylindrical lens.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The electro-optical sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the lens is an elongate lens array comprising a plurality of lenses, the lens array being aligned substantially parallel to the bubble level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the light source is a substantially linear light source aligned substantially parallel to the bubble level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the light source is a cold cathode illuminator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a housing for enclosing and supporting the bubble level, the light source, the lens and the light sensor, the display being pivotally mounted to the housing for altering viewing angles of the display relative to the housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising a handle incorporated into the display for transporting the electro-optical level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the housing has a base surface aligned substantially parallel to the bubble level for supporting the housing on an object to be tested for levelness.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The electro-optical level of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the light sensor is operative to produce a plurality of output voltages at a corresponding plurality of locations along said light sensor, said controller being operative to identify output voltages indicative of at least one end of the bubble.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method for assessing levelness of an object comprising:
<claim-text>providing a bubble level having a bubble tube with a liquid therein and a bubble formed by the liquid in the bubble tube;</claim-text>
<claim-text>placing said bubble tube in a position substantially parallel to a surface of the object;</claim-text>
<claim-text>directing light through the bubble tube;</claim-text>
<claim-text>focusing at least a portion of the light passed through the bubble tube;</claim-text>
<claim-text>sensing characteristics of the focused light at a plurality of locations along the bubble tube;</claim-text>
<claim-text>identifying characteristics sensed for the focused light by measuring output voltages produced by the focused light at each of the plurality locations parallel to the bubble tube and identifying at least one location having a significantly lower output voltage level than locations spaced therefrom for identifying at least one end of the bubble; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>calculating a degree of levelness based on a location sensed for the end of the bubble.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the step of identifying at least one end of the bubble comprises identifying positions for opposed ends of the bubble relative to a longitudinal axis of the bubble tube.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising performing a calibrating step to determine a length of the bubble relative to a longitudinal axis of the bubble tube, and wherein the step of calculating a degree of levelness comprises comparing a location of a single end of the bubble with information calibrated for the length of the bubble.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of establishing a threshold voltage less than a maximum output voltage produced by the focused light and greater than the lower output voltage and identifying at least one location where said measured output voltage substantially equals said threshold voltage for determining location data corresponding to at least one end of the bubble.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
