<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298677-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298677</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10900924</doc-number>
<date>20040728</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>527</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4736</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Optical disc drive apparatus and method</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6157599</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yamashita et al.</name>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>369 4428</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>0299335</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19890100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>63-217535</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19880900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>6-274912</doc-number>
<date>19940900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>06-274912</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19940900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>7-211025</doc-number>
<date>19950600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>6-7310</doc-number>
<date>19960100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-134683</doc-number>
<date>19990600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-090563</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20000300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00010">
<othercit>European Search Report for European Application No. EP 05014293.4 Report issued Apr. 24, 2007.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>Translation of Japan Office Action dated Aug. 29, 2006 for JP Patent Application No. 2005-217315, (4 pgs).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>36</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4427</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4428</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4412</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4414</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4415</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369120</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369122</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369116</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 533</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4736</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060023593</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060202</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Anderson</last-name>
<first-name>Daryl E.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Van Brocklin</last-name>
<first-name>Andrew L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hewlett-Packard Development Company, L.P.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Houston</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hindi</last-name>
<first-name>Nabil</first-name>
<department>2627</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An optical disc drive is has a voice coil motor that carries and moves focal optics to focus a laser beam onto an optical disc The voice coil motor is responsive to input signals which are based on a calibrated temperature. A temperature measurement is made at the voice coil motor for an operating temperature, and a difference is calculated between calibrated and operating temperatures. The temperature differences are used to calculate adjustment in input signals used to drive the voice coil motors.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="232.75mm" wi="185.59mm" file="US07298677-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="273.22mm" wi="198.04mm" file="US07298677-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="233.00mm" wi="186.10mm" file="US07298677-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="263.14mm" wi="177.63mm" file="US07298677-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Optical discs, such as compact discs (CD) and digital versatile discs (DVD) are forms of computer readable media which provide extensive storage for digital information. One side of an optical disc may contain data and is referred to as a data side. The data side may be read only, or may also be written to. The other side of the optical disc that does not contain data may provide for a label and is referred to as the label side. In particular cases, a side or both sides may provide for both data and a label.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">An optical disc drive (ODD) of a computer may be used to read from and may write to a data side of an optical disc. An optical pickup unit (OPU), included within the optical disc drive, is configured with a laser and sensors adapted for reading, and possibly writing, data. Various ODDs and OPUs are available, and are manufactured to specifically read and write to the data side of optical discs.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Using emerging technology, the OPU assembly may be used to produce an image on the label surface of an optical disc configured for such a labeling process. Producing the image includes defining tacks which are concentric circles of the optical disc where the image is written, and focusing focal optics of a laser beam that performs the actual printing of the image on the optical disc.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">An ODD typically includes a voice coil motor (VCM) configured as a sled motor that moves an OPU assembly in a radial direction to a position that is adjacent particular tracks of the optical disc. An OPU assembly may also include a VCM configured as a focus motor that moves focal optics to a particular distance orthogonal to a surface of the disc such as a height above or below the disc, to focus a laser beam for labeling. The VCMs are responsive to an input signal (voltage or current) and move to a particular location when a particular input signal is applied. Therefore, when an input signal is applied to the sled VCM, the OPU assembly is moved adjacent to a particular track. Likewise, when an input signal is applied to the focus VCM, the focal optics are moved to a particular focus position. The VCMs are typically calibrated to move a particular distance when a particular input signal is applied. The calibration is performed at a particular temperature.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, a VCM includes metal windings whose electrical conductivity is affected by temperature changes. Therefore when the VCM is heated, the resistance of the metal windings goes up and electrical conductivity increases. Since a VCM is calibrated at a particular temperature to move a particular distance based on a particular input signal, not accounting for temperature changes can result in inaccurate positioning. For example, if a VCM is operated at a temperature different from the calibration temperature, a particular input signal may move the OPU assembly to an incorrect track position or the focal optics to an incorrect focus position.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Accordingly, a need exists for the present invention.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">An optical disc drive is has a voice coil motor that carries and moves focal optics to focus a laser beam onto an optical disc. The voice coil motor is responsive to input signals which are based on a calibrated temperature. A temperature measurement is made at the voice coil motor for an operating temperature, and a difference is calculated between calibrated and operating temperatures. The temperature differences are used to calculate adjustment in input signals used to drive the voice coil motors.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The following detailed description refers to the accompanying figures. In the figures, the left-most digit(s) of a reference number identifies the figure (FIG.) in which the reference number first appears. Moreover, the same reference numbers are used throughout the drawings to reference like features and components.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram illustrating an exemplary disc media marking system for measuring and adjusting input signal values to control voice coil motors for operation of tracking and focal optics over varying temperatures, according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating an exemplary optical disc drive system used for mapping and labeling according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flow chart illustrating a temperature adjustment and labeling procedure, according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="h-0005" num="0000">Overview</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The following discussion is directed to systems and methods for measuring and compensating for temperature variances of voice coil motors (VCM) that carry OPU assemblies and focal optics used in creating and labeling an optical disc.</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">Exemplary System Environment</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows an exemplary disc media marking system <b>100</b> suitable for measuring and calibrating input voltage values of a voice coil motor. The marking system <b>100</b> includes a disc media marking device <b>105</b> and a display device <b>110</b>. The disc media marking device <b>105</b> may be implemented as a stand-alone appliance device for labeling disc media. Alternatively, the disc media marking device <b>105</b> may be integrated as part of an optical media player or drive, such as a writable compact disc (CD) player or drive which is implemented to label an optical disc as well as record data onto a CD-R (CD recordable disc) and/or a CD-RW (CD-rewritable disc). The disc media marking device <b>105</b> may also be integrated as part of a digital versatile disc (DVD) player or drive which is implemented to label an optical disc as well as record data ont a DVD-R, DVD+R, DVD-RW, DVD+RW disc or the like. An optical media player or drive (optical devices) may be used to read from and may write to a data side of an optical disc. An optical pickup unit (OPU), included within the optical device, is configured with a laser and sensors adapted for reading and writing data. Such writable optical devices may include, for example, a standalone audio CD player which is a peripheral component in an audio system, a CD or DVD drive integrated as standard equipment in a PC (personal computer), a DVD (digital versatile disc) player and/or recorder, and any number of similar embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Disc media marking device <b>105</b> typically includes one or more processors <b>115</b> (e.g., any of microprocessors, controllers, and the like) which process various instructions to control the operation of disc media marking device <b>105</b> and communicate with other electronic and computing devices. Disc media marking device <b>105</b> may be implemented with one or more memory components, examples of which include a random access memory (RAM) <b>120</b>, a disc storage device <b>125</b>, and nonvolatile memory <b>130</b> (e.g., any one or more of a read-only memory (ROM) <b>135</b>, flash memory, EPROM, EEPROM, etc.).</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Disc storage device <b>125</b> may include any type of magnetic or optical storage device, such as a hard disc drive, a magnetic tape, a recordable and/or rewriteable compact disc (CD), a DVD, DVD+RW, and the like. The one or more memory components provide data storage mechanisms to store various information and/or data such as configuration information for disc media marking device <b>105</b>, graphical user interface information, and any other types of information and data related to operational aspects of disc media marking device <b>105</b>. Alternative implementations of disc media marking device <b>105</b> may include a range of processing and memory capabilities, and may include any number of differing memory components than those shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Disc media marking device <b>105</b> may include a firmware component <b>140</b> which is implemented as a permanent memory module stored on ROM <b>135</b>, or with other components in disc media marking device <b>105</b>, such as a component of a processor <b>115</b>. Firmware <b>140</b> is programmed and distributed with disc media marking device <b>105</b> to coordinate operations of the hardware within disc media marking device <b>105</b> and contains programming constructs used to perform such operations.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">An operating system <b>145</b> and one or more application programs may be stored in nonvolatile memory <b>130</b> and executed on processor(s) <b>115</b> to provide a runtime environment. A runtime environment facilitates extensibility of disc media marking device <b>105</b> by allowing various interfaces to be defined that, in turn, allow the application programs to interact with disc media marking device <b>105</b>. In this example, the application programs include a label design application <b>150</b>, an image processing application <b>155</b>, and a print control application <b>160</b>. Furthermore, it is contemplated that VCM gain measurements <b>165</b> are stored in nonvolatile memory such as non-volatile memory <b>130</b>. In certain embodiments, VCM gain measurements <b>165</b> are stored in nonvolatile sections of RAM <b>130</b> or ROM <b>135</b>. VCM gain measurements are inherent to the particular VCM, and specifically related to the metal used in the VCM windings and the number of windings of the VCM and the temperature at which the measurement was made An example of a VCM gain measurement for a copper VCM is 0.426 mm/V at 36 degrees centigrade.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The label design application <b>150</b> generates a label design user interface <b>170</b> for display on display device <b>110</b> from which a user may create a label image to be rendered on a disc media, such as on an optical disc. A user may specify text, a bitmap image for background, a digital photo, a graphic or symbol, and/or any combination thereof to create the label image on the user interface <b>170</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The image processing application <b>155</b> processes the label image created with the label design user interface <b>170</b> to produce a data stream of label image data and laser control data for labeling the image on concentric circular tracks of a disc media (i.e., an optical disc). For example, a continuous tone RGB (red, green, and blue) rectangular raster graphic of the label image may be color mapped and separated into the printing color channels KCMY (black, cyan, magenta, and yellow), or grayscale and then halftoned and converted to concentric circular tracks. This data stream may be formatted as laser control data, and may be augmented with other control commands to control the disc media marking device <b>105</b> rendering a label on the disc media.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A label file using image processing application <b>155</b> may be generated. The label file is communicated to a controller <b>260</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) by print control application <b>160</b> which parses the label file to control a labeling mechanism. Alternatively, the concentric circular tracks may be generated and streamed to the disc media marking device <b>105</b> one track at a time for processing and labelling, through print control application <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The print control application <b>160</b> determines the radius from the hub of the disc of the first track and the subsequent track spacing. After the radius of the first track and the track spacing are determined, the print control application <b>160</b> determines which label image data will correspond to each respective track. The laser mark locations along a particular track are specified in a coordinate system where the concentric circular tracks are defined in coordinates of the radial distance and the distance along each respective track.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Disc media marking device <b>105</b> includes an optical disc drive (ODD) system <b>175</b> which may be configured to produce visible marks on a surface of a disc media (i.e., optical disc), so as to produce a label image on a label surface (i.e., label side) of the optical disc. The ODD system <b>175</b> is described in greater detail herein below with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Disc media marking device <b>105</b> may further include one or more communication interfaces <b>180</b> which may be implemented as any one or more of a serial and/or parallel interface, as a wireless interface, any type of network interface, and as any other type of communication interface. A wireless interface enables disc media marking device <b>105</b> to receive control input commands and other information from an input device, such as from a remote control device or from another infrared (IR), 802.11, Bluetooth, or similar RF input device. A network interface provides a connection between disc media marking device <b>105</b> and a data communication network which allows other electronic and computing devices coupled to a common data communication network to send label image data and other information to disc media marking device <b>105</b> via the network. Similarly, a serial and/or parallel interface provides a data communication path directly between disc media marking device <b>105</b> and another electronic or computing device.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Disc media marking device <b>105</b> may include user input devices <b>185</b> which may include a keyboard, pointing device, selectable controls on a user control panel, and/or other mechanisms to interact with, and to input information to disc media marking device <b>105</b>. Disc media marking device <b>105</b> also includes an audio/video processor <b>190</b> which generates display content for display on display device <b>110</b>, and generates audio content for presentation by a presentation device, such as one or more speakers (not shown). The audio/video processor <b>190</b> may include a display controller which processes the display content to display corresponding images on display device <b>110</b>. A display controller may be implemented as a graphics processor, microcontroller, integrated circuit, and/or similar video processing component to process the images. Video signals and audio signals may be communicated from disc media marking device <b>105</b> to display device <b>110</b> via an RF (radio frequency) link, S-video link, composite video link, component video link, or other similar communication link.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Although shown separately, some of the components of disc media marking device <b>105</b> may be implemented in an application specific integrated circuit (ASIC). Additionally, a system bus (not shown) typically connects the various components within disc media marking device <b>105</b>. A system bus may be implemented as one or more of any of several types of bus structures, including a memory bus or memory controller, a peripheral bus, an accelerated graphics port, or a local bus using any of a variety of bus architectures. Furthermore, disc media marking device <b>105</b> may share a system bus with a host processor.</p>
<p id="h-0007" num="0000">Exemplary ODD Embodiment</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an exemplary embodiment of the ODD system <b>175</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The ODD system <b>175</b> includes an optical pickup unit (OPU) assembly <b>200</b> that includes a sled <b>205</b>, a laser <b>210</b>, a photo sensor <b>212</b>, focal optics <b>215</b> and a voice coil motor (VCM) <b>220</b>. The VCM <b>220</b> responds to an input signal (voltage or current) to cause the focal optics <b>215</b> to move the focal point of a laser beam generated by laser <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">For purposes of illustration, the focal optics <b>215</b> are carried by lens supports <b>225</b>(<b>1</b>), <b>225</b>(<b>2</b>). The focal optics <b>215</b> are configured for travel (i.e. adjustment of the focal point) along a “z” axis <b>230</b> perpendicular to a surface of an optical disc <b>235</b>. Photo sensor <b>212</b> determines a distance along “z” axis <b>230</b> at which an “in focus” condition of the laser beam exists with respect to a particular location on the surface of optical disc <b>235</b>. VCM <b>220</b> is calibrated to move to this particular distance by receiving a particular input signal. However, if the operating temperature when labeling is performed is different from the temperature at which the VCM was calibrated, the laser beam may be out of focus since a different z-axis position value results from the unadjusted input signal. Therefore as discussed below, an adjustment is made to compensate for the change in temperature in order to determine the proper input signal needed to arrive at the desired z-axis position corresponding to the “in focus” position.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">However, in some embodiments it may be desirable to further adjust the z-axis position so as to intentionally defocus the laser beam. This focus offset may be provided in order to provide a better image quality using a marking laser. For example, the size of the visible spots created by a focused laser may be too small to allow efficient labeling, so a defocused laser beam may be used to created larger visible spots. Or the marking laser may create such distortion from its heat when marking a surface, as to provide a need for an adjusted focus offset. A predetermined amount of focus offset may be achieved by providing a corresponding focus offset value for the input signal. This offset value is also typically determined at the calibration temperature of the VCM. Therefore, variances in actual operating temperature may also provide a need to adjust the focus offset value based on the temperature variance.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">A laser beam <b>240</b> is generated by the laser <b>210</b> and directed onto (reflected on) a label side surface <b>245</b> of optical disc <b>235</b>. The laser beam <b>240</b> creates laser marks that correspond to label image data to produce an image of the label side <b>245</b> of the optical disc <b>235</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The ODD system <b>175</b> includes a spindle motor <b>250</b>, a VCM <b>255</b>, and a controller <b>260</b>. VCM <b>255</b> acts as a sled motor that moves OPU assembly <b>200</b> adjacent to particular radial positions or tracks of optical disc <b>235</b>. VCM <b>255</b> is calibrated to move to this particular distance by receiving a particular input signal. VCM <b>255</b> may be referred to as a sled or radial VCM since it provides movement in the radial direction. VCM <b>255</b> may be calibrated for gain—in other words input signal (e.g., millivolts) per movement (microns), such that for example, a particular number of millivolts results in a movement in distance.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">A separate stepper motor <b>256</b> provides a coarse adjustment for radial movement, and particularly is calibrated to move per a step size increment as instructed by controller <b>260</b>. VCM <b>255</b> includes a fine adjust feature <b>257</b>. While stepper motor <b>256</b> is calibrated to move per a step size increment, fine adjust feature <b>257</b> is calibrated to adjust to a finer increment. For example, if stepper motor <b>256</b> is calibrated for a step size of 120 microns, and fine adjust feature <b>256</b> is calibrated for a smaller increment, when 80 microns of movement is requested, stepper motor <b>256</b> moves the sled <b>205</b> by 120 microns, and fine adjust feature <b>257</b> moves the sled <b>205</b> back by 40 microns.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The gain or movement of VCM <b>255</b> (i.e., fine adjust feature <b>256</b>) is affected by temperature changes The gain of VCM <b>255</b> is calibrated at a particular operating temperature (i.e., a predetermined operating temperature gain); however variances in actual operating affect the actual gain of VCM.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In general, controller <b>260</b> may be implemented as a printed circuit board employing a combination of various components discussed above with respect to the disc media marking system <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Accordingly, controller <b>260</b> typically includes a processor <b>263</b> for processing computer/processor-executable instructions from various components stored in a memory <b>266</b>. Processor <b>263</b> is typically one or more of the processors <b>115</b> discussed above with respect to the disc media marking system <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Likewise, memory <b>266</b> is typically the non-volatile memory <b>130</b> and/or firmware <b>140</b> of disc media marking system <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Drivers <b>269</b>, including a laser driver, sled driver, and spindle driver are stored in memory <b>266</b> and executable on processor <b>263</b>. Although these components are represented in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> embodiment as software components stored in memory <b>266</b> and executable on processor <b>263</b>, they may also be implemented as firmware or hardware components.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In general, a spindle driver drives the spindle motor <b>250</b> to control a rotational speed of optical disc <b>235</b> via a spindle <b>272</b>. The spindle driver operates in conjunction with a sled diver which drives the VCM <b>255</b> to control radial (track) positioning of OPU assembly <b>200</b> with respect to disc <b>235</b> along a sled drive mechanism <b>275</b>. In a labeling implementation the sled <b>205</b> of the OPU assembly <b>200</b> is moved along the sled drive mechanism <b>275</b> to various radii (track) positions of optical disc <b>235</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In a labeling implementation, the rotational speed of disc <b>235</b> and the radial position of OPU assembly <b>200</b> are controlled such that laser marks are written at desired positions on the disc <b>235</b> as the label side surface <b>245</b> moves past the laser beam <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A laser driver controls the activation and intensity of laser beam <b>240</b> to write laser marks corresponding to a label image onto the label side surface <b>245</b>. Additionally, the laser driver controls the activation and intensity of the laser beam <b>240</b> to read data maintained on the data side <b>278</b> of the optical disc <b>235</b> when the disc is positioned such that the data side <b>278</b> passes over the laser beam <b>240</b>. In certain cases, the same side is used for data and labeling.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">A driver for VCM <b>220</b> is included among the drivers <b>269</b>. The VCM driver is executable on processor <b>263</b> to adjust a VCM input signal source <b>281</b> which provides an input to VCM <b>220</b>. Furthermore, another driver is included for VCM <b>255</b> executable on processor <b>263</b> to adjust a VCM input signal source <b>284</b> which provides an input to VCM <b>255</b>. Input signals may be either current or voltage. As discussed, VCMs <b>220</b> and <b>255</b> are calibrated at a particular operating temperature, therefore input signals are based on the particular calibrated operating temperature. However, when the OPU assembly is operated at temperatures other than the calibrated operating temperature may result in different distances from the VCMs <b>220</b> and <b>255</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Operating temperatures are read from temperature sensing apparatuses <b>290</b> and <b>293</b>. In this exemplary implementation two temperature sensing apparatuses are provided, temperature sensing apparatus <b>290</b> for VCM <b>220</b> and temperature sensing apparatus <b>293</b> for VCM <b>255</b> to measure operating temperatures at the respective VCMs. In other implementations, a single temperature sensing apparatus may be used to determine general operating temperatures for the VCMs. For better accuracy separate temperature sensing apparatuses are placed at the windings of VCM <b>220</b> and VCM <b>255</b> respectively. Operating temperature measurements are passed to the controller <b>260</b> and may be stored in memory <b>266</b></p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Computing device interface <b>296</b> interfaces the controller <b>260</b> of the ODD system <b>175</b> with another electronic or computing device to receive label image data or a label file (not shown). The computing device interface <b>296</b> can be implemented as an ATAPI (Advanced Technology Attachment Packet Interface), which is one of many small computer parallel or serial device interfaces. Another common computer interface is SCSI (small computer system interface), which is a generalized device interface for attaching peripheral devices to computers. SCSI defines the structure of commands, the way commands are executed, and the way status is processed. Various other physical interfaces include the Parallel Interface, Fiber Channel, IEEE 1394, USB (Universal Serial Bus), and ATA/ATAPI. ATAPI is a command execution protocol for use on an ATA interface so that CD-ROM and tape drives can be connected via the same ATA cable with an ATA hard disc drive. ATAPI devices generally include CD-ROM drives, CD-recordable drives, CD-rewritable drives, DVD (digital versatile disc) drives, tape drives, super floppy drives (e.g., ZIP and LS-120), and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Controller <b>260</b> or processors <b>263</b> may perform the following calculations. Non-temperature compensated input signal values are provided to VCMs <b>220</b> and <b>255</b>. Actual operating temperature is measured and the input signals from VCM input signals <b>281</b> and <b>284</b> are adjusted accordingly in order to arrive at a correctly position the focal optics <b>215</b> and sled <b>205</b></p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Operating temperature measurements are made by temperature sensing apparatuses <b>290</b> and <b>293</b>. Preferably, temperature sensing apparatus <b>290</b> is placed in close proximity to the windings of VCM <b>220</b> and temperature sensing apparatus <b>293</b> is place in close proximity to the windings of VCM <b>255</b>. In other embodiments, a single temperature sensing apparatus is used for VCM <b>220</b> and VCM <b>255</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">A calculation is made as to the effect on the required input signal due to the difference between a calibration temperature at which VCM <b>220</b> or VCM <b>255</b> was previously calibrated, and the current operating temperature measured by the corresponding temperature sensing apparatus <b>290</b> or <b>293</b>. The calibration temperature may be store in a nonvolatile section of memory <b>266</b> and recalled by controller <b>266</b> or processors <b>263</b>. Therefore two delta temperature values are calculated for VCMs <b>220</b> and VCM <b>255</b>. The following equation describes each delta temperature value, where Operating<sub>temp </sub>is the measured operating temperature and Calibrated<sub>temp </sub>is the temperature at which the VCM was calibrated.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Δ<sub>temp</sub>(VCM)=Operating<sub>temp</sub>−Calibrated<sub>temp </sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Each delta temperature value is multiplied by the temperature coefficient (TC) of the respective VCMs <b>220</b> and <b>255</b>. The resultant value is the voltage adjustment needed for the input signal value. Note that, in one embodiment, the TC may be predominantly based on the value of the thermal coefficient of resistance (TCR) of the metal used for the windings of the VCMs. To more accurately gauge thermal effects, however, the TC (temperature coefficient) of the entire system (or VCM), which includes more than just the winding metal TCR, is generally considered. To account for such thermal effects, the TC of the VCM may be determined by design and manufacturing, which typically results in a nominal TC for the system, and minimum and maximum limits for the TC of the system.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">An example of a metal used in a winding for VCM <b>220</b> and <b>255</b> is copper. The TCR of copper is 0.393% per degree centigrade The following equation is calculated to derive an input signal adjustment, in this example a voltage input adjustment.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Adjustment=Δ<sub>temp</sub>(VCM)*(TC)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Each input value in the input signal table <b>287</b> is adjusted by the derived value of “Adjustment”. The following equation describes the readjustment, where “Adjusted Voltage” is the readjusted input signal value and “Input Voltage” is a input signal value of input signal table <b>287</b>.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Adjusted Voltage=Input Voltage+Adjustment*Input Voltage<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">An example is the following. Calibration temperature=36 degrees centigrade; measured operating temperature is 55 degrees centigrade; and TC is 0.393% per degree centigrade.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Adjustment=(55−36)*(0.393)=7.5%<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Therefore if an input signal value or voltage value is 70 mV, it is adjusted by <sub>+</sub>7.5% to arrive at a temperature compensated value of 75.25 mV. This is the voltage applied to the voice coil motor to position the objective lens or the sled.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">With regard to the focus VCM <b>220</b>, a focus offset value may be included in the input signal adjustment For example, if a 30 micron (um) focus offset is desired, an example VCM gain measurement at the calibrated temperature of 36 degrees centigrade is 0.426 mm/V. Therefore to account for this focus offset an additional voltage (input) value is added to the input signal value. In this example, the derived additional voltage is 0.030 mm/(0.426 mm/V)=70.42 mV. However, a temperature compensated additional voltage value where the operating temperature is 55 degrees centigrade is (0.030 mm/0.426 mm/V)(100%+7.50%)=75.70 mV. To achieve the same focus offset at the operating temperature 75.70 mV is added, instead of 70.42 mV.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows an exemplary process <b>300</b> to label a label region of an optical disc. Exemplary process <b>300</b> may be included in ODD <b>175</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Furthermore, ODD <b>175</b> may be implemented with mechanisms and functions for performing process <b>300</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">At block <b>305</b> a temperature measurement is made at a VCM or VCMs such as VCMs <b>220</b> and <b>255</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The temperature measurement is made with a device such as temperature sensing apparatuses <b>290</b> and <b>293</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">At block <b>310</b> a calculation is made as to the difference of the temperature used for calibration and the measured operating temperature from block <b>305</b>. This calculation may be performed for selected VCMs or all VCM.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">At block <b>315</b> a calculation is made as to an adjustment factor where the calculation is the product of the difference of temperature and thermal coefficient (TC) of the particular VCM.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">At block <b>320</b> a calculation is made to determine an adjusted input signal value based on the adjustment factor derived at block <b>315</b>. The adjusted input signal value is based on an input signal value derived from process <b>300</b> either reduced or increased by the adjustment factor derived at block <b>315</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">At block <b>325</b> a decision is made whether a focus offset value is to be determined. A focus offset value may be determined for the VCM that carries the focal optics. If focus offset calculation is not to be performed (i.e., following the “NO” branch of block <b>325</b>), block <b>330</b> is performed. At block <b>330</b> the adjusted input signal value is sent to an input signal source, such as VCM input signal sources <b>281</b> and <b>284</b> in order to generate the input signal for the corresponding VCM to place the sled <b>205</b> adjacent a desired track, or to place focal optics <b>215</b> at a desired focal position</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">At block <b>335</b> after the VCMs receive the adjusted input signal and place the OPU assembly and focal optics in place, labeling may be performed on the particular location.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">If a focus offset value calculation is to be performed (i.e., following the “YES” branch of block <b>325</b>), block <b>340</b> is performed. At block <b>340</b> an adjusted input signal to achieve a desired amount of focus offset is calculated. The input signal is derived by dividing the focus offset distance by the VCM gain and multiplying by the temperature difference calculated in block <b>310</b>. This calculation is performed for the VCM that carries the focal optics.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The focus offset value calculated in block <b>340</b> is added to the adjusted input signal that places the focal optics in proper focus. This combined input signal value is sent to an input signal source such VCM input signal sources <b>281</b> in order to drive the VCM to place the focal optics in proper focus.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Although the invention has been described in language specific to structural features and/or methodological acts, it is to be understood that the invention defined in the appended claims is not necessarily limited to the specific features or acts described. Rather, the specific features and acts are disclosed as exemplary forms of implementing the claimed invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An optical disc drive comprising:
<claim-text>a voice coil motor (VCM) carrying focal optics to focus a laser beam onto an optical disc, the VCM responsive to an input signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a temperature sensing apparatus placed at windings of the VCM that measures an operating temperature at the VCM; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller configured to adjust the input signal when a difference exists between the operating temperature and a calibration temperature of the VCM.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the input signal is a voltage signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the input signal is a current signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the VCM is calibrated for a predetermined focus offset.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the adjusted input signal is further adjusted for a predetermined focus offset.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the temperature sensing apparatus comprises a first temperature sensing apparatus and a second temperature sensing apparatus placed at windings of the VCM.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the VCM has copper windings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An optical disc drive comprising:
<claim-text>a voice coil motor VCM) that moves a sled that carries focal optics, wherein the sled provides radial positioning of the focal optics to focus a laser beam onto an optical disc, the VCM responsive to an input signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a temperature sensing apparatus placed at windings of the VCM that measures an operating temperature at the VCM; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller configured to adjust the input signal when a difference exists between the operating temperature and a calibration temperature of the VCM.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the VCM includes a course adjustment feature and a course adjustment feature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the course adjustment feature moves the sled over a predetermined increment and the fine adjustment feature adjusts per a lower predetermined increment based for a distance corresponding to the input signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the input signal is a voltage signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the input signal is a current signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method comprising:
<claim-text>measuring operating temperatures at a first VCM and a second VCM;</claim-text>
<claim-text>determining temperature differences between the operating temperatures and calibration temperatures of the first VCM and the second VCM; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>adjusting input signals to the first VCM and the second VCM based on the temperature differences.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the measuring comprises separate measurements of the first VCM and the second VCM.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the adjusting is based on a thermal contact resistance values of metals used for the first VCM and the second VCM.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the adjusting further comprises accounting for an adjusted focus offset input signal for the second VCM.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> wherein the adjusted focus offset input signal is based on a VCM gain measurement of the second VCM.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising labeling at the locations based on the first and second VCMs receiving adjusted input signals.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A processor-readable medium comprising processor-executable instructions for mapping and labeling to an optical disc, the processorexecutable instructions comprising instructions for:
<claim-text>measuring temperatures at the first VCM and the second VCM; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>adjusting input signals to the first VCM and second VCM based on a difference between measured temperatures and calibration temperatures used to relate VCM movement to input signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The processor-readable medium of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the adjusting further comprises calculating a focus offset value based on temperature difference of the second VCM and gain measurement of the second VCM.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The processor-readable medium of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> further comprising labeling using the adjusted input signals to drive the first VCM to place the OPU at a proper track and to drive the second VCM to place the focal optics in proper focus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. An ODD comprising:
<claim-text>means for determining operating temperatures at a first VCM and a second VCM;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for calculating differences between the operating temperatures and calibration temperatures for the VCMs; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for adjusting input voltages to the VCMs to account for the differences when labeling an optical disc.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The ODD of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> wherein the means for adjusting further comprises adjusting the input signals to the second VCM based on a temperature dependent focus offset value.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. An optical disc drive comprising:
<claim-text>a voice coil motor (VCM) coupled to an optical pickup unit (OPU);</claim-text>
<claim-text>a predetermined input signal for the VCM that is configured to position the OPU at a predetermined location relative to an optical disc when the VCM is at a calibration temperature;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a temperature sensing apparatus placed at windings of the VCM that measures an operating temperature at the VCM; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller configured to adjust the input signal to form a temperature compensated input signal based on a difference between the operating temperature and the calibration temperature, and to apply the temperature compensated input signal to the VCM so as to position the OPU at the predetermined location when the VCM is at the operating temperature.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the VCM controls an elevation of an OPU above a surface of a disc.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the VCM controls a radial position of an OPU from a center of a disc.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. An optical disc drive comprising:
<claim-text>a focus voice coil motor (VCM) responsive to a first input signal and adapted to focus a laser relative to a disc;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a radial VCM responsive to a second input signal and adapted to radially position the laser relative to the disc;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first temperature sensing apparatus that measures a first operating temperature at windings of the focus VCM;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second temperature sensing apparatus that measures a second operating temperature at windings of the radial VCM; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller that adjusts the first input signal based on a difference between the first operating temperature and a calibration temperature of the focus VCM, and the second input signal based on a difference between the second operating temperature and a calibration temperature of the radial VCM.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the voice coil motor is a plurality of voice coil motors, and wherein the temperature sensing apparatus is a plurality of temperature sensing apparatuses each placed at the windings of a corresponding one of the plurality of voice coil motors.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. An optical disc drive comprising:
<claim-text>a temperature sensing arrangement configured to measure operating temperatures at a first VCM and a second VCM; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a processor configured to
<claim-text>determine temperature differences between the operating temperatures and calibration temperatures of the first VCM and the second VCM, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>adjust input signals to the first VCM and the second VCM based on the temperature differences.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00029">claim 29</claim-ref> wherein the first VCM is a focusing VCM that controls an elevation of an OPU above a surface of an optical disc in the drive, and the second VCM is a tracking VCM that controls a radial position of an OPU from a center of the optical disc.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the adjusting includes calculating a percentage adjustment in each of the input signals by multiplying the temperature difference of the corresponding VCM by a temperature coefficient of the corresponding VCM.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00029">claim 29</claim-ref> wherein the processor adjusts the input signals by calculating a percentage adjustment in each of the input signals, each percentage adjustment derived by multiplying the temperature difference of the corresponding VCM by a temperature coefficient of the corresponding VCM.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00033" num="00033">
<claim-text>33. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the controller is configured to further adjust the input signal for a predetermined focus offset so as to defocus the laser beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00034" num="00034">
<claim-text>34. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00033">claim 33</claim-ref> wherein the predetermined focus offset produces larger visible spots on the optical disc.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00035" num="00035">
<claim-text>35. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref> wherein the processor is further configured to adjust the input signal to the first VCM so as to achieve a predetermined focus offset distance in the elevation of the OPU so as to defocus a laser beam emitted from the OPU onto the surface of the optical disc.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00036" num="00036">
<claim-text>36. The optical disc drive of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref> wherein the controller is configured to further adjust the first input signal based on the difference between the first operating temperature and the calibration temperature of the focus VCM so as to defocus the laser relative to the disc by a predetermined focus offset distance.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
