<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296937-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296937</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11429590</doc-number>
<date>20060505</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>6</main-group>
<subgroup>36</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 92</main-classification>
<further-classification>385 53</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 88</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Transceiver module assembly with unlatch detection switch</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6816376</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Bright et al.</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361704</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6819568</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Cao</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361728</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7090523</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Shirk et al.</name>
<date>20060800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439352</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 88- 92</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bright</last-name>
<first-name>Edward J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Middletown</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fogg</last-name>
<first-name>Michael</first-name>
<address>
<city>Harrisburg</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Miller</last-name>
<first-name>Jason J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tower City</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Tyco Electronics Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Middletown</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Doan</last-name>
<first-name>Jennifer</first-name>
<department>2874</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electrical module assembly is provided that is configured for latching engagement with a receptacle assembly. The module assembly comprises a module housing having an exterior envelope and an interior cavity. The exterior envelope of the module housing is configured to be plugged into the receptacle assembly. A release mechanism is joined to the module housing. The release mechanism is moveable between locked and unlocked positions. The release mechanism is configured to unlock the module housing from the receptacle assembly when the release mechanism is moved from the locked position to the unlocked position. A detection switch is located within the interior cavity of the module housing. The detection switch monitors a position of the release mechanism and provides latched and unlatched state signals based on the position of the release mechanism. The latched state signal indicates that the module housing is locked in the receptacle assembly. The unlatched state signal indicates that the release mechanism is being moved to the unlocked position.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="166.29mm" wi="216.41mm" file="US07296937-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="182.03mm" wi="173.14mm" file="US07296937-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="232.49mm" wi="161.71mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296937-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="218.19mm" wi="169.08mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296937-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="210.23mm" wi="172.55mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296937-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="218.78mm" wi="149.35mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296937-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="210.57mm" wi="130.05mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296937-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="211.16mm" wi="175.68mm" file="US07296937-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention relates generally to a pluggable electronic transceiver module assembly, and more particularly, to a module assembly with a switch built therein to detect when the module assembly is being unplugged from a receptacle assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Various types of fiber optic and copper based transceivers are known that permit communication between electronic host equipment and external devices. These transceivers may be incorporated into cable assembly modules that can be pluggably connected to host equipment to provide flexibility in system configuration. The cable assembly modules are constructed according to various standards for size and compatibility, one standard being the Small Form-factor Pluggable (SFP) module standard. An SFP module is plugged into a receptacle that is mounted on a circuit board within host equipment. The receptacle includes an elongated guide frame, or cage, having a front that is open to an interior space, and an electrical connector disposed at a rear of the interior space of the cage. Both the connector and the guide frame are electrically and mechanically connected to the circuit board such that, when an SFP module is plugged into a receptacle, the SFP module also becomes electrically and mechanically connected to the circuit board. Conventional SFP modules and receptacles typically carry data signals at rates up to 2.5 gigabits per second (Gbps). A standard currently in development for a next generation of SFP modules, presently called the XFP standard, calls for the transceiver modules to carry data signals at rates up to 10 Gbps.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In certain applications, it is desirable to unplug the cable assembly module while the system is operational and the cable assembly module is supporting a communications link with the system. It is undesirable to unplug the cable assembly module while being used to convey data. Instead, it is preferable to shut-down the communications link before unplugging a corresponding cable assembly module.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">However, conventional systems offer limited methods and structures for performing automatic shut-down of a communications link or for detecting the presence or absence of a cable assembly module. Conventional module detection methods determine that a cable assembly module is being removed at or after the point in time, at which the transceiver in the cable assembly module is electrically disconnected from the circuit board. The conventional module detection methods do not provide sufficient time for the system to shut down the communications link before unplugging the cable assembly module.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A need exists for methods and systems to determine when a cable assembly module is about to be unplugged early in the removal process.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In accordance with one embodiment, an electrical module assembly is provided that is configured for latching engagement with a receptacle assembly. The module assembly comprises a module housing having an exterior envelope and an interior cavity. The exterior envelope of the module housing is configured to be plugged into the receptacle assembly. A release mechanism is joined to the module housing and is moveable between locked and unlocked positions. The release mechanism is configured to unlock the module housing from the receptacle assembly when the release mechanism is moved from the locked position to the unlocked position. A detection switch is located within the interior cavity of the module housing. The detection switch monitors a position of the release mechanism and provides latched and unlatched state signals based on the position of the release mechanism. The latched state signal indicates that the module housing is locked in the receptacle assembly. The unlatched state signal indicates that the release mechanism is being moved to the unlocked position.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In accordance with an alternative embodiment, an electrical module/receptacle system is provided. The system comprises a receptacle assembly having a guide frame and a receptacle connector. The receptacle connector and guide frame are configured to be mounted to a circuit board with the receptacle connector being positioned within the guide frame. A module assembly is included that has a module housing with an exterior envelope and an interior cavity. The exterior envelope of the module housing is configured to be plugged into the receptacle assembly. A release mechanism is joined to the module housing. The release mechanism is moveable between locked and unlocked positions. The release mechanism is configured to unlock the module housing from the receptacle assembly when the release mechanism is moved from the locked position to the unlocked position. A detection switch is located within the interior cavity of the module housing. The detection switch monitors a position of the release mechanism and provides latched and unlatched state signals based on the position of the release mechanism. The latched state signal indicates that the module housing is locked in the receptacle assembly, while the unlatched state signal indicates that the release mechanism is being moved to the unlocked position.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an exploded perspective view of a module assembly and a receptacle assembly formed in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a partial exploded view of the module assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> including a release mechanism formed in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevation view of a portion of the module assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> with a cover of the module assembly removed and a detection switch in a closed position.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a side elevation view of the portion of the module assembly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> from an opposite side.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a side elevation view of the portion of the module assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> with the detection switch in an open position.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a side perspective view of a module assembly formed in accordance with an alternative embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a side view of a portion of the module assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> with a cover of the module housing removed.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a schematic diagram of detection switch logic utilized in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an electrical module/receptacle system <b>100</b> formed in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the invention. The system <b>100</b> is adapted to address, among other things, heat dissipation and electromagnetic shielding for components conveying data signals at high rates, such as data transmission rates of 10 gigabits per second (Gbs) or higher. It is appreciated, however, that the benefits and advantages of the invention may accrue equally to other data transmission rates and across a variety of systems and standards. Therefore, while embodiments of the invention are described and illustrated in the context of system <b>100</b>, the invention is not intended to be limited to system <b>100</b>, and system <b>100</b> is therefore provided for purposes of illustration rather than limitation.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the system <b>100</b> generally includes a module assembly <b>102</b> configured to be plugged into a receptacle assembly <b>104</b> that is mounted to a host circuit board <b>106</b>. The host circuit board <b>106</b> is mounted in a host system such as a router or computer (not shown). The host system typically includes a conductive chassis having a bezel <b>108</b> including openings <b>109</b> there through in substantial alignment with a respective receptacle assembly <b>104</b>. The module assembly <b>102</b> has an exterior envelope that is sized to be inserted into the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> through the opening <b>109</b>, and the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> is electrically common with the bezel <b>108</b>. The host system maintains a communications link through the module assembly <b>102</b> and receptacle assembly <b>104</b> when plugged together.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In an illustrative embodiment, the module assembly <b>102</b> includes a module housing <b>110</b> having a base <b>112</b> and a cover <b>114</b> that are secured together to form a protective shell for a circuit board (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) that is disposed within an interior cavity of the module housing <b>110</b>. The circuit board carries electronic circuitry and devices that perform transceiver functions. An edge of the circuit board is exposed through a rear <b>116</b> of the module housing <b>110</b>, and the circuit board is plugged into the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> when in a fully locked position. The module assembly <b>102</b> is adapted for installation into the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> such that a front end <b>118</b> of the module assembly <b>102</b> is extended therefrom.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The module assembly <b>102</b> and receptacle assembly <b>104</b> may be used in any application requiring an interface between a host system and electrical or optical signals. The module assembly <b>102</b> interfaces to the host system through the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> via a receptacle connector <b>120</b> which is located within a receptacle guide frame <b>122</b>, also referred to as a cage. The module assembly <b>102</b> has a front end <b>118</b> that includes a connector interface that is joined to an optical fiber or electrical cable (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). Preferably, the connector interface <b>124</b> comprises a mechanism that cooperates with a fiber or cable assembly (not shown) to secure the fiber or cable assembly to the module assembly <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The module assembly <b>102</b> and the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> reduce EMI emission through one or more of several EMI reduction features, including guide frame <b>122</b>, a gasket assembly <b>125</b> coupled to a forward end of the guide frame <b>122</b> that interfaces with the bezel <b>108</b>, and intermediate and rear gasket assemblies <b>123</b> and <b>127</b>. The EMI reduction features are described in detail in U.S. Pat. No. 6,749,448 titled “Transceiver Module Assembly Ejector Mechanism”, the complete disclosure of which is hereby incorporated by reference in its entirety.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the guide frame <b>122</b> includes a stamped and formed metal body <b>126</b> that defines a shell having a top wall <b>128</b>, a bottom wall <b>130</b>, side walls <b>132</b>, <b>134</b> and a front opening <b>136</b> into the guide frame <b>122</b>. The guide frame <b>122</b> includes latch elements <b>196</b> on opposite side walls <b>132</b>, <b>134</b>. As explained below, the latch elements <b>196</b> engage latch surfaces on the module assembly <b>102</b> to lock the module assembly <b>102</b> in the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>. The bottom wall <b>130</b> has a bottom opening to receive the receptacle connector <b>120</b>. The circuit board within the module assembly <b>102</b> includes contact pads that engage contacts <b>121</b> within the receptacle connector <b>120</b> to form signal paths over which one or more communications links are established and maintained by the host system. When the module assembly <b>102</b> is inserted into the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>, the guide frame <b>122</b> provides conductive walls on all sides thereof. The host board <b>106</b> includes a conductive surface provided thereon and formed as a sheet to underlie the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> to enhance the electromagnetic interference shielding.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The top wall <b>128</b> of the guide frame <b>122</b> may have a large opening overlying -a cavity <b>138</b> that accommodates an optional heat sink <b>150</b>. The heat sink <b>150</b> is positioned to make physical contact with the module assembly <b>102</b> when the module assembly <b>102</b> is installed into the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>. A clip <b>152</b> is mounted over the heat sink <b>150</b> and is secured to the guide frame <b>122</b>. The clip <b>152</b> ensures that the heat sink <b>150</b> is loaded against the module assembly <b>102</b> to facilitate thermal transfer from the module assembly <b>102</b> to the heat sink <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded view of the front end <b>118</b> of the module assembly <b>102</b> illustrating a release mechanism <b>180</b> removed from the module housing <b>110</b>. The module housing <b>110</b> is formed with lower and upper half shells that constitute the base <b>112</b> and cover <b>114</b>, respectively the base <b>112</b> and cover <b>114</b>, when joined, form side walls <b>292</b> and <b>294</b> and define an interior cavity therebetween. The release mechanism <b>180</b> includes a pair of actuator arms <b>184</b> that are mirror images of one another and cooperate with a bail <b>182</b> to unlock the module assembly <b>102</b> from the latched position and to eject the module assembly <b>102</b> from the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). The bail <b>182</b> is a generally rectangular body having a top side <b>250</b>, a bottom side <b>252</b>, and left and right sides <b>254</b>, <b>256</b> defining an opening <b>258</b> which is dimensioned to fit around the connector interface <b>124</b> of the module assembly <b>102</b>. The connector interface <b>124</b> includes a slot <b>260</b> formed in a lower end thereof, and the bottom side <b>252</b> of the bail <b>182</b> is received in the slot <b>260</b> to pivotally mount the bail <b>182</b> to the module assembly <b>102</b>. An angled foot portion <b>262</b> extends from each the lower corners of the bail <b>182</b> at the intersection of the bottom side <b>252</b> and the left and right sides <b>254</b>, <b>256</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Each actuator arm <b>184</b> includes a main body portion <b>264</b> with an axially extending ejector tab <b>266</b> projecting from a forward end <b>265</b> of the main body portion <b>264</b>. A switch actuator arm <b>267</b> is formed on the main body portion <b>264</b> and extends beyond the ejector tab <b>266</b>. The switch actuator arm <b>267</b> is L-shaped with a switch engagement tip <b>269</b> located at the outer end of the switch actuator arm <b>267</b>. The switch actuator arm <b>267</b> operates with a detection switch as explained below to indicate a position of the release mechanism <b>180</b>. The main body portion <b>264</b> also include a foot portion <b>270</b> located at a rear end <b>263</b> of the main body portion <b>264</b>. The foot portion <b>270</b> extends substantially perpendicularly to the main body portion <b>264</b>. A latched contact stop portion <b>272</b> is located at the rear end <b>263</b>. The main body portion <b>264</b> includes an interior surface <b>277</b> with a stepped contour <b>276</b> and an exterior surface <b>279</b> with a tapered leading end <b>278</b>. The tapered leading end <b>278</b> has a gradually reduced thickness to form a ramped surface extending to the ejector tab <b>266</b>. The ejector tab <b>266</b> has a reduced width relative to the main body portion <b>264</b> and includes a ramped surface <b>280</b> extending to a raised boss <b>282</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The ramped surface <b>280</b> of the ejector tab <b>266</b> is inclined oppositely to the tapered leading end <b>278</b> of the actuator arms <b>184</b>. The tapered leading end <b>278</b> and the ramped surface <b>280</b> are arranged side-by-side in a valley configuration and thus are sloped toward one another. The interior surface <b>277</b> of each actuator arm <b>184</b> includes a longitudinal slot <b>284</b> which houses a bias element <b>286</b>, such as a coil spring, in an exemplary embodiment. The bias element <b>286</b> provides spring-loaded release actuation of the module assembly <b>102</b> as the bail <b>182</b> is manipulated by a user.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The module assembly <b>102</b> includes a retention cavity <b>290</b> on each of the side walls <b>292</b>, <b>294</b> thereof. The retention cavities <b>290</b> are shaped generally complementary to the outer profile of the respective actuator arms <b>184</b>. Each of the retention cavities <b>290</b> includes a first portion <b>296</b>, a second portion <b>298</b>, and a third portion <b>300</b>. The first portion <b>296</b> has a width slightly larger than a width of the main body portion <b>264</b> of the actuator arm <b>184</b> and a depth substantially equal to a full depth of the main body portion <b>264</b>. The second portion <b>298</b> has a width substantially equal to the first portion but a depth substantially equal to the reduced depth of the main body portion <b>264</b> adjacent the tapered leading end <b>278</b>. The third portion <b>300</b> has a substantially equal depth to the second portion <b>298</b> but a reduced width that is slightly larger than a width of the ejector tab <b>266</b>. The first and second portions <b>296</b>, <b>298</b> of the retention cavity <b>290</b> are configured to accept the stepped contour <b>276</b> of the main body portion <b>264</b> of the actuator arms <b>184</b>, and the third portion <b>300</b> is configured to receive the ejector tab <b>266</b> with sliding engagement. A shoulder <b>302</b> separates the first portion <b>296</b> from the second portion <b>298</b> and provides an abutment or seat for the bias element <b>286</b> of each of the actuator arms <b>184</b>. The retention cavity <b>290</b> includes a latch surface <b>301</b> between the second and third portions <b>298</b> and <b>300</b>. The latch elements <b>196</b> on the guide frame <b>122</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) engage the latch surfaces <b>301</b> to lock the module assembly <b>102</b> in the receptacle module <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In the example of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the base <b>112</b> and cover <b>114</b> fit together to define the interior cavity. The retention cavity <b>290</b> on side wall <b>294</b> (not visible in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), that receives the actuator arm <b>184</b> with the switch actuator arm <b>267</b>, includes an opening into the interior cavity within the base <b>112</b> and cover <b>114</b>. The opening is located in the second and third portions <b>298</b> and <b>300</b> of the side wall <b>294</b>. When the actuator arm <b>184</b> is loaded into the retention cavity <b>290</b> on the side wall <b>294</b>, the switch actuator arm <b>267</b> extends through the opening in the second and third portions <b>298</b> and <b>300</b>. The structure and operation of the switch actuator arm <b>267</b> are described in more detail below.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">During use, as the module assembly <b>102</b> is inserted into the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>, the ejector tabs <b>266</b> contact the latch elements <b>196</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) of the guide frame <b>122</b> and deflect the latch elements <b>196</b> outwardly to allow the module assembly <b>102</b> to be inserted into the guide frame <b>122</b>. When the module assembly <b>102</b> is fully inserted, the ejector tabs <b>266</b> clear the latch elements <b>196</b>, and the latch elements <b>196</b> deflect inwardly upon the tapered leading ends <b>278</b> of the actuator arms <b>184</b>. The latch surfaces <b>301</b> therefore become latched behind the latch elements <b>196</b> of the guide frame <b>122</b> when the module assembly <b>102</b> is fully installed in the guide frame <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In the latched position, the bail <b>182</b> is positioned substantially upright with the foot portions <b>262</b> of the bail <b>182</b> contacting the foot portions <b>270</b> of the actuator arms <b>184</b> at an obtuse angle. The latched contact stop portions <b>272</b> of the actuator arms <b>184</b> contact the sides <b>254</b>, <b>256</b> of the bail <b>182</b>. The bias elements <b>286</b> are loaded in compression and maintain the bail <b>182</b> in the latched position. As the bail <b>182</b> is pivoted in the direction of arrow G away from the connector interface <b>124</b> about the bottom side <b>252</b>, the foot portions <b>262</b> of the bail <b>182</b> slide upwardly against the foot portions <b>270</b> of the actuator arms <b>184</b> in the direction of arrow H to form a right angle between the foot portions <b>270</b> and <b>262</b>. When moving from the obtuse to the right angle orientation, the foot portions <b>262</b> of the bail <b>182</b> cause the actuator arms <b>184</b> to move longitudinally inward into the retention cavities <b>290</b> in the direction of arrow J, thereby further loading the bias elements <b>286</b> in the actuator arms <b>184</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Further pivoting of the bail <b>182</b> begins to move the foot portions <b>262</b> into an obtuse orientation and away from the foot portions <b>270</b> which permits the bias elements <b>286</b> to relax and push the actuator arms <b>184</b> forward in the direction of arrow K toward the connector interface <b>124</b>. At this point, the latch elements <b>196</b> of the guide frame <b>122</b> are in contact with the ramped surfaces <b>280</b> of the ejector tabs <b>266</b> of the actuator arms <b>184</b>. As the bias elements <b>286</b> force the actuator arms <b>184</b> in a forward direction of arrow K, the ramped surfaces <b>280</b> deflect the latch elements <b>196</b> outwardly out of retention cavities <b>290</b> until the bosses <b>282</b> and latch surfaces <b>301</b> clear the latch elements <b>196</b>. The actuator arms <b>184</b> are displaced forwardly by the bias elements <b>286</b>, and the ejector tabs <b>266</b> are released from the latch elements <b>196</b> of the guide frame <b>122</b>. In the unlatched position, the module assembly <b>102</b> may be removed from the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> by pulling the bail <b>182</b> to slide the module assembly <b>102</b> out of the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>. The bias elements <b>286</b> maintain the bail <b>182</b> in the latched position until the bail <b>182</b> is rotated. The bail <b>182</b> may be pivoted back toward the connector interface <b>124</b> to position the actuator arms <b>184</b> back to the latched position wherein the ejector tabs <b>266</b> engage the latch elements <b>196</b> of the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a side elevation view of a portion of the module assembly <b>102</b> with the cover <b>114</b> removed. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the base <b>112</b> includes sidewalls <b>292</b> and <b>294</b> that are separated by an interior cavity <b>293</b>. The interior cavity <b>293</b> receives a module board, such as printed circuit board <b>295</b>. The circuit board <b>295</b> has a top surface <b>297</b> that is populated with active and passive components and includes contact pads <b>299</b> that are configured to be joined to wires or contacts of a cable assembly, mating plug and the like. The contact pads <b>299</b> are joined to traces <b>289</b> that extend along the top surface <b>297</b>. The top surface <b>297</b> also includes a present pin contact pad <b>401</b> and a power contact pad <b>402</b>. The present pin contact pad <b>401</b> and power contact pad <b>402</b> are joined to corresponding switch signal traces <b>403</b> and <b>404</b>, respectively, that extend along the length of the circuit board <b>295</b>, to be connected to electronics provided on the host circuit board <b>106</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">A detection switch <b>406</b> is mounted proximate to a lead end <b>287</b> of the circuit board <b>295</b>. The detection switch <b>406</b> is engaged and released by the switch engagement tip <b>269</b> of the switch actuator arm <b>267</b> as the actuator arm <b>184</b> is linearly moved along the directions denoted by arrows A and B between latched and unlatched states or positions, respectively. The detection switch <b>406</b> monitors a position of the release mechanism <b>180</b> and provides latched and unlatched state signals over the switch signal traces <b>403</b> and <b>404</b> based on the position of the release mechanism <b>180</b>. The latched state signal indicates that the module housing <b>110</b> is fully locked in the guide frame <b>122</b>. The unlatched state signal indicates that the release mechanism <b>180</b> is being moved to the unlocked position. The detection switch <b>406</b> generates the unlatched state signal at some time interval before signal contacts on circuit board <b>295</b> disconnect from contacts <b>121</b> in the receptacle connector <b>120</b>. For example, the detection switch <b>406</b> may generate the unlatched state signal when the bail <b>182</b> initially begins to move the release mechanism <b>180</b> in the unlatching direction of arrow B from the locked position toward the unlocked position.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The detection switch <b>406</b> includes a spring element <b>408</b> having a base portion <b>410</b> and a V-shaped body <b>412</b> formed integrally at a hinge area <b>416</b> with the base portion <b>410</b>. A dielectric member <b>420</b> is provided on the V-shaped body <b>412</b> at a position to engage the release mechanism <b>180</b> to maintain an insulation interface between the switch spring element <b>408</b> and the switch engagement tip <b>269</b> of the switch actuator arm <b>267</b>. The V-shaped body <b>412</b> has outer tip portions <b>414</b> that are positioned above the power contact pad <b>402</b>. The V-shaped body <b>412</b> pivots at the hinge area <b>416</b> along arcuate paths denoted by arrows C and D between open and closed positions, respectively, with the power contact pad <b>402</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a side elevation view opposite to the view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> of the detection switch element <b>406</b> and switch actuator arm <b>267</b>. When the switch actuator arm <b>267</b> is slid in the direction of arrow A toward the switch spring element <b>408</b>, the switch engagement tip <b>269</b> engages the dielectric member <b>420</b> and forces the outer tip portions <b>414</b> of the V-shaped body <b>412</b> downward along path C into engagement with the power contact pad <b>402</b>, thereby establishing a closed position. When the outer tip portions <b>414</b> engage the power contact pad <b>402</b>, a closed circuit is formed between the present pin contact pad <b>401</b> and the power contact pad <b>402</b>. When the closed circuit is formed, a latched state signal is conveyed to electronic components on the host board <b>106</b> or host system indicating that the module assembly <b>102</b> is fully plugged into the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the base portion <b>410</b> is secured to the circuit board <b>295</b> with a curved clip formed at end <b>418</b> that wraps about the lead end <b>287</b> of the circuit board <b>295</b>. Alternatively, the base portion <b>410</b> may be secured by solder or other means to the contact circuit pad <b>401</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates the detection switch <b>406</b> and the switch actuator arm <b>267</b> when moved relative to the module housing <b>110</b> to the open circuit or fully unlatched position. When the switch actuator arm <b>267</b> is moved to the fully unlatched position, the switch engagement tip <b>269</b> is spaced apart from the dielectric member <b>420</b>. The base portion <b>410</b> and the V-shaped body <b>412</b> are formed with a predetermined obtuse angle <b>417</b> therebetween at the hinge area <b>416</b>, such that, when the switch actuator arm <b>267</b> is slid in the direction of arrow B toward the unplugged position, the outer tip portions <b>414</b> of the V-shaped body <b>412</b> rotate along path D upward and away from the power contact pad <b>402</b>. When the outer tip portions <b>414</b> disengage from the power contact pad <b>402</b>, an open circuit is formed between the switch contact pad <b>401</b> and the power contact pad <b>402</b>. When the open circuit is formed, an unlatched state signal is conveyed to electronic components on the host board <b>106</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) indicating that the module assembly <b>102</b> is about to be unplugged from the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The dimensions and spacing of the actuator arm <b>184</b>, switch actuator arm <b>267</b>, ejector tabs <b>266</b> and detection switch <b>406</b> are configured such that the outer tip portions <b>414</b> disengage from the power contact pad <b>402</b> before or substantially simultaneously with disengagement of the ejector tabs <b>266</b> from the latched position, thereby providing the unlatched state signal before the module assembly <b>102</b> is unplugged from the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>, by a predetermined minimum shut-down time interval. For example, it may be desirable to provide the unlatched state signal by a minimum shut-down time interval of approximately between 50 and 500 milliseconds before contacts within the module assembly <b>102</b> and receptacle assembly <b>104</b> electrically disconnect from one another. As a further example, it may be desirable to provide the unlatched state signal by a predetermined shut-down time interval of approximately 100 milliseconds before contacts within the module assembly <b>102</b> and receptacle assembly <b>104</b> electrically disconnect from one another.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a perspective view of a module assembly <b>310</b> formed in accordance with an alternative embodiment. The module assembly <b>310</b> includes a release mechanism <b>312</b> that includes a pair of actuator arms <b>314</b> which are constructed in a substantially similar manner to one another. Each actuator arm <b>314</b> extends within a retention cavity <b>316</b> formed within corresponding side walls <b>318</b> of the module assembly <b>310</b>. The actuator arms <b>314</b> extend longitudinally along the side walls <b>318</b>, and the actuator arms <b>314</b> cooperate with a bail <b>320</b> to release the module assembly <b>310</b> from the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> as described below.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">At least one of the actuator arms <b>314</b> include a switch actuator arm similar to the switch actuator arm <b>267</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-5</figref>. The module assembly <b>310</b> includes half shells forming a base <b>311</b> and a cover <b>313</b>, that collectively define an interior cavity. The interior cavity within the module assembly <b>310</b> includes a circuit board having a detection switch thereon that is similar to the detection switch <b>406</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The bail <b>320</b> includes a top side <b>322</b> extending transversely across the module assembly <b>310</b> between the side walls <b>318</b>, and two opposing lateral sides <b>324</b> which extend downward from the top side <b>322</b> in a plane parallel to the side walls <b>318</b> of the module assembly <b>310</b>. The top side <b>322</b> and lateral sides <b>324</b> are dimensioned to receive a connector interface <b>326</b> of the module assembly <b>310</b> which provides a site for connection to a cable assembly <b>327</b>, which may include an optical fiber or electrical cable, strain relief features, etc. The connector interface <b>326</b> includes an aperture (not shown) on each lateral side of the module assembly <b>310</b>, and each of the lateral sides <b>324</b> of the bail includes an inward facing cylindrical pin (not shown) which fits into the apertures to pivotally or rotatably mount the lateral sides <b>324</b> of the bail <b>320</b> to the module assembly <b>310</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In an exemplary embodiment, the front end <b>328</b> of the module assembly <b>310</b> includes notched corners <b>330</b> that facilitate operation of the bail <b>320</b> as described below. The lateral sides <b>324</b> of the bail include downwardly extending vertical portions <b>332</b> extending substantially perpendicularly to the horizontal top side <b>322</b> at either end thereof. Horizontal shelf portions <b>334</b> extend in a perpendicular orientation from the vertical portions <b>332</b> but in the same plane as the vertical portions <b>332</b> of the bail <b>320</b>, and vertical actuator portions <b>336</b> extend from the shelf portions <b>334</b> in a parallel arrangement to the vertical portions <b>332</b>. A hook portion <b>338</b> extends from distal ends of each of the actuator portions <b>336</b> of the bail <b>320</b>, and the hook portions <b>338</b> include engagement ledges <b>340</b> extending opposite the actuator portions <b>336</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The actuator arms <b>314</b> include a main body portion <b>342</b> including an axially extending ejector tab <b>344</b>, and a foot portion <b>345</b> extending substantially perpendicularly to the main body portion <b>342</b>. The main body portion <b>342</b> includes a tapered leading end <b>346</b> which has a gradually reduced thickness to form a ramped surface extending to the ejector tab <b>344</b>. The ejector tab <b>344</b> has a reduced width relative to the main body portion <b>342</b> and includes a ramped surface <b>348</b> extending to a raised boss <b>350</b>. The ramped surface <b>348</b> of the ejector tab <b>344</b> is inclined oppositely to the tapered leading end <b>346</b> of the actuator arms <b>314</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The foot portion <b>345</b> of the actuator arms <b>314</b> includes a vertical opening or slot <b>354</b> which defines an engagement surface <b>352</b> for the hook <b>338</b> of the bail <b>320</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the bail <b>320</b> is rotated about the front end <b>328</b> of the module assembly <b>310</b> in the direction of arrow E until the ledge <b>340</b> of the hook <b>338</b> is in contact with the engagement surface <b>352</b> of the slot <b>354</b> in the actuator arms <b>314</b>. When the module assembly <b>310</b> is inserted into receptacle assembly <b>104</b>, the latch elements <b>196</b> of the guide frame <b>122</b> are in contact with latch surfaces <b>351</b> in the retention cavities <b>316</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As the bail <b>320</b> continues to be rotated in the direction of arrow E, the engagement of the ledges <b>340</b> and the hooks <b>338</b> displace or pull the actuator arms <b>314</b> in a direction of arrow B which extends parallel to a longitudinal axis of the module assembly <b>310</b>. As the actuator arms <b>314</b> are moved in the forward direction of Arrow B, the ramped surfaces <b>348</b> outwardly deflect the latch elements <b>196</b> of the guide frame <b>122</b> until the latch surfaces <b>351</b> and bosses <b>350</b> clear and the latch elements <b>196</b> and the retention tabs <b>266</b> are released from the latch elements <b>196</b> of the guide frame <b>122</b>. In the unlatched position, the module assembly <b>310</b> may be removed from the receptacle assembly <b>104</b> by continuing to pull the bail <b>320</b> in the direction of arrow E to slide the module assembly <b>310</b> out of the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Due to direct engagement of the hooks <b>338</b> of the bail <b>320</b> and the slots <b>354</b> of the actuator arms <b>314</b>, release of the module assembly <b>310</b> from a receptacle assembly <b>104</b> is accomplished without internal spring elements. Manufacturing and assembly costs are therefore reduced while nonetheless providing an effective and reliable latch and release mechanism.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a side view of the module assembly <b>310</b> with the cover <b>313</b> removed. A circuit board <b>516</b> is shown with signal contacts <b>512</b> located proximate to a forward end <b>514</b> thereof. The signal contacts <b>512</b> engage contacts <b>121</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) in the receptacle connector <b>120</b>. The bail <b>320</b> and actuator arm <b>314</b> are in the fully locked or plugged position. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates a switch actuator arm <b>367</b> provided on the outer end of the actuator arm <b>314</b>. The switch actuator arm <b>367</b> includes a switch engagement tip <b>369</b> that engages dielectric member <b>520</b> on detection switch <b>506</b>. As explained above, the dimensions and spacing of the actuator arm <b>314</b>, switch actuator arm <b>367</b>, ejector tabs <b>350</b> and detection switch <b>506</b> are configured such that the detection switch <b>506</b> generates an unlatched state signal before or substantially simultaneously with an initial movement of the actuator arm <b>314</b>, thereby providing the unlatch state signal well before the contacts <b>512</b> on the forward end <b>514</b> of the circuit board <b>516</b> are disconnected from the contacts <b>121</b> in receptacle assembly <b>104</b>, by a minimum shut-down time interval.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a schematic diagram of an unlatch detection circuit <b>550</b> implemented in connection with an embodiment of the present invention. The circuit <b>550</b> includes a host board <b>106</b> that is electrically joined to a circuit or module board, such as circuit board <b>295</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). When the circuit board <b>295</b> is joined to the host board <b>106</b>, power source Vcc contact <b>552</b>, present pin <b>554</b> and ground contact <b>556</b> are interconnected therebetween. Traces <b>556</b>, <b>558</b> and <b>560</b> extend from the power source Vcc contact <b>552</b>, present pin <b>554</b> and ground contact <b>556</b> along the length of the circuit board <b>295</b>. The power source Vcc contact <b>552</b> and present pin <b>554</b> terminate at a power contact pad and a present pin contact pad, such as power contact pad <b>402</b> and present pin contact pad <b>401</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>), respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a detection switch <b>570</b> that corresponds to the unlatch switch <b>406</b>. The detection switch <b>570</b> is a normally open switch. When the detection switch <b>570</b> is closed, a “latched” state signal is provided along trace <b>558</b> to the present pin <b>554</b>. The “latched” state signal indicates that the release mechanism is in a fully latched position. When the detection switch <b>570</b> is open, an “unlatched” state signal is provided along trace <b>558</b> to the present pin <b>554</b>. The “unlatched” state signal may constitute a first voltage level determined by the initial voltage Vcc and the voltage drop across resistor <b>572</b>. The “unlatched” state signal indicates that the release mechanism is not in a fully latched position. The “unlatched” state signal may be generated at various stages throughout an unplugging operation of the module assembly <b>102</b> from the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>. For, example, in the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the “unlatched” state signal may be generated before or after the ejector tabs <b>350</b> fully disengage from the receptacle assembly <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In the above examples, the detection switches are normally open switches. Optionally, the switch actuator arm and detection switch may be modified to operate as a normally closed switch when in the unlatched position. Optionally, the switch actuator arm may be constructed to directly bridge the power and present pin contact pads. Optionally, the detection switch may produce signals described above. Optionally, the release mechanism may not directly engage the detection switch, but instead change the detection switch state through magnetic, optical or infrared means.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">While the invention has been described in terms of various specific embodiments, those skilled in the art will recognize that the invention can be practiced with modification within the spirit and scope of the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electrical module assembly configured to engage a receptacle assembly, the module assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a module housing configured to be plugged into, and locked in, the receptacle assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a release mechanism joined to the module housing, the release mechanism being moveable between locked and unlocked positions, the release mechanism being configured to unlock the module housing from the receptacle assembly when the release mechanism moved from the locked position to the unlocked position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detection switch carried by the module housing, the detection switch monitoring a position of the release mechanism and providing electrical latched and unlatched state signals based on the position of the release mechanism, the latched state signal indicating that the module housing is locked in the receptacle assembly, the unlatched state signal indicating that the release mechanism is being moved to the unlocked position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the release mechanism includes an actuator arm having a switch actuation member formed thereon and extending forward from a lead end of the actuator arm, the switch actuation member engaging the detection switch when the release mechanism is moved to the locked position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the detection switch includes a spring element mounted in the module housing, the spring element being movable between a normally open position and a closed position, the switch actuation member deflecting the spring element to the closed position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the module housing includes a side wall having an interior and an exterior, the release mechanism sliding along the exterior of the side wall, the release mechanism including a switch actuation member that slides along the interior of the side wall to engage and disengage the detection switch.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a module board located in the module housing, the module board including power and present pin contact pads located thereon, the detection switch closing and opening a connection between the power and present pin contact pads to produce the latched and unlatched state signals, respectively.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a module board located in the module housing, the module board including a switch signal trace extending along a length thereof, the switch signal trace joined to the detection switch to convey the latched and unlatched state signals to the receptacle module.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the detection switch includes a dielectric member that is positioned to be engaged by the release mechanism when the release mechanism is in the locked position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the module assembly includes module signal contacts positioned to engage corresponding receptacle signal contacts in the receptacle assembly, the detection switch generating the unlatched state signal at least 100 milliseconds before the module and receptacle signal contacts disconnect from one another.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the release mechanism further comprises a bail pivotally mounted to the module housing, the bail being pivoted to move the release mechanism between the locked and the unlocked positions, the detection switch generating the unlatched state signal when the bail begins to move the release mechanism from the locked position toward the unlocked position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the detection switch generates the unlatched state signal before the module housing begins to move relative to the receptacle assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An electrical module/receptacle system, comprising:
<claim-text>a receptacle assembly having a guide frame and a receptacle connector, the receptacle connector and the guide frame being configured to be mounted to a circuit board with the receptacle connector being positioned within the guide frame;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a module assembly having a module housing with an exterior envelope and an interior cavity, the exterior envelope of the module housing being configured to be plugged into, and locked in, the receptacle assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a release mechanism joined to the module housing, the release mechanism being moveable between locked and unlocked positions, the release mechanism being configured to unlock the module housing from the receptacle assembly when the release mechanism is moved from the locked position to the unlocked position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detection switch located within the interior cavity of the module housing, the detection switch monitoring a position of the release mechanism and providing electrical latched and unlatched state signals based on the position of the release mechanism, the latched state signal indicating that the module housing is locked in the receptacle assembly, the unlatched state signal indicating that the release mechanism is being moved to the unlocked position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the release mechanism includes an actuator arm having a switch actuation member formed thereon and extending forward from a lead end of the actuator arm, the switch actuation member engaging the detection switch when the release mechanism is moved to the locked position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the detection switch includes a spring element mounted in the interior cavity of the module housing, the spring element being movable between a normally open position and a closed position, the switch actuation member deflecting the spring element to the closed position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the guide frame includes an EMI gasket coupled to a forward end of the guide frame to provide EMI shielding.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising a module board located in the interior cavity of the module housing, the module board including power and present pin contact pads located thereon, the detection switch closing and opening a connection between the power and present pin contact pads to produce the latched and unlatched state signals, respectively.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising a module board located in the interior cavity of the module housing, the module board including a switch signal trace extending along a length thereof, the switch signal trace joined to the detection switch to convey the latched and unlatched state signals to the receptacle module.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein module and receptacle assemblies include module and receptacle signal contacts positioned to engage one another, the detection switch generating the unlatched state signal before the module and receptacle signal contacts disconnect from one another.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the release mechanism further comprises a bail pivotally mounted to the module housing, the bail being pivoted to move the release mechanism between the locked and the unlocked positions, the detection switch generating the unlatched state signal when the bail begins to move the release mechanism from the locked position toward the unlocked position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the detection switch generates the unlatched state signal before the module housing begins to move relative to the receptacle assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the receptacle connector conveys the latched and unlatched state signals to components on a circuit board to enable shut down of a data channel maintained through the module and receptacle assemblies before the module and receptacle assemblies are electrically disconnected from one another.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
