<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298368-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298368</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10803635</doc-number>
<date>20040317</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>779</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>09</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>09</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>30</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>09</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>36</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345205</main-classification>
<further-classification>345 76</further-classification>
<further-classification>345 90</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Display device having a DAC per pixel</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5959598</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>McKnight</name>
<date>19990900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345 90</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5977940</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Akiyama et al.</name>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345 94</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6014193</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Taira et al.</name>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349 73</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7038641</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hirota et al.</name>
<date>20060500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345 83</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7068251</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lin et al.</name>
<date>20060600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345 87</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7170485</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Huang</name>
<date>20070100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345 98</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7224339</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Koyama et al.</name>
<date>20070500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345 98</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0041266</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Koyama et al.</name>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0075208</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Bae et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345 76</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345 90</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345204</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345205</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345 98</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345100</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050206631</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050922</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Anderson</last-name>
<first-name>Daryl E.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Corrigan, III</last-name>
<first-name>George H</first-name>
<address>
<city>Corvallis</city>
<state>OR</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hewlett-Packard Development Company, L.P.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Houston</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lefkowitz</last-name>
<first-name>Sumati</first-name>
<department>2629</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Amadiz</last-name>
<first-name>Rodney</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An embodiment of the invention is a display device including a plurality of pixels. The pixels in the display include an optical part. There is a digital-to-analog converter for driving the optical part. The digital to analog converter is physically co-located the optical part. Driving circuitry provides digital signals simultaneously to digital-to-analog converters for the plurality of pixels.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="158.41mm" wi="187.11mm" file="US07298368-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="190.75mm" wi="159.00mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298368-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="191.69mm" wi="160.61mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298368-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="207.52mm" wi="160.53mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298368-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="212.85mm" wi="157.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298368-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="79.50mm" wi="82.97mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298368-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention is in the display device field. The invention particularly concerns display drivers.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Display devices for computer-driven and computer-assisted applications are in widespread use. Display devices now range is size from the very small, e.g., for handheld devices, to the very large, e.g., for large displays in conference halls and public spaces, both indoor and outdoor.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Challenges presented by very large display devices include the need for very high frequency signals to drive them. For example, a thin-film transistor (“TFT”) display device with a rectilinear configuration of 1,000×1,000 picture elements (“pixels,” an element of a visual image or picture), using a typical “row, column” addressing scheme, 256 intensity values and displaying 72 frames/second would require a driving signal frequency of (1,000 rows×256 intensity levels×72 frames/second)≈18.4 MHz, and 256 time intervals per frame are required to achieve 256 intensity levels. The 256 time intervals are required because one time interval is required to send either a 1 or a 0, the total of 256 of which bits represents the desired intensity for a given frame distributed time-wise through the frame to reduce artifacts.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Very high frequency signals can present design, operation and control issues. One such issue that becomes important at high frequencies is the effect of electromagnetic interference (“EMI”). This may be particularly important to consider in larger display devices because the required long electrical traces act as antennae. It would be beneficial to drive a given display with lower frequency signals and yet produce the same number of intensity levels, frames/second, etc.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">An embodiment of the invention is a display device including a plurality of pixels. The pixels in the display include an optical part. There is a digital-to-analog converter for driving the optical part. The digital to analog converter is physically co-located the optical part. Driving circuitry provides digital signals simultaneously to digital-to-analog converters for the plurality of pixels.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a partial schematic diagram of an exemplary display device according to an embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a partial schematic diagram of an exemplary display device according to an embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a partial schematic diagram of an exemplary display device according to an embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a partial schematic diagram of an exemplary display device according to an embodiment of the invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flow chart depicting an exemplary method embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The present invention is directed to display devices, methods for driving display devices, and methods of making display devices. An exemplary apparatus embodiment of the invention includes driving circuitry and a digital-to-analog converter (“DAC”) co-located with the optical part of a pixel in a display.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">As used herein, “pixel” encompasses both a picture element that includes a single optical part for the display of a single color and a picture element including a plurality of optical parts for the display of one or more colors, sometimes referred to in the art as a “superpixel”. A preferred pixel of the invention is a tri-color pixel, as current color science and management makes prevailing use of a tri-color scheme. For example, in a display using the red-green-blue (“RGB”) color scheme, a pixel (also called a superpixel) would include at least one distinct optical part for displaying each color, e.g., red, green and blue. Also, while the RGB color scheme is used as an example, other color schemes are possible and within the scope of the invention. The invention is well-suited to any multi-color scheme, and will apply equally as color science changes, for example as new physical display elements and combinations develop. Artisans will accordingly appreciate that the exemplary tri-color pixels and exemplary color management schemes in the preferred embodiment serve as an illustration of multi-color pixels in making use of any color science and any color management scheme.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">“Optical part,” as used herein, encompasses a physical element that transmits or produces a display. This includes, for example, emissive, transmissive, and reflective elements. An example emissive element is a light emitting diode, including, for example, an organic light emitting device (OLED). An example transmissive element is a masking element, such as an element in a liquid crystal array used to selectively pass or block light. Example reflective elements are a digital micro mirror device (DMD) and a diffractive light device (DLD).</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">An exemplary method embodiment of the invention includes loading digital data serially into respective serial shifters of a plurality of pixels, where the digital data include a plurality of bits. The digital data is loaded simultaneously into respective parallel data latches of the plurality of pixels. Conversion of the digital data into analog signals occurs simultaneously in the pixels. The analog signals are sent to optical parts of the pixels to cause a display. Embodiments of the invention allow a reduction in the number of bits required to define an intensity level within a set of intensity levels, permitting operation of a display at relatively lower frequencies. Embodiments of the invention also feature displays including an array of pixels in two dimensions, e.g., in rows and columns, without the display space being taken up by circuitry for connecting the pixels in implementation of the invention. In a typical row-and-column array, there are drivers for both the rows and the columns. This driving circuitry occupies array surface area on both the top and on at least one side of the typical row-and-column array, which limits the ability to abut panels side-by-side without a gap or gaps in the total display area.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Skilled artisans will recognize that the present invention is not limited to any given display geometry. An example embodiment is a rectilinear configuration with rows and columns of pixels (with rows being horizontal bands and columns being vertical bands of pixels with reference to the usual orientation of the display). Another example is a round configuration with concentric bands of pixels, or other configurations of pixels in a display. Many other example geometries will be apparent to artisans.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The invention will now be illustrated with respect to exemplary embodiment devices. Methods of the invention will also be apparent from the following discussion. In describing the invention, particular exemplary devices will be used for purposes of illustration. The drawings are not to scale. Illustrated devices may be schematically presented, and exaggerated for purposes of illustration and understanding of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Turning now to the figures, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of a portion of an exemplary embodiment display <b>10</b> of the invention, formed of a plurality of pixels arranged in an arbitrary geometric configuration, for example, in a rectangular arrangement where pixels may be addressed as rows and columns. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a portion of the display <b>10</b> including two pixels <b>12</b>. While two pixels <b>12</b> are shown, the display may include a very large number of pixels. As an example, a display capable of presenting an HDTV image may have 2,073,600 pixels (in the 1080i format). The pixels in the display are arranged into groups, for example rows.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Each of the pixels <b>12</b> includes three optical parts <b>14</b>, for example red, green, and blue emissive elements and driving circuitry. Each optical part <b>14</b> can produce a display according to a specified, settable intensity. Data bits are received by serial shifters <b>16</b>, forming part of the driving circuitry. The connection of a plurality of serial shifters <b>16</b> of multiple pixels defines a group of pixels, for example a row in a rectilinear display, that receives a data set by a serial shift of bits beginning at one end of the serially-connected serial shifters <b>16</b> one bit at a time until each shifter <b>16</b> in the group of pixels receives a byte of data. In the exemplary embodiments, the shifters each hold a byte of 8 bits, but artisans will appreciate that the principle is generally extendible to n bits, where n is greater than 1 and is preferably at least 8. The number n influences the number of potential distinct intensity levels available to be displayed from corresponding optical parts <b>14</b>. In the example where n=8, there are 256 potential intensity levels that may be set for each optical part.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">By shifting data into the serial shifters, there is no need to include addressing data for pixels <b>12</b> (or optical parts). A simple serial data shift into the group of pixels provides a data byte for each optical part <b>14</b> in the group of pixels. The shifting occurs in accordance with a global clock signal (GCLK) on a global clock line <b>18</b>. In an example embodiment, a data set advances one bit per clock cycle into the serial shifters <b>16</b>. Taking the example of a rectilinear display, a data set would shift into each row, for example in accordance with the signal GCLK in each of the rows of the display.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Once shifting of a data set has been completed, a data byte (for example 8 bits) for each optical part <b>14</b> is moved into a respective data latch <b>20</b> (forming part of the driving circuitry) in accordance with a global load signal (GLD) provided on a global load line <b>22</b>. When a data latch loads a new byte of data it applies a previous byte of data to a respective digital to analog converter (DAC) <b>24</b>, a final part of the driving circuitry in the exemplary <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> embodiment. Each DAC <b>24</b> drives a respective optical part <b>14</b> based upon data that had been shifted into a corresponding serial shifter <b>16</b> and latched by a corresponding latch <b>20</b>. The GLD signal is provided after a predetermined number of GLCK cycles, and after a load into data latches <b>20</b>, the cycle of shifting a new data set into the serial shifters <b>16</b> begins again. In an embodiment of the invention, the optical parts <b>14</b> are emitting parts, such as light emitting diodes, and in other embodiments of the invention the optical transmissive parts that selectively transmit light or reflecting parts that reflect light emitted from a source that may not be included in the pixels <b>12</b>. In preferred embodiments, the display <b>10</b> is an integrated circuit, and with an architecture in accordance with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The driving circuitry, including the DACs, serial shifters, and data latches are physically co-located in the pixels, with the optical parts <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The digital to analog conversion occurs in the pixels, subsequent to the data being shifted to the pixels. For an exemplary display device embodiment of the present invention with a rectilinear configuration of 1,000×1,000 pixels, using a typical “row, column” addressing scheme and groups of 8 bits to define 2<sup>8 </sup>or 256 intensity values and displaying 72 frames/second would require driving signal frequency of (1,000 rows×8 bits×72 frames/second)=576 KHz, and only eight time intervals per frame are required to achieve 256 intensity levels.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Skilled artisans will recognize that the items included in the pixels <b>12</b> may be implemented in a number of ways. Without intending to limit the scope of the invention, these implementations include the following without excluding others not mentioned herein. In an embodiment of the invention, the serial shifters <b>16</b> may be implemented based on charge-coupled-device logic or chains of transmission gates and inverters. In an embodiment of the invention, the parallel data latches <b>20</b> are latches, which may be implemented, e.g., as capacitors. In an embodiment of the invention, the DACs <b>24</b> may be implemented, e.g., as a resistor ladder or as a set of binary resistors. A preferred embodiment is based on complementary metal-oxide semiconductor (“CMOS”) technology. In an embodiment of the invention, the optical parts <b>14</b> may be implemented as light emitting devices, e.g., light emitting diodes (“LED”), an organic light emitting diodes (“OLED”), or as light reflecting devices, e.g., digital micro-mirrors (“DMD”), such as those available from Texas Instruments, or some combination of different kinds of optical parts, such as a combination of radiation and reflection devices.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic diagram of a portion of another exemplary embodiment display <b>26</b> of the invention. The <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> device includes optical parts <b>14</b>, serial shifters <b>16</b>, and latches <b>20</b> that are the same as in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> embodiment, with shifting and loading also being conducted with the GCLK and GLD signals on the global clock and global load lines <b>18</b>, <b>22</b>. Unlike the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> embodiment, pixels <b>28</b> each include one DAC <b>30</b> instead of one DAC for each optical part <b>14</b>. A switch <b>32</b> cycles according to color phases to sequentially and individually apply the output of the DAC <b>30</b>, for example, separate R, G, and B signals to the respective optical parts. The switch <b>32</b> is controlled by a switch signal SW provided on a switch line <b>34</b> that also controls a switch <b>35</b> to individually apply the correct data from respective latches <b>20</b> to the input of the DAC <b>30</b>. Alternatively, a separate signal may be used to control the input to the DAC <b>30</b>, but there must be synchronization between the selection of a latch <b>20</b> by the switch <b>35</b> and the selection of the optical part <b>14</b> by the switch <b>32</b> so that the intensity data is correctly applied. Namely, the data stored in a given latch <b>20</b> must be applied to a corresponding optical part <b>14</b> (e.g., so that data corresponding to the intensity of red, e.g., is applied to a red optical part). The SW signal is at a higher frequency than the load signal so that data from each of the three latches <b>20</b> in each pixel may be applied to a corresponding optical part <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic diagram of a portion of another exemplary embodiment display <b>34</b> of the invention. Pixels <b>36</b> in the display <b>34</b> use switches <b>32</b> and <b>35</b> to cycle through color phases as in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> embodiment. In the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> embodiment, however, serial shifters <b>38</b> are segregated according to color so that data may be serially shifted in parallel. For a three color display, as in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> example, the number of cycles for the GCLK signal to load an entire data set (for example a row) is a third of that required for the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> embodiments because of the separate RDATA, GDATA, and BDATA channels. Otherwise, however, the loading and latching occurs in the same fashion as in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows yet another embodiment display <b>40</b>. The <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> embodiment includes parallel data shifting as in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> embodiment. However, it includes a DAC for each optical part <b>14</b> in pixels <b>42</b>, in like fashion to the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> embodiment. Like parts of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> are labeled with the common reference numbers from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 3</figref>. The display <b>40</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> achieves the parallel loading of data sets for different colors into the serial shifters <b>38</b>, while also achieving the simultaneous driving of different colored optical parts, each of which has a corresponding DAC <b>24</b>. The <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> embodiment accordingly achieves the one third savings (compared to the embodiments of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>) in the number of the GLCK signal to load an entire data set, as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The display <b>40</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> also achieves the parallel driving of optical parts corresponding to different colors provided by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, obviating the need to multiplex the DAC output as is done with the color switches in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Artisans making use of the invention will accordingly appreciate that the features of the exemplary embodiments may be selected and combined to achieve a particular design goal. The various features may be adapted to minimize the number of circuits used, to maximize the speed of the display, or to achieve a metric that balances both.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flow chart depicting the steps of an exemplary method of the invention, applicable to the exemplary embodiment displays. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the digital data is shifted serially (step <b>50</b>) into respective serial shifters. In the case of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, each data set loaded includes data for multiple color channels, while application of the method to the displays of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> has data being shifted serially on separate color lines. When data shifting has been completed, a GLD signal is applied (step <b>52</b>). Application of the GLD signal causes the data in the serial registers to latch (step <b>54</b>) and simultaneously, the previous data set from the latches is applied to the DAC (step <b>56</b>). The application to the DAC will involve switching, in the case of the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> embodiments, as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">While specific embodiments of the present invention have been shown and described, it should be understood that other modifications, substitutions and alternatives are apparent to one of ordinary skill in the art. Such modifications, substitutions and alternatives can be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention, which should be determined from the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Various features of the invention are set forth in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A display device comprising a plurality of pixels, each pixel in the display comprising:
<claim-text>a serial shifter that accepts a serial bit stream and has an n-bit wide output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an n-bit wide data latch that latches data received from the output of the serial shifter; wherein each pixel comprises:
<claim-text>a plurality of optical parts;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data latch corresponding to each optical part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a digital to analog converter for each of said plurality of optical parts to which output of the respective data latch is applied, wherein each optical part is driven by the digital to analog converter; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a serial shifter corresponding to each optical part.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said serial shifters in each pixel are arranged to receive data in parallel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein groups in the plurality of pixels comprise interconnected serial shifters to serially receive a data set.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, further comprising a global clock line to control shifting of data through interconnected serial shifters of groups of pixels in the plurality of pixels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising a global load line to control latching of data by data latches in the plurality of pixels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said optical part comprises a light emitter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said light emitter comprises a light emitting diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said light emitter comprises an organic light emitting diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said optical part comprises a reflector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said reflector comprises a digital micro-mirror.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein said reflector comprises a diffractive light device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein outputs of data latches in the plurality of pixels are applied simultaneously to their analog to digital converters in accordance with a global load signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A display device comprising a plurality of pixels, each pixel in the display comprising:
<claim-text>a serial shifter that accepts a serial bit stream and has an n-bit wide output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an n-bit wide data latch that latches data received from the output of the serial shifter;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a digital to analog converter to which output of the data latch is applied; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an optical part driven by the digital to analog converter, wherein each pixel includes a plurality of optical parts, and wherein each pixel comprises:
<claim-text>a serial shifter corresponding to each optical part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data latch corresponding to each optical part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a single digital to analog converter;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first switch to selectively and individually apply the output of the pixel's data latches to the single digital to analog converter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second switch to selectively and individually apply the output of the single analog to digital converter to the plurality of optical parts.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The display device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein serial shifters in each pixel are arranged to receive data in parallel.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
