<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298153-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298153</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11137187</doc-number>
<date>20050525</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324754</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Eccentric offset Kelvin probe</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4659987</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Coe et al.</name>
<date>19870400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324754</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4721903</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Harsch et al.</name>
<date>19880100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5416428</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Swart</name>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5557213</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Reuter et al.</name>
<date>19960900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324761</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5781023</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Swart et al.</name>
<date>19980700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324761</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6097196</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Verkuil et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6225817</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Sayre et al.</name>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324754</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6384614</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hager et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6400166</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Babson et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6447328</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Feldman</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6570399</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Yeghiayan et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324761</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6685492</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Winter et al.</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439219</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6768327</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Felici et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324754</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6831452</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>McTigue</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324 725</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>4</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324754</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324765</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3241581</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324761-762</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324760</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060267601</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061130</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Farris</last-name>
<first-name>Jason W.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Parkville</city>
<state>MO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Thurston</last-name>
<first-name>William E.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kansas City</city>
<state>MO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Pepper Hamilton LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Interconnect Devices, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>St. Davids</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Ha Tran</first-name>
<department>2829</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Tung X.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An eccentric offset Kelvin probe with a beveled contact tip radially offset from the longitudinal axis of the probe which provides a reduced tip spacing between adjacent pairs of probes.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="59.86mm" wi="147.66mm" file="US07298153-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="243.50mm" wi="154.18mm" file="US07298153-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to contact probes and, more particularly, to Kelvin probes for testing the resistance between two points of a device under test.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">As electronic devices become smaller and smaller it becomes increasingly difficult to automatically test a device with test probes. Probes may be miniaturized to the same scale as the device under test in order to contact the device leads. However, it is often difficult to produce a reliable probe that can withstand the rigors of use in an automated test fixture. Very small test probes have a limited spring force and thus may not adequately penetrate the oxide layer of a device under test to make a good electrical connection. A good electrical contact is especially important for Kelvin probes which test the resistance between two points on a device under test.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In the specific application of testing low resistance or precision components such as power devices, precision resistors and sensitive analog amplifiers, the contact resistance of the probe itself can interfere with the measurement. In these situations, it is conventional to use a technique referred to as either Kelvin measurement or four point measurements. This technique requires that two independent probes contact the same pad, which means the effective pitch between probes must be half that of the pads they are contacting. This places a significant challenge on the probing technology.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The present invention provides a Kelvin probe which includes a barrel, a plunger, which is biased outwardly from one end of the barrel by a spring, and a contact with a needle extending from the other end of the barrel. The needle has an eccentric shaft extending from the contact and an offset beveled tip.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an enlarged cross sectional view of a probe of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an enlarged plan view of the contact end of the probe of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is the contact end of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> rotated ninety degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a right end view of the contact end of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a pair of probes of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a probe of the present invention is generally indicated by reference numeral <b>10</b>. Probe <b>10</b> includes a barrel <b>12</b>, a spring <b>14</b>, a plunger <b>16</b>, a contact <b>18</b> and a needle <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Barrel <b>12</b> provides a housing for spring <b>14</b> and guides the plunger <b>16</b>. Probe <b>10</b> is an interposer housed in a socket without a receptacle. Barrel <b>12</b> may include a crimp <b>22</b> at one end to retain a tail <b>24</b> of plunger <b>16</b>, and a crimp <b>26</b> near the opposite end to secure contact <b>18</b>, for example. It should be understood that other methods of retaining the plunger <b>16</b> and contact <b>18</b> may be used. The contact <b>18</b> and needle <b>20</b> may be a one-piece design machined or cast from a single piece of material and inserted into the end of a barrel, or the barrel <b>12</b>, contact <b>18</b>, and needle <b>20</b> may be a one-piece design from a solid piece of cylindrical stock material back drilled to form the barrel <b>18</b> and with the contact <b>18</b> and needle machined from the other end of the stock material, for example. Although the probe <b>10</b> is illustrated with separate parts assembled together, it should be understood that these parts may be combined or manufactured in many different ways.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The plunger tail <b>24</b> provides a secondary point of electrical contact between the plunger <b>16</b> and the inside diameter of barrel <b>12</b>. Plunger tail <b>24</b> may include a beveled contact end <b>28</b> which translates the axial spring force of spring <b>14</b> into a lateral force to urge the plunger tail <b>24</b> against the inside diameter of the barrel <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Barrel <b>12</b> may be made of gold plated phosphor bronze, a copper, nickel or zinc alloy, or other appropriate material, and may be made in a wide variety of lengths and diameters. For example, the barrel <b>12</b> may range in size from 2.54 mm or less in length with an outside diameter of 0.39 mm or less to more than 7 cm long with an outside diameter of 6.35 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Spring <b>14</b> is generally helical to maintain a consistent counterforce to the plunger <b>16</b>. Spring <b>14</b> may be made of gold plated steel with a spring force determined by the application. Plunger <b>16</b> may be made of beryllium copper, tool steel or stainless steel, for example, and plated with gold or nickel.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2–4</figref>, contact <b>18</b> includes a head <b>30</b> and a neck <b>32</b>. The diameter of head <b>30</b> is generally equal to the outside diameter of barrel <b>12</b>. Neck <b>32</b> is slip fit into the end of barrel <b>12</b> and includes an annular groove <b>34</b>. Crimp <b>26</b> is aligned with the annular groove <b>34</b> to secure contact <b>18</b> in place and to ensure good electrical contact between contact <b>18</b> and barrel <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Head <b>30</b> of contact <b>18</b> includes an axially-aligned groove <b>36</b>, offset from the longitudinal axis of probe <b>10</b>, into which tip <b>20</b> may be press fit. Alternatively, head <b>30</b> may include an axially-aligned aperture (not shown), offset from the longitudinal axis of probe <b>10</b>, into which tip <b>20</b> may be pressed, for example. Additionally, contact <b>18</b> and needle <b>20</b> may be machined or molded as a single element.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 5</figref>, when the tip <b>20</b> is inserted into the groove <b>36</b>, the longitudinal axis of the tip <b>20</b> is offset from the longitudinal axis of the probe <b>10</b>. The contact end <b>38</b> of barrel <b>12</b> extends over the tail <b>40</b> of tip <b>20</b> to secure tip <b>20</b> in place. Tip <b>20</b> includes a beveled end <b>42</b> and contact tip <b>44</b> which is angled toward the outer periphery of the head <b>30</b> and away from the longitudinal axis of the probe <b>10</b>. Tip <b>20</b> may be approximately 0.127 mm in diameter with a longitudinal axis spaced approximately 0.087 mm from the longitudinal axis of the probe <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">When a pair of Kelvin probes <b>10</b> are mounted in a socket (not shown) the center-to-center spacing A of the adjacent probes is approximately 0.5 mm. Plunger tips <b>16</b> separately contact pads <b>46</b> and <b>48</b> on fixture <b>50</b>. The spacing B between the needle tips <b>44</b> of each needle <b>20</b> is approximately 0.1 mm to 0.3 mm or twenty to sixty percent of the center-to-center spacing A, for example. Because of the needles <b>20</b> are offset from the longitudinal axis of the respective probe <b>10</b>, and the ends are beveled <b>42</b>, the needle tips <b>44</b> of adjacent probes <b>10</b> may contact the same pad <b>52</b> on the device under test <b>54</b>. Pad <b>52</b> is the same size as pads <b>46</b> and <b>48</b>. Thus, a larger diameter probe with better electrical characteristics than a smaller probe may be used. Additionally, a larger probe may last longer and include a stronger spring to ensure adequate contact with the device under test.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In the use of Kelvin probing, two independent probes make contact to the same pad. Two pairs of probes are used to measure the resistance between two pads on a device under test. This technique eliminates the series resistance of the probes and any contact resistances of the tips to the pads. It is a precision measurement of the resistance between the two pads, due to the device that is connected.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In this technique, one of the pair of probes on each pad is selected as the current force. A controlled amount of current I, is forced through the two pads, typically ranging from 1 mA to 1 A, using either a constant current power supply, or just a constant voltage supply and measuring the current. If the contact resistance changes, the current will either be kept constant, or the change in current measured.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The second probe on each pad is used to measure the voltage drop, V, between the two pads. Since this is a high impedance measurement, there is little current flowing through the probes and the measured voltage is unaffected by the probe contact resistance. By independently measuring the current through the pads and the voltage across them, the resistance between the pads can be measured as V/I, independent of the probe resistance or contact resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">However, this technique requires two independent probes to contact each pad, which requires a tighter pitch than if only 1 probe were to contact each pad. This tighter pitch is accomplished by the close tip spacing B of the probes <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">It is to be understood that while certain forms of this invention have been illustrated and described, is it not limited thereto except insofar as such limitations are included in the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An assembly for testing of electrical components, said assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a pair of spaced apart Kelvin probes, each of said Kelvin probes comprising:
<claim-text>a plunger having a tip and an end portion opposite said tip,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a barrel for receiving said end portion of said plunger for movement of said plunger along a first longitudinal axis between an extended position where said tip projects from said barrel and a retracted position where said tip partially retracts within said barrel,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a spring within said barrel for biasing said plunger outwardly from said barrel, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a contact having a base and a needle extending from said base,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said base secured within said barrel opposite said plunger,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said needle having a second longitudinal axis generally parallel to said first longitudinal axis, and a beveled tip, and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a socket for receiving said pair of Kelvin probes and securing said Kelvin probes whereas said first longitudinal axes of said pair of Kelvin probes are generally parallel,</claim-text>
<claim-text>whereas the distance between said beveled tips is less than the distance between said plunger tips of said pair of Kelvin probes.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The assembly as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said beveled tip is angled away from said first longitudinal axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The assembly as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the distance between said beveled tips is approximately twenty to sixty percent of the distance between said plunger tips.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The assembly as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the distance between said beveled tips is approximately 0.1 millimeter to 0.3 millimeter.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
