<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296828-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296828</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11099319</doc-number>
<date>20050405</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>0407858.0</doc-number>
<date>20040407</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>358</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>59</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>289  2</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Double knotting system for an agricultural baler</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3101963</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sullivan et al.</name>
<date>19630800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>289 11</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3400959</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Grillot</name>
<date>19680900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>289  2</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4074623</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>White</name>
<date>19780200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>100  3</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4108062</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>White</name>
<date>19780800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>100 11</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4142746</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>White</name>
<date>19790300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>289  2</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4196661</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yatcilla et al.</name>
<date>19800400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>100  4</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4765235</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schrag et al.</name>
<date>19880800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>100  3</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>289  2</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>100  8</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>19</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060012176</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060119</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Schoonheere</last-name>
<first-name>Marnix J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Ichtegem</city>
<country>BE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>BE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>BE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Naeyaert</last-name>
<first-name>Karel</first-name>
<address>
<city>Zedelgem</city>
<country>BE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>BE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>BE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ryse</last-name>
<first-name>Johan A. E. Vande</first-name>
<address>
<city>Bruges</city>
<country>BE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>BE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>BE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sheldrake</last-name>
<first-name>Patrick M.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Stader</last-name>
<first-name>John William</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Harms</last-name>
<first-name>Michael G.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>CNH America LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>New Holland</city>
<state>PA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hurley</last-name>
<first-name>Shaun R.</first-name>
<department>3765</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A double knotting method and apparatus capable of producing two successive knots in a pair of strands during one full operating cycle of a tying mechanism. The tying mechanism is comprised of a twine holder for maintaining a pair of strands in a suitable position, a cutter that co-operates with the twine holder for severing the strands during formation of successive knots, and a release mechanism for releasing the pair of strands from the twine holder before frill successive knot completion. The method and apparatus avoid twine tail formation.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="157.99mm" wi="141.22mm" file="US07296828-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="162.48mm" wi="141.73mm" file="US07296828-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="175.68mm" wi="168.74mm" file="US07296828-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="224.96mm" wi="147.91mm" file="US07296828-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="228.85mm" wi="169.76mm" file="US07296828-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="217.59mm" wi="160.27mm" file="US07296828-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="148.34mm" wi="84.41mm" file="US07296828-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to agricultural balers and, more particularly, to a baler for forming rectangular bales having a bale knotting system using twine to bind the bales.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Rectangular bales conventionally are able to maintain their shape by means of a series of parallel extending twine loops, provided lengthways around the bales. Agricultural balers, utilizing automatic knotters by which two conventional knots are made on every loop for binding a bale, have been available for many years. U.S. Pat. No. 4,142,746, for example, discloses a tying mechanism of the conventional double knotter type. Such a tying mechanism is a complex gathering of elements such as a bill hook for forming the knot, a holder in combination with a retainer for retaining the strands when forming the knot and an arm with an integrated cutter for stripping the formed knot from the bill hook in combination with the separation of the knot from the retained strands. When a bale reaches its desired length, a knot tying cycle is initiated. During this tying cycle, two knots are formed, the first knot for closing the loop of the finished bale and the second knot for starting the loop for the next bale.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In use, such conventional knotters, while being effective in binding bales with twine, result in small pieces of twine, commonly known as twine tails, being wasted after each knotting operation. These twine tails are obtained after the second knot is formed and stripped of the bill hook by a moving stripper arm. In conventional knotters, a stripper arm with an integrated cutter is used to strip the knot from the billhook. At the same time, the cutter will cut the strands that are retained by the holder. In contrast with the forming of the second knot, no twine tails will be obtained when forming the first knot, since the strands are at that point still retained by the holder and needed for forming the second knot. The first knot is merely cut loose from the strands and dropped onto the finished bale.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Although the amount of twine wasted is not great, as the twine tails are approximately only 3 to 5 cm long, they may build up in the vicinity of the knotter and ultimately cause knotter-tying problems. In some situations the twine tails are removed from the baler when the formed bale is pushed out of the baler, then the twine tails drop on the field where they may cause or contribute to environmental pollution. Indeed, nowadays farmers often use synthetic twine instead of natural fibers. Unlike natural fibers, synthetic twine will not be broken down by atmospheric influences, and therefore, the synthetic twine tails remains longer on the field and may be picked up the next harvesting season by a baler. Eventually, the twine tails will end up in the entrails of life-stock, where they may cause digesting problems or even poisoning as a result of the chemical coloring agents contained therein. Some crops that are used for industrial processes must be prevented from being polluted with synthetic twine tails lest the harvested bale would be worthless and could not be used for further processing.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">To attenuate the above disadvantages of the presence of twine tails, U.S. Pat. No. 4,805,391 discloses a system to collect the twine tails. A suction fan, connected on one side by hoses to intake units, and on the other side to a container, conveys twine tails from the knotters to the container. Such a collecting system suffers from the disadvantage that sometimes twine tails escape the action of the fan because insufficient suction power is available. The above described problems of twine tails ending up on the field or hampering the operation of the knotter system, thus still remain. Another disadvantage of this system is the necessity of providing an extra device that moreover needs to be powered to collect the twine tails. Since baler knotters are very complex devices, with a high number of elements rotating and moving in different planes, there is little or no space available for such a device in the area of the knotter.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Apart from double knotter systems forming two knots on a single loop, it has been known for many years how to close a loop around a finished bale with a single knot. The biggest disadvantage of a loop formed with one knot at the end of the baling process is that relatively high forces are applied to the twine when the bale is formed. Single knotter systems indeed require the twine to be pulled through the baling chamber and around the formed bale in order to be able to close the loop. The higher forces on the twine increase the danger of twine failure or the occurrence of misshapen knots.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">On the other hand, single knotter systems have the advantage that various types of knotters may be employed, one of which being the conventional knotter already referred to in connection with the double knotter system and producing the twine tails as already explained. Moreover, another type of knotter suitable for a single knotter system is the so-called loop-knotter, producing a small loop on top of the knot. Since loop-knotters operate according to a tying principle which is different from conventional knotters, no twine tails are generated during formation of a knot. The positioning of a loop-knotter relative to the formed bale is such that the bale will pull the formed knot from the bill hook when the knot is made, cutting the formed knot loose from the remaining strand. The retained strand is then used for forming the next loop around the next forming bale.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">To avoid the formation of twine tails, loop knotters unfortunately cannot readily replace the conventional knotters of a double knotter system, as the operating principle of a double knotter system cannot merely be regarded as a duplication of a single knotter system. When the two knots are formed with a conventional knotter, the bale in the baling chamber remains stationary. This means that no pulling action from the formed bale on the knot can be achieved. So pulling the knot from the bill hook as is done with a single loop-knotter is not possible.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Thus, it is a primary object of the present invention to provide a tying mechanism in the form of a double knotter system solving the above described problems by not producing any twine tails at all.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">It is another object of the present invention to provide a double knotter system for an agricultural baler.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Another object of the present invention is to provide a double knotter system that is durable of construction, relatively easy to manufacture and assemble, and reliable in operation.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">These and other objects are attained by providing a tying mechanism for an agricultural baler, operable to produce two successive knots in a pair of twine strands during one full operating cycle of the tying mechanism. No twine tails will be formed, preventing knotter problems occurring during the baling process. Also environmental pollution will be prevented since no twine tails will be removed from the baler.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The advantages of this invention will be apparent upon consideration of the following detailed disclosure of the invention, especially when taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a fragmentary, side elevational view of a baler having a double knotter tying mechanism;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagrammatic view of a complete and a partial double-knotted loop as known from the prior art;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a diagrammatic view of a complete and a partial double-knotted loop without the forming of twine tails <b>62</b>′ and <b>64</b>′ as seen on <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an enlarged, fragmentary, side elevational view of the knotter, needle and associated mechanism in mid cycle;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a fragmentary, plan view taken substantially along line <b>4</b>-<b>4</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a fragmentary, front perspective view of the knotter with strands of twine draped across the bill hook and held by retaining discs in readiness of preparing a knot;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a fragmentary, elevational view of cams on a drive shaft of the knotter for operating a slack take-up arm and a twine finger;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 to 17</figref> are fragmentary, schematic views illustrating the successive steps of a double-knotting operation;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref> is an enlarged, front elevational view of the tip of a needle which presents the strands to the knotter, illustrating details of the construction thereof; and</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref> is an enlarged view of the bill hook which forms the knot by turning around its lengthways axis, illustrating details of construction thereof.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In the description which follows and in certain passages already set forth, the principles of the present invention will be described in terms of “twine” and “knots” formed in such twine. However, it is to be recognized that such principles extend to wire and twisted junctions of wire as well as twine and knots.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Many of the fastening, connection, processes and other means and components utilized in this invention are widely known and used in the field of the invention described, and their exact nature or type is not necessary for an understanding and use of the invention by a person skilled in the art, and they will not therefore be discussed in significant detail. Also, any reference herein to the terms “left” or “right” are used as a matter of mere convenience, and are determined by standing at the rear of the machine facing in its normal direction of travel. Furthermore, the various components shown or described herein for any specific application of this invention can be varied or altered as anticipated by this invention and the practice of a specific application of any element may already by widely known or used in the art by persons skilled in the art and each will likewise not therefore be discussed in significant detail.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The baler <b>20</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> has a rectangular bale case <b>22</b> that is supported by ground wheels <b>24</b>. The bale case <b>22</b> defines a bale chamber <b>26</b> wherein material is pushed though a curved duct <b>28</b>. A plunger <b>30</b> reciprocates within the bale case <b>22</b> to intermittently pack fresh charges of material from the duct <b>28</b> rearwardly in the chamber <b>26</b> in the direction of the arrow <b>32</b>. When the bales reaches a predetermined size (this is determined by an appropriate bale length sensor (not shown)), a trigger <b>34</b> is pulled by a rod <b>36</b>. This rod <b>36</b> engages a dog clutch <b>38</b>, the clutch <b>38</b> in turn being connected to a tying mechanism and a set of needles <b>42</b>. As will be appreciated, the tying mechanism comprises a set of individual knotters <b>40</b> provided crosswise on top of the bale chamber <b>26</b> at spaced intervals. Each knotter <b>40</b> has an associated needle <b>42</b> for assisting in forming an individual loop around a finished bale. When the bales needs tying, the dog clutch <b>38</b> connects the knotter <b>40</b> and their needles <b>42</b> via a drive chain <b>44</b> to a source of driving power to initiate the tying operation. As the individual knotters <b>40</b> all operate in an identical manner, it suffices to describe the present invention in relation to only one such knotter <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The needle <b>42</b> is swingably mounted on the bale case <b>22</b> by a pivot <b>46</b> and is swung back and forth across the bale chamber <b>26</b> by a linkage <b>48</b>, which is activated by the clutch <b>38</b>. The needle <b>42</b> has an “at-home” or rest position fully below the bale case <b>22</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and a “full-throw” position extending completely across the bale case <b>22</b> as illustrated, for example, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. As illustrated perhaps most clearly in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 18</figref>, the tip <b>50</b> of needle <b>42</b> has an eyelet <b>52</b> defined therein by the opposed furcations <b>54</b> and <b>56</b> of the bifurcated tip <b>50</b> in conjunction with a pair of longitudinally spaced, transversely extending rollers <b>58</b> and <b>60</b>. It will be noted that the roller <b>58</b> is positioned inwardly from the outer extremity of the tip <b>50</b>, while the roller <b>60</b> is positioned outwardly from the roller <b>58</b> more closely adjacent this extremity. Even so, the roller <b>60</b> is positioned a short distance inwardly from the outer extremity of the tip <b>50</b>, and both of the rollers <b>58</b> and <b>60</b> may be tapered toward their mid points, comparable to a diabolo, so as to provide secure seats for the tying strands.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the binding loop as already known for many years in the prior art. It is also shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> that twine tails <b>62</b>′ and <b>64</b>′ are obtained between the last knot <b>70</b> of a first bale and the first knot <b>68</b><i>a </i>of a next bale. As clearly seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, both knots <b>70</b> and <b>68</b><i>a </i>are identical to each other and are so-called conventional knots.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In contrast therewith, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the binding loop without twine tails <b>62</b>′ and <b>64</b>′, as obtained by the present invention. In a finished bale, and still comparable to the prior art, the loop <b>62</b> is made from two strands of binding material, i.e., one strand <b>64</b> along the top side of the bale and a second strand <b>66</b> along the bottom side of the bale and its two opposite, vertical ends. The strands <b>64</b> and <b>66</b> together form the continuous loop <b>62</b>. Together, they fully circumscribe the bale and are circumferential complements of one another. However, in contrast with the prior art, the first knot <b>68</b> of a bale according to the present invention, is a so called loop-knot. This means that the ends of the strands <b>64</b> and <b>66</b> of the knot <b>68</b> are released from a retained position so they can be pulled back by the movement of an arm <b>88</b> (to be described further) to form a small loop on top of the knot. The knot <b>68</b> itself, thus holds the ends of the strands <b>64</b> and <b>66</b>, united with the knot <b>68</b> in contrast with a conventional knot in which the ends are cut off by a cutter <b>94</b> only a short distance from the knot. These ends are then pulled completely through the formed knot, thus forming a conventional knot as known for many years in the prior art (to be described later). As such, twine ends <b>62</b>′ and <b>64</b>′ are obtained, since these twine ends <b>62</b>′ and <b>64</b>′ are retained by the holder <b>86</b> when the cutter <b>94</b> passes. The two knots <b>68</b> and <b>70</b> appear in the loop <b>62</b> at those locations where the strands <b>64</b> and <b>66</b> are substantially end-to-end. This is typically in the area of the top corners of the bale.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, to the left of loop <b>62</b> is a partial loop <b>62</b><i>a </i>which is in the process of being formed. The top strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>emanates from a source of twine supply <b>72</b>, while the bottom strand <b>66</b><i>a </i>emanates from an entirely separate, second source of twine supply <b>74</b>. At the particular point in the sequence chosen for illustration, the knot <b>68</b><i>a </i>is in existence, and the bale is approaching that length where the needle <b>42</b> is ready to swing into operation and present the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>to the knotter <b>40</b> to complete the first knot <b>70</b><i>a </i>(not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">With this short explanation in mind, the details of the embodiment according to the present invention and as illustrated primarily in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref>, <b>5</b>, <b>6</b> and <b>7</b> will now be described. The knotter <b>40</b> is identical in many respects to a “Deering” type knotter available from P. D. Rasspe Sohne, Hamburg, Germany. That is to say, the components of the knotter <b>40</b> which co-operate to form each of the knots of a bale may have a great resemblance to those in a unit provided by the Rasspe Company.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">As such, the knotter <b>40</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> comprises a generally circular element <b>76</b> that is secured to a drive shaft <b>78</b> for rotation with the latter through one full revolution when the clutch <b>38</b> is engaged. The shaft <b>78</b> is supported by a forwardly inclined frame <b>80</b> attached to the top of the bale case <b>22</b>, and the frame <b>80</b> also supports the knotter components for forming the knots in response to rotation of the element <b>76</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Briefly, such components include a rotary bill hook member <b>82</b>, supported by the frame <b>80</b> for rotation about an inclined axis <b>84</b>; a multi-disc holder <b>86</b> rearwardly of and adjacent to the bill hook <b>82</b> for holding strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>in position for engagement by the bill hook <b>82</b> during rotation of the latter; and means for releasing the connected strands from the holder <b>86</b> in the form of an arm <b>88</b> pivotally attached to the frame <b>80</b> by a bolt <b>90</b>. It is to be noted that the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>are held between notches in the rotating multi-disc holder <b>86</b> and a retainer <b>220</b>. The tensioning force of this retainer <b>220</b> to the holder <b>86</b> can be adjusted manually by changing the tension of a leaf-spring <b>200</b> when a bolt <b>210</b> is loosened or tightened. The lower end of the arm <b>88</b> is forked, defining a crotch <b>92</b> that opens away from the holder <b>86</b> beneath the bill hook <b>82</b>. The crotch <b>92</b> carries a cutter <b>94</b> between the bill hook <b>82</b> and the holder <b>86</b> for severing the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>in response to swinging movement of the arm <b>88</b> in the proper direction. Such movement of the arm <b>88</b> to operate the cutter <b>94</b> also serves to bring the proximal areas of the crotch <b>92</b> in engagement with a knot formed on the bill hook <b>82</b> for stripping such knot off of the bill hook <b>82</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In order to transmit driving power from the element <b>76</b> to the bill hook <b>82</b>, the latter is provided with a gear <b>96</b> which is disposed for meshing engagement with a pair of circumferentially spaced gear stretches <b>98</b> and <b>100</b> on the element <b>76</b>. Similarly, driving power is transmitted to the discs of the holder <b>86</b> through a worm gear drive <b>102</b> and a bevel gear <b>104</b> in position for sequential meshing engagement with a pair of circumferentially spaced gear sections <b>106</b> and <b>108</b> on the element <b>76</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In contrast with a typical “Deering” type knotter, a supplementary gear section <b>109</b> is provided after gear section <b>108</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) for a purpose to be described further on. Power to swing the arm <b>88</b> about the pivot bolt <b>90</b> is obtained through a cam follower <b>110</b> at the upper end of the arm <b>88</b> beyond the pivot bolt <b>90</b> which is disposed within a cam track <b>112</b> on the element <b>76</b>. A pair of circumferentially spaced cam shoulders <b>114</b> and <b>116</b> in the track <b>112</b> are positioned to sequentially engage the follower <b>110</b> to operate the latter.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">A finger <b>118</b> is located below the bill hook <b>82</b> and the crotch <b>92</b> of the knotter <b>40</b> and is mounted on an upright pivot <b>120</b> for lateral swinging movement between a standby position illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> and a full-throw, laterally extended position somewhat beyond that illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. An operating link <b>122</b> attached at one end to the finger <b>118</b> and at the opposite end to a crank <b>124</b> serves to effect swinging of the finger <b>118</b>. The crank <b>124</b> is in turn fixed to a transversely extending shaft <b>126</b> that extends to a point behind the element <b>76</b> where it carries a second crank <b>128</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The crank <b>128</b> is biased upwardly in a counter-clockwise direction by a coil spring <b>130</b> and carries a cam follower <b>132</b> at its outermost end. The follower <b>132</b> is in position for operating engagement with a double-lobed cam <b>134</b> fixed to the shaft <b>78</b> for rotation therewith, its lobes <b>136</b> and <b>138</b> being circumferentially spaced apart in accordance with the desired timed relationship between the finger <b>118</b> and the knot-forming components of the knotter <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Also mounted on the shaft <b>78</b> with the cam <b>134</b> is a second cam <b>140</b> having a peripheral land stretch <b>142</b> over approximately 180° of its circumference and a peripheral valley stretch <b>144</b> over the remaining approximately 180° of its circumference. Such stretches <b>142</b> and <b>144</b> are disposed for operating engagement with a cam roller <b>146</b> located at the outer end of a lever <b>148</b> that is fixed at its inner end to a transverse shaft <b>150</b>. The lever <b>148</b>, and hence the shaft <b>150</b>, are biased in a counter-clockwise direction viewing <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> by a coil spring <b>152</b>. The shaft <b>150</b> extends back out to the opposite side of the element <b>76</b> parallel with the shafts <b>78</b> and <b>126</b> to a point substantially in fore-and-aft alignment with the bill hook <b>82</b>. At that location, the shaft <b>150</b> fixedly carries a rearwardly extending slack take-up device <b>154</b>. The device <b>154</b> carries a pair of spaced rollers <b>156</b> and <b>158</b> at its rearmost end around which the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>is entrained as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. A length of the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>is also looped upwardly around another roller <b>160</b> disposed above the device <b>154</b> and carried by the knotter frame <b>80</b> adjacent the drive shaft <b>78</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>may be clamped between a pair of opposed plates <b>162</b> and <b>164</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) of a tensioning unit <b>166</b>. The force with which the plates <b>162</b> and <b>164</b> clamp the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>may be controlled by a wing nut <b>168</b> operating against a spring <b>170</b> that in turn presses against the movable plate <b>164</b>. A tensioning unit similar to unit <b>166</b> may also be provided for the strand <b>66</b><i>a</i>, although such additional unit is not illustrated.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The condition of the partial loop <b>62</b><i>a </i>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, and that of the knotter <b>40</b> and the needle <b>42</b>, corresponds substantially with conditions illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref>, <b>5</b> and <b>8</b>, with the exception that in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the needle <b>42</b> is still in its home position. At this point in the bale forming operation, the bale has reached its desired length and it is time to complete the loop around the bale and make the second knot in the loop. It is remarked that at this specific instance, the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>stretches along the top of the bale directly beneath the crotch <b>92</b> of the arm <b>88</b> but, at least for all effective purposes, is out of contact with the knotter <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, as the needle <b>42</b> swings upwardly toward the knotter <b>40</b>, it carries with it the strand <b>66</b><i>a </i>as the latter is paid out by source <b>74</b>. Note that because the strand <b>66</b><i>a </i>is threaded through the eyelet <b>52</b> of needle <b>42</b>, a length of that strand on the twine source side of the needle <b>42</b> is also carried upwardly toward the knotter <b>40</b>, such extra length being hereinafter denoted <b>66</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">While the needle <b>42</b> approaches the knotter <b>40</b>, no additional length of the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>is pulled from the source <b>72</b>. Even as the trip of the needle <b>42</b>, and more particularly, the roller <b>60</b>, snares the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> and presents strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>in unison to the knotter <b>40</b>, still no additional length of the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>is pulled from source <b>72</b> because the device <b>154</b> rocks upwardly in a counter-clockwise direction to provide the slack necessary in the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>to accommodate the needle movement. In presenting the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a</i>, the needle actually drapes the strands across the bill hook <b>82</b> and thence into awaiting notches of the holder <b>86</b>, whereupon rotation of co-operating discs in the latter, in combination with a pressing retainer <b>220</b>, serve to firmly grip the strands and prevent their escape as the bill hook <b>82</b> begins its rotation as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>. When the needle <b>42</b> delivers the strands <b>64</b> and <b>66</b> to the holder <b>86</b>, the holder <b>86</b> rotates in such a manner that the strands <b>64</b> and <b>66</b> are retained twice in different notches in the holder <b>86</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>). By doing so, two knots <b>70</b><i>a </i>and <b>68</b><i>b </i>can be formed during one knotting cycle as will be explained further, whereby the cutter <b>94</b> severs the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>from the strands <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b </i>after the first knot <b>70</b> is formed, and thus separating the two loops <b>62</b><i>a </i>and <b>62</b><i>b </i>(not shown) from each other. The adjustable leaf-spring <b>200</b> pushes against the retainer <b>220</b>, thus co-operating with the discs in the holder <b>86</b> to retain the strands.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">When starting the formation of the first knot <b>70</b>, the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>are draped across the bill hook <b>82</b>, thereby closing the two lips <b>83</b><i>a </i>and <b>83</b><i>b </i>(<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref>) of the bill hook <b>82</b> because of the pressure of the strands on the upper lip <b>83</b><i>a</i>. Unlike with a typical “Deering” type knotter, the two lips <b>83</b><i>a </i>and <b>83</b><i>b </i>are normally opened, unless they are closed by the strands when they are draped across the bill hook <b>82</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">While the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>are being delivered across the bill hook <b>82</b> to the holder <b>86</b>, the finger <b>118</b> is actuated to swing inwardly and engage at least the strand <b>66</b><i>a </i>as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9 and 10</figref> for the purpose of seating the same deeply within the crotch <b>92</b> so as to assure that the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>are both in proper position across the bill hook <b>82</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">When the bill hook <b>82</b> rotates around its axis <b>84</b>, a cam follower <b>85</b>, which is connected to the upper lip <b>83</b><i>a</i>, engages an element having a cam shoulder (not shown). When rotating, the cam follower will push the upper lip <b>83</b><i>a </i>away from the lower lip <b>83</b><i>b</i>, thus enabling the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>to enter in between the two lips <b>83</b><i>a </i>and <b>83</b><i>b </i>while the bill hook is rotated.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The foregoing described movement on the part of the bill hook <b>82</b> and the holder <b>86</b> are, of course, brought about by operable inter-engagement of the gear stretch <b>98</b> and gear section <b>106</b> on the element <b>76</b> with their respective gears <b>96</b> and <b>104</b> on the bill hook <b>82</b> and the holder <b>86</b>. Such driving inter-engagement continues until a knot has been formed on the bill hook <b>82</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11 and 12</figref>, by which time the needle <b>42</b> has begun to withdraw. At this point, the cam shoulder <b>114</b> of the element <b>76</b> comes into engagement with the roller <b>110</b> of the arm <b>88</b> so as to swing the bottom of the latter, and hence the cutter <b>94</b>, across that portion of the strands between the bill hook <b>82</b> and the holder <b>86</b>, thereby severing the same as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>. The cutter <b>94</b> will move along the retained strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a</i>, and hence cutting these strands loose from the strands <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b</i>. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, it will be seen that at the moment of cutting, the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>extend from in between the lips <b>83</b><i>a </i>and <b>83</b><i>b </i>towards the holder <b>86</b>. On account of the further rotation of the bill hook <b>82</b>, the lips <b>83</b><i>a </i>and <b>83</b><i>b </i>meanwhile are closed again to clamp the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>64</b><i>b </i>in between. Considering that the cutter <b>94</b> moves very closely alongside the bill hook <b>82</b>, the free ends of the cut strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>extend only over a very short distance out of the lips <b>83</b><i>a </i>and <b>83</b><i>b</i>. To complete the knot formation, the arm <b>88</b> engages the strands <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>which are retained in a twisted manner around the bill hook <b>82</b>. In so doing, the strand parts lying on top of the lip <b>83</b><i>a </i>are pulled over the strands parts laying in between the lips <b>83</b><i>a </i>and <b>83</b><i>b</i>, thereby forming the knot. As described above, since the free ends of the strand <b>64</b><i>a </i>and <b>66</b><i>a </i>are very short, they are pulled completely through the knot during its final formation, resulting in the so-called conventional knot <b>70</b><i>a</i>, as best seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>. Besides completing the knot, further motion of the arm <b>88</b> also strips the finished knot <b>70</b><i>a </i>completely from the bill hook <b>82</b> and drops the completed loop on the bale as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">When the knot <b>70</b><i>a </i>is dropped by the knotter <b>40</b> following severance and stripping from the bill hook <b>82</b>, the strand <b>66</b><i>b </i>from source <b>74</b>, as well as strand <b>64</b><i>b </i>from source <b>72</b> is still retained in the second notch of the holder <b>86</b>. At this instance, the upper lip <b>83</b><i>a </i>is open again. Consequently, as the needle <b>42</b> continues to retract, the strand <b>66</b><i>b </i>is draped downwardly across the bale chamber <b>26</b> thereby pushing the tooth <b>83</b><i>a </i>down, while the slack take-up device <b>154</b> lowers to its normal position to pull a small amount of additional twine from the source <b>72</b>. Upon reaching the condition illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>, the strands <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b </i>are in position for initiating the second tying cycle which is started by the finger <b>118</b> (which has been previously returned to its standby position) swinging inwardly to engage the strands <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b </i>and seat them deeply within the crotch <b>92</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>. This assures that the strands <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b </i>are properly positioned across and in engagement with the bill hook <b>82</b>, whereupon the latter and the holder <b>86</b> are operated by their second respective gear stretch <b>100</b> and gear section <b>108</b> on the element <b>76</b>. Thus, the second knot becomes formed as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>, whereupon the arm <b>88</b> is once again actuated, but this time by the second cam shoulder <b>116</b>. When the tension of leaf-spring <b>200</b> is set to a low value, the pressure of the retainer <b>220</b> on the holder <b>86</b> and hence the force that holds the strands fixed within the holder <b>86</b>, will be minimal.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Additionally, the supplementary gear section <b>109</b> provides a prolonged operation of the holder <b>86</b> and will keep the holder <b>86</b> rotating over a longer arc. The strands <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b </i>are no longer retained between the notch in the holder <b>86</b> and the retainer <b>220</b>. Therefore, when the arm <b>88</b> starts its movement for finalizing the knot formation, the cutter <b>94</b> will not be able to effect any cutting action. Indeed, even though the cutter <b>94</b> is very sharp, it will act as a blunt knife and will not be able to cut the strands because instead of holding the strands, the holder <b>86</b> is releasing them on account of the continued rotation of the holder <b>86</b> and the low pressure of the retainer <b>220</b> on the holder <b>86</b>. The strands will therefore just slide over the knife <b>94</b> without being cut, while the arm <b>88</b> continues moving and stripping of the almost completed knot from the bill hook <b>82</b>, thus pulling the strands out of the holder <b>86</b>. This results in the free ends of the strands <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b </i>being considerably longer than the free ends obtained during the first knot formation. As such, upon finalizing the knot, free ends <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b </i>no longer are pulled completely out of the knot, resulting in a so-called loop-knot <b>68</b><i>b</i>, as best seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">This effect may also be realized without the use of a supplementary gear section <b>109</b>. When the tensioning force of the leaf spring <b>200</b> to the retainer <b>220</b> is sufficiently decreased, then the strands will also be pulled out of the holder <b>86</b> by the moving arm <b>88</b>, since they are no longer sufficiently held by the holder <b>86</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">This loop-knot <b>68</b><i>b </i>is the start of a new bight for the next bale. Such bight is in position to receive new material that is packed into the bale chamber <b>26</b> by the plunger <b>30</b>, and the bight grows in length as additional lengths of the strands <b>64</b><i>b </i>and <b>66</b><i>b </i>are simultaneously pulled from their sources <b>72</b> and <b>74</b>. Finally, when the bale has reached its desired size, the sequence returns to its starting point, whereupon the bight is closed by operation of the needle <b>42</b> to complete the loop around the bale and form the other knot.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">From the foregoing, it will be appreciated that the formation of twine tails <b>62</b>′ and <b>64</b>′, as seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, and as described in U.S. Pat. No. 4,142,746 was inherent only to the formation of a first knot for the next bale (or otherwise said, the second knot obtained during a full cycle of the knotter). In accordance with the present invention, by releasing the strands from the holder <b>86</b> before they can become cut during the formation of the second knot in the double-knotter cycle, the generation of twine tails <b>62</b>′ and <b>64</b>′ is avoided.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">As already explained, two complete tying cycles are carried out during each single revolution of the drive shaft <b>78</b>. Thus, each time the needle <b>42</b> swings into operation, two different types of knots are formed by the same knotter <b>40</b>. The first formed knot is a conventional knot <b>70</b> which fully doses the loop of one bale, and the second formed knot is a loop-knot <b>68</b> on the next succeeding bale. The cutter <b>94</b> only operates to sever the two knots from one another, thereby also disconnecting the two bales from each other.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>Having thus described the invention, what is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A tying mechanism for a baler, operable to produce two successive knots in a pair of strands during one full operating cycle of the tying mechanism;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the tying mechanism comprising:
<claim-text>a twine holder for maintaining said pair of strands in a suitable position throughout the complete formation of a first one of said two successive knots and to continue to maintain said pair of strands in a suitable position during the initial stage of the formation of a second one of said successive knots;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cutter co-operating with said twine holder for severing said pair of strands during formation of said first one of said two successive knots;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a releasing mechanism to release said pair of strands from said twine holder before full completion of said second one of said two successive knots, wherein said releasing mechanism is operable to release tension on said pair of strands immediately before the cutter begins to sever said pair of strands during formation of said second one of said two successive knots; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a drive system to provide power and control to said twine holder, said drive system being operable to rotate said twine holder during formation of said second one of said two successive knots to a position for releasing said pair of strands.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The tying mechanism is of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the tension remaining on said pair of strands after release by said releasing mechanism is insufficient for said cutter to effect a cutting action.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The tying mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said releasing mechanism comprises a part of said drive system.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The tying mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said drive mechanism comprises first and second gear sections provided on a circular element for controlling motion of said twine holder during the formation of said respective two successive knots;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said releasing mechanism being formed by a supplementary gear section provided on said circular element for timely engagement after operation of said first and second gear sections.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The tying mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further including:
<claim-text>a retainer co-operating with said twine holder to exert a selectable tension on said pair of strands;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said releasing mechanism further being operable to diminish the co-operating action between said retainer and said twine holder.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The tying mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said two successive knots are not the same type of knot.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The tying mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>at least one of said two successive knots is a loop-knot.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The tying mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first one of said two successive knots is a conventional knot, and said second one of said two successive knots is a loop-knot.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The tying mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first one of said two successive knots is a conventional knot, and said second one of said two successive knots is a loop-knot.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method for producing two successive knots in a pair of strands during one full operating cycle of a tying mechanism; the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>placing said pair of stands under tension by providing a twine holder with a leaf-spring for gripping said pair of twines, said leaf-spring held in place by a bolt;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first one of said two successive knots;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cutting said first one of said two successive knots loose from said pair of strands;</claim-text>
<claim-text>partially forming a second one of said two successive knots;</claim-text>
<claim-text>before completing the formation of said second one of said two successive knots, releasing said pair of strands from a twine holder, wherein said releasing step further comprises the step of releasing said bolt to reduce the tension in said pair of strands.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said step of releasing said pair of strands from said twine holder further comprises the step of moving said twine holder to a position for releasing said pair of strands.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
