<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298211-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298211</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11144856</doc-number>
<date>20050603</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-167382</doc-number>
<date>20040604</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>163</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330267</main-classification>
<further-classification>330261</further-classification>
<further-classification>330271</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Power amplifying apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5229721</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Stade</name>
<date>19930700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330265</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5467058</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fujita</name>
<date>19951100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330267</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6396933</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Jung et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330207 A</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2 073 524</doc-number>
<date>19811000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>08-097645</doc-number>
<date>19960400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-060451</doc-number>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>8</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330255</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330262</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330267</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330271</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050270102</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051208</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Akama</last-name>
<first-name>Hideo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ohlandt, Greeley, Ruggiero &amp; Perle L.L.P.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Agilent Technologies, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Palo Alto</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Khanh Van</first-name>
<department>2817</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A push-pull amplifier includes a pair of transistors, wherein each of the transistors has a control terminal, a first terminal, and a second terminal. A current that flows between the first terminal and the second terminal is controlled in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal, such that when an amount of current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range, a high-frequency component of the signals input to the control terminal of one of the transistors is amplified, and when this current is outside the predetermined range, the high frequency component is not amplified.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="120.65mm" wi="142.83mm" file="US07298211-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="252.56mm" wi="160.70mm" file="US07298211-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="259.59mm" wi="164.08mm" file="US07298211-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="123.53mm" wi="156.29mm" file="US07298211-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="175.43mm" wi="149.61mm" file="US07298211-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention pertains to a power amplifying apparatus and relates in particular to a power amplifying apparatus comprising a push-pull amplifier.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">DISCUSSION OF THE BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A push-pull amplifier is a typical power amplifying means. A push-pull amplifier is an amplifier made from a pair of transistors and is such that the output from each of the transistors in the pair is synthesized to obtain a signal output (for instance, refer to JP (Kokai) 2003-060,451 (pages 4 and 5, FIG. 1)).</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A circuit diagram of a typical power amplifying apparatus comprising a push-pull amplifier is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> comprises an input terminal X<b>1</b>, an operational amplifier A<b>11</b>, a push-pull amplifier <b>100</b>, and an output terminal Y<b>1</b>. Input terminal X<b>1</b> is connected to the inverting input of operational amplifier A<b>11</b>. The output signals of operational amplifier A<b>11</b> are input to a push-pull amplifier <b>100</b>. The output signals of push pull amplifier <b>100</b> are applied to output terminal Y<b>1</b> and to the non-inverting input of operational amplifier A<b>11</b>. It should be noted that a load Z is connected to output terminal Y<b>1</b> in order to facilitate understanding of the description that follows. Moreover, load Z is a resistor.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> is a bipolar push-pull amplifier that uses MOS-type field effect transistors. Push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> comprises an input terminal S<b>1</b>, an output terminal T<b>1</b>, a P channel MOS-type field effect transistor Q<b>11</b>, and an N channel MOS-type field effect transistor Q<b>12</b>. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b> is connected to a positive power source Vcc. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>12</b> is connected to a negative power source Vee. The output signals of operational amplifier A<b>11</b> are applied through a constant-voltage source E<b>11</b> to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b>. Moreover, the output signals of operational amplifier A<b>11</b> are applied through a constant-voltage source E<b>12</b> to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>12</b>. The drain of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b> and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>12</b> are connected together. Moreover, these drains are connected to output terminal Y<b>1</b>. In short, push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> is a drain output-type push-pull amplifier that outputs signals that have been inverted with respect to signals received at S<b>1</b>. Constant-voltage source E<b>11</b> and constant-voltage source E<b>12</b> are used for bias. Push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> can be operated as a class A, class AB, or class B amplifier by adjusting the magnitude of the bias.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Moreover, operational amplifier A<b>11</b> acts in such a way that there is no difference between the voltage at input terminal X<b>1</b> and the voltage at output terminal Y<b>1</b>. As a result, power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> power-amplifies signals input from input terminal X<b>1</b> and outputs them from output terminal Y<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The loop gain (dB) of power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> is the sum of the amplification factor (dB) of operational amplifier A<b>11</b> and the amplification factor (dB) of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b>. In general, the amplification factor of operational amplifier A<b>11</b> is set so that it decreases with an increase in frequency, while the amplification factor of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> is set so that it is constant regardless of frequency. Moreover, the amplification factor of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> decreases as the drain current of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b> or Q<b>12</b> becomes smaller. The reason for this is as follows.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The amplification factor GM of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> is the sum of amplification factor gm<b>1</b> of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b> and amplification factor gm<b>2</b> of field effect transistor Q<b>12</b>. The AC amplification factor of a field effect transistor is represented by mutual conductance gm. It should be noted that mutual conductance gm is also represented as forward transmission admittance |Y<sub>fs</sub>|. The mutual conductance of a field effect transistor is virtually zero as long as the gate voltage is the threshold voltage or less. The drain current increases as gate voltage rises. As a result, mutual conductance gm increases. Therefore, it is assumed that push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> operates as a class AB amplifier. In general, the drain current of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b> is large and the amplification factor gm<b>1</b> of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b> is also large when push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> outputs a large positive voltage. In this case, gm<b>1</b> dominates the amplification factor GM; therefore, GM is large, as well as gm<b>1</b>. The drain current of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b> decreases and gm<b>1</b> also becomes smaller as the output voltage of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> gradually decreases. The drain current of field effect transistor Q<b>12</b> at this time is small and the amplification factor gm<b>2</b> of field effect transistor Q<b>12</b> is also small. There is a gradual increase in gm<b>2</b> as the output voltage of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> falls closer to zero. However, the amplification factor GM is quite small at this time. Thereafter, amplification factor gm<b>2</b> of field effect transistor Q<b>12</b> increases with a further reduction in the output voltage of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b>. The amplification factor GM is now dominated by gm<b>2</b> at this time; therefore, GM is large, as well as gm<b>2</b>. Similarly, the overall amplification factor GM changes dependent on the drain current of each field effect transistor and the output voltage of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> has a finite frequency band; therefore, the frequency band of power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> becomes narrower as the AC amplification factor of push-pull amplifier <b>100</b> decreases. Moreover, the frequency band of power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> changes considerably as the change in the drain current of field effect transistor Q<b>11</b> or Q<b>12</b> becomes larger. Power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> tends to vibrate and outputs an unwanted ringing waveshape as the amount of change in the frequency band increases. Furthermore, there is also a problem with this type of power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> in that when there is high-speed change in the size of the load, it is difficult to maintain a constant output level.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The current amplification factor hfe of a bipolar transistor decreases with a reduction in the collector current. Consequently, the above-mentioned problem similarly occurs in a push-pull amplifier made from a pair of bipolar transistors and a push-pull amplifier made from a pair comprised of a bipolar transistor and a field effect transistor. Moreover, this problem becomes more obvious as the electrical efficiency of the push-pull amplifier improves. This is because the idle drain current and collector current are set at zero or at a relatively small value.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention solves the above-mentioned problems, an object thereof being to provide a push-pull amplifier that prevents the reduction in the AC amplification factor that is attributed to changes in the collector current or the source current of the transistors. Moreover, an object of the present invention is to provide a power amplifying apparatus comprising this type of push-pull amplifier.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The present invention provides that the amplification factor in the high-frequency band of a push-pull amplifier made of a pair comprised of a push-side transistor and a pull-side transistor is compensated when the collector current or source current of the transistor on the push side or of the transistor on the pull side is within a predetermined range. In order to compensate the amplification factor, the push-pull amplifier of the present invention manipulates signals applied to the base or the gate of the transistor on the push side or of the transistor on the pull side, or directly supplements output signals.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present invention provides for a push-pull amplifier. The push-pull amplifier includes a pair of transistors, wherein each of the transistors has a control terminal, a first terminal, and a second terminal. A current that flows between the first terminal and the second terminal is controlled in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal, such that when an amount of current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range, a high-frequency component of the signals input to the control terminal of one of the transistors is amplified, and when this current is outside the predetermined range, the high frequency component is not amplified.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The present invention also provides for a push-pull amplifier having an input terminal, an output terminal, a pair of transistors, and an amplifier. The pair of transistors amplifies signals received at the input terminal, and output to the output terminal. Each of the transistors includes a control terminal, a first terminal, and a second terminal that controls a current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal. The amplifier is for amplifying only a high-frequency component extracted from the signals received at the input terminal, and outputting the amplified signal to the output terminal when an amount of current flowing between the first and second terminals of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range. The amplifier is turned off when the amount of current flowing is outside the predetermined range.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Another aspect of the present invention provides for a power amplifying apparatus. The power amplifying apparatus includes a push-pull amplifier having a pair of transistors, wherein each of the transistors has a control terminal, a first terminal, and a second terminal, and wherein a current that flows between the first terminal and the second terminal is controlled in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal, such that when an amount of current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range, a high-frequency component of signals input to the control terminal of one of the transistors is amplified. When this current is outside the predetermined range, the high-frequency component is not amplified.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Yet another aspect of the present invention provides for a power amplifying apparatus that includes a push-pull amplifier having an input terminal, an output terminal, a pair of transistors, and an amplifier. The pair of transistors amplifies signals received at the input terminal and output to the output terminal. Each of the transistors includes a first terminal, and a second terminal, and a control terminal that controls a current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal. The amplifier is for amplifying only a high-frequency component extracted from the signals received at the input terminal and outputting an amplified signal to the output terminal when an amount of current flowing between the first and second terminals of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range. The amplifier is turned off when the amount of current flowing is outside the predetermined range.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">By means of the present invention, it is possible to control the changes in the AC amplification factor that are attributed to changes in the collector current or source current of one of the pair of transistors of a push-pull amplifier comprising at least one pair of transistors. Moreover, by means of the present invention, it is possible to control the reduction in the AC amplification factor when the collector current or the source current of one of a pair of transistors is small in a push-pull amplifier comprising at least one pair of transistors. As a result, a power amplifying apparatus that uses this type of push-pull amplifier can amplify with stability signals of a higher frequency than in the past.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a drawing showing a power amplifying apparatus <b>10</b> comprising a conventional push-pull amplifier <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a drawing showing a power amplifying apparatus <b>20</b> comprising a push-pull amplifier <b>200</b> of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a drawing showing a power amplifying apparatus <b>30</b> comprising a push-pull amplifier <b>300</b> of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a drawing showing a power amplifying apparatus <b>40</b> comprising a push-pull amplifier <b>400</b> of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a drawing showing a power amplifying apparatus <b>50</b> comprising a push-pull amplifier <b>500</b> of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a drawing showing a power amplifying apparatus <b>60</b> comprising a push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The present invention will be explained in detail based on the embodiments shown in the attached drawings. By means of the present embodiment, the amplification factor of the push-pull amplifier is compensated by manipulating the signals input to the gate of the transistor on the push side. The first embodiment of the present invention is a power amplifying apparatus <b>20</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Power amplifying apparatus <b>20</b> in the figure comprises an input terminal X<b>2</b>, an output terminal Y<b>2</b>, an operational amplifier A<b>21</b>, and a push-pull amplifier <b>200</b>. Signals at input terminal X<b>2</b> and signals at output terminal Y<b>2</b> are applied to operational amplifier A<b>21</b>. Operational amplifier A<b>21</b> inputs to push-pull amplifier <b>200</b> signals such that the difference between the two signals to be input is zero. Push-pull amplifier <b>200</b> power-amplifies input signals and outputs the product to output terminal Y<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Push-pull amplifier <b>200</b> is a bipolar push-pull amplifier that uses an MOS field effect transistor. Push-pull amplifier <b>200</b> comprises an input terminal S<b>2</b>, an output terminal T<b>2</b>, a push-side P channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>21</b>, a pull-side N channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>22</b>, a constant-voltage source E<b>21</b>, and a constant-voltage source E<b>22</b>. The drain of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>22</b> are connected to output terminal T<b>2</b>. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> is connected to a positive power source Vcc. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>22</b> is connected to a negative power source Vee. Signals received at input terminal S<b>2</b>, that is, output signals of operational amplifier A<b>21</b>, are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>21</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b>. Moreover, signals received at input terminal S<b>2</b> are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>22</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>22</b>. The pair of field effect transistors Q<b>21</b> and Q<b>22</b> operates as a class A, class AB, or class B amplifier in accordance with the voltage of constant-voltage sources E<b>21</b> and E<b>22</b>. The structure described above is the basic part of push-pull amplifier <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Furthermore, push-pull amplifier <b>200</b> comprises a resistor R<b>21</b> and an operational amplifier A<b>22</b>. Resistor R<b>21</b> is disposed between the source of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> and positive power source Vcc. Operational amplifier A<b>22</b> detects the potential difference between the two terminals of resistor R<b>21</b> and outputs signals that represent the amount of current flowing between the source and drain of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Push-pull amplifier <b>200</b> comprises a high-pass filter F<b>2</b>, an amplifier A<b>23</b>, a capacitor C<b>2</b>, a resistor R<b>22</b>, and a resistor R<b>23</b>. High-pass filter F<b>2</b> extracts the high-frequency component of signals received at input terminal S<b>2</b> and outputs the filtered product to amplifier A<b>23</b>. The cut-off frequency of high-pass filter F<b>2</b> is set such that it includes the band that should be compensated. Amplifier A<b>23</b> amplifies input signals by a predetermined amplitude and then outputs the amplified signal. Amplifier A<b>23</b> operates in accordance with output signals of operational amplifier A<b>22</b>. In further detail, amplifier A<b>23</b> outputs signals only when the amount of current flowing between the source and drain of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> is a predetermined value or less. Capacitor C<b>2</b> is used in order to obtain the alternating current component from the output signals of amplifier A<b>23</b>. Resistors R<b>22</b> and R<b>23</b> operate as a signal adding means.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Consequently, only signals that have been biased by constant-voltage source E<b>21</b> are applied at the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> is larger than a predetermined value. On the other hand, signals obtained by adding signals that have been biased by constant-voltage source E<b>21</b> and output signals of amplifier A<b>23</b> are applied at the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> when the amount of current flowing between the source and drain of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> is a predetermined value or less. In short, if the amount of current flowing between the source and drain of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> is a predetermined value or less, the high-frequency component of signals input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>21</b> are amplified in comparison to when the amount of current is greater than a predetermined value. The amplification factor of push-pull amplifier <b>200</b> is thereby compensated.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Next, a second embodiment of the present invention will be described. By means of the present embodiment, signals input to the gate of the pull-side transistor are manipulated to compensate the amplification factor of the push-pull amplifier. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a power amplifying apparatus <b>30</b>, the second embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Power amplifying apparatus <b>30</b> in the figure comprises an input terminal X<b>3</b>, an output terminal Y<b>3</b>, an operational amplifier A<b>31</b>, and a push-pull amplifier <b>300</b>. Signals at input terminal X<b>3</b> and signals at output terminal Y<b>3</b> are applied to operational amplifier A<b>31</b>. Operational amplifier A<b>31</b> inputs to push-pull amplifier <b>300</b> signals such that the difference between two signals to be input is zero. Push-pull amplifier <b>300</b> power-amplifies input signals and outputs amplified signals to output terminal Y<b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Push-pull amplifier <b>300</b> is a bipolar push-pull amplifier that uses an MOS field effect transistor. Push-pull amplifier <b>300</b> comprises an input terminal S<b>3</b>, an output terminal T<b>3</b>, a push-side P channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>31</b>, a pull-side N channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>32</b>, a constant-voltage source E<b>31</b>, and a constant-voltage source E<b>32</b>. The drain of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b> and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>32</b> are connected to output terminal T<b>3</b>. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b> is connected to a positive power source Vcc. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>32</b> is connected to a negative power source Vee. Signals received at input terminal S<b>3</b>, that is, output signals of operational amplifier A<b>31</b>, are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>31</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b>. Moreover, signals received at input terminal S<b>3</b> are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>32</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>32</b>. The pair of field effect transistors Q<b>31</b> and Q<b>32</b> operates as a class A or class AB amplifier in accordance with the voltage of constant-voltage sources E<b>31</b> and E<b>32</b>. The structure described above is the basic part of push-pull amplifier <b>300</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Furthermore, push-pull amplifier <b>300</b> comprises a resistor R<b>31</b> and an operational amplifier A<b>32</b>. Resistor R<b>31</b> is disposed between the source of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b> and positive power source Vcc. Operational amplifier A<b>32</b> detects the potential difference between the two terminals of resistor R<b>31</b> and outputs signals that represent the amount of current flowing between the source and drain of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Push-pull amplifier <b>300</b> comprises a high-pass filter F<b>3</b>, an amplifier A<b>33</b>, a capacitor C<b>3</b>, a resistor R<b>32</b>, and a resistor R<b>33</b>. High-pass filter F<b>3</b> extracts the high-frequency component of signals received at input terminal S<b>3</b> and outputs the filtered signal to amplifier A<b>33</b>. The cut-off frequency of high-pass filter F<b>3</b> is set such that it includes the band that should be compensated. Amplifier A<b>33</b> amplifies input signals by a predetermined amplitude and then outputs an amplified signal. Amplifier A<b>33</b> operates in accordance with the output signals of operational amplifier A<b>32</b>. In further detail, amplifier A<b>33</b> outputs signals only when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b> is a predetermined value or less. Capacitor C<b>3</b> is used in order to obtain the alternating current component from the output signals of amplifier A<b>33</b>. Resistors R<b>32</b> and R<b>33</b> operate as a signal adding means.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Consequently, only signals that have been biased by constant-voltage source E<b>32</b> are applied at the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>32</b> when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b> is greater than a predetermined value. On the other hand, signals obtained by adding signals that have been biased by constant-voltage source E<b>32</b> and output signals of amplifier A<b>33</b> are applied at the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>32</b> when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b> is a predetermined value or less. In short, if the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>31</b> is a predetermined value or less, the high-frequency component of signals input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>32</b> is amplified in comparison to when the amount of current is greater than a predetermined value. The amplification factor of push-pull amplifier <b>300</b> is thereby compensated.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">By means of the first and second embodiments, signals applied to the gate of a field effect transistor are manipulated in order to compensate the amplification factor. Embodiments whereby the amplification factor is compensated by directly supplementing output signals will be described next.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The third embodiment of the present invention is a power amplifying apparatus <b>40</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Power amplifying apparatus <b>40</b> in the figure comprises an input terminal X<b>4</b>, an output terminal Y<b>4</b>, an operational amplifier A<b>41</b>, and a push-pull amplifier <b>400</b>. Signals at input terminal X<b>4</b> and signals at output terminal Y<b>4</b> are applied to operational amplifier A<b>41</b>. Operational amplifier A<b>41</b> inputs to push-pull amplifier <b>400</b> signals such that the difference between two signals to be input is zero. Push-pull amplifier <b>400</b> power-amplifies input signals and outputs the amplified signal to output terminal Y<b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Push-pull amplifier <b>400</b> is a bipolar push-pull amplifier that uses an MOS field effect transistor. Push-pull amplifier <b>400</b> comprises an input terminal S<b>4</b>, an output terminal T<b>4</b>, a push-side P channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>41</b>, a pull-side N channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>42</b>, a constant-voltage source E<b>41</b>, and a constant-voltage source E<b>42</b>. The drain of field effect transistor Q<b>41</b> and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>42</b> are connected to output terminal T<b>4</b>. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>41</b> is connected to a positive power source Vcc. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>42</b> is connected to a negative power source Vee. Signals received at input terminal S<b>4</b>, that is, output signals of operational amplifier A<b>41</b>, are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>41</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>41</b>. Moreover, signals received at input terminal S<b>4</b> are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>42</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>42</b>. The pair of field effect transistors Q<b>41</b> and Q<b>42</b> operates as a class A, class AB, or class B amplifier in accordance with the voltage of constant-voltage sources E<b>41</b> and E<b>42</b>. The structure described above is the basic part of push-pull amplifier <b>400</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Furthermore, push-pull amplifier <b>400</b> comprises resistor R<b>4</b> and operational amplifier A<b>42</b>. Resistor R<b>4</b> is disposed between the source of field effect transistor Q<b>41</b> and positive power source Vcc. Operational amplifier A<b>42</b> detects the potential difference between the two terminals of resistor R<b>4</b> and outputs signals that represent the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Push-pull amplifier <b>400</b> comprises a high-pass filter F<b>4</b>, an amplifier A<b>43</b>, and a boost transistor Q<b>43</b>. Boost transistor Q<b>43</b> is a P channel MOS field effect transistor. High-pass filter F<b>4</b> extracts the high-frequency component of signals received at input terminal S<b>4</b> and outputs the filtered signal to amplifier A<b>43</b>. The cut-off frequency of high-pass filter F<b>4</b> is set such that it includes the band that should be compensated. Amplifier A<b>43</b> amplifies input signals by a predetermined amplitude and then outputs the amplified signal. The output signals of amplifier A<b>43</b> are applied to the gate of boost transistor Q<b>43</b>. The source of boost transistor Q<b>43</b> is connected to positive power source Vcc. The drain of boost transistor Q<b>43</b> is connected to output terminal T<b>4</b>. Amplifier A<b>43</b> operates in accordance with output signals of operational amplifier A<b>42</b>. In further detail, amplifier A<b>43</b> amplifies input signals and outputs the amplified signal when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>41</b> is a predetermined value or less. Boost transistor Q<b>43</b> is turned on by signals input to the gate at that time. On the other hand, amplifier A<b>43</b> outputs signals such that boost transistor Q<b>43</b> is turned off when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>41</b> is greater than a predetermined value. In addition, amplifier A<b>43</b> outputs signals such that boost transistor Q<b>43</b> is turned off when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>41</b> is zero, that is, when field effect transistor Q<b>41</b> is off.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Consequently, boost transistor Q<b>43</b> amplifies only the high-frequency component extracted from signals received at input terminal S<b>4</b> and outputs the amplified signal to output terminal T<b>4</b> only when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect ransistor Q<b>41</b> is within a predetermined range. The amplification factor of push-pull amplifier <b>400</b> is thereby compensated.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">A fourth embodiment of the present invention is a power amplifying apparatus <b>50</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Power amplifying apparatus <b>50</b> in the figure comprises an input terminal X<b>5</b>, an output terminal Y<b>5</b>, an operational amplifier A<b>51</b>, and a push-pull amplifier <b>500</b>. Signals at input terminal X<b>5</b> and signals at output terminal Y<b>5</b> are applied to operational amplifier A<b>51</b>. Operational amplifier A<b>51</b> inputs to push-pull amplifier <b>500</b> signals such that the difference between two signals to be input is zero. Push-pull amplifier <b>500</b> power-amplifies input signals and outputs the amplified signal to output terminal Y<b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Push-pull amplifier <b>500</b> is a bipolar push-pull amplifier that uses an MOS field effect transistor. Push-pull amplifier <b>500</b> comprises an input terminal S<b>5</b>, an output terminal T<b>5</b>, a push-side P channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>51</b>, a pull-side N channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>52</b>, a constant-voltage source E<b>51</b>, and a constant-voltage source E<b>52</b>. The drain of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b> and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>52</b> are connected to output terminal T<b>5</b>. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b> is connected to a positive power source Vcc. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>52</b> is connected to a negative power source Vee. Signals received at input terminal S<b>5</b>, that is, output signals of operational amplifier A<b>51</b>, are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>51</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b>. Moreover, signals received at input terminal S<b>5</b> are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>52</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>52</b>. The pair of field effect transistors Q<b>51</b> and Q<b>52</b> operates as a class A, class AB, or class B amplifier in accordance with the voltage of constant-voltage sources E<b>51</b> and E<b>52</b>. The structure described above is the basic part of push-pull amplifier <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Furthermore, push-pull amplifier <b>500</b> comprises a resistor R<b>5</b> and operational amplifier A<b>52</b>. Resistor R<b>5</b> is disposed between the source of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b> and positive power source Vcc. Operational amplifier A<b>52</b> detects the potential difference between the two terminals of resistor R<b>5</b> and outputs signals that represent the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Push-pull amplifier <b>500</b> comprises a high-pass filter F<b>5</b>, an amplifier A<b>53</b>, and a boost transistor Q<b>53</b>. Boost transistor Q<b>53</b> is an N channel MOS field effect transistor. High-pass filter F<b>5</b> extracts the high-frequency component of signals received at input terminal S<b>5</b> and outputs the filtered signal to amplifier A<b>53</b>. The cut-off frequency of high-pass filter F<b>5</b> is set such that it includes the band that should be compensated. Amplifier A<b>53</b> amplifies the input signals by a predetermined amplitude and then outputs the product. The output signals of amplifier A<b>53</b> are applied to the gate of boost transistor Q<b>53</b>. The source of boost transistor Q<b>53</b> is connected to negative power source Vee. The drain of boost transistor Q<b>53</b> is connected to output terminal T<b>5</b>. Amplifier A<b>53</b> operates in accordance with output signals of operational amplifier A<b>52</b>. In further detail, amplifier A<b>53</b> amplifies the input signals and outputs amplified signal when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b> is a predetermined value or less. Boost transistor Q<b>53</b> is turned on by signals input to the gate contemporaneously. On the other hand, amplifier A<b>53</b> outputs signals such that boost transistor Q<b>53</b> is turned off when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b> is greater than a predetermined value. In addition, amplifier A<b>53</b> outputs signals such that boost transistor Q<b>53</b> is turned off when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b> is zero, that is, when field effect transistor Q<b>51</b> is off.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Consequently, boost transistor Q<b>53</b> amplifies only the high-frequency component extracted from signals received at input terminal S<b>5</b> and outputs the amplified signal to output terminal T<b>5</b> only when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>51</b> is within a predetermined range. The amplification factor of push-pull amplifier <b>500</b> is thereby compensated.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The above-mentioned embodiments compensate for the reduction in the amplification factor attributed to the transistor on the push side. A detection means for the drain current and a circuit segment that operates in response to this means can be disposed for the pull side in order to compensate for a reduction in the amplification factor attributed to the transistor on the pull side. A power amplifying apparatus <b>60</b> having this type of push-pull amplifier is described below as a fifth embodiment of the present invention while referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The fifth embodiment expands on the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Power amplifying apparatus <b>60</b> in the figure comprises an input terminal X<b>6</b>, an output terminal Y<b>6</b>, an operational amplifier A<b>61</b>, and a push-pull amplifier <b>600</b>. Signals at input terminal X<b>6</b> and Signals at output terminal Y<b>6</b> are applied to operational amplifier A<b>61</b>. Operational amplifier A<b>61</b> inputs to push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> signals such that the difference between two signals to be input is zero. Push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> power-amplifies input signals and outputs the amplified signal to output terminal Y<b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> is a bipolar push-pull amplifier that uses an MOS field effect transistor. Push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> comprises an input terminal S<b>6</b>, an output terminal T<b>6</b>, a push-side P channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>61</b>, a pull-side N channel MOS field effect transistor Q<b>62</b>, a constant-voltage source E<b>61</b>, and a constant-voltage source E<b>62</b>. The drain of field effect transistor Q<b>61</b> and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>62</b> are connected to output terminal T<b>6</b>. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>61</b> is connected to a positive power source Vcc. The source of field effect transistor Q<b>62</b> is connected to a negative power source Vee. The signals received at input terminal S<b>6</b>, that is, the output signals of operational amplifier A<b>61</b>, are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>61</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>61</b>. Moreover, the signals received at input terminal S<b>6</b> are biased by constant-voltage source E<b>62</b> and input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>62</b>. The pair of field effect transistors Q<b>61</b> and Q<b>62</b> operates as a class A, class AB, or class B amplifier in accordance with the voltage of constant-voltage sources E<b>61</b> and E<b>62</b>. The structure described above is the basic part of push-pull amplifier <b>600</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Furthermore, push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> comprises a resistor R<b>61</b> and an operational amplifier A<b>62</b>. Resistor R<b>61</b> is disposed between the source of field effect transistor Q<b>61</b> and positive power source Vcc. Operational amplifier A<b>62</b> detects the potential difference between the two terminals of resistor R<b>61</b> and outputs signals that represent the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> comprises a high-pass filter F<b>61</b>, an amplifier A<b>63</b>, a capacitor C<b>61</b>, a resistor R<b>62</b>, and a resistor R<b>63</b>. High-pass filter <b>61</b> extracts the high-frequency component of signals received at input terminal S<b>6</b> and outputs the filtered signal to amplifier A<b>63</b>. The cut-off frequency of high-pass filter F<b>61</b> is set such that it includes the band that should be compensated. Amplifier A<b>63</b> amplifies input signals by a predetermined amplitude and then outputs the product. Amplifier A<b>63</b> operates in accordance with the output signals of operational amplifier A<b>62</b>. In further detail, amplifier A<b>63</b> outputs signals only when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>61</b> is a predetermined value or less. Capacitor C<b>61</b> is used in order to obtain the alternating current component from the output signals of amplifier A<b>63</b>. Resistors R<b>62</b> and R<b>63</b> operate as a signal adding means.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Moreover, push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> comprises a resistor R<b>64</b> and an operational amplifier A<b>64</b>. Resistor R<b>64</b> is disposed between the source of field effect transistor Q<b>62</b> and negative power source Vee. Operational amplifier A<b>64</b> detects the potential difference between the two terminals of resistor R<b>64</b> and outputs signals that represent the amount of current flowing between the source and drain of field effect transistor Q<b>62</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> further comprises a high-pass filter F<b>62</b>, an amplifier A<b>65</b>, a capacitor C<b>62</b>, a resistor R<b>65</b>, and a resistor R<b>66</b>. High-pass filter F<b>62</b> extracts the high-frequency component of the signals received at input terminal S<b>6</b> and outputs filtered signal to amplifier A<b>65</b>. The cut-off frequency of high-pass filter F<b>62</b> is set such that it includes the band that should be compensated. Amplifier A<b>65</b> amplifies input signals by a predetermined amplitude and then outputs the amplified signal. Amplifier A<b>65</b> operates in accordance with the output signals of operational amplifier A<b>64</b>. In further detail, amplifier A<b>65</b> outputs signals only when the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>62</b> is a predetermined value or less. Capacitor C<b>62</b> is used in order to obtain the alternating current component from the output signals of amplifier A<b>65</b>. Resistors R<b>65</b> and R<b>66</b> operate as a signal adding means.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">If the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>61</b> of power amplifying apparatus <b>60</b> that is constructed as described above is a predetermined current or less, the high-frequency component of signals input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>61</b> is amplified in comparison with the case when this amount of current is greater than the predetermined current. If the amount of current flowing between the source and the drain of field effect transistor Q<b>62</b> is a pre-determined current or less, the high-frequency component of signals input to the gate of field effect transistor Q<b>62</b> is amplified in comparison to the case when this current is greater than a predetermined current. The amplification factor of push-pull amplifier <b>600</b> is thereby compensated. This compensation is performed from both the push side and the pull side.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The following modifications are possible in each of the above-mentioned embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">First, although the field effect transistors are connected such that a drain output-type of push-pull amplifier is formed in each of the above-mentioned embodiments, the field effect transistors can be connected such that a source follower-type of push-pull amplifier is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Moreover, the field effect transistors in each of the above-mentioned embodiments can be replaced by bipolar transistors and other unipolar transistors. All or some of the field effect transistors can be replaced. Field effect transistors Q<b>43</b> and Q<b>53</b> can also be replaced with active elements. For instance, at least one of field effect transistors Q<b>22</b> and Q<b>23</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> can be replaced with bipolar transistors. Moreover, field effect transistor Q<b>32</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> can be replaced with active elements other than transistors.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A push-pull amplifier comprising a pair of transistors, wherein each of the transistors includes a control terminal, a first terminal, and a second terminal, and wherein a current that flows between the first terminal and the second terminal is controlled in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal, such that when an amount of current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range, a high-frequency component of the signals input to the control terminal of one of the transistors is amplified, and when this current is outside the predetermined range, the high frequency component is not amplified.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The push-pull amplifier according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a detector that detects the current that flows between the first and second terminals of one of the transistors; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a filter that extracts the high-frequency component from an input signal and outputs the high-frequency component only when the current detected by the detector is within the predetermined range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The push-pull amplifier according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said filter has a signal amplifier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A push-pull amplifier comprising:
<claim-text>an input terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pair of transistors, wherein the pair of transistors amplifies signals received at said input terminal, and output to said output terminal, wherein each of the transistors includes a control terminal, a first terminal, and a second terminal that controls a current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an amplifier for amplifying only a high-frequency component extracted from said signals received at said input terminal, and outputting said amplified signal to said output terminal when an amount of current flowing between the first and second terminals of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range, wherein the amplifier is turned off when the amount of current flowing is outside the predetermined range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The push-pull amplifier according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said amplifier comprises:
<claim-text>a detector which detects the current flowing between the first and second terminals of one of the transistors;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a filter which extracts and outputs the high-frequency component from signals received at the input terminal only when the current detected by the detector is within the predetermined range; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transistor that is disposed parallel to one of the transistors and operates in response to the output signals of the filter.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The push-pull amplifier according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said filter has a signal amplifier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A power amplifying apparatus comprising: a push-pull amplifier having a pair of transistors, wherein each of the transistors has a control terminal, a first terminal, and a second terminal, and wherein a current that flows between the first terminal and the second terminal is controlled in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal, such that when an amount of current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range, a high-frequency component of signals input to the control terminal of one of the transistors is amplified, and when this current is outside the predetermined range, the high-frequency component is not amplified.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A power amplifying apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a push-pull amplifier having:
<claim-text>an input terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output terminal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pair of transistors, wherein the pair of transistors amplifies signals received at said input terminal and output to said output terminal, wherein each of the transistors includes a first terminal, and a second terminal, and a control terminal that controls a current flowing between the first terminal and the second terminal in accordance with signals applied to the control terminal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an amplifier for amplifying only a high-frequency component extracted from said signals received at said input terminal and outputting an amplified signal to said output terminal when an amount of current flowing between the first and second terminals of one of the transistors is within a predetermined range, wherein the amplifier is turned off when the amount of current flowing is outside the predetermined range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
