<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297010-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297010</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11226529</doc-number>
<date>20050913</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>62</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439331</main-classification>
<further-classification>439862</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Electrical connector having vertically movable terminals</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6652329</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Howell et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439862</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6814586</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ju</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439 66</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6971902</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Taylor et al.</name>
<date>20051200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439342</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439331</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 73</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439862</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 66</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439632</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 83</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060063429</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060323</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tsai</last-name>
<first-name>Chou Hsuan</first-name>
<address>
<street>15F, No. 4, Lane 127, Sec. 1, Fu-Hsing Rd.</street>
<city>Hsin-Chuang</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Pro-Techtor Int'l Services</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ta</last-name>
<first-name>Tho D.</first-name>
<department>2833</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Girardi</last-name>
<first-name>Vanessa</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electrical connector includes a base and terminals. The base is formed with terminal slots in which the terminals are disposed. Each terminal slot has first and second walls, and third and fourth walls. Each terminal includes a fixing portion, an elastic arm and a pin portion. The fixing portion presses against and is positioned by the terminal slot. The fixing portion has first and second plates that are folded. The first plate contacts the first wall of the terminal slot. The elastic arm is connected to a top of the second plate. The elastic arm extends upward in a direction toward the fixing portion. A connection point is formed on the elastic arm close to a free end of the elastic arm. The pin portion, which is formed by prodding and pressing the fixing portion, extends toward a bottom of the base.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="140.46mm" wi="203.88mm" file="US07297010-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="237.24mm" wi="138.09mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297010-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="237.57mm" wi="183.98mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297010-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="245.03mm" wi="168.83mm" file="US07297010-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="251.29mm" wi="178.99mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297010-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="262.47mm" wi="175.85mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297010-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="242.74mm" wi="152.06mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297010-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention relates in general to an electrical connector, and more particularly to an electrical connector having terminals that may be moved vertically.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Conventionally, a bottom surface of a chip (e.g., a CPU) is formed with a plurality of connection points arranged separately, and an electrical connector connected to the chip is pressed down to fix the chip onto a base, such that the connection points of the chip may elastically contact the terminals in the terminal slots of the base and the electrical connections therebetween may be ensured.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a conventional electrical connector to be connected to a chip includes a base <b>10</b>, on which a plurality of terminal slots <b>11</b> is formed, and a plurality of terminals <b>14</b>, which is inserted into the terminal slots <b>11</b> of the base. Each terminal <b>14</b> has a vertically movable elastic arm <b>15</b> and a fixing portion <b>16</b>. The fixing portion <b>16</b> presses against the terminal slot <b>11</b>. The elastic arm <b>15</b> is connected to a top of the fixing portion <b>16</b> and is formed with a protruding connection point <b>17</b> at a free end thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">When the chip <b>90</b> is placed on the base <b>10</b>, each connection point <b>91</b> of the chip <b>90</b> contacts the connection point <b>17</b> of each terminal <b>14</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, when the chip <b>90</b> is forced down, each terminal <b>14</b> retracts due to the elasticity of the elastic arm <b>15</b>. At this time, the connection point <b>17</b> elastically presses against the connection point <b>91</b> to achieve the electrical connection effect.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The prior art structure has the following drawbacks. That is, the terminal slots <b>11</b> are rectangular and disposed on the base <b>10</b> and the terminals <b>14</b> are inserted into the terminal slots <b>11</b>, so the extendable length of the elastic arm <b>15</b> is limited to the length of the terminal slot <b>11</b>. Because the function of the CPU is getting more and more powerful, the connection points of the CPU are getting more and more. Thus, more and more terminal slots <b>11</b> have to be disposed in the base <b>10</b> such that the length of the terminal slot is reduced. In this case, the extendable length of the elastic arm <b>15</b> of the terminal <b>14</b> is also reduced, and the elastic fatigue tends to occur.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is therefore an object of the invention to provide an electrical connector having a base and terminals, which may be easily assembled and firmly positioned.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Another object of the invention is to provide an electrical connector including elastic arms of terminals, each of which has an easily controlled length, such that the required elastic moving effect may be achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Still another object of the invention is to provide an electrical connector having adjacent first and second terminals and adjacent first and second terminal slots, in which a free end of an elastic arm of the first terminal in the first terminal slot extends to the second terminal slot. Thus, the elastic arm may have a longer extendable length in the horizontal direction, and the contact elasticity between the chip and the elastic arm may be enhanced.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Yet still another object of the invention is to provide an electrical connector, in which free ends of elastic arms will not be interfered to cause deformations of terminals when a chip is placed in an accommodating region of a base.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">To achieve the above-identified objects, the invention provides an electrical connector including a base and a plurality of terminals. The base is formed with a plurality of terminal slots arranged separately. Each of the terminal slots has a first wall and a second wall opposite to the first wall, and a third wall and a fourth wall opposite to the third wall. The terminals are inserted into the plurality of terminal slots of the base. Each of the terminals includes a fixing portion, an elastic arm and a pin portion. The fixing portion presses against the terminal slot and is positioned by the terminal slot. The fixing portion has a first plate and a second plate that are folded and in surface contact with each other. The first plate contacts the first wall of the terminal slot. The elastic arm is connected to a top of the second plate of the fixing portion. The elastic arm extends upward in a direction toward the fixing portion. A connection point is formed on the elastic arm close to a free end of the elastic arm, which is not disposed between the first plate and the second plate. The pin portion, which is formed by prodding and pressing the fixing portion, extends toward a bottom of the base.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to the above-mentioned structure, the base and the terminals may be easily assembled and firmly positioned, and the length of the elastic arm of the terminal may be easily controlled to achieve the desired elastic moving effect.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Other objects, features, and advantages of the invention will become apparent from the following detailed description of the preferred but non-limiting embodiments. The following description is made with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a first usage state of a conventional electrical connector and a chip.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a second usage state of the conventional electrical connector and the chip.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a pictorially exploded view showing an electrical connector according to a preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a pictorially assembled view showing the electrical connector according to the preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a pictorial view showing a usage state of the electrical connector according to the preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a pictorially exploded view showing the terminals combined with the inner seat according to the preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross-sectional view showing the terminals combined with the inner seat according to the preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a pictorial view showing the terminal according to the preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a schematic illustration showing a usage state according to the preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a pictorial view showing a terminal according to a second embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a pictorial view showing a terminal according to a third embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a pictorial view showing a terminal according to a fourth embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a cross-sectional view showing terminals combined with an inner seat according to a fifth embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 to 6</figref>, an electrical connector of this embodiment includes a base, a plurality of terminals <b>60</b>, an upper cover <b>70</b> and a lever <b>80</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The base includes a metallic outer seat <b>30</b> and a plastic inner seat <b>40</b>. The outer seat <b>30</b> has a bottom surface <b>31</b> and two sidewalls <b>32</b>. The bottom surface <b>31</b> is formed with an opening <b>33</b> at a middle portion, a first pivotal portion <b>34</b> at a front end, a second pivotal portion <b>35</b> being a hole, and an engagement sheet <b>36</b> at a side. The inner seat <b>40</b> is fitted in the outer seat <b>30</b>, and a plurality of terminal slots <b>41</b> is arranged in the inner seat <b>40</b>. A periphery of a top of the inner seat is formed with a flange <b>42</b> extending upward to form an accommodating region <b>43</b> for accommodating a chip <b>90</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref>, each terminal slot <b>41</b> has a first wall <b>44</b> and a second wall <b>45</b> opposite to the first wall <b>44</b>, and a third wall <b>46</b> and a fourth wall <b>47</b> opposite to the third wall <b>46</b>, wherein the third wall <b>46</b> and the fourth wall <b>47</b> are higher than the first wall <b>44</b> and the second wall <b>45</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the plurality of terminals <b>60</b> forming a row is inserted into the terminal slots <b>41</b> of the inner seat <b>40</b> of the base downward, and then separated from a material tape <b>616</b>. Each terminal <b>60</b> has a fixing portion <b>61</b>, an elastic arm <b>62</b>, and a pin portion <b>63</b>. The fixing portion <b>61</b> presses against the terminal slot <b>41</b> and is thus positioned and has a first plate <b>64</b> and a second plate <b>65</b> that are folded and in surface contact with each other. The first plate <b>64</b> contacts the first wall <b>44</b> of the terminal slot <b>41</b> and is formed with a first pressing portion <b>66</b> having a wider plate near a top of the first plate <b>64</b>. The first pressing portion <b>66</b> presses against the third wall <b>46</b> and the fourth wall <b>47</b> of the terminal slot. The second plate <b>65</b> is prodded and pressed to form a protruding second pressing portion <b>67</b> to press against the second wall <b>45</b> of the terminal slot. The elastic arm <b>62</b> is connected to a top of the second plate <b>65</b> of the fixing portion <b>61</b>. The elastic arm <b>62</b> firstly extends toward the second wall <b>45</b> and then turns back and extends upward in a slantingly direction toward the fixing portion. A free end <b>68</b> of a first terminal <b>60</b>, which is inserted into a first terminal slot <b>41</b>, strides over the first wall <b>44</b> and then goes to a location above the second terminal slot <b>41</b>, in which a second terminal <b>60</b> adjacent to the first terminal <b>60</b> is disposed. The elastic arm <b>62</b> has a wider lower section <b>69</b> and a narrower upper section <b>610</b>. The lower section <b>69</b> has an arc shape and is formed with an opening <b>611</b> at a middle portion. The free end of the upper section <b>610</b> of the elastic arm of a first terminal in a first terminal slot is located above and corresponds to the opening <b>611</b> of the lower section <b>69</b> of the elastic arm of a second terminal in a second terminal slot adjacent to the first terminal slot. The free end of the first terminal never contacts the second terminal in the second terminal slot adjacent to the first terminal slot because the free end of the first terminal may be moved into the opening of the second terminal. In addition, a highest connection point <b>612</b>, which is higher than the third wall and the fourth wall <b>47</b> of the terminal slot and located in the accommodating region <b>43</b>, is formed on the upper section <b>610</b> of the elastic arm close to the free end <b>68</b>, which is not disposed between the first plate <b>64</b> and the second plate <b>65</b>. The free end <b>68</b> of the elastic arm is flush with the third wall <b>46</b> and the fourth wall <b>47</b>. The pin portion <b>63</b> to be connected to a solder ball <b>613</b> is formed by prodding and pressing the first plate <b>64</b> of the fixing portion <b>61</b> and extends downward to a bottom of the inner seat <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The upper cover <b>70</b> has a covering surface <b>71</b> and two sidewalls <b>72</b>. Two sides of the rear end of the upper cover <b>70</b> are formed with an arced pivotal portion <b>73</b>. The middle of the rear end of the upper cover <b>70</b> is formed with a stopper <b>74</b>. The pivotal portion <b>73</b> is pivotably connected to the second pivotal portion <b>35</b> at the rear end of the outer seat <b>30</b> of the base. A front end of the upper cover <b>70</b> is formed with two protruding sheets <b>75</b>, which extend frontward in a transversal state. When the upper cover <b>70</b> covers the base, the covering surface <b>71</b> can press the periphery of the chip <b>90</b>. In addition, when the upper cover <b>70</b> is lifted up into a longitudinal state, the stopper <b>74</b> can stop the rear end of the inner seat <b>40</b> and prevent the inner seat <b>40</b> from falling out.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The lever <b>80</b> has a first rod <b>81</b> and a second rod <b>82</b> perpendicular to the first rod. The second rod <b>82</b> is pivotably connected to the first pivotal portion <b>34</b> at the front end of the outer seat <b>30</b> of the base, and is bent to form a convex rod <b>83</b>. An external end of the first rod <b>81</b> is bent to form a handle <b>84</b>. When the first rod <b>81</b> is swung toward the rear end of the base, the convex rod <b>83</b> can press the protruding sheet <b>75</b> of the upper cover <b>70</b> to make the upper cover <b>70</b> press the chip <b>90</b> downward and to make the terminals <b>60</b> be electrically connected to the chip <b>90</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, when the lever <b>80</b> is swung and positioned, the first rod <b>81</b> is engaged under the engagement sheet <b>36</b> of the outer seat <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">According to the above-mentioned structure, because the elastic arm <b>62</b> of the terminal <b>60</b> extends to the adjacent terminal slot <b>41</b>, the elastic arm <b>62</b> may have good elasticity. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, when the chip <b>90</b> is pressed by the upper cover <b>70</b> to contact the terminals, the elastic arm <b>62</b> of each of the terminals retracts elastically, and the connection point <b>612</b> may elastically contact the connection point <b>91</b> of the chip <b>90</b>. The elastic arm <b>62</b> of the terminal extends slantingly from bottom to top and is free from contacting the adjacent terminal in the adjacent terminal slot <b>41</b> to cause the short-circuited condition. Because the upper section <b>610</b> of the elastic arm is located above the opening <b>611</b> of the lower section of the elastic arm of the terminal in the adjacent terminal slot, the upper section <b>610</b> of one terminal can be moved into the opening <b>611</b> of another adjacent terminal and never contacts the adjacent terminal when the elastic arm <b>62</b> is pressed.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Thus, the invention has the following advantages.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">1. The fixing portion of the terminal has the first plate <b>64</b> and the second plate <b>65</b> that are folded, so the first plate <b>64</b> may have a wider pressing portion <b>66</b> for pressing against the third and fourth walls <b>46</b> and <b>47</b> of the terminal slot, and the pressing portion <b>61</b> for pressing against the second wall <b>45</b> of the terminal slot may be formed by prodding and pressing a plate surface of the second plate <b>65</b>. Thus, the terminals may be easily assembled and well positioned. In addition, the first plate <b>64</b> may have good structure intensity because the pressing portion of the first plate <b>64</b> is not formed by way of pressing.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">2. The length of the elastic arm <b>62</b> may be controlled according to the length of the second plate <b>65</b> of the fixing portion of the terminal. That is, the shorter the second plate <b>65</b> is, the lower the root of the elastic arm <b>62</b> is, and the larger the elastic movement is. Otherwise, the elastic movement of the elastic arm <b>62</b> is smaller.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">3. The free end of the elastic arm <b>62</b> of the terminal extends to the adjacent terminal slot <b>41</b>, so the elastic arm may have a longer extending length in the horizontal direction and the contact between the chip and the elastic arm is better. In addition, the elastic arm extends slantingly from bottom to top. So, when the chip presses the elastic arm, the elastic arm never contacts the adjacent terminal to cause the short-circuited condition.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">4. The lower section <b>69</b> of the elastic arm has the opening <b>611</b> for receiving the upper section <b>610</b> of the adjacent terminal. Although the free end <b>68</b> of the elastic arm is bent downward to flush with the third and fourth walls <b>46</b> and <b>47</b>, it is unnecessary to worry about that the free end will contact the adjacent terminal. In addition, because the free end <b>68</b> of the elastic arm is not higher than the third and fourth walls <b>46</b> and <b>47</b>, the chip <b>90</b> never interferes with the free end <b>68</b> of the elastic arm to cause the deformation of the terminal when the chip is placed in the accommodating region <b>43</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the second embodiment of the invention is almost the same as the first embodiment except that the pin portion <b>63</b> of the terminal <b>60</b> is formed by pressing the second plate of the fixing portion.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, the third embodiment of the invention is almost the same as the first embodiment except that the first pressing portions <b>66</b> of the fixing portion <b>61</b> of the terminal <b>60</b> are formed at two sides of the top of the second plate <b>65</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, the fourth embodiment of the invention is almost the same as the first embodiment except that the pin portion <b>63</b> of the terminal <b>60</b> extends longitudinally.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, the fifth embodiment of the invention is almost the same as the first embodiment except that the lower section <b>69</b> of the elastic arm of the terminal <b>60</b> has a <img id="CUSTOM-CHARACTER-00001" he="2.79mm" wi="2.46mm" file="US07297010-20071120-P00001.TIF" alt="custom character" img-content="character" img-format="tif"/> shape.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">While the invention has been described by way of examples and in terms of preferred embodiments, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited to the disclosed embodiments. To the contrary, it is intended to cover various modifications. Therefore, the scope of the appended claims should be accorded the broadest interpretation so as to encompass all such modifications.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electrical connector, comprising:
<claim-text>a base formed with a plurality of terminal slots arranged separately, each of the terminal slots has a first wall and a second wall opposite to the first wall, and a third wall and a fourth wall opposite to the third wall; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of terminals respectively inserted into the plurality of terminal slots of the base, each of the terminals comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixing portion for pressing the terminal slot and being positioned by the terminal slot, wherein the fixing portion has a first plate and a second plate that are folded and in surface contact with each other, the first plate contacts the first wall of the terminal slot;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an elastic arm connected to a top of the second plate of the fixing portion, wherein the elastic arm extends upward in a direction toward the fixing portion, and a connection point is formed on the elastic arm close to a free end of the elastic arm, which is not disposed between the first plate and the second plate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pin portion, which is connected to the fixing portion and extends toward a bottom of the base.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first plate of the fixing portion of the terminal has a wider pressing portion for pressing against the third wall and the fourth wall of the terminal slot.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a protruding pressing portion for pressing against the second wall of the terminal slot is connected to the second plate of the fixing portion of the terminal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the pin portion of the terminal is connected to a solder ball.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the pin portion of the terminal is connected to the first plate of the fixing portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the terminals comprise a first terminal and a second terminal adjacent to the first terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the terminal slots comprise a first terminal slot, into which the first terminal is inserted, and a second terminal slot, into which the second terminal is inserted;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the free end of the elastic arm of the first terminal strides over the first wall and goes to a location above the second terminal slot.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the elastic arm of each of the first and second terminals has a wider lower section and a narrower upper section, the lower section is formed with an opening, a free end of the upper section of the elastic arm of the first terminal is located above and corresponds to the opening of the lower section of the elastic arm of the second terminal such that the free end of the first terminal never contacts the second terminal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the third and fourth walls of each of the first and second terminal slots are higher than the first and second walls.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the free end of the elastic arm of each of the first and second terminals is not higher than the third and fourth walls of each of the first and second terminal slots, and the connection point of the elastic arm is higher than the third and fourth walls of each of the first and second terminal slots.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>a top of the base is formed with an accommodating region for accommodating a chip;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the connection points of the plurality of terminals protrude from the terminal slot to the accommodating region; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the connector further comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>an upper cover having a rear end pivotably connected to a rear end of the base, and a front end formed with a protruding sheet, wherein the upper cover presses the chip when the upper cover is closed on the base; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lever having a first rod and a second rod perpendicular to the first rod, wherein the second rod is pivotably connected to a front end of the base and bent to form a convex rod, which presses the protruding sheet of the upper cover when the first rod is swung toward the rear end of the base.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the base comprises a metallic outer seat and a plastic inner seat fit into the outer seat, the plurality of terminal slots and the accommodating region are disposed on the inner seat, and the lever and the upper cover are respectively pivotably connected to a front end and a rear end of the outer seat.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
