<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298452-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298452</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10992335</doc-number>
<date>20041119</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2003-0091997</doc-number>
<date>20031216</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>169</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>62</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>58</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>355 47</main-classification>
<further-classification>355 72</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Patterning apparatus and method for fabricating continuous pattern using the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4206965</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>McGrew</name>
<date>19800600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359  9</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5652645</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jain</name>
<date>19970700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>355 53</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6222157</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Langille et al.</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>21912169</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>4-359465</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19921200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-256476</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>355 47</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>355 53</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>355 72</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>12</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050151944</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050714</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Park</last-name>
<first-name>Suk-Ho</first-name>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Choi</last-name>
<first-name>Young-Jun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Oh</last-name>
<first-name>Hyeon-Seok</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suwon</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lim</last-name>
<first-name>Jae-Ha</first-name>
<address>
<city>Osan</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jung</last-name>
<first-name>Suk-Won</first-name>
<address>
<city>Osan</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Birch, Stewart, Kolasch &amp; Birch, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>LG Electronics Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Korea Electronics Technology Institute</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Henry Hung</first-name>
<department>2851</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A flexible substrate, which has a photosensitive agent applied thereon, is continuously supplied from a supply unit to a guide unit where light is irradiated from a light source on a section of the substrate. A mask is positioned between the substrate and the light source so that the light from the light source selectively subjects the section of the substrate to exposure. Hence, it is possible to form a pattern having a continuous slanted structure for a large-area display panel.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="67.39mm" wi="156.63mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="180.34mm" wi="145.37mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="185.93mm" wi="162.64mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="99.40mm" wi="112.18mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="134.28mm" wi="145.12mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="133.18mm" wi="150.54mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="208.87mm" wi="193.97mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="211.07mm" wi="161.80mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="190.16mm" wi="138.94mm" file="US07298452-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application claims, under 35 U.S.C. § 119, the priority benefit of Korean Patent Application No. P03-091997 filed Dec. 16, 2003 in Republic of Korea, the entire contents of which are herein fully incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a patterning apparatus and a patterning method using the same, and more particularly to an apparatus for fabricating a pattern of a continuous structure, which is used in a large-area display, and a method for fabricating a pattern of a continuous structure using the same.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">As used herein, the pattern of a continuous structure refers to a pattern of, e.g., barrier ribs of a Plasma display panel (PDP), which are arranged in line in one direction with a uniform cross section.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Conventional patterning methods include an electron beam lithography method, an optical lithography method, and an X-ray lithography method.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to the electron beam lithography method, a photosensitive agent, which reacts to electrons, is applied on the upper surface of a substrate and a predetermined pattern is directly etched using electron beams, without any mask. This method can form a high-resolution pattern of 0.2 μm or less, since the electrons have a short wavelength.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, it takes a long time to etch a predetermined pattern using the electron beam lithography method. This decreases productivity. In addition, since the depth of a formed pattern is small, the accuracy of overlay and etching is poor. Furthermore, the method uses expensive electron-emission equipment. Consequently, the electron beam lithography method is not suitable for fabricating a pattern for use in a large-area display panel.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">According to the optical lithography method, a photosensitive agent is applied on the upper surface of a substrate, a mask is placed thereon, and UV rays are irradiated to fabricate a predetermined pattern. This method can form a vertical or slanted pattern according to the irradiation angle of the UV rays.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">However, if the optical lithography method is used, it is difficult to fabricate a vertical pattern with a thickness of a few tens of μm or more, as well as to form a uniformly slanted pattern, due to the diffraction characteristics peculiar to the UV rays. In addition, since the UV rays have dispersion, they cannot be irradiated only on selected portions or form a micro-pattern with a line width of 0.2 μm or less. Accordingly, this method cannot form a highly-integrated pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to an X-ray lithography method, a photosensitive agent is applied on the upper surface of a substrate and X-rays are irradiated via a mask to fabricate a predetermined pattern. Since the X-rays have a short wavelength, this method can form a micro-structure with a line width of 0.1 μm or less.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">However, when a substrate <b>1</b> and a mask <b>2</b> are kept parallel to each other and X-rays are irradiated with a slant to form a pattern <b>1</b><i>a </i>of a slanted structure, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a problem occurs as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">If the mask <b>2</b> is positioned with a slant relative to the X-rays, there is a difference in the traveling distance L<sub>1</sub>, L<sub>2 </sub>of the X-rays to the absorbent body <b>2</b><i>b </i>of the mask <b>2</b>. This decreases the degree of precision in shape. In order to solve this problem, the mask <b>2</b> should have a trapezoid absorbent body, which is difficult to fabricate. Since the width d of the X-rays is not zero, it is also impossible to form a continuous pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In addition, when the substrate <b>1</b> and the mask <b>2</b> are retained parallel to each other and X-rays are irradiated vertically to form a pattern <b>1</b><i>a </i>of a slanted structure, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a problem occurs as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">If the X-rays are irradiated on the upper surface of the substrate <b>1</b>, a thickness T of a photosensitive agent, which has been applied on the upper surface of the substrate, is subject to exposure as far as they penetrate into the substrate. Accordingly, this method can form only a pattern <b>1</b><i>a </i>of a thickness T of tens or hundreds of μm, which corresponds to the thickness of the substrate. In other words, such a conventional vertical irradiation method cannot continuously form a pattern of a three-dimensional slanted structure having a predetermined thickness or more.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Accordingly, the present invention has been made to solve one or more of the above-mentioned problems occurring in the prior art, and an object of the present invention is to provide a patterning apparatus capable of forming a pattern in a relatively large area of substrate and a patterning method using the same.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Another object of the present invention is to provide a patterning apparatus capable of fabricating a highly-integrated pattern and a patterning method using the same.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Another object of the present invention is to provide a patterning apparatus capable of fabricating a continuous pattern and a patterning method using the same.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Another object of the present invention is to provide a patterning apparatus capable of continuously fabricating a pattern of a slanted structure of a predetermined thickness or more and a patterning method using the same.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In order to accomplish one or more of the above objects, there is provided a patterning apparatus comprising: a guide unit for continuously guiding a flexible substrate, which has a photosensitive agent applied thereon, in a predetermined region including the top point of the guide unit; a light source for vertically irradiating beams on a vertical section of the photosensitive agent, which has been applied on the substrate; and a mask positioned between the substrate, which is guided by the guide unit, and the light source so that the beams are selectively transmitted to the photosensitive agent.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The guide unit can be a roller of a cylindrical shape and an auxiliary guide unit, which corresponds to the guide unit, is additionally provided so that the substrate is guided while being forced against the guide unit.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The guide unit is directly driven by a driving motor to move and guide the substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The patterning apparatus further comprises a supply unit for supplying the substrate to the guide unit and a winding unit for collecting the substrate, which has been subject to exposure in the guide unit, both of the supply and winding units providing driving power to move the substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The guide unit and the mask are installed on a frame and the mask is positioned by an alignment controller unit, which is provided on the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The guide unit and the mask are installed on a frame and the guide unit is positioned by a guide unit adjustment unit, which is provided on the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">According to another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a patterning apparatus comprising: a supply unit for continuously supplying a flexible substrate, which has a photosensitive agent applied thereon; a guide unit fixedly installed and adapted to continuously guide the substrate, which is supplied from the supply unit, in a predetermined region including the top point of the guide unit; a light source for vertically irradiating beams on a vertical section of the substrate, which is positioned on the top point of the guide unit; a mask positioned between the substrate, which is guided by the guide unit, and the light source so that the beams are selectively transmitted to the photosensitive agent; and a winding unit for collecting and winding the substrate, which has been subject to exposure in the guide unit.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The guide unit has a curved surface formed at least from its supply unit side to its top point, which contacts the substrate and guides it.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The guide unit has a flat surface formed in a predetermined region from its top point to its winding unit side, which contacts the substrate and guides it.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The guide unit and the mask are installed on a frame and the mask is positioned by an alignment controller unit, which is provided on the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The guide unit and the mask are installed on a frame and the guide unit is positioned by a guide unit adjustment unit, which is provided on the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">According to still another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a patterning method wherein a flexible substrate, which has a photosensitive agent applied on its surface, is supplied from a supply unit; is collected by a winding unit; is contacted by a predetermined region of a guide unit, including at least its top point, between the supply and winding units; and is guided, the method comprising: a first step of continuously guiding the substrate from the supply unit to the predetermined region of the guide unit, including its top point; a second step of irradiating beams from a light source in a direction perpendicular to a vertical section of the photosensitive agent, which is positioned on the top point of the guide unit, via a mask; and a third step of collecting the substrate, which has been subject to exposure in the guide unit, from the guide unit to the supply unit.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The mask is positioned parallel to the vertical section and the beams are vertically irradiated on the mask.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The period of time during which the beams are irradiated on the photosensitive agent and the amount of irradiation are determined by a speed control, which guides and moves the substrate.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The above and other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will be more apparent from the following detailed description taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a patterning process employing a slanted irradiation method in accordance with the background art;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a patterning process with a vertical irradiation method in accordance with the background art;</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the outline of a first embodiment of a patterning apparatus according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref><i>a </i>and <b>4</b><i>b </i>show the principal parts of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> for explaining the concept of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a second embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a third embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref><i>a </i>shows a variation of the third embodiment in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a flow chart of a patterning method according to the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8</figref><i>a </i>to <b>8</b><i>c </i>show examples of a three dimensional structure, which can be fabricated according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Hereinafter, a preferred embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to the accompanying drawings. In the following description and drawings, the same reference numerals are used to designate the same or similar components, and so repetition of the description on the same or similar components will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the outline of a first embodiment of a patterning apparatus according to the present invention and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref><i>a </i>and <b>4</b><i>b </i>show the principal parts of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> for explaining the concept of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As shown, a predetermined region of a flexible substrate <b>10</b>, which has a photosensitive agent applied on its surface, is wound around a guide unit <b>20</b>, which has a shape of a cylindrical roller, and is guided. The guide unit <b>20</b> is rotated by a driving motor <b>30</b>. The driving motor <b>30</b> has a rotation shaft <b>32</b>, which is concentrically connected to the rotation center of the guide unit <b>20</b> to rotate it. For reference, the rotation direction of the guide unit <b>20</b> is not necessarily identical to the movement direction of the substrate <b>10</b> and, for example, may be opposite to the movement direction of the substrate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">A mask <b>40</b> is positioned adjacently to the guide unit <b>20</b> and is parallel to the normal direction Z of the guide unit <b>20</b>. The mask <b>40</b> is composed of an opening <b>42</b>, through which beams <b>52</b> from a light source <b>50</b> (described below) pass, and an absorption unit <b>44</b>, which absorbs the beams <b>52</b>. The opening <b>42</b> is formed in such a manner that its shape corresponds to the sectional shape of a pattern to be formed and the absorption unit <b>44</b> forms a vertical wall around the opening <b>42</b>. The mask <b>40</b> may also be provided with a cover (not shown) to selectively shield the opening <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">A light source <b>50</b> is positioned in a location spaced a predetermined distance from the mask <b>40</b>. The light source <b>50</b> provides beams <b>52</b>, which are irradiated on the photosensitive agent to form a pattern. In other words, the beams <b>52</b> from the light source <b>52</b> pass through the opening <b>42</b> of the mask <b>40</b> and are irradiated on the photosensitive agent of the substrate, which is wound around the guide unit <b>20</b>. In the present embodiment, the light source <b>50</b> emits X-rays, which travel in an exactly straight line, have very little dispersion, and have energy tens of thousands of times larger than other rays.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">It will now be explained how the photosensitive agent on the substrate <b>10</b> is subject to exposure, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref><i>a </i>and <b>4</b><i>b</i>. If the substrate is cut parallel to the Z axis through the center of the guide unit <b>20</b>, a yz section is obtained in a location corresponding to the top point of the guide unit <b>20</b>. Hereinafter, this section will be referred to as a “vertical section H”.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">According to the present invention, the beams <b>52</b> are irradiated vertically on the vertical section H to subject the photosensitive agent to exposure. In particular, by irradiating the beams <b>52</b> on the vertical section H without interruption, while the substrate <b>20</b> is continuously moved, a region is subject to exposure at points to which the beams <b>52</b> are transmitted, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">More theoretically, as a vertical section H, which has been subject to exposure, is moved along the circumstance of the guide unit <b>20</b>, the next vertical section H is positioned on the top point t of the guide unit <b>20</b> for exposure. As such, the photosensitive agent is divided into innumerable vertical sections H, which are subject to exposure successively.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In practice, part “a” of the photosensitive agent is initially subject to exposure. If the substrate <b>10</b> is moved and passes through the top point t of the guide unit, the entire vertical section H is subject to exposure. Of course, if the beams <b>52</b> can pass through the photosensitive agent even at the location where the substrate has passed the top point t, point “b” will be the last portion to be subject to exposure.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The period of time during which the photosensitive agent of the substrate <b>10</b> is subject to exposure can be calculated by multiplying the radius r of the guide unit <b>20</b> by the rotation angle ∂ of the guide unit <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The mask <b>40</b> is preferably positioned parallel to the vertical section H. When passing through the opening <b>42</b> of the mask <b>40</b>, the beams <b>52</b> should be vertically incident on the vertical section H.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a second embodiment of the present invention. For clarity, the same components as in the first embodiment are given the same reference numerals and repeated explanation thereof will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">As shown in the drawing, a guide unit <b>20</b> is positioned on a frame <b>20</b>′ together with a mask <b>40</b> to guide a substrate <b>10</b>, in the present embodiment. The guide unit <b>20</b> is a cylindrical roller and contacts a predetermined region of the substrate <b>10</b> to guide it. An auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b>, which corresponds to the guide unit <b>20</b>, is provided. The auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b> cooperates with the guide unit <b>20</b> to guide the movement of the substrate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">The auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b> is rotated together with the guide unit <b>20</b> and securely forces the moving substrate <b>10</b> against the upper surface of the guide unit <b>20</b>. In other words, the auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b> prevents the substrate <b>10</b> from being spaced from the upper surface of the guide unit <b>20</b> so that the beams <b>52</b> are accurately irradiated on the vertical section H.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b> is not necessarily positioned adjacently to the guide unit <b>20</b>, as shown in the drawing. For example, one auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b> is positioned on a side of the guide unit <b>20</b> where the substrate <b>10</b> is supplied and another is positioned on a side where the substrate <b>10</b> is collected. The region of the substrate <b>10</b>, which contacts the guide unit <b>20</b> and is guided thereby, depends on the difference in location between the auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b> and the guide unit <b>20</b>, as well as the height of the auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The guide unit <b>20</b> may be driven by a driving motor, as in the previous embodiment. To this end, the driving motor may be positioned on a side of a frame <b>20</b>′. If a driving motor is used, driving control may be necessary to control the rotation speed of the driving motor, so that the traveling speed of the substrate <b>10</b> can be controlled.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Meanwhile, it is not mandatory to provide the frame <b>20</b>′ with a driving motor, which supplies driving power to move the substrate <b>10</b>. In other words, a separate driving source may provide the driving power to move the substrate <b>10</b>, while the guide unit <b>20</b> is simply rotated together with the substrate <b>10</b> and guides it. Such a configuration will be described later in relation to a supplying unit <b>60</b> and a winding unit <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The guide unit <b>20</b> may be positioned along the longitudinal direction of the frame <b>20</b>′, that is, along a direction perpendicular to the moving direction of the substrate <b>10</b>. To this end, a guide unit controller unit <b>25</b> is positioned on the frame <b>20</b>′ and the guide unit <b>20</b> is supported thereby.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">The mask <b>40</b> is supported on the frame <b>20</b>′ by an alignment controller unit <b>40</b>′. The alignment controller unit <b>40</b>′ is adapted to adjust the mask <b>40</b> precisely. The alignment controller unit <b>40</b>′ plays the role of aligning the mask <b>40</b> parallel to the vertical section H of the photosensitive agent, which has been applied on the substrate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">A feature is preferably provided to align the light source <b>50</b> relative to the mask <b>40</b>. In particular, the light source <b>50</b> is preferably positioned so that the light, which is irradiated from the light source <b>50</b>, is accurately incident on the vertical section H via the mask <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Meanwhile, a feature is provided to continuously supply the substrate <b>10</b> to the guide unit <b>20</b> and continuously collect the substrate <b>10</b>, which has been subject to exposure. In particular, the substrate <b>10</b> is wound into a roll form and placed in a supply unit <b>60</b>. The substrate <b>10</b> is then continuously unwound and supplied to the guide unit. A winding unit <b>70</b> is also provided to wind the substrate, which has been subject to exposure, into a roll form and collect it from the guide unit <b>20</b>. Alternatively, the substrate, which has been subject to exposure, may be continuously supplied to the next process and wound on the winding portion <b>70</b>, after the pattern formation is over.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">To this end, the winding unit <b>70</b> should exert a drawing force to wind the substrate <b>10</b>. In that case, the winding unit <b>70</b> acts as a driving source. Of course, another driving source may be positioned on the moving path of the substrate <b>10</b> to move the substrate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a third embodiment of the present invention. For clarity, the same components as in the previous embodiment are given the same reference numerals and repeated explanation thereof will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">In the present embodiment, a guide unit <b>120</b>, which guides a substrate <b>10</b>, is not rotated but fixed. The guide unit <b>120</b> does not need to have a curved surface anywhere but in a region adjacent to the top point t thereof, which contacts the substrate <b>10</b> and guides it. Except for this detail, the guide unit <b>120</b> may be arbitrarily configured.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">For reference, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref><i>a</i>, the region from point “a” to the top point t is preferably composed of a curved surface, while the region from the top point “t” to point “b” may be composed of a flat surface. In that case, it is possible to modify the period of time during which the photosensitive agent is subject to exposure, by adjusting the length of the flat surface region.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Although not shown in the drawing, the guide unit <b>120</b> may be provided with an auxiliary guide unit, which forces the moving substrate <b>10</b> against the guide unit <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">As such, in the present embodiment, the guide unit <b>120</b> is fixed and just guides the movement of the substrate <b>10</b>. Accordingly, a supply unit <b>60</b> and a winding unit <b>70</b> provide the power necessary for the movement of the substrate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">The supply unit <b>60</b> continuously supplies the substrate <b>10</b>, while the winding unit <b>70</b> pulls and winds the substrate <b>10</b>. Therefore, the winding unit <b>70</b> acts as a driving source. Of course, a separate driving source may be positioned in the movement path of the substrate <b>10</b> to provide the driving power to move the substrate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">A mask <b>40</b> is positioned parallel to the vertical section H of the substrate <b>10</b> so that beams <b>52</b> are selectively irradiated on the vertical section H. The configuration of the mask <b>40</b> is the same as in the previous embodiment. The beams <b>52</b>, which are irradiated on the substrate <b>10</b>, are provided from a light source <b>50</b>. A feature may also be provided to align the mask <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">A patterning method using a patterning apparatus, configured as above, according to the present invention will now be described in detail with reference to the flow chart shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">A substrate <b>10</b>, which has a photosensitive agent applied on its surface, is continuously supplied between a guide unit <b>20</b> and an auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b> (step <b>1</b>). The substrate <b>10</b> is moved while contacting a surface of the guide unit <b>20</b>. The auxiliary guide unit <b>22</b> plays the role of forcing the substrate <b>10</b> against the surface of the guide unit <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">An alignment controller unit <b>40</b>′ is used to accurately position a mask <b>40</b> so that beams <b>52</b>, which are irradiated from a light source <b>50</b>, are correctly transmitted to a vertical section H (step <b>2</b>). Of course, the light source <b>50</b> should be correctly positioned relative to the mask <b>40</b> or the guide unit <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">The light source <b>50</b> irradiates beams <b>52</b>, while the substrate <b>10</b> is moved and guided by the guide unit <b>20</b>. The beams <b>52</b> pass through an opening <b>42</b> of the mask <b>40</b> and subject the photosensitive agent of the substrate <b>10</b> to exposure with a shape corresponding to that of the opening <b>42</b> (step <b>3</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">As such, while the substrate <b>10</b> is continuously supplied to the guide unit <b>20</b>, the beams <b>52</b>, which are provided from the light source <b>50</b>, continuously pass through the mask <b>40</b> and are irradiated on the vertical section H of the substrate <b>10</b>. Accordingly, the photosensitive agent is continuously subject to exposure and a continuous pattern is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">The period of time during which the photosensitive agent is subject to exposure or a necessary amount of exposure may be obtained by calculation. Of course, the exposure period or the exposure amount should be modified according to the type of the photosensitive agent or the beams <b>52</b>. The exposure period or the exposure amount may be controlled based on the speed of the substrate <b>10</b>, which is moved and guided by the guide unit <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">After the photosensitive agent is subject to exposure in the guide unit <b>20</b>, the substrate <b>10</b> is again wound into a roll form (step S<b>4</b>). Of course, the steps for supply, collection, and exposure of the substrate <b>10</b>, among other steps, are performed simultaneously and continuously, once they are begun.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Several steps should be performed additionally, including removing the photosensitive agent from parts, which have been subject to exposure, or from parts, which have not, to complete a pattern on the photosensitive agent, which has been subject to exposure through the above processes.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8</figref><i>a </i>to <b>8</b><i>c </i>present examples of patterns <b>15</b>, which have been formed on a substrate <b>10</b> according to a method of the present invention. Needless to say, the inventive method can form patterns having various sectional shapes, besides the patterns <b>15</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8</figref><i>a </i>to <b>8</b><i>c. </i></p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">In summary, the basic technological idea of the present invention is as follows: beams <b>52</b> are vertically irradiated on a vertical section H of a substrate <b>10</b>, which is continuously supplied along the outer peripheral surface of a guide unit <b>20</b> and through the top point t thereof, so that patterns of various sectional shapes can be fabricated in a continuous manner.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">As mentioned above, the patterning apparatus and the patterning method according to the present invention are advantageous in that a pattern of a predetermined sectional shape can be formed in a relatively large area and thus a pattern for a large-area display can be fabricated easily.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">Based on a completed pattern, beams are irradiated from a lateral surface, not from a top surface, of the pattern. This minimizes the spacing between patterns and enables the fabrication of a micro-pattern. Accordingly, it is possible to fabricate a highly-integrated pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">The lateral irradiation also makes it possible to continuously fabricate patterns having the same sectional shape. This reduces the process time for forming patterns and improves production efficiency.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">Furthermore, the lateral irradiation makes it relatively easy to adjust the height of the patterns. Accordingly, patterns of various heights can be fabricated. Since the beams are irradiated on the upper and lower portions of a pattern at the same time, the upper and lower portions are subject to the same amount of exposure. This makes the width of the pattern uniform.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">Although a preferred embodiment of the present invention has been described for illustrative purposes, those skilled in the art will appreciate that various modifications, additions and substitutions are possible, without departing from the scope and spirit of the invention as disclosed in the accompanying claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A patterning apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a guide unit for continuously guiding a flexible substrate, which has a photosensitive agent applied thereon, wherein said guide unit is a roller having a cylindrical shape;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light source for irradiating beams on a section of the photosensitive agent, which has been applied on the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a mask positioned between the substrate, which is guided by said guide unit, and said light source so that the beams are selectively transmitted to the photosensitive agent; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an auxiliary guide unit located beside and spaced from said guide unit, so that the substrate is guided while being forced against said guide unit,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide unit presents a curved surface over which the flexible substrate with the photosensitive agent passes while being irradiated by said light source.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the flexible substrate passes over a top point of said guide unit while being irradiated by said light source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a vertical section of the flexible substrate with the photosensitive agent is irradiated by beams of said light source which are approximately perpendicular to the vertical section.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said roller is directly or indirectly driven by a driving motor to rotate in a same direction or an opposite direction as a movement direction of the substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a supply unit for supplying the substrate to said guide unit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a winding unit for collecting the substrate, which has been subject to exposure as it passes by said guide unit, wherein at least one of said supply and winding units provides driving power to move the substrate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said guide unit and said mask are installed on a frame.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>an alignment controller unit for controlling an alignment of said mask.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>an guide unit adjustment unit for controlling a position of said guide unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said light source emits x-rays.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A patterning apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a supply unit for continuously supplying a flexible substrate, which has a photosensitive agent applied thereon;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a guide unit adapted to continuously guide the substrate, which is supplied from said supply unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light source for irradiating beams on a section of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a mask positioned between the substrate, which is guided by said guide unit, and said light source so that the beams are selectively transmitted to the photosensitive agent; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a winding unit for collecting and winding the substrate, which has been subject to exposure as it passes by said guide unit,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide unit has a curved surface formed at least from a point at which the substrate contacts said guide unit from a supply unit side to a point at which the substrate is irradiated,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide unit has a flat surface formed in a predetermined region from the point at which the substrate is irradiated to a point at which the substrate leaves said guide unit to travel to said winding unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said guide unit is fixed in its location.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the substrate is subject to exposure as it passes by a top point of said guide unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein a vertical section of the substrate is subject to exposure as it passes by a top point of said guide unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said guide unit and said mask are installed on a frame.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>an alignment controller unit for controlling an alignment of said mask.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The patterning apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>an guide unit adjustment unit for controlling a position of said guide unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method of pattering a flexible substrate, comprising:
<claim-text>supplying a flexible substrate, which has a photosensitive agent applied on a surface of the substrate.</claim-text>
<claim-text>guiding the flexible substrate to pass a curved portion of a guide unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>operating a light source to emit light beams;</claim-text>
<claim-text>passing the light beams through a mask; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>irritating the light beams, passing through the mask, onto the photosensitive agent of the substrate, as the flexible substrate passes by the curved portion of the guide unit,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said step of irritating the light beams onto the photosensitive agent of the substrate occurs as the flexible substrate passes over a top point of the guide unit,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a vertical section of the photosensitive agent and the substrate is irradiated, and the light beams are irradiated in a direction approximately perpendicular to the vertical section.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, further comprising collecting the irradiated flexible substrate in a winding unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein the mask is positioned parallel to the vertical section.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein a period of time during which the beams are irradiated on the photosensitive agent, and the amount of irradiation are determined by a speed control unit, which guides and moves the flexible substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
