<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297992-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297992</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10997534</doc-number>
<date>20041123</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>50</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>739</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257197</main-classification>
<further-classification>257198</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E21372</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E29188</further-classification>
<further-classification>438310</further-classification>
<further-classification>438312</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Method and structure for integration of phosphorous emitter in an NPN device in a BiCMOS process</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5164797</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Thornton</name>
<date>19921100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>372 4501</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6437376</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ozkan</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257197</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6593640</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kalnitsky et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257565</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0080394</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Babcock et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257555</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>6</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257197</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257565</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257588</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257592</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257555</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257199</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21372</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E29188</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257198</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438311</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438322</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438547</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438309</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438312</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438310</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438317</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>U'Ren</last-name>
<first-name>Greg D.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Corona del Mar</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Farjami &amp; Farjami LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Newport Fab, LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Newport Beach</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Tran</last-name>
<first-name>Minh-Loan</first-name>
<department>2826</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">According to one exemplary embodiment, a heterojunction bipolar transistor includes a base situated on a substrate. The heterojunction bipolar transistor can be an NPN silicon-germanium heterojunction bipolar transistor, for example. The heterojunction bipolar transistor further includes a cap layer situated on the base, where the cap layer includes a barrier region. The barrier region can comprises carbon and has a thickness, where the thickness of the barrier region determines a depth of an emitter-junction of the heterojunction bipolar transistor. An increase in the thickness of the barrier region can cause a decrease in the depth of the emitter-base junction. According to this exemplary embodiment, the heterojunction bipolar transistor further includes an emitter situated over the cap layer, where the emitter comprises an emitter dopant, which can be phosphorus. A diffusion retardant in the barrier region of the cap layer impedes diffusion of the emitter dopant.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="190.67mm" wi="253.41mm" file="US07297992-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="260.27mm" wi="216.07mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297992-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="218.36mm" wi="207.94mm" file="US07297992-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="186.94mm" wi="182.71mm" file="US07297992-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention is generally in the field of fabrication of semiconductor devices. More specifically, the invention is in the field of fabrication of bipolar transistors.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">As Bipolar Complementary-Metal-Oxide-Semiconductor (“BiCMOS”) technology continues to advance in an effort to achieve increased device speed and reduced power consumption, it becomes more difficult to transparently integrate high performance bipolar devices, such as high performance NPN devices, with CMOS devices. High performance NPN devices, such as NPN silicon-germanium (SiGe) heterojunction bipolar transistors (HBT), require a shallow emitter-base junction and low emitter resistance while CMOS devices require a CMOS process with a low thermal budget for advanced BiCMOS technology.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">By way of background, in a BiCMOS process, rapid thermal processing (RTP), which is a high temperature, fast annealing process, is typically used to activate dopants and repair implant damage in the bipolar and CMOS regions of the semiconductor die. Typically, arsenic is used as an emitter dopant for NPN devices because arsenic has a high solid solubility limit, which allows the emitter to be heavily doped with arsenic to achieve a low emitter resistance. Arsenic also has a low diffusion coefficient, which limits the diffusion of arsenic into the base during the RTP process to achieve a shallow emitter-base junction.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As bipolar and CMOS devices are scaled down in advanced BiCMOS processes, CMOS device formation requires a reduced thermal budget. However, the reduced thermal budget results in lower activation of arsenic and, consequently, increased emitter resistance, which reduces NPN device performance. An N type dopant with a lower activation temperature, such as phosphorus, could be used in place of arsenic to dope the emitter of the NPN device. However, the high diffusion coefficient of phosphorus causes phosphorus to diffuse significantly into the base region of the NPN device during RTP. As a result, phosphorus causes an undesirably deep emitter-base junction to be formed in the NPN device, which reduces performance of the NPN device.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Thus, there is a need in the art for an NPN device having low emitter resistance and a shallow emitter-base junction that can be effectively integrated with a CMOS device in a BiCMOS process.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention is directed to method and structure for integrating a phosphorus emitter in an NPN device in a BiCMOS process. The present invention overcomes the need in the art for an NPN device having a low emitter resistance and a shallow emitter-base junction that can be effectively integrated with a CMOS device in a BiCMOS process.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">According to one exemplary embodiment, a heterojunction bipolar transistor includes a base situated on a substrate. The heterojunction bipolar transistor can be an NPN silicon-germanium heterojunction bipolar transistor, for example. The heterojunction bipolar transistor further includes a cap layer situated on the base, where the cap layer includes a barrier region. The cap layer may be silicon, for example, and the barrier region can comprise carbon. The barrier region may have a thickness of between approximately 50.0 Angstroms and approximately 75.0 Angstroms, for example. The barrier region has a thickness, where the thickness of the barrier region determines a depth of an emitter-junction of the heterojunction bipolar transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According to this exemplary embodiment, the heterojunction bipolar transistor further includes an emitter situated over the cap layer, where the emitter comprises an emitter dopant. A diffusion retardant in the barrier region of the cap layer impedes diffusion of the emitter dopant, which can be phosphorus. The diffusion retardant may have a concentration of between approximately 0.2 atomic percent and approximately 1.0 atomic percent in the barrier region, for example. In another embodiment, the present invention is a method that achieves the above-described heterojunction bipolar transistor. Other features and advantages of the present invention will become more readily apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art after reviewing the following detailed description and accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an exemplary structure, including an exemplary NPN SiGe HBT, in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a graph showing dopant profiles in a cap layer and a base of an exemplary NPN SiGe HBT in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a flowchart illustrating the steps taken to implement an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The present invention is directed to method and structure for integrating a phosphorus emitter in an NPN device in a BiCMOS process. The following description contains specific information pertaining to the implementation of the present invention. One skilled in the art will recognize that the present invention may be implemented in a manner different from that specifically discussed in the present application. Moreover, some of the specific details of the invention are not discussed in order not to obscure the invention. The specific details not described in the present application are within the knowledge of a person of ordinary skill in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The drawings in the present application and their accompanying detailed description are directed to merely exemplary embodiments of the invention. To maintain brevity, other embodiments of the invention which use the principles of the present invention are not specifically described in the present application and are not specifically illustrated by the present drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a cross-sectional view of structure <b>100</b>, which is utilized to describe one embodiment of the present invention. Certain details and features have been left out of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> that are apparent to a person of ordinary skill in the art. Although structure <b>100</b> illustrates an exemplary NPN SiGe HBT, the present invention manifestly applies to other similar or related structures, such as other NPN devices. Structure <b>100</b> includes NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b>, which includes collector <b>104</b>, base <b>106</b>, cap layer <b>108</b>, and emitter <b>110</b>. NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b> can be integrated with a CMOS device (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) in a BiCMOS process.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, buried layer <b>112</b>, which can comprise heavily doped N type material, can be formed in substrate <b>114</b> in a manner known in the art. Also shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, collector sinker <b>116</b>, which can also comprise heavily doped N type material, can be formed by diffusion of a high concentration of dopants from the surface of collector sinker <b>116</b> down to buried layer <b>112</b>. Buried layer <b>112</b>, along with collector sinker <b>116</b>, provide a low resistance electrical pathway from collector <b>104</b> through buried layer <b>112</b> and collector sinker <b>116</b> to a collector contact (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Further shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, deep trench structures <b>118</b> and <b>120</b> and field oxide structures <b>122</b>, <b>124</b>, and <b>126</b> are situated in substrate <b>114</b> and provide electrical isolation between NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b> and other devices on substrate <b>114</b>. Deep trench structures <b>118</b> and <b>120</b> and field oxide structures <b>122</b>, <b>124</b>, and <b>126</b> can comprise silicon oxide material and can be formed in a manner known in the art. Also shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, collector <b>104</b> is situated over buried layer <b>112</b> and can be N type single crystal silicon, which might be deposited epitaxially using a chemical vapor deposition (CVD) process, a reduced pressure chemical vapor deposition (RPCVD) process, or other appropriate process.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Also shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, base <b>106</b> is situated over substrate <b>114</b> and situated on top of, and forms a junction with, collector <b>104</b>. Base <b>106</b> can be P type silicon-germanium single crystal, which can include a base dopant, such as boron, and might be deposited epitaxially in a “nonselective” RPCVD process or other appropriate process. Further shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, cap layer <b>108</b> is situated over base <b>106</b> and can comprise single crystal silicon, which might be epitaxially deposited using a CVD process, a RPCVD process, or other appropriate process. In one embodiment, cap layer <b>108</b> can comprise silicon-germanium. By way of example, thickness <b>128</b> of cap layer <b>108</b> can be approximately 100.0 Angstroms.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, cap layer <b>108</b> includes barrier region <b>130</b> which, in accordance to the teachings of an embodiment of the present invention, can comprise carbon. Barrier region <b>130</b> extends from top surface <b>132</b> of cap layer <b>108</b> toward base <b>106</b> and can be formed by doping a portion of cap layer <b>108</b> with carbon. By way of example, thickness <b>134</b> of barrier region <b>130</b> can be between approximately 50.0 Angstroms and approximately 75.0 Angstroms. In one embodiment, thickness <b>134</b> of barrier region <b>130</b> can be approximately equal to thickness <b>128</b> of cap layer <b>108</b>. In one embodiment, barrier region <b>130</b> can have a carbon concentration level of between approximately 0.2 atomic percent and approximately 1.0 atomic percent. In one embodiment of the present invention, barrier region <b>130</b> is formed in cap layer <b>108</b> to retard diffusion of phosphorus, which is utilized in one embodiment as an emitter dopant.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As further shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, emitter <b>110</b> is situated on cap layer <b>108</b> and can comprise N type polycrystalline silicon which, according to an embodiment of the present invention, can be doped with an emitter dopant such as phosphorus. In one embodiment, emitter <b>110</b> may comprise amorphous silicon, which can be doped with phosphorus. Emitter <b>110</b> may be formed by depositing, patterning, etching, and doping a layer of polycrystalline silicon with phosphorus, i.e. an N type dopant, in a manner known in the art. By application of heat to structure <b>100</b> in a subsequent RTP process, phosphorus in emitter <b>110</b> can diffuse into base <b>106</b> to form an emitter-base junction. Also shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, dielectric segments <b>136</b> and <b>138</b>, which can comprise silicon oxide, provide electrical isolation between emitter <b>110</b> and base <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">By way of background, characteristics and functionality of the present exemplary NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b> are affected and can be tailored by varying steps of the fabrication process. In particular, it is desirable to accurately control the dopant profiles of cap layer <b>108</b> and base <b>106</b> to achieve a desired NPN HBT performance. In the present application, a dopant profile in cap layer <b>108</b> is also referred to as a concentration of a cap layer dopant, such as carbon, in cap layer <b>108</b> and a dopant profile in base <b>106</b> is also referred to as a concentration of a base dopant, such as boron, in base <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Graph <b>200</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows exemplary dopant profiles in the cap layer and base of an exemplary NPN SiGe HBT in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. In particular, carbon profile <b>202</b> in graph <b>200</b> shows a carbon profile in cap layer <b>108</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Also, boron profile <b>204</b>, germanium profile <b>206</b>, and carbon profile <b>208</b>, respectively, in graph <b>200</b> show boron, germanium, and carbon profiles in base <b>106</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Graph <b>200</b> includes concentration level axis <b>210</b> plotted against depth axis <b>212</b>. Concentration level axis <b>210</b> shows a relative concentration level of carbon in carbon profile <b>202</b> in cap layer <b>108</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Concentration level axis <b>210</b> also shows relative concentration levels of boron, germanium, and carbon, respectively, in boron profile <b>204</b>, germanium profile <b>206</b>, and carbon profile <b>208</b> in base <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Depth axis <b>212</b> shows increasing depth in cap layer <b>108</b> and base <b>106</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, starting at top surface <b>132</b> of cap layer <b>108</b>. Thus, “0” on depth axis <b>212</b> indicates the approximate transition from emitter <b>110</b> to cap layer <b>108</b>. Additionally, depth <b>214</b> on depth axis <b>212</b> indicates the collector-base junction, i.e. the transition from base <b>106</b> to collector <b>104</b>, of NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Boron profile <b>204</b> shows the concentration of boron in base <b>106</b>, plotted against depth, i.e. distance into base <b>106</b>. It is noted that boron is used as an exemplary P type dopant in the present exemplary NPN SiGe HBT for the purpose of illustrating the present invention by way of a specific example. However, the principles of the present invention apply equally to an NPN HBT using a different P type dopant in its base and even to a PNP HBT using an N type dopant in its base.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Continuing with graph <b>200</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, germanium profile <b>206</b> shows the concentration of germanium in base <b>106</b>, plotted against depth, i.e. distance into base <b>106</b>. Germanium profile <b>206</b> begins at depth <b>216</b>, i.e. the top surface of base <b>106</b>, and it (i.e. germanium profile <b>206</b>) ends at depth <b>214</b>, which corresponds to the collector-base junction, i.e. the transition from base <b>106</b> to collector <b>104</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The germanium concentration level ramps up from germanium concentration level <b>218</b> to germanium concentration level <b>220</b> and ramps down to germanium concentration level <b>222</b> in base <b>106</b>. In one embodiment, the germanium concentration levels <b>218</b> and <b>222</b> may be approximately equal to 0.0 atomic percent of germanium. By way of background, increasing the concentration of germanium in a base of an NPN SiGe HBT allows an electric field to build up in the base, which produces the desirable result of increasing performance of the NPN SiGe HBT.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Continuing with graph <b>200</b>, carbon profile <b>208</b> shows the concentration of carbon in base <b>106</b>, plotted against depth, i.e. distance into base <b>106</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, carbon profile <b>208</b> increases to carbon concentration level <b>224</b> between depth <b>226</b> and depth <b>228</b> in base <b>106</b>. By way of example, carbon concentration level <b>224</b> can be approximately 0.2 atomic percent of carbon. According to embodiments of the invention, carbon is introduced into base <b>106</b> of NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b> to retard boron diffusion, which can undesirably increase the effective base width. For example, an RTP process utilized in the fabrication of NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b> can cause boron to diffuse into adjoining silicon regions of NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b>, which can severely degrade the performance of NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Continuing with graph <b>200</b>, carbon profile <b>202</b> shows the concentration of carbon in cap layer <b>108</b>, plotted against depth, i.e. distance into cap layer <b>108</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, carbon profile <b>202</b> has carbon concentration level <b>232</b> between “0” on depth axis <b>212</b>, i.e. top surface <b>132</b> of cap layer <b>108</b>, and depth <b>230</b>. By way of example, carbon concentration level <b>230</b> can be between approximately 0.2 atomic percent of carbon and approximately 1.0 atomic percent of carbon. The portion of cap layer <b>108</b> between “0” on depth axis <b>212</b> and depth <b>230</b> corresponds to barrier region <b>130</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. According to the embodiments of the invention, barrier region <b>130</b>, which is doped with carbon, is formed to retard diffusion of phosphorus which, according to embodiments of the invention, is used as an N type dopant in emitter <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">By forming barrier region <b>130</b> in cap layer <b>108</b>, the present invention retards diffusion of an emitter dopant, for example phosphorus, into base <b>106</b> during a subsequent RTP process, which is used to activate emitter, base, and collector dopants in NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b>. By retarding diffusion of a dopant such as phosphorus into base <b>106</b>, the present invention advantageously achieves control over the depth of the emitter-base junction, formed during the RTP process.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">By way of background, the emitter-base junction of an NPN SiGe HBT is typically formed during an anneal process, such as an RTP process, where an N type emitter dopant, such as phosphorus, diffuses into the base in close proximity of a P type base dopant, such as boron. By controlling thickness <b>134</b> of barrier region <b>130</b>, the present invention can control the diffusion of the emitter dopant, i.e. phosphorus, into base <b>106</b> and, consequently, control the depth of the emitter-base junction. For example, decreasing thickness <b>134</b> of barrier region <b>130</b> provides a deeper emitter-base junction while increasing thickness <b>134</b> of barrier region <b>130</b> provides a shallower emitter-base junction.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Also, by forming carbon-doped barrier region <b>130</b> in cap layer <b>108</b>, the present invention can effectively utilize phosphorus as an emitter dopant in a BiCMOS process which requires a reduced thermal budget. By way of background, advanced BiCMOS processes require a reduced thermal budget with a lower RTP temperature, such as an RTP temperature of approximately 1000.0° C. or lower, to transparently and effectively integrate CMOS and NPN devices. However, at an RTP temperature of approximately 1000.0° C., a conventional emitter dopant, such as arsenic, does not completely activate, which undesirably increases emitter resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Although phosphorus has high activation at an RTP temperature of approximately 1000.0° C., phosphorus also has a higher diffusion coefficient than arsenic. As a result, in a conventional fabrication process, phosphorus can diffuse deeper into the base than arsenic and, thereby, cause an undesirably deep emitter-base junction, which reduces the speed of the NPN device. However, by forming a barrier region comprising carbon in a cap layer to retard phosphorus diffusion, the present invention can utilize phosphorus as an emitter dopant to achieve a transistor with a desirably low emitter resistance and a desirably shallow emitter-base junction in an advanced BiCMOS process.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows flowchart <b>300</b>, which describes the steps, according to one embodiment of the present invention, of a process by which the NPN SiGe HBT in structure <b>100</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is fabricated. Certain details and features have been left out of flowchart <b>300</b> that are apparent to a person of ordinary skill in the art. For example, a step may consist of one or more substeps or may involve specialized equipment or materials, as known in the art. Steps <b>302</b> through <b>308</b> indicated in flowchart <b>300</b> are sufficient to describe one embodiment of the present invention, other embodiments of the invention may utilize steps different from those shown in flowchart <b>300</b>. It is noted that the processing steps shown in flowchart <b>300</b> are performed on a wafer, which, prior to step <b>302</b>, includes a silicon substrate including field a collector, a collector sinker, field oxide and deep trench structures, and a buried layer.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">At step <b>302</b> in flowchart <b>300</b>, a P type base, i.e. base <b>106</b>, is formed over an N type collector, i.e. collector <b>104</b>, in a substrate, i.e. substrate <b>114</b>. Base <b>106</b> forms a junction with collector <b>104</b> and can be P type silicon-germanium single crystal, which can include a base dopant, such as boron, and might be deposited epitaxially in a “nonselective” RPCVD process or other appropriate process. Base <b>106</b> can also includes carbon, which is used to retard the diffusion of boron during a subsequent RTP process. At step <b>304</b>, a cap layer, i.e. cap layer <b>108</b>, which includes a barrier region, i.e. barrier region <b>130</b>, is formed over the base. Cap layer <b>108</b> is situated over base <b>106</b> and can comprise single crystal silicon, which might be epitaxially deposited using a CVD process, a RPCVD process, or other appropriate process.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Barrier region <b>130</b> can be formed by doping a portion of cap layer <b>108</b> with carbon and has thickness <b>134</b>. By way of example, thickness <b>134</b> can be between approximately 50.0 Angstroms and approximately 75.0 Angstroms. By way of example, barrier region <b>130</b> can have a carbon concentration level of between approximately 0.2 atomic percent and approximately 1.0 atomic percent. Barrier region <b>130</b> is formed to retard the diffusion of an emitter dopant such as phosphorus. In step <b>306</b>, a phosphorus-doped N type emitter, i.e. emitter <b>110</b>, is formed over the cap layer. Emitter <b>110</b> is situated on cap layer <b>108</b> and can comprise N type polycrystalline silicon, which can be doped with phosphorus. Emitter <b>110</b> may be formed by depositing, patterning, etching, and doping a layer of polycrystalline silicon with phosphorus, i.e. an N type dopant, in a manner known in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In step <b>308</b>, a RTP process is performed to activate emitter, base, and collector dopants and to form an emitter-base junction in, for example, NPN SiGe HBT <b>102</b>. The emitter-base junction can be formed by diffusion of phosphorus into base <b>106</b> at an RTP temperature of approximately 1000.0° C., for example. Barrier region <b>130</b>, which comprises carbon, retards the diffusion of phosphorus, which enables the depth of emitter-base junction to be controlled. For example, the depth of the emitter-base junction can be controlled by appropriately determining the thickness, i.e. thickness <b>134</b>, of barrier region <b>130</b> and the carbon concentration in barrier region <b>130</b>. For example, thickness <b>134</b> can be between approximately 50.0 Angstroms and approximately 75.0 Angstroms while the carbon concentration in barrier region <b>130</b> can be between approximately 0.2 atomic percent of carbon and approximately 1.0 atomic percent of carbon.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Thus, as discussed above, the present invention forms a barrier layer comprising a diffusion retardant, for example, carbon, in a cap layer to impede diffusion of an emitter dopant, for example, phosphorus, into the base of a transistor. As a result, the present invention effectively integrates a phosphorus emitter in a transistor, such as an NPN SiGe HBT, in an advanced BiCMOS process, to advantageously achieve a desirably low emitter resistance and a desirably shallow emitter-base junction.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">From the above description of the invention it is manifest that various techniques can be used for implementing the concepts of the present invention without departing from its scope. Moreover, while the invention has been described with specific reference to certain embodiments, a person of ordinary skills in the art would recognize that changes can be made in form and detail without departing from the spirit and the scope of the invention. For example, the principles of the present invention are also applicable to transistors using a P type dopant other than boron, or using a diffusion retardant other than carbon. Moreover, the present invention is applicable to transistors using semiconductors other than silicon or germanium. Further, the present invention's principles can also be applied to PNP transistors, PNP HBTs, or PNP SiGe HBTs.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">As such, the described embodiments are to be considered in all respects as illustrative and not restrictive. It should also be understood that the invention is not limited to the particular embodiments described herein, but is capable of many rearrangements, modifications, and substitutions without departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Thus, method and structure for integrating a phosphorus emitter in an NPN device in a BiCMOS process have been described.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A heterojunction bipolar transistor comprising:
<claim-text>a base situated over a collector, said collector being situated in a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cap layer situated on said base, said cap layer comprising a barrier region;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an emitter situated over said cap layer, said emitter comprising an emitter dopant;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a diffusion retardant in said barrier region of said cap layer impedes diffusion of said emitter dopant, wherein said barrier region has a thickness, wherein said thickness of said barrier region determines a depth of an emitter-base junction of said heterojunction bipolar transistor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The heterojunction bipolar transistor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein an increase in said thickness of said barrier region causes a decrease in said depth of said emitter-base junction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The heterojunction bipolar transistor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said diffusion retardant has a concentration of between approximately 0.2 atomic percent and approximately 1.0 atomic percent in said barrier region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A method of fabricating a heterojunction bipolar transistor, said method comprising steps of:
<claim-text>forming a base over a collector, said collector being situated in a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a cap layer over said base, said cap layer comprising a barrier region;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming an emitter over said cap layer, said emitter comprising an emitter dopant;</claim-text>
<claim-text>performing rapid thermal processing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said barrier region of said cap layer impedes diffusion of said emitter dopant into said base during said rapid thermal processing step, wherein a diffusion retardant in said barrier region of said cap layer impedes diffusion of said emitter dopant.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein said barrier region has a thickness, wherein said thickness of said barrier region determines a depth of an emitter-base junction of said heterojunction bipolar transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein an increase in said thickness of said barrier region causes a decrease in said depth of said emitter-base junction.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
