<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297095-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297095</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10547870</doc-number>
<date>20040225</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>84</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>26</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>71</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>482142</main-classification>
<further-classification>482 94</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Rotary torso exercise bench</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6015370</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Pandozy</name>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>482 97</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6468191</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Cameron</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>482140</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>15</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>482142</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>D21676</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>D21686</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>D21690</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>D21 94- 96</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060172869</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060803</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zachary</last-name>
<first-name>Kyriacos Mark</first-name>
<address>
<street>819 W. Seminary Ave.</street>
<city>Lutherville</city>
<state>MD</state>
<postcode>21093</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ober/Kaler</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Craig</last-name>
<first-name>Royal W.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Amerson</last-name>
<first-name>Lori</first-name>
<department>3764</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/US2004/005667</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040225</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20050902</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2004/078268</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20040916</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A rotary torso exercise machine that isolates and targets the internal and external oblique muscles on both sides of the torso as well as providing conditioning to the rectus abdominis muscle. The machine supports a user's body in a generally supine position and includes five essential features, a frame, fixed feet stabilizing rollers, a fixed lower torso support or seat, a rotatable upper torso support, and a peg for holding free weights that impart resistance against the rotation of the upper torso support. The user may selectively vary the mount and direction of resistance as well as the degree of rotation. The machine may be easily converted for use as either a back or abdominal exercise.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="128.19mm" wi="179.15mm" file="US07297095-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="179.32mm" wi="128.78mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="127.93mm" wi="135.81mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="189.06mm" wi="129.54mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="159.51mm" wi="122.94mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="143.09mm" wi="129.46mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="156.72mm" wi="131.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="131.15mm" wi="133.77mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="160.27mm" wi="136.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="117.43mm" wi="123.36mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297095-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to an exercise machine. Specifically, it relates to a rotary torso exercise machine.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Rotary torso exercises are used to workout the mid-section of the body. Specifically, these exercises target the oblique muscles on both sides of the midsection. Rotating your torso to the right works the right internal and left external oblique muscles. Rotating your torso to the left works the left internal and right external oblique muscles. The rectus abdominis muscle is also involved in both movements. Thus, rotary torso exercises are ideal for overall midsection strengthening. Conditioning the rotary torso muscles is particularly important for sports requiring a swinging motion, such as golf, baseball, tennis, hockey, lacrosse, etc., not only to improve the swing, but to prevent injury. Rotary torso exercise machines are exercise machines, which use resistance or weights, to facilitate these rotary torso exercises.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Commercial use exercise machines for gyms and the like typically target one muscle group and are set up as stations. Users move from station to station to perform a variety of exercises on different muscle groups. Exercise machines that target rotary torso muscles, particularly, traditionally have an arrangement similar to that disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 4,456,245 to Baldwin issued Jun. 26, 1984. The rotary torso machine is configured so that a user's body is supported in a generally upright seated position, upper and lower torso portions are engaged so as to restrict movement of the user's body to rotary movement of the upper torso relative to the lower torso about an axis extending longitudinally of the user's body, and force (by means of weights in this instance) is imposed to resist such movement.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Many exercise machines, often designed for home use or smaller gyms, are configured to allow the user to perform a variety of exercises, including rotary torso exercises. Because of the multi-use configurations these machines oftentimes are not able to provide the best exercise for any given muscle/muscle group. For example, U.S. Pat. No. 6,015,370 to Pandozy issued on Jan. 18, 2000, discloses an apparatus and a method for performing four exercises including the rotation or torsion of the lower spine and the lower back muscles. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the user is lying on his back with his upper torso stationary, hips flexed and squeezing one end of a bar between his thighs/knees. The bar is perpendicular to the ground and weights are stacked on a pin at the other end of the bar. At some point between the opposing ends the bar is rotatably mounted on an axle. The exercise is performed by rotation of the hips to the right or left, using stacked free weights as resistance. Another exercise machine advertised on-line by http://www.quantumfitness.com/ab/roto_crunch.shtml, combines a number of mid-torso and abdominal exercises, including a rotary torso machine, on one machine, with the user in the seated position.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Rotary torso exercises with the greatest benefit, are performed with the hips at least partially extended in either a standing or supine position (vice a seated position with hips flexed), so that the targeted oblique and rectus abdominas muscles are able reach maximum extended and flexed positions. In a seated positioned the hips are flexed such that the targeted muscles are necessarily slightly flexed and unable to reach maximum extension during the rotary torso exercises. Performing the exercise in a supine position with hips at least partially extended, vice sitting or standing, also reduces pressure and weight on the lower back and spine, allowing the user to work the targeted area without stress to other areas. Allowing the user to selectively vary the resistance levels as well as the degrees and directions of rotation, further increases the user's ability to effectively target and condition specific muscles in the torso area.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">It would be advantageous over the prior art to provide a rotary torso machine, suitable for commercial use, in which a user's body is supported in a generally supine position with hips at least partially extended with the upper and lower torso portions separately supported and engaged so as to restrict movement of the user's body to rotary movement of the upper torso relative to the lower torso about an axis extending longitudinally of the user's body, and free weights are used to impose and to vary resistance to such movement. Additionally it would be advantageous to provide a mechanism that allows the user to engage the resistance at a desired degree of rotation and to vary the degree and direction of rotation. Lastly, it would be advantageous to provide such a rotary torso machine that may be easily converted to an effective back or abdominal exercise machine. Such a machine would be ideal for home or small gym use, where space for multiple exercise machines may be limited.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It is an object of the present invention to provide a novel method and apparatus for exercising the rotary torso muscles of the human body in a safe, efficient and accurate manner. The exercise machine of the present invention is particularly suited for commercial use in gyms and the like as it targets one muscle group. To accomplish this objective, the present invention is a rotary torso exercise device that works on the torso or mid-section of the body. Specifically, the exercises performed using the device isolate and target the internal and external oblique muscles on both sides of the midsection as well as providing some conditioning to the rectus abdominis muscle.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The device is an exercise machine on which a user's body is supported in a generally supine position. The machine is comprised of a frame structure with an upper torso support (including a head and back rest), a lower torso support (including a seat) and feet stabilizing rollers, aligned longitudinally. While the lower torso support and rollers remain fixed during the exercises, the position of these features relative to upper torso support along the longitudinal axis is adjustable depending upon the size of the user. Attached to the upper torso support are right and left side bars with handles which the user grips for added support and to maintain proper positioning throughout the exercise. The upper torso support is rotatably attached to the frame. In use, the user's upper and lower torsos are engaged so as to restrict movement of the user's body to rotary movement of the upper torso relative to the lower torso about an axis extending longitudinally of the user's body, and force is imposed to resist such movement. Resistance to the rotation movement is provided by free weights.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In one embodiment the head of the frame contains a through bore with an axle mounted there-through. Fixedly attached to the one end of the axle is a weight bar. Attached to the opposite end of the weight bar is a peg for removably mounting free weights. Attached to the inner end of the axle is the upper torso support. In use, the user, holding the handles on the side bars rotates his upper torso to turn the axle. The weights on the weight bar provide resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">This embodiment further comprises a hand control mechanism in which releasing the hand control releases tension on a wire and thereby engages a pin into one of a plurality of wholes encircling the perimeter of a disk that is fixedly attached to the axle. When the pin is engaged, the upper torso support remains in a fixed position about the axle, and rotation of the upper torso support is met with resistance from the weights. Depressing the hand control mechanism tenses the wire and disengages the pin from the disk. When the pin is disengaged, the upper torso support may rotate freely about the axle without resistance. Varying the position of the pin, varies the position of the upper torso support relative to the position of the weight bar, thereby allowing the user to vary the degree of rotation about the user's longitudinal axis during which resistance is imparted as well as the direction of resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In another embodiment, the right and left side bars of the upper torso support are formed from a single U-shaped bar. Multiple weight pegs are attached to the U-shaped bar for holding the free weights used to provide resistance during the rotary torso exercises. The relative positions of the weight pegs (and thus the weights) about the U-shaped bar are adjustable to vary the degree of rotation about the user's longitudinal axis during which resistance is imparted as well as the direction of resistance. Multiple bearings are mounted on the frame to form a track through which the U-shaped bar is guided as the user rotates the upper torso support.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Another object of the present invention is to provide such a rotary torso device, ideal for home use, that may be easily converted to perform abdominal and back exercises by connecting an additional cushioned bar to one of the handles, adjusting the seat (lower torso support) position to be aligned with the additional cushioned bar and changing the position of the feet stabilizing rollers to align with the seat, perpendicular to the longitudinal alignment of the frame. The ability to change the position of the rollers is accomplished by either a pivoting mechanism within the frame or by providing multiple receivers about the frame to receive the rollers at a desired position.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Other objects, features, and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description of the preferred embodiments and certain modifications thereof when taken together with the accompanying drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side view drawing of the preferred embodiment of the rotary torso machine of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded drawing of the pin mechanism for varying the position of the upper torso support relative to the weight bar.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side view drawing of an alternative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a drawing of the preferred modification of the rotary torso machine of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> for use as an abdominal exercise machine.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a drawing of the preferred modification of the rotary torso machine of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> for use as a back exercise machine.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref><i>a</i>-<i>b </i>is a drawing of an alternate modification of the rotary torso machine of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, for use as an abdominal exercise machine.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7</figref><i>a</i>-<i>b </i>is a drawing of an alternate modification of the rotary torso machine of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> for use as a back exercise machine.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BEST MODE OF CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">While the present invention will be described more fully hereinafter with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which the best mode of carrying out the present invention is shown, it is to be understood that the invention herein described may be modified by those skilled in the art of the invention, while still achieving the favorable results of this invention. Accordingly, the description which follows is to be understood as being a broad, teaching disclosure directed to persons of skill in the appropriate arts, and not as limiting upon the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The rotary torso exercise machine of the present invention is essentially an exercise machine on which a user's body is supported in a generally supine position. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 3</figref> illustrate two similar embodiments of a rotary torso machine (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, <b>100</b> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, <b>200</b>). Both embodiments are comprised of five main features: (1) a freestanding frame (<b>101</b>, <b>201</b>), (2) feet stabilizing rollers (<b>102</b>, <b>202</b>), (3) a fixed lower torso support or seat (<b>103</b>, <b>203</b>), (4) a rotatable upper torso support (<b>104</b>, <b>204</b>) connected (directly or indirectly) to the frame <b>102</b>, <b>201</b>, and (5) a peg (<b>125</b>, <b>225</b>) for holding free weights (<b>105</b>, <b>205</b>) that impart resistance against the rotation of the upper torso support (<b>104</b>, <b>204</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The frame (<b>101</b>, <b>201</b>) is the supporting structure preferably made of commercial grade hollow 2″ square steel tubing having a first end <b>106</b>, <b>206</b> and a second end <b>107</b>, <b>207</b>. However, those skilled in the art will recognize that other materials may be suitable for constructing the frame. The upper torso support <b>104</b>, <b>204</b>, lower torso support <b>103</b>, <b>203</b> and rollers <b>102</b>, <b>202</b>, are connected to the frame <b>101</b>, <b>201</b> such that they maintain the position of the user's upper torso, lower, and feet, respectively, in a generally supine position along the longitudinal axis extending the length the frame from the first end <b>106</b>, <b>206</b> to the second end <b>107</b>, <b>207</b>. While the lower torso support <b>103</b>, <b>203</b> and rollers <b>102</b>, <b>202</b> remain fixed during the exercises, the position of these features along the length of the frame may be adjusted by adjustment mechanisms <b>110</b> and <b>111</b> (See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and discussion below), respectively, to accommodate users of various sizes.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The rollers <b>102</b>, <b>202</b> are rotatably mounted to the frame <b>101</b>, <b>201</b> at the second end <b>107</b>, <b>207</b>. The rollers <b>102</b>, <b>202</b> are preferably wrapped in a padded cushion <b>108</b>, <b>208</b> for comfort. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the rollers <b>102</b> may be one element of an adjustable position foot hold <b>115</b>, also including an integral foot rest <b>109</b> and a connecting bar <b>113</b>. The foot hold <b>115</b> is designed immobilize the user's feet during the exercise. The preferred means of connecting the foot hold <b>115</b> onto the frame <b>101</b> is to slide a horizontal connecting bar <b>113</b> into a receiver <b>165</b> at the second end <b>107</b> of the frame <b>101</b>. Bar <b>113</b> further includes a plurality of holes <b>116</b> aligned along the length of bar <b>113</b>. As the user slides the bar <b>113</b> into the frame, the user pulls up adjustment mechanism <b>111</b> (i.e. a simple peg or a spring loaded peg) which allows the bar <b>113</b> to slide freely into the frame <b>101</b> for lateral adjustment. When the mechanism <b>111</b> is released, the bar <b>113</b> is engaged securing the foot hold <b>115</b>. Optionally, the adjustable foot hold <b>115</b> may be configured with a vertical positioning feature to allow the user to adjust not only the relative position of the foot hold <b>115</b> along the longitudinal axis, but also the height of the foot hold <b>115</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Again referring to both <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 3</figref>, the lower torso support <b>103</b>, <b>203</b> is comprised of a pedestal <b>118</b>, <b>218</b> welded or otherwise attached along a midsection <b>170</b>, <b>270</b> to frame <b>101</b>, <b>201</b>. A cushioned seat <b>117</b>, <b>217</b> is slideably attached to the top of pedestal <b>118</b>, <b>218</b> by bracket <b>110</b>, <b>210</b> (or otherwise) thereby allowing the user to adjust the lateral position of seat <b>117</b>, <b>217</b> relative to the upper torso support <b>104</b>, <b>204</b> and the feet stabilizing rollers <b>102</b>, <b>202</b>, along the longitudinal axis. Optionally, the lower torso support <b>103</b>, <b>203</b>, may include a seatbelt <b>150</b>, <b>250</b> to immobilize the user's lower torso during the exercise.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In the preferred embodiment, referring in combination to the illustrations in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and the exploded drawing of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the upper torso support <b>104</b> is designed to support the head, shoulders and upper torso of the user in a supine position. It is comprised of one or more cushions <b>119</b>, attached to and supported by a rigid flat head/back rest structure <b>120</b>. The upper torso support <b>104</b> is further comprised of left and right side bars <b>121</b> as well as a center support bar <b>122</b> molded or otherwise attached to the head/back rest <b>120</b>. Side bars <b>121</b> and support bar <b>122</b> are ideally formed from the same hollow steel tubing as the frame <b>101</b>. The center support bar <b>122</b> of the upper torso support <b>104</b> is rotatably attached to the first end <b>106</b> of the frame <b>101</b>. The preferred means of rotatably attaching the center support arm <b>122</b> to the first end <b>106</b> includes a through bore (not shown) on the center support arm <b>122</b> for mounting the it onto one an axle <b>123</b>, such that it may rotate about the axle <b>123</b>. The axle <b>123</b> is in turn mounted on bushings or bearings (not shown) installed either in a corresponding through-bore in the first end <b>106</b> of frame <b>101</b> or in a bearing block mounted atop first end <b>106</b> that extends along the longitudinal axis of the frame. The axle <b>123</b> extends into another through-bore (not shown) in one end of yet another support bar (weight support arm <b>124</b>) where it is fixedly attached. The opposite end of weight support arm <b>124</b> has an attached protruding peg <b>125</b> for supporting free weights <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Attached to the side bars <b>121</b> are adjustable handles <b>126</b> for providing the user with additional support and bracing during exercises. As with the foot hold <b>115</b>, the preferred means of connecting the handles <b>126</b> onto the sidebars <b>121</b> is to slide a connecting bar <b>132</b> into the hollow of the side bar <b>121</b>. Connecting bar <b>132</b> further includes a plurality of holes <b>133</b> aligned along the length of bar <b>132</b>. As the user slides the bar <b>132</b> into the frame, the user pulls up mechanism <b>134</b> (i.e. a simple peg or a spring loaded peg) which allows the bar <b>132</b> to slide freely into the side bar <b>121</b>, adjusting the height of the handles <b>126</b>. When the mechanism <b>134</b> is released, the bar <b>132</b> is engaged securing the handles <b>126</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Attached to one of the handles <b>126</b> is a hand controlled actuator <b>127</b> connected to cable <b>128</b>. The cable <b>128</b> is in turn connected to a pin mechanism <b>179</b> (i.e. spring loaded pin mechanism) that is fixed to the support bar <b>122</b> adjacent the axle <b>123</b>. Fixedly attached to axle <b>123</b> is a disk <b>130</b> having a plurality of holes <b>131</b> adjacent its perimeter for engagement with the pin mechanism <b>179</b>. Depressing and releasing the actuator <b>127</b> pulls and releases the cable <b>128</b>, respectively, and thereby selectively disengages and engages (locks) the pin <b>129</b> of spring loaded pin mechanism <b>179</b> into disk <b>130</b>. When the pin <b>129</b> is engaged in a hole <b>131</b>, the support bar <b>122</b> is effectively fixed or locked to the axle <b>123</b>, such that rotation of support bar <b>122</b> rotates the axle <b>123</b>, which meets resistance imparted by weights <b>105</b> on arm <b>124</b>. When the pin <b>129</b> is disengaged from a hole <b>131</b>, the support bar <b>122</b> is free to rotate about the axle <b>123</b> in order to vary the position of the pin. Varying the position of the pin <b>129</b> engaged in the disk <b>130</b>, varies the position of the upper torso support <b>104</b> relative to the position of the weight support <b>124</b>, thereby allowing the user to vary the degree of rotation about the user's longitudinal axis during which resistance is imparted as well as the direction of resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The weight support arm <b>124</b> is further comprised of an optional stopping mechanism <b>132</b> (i.e. peg or spring loaded peg mechanism), which may be engaged on either side of the frame <b>101</b> and when engaged prevents the weight support <b>124</b> from rotating beyond a predetermined angle <b>178</b> relative to the frame <b>101</b> (i.e. stops the arm <b>124</b> at an angle of <b>25</b> degrees from perpendicular).</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In operation of the above-described device, the user places free weights <b>105</b> on weight peg <b>125</b>. The user then sits on lower torso support <b>103</b>, placing his feet in foot hold <b>115</b> and lying back onto upper to support <b>104</b>. In the preferred position the lower back remains flat. Holding handles <b>126</b>, the user depresses actuator <b>127</b>, rotates upper torso support <b>104</b> to the desired starting position, and releases actuator <b>127</b>. The user then begins the rotation exercise against the resistance imparted by weights <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In the alternate embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the upper torso support <b>204</b> is similarly designed to support the head, shoulders and upper torso of the user. Upper torso support <b>204</b> is comprised of one or more cushions <b>219</b>, attached to and supported by head/back rest structure <b>220</b>. Attached to the head/back rest <b>220</b> is a U-shaped bar <b>230</b> forming right and left side bars <b>221</b> to the upper torso support <b>204</b>. The semi-circular base <b>280</b> of the U-shaped bar <b>230</b> forms the means for rotating the upper torso. As with the embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, adjustable handles <b>226</b> are connected to the side bars <b>221</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In this alternate embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the U-Shaped bar <b>230</b> further includes a hollow track <b>240</b>. Multiple weight pegs <b>225</b> are seated in the track <b>240</b>. Free weights <b>205</b> are placed on one or more pegs <b>225</b> to impart resistance during the rotation exercises. Each peg <b>225</b> has an engagement mechanism <b>227</b> (i.e. screw or quick release) that when engaged fixes the position of the peg <b>225</b> seated in the track <b>240</b> and when disengaged allows the peg <b>225</b> to slide in the track. Varying the position of the weight pegs <b>225</b> allows the user to vary the position of the weights <b>205</b> and, thereby, the direction of resistance and the degree of rotation during which resistance is imparted. At least three roller bearings <b>241</b> are mounted on the frame <b>201</b>. The bearings <b>241</b> secure the U-shaped bar <b>240</b> vertically to the frame <b>201</b> and guide the U-shaped bar <b>240</b> in a smooth rotation about the longitudinal axis extending the length of the frame as the user rotates his upper torso.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In operation, the user adjusts the position of the weight pegs <b>225</b> in track <b>240</b>. The user then places free weights <b>205</b> on one of the pegs <b>225</b>. The position of the weights <b>225</b> about the track causes the U-shaped bar <b>230</b> to rotate and thereby vary the starting position of the exercise and the degree and direction of rotation of the exercise. The user sits on lower torso support <b>204</b>, hooking feet under rollers <b>202</b> and lays back into upper torso support <b>204</b>. Holding handles <b>126</b>, the user begins the rotation exercises.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Another object of the present invention is to provide a rotary torso device, such as those illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref> and/or <b>2</b>, that may be easily converted to perform abdominal and back exercises. The means for converting the rotary torso device of the present invention into a back and/or abdominal exercise machine is illustrated herein with regards the embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. However, the same modifications may be applied to the device of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-7</figref> combined, the modifications may be accomplished by sliding a cushioned hollow bar <b>160</b> onto one of the handles <b>126</b>, adjusting the position of the seat <b>117</b> so that it is positioned adjacent to the upper torso support <b>104</b> and changing the position of the foot hold <b>115</b> to align with seat <b>117</b> perpendicular to the longitudinal axis extending the length of the frame <b>101</b>. When the cushioned bar <b>160</b> and foot hold <b>115</b> are positioned on the same side of frame <b>101</b>, the device is modified for use as an abdominal exercise machine (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 6</figref>). When the cushioned bar <b>160</b> and the foot hold <b>115</b> are positioned on opposite sides of the frame <b>101</b>, the device is modified for use as a back exercise machine (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 7</figref>). In order to change the position of the seat <b>117</b> and foot hold <b>115</b>, the frame <b>101</b> may be modified in one of two ways.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In the embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, the midsection <b>170</b> of frame <b>101</b> is configured with a hollow cross bar <b>161</b> for receiving the connecting bar <b>113</b> of the foot hold <b>115</b> from either side of the frame <b>101</b>. The cushioned seat <b>117</b> is slidably attached to the top of pedestal <b>118</b> so that the user may adjust the position of seat <b>117</b> adjacent to the upper torso support <b>104</b>. Alternatively, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref>, the midsection <b>170</b> of frame <b>101</b> is configured with a lockable pivoting joint <b>162</b> (locked position <b>1</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref><i>a </i>and <b>7</b><i>a</i>) and locked position <b>2</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref><i>b </i>and <b>7</b><i>b</i>). In position <b>1</b>, the frame <b>101</b> is configured for use as a rotary torso machine. In position <b>2</b>, the frame <b>101</b> is pivoted about the joint <b>162</b>, moving the seat <b>117</b> adjacent to the upper torso support <b>104</b> and foot hold <b>115</b> in perpendicular alignment with the length of the frame <b>101</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In operation, the abdominal and back exercises are performed in a seated on seat <b>117</b> with feet secured in foot hold <b>115</b>. The user will add weights <b>105</b> and adjust the degree and direction of rotation, as discussed above. Abdominal exercises are performed by the using abdominal muscles to push forward on the cushioned bar <b>160</b>. Back exercises are performed by using the back muscles to push backwards against the cushioned bar <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In light of the foregoing, it should be apparent that the rotary torso machine of the present invention provides a unique exercise machine for safely and effectively targeting the rotary torso muscles, and thus ideally suited for commercial use in gyms and the like. It should also be apparent that such a rotary torso machine that is easily converted to a safe and effective abdominal or back exercise machine is ideally suited for use in homes, small gyms or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Having now fully set forth the preferred embodiments and certain modifications of the concept underlying the present invention, various other embodiments as well as certain variations and modifications of the embodiments herein shown and described will obviously occur to those skilled in the art upon becoming familiar with said underlying concept. It is to be understood, therefore, that the invention may be practiced otherwise than as specifically set forth in the appended claims.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">INDUSTRIAL APPLICABILITY</heading>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">There is a significant commercial demand for exercise stations suited for commercial use in gyms and the like that safely and effectively target one muscle group, and particularly the rotary torso muscles. The above-described rotary torso exercise machine places the user in the best position for carrying out rotary torso exercises, namely supine with hips at least slightly extended and feet and lower torso immobile. The device further allows the user to vary the direction and degree of resistance imparted during the exercise. Additionally, the rotary torso exercise machine is easily convertible to target other exercise groups, such as a safe and effective abdominal or back exercise machine, making it well-suited for small gyms or the like.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A rotary torso exercise machine, comprising:
<claim-text>a freestanding frame including two opposing ends, wherein said ends comprise a first end and a second end; and a mid-section between said ends;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an upper torso support rotatably attached to a first end of said frame for supporting a user's upper torso in a supine position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lower torso support attached along a mid-section of said frame, said lower torso support for supporting a user's lower torso in alignment with the upper torso in said supine position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>feet stabilizing rollers attached to a second end of said frame for stabilizing the user's feet in said supine position; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a peg protruding from said upper torso support, for holding free weights to impart resistance against rotation of said upper torso support.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said frame is comprised of hollow tubing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said upper and lower torso supports further comprise cushioning for comfort.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A rotary torso exercise machine comprising: a freestanding frame: an upper torso support rotatably attached to a first end of said frame for supporting a user's upper torso in a supine position: a lower torso support attached alone a mid-section of said frame, said lower torso support for supporting a user's lower torso in alignment with the upper torso in said supine position wherein said lower torso support further comprises a pedestal fixed to a mid-section of said frame and a cushioned seat adjustably attached to said pedestal for lateral positioning along said frame: feet stabilizing rollers attached to a second end of said frame for stabilizing the user's feet in said supine position: and, a peg protruding from said upper torso support, for holding free weights to impart resistance against rotation of said upper torso support.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A rotary torso exercise machine comprising: a freestanding frame: an upper torso support rotatably attached to a first end of said frame for supporting a user's upper torso in a supine position: a lower torso support attached along a mid-section of said frame, said lower torso support for supporting a user's lower torso in alignment with the upper torso in said supine Position: feet stabilizing rollers attached to a second end of said frame for stabilizing the user's feet in said supine position wherein said feet stabilizing rollers further comprise opposing foot rests mounted on a connecting bar, said connecting bar for adjustably connecting said feet stabilizing rollers to said frame: and, a peg protruding from said upper torso support, for holding free weights to impart resistance against rotation of said upper torso support.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said connecting bar is a telescoping connecting bar inserted into said frame, said connecting bar being defined by a plurality of holes along its length, and said frame further comprising a peg mechanism for engaging and disengaging the holes of said sliding connecting bar to adjust the lateral position of said foothold relative to said frame.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said rotatable upper torso support supports the head, shoulders and upper torso of the user during rotation exercises and further comprises left and right side bars with handles for providing the user with additional support and bracing during exercises.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising a weight support arm and a pin mechanism; said weight support arm being rotatably attached at one end to the first end of said frame, the other end of said weight support arm having a protruding peg for holding said free weights; said pin mechanism selectively locking the weight support arm at one of a variety of angular positions relative to said upper torso support; and whereby when free weights are held on the peg of said weight support arm and said pin mechanism is engaged to lock the weight support arm relative to said upper torso support, the user's upper and lower torsos are engaged so as to resist rotary movement of the upper torso relative to the user's lower torso against a weight of said free weights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said upper torso support is further comprised of a head/back rest and a center support bar; and wherein rotatably mounted in the first end of said frame is an axle; fixedly attached to one end of said axle is said weight support arm and rotatably attached on the other end of said axle is said center support bar.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein fixedly attached to said axle is a disk having a plurality of holes adjacent its perimeter; wherein said pin mechanism is comprised of a cable connected to a pin and is fixed to said center support bar adjacent said axle; and wherein one of said handles further comprises a hand controlled actuator; whereby, depressing and releasing the actuator actuates the pin mechanism by pulling and releasing the cable, respectively, disengaging and engaging the pin with one of the holes of said disk such that when the disk is engaged the center support bar is locked to the axle and rotation of the center support bar meets resistance imparted by the free weights held on the weight support arm and when the disk is disengaged the center support bar freely rotates about the axle; thereby the user may vary the position of the upper torso support relative to the position of the weight support arm in order to vary the degree of rotation about the user's longitudinal axis during which resistance is imparted as well as the direction of resistance.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said weight support arm is further comprised of a stopping mechanism which may be engaged to prevent movement of the weight support arm beyond a predetermined angle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The rotary torso exercise machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said upper torso support is comprised of a head/back rest attached to a U-shaped bar; said U-shaped bar forming said right and left side bars and having a semi-circular base; and wherein said frame further comprises at least three bearings for vertically securing the semi circular base of the U-shaped bar to the frame and for guiding the it in a smooth rotation as the user rotates his upper torso.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The rotary torso machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>; wherein said U-shaped bar is further comprised of a hollow track extending the length of the semi-circular base; wherein slideably seated in said track are multiple weight pegs, said weight pegs for holding the free weights for imparting resistance during the rotation exercises; and wherein each of said weight pegs is further comprised of an engagement mechanism for fixing the position of the weight peg in said track; whereby, varying the position of said weight pegs in said track allows the user to vary the position of the weights and, thereby the direction of resistance and the degree of rotation during which resistance is imparted.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The rotary torso machine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, convertible for use as either a back or abdominal exercise machine by repositioning said seat adjacent said upper torso support, repositioning said foot hold perpendicular to said longitudinal axis extending the length of said machine and aligned with said seat, and mounting a cushioned bar on one of said handles; wherein mounting the cushioned bar on the opposite side of the machine as the foot hold converts the machine for use as a back exercise machine and mounting the cushioned bar on the same side of the machine as the foot hold converts the machine for use as an abdominal exercise machine.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The rotary torso machine, according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said lower torso support is further comprised of a seat belt for immobilizing the user's lower torso.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
