<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296880-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296880</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10997977</doc-number>
<date>20041129</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-2003-0097576</doc-number>
<date>20031226</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>248</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>41</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>2</main-group>
<subgroup>05</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347 63</main-classification>
<further-classification>347 64</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Ink-jet printer head having laminated protective layer and method of fabricating the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4951063</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hawkins et al.</name>
<date>19900800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347 62</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4968992</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Komuro</name>
<date>19901100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347 64</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5045870</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lamey et al.</name>
<date>19910900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347 59</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5870121</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chan</name>
<date>19990200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347 59</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6848772</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kim</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>347 63</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>04-39064</doc-number>
<date>19920200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>06-008441</doc-number>
<date>19940100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>0026105</doc-number>
<date>19960600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>960026105</doc-number>
<date>19960600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-334075</doc-number>
<date>19991200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>1996-0026105</doc-number>
<date>19960600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>Korean Official Action issued on Aug. 18, 2005, for Korean Patent Application No. 2003-97576 (lising 1 reference).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347 20</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347 44</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347 47</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347 56- 59</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347 61- 67</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>14</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050140748</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050630</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Min</last-name>
<first-name>Jae-sik</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ha</last-name>
<first-name>Young-ung</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Stanzione &amp; Kim, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung Electronics Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Stephens</last-name>
<first-name>Juanita D.</first-name>
<department>2853</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A heat transfer type ink-jet print head and a method of fabricating the same. A method of fabricating an ink-jet print head includes operations of sequentially laminating a heat generation layer and an electrode layer on a substrate, laminating a protective layer on the top surfaces of the electrode layer and the heat generation layer by sequentially laminating a first protective layer and a second protective layer on the top surfaces of the electrode layer and the heat generation layer, and laminating an ink chamber barrier and a nozzle plate on the top surface of the protective layer to form an ink chamber, wherein defects such as “pin-holes” generated during the formation of the first protective layer are removed by applying a plasma on the first protective layer, and the second protective layer is laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer after any defect produced when laminating the first protective layer is removed.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="93.64mm" wi="278.81mm" file="US07296880-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="204.72mm" wi="131.40mm" file="US07296880-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="179.41mm" wi="102.87mm" file="US07296880-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="182.03mm" wi="106.00mm" file="US07296880-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="197.78mm" wi="132.16mm" file="US07296880-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="201.59mm" wi="128.52mm" file="US07296880-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="214.38mm" wi="130.81mm" file="US07296880-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="226.31mm" wi="153.42mm" file="US07296880-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the benefit of Korean Patent Application No. 2003-97576 filed Dec. 26, 2003, in the Korean Intellectual Property Office, the disclosure of which is incorporated herein in its entirety and by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present general inventive concept relates to an ink-jet print head, and more particularly, to a thermal transfer type ink-jet print head having a protective layer to protect a heat generation layer, and a method of fabricating the same.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Conventionally, an ink-jet print heads may be classified into a piezoelectric type, which ejects ink using a piezoelectric member, and a heat transfer type, which ejects ink using bubbles generated when the ink is instantly heated by a heat generation member.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a conventional heat transfer type ink-jet print head.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a conventional ink-jet print head <b>100</b> comprises a heat generation layer <b>130</b>, an electrode layer <b>140</b>, a protective layer <b>160</b>, which are laminated on a main substrate in this order, and a nozzle <b>195</b>. Here, the heat generation layer <b>130</b> functions to instantly heat ink filled in an ink chamber <b>115</b>, and the electrode layer <b>140</b> functions to apply electric power to the heat generation layer <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The protective layer <b>160</b> functions to protect the heat generation layer <b>130</b>. Such a conventional protective layer <b>160</b> comprises a first protective layer <b>170</b> and a second protective layer <b>180</b> sequentially laminated on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>130</b> and the electrode layer <b>140</b> as disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 4,335,389. Here, the second protective layer <b>180</b> functions to prevent a failure of the heat generation layer <b>130</b>, which is caused by cavitation force generated when bubbles formed within the ink chamber <b>115</b> are contracted after the ink is ejected. In general, the second protective layer <b>180</b> is formed by depositing tantalum (Ta) or tantalum nitride (TaNx) on the top surface of the first protective layer <b>170</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In addition, the first protective layer <b>170</b> functions to insulate the heat generation layer <b>130</b> and the electrode layer <b>140</b> and is formed by depositing any of silicon oxide (SiOx) silicon nitride (SiNx) on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>130</b> and the electrode layer <b>140</b>. The first protective layer <b>170</b> is generally formed by depositing SiNx, which is superior to SiOx in heat conductivity, on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>130</b> and the electrode layer <b>140</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Meanwhile, a conventional first protective layer <b>170</b> formed as described above has defects such as fine holes usually called “pinholes,” which are formed at the time of forming the layer. In particular, these pinholes are inevitably formed due to characteristics of a process of forming such a protective layer and the material thereof. However, when the ink-jet print head <b>100</b> is used for a long time, the above-mentioned pinholes principally contribute to cause a failure of the first protective layer <b>170</b> due to cavitation force. Such a failure of the first protective layer <b>170</b> is more frequently produced at an area C where the heat generation layer <b>130</b> and the electrode layer <b>140</b> are joined to one another with a step being formed between them. As such, if the first protective layer <b>170</b> suffers a failure, a problem can be caused in that the heat generation layer <b>130</b> may also suffer a failure by cavitation force. In addition, the heat generation layer <b>130</b> may be electrically shorted with the second protective layer <b>180</b> or the ink may be filled in the ink chamber <b>115</b> through the damaged part of the first protective layer <b>170</b>, whereby the heat generation layer <b>130</b> could also suffer a failure. As a result, the duration and/or quality of the ink-jet print head will be deteriorated.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Accordingly, the present general inventive concept has been conceived to solve the above-mentioned and/or other problems occurring in the prior art, and it is an aspect of the present general inventive concept to provide an ink-jet print head with a structure improved to prevent a failure of a heat generation layer, thereby enhancing the duration and quality of the ink-jet print head, and a method of fabricating the same.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Additional aspects and advantages of the present general inventive concept will be set forth in part in the description which follows and, in part, will be obvious from the description, or may be learned by practice of the general inventive concept.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The foregoing and/or other aspects and advantages of the present general inventive concept are achieved by providing an ink-jet print head comprising: a main substrate; an ink chamber formed on the main substrate to contain ink introduced through an ink supply passage with a nozzle to eject ink being formed at a top end of the ink chamber; a heat generation layer laminated on the bottom surface of the ink chamber; an electrode layer laminated on a top surface of the heat generation layer to supply electric power to the heat generation layer, the electrode layer being patterned to a predetermined shape so that some areas of the heat generation layer are exposed to an interior of the ink chamber; and a protective layer laminated on the top surfaces of the electrode layer and the heat generation layer, which are exposed to the interior of the ink chamber, wherein the protective layer comprises a first protective layer laminated on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer and the electrode layer and a top surface of the first protective layer is subject to surface treatment by applying plasma to the top surface of the first protective layer, so that pinholes are removed from the top surface of the first protective layer.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The first protective layer may comprise at least two films sequentially laminated on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer and the electrode layer which are exposed to the interior of the ink chamber, and top surfaces of the at least two films are respectively subject to surface treatment by applying a plasma to the top surfaces.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">By this process, it is possible to prohibit the occurrence of pinholes when forming the first protective layer, whereby the failure of the heat generation layer caused by the failure of the first protective layer and pinholes when the ink-jet print head is driven can be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Meanwhile, it is possible that all of the at least two films essentially consist of SiNx, and a reaction gas used when the plasma is applied is ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>).</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In addition, the first protective layer can be laminated on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer and the electrode layer which have been subjected to surface treatment by applying the plasma to the top surfaces thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Meanwhile, it is possible that the ink chamber is circumferentially surrounded by an ink chamber barrier laminated on the protective layer and a nozzle plate laminated on a top of the ink chamber barrier, the nozzle being formed through the nozzle plate, and the outlet of the ink supply passage itself and the ink supply passage are coaxially arranged.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Furthermore, it is also possible that the protective layer further comprises a second protective layer laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer, and the second protective layer may comprise at least two films formed from different materials, wherein the at least two films are alternately laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Moreover, it is also possible that the second protective layer comprises first and second films alternately laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer, wherein the first films essentially consist of Ta and the second films essentially consist of TaNx, and wherein the uppermost and the lowermost of the second protective layer being formed with the second films.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">By this, because the second protective layer is also formed in a multilayered film structure, the heat generation layer can be more effectively protected.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The foregoing and/or other aspects and advantages of the present general inventive concept may also be achieved by providing a method of fabricating an ink-jet print head comprising the operations of: sequentially laminating a heat generation layer and an electrode layer on a substrate; patterning the electrode layer to cause some areas of the top surface of the heat generation layer to be exposed; laminating a protective layer on the top surfaces of the electrode layer and the heat generation layer; and laminating an ink chamber barrier and a nozzle plate on the top surface of the protective layer to form an ink chamber, wherein the operation of laminating a protective layer comprises the operation of sequentially laminating a first protective layer and a second protective layer on the top surfaces of the electrode layer and the heat generation layer, and the second protective layer is laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer after any defect generated when laminating the first protective layer is removed.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">According to an aspect of the present general inventive concept, the removal of defects from the first protective layer is effected by applying a plasma to the first protective layer.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In addition, it is possible that the first protective layer is formed by sequentially laminating at least two films, and the at least two films are formed from a same material.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">It is also possible that the at least two films are respectively formed by separately depositing SiNx, and the first protective layer is laminated after the plasma is applied to the top surfaces of the heat generation layer and the electrode layer.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Here, it is possible that the reaction gas used when applying the plasma is ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) and each of the at least two films has a thickness in the range of about 100˜1100 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">By this process, it is possible to remove any defects such as pinholes formed in each film. In addition, the top surface of each film, which has been subjected to surface treatment, will function as a seed layer to render another film laminated on its top surface to be rigidly bonded and to facilitate the deposition of a next film.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Meanwhile, the second protective layer may comprise one or more first films formed by sputtering of Ta and one or more second films formed by reactive sputtering of TaNx, wherein the first and second films are alternately deposited on a top surface of the first protective layer; an uppermost and a lowermost of the second protective layer are formed with the second films.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In addition, it is also possible that the ink chamber barrier and the nozzle plate are formed through a monolithic lamination process.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">By this process, miniaturization and integration of an ink-jet print head can be facilitated</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">These and/or other aspects and advantages of the present general inventive concept will become apparent and more readily appreciated from the following description of the embodiments, taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings of which:</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional view showing a conventional ink-jet print head;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional view showing an ink-jet print head according to an embodiment of the present general inventive concept;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an enlarged view of the part A of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A to 4I</figref> sequential show a process of fabricating the ink-jet print head according to the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross-sectional view showing an ink-jet print head according to another embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an enlarged view of the part B of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Certain embodiments of the present general inventive concept will be described in greater detail with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In the following description, same drawing reference numerals are used for the same elements even in different drawings. The matters defined in the description such as a detailed construction and elements are nothing but the ones provided to assist in a comprehensive understanding of the general inventive concept. Thus, it is apparent that the present general inventive concept can be carried out without those defined matters. Also, well-known functions or constructions are not described in detail since they would obscure the invention in unnecessary detail.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Hereinbelow, preferred embodiments of the present general inventive concept will be described in detail with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an ink-jet print head according to an embodiment of the present general inventive concept. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the ink-jet print head <b>200</b> according to the present embodiment comprises a main substrate <b>210</b>, a heat insulation layer <b>220</b>, a heat generation layer <b>230</b>, an electrode layer <b>240</b>, a protective layer <b>250</b>, an ink chamber barrier <b>280</b>, and a nozzle plate <b>290</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The heat generation layer <b>230</b> functions to instantly heat the ink filled in the ink chamber <b>215</b>, which is formed by the ink chamber barrier <b>280</b> and the nozzle plate <b>290</b>, and the heat generation layer <b>230</b> is typically formed from tantalum-aluminum alloy (Ta—Al alloy). The heat insulation layer <b>220</b>, which is formed from SiO<sub>2</sub>, is interposed between the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the main substrate <b>210</b>, whereby heat transfer from the heat generation layer <b>230</b> to the main substrate <b>210</b> can be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The electrode layer <b>240</b> functions to apply electric power to the heat generation layer <b>230</b>, and the electrode layer <b>240</b> is typically formed from aluminum (Al), which has a high electric conductivity.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Meanwhile, the protective layer <b>250</b> comprises a first protective layer <b>260</b> and a second protective layer <b>270</b>. Here, the second protective layer <b>270</b> functions to prevent a failure of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> caused by a cavitation force generated when bubbles (now shown) are contracted within the ink chamber <b>215</b> after the ink ejection through an a nozzle <b>295</b> is completed. The second protective layer <b>270</b> also functions to prevent the heat generation layer <b>230</b> from being oxidized by ink charged into the ink chamber <b>215</b>. In addition, the first protective layer <b>260</b> functions not only to prevent the failure and oxidization of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> as does the second protective layer <b>270</b>, but also to prevent the heat generation layer <b>230</b> from being electrically shorted with the first protective layer <b>260</b> or ink charged into the ink chamber <b>215</b>. Accordingly, the first protective layer <b>260</b> may be referred to as an insulation layer or a dielectric layer.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the first protective layer <b>260</b> according to the present embodiment is subjected to a separate process to remove any defects such as pinholes from the first protective layer <b>260</b>. According to the present general inventive concept, any defect present in the first protective layer <b>260</b> is removed by a plasma applied to the top surface of the first protective layer <b>260</b>. Such a process to remove defects in this manner is called a “stuffing treatment.” The thickness of the first protective layer <b>260</b> to effectively execute the stuffing treatment using the plasma is about 1000 Å. However, considering the heat transfer efficiency and insulation efficiency of the first effective layer <b>260</b>, the total thickness of the first protective layer <b>260</b> is typically in the range of about 3000˜7000 Å. In order to prohibit the deterioration in efficiency of the stuffing treatment due to this, the first protective layer <b>260</b> in this embodiment is formed by sequentially laminating plural films <b>261</b>, and the top surface of each film is subject to stuffing treatment before the next film is deposited. In addition, it is possible that a thickness t<b>1</b> of each film ranges between 100˜1100 Å to improve the efficiency of removing defects by the stuffing treatment as described above. This is because if a film <b>261</b> is formed too thick during a single lamination process, the effect of removing defects by applying the plasma as described above is only effective on the surface of the film <b>261</b>. In this embodiment, a total of four films <b>261</b> are laminated in a thickness t<b>1</b> of about 800 Å, respectively, thus forming a first protective layer <b>260</b>. Accordingly, the total thickness t of the first protective layer <b>260</b> is about 3200 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Meanwhile, the respective films <b>261</b> may be formed from a same material, in particular, a material selected from SiOx and SiNx, which have a good insulation property. The first protective layer <b>260</b> in this embodiment is formed by separately depositing SiNx, which is superior to SiOx in heat conductivity, through a plasma enhanced chemical vapor deposition (PECVD) process. Because the films <b>261</b> are respectively formed by depositing SiNx as described above, it is possible to introduce gaseous ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) into the reaction area when applying the plasma as a reaction gas. Although reference numerals <b>265</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> appear to be formed layers, these reference numerals <b>265</b> are only provided to aid in pointing out where the stuffing treatment occurs, and no practical layer is formed by such stuffing treatment.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">According to the present embodiment, it is possible that the first protective layer <b>260</b> is laminated on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layer <b>240</b> after the top surfaces have been treated by applying the plasma. Here, it is more preferable that gaseous ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) is introduced into a reaction area on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layer <b>240</b> at the time of applying the plasma, thereby using the ammonia as the reaction gas. The top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layer <b>240</b> treated in this manner serve as seed layers to improve a bonding force between the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layer <b>240</b> and the first protective layer <b>260</b> and to allow the films <b>261</b> to be more tightly laminated. Although reference numeral <b>263</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> appears to be a formed layer, this reference numeral <b>263</b> is only provided to aid in pointing out where the stuffing treatment occurs, and no practical layer is formed by such stuffing treatment.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Hereinbelow, a method of fabricating the ink-jet print head according to the previous embodiment is described in detail with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">At first, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>a</i>, a heat insulation layer <b>220</b> is formed on a main substrate <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Then, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>, a heat generation layer <b>230</b> and an electrode layer <b>240</b> are formed on the top surface of the heat insulation layer <b>220</b> at which point the electrode layer <b>240</b> is patterned through an etching process, such as lithography, to expose some areas of the top surface of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> at the bottom surface of an ink chamber <b>215</b>. Here, the heat generation layer <b>230</b> may have a heat-generative resistance member formed from Ta—Al through a vacuum deposition process, and the electrode may be formed by depositing Al.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">When the deposition of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layer <b>240</b> is completed, surface treatment is performed on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layer <b>240</b> by applying plasma to the top surfaces, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>. At this time, it is preferable to introduce gaseous ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) into the reaction area. Meanwhile, no practical layer is formed through such surface treatment. In other words, although <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> may appear to illustrate that a layer is formed at reference numeral <b>263</b> on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layer <b>240</b>, reference numeral <b>263</b> is not a formed layer, but is only illustrated in this <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> in order to help understanding of where the stuffing treatment to remove defects occurs.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">When the surface treatment of the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layer <b>240</b> is completed, the first protective layer <b>260</b> is deposited as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4D</figref>. The first protective layer <b>260</b> in this embodiment is formed in a multi-layered film structure with plural films <b>261</b> being laminated. The respective films <b>261</b> are separately formed from SiNx by repeatedly performing plasma enhanced chemical vapor deposition (PECVD). The plasma enhanced chemical vapor deposition is employed because the electrode layer <b>240</b> is formed from Al. That is, because the melting point of Al is about 600° C., the plasma enhanced chemical vapor deposition performed at about 400° C. is employed so as to prohibit the characteristic change of Al. In such a plasma enhanced chemical vapor deposition process, it is possible that SiH<sub>3 </sub>or NH<sub>3 </sub>is used as reaction gas, CCP (Capacitive Coupled Plasma) is used as a plasma, and plural frequency generators are employed so that RF (Radio Frequency, 13.56 MHz) and LF (Low Frequency, 400 kHz) can be concurrently applied. It is also possible that the pressure at the time of reaction is controlled using N<sub>2 </sub>gas.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Meanwhile, it is possible that the respective top surfaces of the films <b>261</b> are subject to stuffing treatment by applying plasma to the surfaces similar to the stuffing treatment applied to the top surfaces of the heat generation layer <b>230</b> and the electrode layers <b>240</b>. The plasma applied to the top surfaces of the films <b>261</b> is preferably CCP, and more preferably CCP with ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>) being used as a reaction gas. By this stuffing treatment, it is possible to remove defects such as pinholes formed in each of the films <b>261</b>. In addition, each of the films <b>261</b> which were subjected to stuffing treatment respectively serves as a seed layer to render another film to be rigidly bonded to its top surface and to facilitate the deposition of a next film. It is to be noted that although it appears in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4D</figref> that reference numeral <b>265</b> is a separate layer formed on each of the films <b>261</b>, reference numeral <b>265</b> is only provided to aid in pointing out where the stuffing treatment occurs, and no practical layer is separately formed through such stuffing treatment.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">When the deposition of the first protective layer <b>260</b> is completed, the second protective layer <b>270</b> is laminated thereby completing the protective layer <b>250</b>, and the second protective layer <b>270</b> is patterned to a predetermined shape, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4E</figref>. It is possible that the second protective layer <b>270</b> is formed by depositing either Ta or TaNx on the top surface of the first protective layer <b>260</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4F</figref> shows a state in which a photoresist mold (M<b>1</b>) is laminated on the top surface of the second protective layer <b>270</b> and then patterned.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">When the patterning of the photoresist mold M<b>1</b> as described above is completed, a metallic material is electroplated or an epoxy is deposited on the etched area of the photoresist mold M<b>1</b>, thereby forming an ink chamber barrier <b>280</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4G</figref>. The process of forming such an ink chamber barrier <b>280</b> using a photoresist mold M<b>1</b> as described above is called as a monolithic laminating process, which can facilitate miniaturization and integration of the ink print head <b>200</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Meanwhile, if the ink chamber barrier <b>280</b> is formed through such a monolithic laminating process as described above, it is preferable that a nozzle plate <b>290</b> with a nozzle <b>295</b> is also formed through such a monolithic laminating process using a patterned photoresist mold M<b>2</b>. If such a monolithic laminating process is not employed, the ink chamber barrier <b>280</b> and the first protective layer <b>260</b> can be bonded with each other using an additional adhesive layer (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">When the lamination of the nozzle plate <b>290</b> is completed as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4H</figref>, the photoresist molds M<b>1</b> and M<b>2</b> are subject to wet etching and removed to form an ink chamber <b>215</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4I</figref>. In addition, the heat insulation layer <b>220</b>, the heat generation layer <b>230</b>, the protective layer <b>250</b> and the main substrate <b>210</b> are etched to form an ink supply passage. At this time, the ink supply passage <b>217</b> can be arranged coaxially with the nozzle so as to facilitate miniaturization of the ink-jet print head <b>200</b>, and the ink supply passage <b>217</b> can be formed through a dry etching process.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Hereinbelow, an ink-jet print head according to another embodiment of the present general inventive concept is described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the ink-jet print head <b>300</b> according to this embodiment is characterized in that a first protective layer <b>360</b> has a multi-layered film structure similar to the first protective layer <b>260</b> described above, and a second protective layer <b>370</b> is formed in a multi-layered film structure, thereby forming a resultant protective layer <b>350</b>. This is because various properties necessarily required to protect the heat generation layer <b>230</b>, such as hardness, elasticity, and anti-oxidation cannot be satisfied with a second protective layer <b>370</b> formed from a single material (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). That is, if such a second protective layer <b>370</b> is formed from Ta only, it is superior in elasticity but can not meet the requirements for hardness and anti-oxidation. Whereas, if such a second protective layer <b>370</b> is formed from TaNx only, it is superior in hardness and anti-oxidation but cannot meet the requirements for elasticity. Therefore, in order to solve this problem, the second protective layer <b>370</b> according to this embodiment is formed by alternately laminating plural first films <b>372</b> and plural second films <b>373</b>. According to this process, the second protective layer <b>370</b> is improved in terms of elasticity, hardness and anti-oxidation, as compared to the conventional second protective <b>180</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) formed from a single material. The first films <b>372</b> are formed through a sputtering process and the second films <b>373</b> are formed through a reactive sputtering process, in which N<sub>2 </sub>gas is introduced and reacted when sputtering Ta.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Furthermore, the lowermost surface of the second protective layer <b>370</b> is preferably formed with a second film <b>373</b>. By this process, the bonding force between the first protective layer <b>360</b> and the second protective layer <b>370</b> is enhanced. In addition, the uppermost surface of the second protective layer <b>370</b> is preferably formed by a second film <b>373</b>. According to this process, it is possible to prohibit the oxidation of the second protective layer <b>370</b> caused by ink charged into the ink chamber <b>215</b>. Meanwhile, the remaining technical configuration of the ink-jet print head except the second protective layer <b>370</b> is identical to that of the ink-jet print head <b>200</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) of the afore-mentioned previous embodiment. Therefore, a detailed description thereof is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">According to the embodiments of the present general inventive concept as described above, a first protective layer is formed in a multi-layered film structure, thereby prohibiting an occurrence of pinholes in the first protective layer. Accordingly, it is possible to prevent a failure of the first protection layer due to an external force exerted in response to ejection of ink. Consequently, it is possible not only to prohibit the failure of a heat generation layer due to such an external force but also to prevent the heat generation layer or an electrode layer from being electrically shorted with the ink contained within an ink chamber or a second protective layer. To this end, the duration and quality of an ink-jet print head can be enhanced.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Moreover, because the second protective layer is also formed in a multi-layered film structure, the heat generation layer can be more effectively protected.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">While exemplary embodiments of the present general inventive concept have been shown and described with reference to the representative embodiments thereof in order to exemplify the principle of the present general inventive concept, the present general inventive concept is not limited to these embodiments. It will be understood that various modifications and changes can be made by those skilled in the art without departing from the spirit and scope of the general inventive concept as defined by the appended claims. Therefore, it shall be considered that such modifications, changes and equivalents thereof are all included within the scope of the present general inventive concept.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Although a few embodiments of the present general inventive concept have been shown and described, it will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that changes may be made in these embodiments without departing from the principles and spirit of the general inventive concept, the scope of which is defined in the appended claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An ink-jet print head comprising:
<claim-text>a main substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an ink chamber formed on the main substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat generation layer laminated on a bottom surface of the ink chamber;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electrode layer laminated on a top surface of the heat generation layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a protective layer laminated on top surfaces of the electrode layer and the heat generation layer, wherein the protective layer comprises a first protective layer laminated on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer and the electrode layer and a top surface of the first protective layer is subject to surface treatment by applying a plasma thereto to remove pinholes from the top surface of the first protective layer so that the top surface is devoid of pinholes without substantially reducing a thickness of the treated first protective layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. An ink-jet print head as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first protective layer comprises at least two films sequentially laminated on the top surfaces of the heat generation layer and the electrode layer which are exposed to the interior of the ink chamber, and top surfaces of the at least two films are respectively subject to surface treatment by applying a plasma to the top surfaces thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. An ink-jet print head as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein all of the at least two films essentially consist of SiNx, and a reaction gas used when applying the plasma is ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. An ink-jet print head as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein heat generation layer and the electrode layer were subjected to surface treatment to remove pinholes by applying the plasma to the top surfaces thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An ink-jet print head as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein each of the at least two films has a thickness in the range of about 100˜1100 Å.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An ink-jet print head as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the protective layer further comprises a second protective layer laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An ink-jet print head as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the second protective layer comprises at least two films formed from different materials, wherein the at least two films are alternately laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An ink-jet print head as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the second protective layer comprise plural first films and plural second films alternately laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer,
<claim-text>wherein the first films essentially consist of Ta and the second films essentially consist of TaNx, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the uppermost and the lowermost of the second protective layer are formed with the second films.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An ink-jet print head comprising:
<claim-text>a main substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an ink chamber formed on the main substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat generation layer formed on a bottom surface of the ink chamber;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electrode layer formed on a top surface of the heat generation layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of first protective layers formed on top surfaces of the electrode and heat generation layer, wherein the top surface of each of the plurality of first protective layers is devoid of pinholes following a surface treatment using a plasma applied during formation of each of the plurality of first protective layers and wherein the surface treatment does not substantially reduce a thickness of each of the treated first protective layers.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The ink-jet head of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of second protective layers formed on a top surface of the plurality of first protective layers, comprising at least two different materials.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The ink-jet head of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of second protective layers comprise a plurality of first films comprising a first material, and a plurality of second films comprising a material different from the first material, alternately laminated on the top surface of the first protective layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The ink-jet head of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the uppermost layer and the lowermost layer of the plurality of second protective layers are formed with the same material.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
