<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297629-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297629</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10942555</doc-number>
<date>20040915</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>277</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>4763</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438638</main-classification>
<further-classification>438687</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Ultra-thick metal-copper dual damascene process</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5926732</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Matsuura</name>
<date>19990700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438622</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6204168</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Naik et al.</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438638</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6211069</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hu et al.</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438637</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6287960</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lao</name>
<date>20010900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438637</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6350682</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Liao</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438638</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438638</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>24</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060057842</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060316</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wang</last-name>
<first-name>Sung-Hsiung</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hsinchu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Tung &amp; Associates</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Hsin Chu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Smoot</last-name>
<first-name>Stephen W.</first-name>
<department>2813</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Novel dual damascene methods characterized by short cycle time and low expense. In one embodiment, the method includes providing a dielectric layer on a substrate; etching a via in the dielectric layer; filling the via with a conductive metal such as copper; providing a second dielectric layer over the via; etching a trench in the second dielectric layer; and filling the trench with a conductive metal such as copper. In another embodiment, the method includes providing a dielectric layer on a substrate; etching a partial via in the dielectric layer; etching a partial trench in the dielectric layer over the partial via; completing the via and the trench in a single etching step; and filling the via and the trench with a conductive metal such as copper to complete the via and metal line, respectively.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="47.58mm" wi="212.17mm" file="US07297629-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="170.35mm" wi="155.53mm" file="US07297629-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="221.23mm" wi="159.68mm" file="US07297629-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="220.81mm" wi="148.51mm" file="US07297629-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to dual damascene processes used to form copper lines and vias in the fabrication of semiconductor integrated circuits. More particularly, the present invention relates to novel dual damascene processes which are characterized by low cost and short cycle times.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The fabrication of various solid state devices requires the use of planar substrates, or semiconductor wafers, on which integrated circuits are fabricated. The final number, or yield, of functional integrated circuits on a wafer at the end of the IC fabrication process is of utmost importance to semiconductor manufacturers, and increasing the yield of circuits on the wafer is the main goal of semiconductor fabrication. After packaging, the circuits on the wafers are tested, wherein non-functional dies are marked using an inking process and the functional dies on the wafer are separated and sold. IC fabricators increase the yield of dies on a wafer by exploiting economies of scale. Over 1000 dies may be formed on a single wafer which measures from six to twelve inches in diameter.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Various processing steps are used to fabricate integrated circuits on a semiconductor wafer. These steps include deposition of a conducting layer on the silicon wafer substrate; formation of a photoresist or other mask such as titanium oxide or silicon oxide, in the form of the desired metal interconnection pattern, using standard lithographic or photolithographic techniques; subjecting the wafer substrate to a dry etching process to remove the conducting layer from the areas not covered by the mask, thereby etching the conducting layer in the form of the masked pattern on the substrate; removing or stripping the mask layer from the substrate typically using reactive plasma and chlorine gas, thereby exposing the top surface of the conductive interconnect layer; and cooling and drying the wafer substrate by applying water and nitrogen gas to the wafer substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The numerous processing steps outlined above are used to cumulatively apply multiple electrically conductive and insulative layers on the wafer and pattern the layers to form the circuits. The final yield of functional circuits on the wafer depends on proper application of each layer during the process steps. Proper application of those layers depends, in turn, on coating the material in a uniform spread over the surface of the wafer in an economical and efficient manner.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the semiconductor industry, copper is being increasingly used as the interconnect material for microchip fabrication. The conventional method of depositing a metal conducting layer and then etching the layer in the pattern of the desired metal line interconnects and vias cannot be used with copper because copper is not suitable for dry-etching. Special considerations must also be undertaken in order to prevent diffusion of copper into silicon during processing. Therefore, the dual-damascene process has been developed and is widely used to form copper metal line interconnects and vias in semiconductor technology. In the dual-damascene process, the dielectric layer rather than the metal layer is etched to form trenches and vias, after which the metal is deposited into the trenches and vias to form the desired interconnects. Finally, the deposited copper is subjected to chemical mechanical planarization (CMP) to remove excess copper (copper overburden) extending from the trenches.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">While there exist many variations of a dual-damascene process flow, the process typically begins with deposition of a silicon dioxide dielectric layer of desired thickness which corresponds to the thickness for the via or vias to be etched in the dielectric layer. Next, a thin etch stop layer, typically silicon nitride, is deposited on the dielectric layer. Photolithography is then used to pattern via openings over the etch stop layer, after which dry etching is used to etch via openings in the etch stop layer. The patterned photoresist is then stripped from the etch stop layer after completion of the etch. A remaining dielectric layer the thickness of which corresponds to the thickness of the trench for the metal interconnect lines is then deposited on the etch stop layer, and photolithography followed by dry etching is used to pattern the trenches in the remaining dielectric layer and the vias beneath the trenches. The trench etching stops at the etch stop layer, while the vias are etched in the first dielectric layer through the openings in the etch stop layer and beneath the trenches. Next, a barrier material of Ta or TaN is deposited on the sidewalls and bottoms of the trenches and vias using ionized PVD. A uniform copper seed layer is then deposited on the barrier layer using CVD. After the trenches and vias are filled with copper, the copper overburden extending from the trenches is removed and the upper surfaces of the metal lines planarized using CMP. In the dual damascene process described above, the vias and the trenches are etched in the same step, and the etch stop layer defines the bottom of the trenches. In other variations, the trench is patterned and etched after the via.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A significant advantage of the dual-damascene process is the creation of a two-leveled metal inlay which includes both via holes and metal line trenches that undergo copper fill at the same time. This eliminates the requirement of forming the trenches for the metal interconnect lines and the holes for the vias in separate processing steps. The process further eliminates the interface between the vias and the metal lines.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another important advantage of the dual-damascene process is that completion of the process typically requires 20% to 30% fewer steps than the traditional aluminum metal interconnect process. Furthermore, the dual damascene process omits some of the more difficult steps of traditional aluminum metallization, including aluminum etch and many of the tungsten and dielectric CMP steps. Reducing the number of process steps required for semiconductor fabrication significantly improves the yield of the fabrication process, since fewer process steps translate into fewer sources of error that reduce yield.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">While the traditional dual damascene process is attended by many advantages, some of the disadvantages include high cost, excessive process complexity and inordinately long process cycle time. Accordingly, a new and improved dual damascene process is needed which is characterized by low cost and a shorter cycle time.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Accordingly, an object of the present invention is to provide a new and improved method for fabricating metal lines and vias on a substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Another object of the present invention is to provide a new and improved dual damascene process for semiconductor fabrication.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Still another object of the present invention is to provide a new and improved dual damascene process which is characterized by a short cycle time and low cost.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Yet another object of the present invention is to provide a dual damascene process which includes fabricating vias on a substrate followed by fabrication of metal lines in conductive communication with the vias.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A still further object of the present invention is to provide a dual damascene process which includes formation of a partial via; completion of the via and formation of a trench above the via in a single step; and filling of the via and trench with copper to complete the metal line and via on the substrate.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In accordance with these and other objects and advantages, the present invention is generally directed to novel dual damascene methods characterized by short cycle time and low expense. In one embodiment, the method includes providing a dielectric layer on a substrate; etching a via in the dielectric layer; filling the via with a conductive metal such as copper; providing a second dielectric layer over the via; etching a trench in the second dielectric layer; and filling the trench with a conductive metal such as copper. In another embodiment, the method includes providing a dielectric layer on a substrate; etching a partial via in the dielectric layer; etching a partial trench in the dielectric layer over the partial via; completing the via and the trench in a single etching step; and filling the via and the trench with a conductive metal such as copper to complete the via and metal line, respectively.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The invention will now be described, by way of example, with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a sectional view of a dielectric layer and a patterned photoresist provided on the dielectric layer preparatory to etching of vias in the dielectric layer in a first step according to a first embodiment of the method of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> is a sectional view illustrating multiple vias etched in a dielectric layer in a second step according to a first embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref> is a sectional view illustrating stripping of patterned photoresist from the via-etched dielectric layer in a third step;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1D</figref> is a sectional view illustrating removal of a cap hard mask layer from the dielectric layer in a fourth step;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1E</figref> is a sectional view illustrating deposition of a barrier layer and a seed layer on the dielectric layer and on the sidewalls and bottoms of the vias in a fifth step;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1F</figref> is a sectional view illustrating filling of the vias with copper and deposition of a copper layer on the dielectric layer in a sixth step;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1G</figref> is a sectional view illustrating planarization of the copper layer deposited in the step of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1F</figref> in a seventh step;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1H</figref> is a sectional view illustrating deposition of a second dielectric layer on the planarized copper layer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1G</figref> in an eighth step;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1I</figref> is a sectional view illustrating deposition of a patterned photoresist on the second dielectric layer in a ninth step according to a desired trench pattern to be etched in the second dielectric layer;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1J</figref> is a sectional view illustrating etching of trenches in the second dielectric layer in a tenth step;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1K</figref> is a sectional view illustrating etching of an etch stop layer between the trenches and the vias in an eleventh step;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1L</figref> is a sectional view illustrating deposition of a barrier and seed layer on the second dielectric layer and the sidewalls and bottoms of the trenches in a twelfth step;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1M</figref> is a sectional view illustrating deposition of copper in the trenches in the second dielectric layer and formation of a copper layer on the dielectric layer in a thirteenth step;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1N</figref> is a sectional view illustrating planarization of the copper layer and completion of the process of the first embodiment in a fourteenth step;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a sectional view illustrating a top dielectric layer deposited on a top etch stop layer provided on a bottom dielectric layer and a patterned photoresist layer for the formation of vias deposited on the top dielectric layer in a first step according to a second embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a sectional view illustrating partial vias etched in the top dielectric layer in a second step;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> is a sectional view illustrating deposition of a patterned photoresist for the formation of trenches in the top dielectric layer in a third step;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref> is a sectional view illustrating etching of trenches in the top dielectric layer and completion of the vias to the top etch stop layer between the top dielectric layer and the bottom dielectric layer in a fourth step;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2E</figref> is a sectional view illustrating etching of the vias through the top etch stop layer in a fifth step;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref> is a sectional view illustrating etching of the vias through the bottom dielectric layer to a bottom etch stop layer in a sixth step;</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2G</figref> is a sectional view illustrating etching of the top etch stop layer at the bottom of the trenches in a seventh step;</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2H</figref> is a sectional view illustrating deposition of a barrier layer and a seed layer on the sidewalls and bottoms of the trenches and vias in an eighth step;</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2I</figref> is a sectional view illustrating filling of the vias and trenches with copper and deposition of a copper layer on the top dielectric layer in a ninth step; and</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2J</figref> is a sectional view illustrating planarization of the copper layer in a tenth step.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Referring initially to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A-1N</figref>, in a first embodiment according to the novel dual damascene processes of the present invention, vias and metal lines are sequentially fabricated to form a metal line and via system <b>1</b>. Fabrication of the system <b>1</b> according to the first embodiment begins with formation of the vias, as will be hereinafter described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A-1G</figref>, followed by formation of the metal lines above the vias, as will be hereinafter described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1H-1N</figref>. The dual damascene processes of the present invention provide methods which are characterized by low cost and shortened cycle times as compared to conventional dual damascene processes.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>, fabrication of the system <b>1</b> includes initial deposition of a metal conductive layer <b>3</b> on a substrate (not shown). A bottom etch stop layer <b>5</b>, which is typically SiN (silicon nitride), is deposited on the conductive layer <b>3</b> and has a thickness of typically about 500 angstroms. A bottom dielectric layer <b>7</b>, typically SiON, is then deposited on the bottom etch stop layer <b>5</b> and may have a thickness of typically about 600 angstroms. A top etch stop layer <b>9</b>, also having a thickness of typically about 500 angetroms, is then deposited on the bottom dielectric layer <b>7</b>. A patterned photoresist <b>11</b>, having multiple via etch exposure openings <b>13</b> which correspond positionally and dimensionally to the desired pattern for the vias to be formed in the system <b>1</b>, is deposited on the top etch stop layer <b>9</b>. Each of the via etch exposure openings <b>13</b> has a CD (critical dimension) size of typically about 0.38-0.40 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The vies <b>15</b> are formed by etching through the top etch stop layer <b>9</b> and then the bottom dielectric layer <b>7</b> downwardly through the via etch exposure openings <b>13</b> in the patterned photoresist <b>11</b>, until the etching stops at the bottom etch stop layer <b>5</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>. The etch process may be a self-aligned etch process. Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref>, the patterned photoresist <b>11</b> is stripped from the underlying top etch stop layer <b>9</b> and then typically subjected to a wet cleaning process to remove photoresist residue therefrom, as is known by those skilled in the art. The portions of the bottom etch stop layer <b>5</b> which separate each via <b>15</b> from the underlying conductive layer <b>3</b> are then etched away to establish communication between each via <b>15</b> and the underlying conductive layer <b>3</b>, as indicated by reference numeral <b>5</b><i>a </i>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1D</figref>. Next, the partially fabricated system <b>1</b> is typically subjected to wet cleaning, CD measurement, AEI (after-etch inspection) and pre-bake prior to deposition of a barrier layer <b>17</b> on the sidewalls and bottom of each via <b>15</b>, followed by deposition of a copper seed layer <b>19</b> on the barrier layer <b>17</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1E</figref>. Typically, the barrier layer <b>17</b> is TaN and has a thickness of about 300 angstroms. The copper seed layer <b>19</b> has a thickness of typically about 1,800 angstroms. Deposition of the barrier layer <b>17</b> and the seed layer <b>19</b> may be preceded and followed by charging of the processing environment with nitrogen gas. The vias <b>15</b> are then tilled with copper via infills <b>22</b>, and a copper plating layer <b>21</b> which is continuous with the copper via infills <b>22</b> is deposited on the portion of the seed layer <b>19</b> which was previously deposited on the bottom dielectric layer <b>7</b>. Finally, after charging of the processing environment with nitrogen, the copper plating layer <b>21</b> is subjected to CMP (chemical mechanical planarization) to planarize the copper plating layer <b>21</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1G</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1H-1N</figref>, metal lines are then formed in the system <b>1</b> above the copper-inlaid vias <b>15</b> as follows. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1H</figref>, a top dielectric layer <b>23</b> which may be SiON, which may include an additional overlying dielectric/hard mask layer <b>9</b><i>b</i>, and have a thickness of typically about 600 angstroms, is initially deposited on the planarized copper plating layer <b>21</b>. Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1I</figref>, a patterned photoresist <b>25</b>, having multiple trench etch exposure openings <b>27</b> which correspond positionally and dimensionally to the desired pattern for the trenches to be etched, is deposited over the top dielectric layer <b>23</b>. Each of the trench etch exposure openings <b>27</b> has a CD of typically at least about 2.5 μm. Trenches <b>29</b>, each corresponding to the width and position of a corresponding one of the trench etch exposure openings <b>27</b> in the patterned photoresist <b>25</b>, are then etched beneath each opening <b>27</b>, through the underlying top dielectric opening <b>23</b> and the copper plating layer <b>21</b>, to the top etch stop layer <b>9</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1J</figref>. The etch process may be a self-aligned etch process. Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1K</figref>, the portion of the top etch stop layer <b>9</b> which separates each trench <b>29</b> from the underlying via <b>15</b> is etched to establish communication between the vias <b>15</b> and the trenches <b>29</b>, as indicated by reference numeral <b>9</b><i>a</i>. This is typically followed by wet cleaning to remove etch particles as well as CD measurement and AET (after-etching inspection). A barrier layer <b>31</b> is next deposited on the sidewalls and bottom of the trenches <b>29</b>, as well as on the upper surface of the top dielectric layer <b>23</b>, and a copper seed layer <b>33</b> is deposited on the barrier layer <b>31</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1L</figref>. The barrier layer <b>31</b> is typically TaN and has a thickness of about 300 angstroms, whereas the copper seed layer <b>33</b> has a thickness of typically about 1,800 angetroms. Both before and after the barrier layer <b>31</b> and the seed layer <b>33</b> are deposited, the processing environment may be charged with nitrogen. The trenches <b>29</b> are then filled with copper trench infills <b>36</b>, and a copper plating layer <b>35</b> which is continuous with the copper trench infills <b>36</b> is deposited on the portion of the seed layer <b>33</b> which was previously deposited on the bottom dielectric layer <b>7</b> with the barrier layer <b>31</b>. Finally, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1N</figref>, the copper plating layer <b>35</b> is subjected to CMP (chemical mechanical planarization) to substantially planarize the copper plating layer <b>35</b>. Accordingly, the copper trench infills <b>36</b> define metal lines that connect devices (not shown) to each other in the integrated circuit off which the system <b>1</b> is a part, and the copper via infills <b>22</b> connect the metal lines to the underlying conductive layer <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A-2J</figref>, in a second embodiment according to the methods of the present invention, a metal line and via system <b>41</b> is fabricated by initially depositing a bottom etch stop layer <b>45</b> on a conductive layer <b>43</b> previously deposited on a substrate (not shown) or an insulative layer (not shown), as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>. The bottom etch stop layer <b>45</b> is typically SiN (silicon nitride) and may be about 500 angstroms thick, or in the range of 300 Å-3000 Å. Next, a bottom dielectric layer <b>47</b>, typically silicon dioxide SiO<sub>2 </sub>and having a thickness of about 600 angstroms, or in the range of 300 Å-2000 Å, is deposited on the bottom etch stop layer <b>45</b>. A top etch stop layer <b>49</b> is deposited on the bottom dielectric layer <b>47</b>, and a top dielectric layer <b>51</b> is deposited on the top etch stop layer <b>49</b>. An additional dielectric/hard mask layer <b>49</b><i>b </i>may be formed on the top dielectric layer <b>51</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>. A patterned photoresist <b>53</b>, having multiple via etch exposure openings <b>55</b> corresponding the positions and dimensions of vias to be etched, is deposited over the top dielectric layer <b>51</b>. Each of the via etch exposure openings <b>55</b> has a CD of typically about 0.20 μm to about 2 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, each of multiple partial vias <b>57</b> is then etched in the top dielectric layer <b>51</b>. The etch process may be a self-aligned etch process. Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>, a patterned photoresist <b>59</b>, having multipie trench etch exposure openings <b>61</b> corresponding positionally and dimensionally to the respective trenches to be etched, is deposited on the top dielectric layer <b>51</b>, with each trench etch exposure opening <b>61</b> disposed in communication with one or more underlying partial vias <b>57</b>. The CD of each trench etch exposure opening <b>61</b> is typically at least about 0.5 μm. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>, partial trenches <b>63</b> are then etched typically using a self-aligned etch process in the top dielectric layer <b>51</b>, beneath the respective trench etch exposure openings <b>61</b>. Simultaneously, the partial vias <b>57</b> are etched downwardly through the top dielectric layer <b>51</b> in advance of the downwardly-etching partial trenches <b>63</b>, until the bottom ends of the partial vias <b>57</b> reach the top etch stop layer <b>49</b>. Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2E and 2F</figref>, the partial trenches <b>63</b> are etched through the top dielectric layer <b>51</b> to the top etch stop layer <b>49</b>, at which point the partial trenches <b>63</b> define complete trenches <b>67</b>. Simultaneously, the partial vias <b>57</b> are etched downwardly through the top etch stop layer <b>49</b> and the bottom dielectric layer <b>47</b>, respectively, and define complete vias <b>65</b> when they reach and are stopped by the bottom etch stop layer <b>45</b>. The patterned photoresist <b>59</b> is then stripped from the top dielectric layer <b>51</b>, as further shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2G</figref>, the portion of the top etch stop layer <b>49</b> between each complete trench <b>67</b> and the underlying via or vias <b>65</b> is next etched away to expose the bottom dielectric layer <b>47</b> at the bottom of each trench <b>67</b>. In similar fashion, the portion of the bottom etch stop layer <b>45</b> between each complete via <b>65</b> and the conductive layer <b>43</b> is etched away to establish communication between each complete via <b>65</b> and the underlying conductive layer <b>43</b>. This is followed by wet cleaning of the system <b>41</b> typically using an ST-<b>250</b> solvent, CD measurement for the complete vias <b>65</b> and the complete trenches <b>67</b>, and pre-baking of the system <b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2H</figref>, a barrier layer <b>69</b> is then deposited on the sidewalls of the complete vias <b>65</b> and complete trenches <b>67</b>, as well as on the exposed upper surface of the top dielectric layer <b>51</b>. A seed layer <b>71</b> is then deposited on the barrier layer <b>69</b>. In a preferred embodiment, the barrier layer <b>69</b> is TaN and has a thickness of typically about 300 angstroms, or in the range of 200 Å-1000 Å, whereas the seed layer <b>71</b> is copper and has a thickness of typically about 1,800 angstroms, or in the range of 1000 Å-3000 Å. Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2H and 2I</figref>, in a single process step the complete vias <b>65</b> are filled with respective copper trench infills <b>75</b>, the complete trenches <b>67</b> are filled with copper trench infills <b>74</b>, and a copper plating layer <b>73</b> which is continuous with the copper trench infills <b>74</b> is deposited on the portion of the seed layer <b>71</b> which was previously deposited on the top dielectric layer <b>51</b>. Finally, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2J</figref>, the copper plating layer <b>73</b> is subjected to CMP (chemical mechanical planarization) to substantially planarize the copper plating layer <b>73</b>. Accordingly, the copper trench infills <b>74</b> define metal lines that connect devices (not shown) to each other in the integrated circuit of which the system <b>41</b> is a part, and the copper via infills <b>75</b> connect the metal lines to the underlying conductive layer <b>43</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">While the preferred embodiments of the invention have been described above, it will be recognized and understood that various modifications can be made in the invention and the appended claims are intended to cover all such modifications which may fall within the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of forming a metal line and a via, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>providing a conductive layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a bottom dielectric layer on said conductive layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming at least one via in said bottom dielectric layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a conductive metal filling said at least one via and overlying said bottom dielectric layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a top dielectric layer over said at least one via and said conductive metal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching at least one trench in said top dielectric layer extending to said at least one conductive metal filled via; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a conductive metal in said at least one trench to define said metal line.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said etching at least one via and said etching at least one trench each comprises a self-aligned etching process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least one via has a CD measurement of about 0.2 um to about 2 um.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein said etching at least one via and said etching at least one trench each comprises a self-aligned etching process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least one trench has a CD measurement of at least about 0.5 um.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein said etching at least one via and said etching at least one trench each comprises a self-aligned etching process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein said at least one via has a CD measurement of about 0.2 um to about 2 um.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said conductive metal comprises copper.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A method of forming a metal line and a via, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>providing a conductive layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a bottom dielectric layer over said conductive layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a top dielectric layer over said bottom dielectric layer</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching at least one partial via in said top dielectric layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>depositing a photoresist layer over said at least one partial via;</claim-text>
<claim-text>patterning said photoresist layer with a trench etch opening over said at least one partial via;</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching at least one partial trench in said top dielectric layer over said at least one partial via;</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching said at least one partial trench through said top dielectric layer while simultaneously etching said at least one partial via through said bottom dielectric layer to define at least one complete trench and one complete vial; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a metal infill in said at least one complete via and said at least one complete trench.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said etching said at least one partial via and said etching said at least one partial trench each comprises a self-aligned etching process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said at least one complete via has a CD measurement of about 0.2 um to about 2 um.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said etching said at least one partial via and said etching said at least one partial trench each comprises a self-aligned etching process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said at least one complete trench has a CD measurement of at least about 0.5 um.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said etching said at least one partial via and said etching said at least one partial trench each comprises a self-aligned etching process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said at least one complete via has a CD measurement of about 0.2 um to about 2 um.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein said etching said at least one partial via and said etching said at least one partial trench each comprises a self-aligned etching process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method of forming a metal line and a via, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>providing a conductive layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a bottom etch stop layer on said conductive layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a bottom dielectric layer on said bottom etch stop layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a top etch stop layer on said bottom dielectric layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a top dielectric layer on said top etch stop layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching at least one partial via in said top dielectric layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>patterning a photoresist layer with a trench etch opening over said at least one partial via;</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching at least one partial trench in said top dielectric layer over said at least one partial via;</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching said at least one partial via through said top etch stop layer and said bottom dielectric layer to said bottom etch stop layer to define at least one via while simultaneously etching said at least one partial trench through said top dielectric layer to said top etch stop layer to define at least one complete trench;</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing said bottom etch stop layer at a bottom of said at least one via to expose said conductive layer to define at least one complete via; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a metal infill in said at least one complete via and said at least one complete trench.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein said etching said at least one partial via and said etching said at least one partial trench each comprises a self-aligned etching process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein said at least one complete via has a CD measurement of about 0.2 um to about 2 um.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein said at least one complete trench has a CD measurement of at least about 0.5 um.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
