<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298504-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298504</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10847292</doc-number>
<date>20040518</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-022618</doc-number>
<date>19990129</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>577</us-term-extension>
<disclaimer>
<text>This patent is subject to a terminal disclaimer.</text>
</disclaimer>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  113</main-classification>
<further-classification>358  11</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e73">Image formation apparatus limiting print operation according to additional information embedded in input image data</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5467169</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Morikawa</name>
<date>19951100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5659639</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mahoney et al.</name>
<date>19970800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5671277</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ikenoue et al.</name>
<date>19970900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6522421</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chapman et al.</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>7-110645</doc-number>
<date>19950400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>7-129270</doc-number>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-262141</doc-number>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  11-  118</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  327</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>35842602</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>09494253</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20000131</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7113291</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10847292</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040263891</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20041230</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yamada</last-name>
<first-name>Osamu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Toyokawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Toyama</last-name>
<first-name>Katsuhisa</first-name>
<address>
<city>Toyokawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>McDermott Will &amp; Emery LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Minolta Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Osaka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Tran</last-name>
<first-name>Douglas Q.</first-name>
<department>2625</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An image formation apparatus includes a scanner unit entering image data, a printer unit printing out input image data, a signature information detection unit detecting additional information including destination information from the image data, and a communication processing unit transmitting information related to printing of image data to the detected destination. Additional information including destination information is detected from the image data. Information related to printing of image data is transmitted to the destination detected from the image data. Accordingly, information related to printing when image data is printed is audited at the destination side.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="55.37mm" wi="162.81mm" file="US07298504-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="175.34mm" wi="147.15mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298504-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="199.05mm" wi="123.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298504-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="184.57mm" wi="139.19mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298504-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="201.25mm" wi="136.65mm" file="US07298504-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="198.04mm" wi="100.58mm" file="US07298504-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="167.56mm" wi="71.54mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298504-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of application Ser. No. 09/494,253 filed Jan. 31, 2000, now U.S. Pat. No. 7,113,291.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This application is based on Japanese Patent Application No. 11-22618 filed in Japan, the contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The present invention relates to image formation apparatuses such as digital copy machines and printers. Particularly, the present invention relates to an image formation apparatus that limits the print operation according to additional information embedded in input image data.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">It is now possible to easily copy a document image by virtue of the spread of digital copy machines. Also, digital data can be printed onto a recording medium such as a sheet of paper by providing to a digital copy machine an image produced by a computer, a photograph, a picture, and digital data obtained by shooting using a digital camera.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">There are cases where the digital data of a document or a computer-produced image that is to be copied is owned by the creator thereof. The creator may not wish to have the document or the digital data printed out. The concealment technique of embedding ID information or a logo as signature information into the document or digital data is known in order to prevent unlimited printing of documents and digital data.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">By verifying the printed out sheet as to the image or digital data in which signature information is embedded, the document image or digital data that is the source of the printout can be identified. However, royalties associated with the printing of the image or digital data cannot be collected appropriately. An unscrupulous user can obtain a printout freely.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The present invention is directed to solve the above problems, and an object is to provide an image formation apparatus that can audit information related to printing of image data.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Another object of the present invention is to provide an image formation apparatus that can limit the printing condition by which image data is to be printed.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A further object of the present invention is to provide an image formation apparatus that can print out image data at a different picture quality.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Still another object of the present invention is to provide an image recording apparatus that can audit information related to printing of image data.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to an aspect of the present invention, an image formation apparatus includes an input unit entering image data, a printer unit printing out the input image data, a detector detecting additional information in which destination information is included from the image data, and a transmission controller transmitting print information related to printing of image data to the detected destination.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to another aspect of the present invention, an image formation apparatus includes an input unit entering image data, a printer unit printing out the image data, a memory storing trigger information to initiate execution of a control operation and the control operation in correspondence, a detector detecting additional information including the trigger information from the image data, and a controller responsive to detection of the trigger information to execute the control operation corresponding to the trigger information stored in the memory. The control operation includes a transmission operation of transmitting print information related to printing of image data to a destination.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to the present invention, an image formation apparatus that can audit information related to printing of image data can be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">According to a further aspect of the present invention, an image recording apparatus includes an input unit entering image data, a record unit recording the image data to a recording medium, a detector detecting additional information in which destination information is included from the image data, and a transmission controller transmitting record information related to recording of image data to the detected destination.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">According to still another aspect of the present invention, an image recording apparatus includes an input unit entering image data, a record unit recording the image data to a recording medium, a detector detecting additional information in which trigger information to initiate execution of a predetermined control operation is included from the image data, and a controller executing the predetermined control operation in response to detection of the trigger information. The predetermined control operation includes a transmission operation of transmitting information related to recording of image data to the destination.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">According to the present invention, an image recording apparatus that can audit record information related to recording of image data can be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The foregoing and other objects, features, aspects and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description of the present invention when taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows an entire structure of a digital copy machine according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram to describe the structure of a control unit of the digital copy machine of an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a plan view of an operation panel provided at a top face of a digital copy machine according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow chart showing the process carried out by a digital copy machine according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flow chart showing the limitation process carried out at step S<b>07</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows the trigger information and control operations stored in the storage unit of the digital copy machine of an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Embodiments of the present invention will be described hereinafter with reference to the drawings. In the drawings, the same reference characters denote the same or corresponding components.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a digital copy machine <b>100</b> is connected to a copy vender <b>151</b> that collects the copy fee according to the number of prints.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Digital copy machine <b>100</b> includes an image reader <b>101</b> reading out image data from a document, and a printer unit <b>102</b> printing out an image onto a sheet.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">A document placed on a document platen <b>103</b> of image reader <b>101</b> is irradiated by an exposure lamp <b>105</b> of a scanner <b>104</b>. The light reflected from the document plane passes through mirrors <b>106</b>-<b>108</b> and the collective lens form an image on a full color CCD (charge coupled device) sensor <b>109</b>. Full color CCD sensor <b>109</b> converts the light reflected from the document plane into electric signals (analog signals) of red (R), green (G) and blue (B). The converted signals are provided to a processing unit <b>111</b>. Scanner <b>104</b> moves in the direction of the arrow in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (subscanning direction) by a scanner motor <b>112</b> to scan the entire document.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Processing unit <b>111</b> converts the input analog signals into predetermined digital signals and stores the same in an image memory <b>110</b>. The digital signals stored in image memory <b>110</b> are converted into laser driving signals and output to a laser device <b>112</b>. Laser device <b>112</b> outputs a laser beam according to the input digital signal.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Processing unit <b>111</b> is connected to a communication processing unit not shown. Digital data transmitted from an external personal computer or the like is received at the communication processing unit. The received digital data is applied to processing unit <b>111</b>. The digital data input to processing unit <b>111</b> is stored in image memory <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">At printer unit <b>102</b>, the laser beam output from laser device <b>112</b> is directed onto a photoreceptor drum <b>115</b> that is charged by a corona charger <b>114</b>, whereby an electrostatic latent image is formed. Toner developer units <b>116</b>-<b>119</b> of the four colors of cyan, magenta, yellow and black are sequentially selected, and the electrostatic latent image on photoreceptor drum <b>115</b> is developed. An appropriate sheet is delivered from sheet cassettes <b>120</b>-<b>122</b>. The sheet passes through a timing roller <b>123</b>. The sheet is attracted on a transfer drum <b>126</b> by an electrostatic absorption charger <b>125</b> provided opposite to an absorption roller <b>124</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The toner image developed on photoreceptor drum <b>115</b> is transferred onto the sheet wound around transfer drum <b>126</b> by a transfer charger <b>127</b>. The rotation of transfer drum <b>115</b> is controlled by a drum motor <b>128</b>. In a full color copy mode, the above printing step is repeated for the four colors of cyan, magenta, yellow and black.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In other words, transfer drum <b>126</b> is rotated <b>4</b> times. Then, the sheet is detached from transfer drum <b>126</b> by virtue of the discharge at the surface of transfer drum <b>126</b> and the action of a separation claw <b>131</b> through means of a separation charger <b>129</b> and a discharger <b>130</b>. The sheet passes through a fix device <b>132</b> to be subjected to the fixing process and then output onto a discharge tray <b>133</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Fix device <b>132</b> includes an upper roller <b>134</b> and a lower roller <b>135</b>. Respective rollers <b>134</b> and <b>135</b> are adjusted to attain a predetermined temperature by a heater.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">When in a dual copy mode, the sheet discharged by a sheet inversion unit <b>136</b> is inverted. An image is formed again on the inverted sheet located on transfer drum <b>126</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Copy vender <b>151</b> includes a coin inlet <b>153</b> through which a coin is inserted, a coin return button <b>154</b>, a coin outlet <b>155</b>, and a display <b>156</b> that displays the amount of inserted coins. Digital copy machine <b>100</b> and copy vender <b>151</b> are connected by a cable through a connector <b>152</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In the present embodiment, printing is allowed by inserting a coin. Alternatively, printing can be permitted by the insertion of a monetary bill, a prepaid card, an IC card, a cash card, and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram to describe the structure of the control unit of the digital copy machine of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, digital copy machine <b>100</b> includes processing unit <b>111</b> to provide the entire control of digital copy machine <b>100</b>, an operation panel <b>300</b> to set the printing condition of digital copy machine <b>100</b> and also the correspondence between trigger information and control information that will be described afterwards, a storage unit <b>203</b> storing trigger information and control operation in correspondence set by operation panel <b>300</b>, the aforementioned scanner unit <b>101</b>, printer unit <b>102</b>, image memory <b>110</b>, a signature information detection unit <b>200</b> to detect signature information from the image data stored in image memory <b>110</b>, a signature information recognition unit <b>201</b> to recognize the detected signature information, a communication processing unit <b>202</b> connected to external personal computers <b>251</b> and <b>252</b> and to a copyright management server <b>250</b> through Local Area Network (hereinafter referred to as LAN), and a serial I/O <b>204</b> for serial connection with copy vender <b>151</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Operation panel <b>300</b> is provided at the top face of digital copy machine <b>100</b> to input the setting of print conditions in printing out through printer unit <b>102</b> of digital copy machine <b>100</b> and the setting of trigger information and control operation. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a plan view of operation panel <b>300</b>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, operation panel <b>300</b> includes a liquid crystal display unit <b>303</b>, a touch panel <b>304</b> provided thereon and formed of a transparent member, a ten-key <b>301</b> to input numerics such as the number of prints and the print magnification rate and the like, and a start key <b>313</b> to designate initiation of printing.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Liquid crystal display <b>303</b> displays the print condition currently set in digital copy machine <b>100</b> and the internal status. The operator depresses touch panel <b>304</b> on liquid crystal display <b>303</b> according to a menu displayed at liquid crystal display <b>303</b> to input the print condition and set the trigger information and the control operation corresponding to the trigger information. Alphanumerics and kanji characters can be input by displaying Japanese syllabary and alphabets on liquid crystal display <b>303</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the trigger information and control operation input through operation panel <b>303</b> are stored in correspondence in storage unit <b>203</b>. The trigger information and control operation will be described in detail afterwards.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Communication processing unit <b>202</b> transfers data between externally connected personal computer, LAN and public switched telephone network (PSTN) and processing unit <b>111</b>. Communication processing unit <b>202</b> mainly includes an input/output control unit providing communication control to transmit/receive control signals and image data directly to/from a personal computer, a network control unit connected to LAN to provide network control to transmit/receive control signals and image data to/from an external LAN-connected apparatus, a facsimile conversion unit to transmit/receive data to/from processing unit <b>111</b> and carry out conversion such as the pixel density, coding method and the like in a facsimile operation, and a G3 unit that provides communication control such as modulation and demodulation of image data and control signals in a facsimile operation, and connected to the telephone line to provide communication control with the PSTN.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the configuration of communication processing unit <b>202</b> connected with external personal computers <b>251</b> and <b>252</b> and copyright management server <b>250</b> through the LAN. Here, communication control unit <b>202</b> uses the network control unit to transmit/receive control signals and image data to/from personal computers <b>251</b> and <b>252</b> and copyright management server <b>250</b> via the LAN.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Processing unit <b>111</b> is connected with serial Input and Output interface (I/O) <b>204</b> to effect serial communication with copy vender <b>151</b> connected to serial I/O <b>204</b>. Processing unit <b>111</b> carries out serial communication with copy vender <b>151</b>, whereby a copy fee in accordance with the printing process carried out by printer unit <b>102</b> is collected by copy vender <b>151</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Image data to be printed out by printer unit <b>102</b> is stored in image memory <b>110</b>. Image memory <b>110</b> stores image data read in by scanner unit <b>101</b> and image data received at communication processing unit <b>202</b> from external personal computers <b>251</b> and <b>252</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Signature information detection unit <b>200</b> detects signature information from the image data stored in image memory <b>110</b>. Here, signature information refers to additional information such as ID, logo marks, the label of the copyrighted document, code information, and the like embedded in the image data. The well known art is employed as to the technique of embedding signature information in the readout image data of a document or the technique of detecting signature information from image data in which signature information is embedded. For example, the technique of embedding signature information in image data includes the method of adding signature information into the luminous value of an image, and the method of converting image data into frequency components to embed signature information into a particular frequency component. FFT (Fast Fourier Transform), DCD (Discrete Cosine Transform) and the like are used for frequency conversion. Signature information may include trigger information to initiate execution of a particular control operation, print condition, image processing condition, and electronic mail address, as will be described afterwards.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Signature information recognition unit <b>201</b> recognizes signature information as character information corresponding to the image information detected by signature information detection unit <b>200</b>. In this case, the well known character recognition method is employed.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Copyright management server <b>250</b> is a computer to audit the copy fee for each document or image data. The copy fee is calculated for each document according to the received number of prints from communication processing unit <b>202</b>, whereby the payment charging process is carried out.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow chart showing the process carried out by digital copy machine <b>100</b>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, digital copy machine <b>100</b> determines whether image data has been read out or not (step S<b>01</b>). This determination of image data read out is effected by sensing depression of start button <b>313</b> on operation panel <b>300</b>. This determination can be made at the time point when image data that is the digital version by processing unit <b>111</b> of analog signals read out from scanner unit <b>101</b> is stored in image memory <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In the case where image data readout is detected, control proceeds to step S<b>03</b>. In the case where image data readout is not detected, determination is made whether image data has been input or not (step S<b>02</b>). Input of image data refers to reception of image data from external-connected personal computers <b>251</b> and <b>252</b> at communication processing unit <b>202</b> through the LAN. Input of image data is sensed at the time point when the received image data is stored in image memory <b>110</b>. In the case where image data input is detected, control proceeds to S<b>03</b>, otherwise to step S<b>01</b> since image data will not be stored in image memory <b>110</b> by image data readout or image data input.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">At step S<b>03</b>, signature information detection unit <b>200</b> detects the signature information from the image data stored in image memory <b>110</b>. The detected signature information is currently image data.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">At step S<b>03</b>, determination is made whether signature information has been detected or not (step S<b>02</b>). When signature information has not been detected, the image data read in by scanner unit <b>101</b> or the image data received by communication processing unit <b>202</b> is printed out by printer unit <b>102</b> (step S<b>10</b>). In the case where signature information has been detected (YES at step S<b>04</b>), character recognition is effected for the signature information detected at signature information recognition unit <b>201</b>. Character recognition here is the process of converting the signature information which is the image data detected by signature information detection unit <b>200</b> into character data to recognize the signature information as characters. The well known character recognition technique is employed for this process.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Determination is made whether the signature information recognized as characters is trigger information or not (step S<b>06</b>). Trigger information is code information set through operation panel <b>300</b>, for example, numerics or alphabets of a predetermined number of characters. Trigger information is a mark to initiate execution of a predetermined control operation. Therefore, the trigger information does not necessary correspond to character data, and may be image data. In the case where trigger information is image data, conversion into character data is not carried out in recognizing the signature information by signature information recognition unit <b>201</b>. The presence/absence of trigger information is determined at step S<b>06</b> directly by the image data.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In the case where the signature information is not trigger information (NO at step S<b>06</b>), control proceeds to step S<b>07</b> to carry out the process to limit printing with respect to copyrighted material. This limitation process will be described afterwards.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In the case where the signature information is trigger information (YES at step S<b>06</b>), the control operation corresponding to the trigger information detected in step S<b>06</b> is retrieved from strage unit <b>203</b> (step S<b>08</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Here, trigger information and control operation will be described. Trigger information and corresponding control operation are input through operation panel <b>300</b>. First, operation panel <b>300</b> is set to the mode to input trigger information. Using alphanumerics key and the like displayed on liquid crystal display <b>303</b>, a code which is the trigger information is input. Here, alphabets of three characters are taken as a way of example. Next, a control operation corresponding to that trigger information is selected. More specifically, a plurality of selections are displayed on liquid crystal display <b>303</b>. An appropriate selection is made by depressing touch panel <b>304</b>. Following the selection of all the control operations required, the “*” key of ten-key <b>301</b> is depressed, whereby the trigger information and corresponding control operation are registered in storage unit <b>203</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows trigger information and corresponding control operations stored in storage unit <b>203</b>. For the trigger information of “AAA”, correspondence is established of control operation <b>1</b> of “print”, control operation <b>2</b> of “count number of prints”, and control operation <b>3</b> of “transmit number of prints to address aaaa”. More specifically, when the trigger information of “AAA” is recognized by signature information recognition unit <b>201</b>, the operation of printing by printer unit <b>102</b> the image data stored in image memory <b>110</b> is carried out as the first control operation, the operation of counting the number of prints of the image data by printer unit <b>102</b> is carried out as the second control operation, and the operation of transmitting to copyright management server <b>250</b> having the electronic mail address of “aaaa” the number of counted prints in the second control operation is carried out as the third operation.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Similarly, for the trigger operation of “BBB”, correspondence is established of the operation of “binarization process on image data” as control operation <b>1</b>, and the operation of “print” as control operation <b>2</b>. When trigger information “BBB” is recognized by signature information recognition unit <b>201</b>, the image process of binarizing the multi-value image data stored in image memory <b>110</b> is carried out by processing unit <b>111</b> as the first control operation, and the operation of printing out the image data subjected to binarization in the second control operation is carried out by printer unit <b>102</b> as the second control operation.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">For the trigger information of “CCC”, correspondence of the operation of “suppress print” as control operation <b>1</b> and the operation of “display print disabled on screen” as control operation <b>2</b> is established and stored. When the trigger information of “CCC” is recognized by signature information recognition unit <b>201</b>, a signal inhibiting image data printing is output to printer unit <b>102</b> and the image data stored in image memory <b>110</b> is erased as the first operation. Then, a message of “this document cannot be printed”, for example, is displayed on liquid crystal display <b>303</b> of operation panel <b>300</b> as the second operation.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Thus, upon recognition of trigger information by signature information recognition unit <b>201</b>, the series of control operations in correspondence with the recognized trigger information is retrieved from storage unit <b>203</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Returning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, upon retrieval of the control operation corresponding to the recognized trigger information from storage unit <b>203</b> at step S<b>08</b>, the retrieved control operation is executed (step S<b>09</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">The limitation process carried out at step S<b>07</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> will be described with reference to the flow chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, determination is made whether the signature information recognized by signature information recognition unit <b>201</b> includes a processing condition or not (step S<b>21</b>). A processing condition refers to the designation of carrying out a particular image process on the image data stored in image memory <b>110</b>. The particular image process includes, for example, image data binarization process, image data magnification/shrink process, modifying the resolution of the image data, the process of reducing the color of image data, for example, converting color image data into black and white image data, and the like. This process is effective in the case where the creator of the document wishes to degrade the quality of the copied product than that of the original document.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">In the case where the recognized signature information includes a process condition, an image process according to the process condition is carried out by processing unit <b>111</b> on the image data stored in image memory <b>110</b> (step S<b>22</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Then, determination is made whether a printing condition is included in the recognized signature information (step S<b>23</b>). Here, a printing condition refers to the condition for a printing operation by printer unit <b>102</b>. For example, the condition includes the number of prints, the printing density, the magnification/shrinkage rate, and the like. This printing condition is effective when the creator wishes to specify the number of copies that can be printed out for the purpose of limiting the number of the copies, or when the creator wishes to lower the density of the printout to degrade the quality from the original document, or when a shrinkage rate is specified so that the size of the printed out copy becomes smaller than that of the original document.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">The print condition also includes a print inhibit signal. This is effective in the case where the creator of the document wishes to prevent his/her work from being copied. At step S<b>24</b>, determination is made whether the print condition corresponds to “inhibit signal” or not. In the case of an inhibit signal, the subsequent process is not executed and control returns to the main routine of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">In the case where the print condition does not correspond to an inhibit signal (NO at step S<b>24</b>), printer unit <b>102</b> is set to the print condition included in the signature information (step S<b>25</b>). Then, printing is carried out under the set printing condition (step S<b>26</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">When the printing ends, determination is made whether a mail address is included in the recognized signature information (step S<b>27</b>). When a mail address is included in the recognized signature information (YES at step S<b>27</b>), the number of prints output at step S<b>26</b>, the code information indicating the printed copyrighted material (document), and information indicating the printing event are transmitted from communication processing unit <b>202</b> to the mail address (step S<b>28</b>). In the present embodiment, the number of prints is transmitted as one of the printing condition. However, other printing conditions, for example, whether of a color mode or black and white mode, the print scaling rate, sheet size, and the like can be transmitted.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The mail address included in the signature information is the mail address of the owner of the document or copyright management server <b>250</b>. The creator of the document or the facility auditing the copyright can identify the number of printouts of the document. Accordingly, the creator of the document or the facility auditing the copyright can charge royalties and the like to the person or entity that has carried out the copy. Also, the amount of the copies printed out can be identified.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">At this stage, communication can be established between communication processing unit <b>202</b> and copyright management server <b>250</b> to transmit the copy charge to communication processing unit <b>202</b> from copyright management server <b>250</b>, so that the copy fee can be collected through copy vender <b>151</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The digital copy machine of the present embodiment detects and recognizes signature information from the image data read out by scanner unit <b>101</b> or the image data received at communication processing unit <b>202</b>. In the case where the signature information includes a processing condition designating a particular image process, the designated image process is applied on the image data, so that the image process intended by the creator of the document of interest is applied to output the image data on a recording medium such as a sheet of paper. Accordingly, the quality of the image data printed out on the recording medium can be degraded than that of the original document.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">In the case where the signature information includes a print condition, printer unit <b>102</b> is set to the print condition included in the signature information. Therefore, the image data can be printed out according to the printing condition desired by the creator. In the case where the printing condition corresponds to an inhibit signal, printing is suppressed at printer unit <b>102</b>. Therefore, copy of the original can be inhibited to prevent output of the image data onto a sheet of paper and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">In the case where the signature information includes a mail address, the number of prints carried out by printer unit <b>102</b> is transmitted to the mail address from communication processing unit <b>202</b>. By setting the mail address to the mail address of the creator or copyright management server <b>250</b>, the number of prints of the document or image data can be identified on the part of the creator or copyright management server <b>250</b>. Thus, the creator or the copyright administrator can charge the person or entity that has carried out printing of the original or image data.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">In the case where the signature information includes trigger information to initiate execution of a predetermined control operation, the control operation corresponding to the trigger information included in the signature information stored in storage unit <b>203</b> is executed. The above-described advantages can be obtained by providing setting of the image process according to the above processing condition in the control operation, printing according to a printing condition, data transmission to a mail address, and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">Since the trigger information and control operation can be input and set through operation panel <b>303</b>, the condition of printing out the image data stored in image memory <b>110</b> onto a recording medium such as paper can be modified arbitrarily.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Although the present invention has been described and illustrated in detail, it is clearly understood that the same is by way of illustration and example only and is not to be taken by way of limitation, the spirit and scope of the present invention being limited only by the terms of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An image processing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>an input unit entering image data;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a processing unit processing said image data;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a memory storing trigger information to initiate execution of a control operation and said control operation in correspondence;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detector detecting additional information including said trigger information from said image data; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller responsive to detection of said trigger information to execute said control operation corresponding to said trigger information stored in said memory,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said control operation includes a transmission operation transmitting information related to processing of said image data to a destination.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The image processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising an operation unit setting said trigger information and said control operation in correspondence.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The image processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said information related to processing of said image data includes information indicating an event of processing said image data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The image processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said information related to processing of said image data includes an image processing condition in processing said image data.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The image processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said control operation includes an image processing operation processing said image data according to a predetermined image processing condition.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The image processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said transmission operation includes an operation of transmitting said information related to processing of said image data to a destination specified by an electronic mail address through electronic mail.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An image processing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>an input unit entering image data;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a processing unit processing input image data;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detector detecting additional information from said image data, said additional information including trigger information to initiate execution of a predetermined control operation; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller executing said predetermined control operation in response to detection of said trigger information,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said predetermined control operation includes a transmission operation transmitting information related to processing of said image data to a destination.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
