<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298036-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298036</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11283340</doc-number>
<date>20051118</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>35</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>23</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257686</main-classification>
<further-classification>257777</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E23069</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E2307</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Scaling of functional assignments in packages</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6013877</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Degani et al.</name>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>174264</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7112878</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Akram</name>
<date>20060900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257686</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257686</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257777</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E23069</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E2307</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070114644</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070524</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Miller</last-name>
<first-name>Leah M.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fremont</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hall</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey A.</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Jose</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Luedeka, Neely &amp; Graham, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>LSI Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Milpitas</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Tran</last-name>
<first-name>Long K.</first-name>
<department>2818</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A family of package substrates adapted to receive a family of integrated circuits having different sizes and provide electrical connections between the integrated circuits and a circuit board. Each package substrate in the family includes a package substrate having a die side and a circuit board side. The package substrate has a size that is consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates. The die side has integrated circuit contacts disposed in a pattern designed to make electrical connections to a given integrated circuit in the family of integrated circuits for which the package substrate is designed, as defined by locations of contacts on the given integrated circuit. The circuit board side has circuit board contacts disposed in a pattern and with functional assignments that are consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="116.33mm" wi="138.60mm" file="US07298036-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="251.46mm" wi="197.19mm" file="US07298036-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates to the field of integrated circuit fabrication. More particularly, this invention relates to the design and construction of package substrates.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Integrated circuits are often packaged prior to sale and use, by physically and electrically connecting them to a package substrate, and then covering them in some manner against the package substrate. The package substrate provides all the necessary electrical connections between the electrical contacts for the integrated circuit, on one side of the package substrate, and the electrical contacts on either the printed circuit board or socket, that will connect to the other side of the package substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">As the term is used herein, “integrated circuit” includes devices such as those formed on monolithic semiconducting substrates, such as those formed of group IV materials like silicon or germanium, or group III-V compounds like gallium arsenide, or mixtures of such materials. The term includes all types of devices formed, such as memory and logic, and all designs of such devices, such as MOS and bipolar. The term also comprehends applications such as flat panel displays, solar cells, and charge coupled devices.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">As the design of a given integrated circuit evolves, it tends to be reduced in the size of the die on which it is formed. In addition, families of integrated circuits that provide the same basic functionality, but with different options or implementations, may also vary in size. Typically, a different package substrate is designed for use with each one of the different sized devices.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Traditionally, the locations of the electrical connections on both sides of the package substrate are determined based on general routing rules. The electrical connections on the die side of the package substrate are often placed according to the location of the contacts on the die, depending on the type of integrated circuit used. The electrical connections on the board side of the package substrate are often placed according to the easiest method of routing out the connections, allowing for proper signal isolation and other similar considerations. Also, the size of the package substrate that is used for a given die typically varies with the size of the die, with bigger substrates for bigger dice, and smaller substrates for smaller dice. All of this tends to change the pin out locations for each of the different package substrates.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The result of this design and fabrication process is that the package substrates for the dice within a given family of integrated circuits will all tend to have different sizes and different pin outs, just like the different integrated circuits that are mounted to them. Unfortunately, this requires either a different connection pattern or socket on the circuit board that is designed to use the packaged integrated circuit, for each of the different sizes or varieties of integrated circuit that might be used on the circuit board. This adds to the number of different circuit boards that must be produced and inventoried, adds to the complexity of board assembly, and thereby tends to increase costs. This also limits the ability to migrate to a different integrated circuit size during the product definition and development phase.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">What is needed, therefore, is a system that overcomes problems such as those described above, at least in part.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The above and other needs are met by a family of package substrates adapted to receive a family of integrated circuits having different sizes and provide electrical connections between the integrated circuits and a circuit board. Each package substrate in the family includes a package substrate having a die side and a circuit board side. The package substrate has a size that is consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates. The die side has integrated circuit contacts disposed in a pattern designed to make electrical connections to a given integrated circuit in the family of integrated circuits for which the package substrate is designed, as defined by locations of contacts on the given integrated circuit. The circuit board side has circuit board contacts disposed in a pattern and with functional assignments that are consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Thus, the preferred embodiments of the present invention provide a means to create a family of packages that allow the die size of the integrated circuit to grow or shrink dramatically, while still maintaining the same pin out for the package. This enables a board designer to create a single board design, independent of any changes that may occur at the die level.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According another aspect of the invention there is described a package substrate adapted to receive a family of integrated circuits having different sizes and provide electrical connections between the integrated circuits and a circuit board. The package substrate includes a package substrate having a die side and a circuit board side. The package substrate has a size that is sufficient to accommodate all of the different sizes in the family of integrated circuits. The die side has integrated circuit contacts disposed in a pattern designed to make electrical connections to the integrated circuits in the family of integrated circuits, as defined by locations of contacts on the integrated circuits. The circuit board side has circuit board contacts disposed in a pattern and with functional assignments that are consistent for all of the integrated circuits in the family of integrated circuits.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to a further aspect of the invention there is described a family of package substrates adapted to receive a family of integrated circuits having different sizes and provide electrical connections between the integrated circuits and a circuit board. Each package substrate in the family includes a package substrate having a die side and a circuit board side. The package substrate has a size that is consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates. The die side has integrated circuit contacts disposed in a pattern designed to make electrical connections to a given integrated circuit in the family of integrated circuits for which the package substrate is designed, as defined by locations of contacts on the given integrated circuit. The circuit board side has circuit board contacts disposed in a pattern that is consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates. The circuit board contacts that are not required to make unique electrical connections to the given integrated circuit are commonly electrically connected within the package substrate.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Further advantages of the invention are apparent by reference to the detailed description when considered in conjunction with the figures, which are not to scale so as to more clearly show the details, wherein like reference numbers indicate like elements throughout the several views, and wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a plan view of a ball contact side of a preferred embodiment of a package substrate according to the present invention, depicting in phantom the outer dimensions of three different sizes of integrated circuit that could be used with the package substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross section view of the preferred embodiment of the package substrate according to the present invention, depicting a first size of integrated circuit that could be used with the package substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross section view of the preferred embodiment of the package substrate according to the present invention, depicting a second size of integrated circuit that could be used with the package substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross section view of the preferred embodiment of the package substrate according to the present invention, depicting a third size of integrated circuit that could be used with the package substrate.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The preferred embodiments of the present invention provide a means to create a family of packages that allow the die size of the integrated circuit to grow or shrink dramatically, while still maintaining the same pin out for the package. This enables a board designer to create a single board design, independent of any changes that may occur at the die level.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">With reference now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> there is depicted a plan view of a ball contact side of a preferred embodiment of a package substrate <b>12</b> according to the present invention, depicting in phantom the outer dimensions of three different sizes of integrated circuits <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, and <b>18</b>, that could be used with the package substrate <b>12</b>. An integrated circuit <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, and <b>18</b> together with the package substrate <b>12</b> comprise a packaged integrated circuit <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Also depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> are electrical contacts <b>20</b> disposed on the circuit board side of the package substrate <b>12</b>. The electrical contacts <b>20</b> are variously given designations of P for power contacts, G for ground contacts, and S for signal contacts. It is appreciated that these designations are only representative of the various electrical connections that a packaged integrated circuit would require, and the placement of the contacts in the figures is purely by way of example only, without any consideration being made to the appropriateness of the layout.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the package substrates <b>12</b> according to the preferred embodiment of the invention are designed to accept several different chip sizes <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, and <b>18</b> on the die side, while presenting a common contact pattern <b>20</b> on the circuit board side. In various embodiments, either a single package substrate <b>12</b> is designed to accommodate more than one different size of integrated circuit <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, and <b>18</b>, or more preferably, different package substrates <b>12</b> are designed to each accommodate a single size of integrated circuit <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, and <b>18</b>. However, in each case, the package substrates <b>12</b> are designed to stay at the same size and to present a consistent contact <b>20</b> pattern on the circuit board side of the package substrate <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> depicts a cross section view of the preferred embodiment of the package substrate <b>12</b> according to the present invention, depicting a first size <b>18</b> of integrated circuit that could be used with the package substrate <b>12</b>. As depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, even though the integrated circuit <b>18</b> is fairly small, and a smaller package substrate <b>12</b> could be used, the size of the package substrate <b>12</b> is kept at a standard size. Further, the contacts <b>20</b> are kept in a standard pattern, and the electrical connections <b>24</b> are routed as appropriate from a given electrical contact <b>22</b> on the integrated circuit <b>18</b> to a standard contact <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> depicts a cross section view of the preferred embodiment of the package substrate <b>12</b> according to the present invention, depicting a second size <b>16</b> of integrated circuit that could be used with the package substrate <b>12</b>. As depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, even though the integrated circuit <b>16</b> is of an intermediate size, and a smaller package substrate <b>12</b> could be used, the size of the package substrate <b>12</b> is kept at a standard size. Further, the contacts <b>20</b> are kept in a standard pattern, and the electrical connections <b>24</b> are routed as appropriate from a given electrical contact <b>22</b> on the integrated circuit <b>16</b> to a standard contact <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> depicts a cross section view of the preferred embodiment of the package substrate <b>12</b> according to the present invention, depicting a third size <b>14</b> of integrated circuit that could be used with the package substrate <b>12</b>. As depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, even though the integrated circuit <b>14</b> is fairly large, the size of the package substrate <b>12</b> is kept at a standard size. Further, the contacts <b>20</b> are kept in a standard pattern, and the electrical connections <b>24</b> are routed as appropriate from a given electrical contact <b>22</b> on the integrated circuit <b>14</b> to a standard contact <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Thus, the present invention might not reduce the number of different package substrates <b>12</b> that are needed to accommodate the various integrated circuit sizes <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, and <b>18</b> in all embodiments, but will reduce the number of different designs for a circuit board that is required in order to make use of the different integrated circuits <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, and <b>18</b>. This is accomplished by providing a consistent contact <b>20</b> pattern and pin out on the circuit board side of the package substrate <b>12</b> for all of the package substrates <b>12</b> in the family.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In this manner, preferably all of the contacts on the circuit board that connect to the contacts <b>20</b> of the packaged integrated circuit <b>10</b> can be kept in a single pattern for all of the various integrated circuits that might be used in that position on the circuit board. This reduces the number of different circuit boards that must be designed, fabricated, and inventoried, and thus tends to reduce circuit board fabrication costs.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The family of integrated circuits is preferably floor-planned in such a manner so as to allow the migration from one integrated circuit <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, <b>18</b> size to another, while maintaining functional equivalency. The package substrate <b>12</b>, which is common to all integrated circuits <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, <b>18</b> of varying sizes in the family, preferably has a set maximum signal count that it can support. This maximum signal count is set to the signal count of the integrated circuit <b>18</b> in the family which has the minimum number of signals. For all of the integrated circuits <b>14</b>, <b>16</b> in the family that have connections on the die for a greater number of signals than the minimum signal count family member <b>18</b>, the signal connections on the die side that exceed the maximum package substrate <b>12</b> supported signal count are tied to ground, as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The ball side connections of the package substrate <b>12</b> do not change.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The package substrates according to the preferred embodiments of the present invention also enable the multiple use of test hardware that is employed to access the packaged integrated circuits offered in the package family.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">This various embodiments of the present invention can be extended to any package <b>10</b> cross section, ball count <b>20</b>, body size <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, and <b>18</b>, and varying bump pitches <b>22</b>. Any integrated circuit package substrate <b>12</b> technology, such as BGA, CSP, and so forth, in either ceramic or plastic, or wire bond or flip chip versions can be used with the various embodiments of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The foregoing description of preferred embodiments for this invention has been presented for purposes of illustration and description. It is not intended to be exhaustive or to limit the invention to the precise form disclosed. Obvious modifications or variations are possible in light of the above teachings. The embodiments are chosen and described in an effort to provide the best illustrations of the principles of the invention and its practical application, and to thereby enable one of ordinary skill in the art to utilize the invention in various embodiments and with various modifications as are suited to the particular use contemplated. All such modifications and variations are within the scope of the invention as determined by the appended claims when interpreted in accordance with the breadth to which they are fairly, legally, and equitably entitled.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A family of ball bond package substrates adapted to receive a family of integrated circuits having different sizes and provide electrical connections between the integrated circuits and a circuit board, where each package substrate in the family comprises:
<claim-text>a package substrate having a die side and a circuit board side, the package substrate having a size that is consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the die side having ball bond integrated circuit contacts disposed in a pattern designed to make electrical connections to a given one of the different sizes of integrated circuit in the family of integrated circuits for which the package substrate is designed, as defined by locations of contacts on the given integrated circuit, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the circuit board side having circuit board contacts with a same pattern and same functional assignments that are consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A ball bond package substrate adapted to receive a family of integrated circuits having different sizes and provide electrical connections between the integrated circuits and a circuit board, where the package substrate comprises:
<claim-text>a die side and a circuit board side, and having a size that is sufficient to accommodate all of the different sizes in the family of integrated circuits,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the die side having ball bond integrated circuit contacts disposed in a pattern designed to make electrical connections to the different sizes of integrated circuits in the family of integrated circuits, as defined by locations of contacts on the integrated circuits, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the circuit board side having circuit board contacts disposed in a pattern and with functional assignments that are consistent for all of the integrated circuits in the family of integrated circuits.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A family of ball bond package substrates adapted to receive a family of integrated circuits having different sizes and provide electrical connections between the integrated circuits and a circuit board, where each package substrate in the family comprises:
<claim-text>a die side and a circuit board side, and having a size that is consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the die side having ball bond integrated circuit contacts disposed in a pattern designed to make electrical connections to a given one of the different sizes of integrated circuits in the family of integrated circuits for which the package substrate is designed, as defined by locations of contacts on the given integrated circuit, where integrated circuit contacts that exceed a maximum number of unique integrated circuit contacts are commonly electrically connected within the package substrate, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the circuit board side having circuit board contacts disposed in a pattern that is consistent for all of the package substrates in the family of package substrates.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
