<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296942-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296942</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10545876</doc-number>
<date>20040123</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>43</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>43</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>401117</main-classification>
<further-classification>401115</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Writing instrument</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2605746</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kahn et al.</name>
<date>19520800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2757639</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wichmann</name>
<date>19560800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>401115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2870741</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kersten</name>
<date>19590100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>401100</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4469462</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hashimoto et al.</name>
<date>19840900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6585441</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Shamitoff</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>401115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>52733</doc-number>
<date>18891200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>FR</country>
<doc-number>1 100962</doc-number>
<date>19550900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>FR</country>
<doc-number>1 127 686</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19561200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>British Search Report for British Application No. GB 0303670.4; Date of Search Mar. 17, 2003.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00010">
<othercit>International Search Report for PCT Application No. PCT/GB2004/000289; Filed Jan. 23, 2004; Date of Completion May 3, 2004; Date of Mailing Jul. 1, 2004.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>401 99</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>401115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>401117</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>401109</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060171762</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060803</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mayne</last-name>
<first-name>Geoffrey Peter</first-name>
<address>
<street>164 Somerset Road</street>
<city>Handsworth Birmingham B20 2J0</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>GB</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>GB</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Alston &amp; Bird LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Walczak</last-name>
<first-name>David J.</first-name>
<department>3751</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/GB2004/000289</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040123</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20050817</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2004/074002</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20040902</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A ball point pen has a retractable ink container (<b>13</b>) and writing tip (<b>12</b>) that are releasably held in the extended position by a locking element (<b>19</b>) freely movable in a transparent enclosure (<b>18</b>) at the remote end of the barrel (<b>11</b>). The locking element (<b>19</b>) may have the appearance of a football or golf ball. In another embodiment the locking element is elongated and has flat sides that may carry advertising or promotional markings.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="229.62mm" wi="121.84mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="230.63mm" wi="134.28mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="228.94mm" wi="131.32mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="225.30mm" wi="83.14mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="222.33mm" wi="96.60mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="240.71mm" wi="104.48mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="226.14mm" wi="99.23mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="226.91mm" wi="117.77mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="227.50mm" wi="111.84mm" file="US07296942-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION  </heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates to an improved writing instrument of the kind having a writing tip, such as a ball point, at one end of a writing fluid chamber, the chamber and tip being retractable into a barrel or housing of the instrument when it is not in use to prevent inadvertent marking e.g. of hands or clothing. To write with the instrument the tip and chamber are moved relative to the barrel until the tip projects from one end of the barrel, releasable locking means being used to hold the tip in the extended position.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">An object of the present invention is to provide a mechanism for such a writing instrument which is attractive and fun to use and which lends itself to the display of advertising or promotional material.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION </heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In accordance with the present invention there is provided a writing instrument comprising a barrel, a writing fluid container moveable axially of the barrel whereby a writing tip of the container can be projected from or withdrawn into one end of the barrel, spring means biasing the container to the withdrawn position, a trigger extending from the container and projecting through an opening in the barrel whereby the container can be moved against the action of the spring to the projected position and means for releasably holding the container in the projected position, said holding means comprising a locking element which is freely moveable within an enclosure at the other end of the barrel, the enclosure having a shape such that said element may be interposed between the container and a component of the enclosure to hold the container in the projected position in a first position of said element and is displaceable under gravity or by inertia transversely of the enclosure to a second position, when released from the influence of the spring means by actuation of the trigger, in which second position said element does not prevent movement of the container to the withdrawn position.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Preferably the enclosure is transparent.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In one embodiment of the invention stop means projects inwardly of one side of the enclosure and the container has at its end remote from the tip a plunger from which the trigger extends, the plunger having a flange or lip extending upwardly in a lengthwise direction of the enclosure on the opposite side of the latter to the stop means, the locking element being dimensioned to pass the stop means except when held by the spring means between the latter and the flange or lip.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Preferably the stop means is intermediate the ends of the enclosure and on the side of the stop means remote from the plunger is a compartment of the enclosure in which the locking element is freely moveable.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The locking element is preferably of a rounded configuration and may be generally spherical.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The enclosure may be an enlargement of said other end of the barrel.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In another embodiment of the invention the locking element is elongated axially of the enclosure; one end of the latter being stepped and the arrangement is such that with the locking element between the container and the step of the enclosure the spring means is unable to move the container to the withdrawn position.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The locking element may be pivotable at one end and moveable transversely of the enclosure at its other end.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The locking element may have a relatively larger, rounded end in contact with a plunger at the end of the container remote from the tip and a relatively thinner end for engaging the step, the arrangement being such that with the plunger drawn against the spring means the locking element is able to rock on the plunger to align its thinner end with, the step.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Alternatively said step may be provided on a plunger at the end of the container remote from the tip and the locking element may have a relatively thicker end which is pivotally mounted at the end of the enclosure remote from the plunger and a relatively thinner end which can be moved across the enclosure between positions aligned with or not aligned with the step.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In yet another embodiment of the invention the trigger extends from a plunger at the end of the container remote from the tips the plunger being a sliding fit within a first compartment of the enclosure, said first compartment communicating with a second compartment of the enclosure offset laterally from the first compartment and the locking element being displaceable under gravity or inertia between the compartments when the plunger is moved to compress the spring, the arrangement being such that when the locking element occupies the first compartment it prevents withdrawal of the container and such that when the locking element occupies the second compartment the spring means may move the container to its withdrawn position. In this embodiment the locking element is preferably in the form of a ball.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The end of the plunger remote from the container is preferably chamfered to prevent escape of the locking element from the first compartment when the container is held in the projecting position.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Preferred embodiments of the present invention will now be described with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a sectional elevation of a first embodiment of a writing instrument in accordance with the invention, showing the writing tip extended;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a similar view of the writing instrument of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> but showing the writing tip retracted;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a sectional elevation of a second embodiment of a writing instrument in accordance with the invention showing the writing tip in the extended position;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view similar to that of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> but showing the writing tip in the retracted position;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a sectional elevation of a third embodiment of a writing instrument in accordance with the invention showing the writing tip in the extended position;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> but showing the writing tip in the retracted position;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a sectional elevation of a fourth embodiment of a writing instrument in accordance with the invention showing the writing tip in the retracted position; and</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> but showing the writing tip in the extended position.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The writing instrument <b>10</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> has a barrel <b>11</b> from one end of which a writing tip <b>12</b> of an ink container <b>13</b> can project, the container with its tip being biased by a compression spring <b>14</b> acting between the barrel and a stop <b>40</b> on the container <b>13</b> to retract the container <b>13</b> and its tip <b>12</b> into the barrel <b>11</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Alternatively the spring <b>14</b> may extend throughout the length of the container <b>13</b> and act on the underside of a plunger <b>15</b> integral with the end of the container <b>13</b> remote from its tip <b>12</b>. Projecting from the plunger <b>15</b> is an integral trigger or latch <b>16</b>. This extends out of the barrel <b>11</b> through a slot <b>17</b> which is elongated axially of the barrel <b>11</b> sufficiently to allow the trigger <b>16</b> to be moved against the action of spring <b>14</b> against the stop until the tip <b>12</b> is extended from the barrel <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">At the end of the barrel <b>11</b> remote from the tip <b>12</b> is a transparent enlargement <b>18</b> providing an enclosure for a spherical locking element or ball <b>19</b> which is freely moveable throughout the enclosure. Midway along the length of the enclosure a stop <b>20</b> projects inwardly of the enclosure. A lip or flange <b>21</b> projects into the enclosure from the plunger <b>15</b> on the side of the enclosure remote from the stop <b>20</b>, the dimensions of these components being such that the ball <b>19</b> can pass the stop <b>20</b> if not in contact with the flange <b>21</b>, but such that if the ball <b>19</b> is trapped between the flange <b>21</b> and the stop <b>20</b> it will prevent movement of the plunger <b>15</b> inwardly of the enclosure.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">If desired only part of the enlargement may be transparent, such that the ball <b>19</b> is visible only in one of it two positions. Transparency may be provided by a temperature sensitive material such that the interior of the enclosure is visible only when the enclosure is heated by being held in the hand, at other times being opaque.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">To allow the tip <b>12</b> to be retracted into the barrel <b>11</b> the trigger <b>16</b> is first depressed against the spring <b>14</b> sufficiently to allow the ball <b>19</b> to pass the stop <b>20</b>. The writing instrument can if necessary be inverted and/or shaken until the ball <b>19</b> rolls by gravity or through inertia into the upper compartment of the enclosure above the stop <b>20</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The spring <b>14</b> is now able to move the plunger <b>15</b> inwardly of the enclosure <b>18</b> until the writing tip <b>12</b> is retracted (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">To reverse this sequence the instrument <b>10</b> is held upright while the trigger <b>16</b> is depressed sufficiently to allow the ball <b>19</b> to fall past the stop <b>20</b>. When the trigger <b>16</b> is now released the ball <b>19</b> will become trapped between the flange <b>21</b> and the stop <b>20</b>, holding the tip <b>12</b> in its extended position.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The ball <b>19</b> may be shaped and marked to resemble a football, a golf ball, a cricket ball or any other sporting ball. The ball and/or other components of the writing instrument may carry markings identifying a particular sporting club, society or side so that the instrument can be used as an advertising and promotional item as well as a novelty item.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In the alternative embodiment of the present invention illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> a writing instrument <b>10</b>A has a barrel <b>11</b>A from one end of which the tip <b>12</b>A of an ink container <b>13</b>A may extend. At the end of the container <b>13</b>A remote from the tip <b>12</b>A it is integral with a plunger <b>15</b>A from which a trigger or latch <b>16</b>A projects out of the barrel <b>11</b>A through a slot <b>17</b>A. A spring <b>14</b>A biases the plunger <b>15</b>A and container <b>13</b>A to the retracted position of the tip <b>12</b>A (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In this embodiment however the locking element <b>19</b>A is not spherical but is elongated and lies within a transparent enclosure <b>18</b>A at the end of the barrel <b>11</b>A remote from the tip <b>12</b>A. The locking element <b>19</b>A is flat-sided and has a thicker, rounded end <b>22</b> resting in a groove <b>23</b> in the facing end of the plunger <b>15</b>A. Within the enclosure <b>18</b>A at a position remote from the plunger <b>15</b>A is a block <b>24</b> which only partly extends across the enclosure thus providing a step <b>25</b> which can be selectively confronted by the narrower end <b>27</b> of the locking element <b>19</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In use of the instrument of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, to retract the tip <b>12</b>A from the position of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> to the position of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> first the trigger <b>16</b>A is depressed sufficiently to free the locking member <b>19</b>A. This can then be moved across the enclosure <b>18</b>A, rotating on its rounded end <b>22</b>, until its narrower end <b>27</b> comes out of alignment with the step <b>25</b>. This can be achieved either by shaking the instrument, so that the locking element <b>19</b>A is moved by inertia, or by holding the instrument horizontally so that the locking element <b>19</b>A moves to its new position under gravity. When the trigger <b>16</b>A is now released the spring <b>14</b>A can raise the plunger <b>15</b>A until the trigger <b>16</b>A abuts the upper end of the slot <b>17</b>A, defining the retracted position of the tip <b>12</b>A into the barrel <b>11</b>A (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>). To extend the tip <b>12</b>A again the trigger <b>16</b>A is depressed sufficiently to allow the locking member <b>19</b>A to move back across the enclosure <b>18</b>A until its narrower end <b>27</b> is aligned with the step <b>25</b>, this again being achieved by gravity or inertia When the trigger <b>16</b>A is now released the locking member <b>19</b>A jams between the plunger <b>15</b>A and the step <b>25</b>, holding the tip <b>12</b>A in its extended position.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The writing instrument of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref> has a locking system which is effectively an inversion of that of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>. The elongated and tapered locking element <b>19</b>B has a thicker, rounded end <b>22</b>B at the end of the enclosure <b>18</b>B remote from the ink container <b>13</b>B. Preferably the locking element <b>19</b>B is pivoted by a pin <b>26</b> spanning the enclosure <b>18</b>B. The end of the plunger <b>15</b>B presented to the locking element <b>19</b>B is stepped as at <b>25</b>B. When the thinner end of the locking element <b>19</b>B is aligned with the step <b>25</b>B the writing tip <b>12</b>B is held in the extended position. When not aligned with the step <b>25</b>B (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) the container <b>13</b>B can be moved by the spring <b>14</b>B to the retracted position.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Either or both of the flat sides of the locking element <b>19</b>A or <b>19</b>B may be marked with advertising or promotional material.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 and 8</figref> the enclosure <b>18</b>C has a first compartment <b>27</b> in which the plunger <b>15</b>C is a sliding fit and a second compartment <b>28</b> offset from the first compartment and communicating therewith at the upper end of the writing instrument. A locking element in the form of a ball <b>19</b>C is free to move transversely of the enclosure <b>18</b>C between the compartments <b>27</b> and <b>28</b> when freed to do so by the plunger <b>15</b>C. To project the writing tip <b>12</b>C from the barrel <b>11</b>C the trigger <b>16</b>C is depressed, compressing the spring <b>14</b>C. Once the plunger <b>15</b>C has moved out of alignment with the compartment <b>28</b> the ball <b>19</b>C is free to roll across from the position of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> to the position of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, this being achieved either by “flipping” the instrument so that the ball moves relatively by inertia or turning it until the ball <b>19</b>C moves under gravity. When the trigger <b>16</b>C is now released the ball <b>19</b>C is trapped between the plunger <b>15</b>C and the top of the enclosure <b>18</b>C by the spring <b>14</b>C. To enhance this effect and prevent accidental dislodgement of the ball <b>19</b>C the top end <b>30</b> of the plunger <b>15</b>C is preferably chamfered as shown.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In this embodiment the “overhang” provided by the compartment <b>28</b> is used as the root of a pocket clip <b>31</b> for the instrument.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">For the avoidance of doubt, “writing instrument” and “writing fluid” as used herein and in the appended claims are intended to embrace instruments and fluids used for any graphic purpose and not merely the formation of lettering.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A writing instrument comprising a barrel, a writing fluid container moveable in an axial direction of the barrel whereby a writing tip of the container can be projected from or withdrawn into one end of the barrel, a spring exerting a force biasing the container to the withdrawn position, a trigger extending from the container and projecting through an opening in the barrel whereby the container can be moved against the force of the spring to the projected position, and a mechanism for releasably holding the container in the projected position, said holding mechanism comprising a locking element located within an enclosure at the other end of the barrel, the locking element having a height in the axial direction, wherein the locking element and enclosure are configured such that when the writing tip is in the withdrawn position the locking element is disposed within a portion of the enclosure having a depth in the axial direction that is greater than the height of the locking element and the locking element is freely movable over said depth, and when the writing tip is in the projected position the locking element may be immobilized to hold the writing tip in said projected position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A writing instrument as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the enclosure is transparent.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A writing instrument as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising stop means that projects inwardly of one side of the enclosure, and wherein the container has at its end remote from the tip a plunger from which the trigger extends, the plunger having a flange or lip extending upwardly in a lengthwise direction of the enclosure on an opposite side of the enclosure from the stop means, the locking element being dimensioned to pass the stop means except when held by the spring between the stop means and the flange or lip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A writing instrument as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the stop means is intermediate the ends of the enclosure and on the side of the stop means remote from the plunger is the chamber of the enclosure in which the locking element is freely moveable.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A writing instrument as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the locking element is of a rounded configuration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A writing instrument as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the locking element is generally spherical.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A writing instrument as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the enclosure is an enlargement of said other end of the barrel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A writing instrument as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the locking element is elongated axially of the enclosure, one end of the enclosure defining a step and the writing instrument being structured and arranged such that with the locking element between the container and the step of the enclosure the spring is unable to move the container to the withdrawn position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A writing instrument comprising a writing tip movable in an axial direction between a furthest retracted position and an extended position, and further comprising a locking element having a height in the axial direction and arranged for selectively locking the writing tip in the extended position, wherein when the writing tip is in the furthest retracted position the locking element is disposed within an enclosure having a depth in the axial direction that is greater than the height of the locking element and the locking element is freely movable over said depth.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A writing instrument comprising a barrel and a writing tip movable within the barrel in an axial direction between a retracted position and an extended position, and further comprising a locking element having a height in the axial direction and arranged for selectively locking the writing tip in the extended position, wherein when the writing tip is in the retracted position the locking element is disposed within a portion of an enclosure at one end of the barrel, said portion of the enclosure being defined between an end wall of the enclosure and a stop projecting laterally into the enclosure, said portion of the enclosure having a depth in the axial direction that is greater than the height of the locking element and the locking element being freely movable over said depth.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
