<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299121-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299121</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11394094</doc-number>
<date>20060331</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-102630</doc-number>
<date>20050331</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>43</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>19</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>P</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701101</main-classification>
<further-classification>701114</further-classification>
<further-classification>12340611</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Electronic control device for aviation engine</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4656588</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kubo</name>
<date>19870400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>701 76</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5140592</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Idleman et al.</name>
<date>19920800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>714  5</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5274645</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Idleman et al.</name>
<date>19931200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>714  6</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5422808</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Catanese et al.</name>
<date>19950600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>700 79</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6357427</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Luttrelll et al.</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6591167</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Minowa et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>701  1</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701101</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701102</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123609</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123625</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>12340611</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>12340612</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060235601</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061019</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Uruno</last-name>
<first-name>Hiroshi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Saitama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hamauzu</last-name>
<first-name>Akira</first-name>
<address>
<city>Saitama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yokoyama</last-name>
<first-name>Kiyoaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Saitama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kitaura</last-name>
<first-name>Hirohisa</first-name>
<address>
<city>Saitama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Birch, Stewart, Kolasch &amp; Birch, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Honda Motor Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Kwon</last-name>
<first-name>John T.</first-name>
<department>3747</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electronic control device is provided for an aviation engine. Each cylinder of the engine is equipped with main ignition plugs and back-up ignition plugs. Lane A including a first CPU and lane B including a second CPU are included in an ECU. The ignition control system is multiplexed by the two lanes A, B. The first and second CPU independently calculate ignition timing for each cylinder based on each sensor signal, and then exchange the results of these calculations with each other. At each cylinder, ignition timing is synchronized in such a manner that ignition timing of the main ignition plugs and ignition timing of the back-up ignition plugs match. The electronic control device so configured has a high level of redundancy with a small number of CPU's. Thus, electronic control device can be provided for the aviation engine with few limitations placed in relation to installation location.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="160.70mm" wi="187.79mm" file="US07299121-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="189.23mm" wi="162.98mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299121-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="190.50mm" wi="174.92mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299121-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="70.02mm" wi="171.53mm" file="US07299121-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="172.21mm" wi="148.93mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299121-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="186.27mm" wi="172.97mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299121-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application claims priority under 35 U.S.C. ยง119 to Japanese Patent Application Ser. No. 2001-284060, filed Sep. 18, 2001, the entire contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to an electronic control device for an aviation engine and particularly relates to an electronic control device for an aviation engine for automatically controlling all fuel consumption and ignition timing etc. using a computer.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of Background Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">FADEC (Full Authority Digital Engine Control) is a generic name for a system for electronically controlling an aviation engine, that receives information regarding the position of a throttle lever operated by a pilot and the engine, together with various information from various sensors fitted to the aviation craft, and controls the engine so as to obtain optimum engine thrust. Engine control is therefore electrical rather than mechanical as a result of adoption of FADEC, which enables improved responsiveness and accurate engine control. Further transmission of signals from the throttle lever in the cockpit to the engine are also changed to being electrical signals in a wire rather than carried out mechanically using cables as a result of the adoption of FADEC. This kind of FADEC is disclosed, for example, in U.S. Pat. No. 6,357,427 B1.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block view of an ignition control system for a four cylinder aviation engine of the related art to which FADEC is applied, and shows a configuration where two ECU's <b>100</b> and <b>200</b> control two cylinders at a time independently. Each cylinder is equipped with main ignition plugs (<b>1</b>T to <b>4</b>T) and back-up ignition plugs (<b>1</b>B to <b>4</b>B) for backing these up.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">At the first ECU <b>100</b>, the main ignition plug <b>1</b>T of the first cylinder and the back-up ignition plug <b>2</b>B of the second cylinder are supplied with electricity by the simultaneous ignition type first ignition coil <b>21</b>. The back-up ignition plug <b>1</b>B of the first cylinder and the main ignition plug <b>2</b>T of the second cylinder are supplied with electricity by the simultaneous ignition type second ignition coil <b>22</b>. The first CPU <b>11</b> and second CPU <b>12</b> are connected via the first and second igniters <b>31</b> and <b>32</b> upstream of the first and second ignition coils <b>21</b>, <b>22</b>. The first and second CPU <b>11</b> and <b>12</b> acquire crank speed and cam timing via the sensor input interface <b>41</b> and control energizing of the ignition coils <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> using ignition timing decided based on this information.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Similarly, at the second ECU <b>200</b>, the main ignition plug <b>3</b>T of the third cylinder and the back-up ignition plug <b>4</b>B of the fourth cylinder are supplied with electricity by the simultaneous ignition type first ignition coil <b>23</b>. The back-up ignition plug <b>3</b>B of the third cylinder and the main ignition plug <b>4</b>T of the fourth cylinder are supplied with electricity by the simultaneous ignition type fourth ignition coil <b>24</b>. The third CPU <b>13</b> and fourth CPU <b>14</b> are connected via the third and fourth igniters <b>33</b> and <b>34</b> upstream of the third and fourth ignition coils <b>23</b>, <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The third and fourth CPU <b>13</b> and <b>14</b> acquire crank speed and cam timing via the sensor input interface <b>42</b> and control energizing of the ignition coils <b>23</b>, <b>24</b> using ignition timing decided based on this information.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According to this configuration, the main ignition plugs and the back-up ignition plugs are always ignited at all of the cylinders by each of the simultaneous ignition type ignition coils <b>21</b> to <b>24</b>. This means that if one of the systems goes down at one ECU, this is compensated for by each cylinder of the other system firing. Namely, a redundancy function is implemented for the engine ignition.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block view of a fuel injection system for a four cylinder aviation engine of the related art applied to FADEC, with the same numerals as before showing the same functions.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A normal injection signal line from the first CPU <b>11</b> is secured at the first injector <b>1</b>J injecting fuel to within the first cylinder <b>1</b> via a high-side driver <b>51</b> with a current limiter. The normal injection signal outputted from the driver <b>51</b> is always monitored by the second CPU <b>12</b>. Further, an alternate injection signal line from the second CPU <b>12</b> is secured at the first injector via a high side driver <b>56</b> with a current limiter.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Similarly, a normal injection signal line from the second CPU <b>12</b> is secured at the first injector <b>2</b>J injecting fuel to within the first cylinder <b>2</b> via a high-side driver <b>52</b> with a current limiter. The normal injection signal outputted from the driver <b>52</b> is always monitored by the first CPU <b>121</b>. Further, an alternate injection signal line from the first CPU <b>11</b> is secured at the second injector via a high side driver <b>55</b> with a current limiter.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Similarly, normal injection signal line from the third CPU <b>13</b> is secured at the third injector <b>3</b>J injecting fuel to within the third cylinder <b>3</b> via a high-side driver <b>53</b> with a current limiter. The normal injection signal outputted from the driver <b>53</b> is always monitored by the fourth CPU <b>14</b>. Further, an alternate injection signal line from the fourth CPU <b>14</b> is secured at the third injector via a high side driver <b>58</b> with a current limiter.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Similarly, normal injection signal line from the fourth CPU <b>14</b> is secured at the fourth injector <b>4</b>J injecting fuel to within the fourth cylinder <b>4</b> via a high-side driver <b>54</b> with a current limiter. The normal injection signal outputted from the driver <b>54</b> is always monitored by the third CPU <b>13</b>. Further, an alternate injection signal line from the third CPU <b>13</b> is secured at the fourth injector via a high side driver <b>57</b> with a current limiter.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In this configuration, each CPU calculates the amount of normal injection and the amount of alternate injection so that, for example, in the case of the first CPU <b>11</b>, the amount for the normal injection for the first injector <b>1</b>J and the amount for the alternate injection for the second injector <b>2</b>J is calculated. In this way, if a normal injection signal is not outputted by the high side driver <b>52</b> with a current limiter even after a predetermined time elapses from the timing of the start of injection obtained from the alternate injection amount, it is determined that an abnormality has occurred at the normal injection system of the second injector <b>2</b>J and an alternate injection signal is outputted.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The technology of the related art described above has the following technological problems.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">(1) An expensive CPU is required for each of the cylinders.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">(2) Each ECU only carries out control of two cylinder sections. This means that ignition control and fuel injection control for two cylinders is not possible when, for example, there is an accident such as damage or disengagement etc. of a connector for the sensor input interface.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">(3) Each CPU operates independently. This means that in cases where complex ignition control such as lag angle control and advance angle control etc. is carried out taking not only crank and cam timing but also detection signals such as for an intake negative pressure sensor or nock sensor etc. as parameters, errors occur in the results of calculations of each CPU. As a result, in the case of ignition control, a shift occurs in the ignition timing of the main ignition plug and the ignition timing of the back-up ignition plug at each cylinder.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">(4) The casing for the ECU is large for the type where an ignition coil is built into the ECU and restrictions on the fitting position are therefore substantial. When the ECU is fitted at a position away from the engine, the distance between the ignition coil and the ignition plug becomes substantial and the long high tension cable is therefore necessary. Because of this, not only is secondary energy loss in ignition substantial and a fall in voltage supplied to the ignition plug invited, but also influence on emission performance is substantial.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY AND OBJECTS OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In order to resolve the aforementioned problems, it is the object of the present invention to bring about a high level of redundancy with a small number of CPU's, so as to provide an electronic control device for an aviation engine with few limitations placed in relation to installation location.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">According to a first aspect of the present invention, an electronic control device for an aviation engine for multiplex-controlling a multi-cylinder aviation engine using digital signals includes an ECU containing at least: a plurality of sensors for monitoring states of the engine, a first CPU for executing main control of all cylinders, a second CPU for executing back-up control of all cylinders, a communication circuit connected to the first and second CPU, and a sensor input interface for supplying detection signals of the sensors to each of the first and second CPU's, wherein a control system is multiplexed using a first lane containing the first CPU and a second lane containing the second CPU, and the first and second CPUs are mutually synchronized to control timing through communication using the communication circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">According to a second aspect of the present invention, sensor input interfaces are provided independently so as to correspond to the first and second CPU's respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">According to a third aspect of the present invention, the aviation engine is a four cylinder engine where each cylinder is equipped with a main ignition plug and a back-up ignition plug, including a simultaneous ignition-type first ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the main ignition plugs of the first and second cylinders, a simultaneous ignition-type second ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to third and fourth cylinders, a simultaneous ignition type third ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the first and second cylinder back-up ignition plugs, and a simultaneous ignition type first ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the back-up ignition plugs of the third and fourth cylinders, with each ignition coil being arranged outside of the ECU.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">According to a fourth aspect of the present invention, the aviation engine is provided with an injector at each cylinder, and comprises a normal signal system for supplying a normal injection signal from the first CPU to injectors of all of the cylinders, an alternate signal system for supplying an alternate signal from the second CPU to injectors of all of the cylinders, switching means for selectively connecting one of the normal signal system and the alternate signal system to the injectors of all of the cylinders, and means for notifying the first CPU of the operating conditions for the normal signal system, wherein when an abnormal operation of the normal signal system is detected by the first CPU when the normal signal system is connected to the injectors of all of the cylinders, the switching means is controlled so that the alternate signal system is connected to the injectors of all of the cylinders.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">According to the present invention, the following effects are achieved:</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">According to the first aspect of the invention, each CPU independently controls all of the cylinders. This means that if one CPU or the lane thereof malfunctions, control of all the cylinders is continued by the other CPU or its lane. However, each CPU is capable of mutually communicating and control timing can therefore by synchronized.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">According to the second aspect of the invention, a sensor input interface is provided for each CPU. This means that even if one sensor input interface malfunctions so that control using the lane including the sensor input interface is impossible, it is possible for control of all of the cylinders to be continued using the lane including the other CPU.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">According to the third aspect of the invention, it is possible to carry out ignition control in parallel using each CPU. This means that even if a lane including one CPU malfunctions, it is possible to continue ignition control using the lane including the other CPU without carrying out lane switching.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">According to the fourth aspect invention of claim <b>4</b>, even in cases where the control subject is switched over from a lane including one CPU to a lane including the other CPU, each CPU communicates with each other so that synchronization of control timing is always established and superior lane switching can therefore be carried out.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Further scope of applicability of the present invention will become apparent from the detailed description given hereinafter. However, it should be understood that the detailed description and specific examples, while indicating preferred embodiments of the invention, are given by way of illustration only, since various changes and modifications within the spirit and scope of the invention will become apparent to those skilled in the art from this detailed description.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The present invention will become more fully understood from the detailed description given hereinbelow and the accompanying drawings which are given by way of illustration only, and thus are not limitative of the present invention, and wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block view of an ignition control device for use with an aviation engine of a first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block view of a fuel injection system for use with an aviation engine of a second embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a view showing lane switching timing of a second embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block view of an ignition control system of an aviation engine of the related art applied to a FADEC; and</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block view of a fuel injection system of an aviation engine of the related art applied to a FADEC.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A detailed description will now be given of preferred embodiments of the present invention with reference to the drawings. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block view showing a block view of an ignition control device for use with an aviation engine of a first embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Each cylinder is equipped with main ignition plugs (<b>1</b>T to <b>4</b>T) and back-up ignition plugs (<b>1</b>B to <b>4</b>B) for backing these up. Lane A including CPU <b>71</b> and lane B including CPU <b>72</b> are included at ECU <b>300</b> and the ignition control system is multiplexed by these two lanes A, B.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">At lane A, the main ignition plug <b>1</b>T of the first cylinder and the main ignition plug <b>2</b>T of the second cylinder are supplied with electricity by the simultaneous ignition type first ignition coil <b>21</b>. The main ignition plug <b>3</b>T of the third cylinder and the main ignition plug <b>4</b>T of the fourth cylinder are supplied with electricity by the simultaneous ignition type second ignition coil <b>22</b>. The primary sides of each of the ignition coils <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> are connected to power supply lines via high side power switches <b>61</b>, <b>62</b> with current limiting circuits and are connected to the first CPU <b>71</b> via igniters <b>31</b>, <b>32</b>. The first CPU <b>71</b> calculates ignition timing for all of the cylinders based on various sensor signals inputted via the sensor input interface <b>41</b> and executes main ignition based on the results of these calculations.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">At lane B, the back-up ignition plug <b>1</b>B of the first cylinder and the back-up ignition plug <b>2</b>B of the second cylinder are supplied with electricity by the simultaneous ignition type third ignition coil <b>23</b>. The back-up ignition plug <b>3</b>B of the third cylinder and the back-up ignition plug <b>4</b>B of the fourth cylinder are supplied with electricity by the simultaneous ignition type fourth ignition coil <b>24</b>. The primary sides of each of the ignition coils <b>23</b>, <b>24</b> are connected to power supply lines via high side power switches <b>63</b>, <b>64</b> with current limiting circuits and are connected to the second CPU <b>72</b> via igniters <b>33</b>, <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The first and second CPU <b>71</b> and <b>72</b> independently calculate ignition timing for each cylinder based on each sensor signal and exchange the results of these calculations with the other CPU through communication. At each cylinder, ignition timing is synchronized in such a manner that ignition timing of the main ignition plugs (<b>1</b>T to <b>4</b>T) and ignition timing of the back-up ignition plugs (<b>1</b>B to <b>4</b>B) match. Therefore, even if a malfunction occurs in one lane so that one of either the main ignition or the back-up ignition fails, continuation is possible using the other of the main ignition or the back-up ignition using the remaining lane.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block view of a fuel injection system for an aviation engine of a second embodiment of the present invention, with the same numerals as before showing the same functions. Lane A including CPU <b>71</b> and lane B including CPU <b>72</b> are included at ECU <b>300</b> and the fuel injection system is multiplexed by these two lanes A, B.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">When a signal line for normal injection is ensured from the first CPU <b>71</b> of the lane A via an injector driver <b>91</b> at the first injector <b>1</b>J injecting fuel to within the first cylinder, a power supply line for normal injection is ensured via a high side power switch <b>81</b> with a current limiter. Operation of the driver <b>91</b> and switch <b>81</b> is monitored by the first CPU <b>71</b>. Further, when a signal line for alternate injection use is ensured at the first injector <b>1</b>J from that second CPU <b>72</b> of lane B via an injector driver <b>93</b>, a power supply line for alternate injection use is ensured via a high side power switch <b>83</b> with a current limiter. Operation of the driver <b>93</b> and switch <b>83</b> are monitored by the second CPU <b>72</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Similarly, when a signal line for normal injection is ensured from the first CPU <b>71</b> of the lane A via an injector driver <b>92</b> at the second injector <b>2</b>J injecting fuel to within the first cylinder, a power supply line for normal injection is ensured via a high side power switch <b>82</b> with a current limiter. Operation of the driver <b>92</b> and switch <b>82</b> is monitored by the first CPU <b>71</b>. Further, when a signal line for alternate injection use is ensured at the second injector <b>2</b>J from that second CPU <b>72</b> of lane B via an injector driver <b>94</b>, a power supply line for alternate injection use is ensured via a high side power switch <b>84</b> with a current limiter. Operation of the driver <b>94</b> and switch <b>84</b> are monitored by the second CPU <b>72</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Although not shown in the drawings, at the third injector <b>3</b>J injecting fuel to within the third cylinder and a fourth injector <b>4</b>J injecting fuel into the fourth cylinder, as with the first and second injectors J<b>1</b> and J<b>2</b>, a signal line for normal injection use and a power supply line are ensured with the first CPU <b>71</b> of the lane A, and a signal line for alternate injection and power supply line are ensured with the second CPU <b>72</b> of lane B. A lane switching circuit <b>5</b> selectively connects just one of the signal line for normal injection and the signal line for alternate signal use to each injector.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In the above configuration, lane A (front side) is always selected by the lane switching circuit and all of the injectors are controlled by the first CPU <b>71</b>. As shown in the example in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, when fuel injection is controlled by lane A, when a malfunction occurs at lane A due to whatever cause at time t<b>1</b> so that this is detected by signal return monitoring of the drivers <b>91</b>, <b>92</b> and/or power switches <b>81</b>, <b>82</b>, the control lane is switched over from lane A to lane B (alternate side) by the lane switching circuit <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The invention being thus described, it will be obvious that the same may be varied in many ways. Such variations are not to be regarded as a departure from the spirit and scope of the invention, and all such modifications as would be obvious to one skilled in the art are intended to be included within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electronic control device for an aviation engine for multiplex-controlling a multi-cylinder aviation engine using digital signals, comprising:
<claim-text>an ECU, the ECU including:
<claim-text>a plurality of sensors for monitoring states of the engine,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first CPU for executing main control of all cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second CPU for executing back-up control of all cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a communication circuit connected to the first and second CPU's, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sensor input interface for supplying detection signals of the sensors to each of the first and second CPUs,</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a control system is multiplexed using a first lane including the first CPU and a second lane containing the second CPU, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first and second CPUs are mutually synchronized to control timing through communication using the communication circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the two sensor input interfaces are provided independently so as to correspond to the first and second CPUs respectively.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the aviation engine is a four cylinder engine, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the cylinders is equipped with a main ignition plug and a back-up ignition plug,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the control device including a first simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the main ignition plugs of the first and second cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second simultaneous second ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the third and fourth cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the first and second cylinder back-up ignition plugs, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the back-up ignition plugs of the third and fourth cylinders, with each of the ignition coils being arranged outside of the ECU.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the aviation engine is a four cylinder engine, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the cylinders is equipped with a main ignition plug and a back-up ignition plug,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the control device including a first simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the main ignition plugs of the first and second cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to third and fourth cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the first and second cylinder back-up ignition plugs, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the back-up ignition plugs of the third and fourth cylinders, with each of the ignition coils being arranged outside of the ECU.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the aviation engine is provided with an injector at each cylinder, and further comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a normal signal system for supplying a normal injection signal from the first CPU to the injectors of all of the cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>an alternate signal system for supplying an alternate signal from the second CPU to the injectors of all of the cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>switching means for selectively connecting one of the normal signal system and the alternate signal system to the injectors of all of the cylinders, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for notifying the first CPU of the operating conditions for the normal signal system, wherein when an abnormal operation of the normal signal system is detected by the first CPU when the normal signal system is connected to the injectors of all of the cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the switching means being controlled so that the alternate signal system is connected to the injectors of all of the cylinders.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein each of the first and second ignition coils has a primary side connected respectively to a power supply line via first and second high side power switches, the primary side also being connected respectively to the first CPU via first and second igniters.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first CPU calculates ignition timing for all of the cylinders based on various sensor signals inputted via the sensor input interface and executes main ignition based on results of the calculations.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein each of the third and fourth ignition coils a primary side connected respectively to a power supply line via third and fourth high side power switches, the primary side also being connected respectively to the second CPU via third and fourth igniters.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the switching means selectively connects only one of a normal injection signal line and an alternate injection signal line to each of the injectors.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, when fuel injection is controlled by the first lane, and a malfunction occurs in the first lane, the malfunction is detected by signal return monitoring of drivers or power switches of the first lane, control is switched over from the first lane to the second lane by the switching means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An electronic control device for an aviation engine for multiplex-controlling a multi-cylinder aviation engine using digital signals, comprising:
<claim-text>an ECU, the ECU including:
<claim-text>a plurality of sensors for monitoring states of the engine,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first CPU for executing main control of all cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second CPU for executing back-up control of all cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a communication circuit connected to the first and second CPU's, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sensor input interface for supplying detection signals of the sensors to each of the first and second CPUs,</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a control system is multiplexed using a first lane including the first CPU and a second lane containing the second CPU, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first and second CPUs are mutually synchronized to control timing through communication using the communication circuit,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the cylinders are connected in parallel to the ECU.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the two sensor input interfaces are provided independently so as to correspond to the first and second CPUs respectively.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the aviation engine is a four cylinder engine, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the cylinders is equipped with a main ignition plug and a back-up ignition plug, including a first simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the main ignition plugs of the first and second cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to third and fourth cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the first and second cylinder back-up ignition plugs, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the back-up ignition plugs of the third and fourth cylinders, with each of the ignition coils being arranged outside of the ECU.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the aviation engine is a four cylinder engine, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the cylinders is equipped with a main ignition plug and a back-up ignition plug, including a first simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the main ignition plugs of the first and second cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the first CPU, for supplying ignition energy to third and fourth cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the first and second cylinder back-up ignition plugs, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth simultaneous ignition coil, controlled by the second CPU, for supplying ignition energy to the back-up ignition plugs of the third and fourth cylinders, with each of the ignition coils being arranged outside of the ECU.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the aviation engine is provided with an injector at each cylinder, and further comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a normal signal system for supplying a normal injection signal from the first CPU to injectors of all of the cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>an alternate signal system for supplying an alternate signal from the second CPU to the injectors of all of the cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>switching means for selectively connecting one of the normal signal system and the alternate signal system to the injectors of all of the cylinders, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for notifying the first CPU of the operating conditions for the normal signal system, wherein when an abnormal operation of the normal signal system is detected by the first CPU when the normal signal system is connected to the injectors of all of the cylinders,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the switching means being controlled so that the alternate signal system is connected to the injectors of all of the cylinders.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein each of the first and second ignition coils has a primary side connected respectively to a power supply line via first and second high side power switches, the primary side also being connected respectively to the first CPU via first and second igniters.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the first CPU calculates ignition timing for all of the cylinders based on various sensor signals inputted via the sensor input interface and executes main ignition based on results of the calculations.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein each of the third and fourth ignition coils has a primary side connected respectively to a power supply line via third and fourth high side power switches, the primary side also being connected respectively to the second CPU via third and fourth igniters.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the switching means selectively connects just one of a normal injection signal line and an alternate injection signal line to each of the injectors.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The electronic control device for an aviation engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, when fuel injection is controlled by the first lane, and a malfunction occurs in the first lane, the malfunction is detected by signal return monitoring of drivers or power switches of the first lane, control is switched over from the first lane to the second lane by the switching means.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
