<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296899-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296899</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11616995</doc-number>
<date>20061228</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>92118428 A</doc-number>
<date>20030704</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>14</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 85</main-classification>
<further-classification>353122</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Projector</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6147720</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Guerinot et al.</name>
<date>20001100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6642969</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Tew</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6643069</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Dewald</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6698898</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Terami et al.</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6709111</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hirao et al.</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6710762</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hasegawa</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6802615</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Okada</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6824275</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Penn</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6886942</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Okada et al.</name>
<date>20050500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0184572</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kaise</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0151933</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Tsai et al.</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0151937</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Sugitani</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>332876</doc-number>
<date>19850900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>413753</doc-number>
<date>19860700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>525157</doc-number>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>10</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 84</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 85</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353122</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349  5</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349  7</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10881184</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040630</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7175288</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11616995</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070103651</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070510</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wu</last-name>
<first-name>Tsung-Hsun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taoyuan County</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Thomas, Kayden, Horstemeyer &amp; Risley</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Benq Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taoyuan Shien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Dowling</last-name>
<first-name>William C.</first-name>
<department>2851</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A projector includes a lamp, a ballast, a micro controller unit and an optical engine. The lamp emits a light ray. The ballast starts the lamp and selectively outputs an operating power and a blanking power to the lamp. The micro controller unit controls the ballast. The optical engine receives the light ray and outputs a projecting image to a screen outside the projector. When the projector enters a blanking mode from a normal operating mode, the micro controller unit outputs a control signal to the ballast, and the power supplied from the ballast to the lamp is changed from the operating power to the blanking power.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="140.89mm" wi="218.36mm" file="US07296899-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="231.39mm" wi="181.69mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296899-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="220.30mm" wi="156.89mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296899-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/881,184 filed Jun. 30, 2004, now U.S. Pat. No. 7,175,288 which claims the benefit of Taiwan application Ser. No. 092118428, filed Jul. 4, 2003, the subject matter of which is incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The invention relates to a projector, and more particularly to a projector with reduced power of an emitting lamp in a blanking mode.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The conventional digital light processing (DLP) projector includes a lamp, an optical engine and a lens. The optical engine has a digital micro-mirror device (DMD), multiple reflective devices, a color wheel and a light pipe. The lamp emits a light ray. The light ray emitted from the lamp passes through the color wheel, which generates at least three primary-color light rays. The three primary-color light rays are conducted by the light pipe, and then enter the reflective devices. Thereafter, the three primary-color light rays reflected from the reflective devices are incident to the DMD. When the projector is in a normal mode, the three primary-color light rays are reflected by the DMD and pass through the lens, and then a projecting image is projected onto a screen outside the projector.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In general, the projector further has a blanking mode in addition to the above-mentioned normal mode. Since the lamp of the projector is a high brightness bulb set, the lamp cannot be immediately turned on of off because a predetermined period of time is required to either preheat after the lamp is turned on, or dissipate heat after the lamp is turned off. Consequently, the lamp of the projector is designed to have a blanking mode, in which the projector temporarily stops outputting the projecting image onto the screen. When the projector is in the blanking mode, no image is displayed on the screen. The operation of the conventional DLP projector in the blanking mode is such that all of the incident light rays to the DMD are reflected to an inner wall of the optical engine without being projecting out of the DLP projector by rotating the mirror angles of the micro-mirrors of the DMD.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">However, when the DLP projector is in the blanking mode, all of the light rays are reflected from the DMD to the inner wall of the optical engine, thereby causing an overheating condition in the optical engine. Since the optical engine is a closed chamber and the light rays are reflected multiple times in the closed chamber after they are reflected by the inner wall, the temperature of the optical engine sequentially rises and the energy is thus wasted.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In addition, the problem of overheating of the optical engine also may occur in the blanking mode in the conventional transmittive LCD projector. In the blanking mode, the ploarizer of the LCD (liquid crystal display) panel blocks all of the light rays, and the temperature of the LCD projector keeps on rising accordingly. When the temperature of the DLP projector or LCD projector is too high, error operations will be caused or even the elements will be burn out. Consequently, it is quite necessary to provide a projector capable of solving the problems of overheating and energy wasting.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">It is therefore an object of the invention to provide a projector having a ballast, which is controlled such that the output power of a lamp of the projector is reduced when the projector enters a blanking mode. Thus, the problems of overheating and energy wasting may be properly solved.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The invention achieves the above-identified object by providing a projector including a lamp, a ballast, a micro controller unit and an optical engine. The lamp emits a light ray. The ballast starts the lamp and selectively supplies an operating power and a blanking power to the lamp. The micro controller unit controls the ballast. The optical engine receives the light ray and outputs a projecting image to a screen outside the projector. When the projector enters a blanking mode from a normal operating mode, the micro controller unit outputs a control signal to the ballast, and the power supplied from the ballast to the lamp is changed from the operating power to the blanking power.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The invention also achieves the above-identified object by providing a digital light processing projector including a switch, a lamp, a ballast, a micro controller unit and an optical engine. The lamp emits a light ray. The ballast starts the lamp and supplies a power to the lamp. The micro controller unit is coupled to the switch to control the ballast. The optical engine receives the light ray and outputs a projecting image to a screen outside the projector. The optical engine has a digital micro-mirror device (DMD), and the light ray emitted from the lamp is incident to the DMD. When the projector is in a normal mode, the light ray is reflected by the DMD and projected onto the screen. When the switch is triggered, the projector enters a blanking mode, and the DMD reflects the light ray to an inner wall of the optical engine. The ballast reduces the output power of the lamp.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Other objects, features, and advantages of the invention will become apparent from the following detailed description of the preferred but non-limiting embodiments. The following description is made with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a system architecture diagram showing a digital light processing (DLP) projector according to a first embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a system architecture diagram showing a LCD projector according to a second embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The spirit of the invention resides in that when the projector is switched into a blanking mode, a micro controller unit (MCU) inside the projector will be triggered to control a ballast to reduce the output power of a lamp of the projector. After the power of the lamp is reduced, the optical energy projected from the DMD to the inner wall of the optical engine or the light blocked by the ploarizer is also reduced. Thus, the problems of overheating and energy wasting may be properly solved.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a system architecture diagram showing a digital light processing (DLP) projector <b>100</b> according to a first embodiment of the invention. The DLP projector includes a lamp <b>102</b>, a ballast <b>104</b>, a micro controller unit <b>105</b>, an optical engine <b>106</b>, an analog-to-digital converter (ADC) <b>108</b>, a scaling circuit <b>110</b>, a DMD driver <b>112</b>, a switch <b>114</b> and a lens <b>122</b>. The optical engine <b>106</b> includes a DMD <b>1060</b>, multiple reflective devices such as reflecting mirrors <b>1062</b>, a color wheel <b>1064</b>, and a light pipe <b>1066</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The ADC <b>108</b> converts an analog image signal S_A into a digital image signal S_D. The scaling circuit <b>110</b> processes the digital image signal S_D to make the digital image signal S_D satisfy the image resolution for the DLP projector <b>100</b>. The DMD driver <b>112</b> receives the digital image signal S_D processed by the scaling circuit <b>110</b>, and controls the DMD <b>1060</b> according to the digital image signal S_D.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The lamp <b>102</b> emits a light ray <b>116</b>. The ballast <b>104</b> starts the lamp <b>102</b> and selectively supplies an operating power and a blanking power to the lamp <b>102</b>. The micro controller unit <b>105</b> controls the output power of the ballast <b>104</b>. The optical engine <b>106</b> receives the light ray <b>116</b> and outputs a projecting image <b>118</b> to a screen <b>120</b> outside the DLP projector <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">When the DLP projector <b>100</b> is normally operating in a normal mode, the ballast <b>104</b> supplies the operating power to the lamp <b>102</b>. After the light ray <b>116</b> emitted from the lamp <b>102</b> is incident to the optical engine <b>106</b>, the light ray <b>116</b> passes through the color wheel <b>1064</b>, which is a typically a disk composed of red, green and blue sectors and is driven by a motor <b>1068</b> to rotate. After the light ray <b>116</b> passes through the color wheel <b>1064</b>, light rays with three primary colors are generated in a time-sharing manner. The light ray is conducted by the light pipe <b>1066</b> and then incident to the reflecting mirror <b>1062</b>. The reflecting mirror <b>1062</b> reflects the light ray, which is then incident to the DMD <b>1060</b>. The DMD driver <b>112</b> controls the DMD <b>1060</b> according to the digital image signal S_D processed by the scaling circuit <b>110</b> so as to change the angles of the micro-mirrors in the DMD <b>1060</b>. The light ray <b>116</b> incident to the DMD <b>1060</b> is reflected by the DMD <b>1060</b> and processed by the lens <b>122</b>. Then, the projecting image <b>118</b> is generated and projected onto the screen <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">When the DLP projector <b>100</b> enters a blanking mode from a normal operating mode, the micro controller unit <b>105</b> outputs a control signal CTR to the ballast <b>104</b>. The power supplied from the ballast <b>104</b> to the lamp <b>102</b> is changed from the operating power to the blanking power. In the blanking mode, the DMD <b>1060</b> reflects the light ray <b>116</b>, which is reflected from the reflecting mirror <b>1062</b>, to the inner wall of the optical engine <b>106</b>, and the light ray reflected form the DMD <b>1060</b> cannot enter the lens <b>122</b>. At this time, no projecting image is presented on the screen <b>120</b>. It is to be noted that the blanking power is smaller than the operating power. Meanwhile, the micro controller unit <b>105</b> also outputs another control signal to stop the motor <b>1068</b> and thus the rotation of the color wheel <b>1064</b>, thereby reducing the noise and power consumption caused by the color wheel <b>1064</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">For example, when the operating power equals to 200 watts, the blanking power may be 160 watts or even lower. When the DLP projector <b>100</b> of this embodiment enters the blanking mode, the ballast <b>104</b> controls the output power of the lamp <b>102</b> to be the smaller blanking power. So, when the DMD <b>1060</b> reflects the light ray <b>116</b> to the inner wall of the optical engine <b>106</b>, the smaller blanking power will ease the temperature rising of the optical engine <b>106</b>. Compared to the conventional projector, the projector of the embodiment is free from the overheating condition, so the possibility of error operations or burn-out elements in the projector of this embodiment is smaller than that in the conventional projector. Furthermore, the smaller blanking power used in the blanking mode of this embodiment may advantageously save the energy.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In addition, there are many methods for triggering the projector of this embodiment to enter the blanking mode. In this embodiment, a micro controller unit <b>105</b> triggered by a switch <b>114</b> is described as an example. The micro controller unit <b>105</b> has an input pin <b>105</b>A, and the switch <b>114</b> has a first terminal <b>114</b>A and a second terminal <b>114</b>B. The input pin <b>105</b>A is coupled to a first terminal of a resistor R, and a second terminal of the resistor R is coupled to a first level Vcc. The first terminal <b>114</b>A of the switch <b>114</b> is coupled to the input pin <b>105</b>A, and the second terminal <b>114</b>B of the switch <b>114</b> is coupled to a second level such as a ground level.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">When the switch <b>114</b> is not pressed yet, the first level Vcc is input to the input pin <b>105</b>A of the micro controller unit <b>105</b> such that the DLP projector <b>100</b> is kept at the normal mode and the ballast <b>104</b> supplies the operating power to the lamp <b>102</b>. When the user presses the switch <b>114</b>, the switch <b>114</b> is triggered, and the first terminal <b>114</b>A of the switch <b>114</b> is electrically connected to the second terminal <b>114</b>B. At this time, a ground signal is input to the input pin <b>105</b>A of the micro controller unit <b>105</b>, and the micro controller unit <b>105</b> is triggered. The triggered micro controller unit <b>105</b> makes the DLP projector <b>100</b> enter the blanking mode, and outputs the control signal CTR to the ballast <b>104</b>. The power of the lamp <b>102</b> provided by the ballast <b>104</b> is changed from the operating power to the lower blanking power.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a system architecture diagram showing a LCD projector according to a second embodiment of the invention. The LCD projector <b>200</b> includes a lamp <b>202</b>, a ballast <b>204</b>, a micro controller unit <b>205</b>, an optical engine <b>206</b>, a switch <b>214</b> and a lens <b>222</b>. The optical engine <b>206</b> includes a red LCD (liquid crystal display) panel <b>240</b>A, a blue LCD panel <b>240</b>B, a green LCD panel <b>240</b>C, at least one reflecting mirror, a beam splitter, and a beam combiner, such as reflecting mirrors <b>230</b>A, <b>230</b>B and <b>230</b>C, polarization beam splitters <b>232</b>A and <b>232</b>B, and an X-cube <b>234</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In the normal mode, the power supplied from the ballast <b>204</b> to the lamp <b>202</b> is the operating power. The light ray <b>216</b> emitted from the lamp <b>202</b> is incident to the polarization beam splitter <b>232</b>A, which splits the light ray <b>216</b> into two light rays incident to the polarization beam splitter <b>232</b>B and the reflecting mirror <b>230</b>B, respectively. The light rays split by the polarization beam splitter <b>232</b>B are incident to the blue LCD panel <b>240</b>B and the reflecting mirror <b>230</b>A, respectively. The reflecting mirror <b>230</b>A reflects the light ray to the reflecting mirror <b>230</b>C, which reflects the light ray to the red LCD panel <b>240</b>A. The light ray reflected from the reflecting mirror <b>230</b>B is incident to the green LCD panel <b>240</b>C. Three primary-color light rays including red, green, and blue light rays may be obtained after the light ray <b>216</b> is split by the polarization beam splitters <b>232</b>A and <b>232</b>B. The three primary-color light rays are processed by the red LCD panel <b>240</b>A, the blue LCD panel <b>240</b>B, and the green LCD panel <b>240</b>C, and are then incident to the X-cube <b>234</b>, which combines the three primary-color light rays. The combined light ray is then incident to the lens <b>222</b>, and a projecting image <b>218</b> on a screen <b>220</b> may be obtained.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">There are many methods for triggering the LCD projector of this embodiment to enter the blanking mode. In this embodiment, a micro controller unit <b>205</b> triggered by a switch <b>214</b> is described as an example. After the user has pressed the switch <b>214</b>, the ground signal is input to the micro controller unit <b>205</b>, and the micro controller unit <b>205</b> is triggered. The triggered micro controller unit <b>205</b> makes the LCD projector <b>200</b> enter the blanking mode, and outputs a control signal CTR′ to the ballast <b>204</b>. The power supplied from the ballast <b>204</b> to the lamp <b>202</b> is changed from the operating power to the lower blanking power.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In this embodiment, when the LCD projector <b>200</b> enters the blanking mode, the three primary-color light rays incident to the red LCD panel <b>240</b>A, the blue LCD panel <b>240</b>B and the green LCD panel <b>240</b>C are blocked by the polarizer in the display panel. In the LCD projector <b>200</b> of this invention, the power output from the lamp <b>202</b> in the blanking mode is lower than that in the normal mode. So, the optical energy blocked by the polarizer in this embodiment is smaller than that in the conventional LCD projector. Consequently, compared to the conventional projector, the LCD projector of this embodiment is free from the condition of overheating, and the energy may be advantageously saved.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">While the invention has been described by way of examples and in terms of preferred embodiments, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited thereto. On the contrary, it is intended to cover various modifications and similar arrangements and procedures, and the scope of the appended claims therefore should be accorded the broadest interpretation so as to encompass all such modifications and similar arrangements and procedures.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A projector, comprising:
<claim-text>a lamp;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a ballast for selectively supplying an operating power and a blanking power to the lamp for emitting a light ray; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an optical engine for receiving the light ray;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein when the lamp receives the operating power, the projector outputting a projecting image to a screen outside the projector, wherein when the lamp receives the blanking power, the screen is substantially blank and the light ray is blocked inside the projector by the optical engine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the operating power is higher than the blanking power.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a switch; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a micro controller unit for controlling the ballast;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein when the switch is triggered, the micro controller unit outputs a control signal to the ballast and the ballast supplies the lamp with the blanking power.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the micro controller unit has an input pin, the switch has a first terminal and a second terminal, the input pin is coupled to a first terminal of a resistor, a second terminal of the resistor is coupled to a first level, the first terminal of the switch is coupled to the input pin, the second terminal of the switch is coupled to a second level, and when the switch is triggered, the first terminal of the switch is electrically connected to the second terminal of the switch.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, the optical engine further comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of LCD panels;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein when the switch is triggered, the LCD panels block the light ray.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, the optical engine further comprising:
<claim-text>a digital micro-mirror device (DMD);</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein when the switch is triggered, the DMD reflects the light ray to an inner wall of the optical engine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, the projector further comprising:
<claim-text>a color wheel for the light ray emitted from the lamp passing through; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a motor for driving the color wheel to rotate, the micro controller unit controlling the motor to stop rotating when the switch is triggered.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, the optical engine further comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of LCD panels;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein when the ballast supplies the operating power, the light ray is incident to the LCD panels and generating the projecting image and when the ballast supplies the blanking power, the light ray is blocked by the LCD panels.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, the optical engine further comprising:
<claim-text>a digital micro-mirror device (DMD);</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein when the ballast supplies the operating power, the light ray is reflected by the DMD and projected onto the screen and when the ballast supplies the blanking power, the DMD reflects the light ray to an inner wall of the optical engine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A LCD projector, comprising:
<claim-text>a lamp;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a ballast for selectively supplying an operating power and a blanking power to the lamp for emitting a light ray; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an optical engine for receiving the light ray, the optical engine having a plurality of LCD panels;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein when the lamp receives the operating power and outputting the light ray, the light ray incident to the LCD panels and outputting a projecting image to a screen outside the projector and when the lamp receives the blanking power, the light ray is blocked by the LCD panels inside the projector.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The LCD projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the operating power is higher than the blanking power.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The LCD projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a switch; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a micro controller unit for controlling the ballast;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein when the switch is triggered, the micro controller unit outputs a control signal to the ballast and the ballast supplies the lamp with the blanking power.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The LCD projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein when the ballast supplies the operating power, the LCD projector is in a normal mode and when the ballast supplies the blanking power, the LCD projector is in a blanking mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
