<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297632-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297632</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11082517</doc-number>
<date>20050317</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>311</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438692</main-classification>
<further-classification>438691</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Scratch reduction for chemical mechanical polishing</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5876490</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ronay</name>
<date>19990300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>106  3</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6098638</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Miyashita et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6435942</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Jin et al.</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6435945</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Somekh</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6546939</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Small</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6979650</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Nakabayshi et al.</name>
<date>20051200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438692</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7029509</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kim et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 51308</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7052969</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Sahota et al.</name>
<date>20060500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438424</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438692</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438693</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438424</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438691</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060211250</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060921</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hou</last-name>
<first-name>Chuang-Ping</first-name>
<address>
<city>YongKong</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jang</last-name>
<first-name>Syun-Ming</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hsin-Chu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Ying-Ho</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fu</last-name>
<first-name>Chu-Yun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tseng</last-name>
<first-name>Tung-Ching</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Haynes and Boone, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company, Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Hsin-Chu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Pham</last-name>
<first-name>Long</first-name>
<department>2814</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method for forming a semiconductor device utilizing a chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) process is provided. In one example, the method includes sequentially performing a first CMP process for removing a first portion of an oxide surface of a semiconductor device using a high selectivity slurry (HSS) and a first polish pad, interrupting the first CMP process, cleaning the semiconductor device and the first polish pad, and performing a second CMP process for removing a second portion of the oxide surface.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="90.34mm" wi="145.88mm" file="US07297632-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="225.38mm" wi="150.79mm" file="US07297632-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="188.04mm" wi="159.60mm" file="US07297632-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present disclosure relates generally to the manufacturing of semiconductor devices, and more particularly to a chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) process utilized in semiconductor manufacturing.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The semiconductor integrated circuit (IC) industry has experienced rapid growth. Technological advances in IC materials and design have produced generations of ICs where each generation has smaller feature sizes and more complex circuits than those from the previous generation.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">As IC technology has moved from 130 nanometers (nm) to 90 nm and beyond, planarizing techniques, such as chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP), are required to selectively remove high elevation features by a combination of mechanical polishing and chemical reaction. A typical system for CMP may have one or more platens, each for performing a separate CMP process. Generally, a wafer is mounted on a rotating carrier, and a CMP process is performed at each platen. Typically, an abrasive-containing aqueous slurry is provided during CMP to facilitate the process.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Several techniques have been used to advance the results of CMP. For example, oxide device reverse (ODR) is often used to remove a significant amount of oxide on large active areas. ODR requires more extra process steps and a mask (referred to as an ODR mask), and still could benefit from better thickness control. Another example is to use a high selectivity slurry (HSS) for a direct CMP procedure. In comparison with conventional silica-based slurries, the utilization of a HSS results in superior within-wafer (WIW) uniformity of trench oxide and active Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4 </sub>thickness, and superior within-die (WID) uniformity of trench oxide and active Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4 </sub>thickness. However, the utilization of HSS also results in increased scratch rates on the wafer, and therefore high defect rates.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">What is desired is a new and improved system and method for enhancing the CMP process.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Aspects of the present disclosure are best understood from the following detailed description when read with the accompanying figures. It is emphasized that, in accordance with the standard practice in the industry, various features are not drawn to scale. In fact, the dimensions of the various features may be arbitrarily increased or reduced for clarity of discussion.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a system for implementing one or more embodiments of the present invention during fabrication of a semiconductor integrated circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a flow chart of a CMP method according to one or more embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a </i>and <b>3</b><i>b </i>are cross sectional views of the semiconductor integrated circuit of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> during processing according to embodiments of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">It is to be understood that the following disclosure provides many different embodiments, or examples, for implementing different features of the disclosure. Specific examples of components and arrangements are described below to simplify the present disclosure. These are, of course, merely examples and are not intended to be limiting. In addition, the present disclosure may repeat reference numerals and/or letters in the various examples. This repetition is for the purpose of simplicity and clarity and does not in itself dictate a relationship between the various embodiments and/or configurations discussed. Moreover, the formation of a first feature over or on a second feature in the description that follows may include embodiments in which the first and second features are formed in direct contact, and may also include embodiments in which additional features may be formed interposing the first and second features, such that the first and second features may not be in direct contact.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a semiconductor device <b>100</b> includes a substrate <b>102</b>. The substrate <b>102</b> may include one or more insulators, conductors, and/or semiconductor layers. For example, the substrate <b>102</b> may include an elementary semiconductor, such as crystal silicon, polycrystalline silicon, amorphous silicon, and/or germanium; a compound semiconductor, such as silicon carbide and/or gallium arsenic; an alloy semiconductor, such as SiGe, GaAsP, AlInAs, AlGaAs, and/or GaInP. Further, the substrate <b>102</b> may include a bulk semiconductor, such as bulk silicon, and such a bulk semiconductor may include an epi silicon layer. It may also or alternatively include a semiconductor-on-insulator substrate, such as a silicon-on-insulator (SOI) substrate, or a thin-film transistor (TFT) substrate. The substrate <b>102</b> may also or alternatively include a multiple silicon structure or a multilayer compound semiconductor structure.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An oxide layer <b>104</b>, which may include silicon dioxide or any other suitable material, may be formed over the substrate <b>102</b> by thermal oxidation and/or other suitable methods. In one example, the thickness of the oxide layer <b>104</b> is between about 90 angstroms to about 130 angstroms, although other thicknesses are also contemplated by the present disclosure.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The semiconductor device <b>100</b> may further include a silicon nitride layer <b>106</b>, which may be deposited over the oxide layer <b>104</b> by chemical vapor deposition (CVD) and/or any other suitable methods. The silicon nitride layer <b>106</b> may have a thickness of between about 600 angstroms to about 700 angstroms. It is noted that other thicknesses of the silicon nitride layer <b>106</b> are also contemplated by the present disclosure.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The semiconductor device <b>100</b> includes a dielectric layer <b>110</b>, which may be used to fill trenches <b>120</b> in the substrate <b>102</b> and cover the silicon nitride layer <b>106</b>. The dielectric layer <b>110</b> may be formed by CVD, plasma-enhanced CVD (PECVD), atomic layer deposition (ALD), physical vapor deposition (PVD), spin-on coating and/or other suitable methods. The dielectric layer <b>110</b> may be an inter-metal dielectric (IMD), and may include silicon oxide, polyimide, spin-on-glass (SOG), fluoride-doped silicate glass (FSG), Black Diamond® (a product of Applied Materials of Santa Clara, Calif.), Xerogel, Aerogel, amorphous fluorinated carbon, and/or other materials. In the present embodiment, the dielectric layer <b>110</b> may serve to isolate one or more shallow trenches <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In some embodiments, the dielectric layer <b>110</b> may have already received some type of planarization process, such as an oxide device reverse (ODR) process that removes portions of the layer not directly over the shallow trenches <b>120</b>. The portions of the dielectric layer <b>110</b> may have been removed by dry etching or other etching methods, and some embodiments may utilize a direct CMP process. It is understood that other embodiments may not use a pre-planarization process.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The semiconductor device <b>100</b> is loaded onto a CMP system <b>140</b>. The CMP system <b>140</b> includes one or more polishing heads <b>150</b> for receiving and securing the semiconductor device <b>100</b>. The CMP system <b>140</b> also includes one or more slurries <b>152</b> and polishing pads <b>154</b>. Generally, a slurry includes small, abrasive particles of specific sizes (typically about 10 nm to 100 nm in diameters) and shapes suspended in an aqueous solution. The abrasive particles may be as hard as the film that is to be polished. Acids or bases may be optionally added to the solution, depending on the material to be polished. The polishing rate may be affected by various slurry parameters, such as the chemical composition of the slurry solution, the concentration of the solid particles in the slurry, and the shape, size, and distribution of the slurry particles. An automatic slurry feeding system may be used to ensure the proper delivery of the slurry.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In the present embodiment, the slurry <b>152</b> utilizes a high selectivity slurry (HSS) including additives (e.g., surfactants) and abrasives (e.g., polishing agents). Typically, the weight of the additives are between about 1.8% and about 2.4%. In this example, the abrasives may include ceria (CeO<sub>2</sub>), ZrO<sub>2</sub>, ThO<sub>2</sub>, TiO<sub>2</sub>, Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3 </sub>and/or other suitable materials. For the sake of example, ceria will be further discussed. Many of the most active polishing agents (abrasives) have many more “Lewis Acid” active sites (i.e., electron pair acceptors) in the abrasive's surface than do silica-based abrasives. The Lewis Acid active sites generate chemical bonding with the polished silicon oxide surface having alkali sites (i.e., electron pair donors). The same additives can passivate the polished stop layer (such as Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, SiON, SiC, etc.) and achieve similar results (such as higher selectivity, better planarity and worse scratching performance). The chemical structure and concentration of additives can be chosen for selectivity, planarity and scratching performance.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">It is contemplated that the slurry <b>152</b> may alternatively include ceria, ZrO<sub>2</sub>, or any other suitable material suspended in an aqueous solution, such as alkaline or any other suitable solution, and may include any suitable concentration of additives known in the art. The slurry <b>152</b> may be procured from a commercial supplier, such as Cabot Corp., Rode Inc., or Hitachi Chem. Corp.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">During shallow trench isolation (STI) CMP polishing with high-selectivity slurry (HSS), the lower area (e.g., trench oxide within the trench) is protected by the additives of HSS and the higher area (e.g., the upper surface) is polished by ceria chemical bonding and mechanical abrasion. Accordingly, the HSS having ceria abrasives and additives can achieve better planarity than the conventional silica-based slurry.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Compared to conventional silica-based slurries, ceria-based HSS exhibits better within-wafer (WIW) uniformity of trench oxide and active silicon nitride (Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>) thickness, and within-die (WID) uniformity of trench oxide and active silicon nitride (Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>) thickness (i.e., the WIW uniformity and WID uniformity are each smaller for the ceria-based HSS).</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">During STI-CMP with HSS (e.g., CeO<sub>2</sub>-based abrasives), there is more absorbed additive on Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4 </sub>(silicon nitride) films than on SiO<sub>2 </sub>(silicon oxide) film. Adding suitable surface additives that are easily adsorbed on a silicon nitride surface reduces the nitride polish rate without significantly reducing the oxide polish rate and can increase the polish rate selectivity of oxide to nitride. However, the mechanical abrasion of the trench oxide and silicon nitride surfaces causes scratches in the polished trench oxide surface and scratches in the polished silicon nitride surface. This is due, in some embodiments, to the hardness of the trench oxide, which is softer than that of the silicon nitride stop layer, and thus scratches are more easily generated in the polished trench oxide surface than in the polished silicon nitride surface.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In some embodiments, the present invention promotes the removal of the extra additives adsorbed on the surface to be polished, and hence the increased chemical bonding between the abrasives (e.g., CeO<sub>2</sub>, ZrO<sub>2</sub>, ThO<sub>2</sub>, TiO<sub>2 </sub>and Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) and the polished surface, e.g. silicon oxide, before the completion of the polishing. This helps to reduce the scratching of the polished surface and improve the device yield. A high-selectivity slurry consumption is reduced from about 20% to 40% using one or more embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a method <b>200</b> can be used for performing chemical mechanical polishing with HSS with a reduced amount of scratches or other defects. Execution begins at step <b>212</b>, where a wafer (e.g., the semiconductor device <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) is loaded into a CMP system (e.g., the system <b>140</b>). At step <b>213</b>, the weight of the additives in the slurry <b>152</b> may be reduced to between about 0.4% and about 1.7% (as described above, the typical weight of additives is between about 1.8% and about 2.4%). Since additives tend to reduce the chemical bonding ability between the slurry <b>152</b> and the surface of the semiconductor device <b>100</b>, such a reduction may decrease the scratch rate of the semiconductor device <b>100</b> during the CMP operation described below.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">At step <b>214</b>, a first portion of the dielectric material <b>110</b> removed. A polishing pressure of between about 2 pounds per inch (psi) and about 5 psi (or other suitable pressures) may be applied between the semiconductor device <b>100</b> and the polish pad <b>154</b>, which may have a rotational speed of between approximately 50 rotations per minute (RPM) to approximately 100 RPM (although other speeds are also contemplated). The slurry <b>152</b> may be distributed onto the polish pad <b>154</b> at the speed of between about 150 milliliters per minute (ml/min) to about 350 ml/min (although other speeds are contemplated). Generally, step <b>214</b> is a timed polishing process that may last, for example, between about 30 seconds and 40 seconds.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In furtherance of the example, at step <b>216</b>, the semiconductor device <b>100</b> and polish pad <b>154</b> are cleaned by a high pressure de-ionized water rinse or similar wet clean. In one example, the water pressure is between approximately 10 psi and 100 psi. Generally, step <b>216</b> is a timed cleaning process that may last between about 10 seconds and 60 seconds. The cleaning may remove HSS additives bonded on the surfaces of the semiconductor device <b>100</b> and on the polish pad <b>154</b>, thereby reducing the scratch rate of the semiconductor device <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">It is contemplated that step <b>216</b> may be performed while the semiconductor device <b>100</b> remains on the platen <b>150</b>. Alternatively, the semiconductor device <b>100</b> may be removed from the platen <b>150</b> by a robot arm (not shown) and cleaned in a separate station. If applicable, the semiconductor device <b>100</b> is again loaded onto the platen <b>150</b> following step <b>216</b> or onto another platen.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">At step <b>218</b>, a second portion of the remaining dielectric material <b>110</b> is removed. Step <b>218</b> may be similar to step <b>214</b> in terms of polishing pressure, platen rotational speed, slurry distribution rate and/or duration. In one example, endpoint detection may be utilized to measure the reflectivity of the semiconductor device <b>100</b>. As the dielectric material <b>110</b> is removed over time to expose an underlying portion of the silicon nitride layer <b>106</b>, the reflectivity from the surface of the semiconductor device <b>100</b> will change accordingly. Upon the detection of such a change, the polishing step <b>218</b> may be terminated. Alternatively, a timer with a suitable duration may be utilized to monitor the completion of this polishing operation.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">At step <b>220</b>, buff polishing is performed on the semiconductor device <b>100</b>, using a mixture of de-ionized water and the remaining HSS as the slurry. In one example, the mixture includes between about 20% and about 80% de-ionized water, and between about 20% and about 80% HSS. It is contemplated that the buff polishing may be performed at a polishing pressure of between approximately 2 psi and approximately 5 psi, while the platen <b>154</b> may be rotated at a speed of between about 50 RPM and about 100 RPM. In addition, the de-ionized water and HSS mixture may be distributed at a speed of between approximately 150 ml/min and 350 ml/min. Generally, step <b>120</b> is a timed polishing process that may last between about 10 seconds and 30 seconds. It is contemplated that additives remaining on the semiconductor device <b>100</b> may be removed during this step <b>220</b>, thereby reducing the scratch rate of the finished semiconductor device.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">At step <b>222</b>, an optional wafer rinse and platen rinse may be performed during the unloading of the semiconductor device <b>100</b>. Thereafter, additional steps are performed for forming a final semiconductor device. Since those additional steps are known in the art, they will not be further described herein.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">It is contemplated that many variations may be utilized for performing the method <b>200</b>. Specific examples of certain steps or combinations of steps are described in greater detail below.</p>
<p id="h-0004" num="0000">De-Ionized Water High Pressure Rinse (DIW-HPR)</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a </i>and <b>3</b><i>b</i>, in some embodiments, the step <b>216</b> utilizes a deionized water (DIW) high pressure rinse (HPR). Legends <b>250</b> and <b>251</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a </i>and <b>3</b><i>b</i>, respectively, identify the abrasive (e.g., CeO<sub>2</sub>), the additives, and DIW <b>252</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>a</i>, the DIW <b>252</b> is directed at high pressure onto the semiconductor device <b>100</b> and the polish pad <b>154</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>b</i>, the DIW <b>252</b> effectively removes at least some of the additives otherwise bonded to the partially polished surface <b>254</b> of the oxide layer <b>110</b> overlying STI <b>120</b> and nitride CMP stop layer <b>106</b>. This “refreshes” the surface of oxide layer <b>110</b> before the abrasive-HSS polishing. One sample formula for the CMP process according to the present embodiment is:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0032">Pre-HPR Clean-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0033">Slurry Feed-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0003" num="0034">Polish Head Down-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0004" num="0035">First HSS Main Polish-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0005" num="0036">Slurry Feed Stop-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0006" num="0037">Polish Head Up-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0007" num="0038">DIW-HPR-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0008" num="0039">DIW Stop-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0009" num="0040">Slurry Feed-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0010" num="0041">Polish Head Down-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0011" num="0042">Second HSS Main Polish-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0012" num="0043">Slurry Feed Stop-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0013" num="0044">Polish Head Up-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0014" num="0045">Post-CMP DIW Clean-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0015" num="0046">Finish</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0047">It is noted that by introducing a DIW-HPR between the steps of the HSS main-polish process, the rinse may also be used to clean the polished material surface <b>254</b> and the polish pad <b>154</b>. The DIW-HPR removes the additives adsorbed on the polished wafer surface <b>254</b> and any surplus additives on the polish pad, thus improving the auto-stop polish phenomenon and reducing scratches.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0048">About 40% to about 100% of the additives may be removed from the polished surface and the polish pad using the first method DIW-HPR of the present embodiment. This has been found to improve the scratch performance from about 30% to about 35%.</p>
<p id="h-0005" num="0000">Extra De-Ionized Water Buff-Polish Step After HSS Polish</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0049">In accordance with another embodiment, a buff-polish can be used at step <b>220</b>. The buff-polish increases the polish rate selectivity of silicon oxide to silicon nitride using a mixture of de-ionized water and the remaining HSS as the slurry. Also, the HSS polish time can be decreased and scratches may be reduced from about 40% to about 45%. One sample formula for the CMP process according to the present embodiment is:
<ul id="ul0003" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0003-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0004" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0004-0001" num="0050">Pre-HPR Clean-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0002" num="0051">Slurry Feed-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0003" num="0052">Polish Head Down-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0004" num="0053">HSS Main Polish-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0005" num="0054">Slurry Feed Stop-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0006" num="0055">DIW-Feed-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0007" num="0056">HSS DIW Buff-Polish-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0008" num="0057">DIW Feed Stop-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0009" num="0058">Polish Head Up-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0010" num="0059">Post-CMP DIW Clean-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0011" num="0060">Finish</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0061">It is noted that in the present example, the extra DIW-feed removes the additives adsorbed on the polished wafer surface and dilutes the additive concentration in the remaining HSS. Thus, it would increase the silicon oxide polish rate, improve the auto-stop polish phenomenon, and reduce scratches. It is further noted that the HSS DIW Buff-Polish does not require a softer pad <b>154</b>.</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">Scratch Reduction by Initially Decreasing Additive Content</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0062">In accordance with another embodiment, the additive content used for one or more of the HSS polishing steps <b>214</b>, <b>218</b> can be reduced. This may result in scratches being reduced from about 30% to about 70%.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0063">In experiments, from a baseline from about 1.8 to 2.4 wt % additive of the high-selectivity slurry (HSS) having a quantity of total defect/reviewed of 2174/233 ea with a total of 106 ea scratches includes a quantity of deep scratches/micro-scratches of 8/98 ea:
<ul id="ul0005" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0005-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0006" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0006-0001" num="0064">1<sup>st </sup>experiment: from about 1.7 to 1.1 wt % additive of the high-selectivity slurry; quantity of total defect reviewed: 1928/175 ea with a quantity of total scratches of 70 ea includes quantity of deep scratches/micro-scratches of 5/65; and</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0002" num="0065">2<sup>nd </sup>experiment: from about 1.0 to 0.4 wt % additive of the high-selectivity slurry; quantity of total defect reviewed: 1865/151 ea; with a quantity of total scratches of 31 ea includes a quantity of deep scratches/micro-scratches of 0/31.
<br/>
Therefore, a reduction in the number of total scratches (sum of deep- and micro-scratches) of about 30% and 70%, respectively, is provided by decreasing the additive content from the baseline (from about 2.4 to 2.8 wt %) in the 1<sup>st </sup>and 2<sup>nd </sup>experiments.
<br/>
Switch the Polished Wafer to Another Polish Pads
</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0066">In accordance with another embodiment, the polished wafers may be switched to another polish pad during the HSS polishing to reduce the amount of additives and to reduce scratching by about 30% to about 35%. One sample formula for the CMP process according to the present embodiment is:
<ul id="ul0007" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0007-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0008" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0008-0001" num="0067">Pre-HPR Clean-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0002" num="0068">Slurry Feed-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0003" num="0069">Polish Head Down-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0004" num="0070">Main Polish Using A 1<sup>st </sup>Polish Pad-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0005" num="0071">Slurry Feed Stop-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0006" num="0072">Polish Head Up-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0007" num="0073">Post-CMP DIW Clean-&gt;
<br/>
Switch the Polished Wafer from the 1<sup>st </sup>Polish Pad To A 2<sup>nd </sup>Polish Pad-&gt;
</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0008" num="0074">Slurry Feed-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0009" num="0075">Polish head down-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0010" num="0076">Main Polish Using A 2<sup>nd </sup>Polish Pad-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0011" num="0077">Post-CMP DIW Clean-&gt;</li>
        <li id="ul0008-0012" num="0078">Finish</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0079">Switching of the polish pads effectively reduces the amount of additive available on the polished wafer surface. This may result in a reduction of the scratches from about 30% to about 35%.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0080">It is contemplated that many variations may be utilized for performing the method <b>200</b>. In one example, step <b>214</b> may be performed for approximately the same duration as that of step <b>218</b>. In a second example, step <b>214</b> may be terminated when approximately half of the dielectric material <b>110</b> has been removed. In a third example, step <b>216</b> may be repeated multiple times during the CMP operation. In a fourth example, following step <b>216</b>, the partial semiconductor device is loaded onto a different platen. In a fifth example, the polish pad <b>154</b> may be replaced at least once by a clean polish pad during the CMP operation. In a sixth example, at step <b>220</b>, instead of a mixture of HSS and de-ionized water, the slurry may include de-ionized water only. Therefore, a variety of modifications are contemplated by this disclosure.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0081">Although only a few exemplary embodiments of this disclosure have been described in details above, those skilled in the art will readily appreciate that many modifications are possible in the exemplary embodiments without materially departing from the novel teachings and advantages of this disclosure. Also, features illustrated and discussed above with respect to some embodiments can be combined with features illustrated and discussed above with respect to other embodiments. Accordingly, all such modifications are intended to be included within the scope of this disclosure.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for forming a semiconductor device utilizing a chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) process, sequentially comprising:
<claim-text>performing a first CMP process for removing a first portion of an oxide surface of a semiconductor device using a high selectivity slurry (HSS) and a first polish pad;</claim-text>
<claim-text>interrupting the first CMP process;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cleaning the semiconductor device and the first polish pad; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>performing a second CMP process for removing a second portion of the oxide surface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the semiconductor device comprises at least one shallow trench isolation structure and copper single/dual damascene structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the oxide surface fills at least a part of the shallow trench isolation structure and copper forms the damascene structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the HSS comprises ceria.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the HSS comprises a substance selected from the group comprising ZrO<sub>2</sub>, ThO<sub>2</sub>, TiO<sub>2 </sub>and Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein different polishing pads are used for the first and second CMP processes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein different platens are used for the first and second CMP processes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the cleaning includes using a high pressure de-ionized water rinse of the oxide surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the cleaning includes buffing the oxide surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method for forming a semiconductor device utilizing a chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) process, comprising:
<claim-text>providing a semiconductor device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>performing a CMP process on the semiconductor device with at least one high selectivity slurry (HSS); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>buff polishing the semiconductor device with a slurry, wherein the slurry comprises de-ionized water and the remaining HSS from the CMP process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the semiconductor device comprises at least one shallow trench isolation structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the at least one HSS comprises ceria.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the at least one HSS comprises a substance selected from the group comprising ZrO<sub>2</sub>, ThO<sub>2</sub>, TiO<sub>2 </sub>and Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method for fonning a semiconductor device utilizing a chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) process, comprising:
<claim-text>performing a first CMP process on a surface of the semiconductor device using a high selectivity slurry (HSS) having additives with a first weight of concentration;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cleaning the surface of the semiconductor device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>performing a second CMP process on the surface of the semiconductor device using a high selectivity slurry (HSS) having additives with a second weight of concentration.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the semiconductor device comprises at least one shallow trench isolation structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the second weight of concentration is approximately 0.4%.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the second weight of concentration is approximately 1.7%.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the second weight of concentration is between about 0.4% and about 1.7%.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method of reducing scratching of a surface of a semiconductor substrate using a polish head and a polish pad, the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>providing a high-selectivity-slurry (HSS) including a first weight percentage of additives and a weight percentage of abrasives, wherein the first weight percentage of additives is from about 2.4 to 1.8 wt % and the second weight percentage of additives is from about 1.7 to 1.1 wt %;</claim-text>
<claim-text>reducing the first weight percentage of additives to a second weight percentage that is less than the first weight percentage by adding a deionized water buff-polish step during the CMP process;</claim-text>
<claim-text>performing a chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) process to the surface using the HSS having the second weight percentage, whereby scratching of the surface is reduced; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>interrupting the CMP process to clean the surface of the semiconductor substrate and the polishing pad before completing the CMP process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A method of performing a chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) process on a semiconductor device having at least one shallow trench structure, comprising:
<claim-text>selecting a high selectivity slurry (HSS) having additives with a weight of concentration ranging between about 0.4% and about 1.7%;</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing a first portion of a dielectric layer using the HSS and a polish pad;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cleaning the semiconductor device and the polish pad with high pressure de-ionized water;</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing a second portion of the dielectric layer using the HSS and the polish pad; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>buff polishing the semiconductor device using a mixture of the remaining HSS and de-ionized water as a slurry.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref> further comprising replacing the polish pad with a new polish pad.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
