<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298993-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298993</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11030475</doc-number>
<date>20050105</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>190</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399176</main-classification>
<further-classification>399168</further-classification>
<further-classification>399174</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Imaging methods, image engines, and photoconductor charging systems</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5943533</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ogata et al.</name>
<date>19990800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399168</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6721523</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Sugiura et al.</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399176</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6751427</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Sugiara</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0228172</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Nakamura et al.</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399176</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0008396</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Nakamura et al.</name>
<date>20050100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399175</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0135839</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Inoue</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399175</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>06222649</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19940800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>62</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399168</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399174-176</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060147227</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060706</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Michael H.</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Jose</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tagansky</last-name>
<first-name>Boaz</first-name>
<address>
<city>Rishon-Lezion</city>
<country>IL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>IL</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>IL</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gila</last-name>
<first-name>Omer</first-name>
<address>
<city>Cupertino</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Holland</last-name>
<first-name>William D.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Palo Alto</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chang</last-name>
<first-name>Seongsik</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Jose</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hewlett-Packard Development Company, L.P.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Houston</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hirshfeld</last-name>
<first-name>Andrew H.</first-name>
<department>2858</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Dole</last-name>
<first-name>Timothy J</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Imaging methods, image engines, and photoconductor charging systems are described. According to one embodiment, an imaging method includes providing a charge device configured to provide an electrical charge to a surface of an imaging member which is usable for imaging, moving a surface of the charge device adjacent to the imaging member and a bias member, during the moving, first charging a discharged portion of the surface of the charge device using the bias member providing a charged portion of the surface of the charge device, during the moving, second charging a portion of the surface of the imaging member using the charged portion of the charge device, the second charging providing the discharged portion of the surface of the charge device, and repeating the first charging and the second charging during the moving.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="116.25mm" wi="163.58mm" file="US07298993-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="242.49mm" wi="166.45mm" file="US07298993-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="217.93mm" wi="151.38mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298993-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="188.98mm" wi="161.12mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298993-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="140.89mm" wi="164.17mm" file="US07298993-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="177.80mm" wi="153.67mm" file="US07298993-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="174.24mm" wi="156.38mm" file="US07298993-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="205.66mm" wi="79.16mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298993-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="192.96mm" wi="133.94mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298993-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE DISCLOSURE</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Aspects of the disclosure relate to imaging methods, image engines, and photoconductor charging systems.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE DISCLOSURE</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A multi-step electrophotographic (EP) process is the basis for numerous laser printers, copiers, multiple function devices, and other configurations. In a first step, a photoconductor is electrically charged for the subsequent formation of latent images. The photoconductor may be charged using one or more charge roller, corona or scorotron in some implementations. In but one example, the Indigo 3000 press available from The Hewlett-Packard Company has three sets of double scorotrons for charging the photoconductor.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A charge roller may include a metal shaft with a conductive elastomer surrounding it. The outer portion has been constructed in two ways in some arrangements. A first example includes a single layer with a moderately conductive material, usually an ionic conductive agent, mixed inside. A single-layer charge roller may also have a thin (e.g., thickness of a few microns) insulating layer outwardly of the conductive material or layer.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Another example of a charge roller has plural layers including an insulating outer sleeve of increased thickness (e.g., greater than a few microns) and an inner elastomeric region which may be loaded with a highly conductive network such as carbon. A double-layer charge roller generally charges less uniformly compared with a single layer charge roller due to the difficulty in providing a constant sleeve thickness. Accordingly, a single-layer charge roller system may provide images of increased quality and may be preferred for high-quality color image applications.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A core of a charge roller may be supplied with direct current (DC) electrical energy and possibly an additional alternating current (AC) voltage during use. If DC energy is used alone, the shaft voltage may be roughly 600 V higher than a desired voltage to be provided at a surface of the photoconductor. The extra 600 V is provided to generate ions in the air as dictated by the Paschen curve. With usage of AC energy, the voltage of the DC energy may be close to a desired photoconductor voltage with an AC amplitude of 600 V peak or more. The addition of AC usually creates a more uniform charge layer on the photoconductor adding or subtracting the photoconductor surface charge as needed.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The conduction mechanism of a single-layer charge roller is mobile ion movement in response to an applied electric field. If material (e.g., elastomer) is sandwiched between the two electrodes (e.g., charge roller shaft and photoconductor) and a voltage is applied, a current flows, generally falling with time. This is consistent with ions moving and accumulating at one side and leaving behind a charged layer of the opposite polarity on the other side which decreases the electric field available for moving current within the layer. Some charge injection may also occur at the electrodes which could neutralize some of the ions, thus decreasing the ion concentration over time.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">For printers of relatively reduced speed, the charge roller may be engineered to last the life of a replaceable cartridge. For relatively high-speed machines, the charge roller may be expected to have extended use before needing replacement.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Over time, a charge voltage of a photoconductor may fall or drop. For example, referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, measurements indicate that photoconductor charge voltage may drop over time with partial recovery during stoppage of imaging operations. In some situations, recovery may not occur even after imaging operations have ceased (e.g., no recovery is evident after a hour break at approximately 80,000 photoconductor page cycles (impressions) of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The non-recovery of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> may probably be attributed to two factors. First, a charge roller surface having a charge may attract charges of the opposite sign during operation. This can be partially remedied by turning off the charge roller since the charges may turn back towards the conductive shaft. In addition, some ions may leach from the surface due to relatively high concentrations and proximity to the surface and are lost due to recombination, decreasing the roller ion concentration. The long-term reduction in the photoconductor charge voltage is likely due to the latter. Accordingly, DC bias may be increased to provide a substantially constant photoconductor charge voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The above-described situation may worsen if high-speed printing is implemented in non-stop applications because the charge roller may not be allowed to sufficiently recover. In this case, additional problems may be present. For example, the charge roller may physically degrade due to high ionic concentration at an interface for most desired charge roller formulations. The high concentration may alter a local environment within the charge roller causing polymeric bonds of the charge roller to break. The result is that the elastomeric portions of the charge roller may return to a liquid state in the local region. The environment may be catalytic because the deterioration has been observed to continue long after the voltage is removed and the charge roller may continue to disintegrate. Affected regions of the charge roller may have a surface defect or a sticky surface stain which may negatively impact electrophotographic processes.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Rollers of similar composition used to donate charge or bias a surface may suffer the same drawbacks (e.g., if run at high speed in non-stop applications). An example is a transfer roller used in some electrophotographic applications which helps move toner from the photoconductor to the printing media wherein a voltage is applied between the transfer roller and the photoconductor to attract toner from the imaged photoconductor.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">At least some aspects of the disclosure include methods and apparatus for providing improved generation of hard images upon media.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to some aspects, imaging methods, image engines, and photoconductor charging systems are described.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to one embodiment, an imaging method comprises providing a charge device configured to provide an electrical charge to a surface of an imaging member which is usable for imaging, moving a surface of the charge device adjacent to the imaging member and a bias member, during the moving, first charging a discharged portion of the surface of the charge device using the bias member providing a charged portion of the surface of the charge device, during the moving, second charging a portion of the surface of the imaging member using the charged portion of the charge device, the second charging providing the discharged portion of the surface of the charge device;, and repeating the first charging and the second charging during the moving.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to another embodiment, an image engine comprises an imaging member configured to receive an electrical charge during imaging operations of the image engine, a discharge device configured to discharge selected portions of the imaging member to form latent images during the imaging operations of the image engine, a charge device positioned adjacent to the imaging member and having a surface comprising a plurality of portions, a bias member positioned adjacent to the charge device, and wherein individual ones of the surface portions of the charge device are rotated adjacent to the bias member to receive an electrical charge from the bias member and are rotated adjacent to the imaging member to impart the electrical charge to the imaging member during the imaging operations of the image engine.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a graphical representation of charge voltage of a photoconductor with respect to number of impressions.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a graphical representation of charge voltage of a photoconductor with respect to number of impressions.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a functional block diagram of a hard imaging device according to one embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a functional block diagram of an image engine according to one embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an illustrative representation of an image engine according to one embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an illustrative representation of a charge system according to an embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is an illustrative representation of a charge system according to an embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is an illustrative representation of a charge system according to an embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is an illustrative representation of a charge roller and a modified bias roller for implementing testing of exemplary aspects according to one embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is an illustrative representation of an image engine according to one embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Referring initially to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, an exemplary hard image device <b>10</b> is shown. Hard imaging device <b>10</b> is configured to form hard images upon output media, such as paper. In one embodiment, device <b>10</b> may be implemented as an electrophotographic press configured to print numerous hard images upon media at relative fast rates for extended periods of time (e.g., tens of thousands of sheets of media imaged per day). Other electrophotographic configurations or implementations of device <b>10</b> are possible including laser printers, copiers, facsimile devices, or other arrangements configured to form hard images upon media.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The depicted exemplary hard imaging device <b>10</b> includes a user/communications interface <b>12</b>, processing circuitry <b>14</b>, and an image engine <b>16</b>. Additional components may be utilized to provide generation of hard images (e.g., media handling equipment, storage circuitry or memory configured to store image data, software, firmware, or other programming, etc.).</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">User/communications interface <b>12</b> is configured to interact with a user and/or implement external communications with respect to device <b>10</b>. For example, interface <b>12</b> may include an input device such as a keyboard as well as a display (e.g., graphical user interface). Interface <b>12</b> may include an electrical interface such as a network interface card (NIC) in one embodiment to implement electrical data communications (input and/or output) externally of device <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Processing circuitry <b>14</b> is configured to process received user input, process image data, implement external communications, monitor imaging operations of device <b>10</b> and/or control imaging operations of device <b>10</b>. Processing circuitry <b>14</b> may comprise circuitry configured to implement desired programming provided by appropriate media (e.g., hard disk, memory, etc.) in at least one embodiment. For example, the processing circuitry <b>14</b> may be implemented as one or more of a processor and/or other structure configured to execute executable instructions including, for example, software and/or firmware instructions, and/or hardware circuitry. Exemplary embodiments of processing circuitry <b>14</b> include hardware logic, PGA, FPGA, ASIC, state machines, and/or other structures alone or in combination with a processor. These examples of processing circuitry <b>14</b> are for illustration and other configurations are possible.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Image engine <b>16</b> is configured to form hard images upon media. For example, processing circuitry <b>14</b> may perform image processing operations upon data (e.g., rasterization) and provide the image data to image engine <b>16</b> for hard imaging upon media. An exemplary image engine <b>16</b> is configured to generate hard images upon media according to the received image data.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-5</figref>, details regarding an exemplary configuration of image engine <b>16</b> configured to implement electrophotographic imaging operations according to one embodiment are shown. The depicted image engine includes an imaging member <b>20</b>, a charge system <b>22</b>, a discharge device <b>24</b>, a development station <b>26</b>, a transfer member <b>28</b> and a cleaning station <b>54</b>. Imaging member <b>20</b> is configured to receive an electrical charge from charge system <b>22</b> and may comprise a photoconductor, imaging media (e.g., paper) or other member configured to receive a charge for imaging. Other configurations of image engine <b>16</b> are possible including more, less or alternative components.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In one embodiment, imaging member <b>20</b> may comprise a photoconductor implemented as a photoconductor drum <b>40</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) in one example. An imaging region of member <b>20</b> may refer to portions of the outer surface wherein latent images are formed and developed as described further below. The imaging member <b>20</b> may rotate about an axis <b>41</b> in a counterclockwise direction in the exemplary described photoconductor drum embodiment wherein the outer surface passes adjacent to charge system <b>22</b>, discharge device <b>24</b>, development station <b>26</b> and transfer member <b>28</b>. Other configurations of photoconductor (e.g., a photoconductor belt) are possible in other embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Charge system <b>22</b> includes a charge device <b>42</b> which is embodied as a charge roller <b>49</b> in the described exemplary embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. Other embodiments of charge system <b>22</b> configured to provide an electrical charge are possible, for example, described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-8</figref> and <b>10</b>. Charge devices <b>42</b> apply an electrical charge to imaging members <b>20</b> such as a photoconductor, media or other components or structures for implementing imaging operations and which may be electrically charged. Charge device <b>42</b> embodied as a charge roller <b>49</b> is configured to provide an electrical charge (e.g., approximately negative 1000 V) to another imaging structure, such as the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b> in one arrangement. The outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b> may be charged to other voltages and/or polarities in other embodiments. In one embodiment, charge roller <b>49</b> is configured to rotate about axis <b>43</b> and contact the imaging region of the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b> to provide the electrical charge to the imaging region. Additional details regarding exemplary embodiments of charge systems <b>22</b> are shown and described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-8</figref> and <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In the exemplary described embodiment, discharge device <b>24</b> is configured to discharge the electrical charge on the imaging member <b>20</b> at selected locations corresponding to a desired image to be formed. The discharging of the electrical charge provides a latent image upon the imaging region of the imaging member <b>20</b>. In one embodiment, discharge device <b>24</b> may be implemented as a light source <b>44</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) such as a laser.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Development station <b>26</b> is configured to provide a marking agent, such as dry toner in a dry configuration or liquid ink in a liquid configuration. The marking agent may be electrically charged and attracted to the discharged locations of the imaging region of the imaging member <b>20</b> corresponding to the latent image to develop the latent image. Development station <b>26</b> may include a plurality of development rollers <b>46</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) which may provide marking agents of different colors to develop the latent images in one embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The marking agent of the developed image formed upon the imaging region of the imaging member <b>20</b> may be transferred to media <b>30</b> such as paper <b>52</b> using a transfer member <b>28</b>. In one embodiment, transfer member <b>28</b> is configured as a transfer drum <b>48</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>). An impression drum <b>50</b> may define a nip with transfer drum <b>48</b> to transfer the developed image to paper <b>52</b> in the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A cleaning station <b>54</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> may be provided to remove any marking agent which was not transferred from the imaging region to transfer drum <b>48</b> prior to recharging by charge roller <b>49</b>. In one embodiment, cleaning station <b>54</b> may apply an imaging oil to the surface of imaging member <b>20</b> to assist with the removal of marking agent from the surface which was not transferred using transfer member <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">At least some aspects of this disclosure are related to increasing the longevity of charge devices <b>42</b>. Some aspects are discussed with respect to the exemplary embodiments of charge systems <b>22</b>, <b>22</b><i>a</i>, <b>22</b><i>b</i>, <b>22</b><i>c </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-10</figref>. Other configurations of charge systems <b>22</b> or charge devices <b>42</b> are possible.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the illustrated exemplary charge system <b>22</b> includes charge device <b>42</b> embodied as charge roller <b>49</b>, a first DC power supply <b>60</b>, a second DC power supply <b>62</b> and a bias member <b>64</b>. Charge device <b>42</b> is positioned to contact imaging member <b>20</b> at a nip location <b>45</b>. Charge device <b>42</b> rotates with imaging member <b>20</b> embodied as a photoconductor drum <b>40</b> in the illustrated embodiment. In the illustrated embodiments, charge device <b>42</b> charges the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b> from −50 V (i.e., discharged portions of the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b>) to −1000 V (i.e., charged portions of the outer surface). Charging may predominantly occur in a pre-nip region approximate 0.5 mm short of nip location <b>45</b> in at least one embodiment. In other embodiments, charge device <b>42</b> and imaging member <b>20</b> may be spaced at nip location <b>45</b> wherein charging of imaging member <b>20</b> occurs.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Bias member <b>64</b> may be implemented as a metal roller configured to contact charge device <b>42</b> at a nip location <b>47</b> in one embodiment. Bias member <b>64</b> may rotate with charge device <b>42</b> in one exemplary arrangement. Other current-carrying configurations of bias member <b>64</b> are possible including metal brushes or blades for example. In addition, bias member <b>64</b> may comprise carbon-loaded materials or other conductors other than metallic structures.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Portions of charge device <b>42</b> which have supplied charge carriers to charge imaging member <b>20</b> become discharged portions of charge device <b>42</b> after the charging. The discharged portions of charge device <b>42</b> are then rotated to contact bias member <b>64</b> whereby they are again charged for subsequent charging of the imaging member <b>20</b>. At a given moment in time, bias member <b>64</b> charges the portion of the outer surface of charge device <b>42</b> approximate nip location <b>47</b>. Accordingly, less than an entirety of an outer surface of charge device <b>42</b> is charged by the bias member <b>64</b> at a given moment in time. In other embodiments, bias member <b>64</b> and charge device <b>42</b> may be spaced at nip location <b>47</b> wherein charging of charge device <b>42</b> occurs.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Charge device <b>42</b> includes a core <b>70</b> and an outer layer <b>72</b> about core <b>70</b> in the exemplary illustrated arrangement. In one implementation, core <b>70</b> is a metal shaft and outer layer <b>72</b> may be embodied as a conductive elastomer layer which may be constructed as described above in possible single layer and double layer embodiments. Outer layer <b>72</b> is configured to store charge carriers in one embodiment. For example, the charge carriers may be donated by bias member <b>64</b> and passed to imaging member <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">It is believed that DC current flow within outer layer <b>72</b> (e.g., between core <b>70</b> and outer layer <b>72</b>) during imaging operations may lead to degradation of outer layer <b>72</b>. Some results suggest that the process of disintegration may be initiated after a certain total net DC charge has passed through the material of the outer layer <b>72</b>. According to one aspect of charge system <b>22</b>, net DC current flow within layer <b>72</b> (e.g., into or out of core <b>70</b>) is reduced, minimized or eliminated to reduce degradation of charge device <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, DC power supply <b>60</b> is coupled with bias member <b>64</b> and DC power supply <b>62</b> is coupled with core <b>70</b> of charge device <b>42</b>. As discussed further below, power supply <b>60</b> may apply a desired electrical bias to bias member <b>64</b> to reduce net DC current or charge flowing within layer <b>72</b>. Power supply <b>62</b> may apply a desired electrical bias to core <b>70</b> to provide an appropriate charge to the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b> as is also discussed further below.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In one embodiment, charge system <b>22</b> is arranged to provide a charge of approximately −1000 V upon the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b> rotated adjacent to charge device <b>42</b>. Second power supply <b>62</b> is configured to provide electrical energy having a sufficient voltage magnitude to overcome losses while providing the desired voltage upon the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b>. For example, power supply <b>62</b> may provide a voltage of approximately −1600 V to core <b>70</b> to provide the desired voltage to the outer surface (e.g., −1000 V).</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As mentioned above, power supply <b>60</b> may charge bias member <b>64</b> to a proper voltage to reduce the net DC current or charge flowing in outer layer <b>72</b> during charging of imaging member <b>20</b>. In the above-described example wherein the surface of imaging member <b>20</b> is charged to approximately −1000 V, power supply <b>60</b> may provide a bias voltage of approximately −1800 V to bias member <b>64</b>. Accordingly, power supplies <b>60</b>, <b>62</b> provide voltages of the same polarity to charge device <b>42</b> and bias member <b>64</b> in at least one embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">It is believed that DC current passing through outer layer <b>72</b> (either into core <b>70</b> or from core <b>70</b>) may be related to disintegration of charge device <b>42</b> and/or voltage drops of charge received by the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b> during charging of imaging member <b>20</b>. More specifically, the continuous passage of DC current in a single direction (e.g., either radially into or out of core <b>70</b>) may lead to the negative operational aspects described above. Bias member <b>64</b> applies current to charge device <b>42</b> to provide current passing in different directions (e.g., different radial directions) through outer layer <b>72</b> during imaging operations to reduce DC current flow in a single direction through layer <b>72</b> (e.g., into or out of core <b>70</b>) during imaging.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Consider a surface patch on the outer surface of charge device <b>42</b> and a region of outer layer <b>72</b> inward of the surface patch. When the patch contacts imaging member <b>20</b>, charge carriers (e.g., depending upon the biasing polarities involved exemplary charge carriers include electrons, negatively charged ions, positively charged ions, etc.) from the patch and the underlying region are donated or transported in a substantially radial direction of charge device <b>42</b> to the discharged surface of imaging member <b>20</b> to charge the surface from −50 V to approximately −1000 V. After the charge device <b>42</b> rotates 180 degrees in the illustrative example, the patch contacts bias member <b>64</b> which donates charge carriers which are transported in a substantially radial direction of charge device <b>42</b> to the patch and underlying region for restoration to a rest state. The charging of charge device <b>42</b> may be imparted from an area and a direction external of the outer surface of the charge device <b>42</b> in at least one embodiment. As shown, different portions of charge device <b>42</b> may be simultaneously donating and receiving charge carriers during imaging operations.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Accordingly, in one embodiment, during charging of imaging member <b>20</b>, charge carriers of one sign flow in one direction with respect to the outer surface of charge device <b>42</b> while charge carriers of the same sign flow in an opposite direction with respect to the outer surface of charge device <b>42</b> during charging of charge device <b>42</b> by bias member <b>64</b>. It follows that the DC current flow relative to the outer surface of charge device <b>42</b> is substantially b-directional or AC in nature and the net DC current flow through material of outer layer <b>72</b> is substantially zero in the exemplary embodiments of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-8</figref> during imaging operations leading to extended life of charge device <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">According to the described example wherein the imaging member <b>20</b> is negatively charged, negative charge carriers flow from the charge device <b>42</b> to the imaging member <b>20</b> when the imaging member <b>20</b> is being charged and negative charge carriers flow from the bias member <b>64</b> to the charge device <b>42</b> when the charge device <b>42</b> is being charged. With respect to the outer surface of charge device <b>42</b>, the directions of the above-described charge carrier flow are opposite for the charging of the imaging member <b>20</b> and the charge device <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Referring to the embodiments of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7-8</figref>, exemplary charging systems <b>22</b><i>a</i>, <b>22</b><i>b </i>may utilize AC voltages to implement charging of imaging member <b>20</b>. The utilization of AC voltages may result in more efficient charging by the respective systems <b>22</b><i>a</i>, <b>22</b><i>b </i>compared with the DC charging system <b>22</b>. The AC voltages may more efficiently initiate Paschen breakdown in the air gaps adjacent to contact nip <b>45</b> between imaging member <b>20</b> and charge device <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, an exemplary charging system <b>22</b><i>a </i>which utilizes AC voltages is shown. The depicted charging system <b>22</b><i>a </i>includes a DC power supply <b>80</b>, an AC power supply <b>82</b>, a step-up transformer <b>84</b> and a coupling capacitor <b>86</b> in addition to the previously described illustrated components of charging system <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In embodiments wherein the imaging member <b>20</b> is charged to −1000 V, DC power supply <b>80</b> may provide a DC voltage of about −1300 V and AC power supply <b>82</b> may provide electrical energy of 1400 V peak-to-peak and having a frequency of 6 kHz in one implementation. Transformer <b>84</b> adds the AC voltage to the output of the DC power supply <b>80</b> to produce the drive voltage for bias member <b>64</b>. Coupling capacitor <b>86</b> passes the AC voltage to core <b>70</b> of charge device <b>42</b>. Application of the AC voltage to charge device <b>42</b> and bias member <b>64</b> induces Paschen breakdown in the air gaps adjacent to contact nip <b>45</b> of imaging member <b>20</b> and charge device <b>42</b> providing imaging member <b>20</b> with a more uniform voltage compared with the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. In addition, loading upon AC power supply <b>82</b> may be reduced if the charge device <b>42</b> and bias member <b>64</b> are maintained at substantially the same AC voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">A value of coupling capacitor <b>86</b> may be chosen so the AC reactance of the coupling capacitor <b>86</b> is relatively small compared to the AC reactance of the charge device <b>42</b>. In one embodiment, a value of coupling capacitor <b>86</b> may be 0.01 uF or larger for an embodiment wherein a capacitance of the core <b>70</b> to imaging member <b>20</b> is approximately 600 pF.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, another possible embodiment of charging system <b>22</b><i>b </i>utilizing AC voltages is shown. With respect to the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the depicted charging system <b>22</b><i>b </i>omits capacitor <b>86</b>, and includes a transformer <b>84</b><i>a </i>having plural secondary windings, plural DC power supplies <b>90</b>, <b>92</b> and an AC power supply <b>94</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">As shown, first and second DC power supplies <b>90</b>, <b>92</b> are coupled with first and second secondary windings of transformer <b>84</b><i>a</i>, respectively. First DC power supply <b>90</b> may provide a DC voltage of approximately −1200 V and second DC power supply <b>92</b> may provide a DC voltage of approximately −1300 V to charge the outer surface of imaging member <b>20</b> to −1000 V according to the exemplary disclosed embodiment. AC power supply <b>94</b> may provide an AC voltage of 600 V peak-to-peak at a frequency of 6 kHz in one embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">As discussed above with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the implementation of bias member <b>64</b> in the arrangement of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7-8</figref> provides DC current flow in the outer layer <b>72</b> in opposing directions. Accordingly, during imaging operations, the net DC current flow within outer layer <b>72</b> is reduced (e.g., substantially zero in the described embodiments) which has been observed to improve the longevity of charge device <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The embodiments described herein are applicable to Indigo digital presses available from The Hewlett-Packard Company. The voltage values of the above-described embodiments may be tailored for application to other digital press configurations. For example, the described charge systems <b>22</b>, <b>22</b><i>a</i>, <b>22</b><i>b </i>may be used to charge a positive-charging imaging member <b>20</b> wherein positive charge carriers would be conducted reversing all of the above-described DC voltages (i.e., the charge carriers include electrons or negative ions in the above-described embodiments having a negative-charging imaging member <b>20</b>). If negative charges are also involved, they move in a direction opposite to that of positive charges. The values of the generated DC voltages may also be adjusted to achieve other desired charged voltages of the imaging member <b>20</b>. In addition, the frequency of the AC voltage may be tailored to a minimum value to reduce or avoid visible banding plus a small safety margin reducing the current and power provided by the AC supply to a minimum value. In general, lower frequencies may be used for hard imaging devices <b>10</b> having slower process speeds. In the above-described embodiments, AC voltage having a frequency of 6 kHz may be used for process speeds of hard imaging devices <b>10</b> of 1.2 meters/second.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, a configuration of a charge roller <b>100</b> with a modified bias roller <b>102</b> was tested in an Indigo 2000 Press available from The Hewlett-Packard Company. In order to test both configurations with and without the bias roller <b>102</b> simultaneously, a section <b>104</b> of the bias roller <b>102</b> was tapered down to a smaller diameter within which the bias roller <b>102</b> is not in contact with the charge roller <b>100</b>. Remaining sections <b>106</b> of bias roller <b>102</b> are in contact with the charge roller <b>100</b>. The length of the section <b>104</b> is a third of the length of the charge roller <b>100</b> in the illustration.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">AC voltage was not used during the tests illustrated using the arrangement of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> while two DC power supplies were used, one for the bias roller <b>102</b> and one for the core of the charge roller <b>100</b> as described above with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> in one implementation. The voltage for the core of the charge roller <b>100</b> was adjusted to obtain the proper photoconductor charge voltage. The voltage for the bias roller <b>102</b> was adjusted so that the current drawn from the respective adjusted power supply of the bias roller <b>102</b> was twice as much as the current drawn from the power supply coupled with the charge roller <b>100</b>. In this way, a middle section <b>108</b> of the charge roller <b>100</b> was solely driven by the charge roller power supply and outer sections solely by the bias roller <b>102</b>. Assuming the outer sections of the charge roller <b>100</b> are driven solely by the bias roller <b>102</b>, the net DC current flow within the outer sections of charge roller <b>100</b> was substantially zero throughout the charging experiment.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">After a semi-continuous run of 200 K impressions (60 K impressions per day) middle section <b>108</b> of charge roller <b>100</b> started showing surface damage while the outer sections showed no surface damage. Some of the rubber material of the middle section <b>108</b> liquefied and portions of the outer layer became detached in these areas. Simple application of finger pressure produced wrinkles on the charge roller surface coating in the middle section <b>108</b> and the liquefied charge roller material leaked out through breaks in a coating. The outer sections of charge device <b>100</b> showed no visible damage or change compared with the beginning of the experiment.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, another example of an image engine <b>16</b><i>a </i>including another configuration of a charge system <b>22</b><i>c </i>is shown. The depicted exemplary image engine <b>16</b><i>a </i>omits illustration and discussion of other components discussed above which may be provided, such as charge systems <b>22</b>, <b>22</b><i>a </i>or <b>22</b><i>b </i>to charge photoconductor drum <b>40</b>, discharge device <b>24</b>, development station <b>26</b> or other appropriate components to implement imaging operations.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The depicted image engine <b>16</b><i>a </i>includes transfer member <b>28</b><i>a </i>including a transfer drum <b>48</b>. Charge system <b>22</b><i>c </i>is implemented using transfer drum <b>48</b> and bias member <b>64</b> in the depicted embodiment. Transfer drum <b>48</b> defines a nip <b>53</b> with photoconductor drum <b>40</b> in the illustrated embodiment. Media <b>30</b> is configured to pass through nip <b>53</b> to receive developed images from photoconductor drum <b>40</b>. Transfer drum <b>48</b> and bias member <b>64</b> of charge system <b>22</b><i>c </i>may be coupled with respective power supplies (not shown). For example, transfer drum <b>48</b> may be referred to as a charge device <b>42</b><i>a </i>electrically biased to assist with the attraction of the developed image from the photoconductor drum <b>40</b>. More specifically; charge device <b>42</b><i>a </i>implemented as transfer drum <b>48</b> may charge the imaging member <b>20</b><i>a </i>comprising media <b>30</b> in the depicted example to assist with the transfer of developed images. Outer surface portions of charge device <b>42</b><i>a </i>which charge media <b>30</b> may be discharged during imaging. Bias member <b>64</b> may rotate with charge device <b>42</b><i>a </i>and be used to charge discharged portions of the outer surface of charge device <b>42</b><i>a </i>to reduce degradation of charge device <b>42</b><i>a </i>as described above. The embodiments herein illustrate exemplary aspects of the disclosure and other configurations of charge systems, charge devices and bias members are possible.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The protection sought is not to be limited to the disclosed embodiments, which are given by way of example only, but instead is to be limited only by the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An imaging method comprising:
<claim-text>providing a charge device configured to provide an electrical charge to a surface of an imaging member which is usable for imaging;</claim-text>
<claim-text>moving a surface of the charge device adjacent to the imaging member and a bias member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>during the moving, first charging a discharged portion of the surface of the charge device using the bias member providing a charged portion of the surface of the charge device; during the moving, second charging a portion of the surface of the imaging member using the charged portion of the charge device, the second charging providing the discharged portion of the surface of the charge device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>repeating the first charging and the second charging during the moving; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing electrical energy independent of the bias member to the charge device to bias the charge device during the second charging.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the providing the charge device comprises providing a charge roller, and the moving comprises rotating the surface of the charge roller adjacent to and in contact with the imaging member comprising a photoconductor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the providing the charge device comprises providing a transfer member configured to provide the electrical charge to the surface of the imaging member comprising media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising biasing the bias member at a substantially constant DC voltage, and the providing comprises providing the electrical energy having a substantially constant DC voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein substantially zero net DC current flows with respect to the surface of the charge device during the first and second chargings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising providing electrical energy to the bias member having the same polarity as the electrical energy provided to the charging device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising providing an AC voltage to the bias member and the providing electrical energy comprises providing an AC voltage to the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein a plurality of charge carriers of one polarity move in a first direction relative to the surface of the charge device during the first charging and a plurality of charge carriers of the same polarity move in a second direction relative to the surface of the charge device during the second charging and substantially opposite to the first direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first charging comprises charging less than an entirety of the surface of the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising applying an AC voltage to the bias member during the moving and the providing electrical energy comprises providing an AC voltage to the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising applying a DC voltage to the bias member and the providing the electrical energy comprises applying a DC voltage to the charge device during the moving.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the moving comprises moving the surface of the charge device through a plurality of complete revolutions, and wherein the providing electrical energy comprises providing the electrical energy having a constant voltage to the charge device during entireties of the moving the surface of the charge device through the complete revolutions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the moving comprises moving the surface of the charge device through a plurality of complete revolutions, and
<claim-text>wherein the providing electrical energy comprises biasing the charge device using electrical energy having a first voltage; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>biasing the bias member using electrical energy having a second voltage, and an absolute value of the second voltage is greater than an absolute value of the first voltage during entireties of the moving the surface of the charge device through the complete revolutions.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising;
<claim-text>biasing the bias member using electrical energy during the first charging and the second charging, and wherein a voltage of the electrical energy used to bias the bias member has a larger absolute value than an absolute value of a voltage of the electrical energy provided to the charge device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>printing images during the biasing and the providing.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the moving comprises moving the surface of the charge device through a plurality of complete revolutions, and wherein the voltage of the electrical energy provided to the charge device is constant during entireties of the moving the surface of the charge device through the complete revolutions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising; during the moving, forming a latent image using the portion of the surface of the imaging member; and during the moving, developing the latent image using a marking agent comprising a liquid ink.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first charging and the second charging individually comprise conducting current one of into and out of the surface of the charge device comprising an electrically conductive outer surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first charging and the second charging individually comprise conducting current external of the charge device and one of into and out of the surface of the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. An imaging method comprising:
<claim-text>providing an imaging member having a surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a charge device configured to provide an electrical charge to the surface of the imaging member which is usable for imaging;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first transporting a plurality of charge carriers intermediate the imaging member and the charge device to charge a portion of the surface of the imaging member using the charge device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>second transporting a plurality of charge carriers to charge a portion of a surface of the charge device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the charge carriers of the first transporting travel in a first direction with respect to the surface of the charge device and the charge carriers of the second transporting travel in a second direction with respect to the surface of the charge device substantially opposite to the first direction; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>applying electrical energy to the charge device during and independent of the first and second transportings.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the charge carriers of the first and second transportings have the same polarity.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the charge device comprises a charge roller, and further comprising rotating the surface of the charge device adjacent to a bias member, and wherein the second transporting comprises transporting the charge carriers intermediate the bias member and the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the charge device comprises a charge roller and the first direction and the second direction comprise substantially opposite radial directions of the charge roller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the first transporting comprises donating charge carriers of one polarity from the charge device and the second transporting comprises donating charge carriers of the same polarity from a bias member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the second transporting comprises transporting the charge carriers intermediate the charge device and a bias member located externally of the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the first transporting comprises transporting the charge carriers one of into and out of the surface of the charge device and the second transporting comprises transporting the charge carriers the other of into and out of the surface of the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the second transporting comprises transporting the charge carriers to charge less than an entirety of the surface of the charge device at a given moment in time.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the first and second transportings are simultaneous.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref> wherein the first transporting comprises first charging the portion of the Imaging member using another portion of the surface of the charge device at one moment in time, and the second transporting comprises second charging less than an entirety of the surface of the charge device including the portion during the one moment in time.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein substantially zero net DC current flows within an outer layer of the charge device during the first and second transportings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the first and second transportings individually comprise transporting respective ones of the charge carriers using the surface of the charge device comprising an electrically conductive outer surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. An imaging method comprising:
<claim-text>providing an imaging member having a surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a charge device configured to provide an electrical charge to the surface of the imaging member which is usable for imaging;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first charging a portion of a surface of the charge device from a direction external of the surface of the charge device, the first charging providing a charged portion of the surface of the charge device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>after the first charging, second charging a portion of the surface of the imaging member using the charged portion of the surface of the charge device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing electrical energy independent of the first charging to the charge device to bias the charge device during the second charging.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00031">claim 31</claim-ref> wherein the first and second chargings comprise moving charge carriers of one polarity in substantially opposite directions with respect to the surface of the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00033" num="00033">
<claim-text>33. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00031">claim 31</claim-ref> wherein the first and second chargings comprise moving charge carriers between an area outside of the charge device and an outwardly exposed surface of the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00034" num="00034">
<claim-text>34. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00031">claim 31</claim-ref> wherein the providing the charge device comprises providing the charge device comprising an outer layer configured to store plural charge carriers received during the first charging.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00035" num="00035">
<claim-text>35. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00034">claim 34</claim-ref> wherein substantially zero net DC current flows within the outer layer during the first and second chargings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00036" num="00036">
<claim-text>36. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00031">claim 31</claim-ref> wherein the first charging comprises charging the portion of the surface of the charge device which comprises an electrically conductive outer surface and wherein the second charging comprises charging using the charged portion of the electrically conductive outer surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00037" num="00037">
<claim-text>37. An image engine comprising:
<claim-text>an imaging member configured to receive an electrical charge during imaging operations of the image engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a discharge device configured to discharge selected portions of the imaging member to form latent images during the imaging operations of the image engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a charge device positioned adjacent to the imaging member and having a surface comprising a plurality of portions;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bias member positioned adjacent to, the charge device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein individual ones of the surface portions of the charge device are rotated adjacent to the bias member to receive an electrical charge from the bias member and are rotated adjacent to the imaging member to impart the electrical charge to the imaging member during the imaging operations of the image engine; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>circuitry configured to provide electrical energy independent of the bias member to the charge device to bias the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00038" num="00038">
<claim-text>38. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein a plurality of charge carriers of one polarity are transported in a first direction relative to the surface of the charge device intermediate the charge device and the bias member and in a second direction relative to the surface of the charge device intermediate the charge device and the imaging member opposite to the first direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00039" num="00039">
<claim-text>39. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00038">claim 38</claim-ref> wherein the charge device comprises a charge roller and the first and second directions comprise opposing radial directions of the charge roller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00040" num="00040">
<claim-text>40. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein substantially no net DC current flows within an outer layer of the charge device during the reception of the electrical charge by the charge device and the imparting of the electrical charge to the imaging member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00041" num="00041">
<claim-text>41. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein the charge device contacts the bias member and the imaging member during the reception of the electrical charge by the charge device and the imparting of the electrical charge to the imaging member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00042" num="00042">
<claim-text>42. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> further comprising a development station configured to apply a liquid marking agent to a surface of the imaging member to develop the latent images.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00043" num="00043">
<claim-text>43. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00042">claim 42</claim-ref> further comprising a transfer member configured to transfer the developed latent images to media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00044" num="00044">
<claim-text>44. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00043">claim 43</claim-ref> wherein the transfer member comprises another charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00045" num="00045">
<claim-text>45. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein an AC voltage is applied to the bias member and the charge device during the imaging operations.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00046" num="00046">
<claim-text>46. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein plural DC voltages are applied to the bias member and the charge device during the imaging operations.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00047" num="00047">
<claim-text>47. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein the charge device rotates through a plurality of complete revolutions during the imaging operations of the image engine, and wherein the circuitry comprises circuitry configured to apply the electrical energy at a constant voltage to the charge device during the complete revolutions of the charge device during the imaging operations of the image engine.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00048" num="00048">
<claim-text>48. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein the charge device rotates through a plurality of complete revolutions during the imaging operations of the image engine, and further comprising circuitry configured to apply electrical energy to the bias member, and wherein a voltage of the electrical energy applied to the bias member has a larger absolute value than an absolute value of a voltage of the electrical energy provided to the charge device during the complete revolutions of the charge device during the imaging operations of the image engine.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00049" num="00049">
<claim-text>49. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> further comprising a development station configured in a dry configuration to apply a dry toner marking agent to a surface of the imaging member to develop the latent images.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00050" num="00050">
<claim-text>50. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> further comprising a development station configured in a liquid configuration to apply a liquid ink marking agent comprising a liquid to a surface of the imaging member to develop the latent images.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00051" num="00051">
<claim-text>51. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein the surface of the charge device comprises an electrically conductive outer surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00052" num="00052">
<claim-text>52. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein the portions of the surface of the charge device are individually configured to conduct current externally of the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00053" num="00053">
<claim-text>53. A photoconductor charging system comprising:
<claim-text>a bias member configured to provide an electrical charge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a charge device positioned adjacent to the bias member at a first nip location and adjacent to a photoconductor configured to form latent images at a second nip location;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the charge device is configured to rotate during imaging operations, and at a given moment in time, a charged portion of the charge device electrically charges a portion of the photoconductor located at the second nip location and a discharged portion of the charge device located at the first nip location is charged by the electrical charge of the bias member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>supply circuitry configured to provide electrical energy to the charge device independent of the bias member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00054" num="00054">
<claim-text>54. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00053">claim 53</claim-ref> wherein the charge device comprises a charge roller and a plurality of charge carriers of one polarity are transported in a first radial direction relative to a surface of the charge device at the first nip location and a second radial direction substantially opposite to the first radial direction at the second nip location.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00055" num="00055">
<claim-text>55. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00053">claim 53</claim-ref> wherein substantially no net DC current flows within an outer layer of the charge device during the imaging operations.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00056" num="00056">
<claim-text>56. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00053">claim 53</claim-ref> wherein the charge device is configured to contact the bias member and the photoconductor during the imaging operations.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00057" num="00057">
<claim-text>57. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00053">claim 53</claim-ref> wherein the charged portion of the charge device comprises an electrically conductive outer surface of the charge device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00058" num="00058">
<claim-text>58. An image engine comprising:
<claim-text>means for forming latent images during imaging operations of the image engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first means for electrically charging a surface of the means for forming latent images during the imaging operations;</claim-text>
<claim-text>second means for electrically charging a surface of the first means during the imaging operations;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first means comprises means for moving the surface of the first means adjacent to the means for forming latent images and the second means during the imaging operations of the image engine, and plural charge carriers flow in a first direction relative to a portion of the surface of the first means during the electrical charging of the first means by the second means and plural charge carriers flow in a second direction substantially opposite to the first direction during the electrical charging of the means for forming by the first means; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for providing electrical energy independent of the second means to the first means for biasing the first means during the electrical charging of the means for forming latent images by the first means.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00059" num="00059">
<claim-text>59. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00058">claim 58</claim-ref> wherein the plural charge carriers flowing in the first and second directions have the same polarity.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00060" num="00060">
<claim-text>60. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00058">claim 58</claim-ref> wherein the first and the second directions comprise substantially opposing radial directions of the first means comprising a charge roller for rotating about an axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00061" num="00061">
<claim-text>61. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00058">claim 58</claim-ref> wherein the first means comprises means for receiving the electrical energy and means for transporting the charge carriers, and substantially no net direct current energy flows intermediate the means for receiving the electrical energy and the means for transporting the charge carriers during the imaging operations.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00062" num="00062">
<claim-text>62. The engine of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00058">claim 58</claim-ref> wherein the first means comprises means for conducting current external to the first means.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
