<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297036-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297036</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11430642</doc-number>
<date>20060509</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>20</main-group>
<subgroup>14</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>440 75</main-classification>
<further-classification>192 21</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Clutch retention system for a marine propulsion device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3608684</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Shimanckas</name>
<date>19710900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192 20</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4223773</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Croisant et al.</name>
<date>19800900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192 4891</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4302196</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Blanchard</name>
<date>19811100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>440 75</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4986774</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wantz</name>
<date>19910100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>440 75</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5449306</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nakayasu et al.</name>
<date>19950900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>440 75</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5520559</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nakayasu et al.</name>
<date>19960500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>440 75</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6062360</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Shields</name>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192 21</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6112873</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Prasse et al.</name>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192 6983</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6544083</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Sawyer et al.</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>440 75</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6893305</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Natsume et al.</name>
<date>20050500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>440 75</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6960107</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Schaub et al.</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>440 75</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>440 75</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>440 76</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>440 78</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>440 83</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>192 21</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>192 51</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Weronke</last-name>
<first-name>Robert B.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Oshkosh</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Andrews</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fond du Lac</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Leroux</last-name>
<first-name>John C.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Oshkosh</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lanyi</last-name>
<first-name>William D.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Brunswick Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Lake Forest</city>
<state>IL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Olson</last-name>
<first-name>Lars A.</first-name>
<department>3617</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">In a marine transmission, trailing faces of each of a plurality of gear projections extending axially from a forward gear are provided with a rake angle. This rake angle of each trailing face cooperates with an associated surface of each of a plurality of clutch projections to retain a dog clutch in an axial position relative to the forward gear even during periods when a marine vessel is rapidly decelerating and, as a result, the dog clutch moves into driving relation with the forward gear.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="174.33mm" wi="223.27mm" file="US07297036-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="220.56mm" wi="173.23mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297036-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="224.45mm" wi="175.26mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297036-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="214.29mm" wi="179.24mm" file="US07297036-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="203.37mm" wi="168.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297036-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="219.12mm" wi="110.15mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297036-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention is generally related to a transmission mechanism for a marine propulsion device and, more particularly, to a system which retains a clutch mechanism in its proper position when a driven shaft is caused to rotate at a speed greater than its associated driving shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Those skilled in the art of marine propulsion devices are familiar with many different techniques and structures used to transfer torque from a driving shaft to a driven, or propeller, shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">U.S. Pat. No. 3,608,684, which issued to Shimanckas on Sep. 28, 1971, describes a clutch for a marine propulsion device. The device affords reverse operation by rotation of the driveshaft housing about a vertical axis. It includes a clutch in the lower unit gear case for selectively engaging or disengaging the propeller shaft with the driveshaft. The clutch is responsive to axial movement of the driveshaft caused by moving a control handle accessible to the operator.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">U.S. Pat. No. 4,223,773, which issued to Croisant et al. on Sep. 23, 1980, discloses a drive engaging apparatus. A clutch apparatus for a marine drive lower gear case includes a propeller shaft rotatably mounted in a gear case housing. A drive gear for both forward and reverse is positioned in the housing coaxial with the propeller shaft and a clutch member is rotatably fixed on the propeller shaft and movable axially into drive engagement with the drive gear. Clutch engaging elements are provided on opposed portions of the drive gears and the clutch member. Shift means utilizing a positive acting cam means positively move the clutch member into and out of engagement from the drive gears. The shift means also include a releasable latch means to positively maintain the shift means in the engaged position and a preloading means between the shift means and the clutch member to snap the clutch member into engagement.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">U.S. Pat. No. 4,302,196, which issued to Blanchard on Nov. 24, 1981, describes a marine propulsion unit including propeller shaft thrust transmitting means. The marine propulsion device includes a driveshaft housing mounted for vertical swinging movement about a horizontal axis relative to a boat, a propeller shaft rotatably mounted in the driveshaft housing and having an axis of rotation, and a propeller carried by the propeller shaft. The marine propulsion device also includes a first bevel gear mounted in the driveshaft housing and in coaxial relation to the propeller shaft, a second bevel gear mounted in the driveshaft housing and in coaxial relation to the propeller shaft, and a clutch mechanism for selectively drivingly connecting the bevel gears to the propeller shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">U.S. Pat. No. 4,986,774, which issued to Wantz on Jan. 22, 1991, discloses a desmodromic shift adaptor for a counter-rotating propeller shaft assembly. The adaptor member accommodates use of a desmodromic cam-actuated shifting mechanism. The adaptor member includes a cup, which is adapted to mount the fore one of the forward and reverse gears through a bearing member. The adaptor member further includes an internal passage within which is disposed the movable cam of the shifting mechanism, and an opening is in communication with the passage for allowing connection of the shift shaft to the shifting cam after assembly of the adapter member into the gear case cavity.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">U.S. Pat. No. 5,449,306, which issued to Nakayasu et al. on Sep. 12, 1995, describes a shifting mechanism for an outboard drive. It provides reduced coupling shock when the forward gears are engaged by a dual clutch assembly, as well as providing for consistent and quick engagement of the clutch assembly with the gear. The shifting mechanism involves a first gear and a corresponding first clutch, and a second gear and a corresponding second clutch. A plunger carries the first and second clutches which are arranged on the plunger at unequal distances from their respective gears.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">U.S. Pat. No. 6,112,873, which issued to Prasse et al. on Sep. 5, 2000, describes an anti-backlash dog type clutch. The clutch is provided for mounting on a rotatable shaft. The drive clutch includes a drive gear having a plurality of gear teeth projecting therefrom. A sleeve is slidably mounted on the shaft for rotational movement therewith. The sleeve includes a plurality of gear engaging recesses therein of arcuate lengths greater than the predetermined arcuate lengths of the gear teeth. The sleeve is movable between a first retracted position and a second engaged position wherein the gear teeth are received within corresponding gear engagement recesses in the sleeve in order to translate rotation of the drive gear to the shaft. A plurality of anti-backlash elements are provided to compensate for the difference in the arcuate lengths of the gear teeth and their corresponding gear engagement recesses in the sleeve.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">U.S. Pat. No. 6,544,083, which issued to Sawyer et al. on Apr. 8, 2003, discloses a shift mechanism for a marine propulsion system. The mechanism is provided in which a cam structure comprises a protrusion that is shaped to extend into a channel formed in a cam follower structure. The cam follower structure can be provided with first and second channels that allow the protrusion of the cam to be extended into either channel which accommodates both port and starboard shifting mechanisms. The cam surface formed on the protrusion of the cam moves in contact with a selected cam follower surface formed in the selected one of two alternative channels to cause the cam follower to move axially and to cause a clutch member to engage with either a first or second drive gear.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">U.S. Pat. No. 6,960,107, which issued to Schaub et al. on Nov. 1, 2005, discloses a marine transmission with a cone clutch used for direct transfer of torque. A transmission for a marine propulsion system uses a cone clutch in such a way that, when in a forward gear position, torque is transmitted from the input shaft, or driving shaft, to an output shaft, or driven shaft, solely through the cone clutch. When in forward gear position, driving torque between the driving and driven shafts is not transmitted through any gear teeth. When in reverse gear position, torque is transmitted through an assembly of bevel gears.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The patents described above are hereby expressly incorporated by reference in the description of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In certain applications, a driven shaft, such as a propeller shaft, can be caused to rotate faster than an associated driving shaft. Under these conditions, it is possible that a dog clutch member can become disengaged from an associated bevel gear member. It would therefore be significantly beneficial if a system could be provided in which the clutch member is positively retained in meshing relation with the associated bevel gear under these circumstances.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A transmission for a marine propulsion device, made in accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention, comprises a propeller shaft supported for rotation about a propeller shaft axis and first and second gears which are disposed for rotation about the propeller shaft axis. A driveshaft is supported for rotation about a driveshaft axis which is generally perpendicular to the propeller shaft axis in a preferred embodiment of the present invention. A drive gear is attached for rotation with the driveshaft. The first and second gears are disposed in meshing relation with the drive gear for rotation in opposite directions from each other about the propeller shaft. A dog clutch is attached for rotation with a propeller shaft about the propeller shaft axis and between the first and second gears. The dog clutch is movable parallel to the propeller shaft axis in a first direction toward the first gear and away from the second gear and in a second direction toward the second gear and away from the first gear. A first plurality of clutch projections extend from the dog clutch in a direction toward the first gear. A second plurality of gear projections extend from the first gear in a direction toward the dog clutch. Each of the first plurality of gear projections has a leading face and a trailing face. The leading face and the trailing face are each disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the leading face and the trailing face are each disposed at a right angle which is greater than three degrees and, in a particularly preferred embodiment of the present invention, the leading and trailing faces are each disposed at a rake angle which is generally equal to five degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">A second plurality of gear projections extend from the second gear in a direction toward the dog clutch. Each of the second plurality of gear projections has a leading face and a trailing face. The leading face is disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree and the trailing face is disposed at a rake angle which is generally equal to zero degrees. In one embodiment of the present invention, the first face and the second face are each disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree. The first face of each of the first plurality of clutch projections is disposable in contact relation with the leading face of the associated one of the first plurality of gear projections when the first gear is in driving relation with the dog clutch and the leading face of each of the first plurality of gear projections is providing a driving force against the first face of an associated one of the first plurality of clutch projections in order to cause the dog clutch and the propeller shaft to rotate in synchrony with the first gear. The second face of each of the first plurality of clutch projections is disposable in contact relation with the trailing face of an associated one of the first plurality of gear projections when the dog clutch is in driving relation with the first gear and the second face of each of the first plurality of clutch projections is providing a driving force against the trailing face of an associated one of the first plurality of gear projections to cause the dog clutch and the propeller shaft to rotate in synchrony with the first gear.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the dog clutch is attached to the propeller shaft by a plurality of spline teeth. The first gear can be a forward gear which, when the plurality of teeth projections is engaged in driving relation with the first plurality of clutch projections, a propeller of the marine propulsion system rotates in a direction which exerts a force on an associated marine vessel in a forward direction. The first and second gears can be bevel gears and the drive gear can also be a bevel gear which is in mesh relation with the first and second gears.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The present invention will be more fully and completely understood from a reading of the description of the preferred embodiment in conjunction with the drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side section view of a marine propulsion device incorporating the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an enlarged view of a portion of the illustration of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an isometric view of a forward gear of a marine propulsion system;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an isometric view of a dog clutch of a marine propulsion transmission;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a developed view of a plurality of gear projections of a forward gear in association with a clutch projection of a dog clutch when the forward gear is in driving relation with a driven dog clutch; and</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is generally similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> but shows the dog clutch in driving relation with a driven forward gear.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Throughout the description of the preferred embodiment of the present invention, like components will be identified by like reference numerals.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a section view of a marine propulsion device <b>10</b> which incorporates a preferred embodiment of the present invention. In a manner which is generally familiar to those skilled in the art, a driveshaft <b>14</b> is supported for rotation about a generally vertical axis <b>16</b>. A lower portion of the driveshaft <b>14</b> is attached to a drive gear <b>18</b> which is also rotatable about the driveshaft axis <b>16</b>. First and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, are supported for rotation about a propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>. A propeller shaft <b>30</b> is supported for rotation about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the components described above are supported within a gear case structure <b>40</b>. For purposes of general reference, the gear case structure <b>40</b> has a skeg <b>42</b> extending downwardly from its outer surface. The skeg <b>42</b> is partially illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A propeller structure <b>50</b> is shown attached to the propeller shaft <b>30</b> for rotation about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>. A shift shaft <b>56</b> is supported for rotation about a generally vertical axis and is operatively associated with a horizontally disposed shaft <b>60</b> that allows a dog clutch <b>70</b> to be moved axially in a direction parallel to the propeller shaft <b>26</b> when the shift shaft <b>56</b> is rotated about its central axis.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an enlarged representation of a portion of the structure shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, those skilled in the art are familiar with the basic operation of the illustrated structure. When an associated internal combustion engine is operating, the driveshaft <b>14</b> continually rotates about its driveshaft axis <b>16</b>. The drive gear <b>18</b> is attached to the bottom portion of the driveshaft <b>14</b> and continually rotates with it. The drive gear <b>18</b> is in continual meshing relation with teeth of the first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>. The first and second gears are supported for rotation about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b> in a manner that is generally independent of the propeller shaft <b>30</b>. In other words, the first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, can rotate about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b> without causing the propeller shaft <b>30</b> to rotate. This type of operation occurs when the transmission is in a neutral gear position. Because of the meshing association between the drive gear <b>14</b> and the first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, the first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, rotate in opposite directions about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b> under all conditions. The dog clutch <b>70</b> is movable in a direction which is generally parallel to the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b> in response to rotation of the shift shaft <b>56</b> about its central axis <b>57</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, it should be understood that the first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, are typically arranged so that engagement of one of these two gears causes the propeller shaft <b>30</b> to rotate in a direction which propels a marine vessel in a forward direction. This one of the first and second gears, <b>20</b> or <b>22</b>, is the forward gear as a result of the rotational direction of the driveshaft <b>14</b> about the driveshaft axis <b>16</b> and the pitch of the blades <b>80</b> of the propeller <b>50</b>. However, it should be clearly understood that the selection of the forward gear, from the choice of the first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, is not limiting to the scope of the present invention. In other words, the basic concept of the subject invention can be used to improve the operation of the transmission for a marine propulsion device under either of the two alternative circumstances described above. For purposes of illustrating and describing a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the first gear <b>20</b> will be assumed to be the forward gear and the second gear <b>22</b> will be assumed to be the reverse gear.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an isometric view of the first gear <b>20</b>. As described above, the first gear shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> will be assumed to be the forward gear of the marine propulsion system. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the gear teeth of the bevel gear, located in the region identified by reference numeral <b>88</b>, are not shown. However, it should be understood that the teeth in this region would be provided, in a manner which is very familiar to those skilled in the art, and configured along the surface of the region <b>88</b> which is formed generally in the shape of a frustum of a cone. The first gear <b>20</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is configured to be rotatable about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b> with its internal cylindrical surface <b>90</b> being rotatable about an outer surface of the propeller shaft <b>30</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>. It should be understood, however, that the internal cylindrical surface <b>90</b> is supported in non-contact association with an associated outer surface of the propeller shaft <b>30</b>. This relationship is maintained so that the rotation of the first gear <b>20</b> is independent of the rotation of the propeller shaft <b>30</b> unless these two components are linked together by the dog clutch <b>70</b> described above.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>, the first gear <b>20</b> will be assumed to rotate in the direction represented by arrow R in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. A plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> extend from the first gear <b>20</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in a direction toward the dog clutch <b>70</b>. Each of the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> has a leading face <b>101</b> and a trailing face <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an isometric view of the dog clutch <b>70</b>. As shown, the dog clutch <b>70</b> is rotatable about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>. A first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> extend from the dog clutch <b>70</b> in a direction toward the first gear <b>20</b>. This first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> is illustrated as extending toward the left in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, those skilled in the art of marine transmissions are familiar with the fact that the dog clutch <b>70</b> is attached to the propeller shaft <b>30</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, by a plurality of spline teeth. The internal spline teeth of the dog clutch <b>70</b> are identified by reference numeral <b>210</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. This spline arrangement attaches the dog clutch <b>70</b> to the propeller shaft <b>30</b> for synchronous rotation therewith.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Each of the first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> has a first face <b>201</b> and a second face <b>202</b>. The first and second faces of each of the first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> are each disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree and, in a particularly preferred embodiment of the present invention, is generally equal to approximately five degrees. As will be described in greater detail below, these rake angles of the first and second faces, <b>201</b> and <b>202</b>, result in the fact that these first and second faces are disposed in individual planes that are not parallel to the propeller axis <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, it should be clearly understood that it is well known to those skilled in the art of marine propulsion systems that the first and second faces, <b>201</b> and <b>202</b>, of the dog clutch <b>70</b> are configured at rake angles greater than zero degrees. This is done even though the second faces <b>202</b> of the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> is not intended to be placed in direct contact with the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> described above in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. This provision of rake angles of the second faces <b>202</b> of the dog clutch <b>70</b> is done as a convenience during the manufacture of the dog clutch. In other words, a milling cutter is typically configured to form adjacent first and second faces, <b>201</b> and <b>202</b>, between adjacent clutch projections during a single pass of the milling cutter in a direction which forms two diametrically opposite gaps between opposite pairs of clutch projections <b>200</b> in a single pass. As a result, a second face <b>202</b> of each clutch projection <b>200</b> is formed with a rake angle greater than zero degrees even though it is not intended that it ever be placed in direct contact with an associated surface of the first gear <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, it should be understood that when the dog clutch <b>70</b> is moved axially in a direction parallel to the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b> so that the first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> is moved into contact with the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b>, the leading faces <b>101</b> of each of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> moves into contact with an associated first face <b>201</b> of one of the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b>. Arrows R in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> show the resulting rotation of the first gear <b>20</b> and the dog clutch <b>70</b> in synchrony with each other about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>. This meshing of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> with the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> causes the dog clutch <b>70</b> to rotate in synchrony with the first gear <b>20</b> about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>. The splined connection between the dog clutch <b>70</b> and the propeller shaft <b>30</b> causes the propeller shaft <b>30</b> to rotate about the propeller shaft axis <b>20</b>. In other words, the engagement of the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> with the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> result in the transfer of torque from the driveshaft <b>14</b> to the propeller shaft <b>30</b> in the direction dictated by the rotational direction of the first gear <b>20</b> about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>. This basic operation of the components illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref> is generally known to those skilled in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref>, it should be understood that, under certain circumstances, the propeller shaft <b>30</b> can be caused to rotate at a speed greater than the first gear <b>20</b>. Most typically, this circumstance can arise when a rapid deceleration of the driveshaft <b>14</b> occurs. In other words, when the operator of a marine vessel rapidly decreases the operating speed of an associated internal combustion engine, the driveshaft <b>14</b> decelerates more quickly than the propeller shaft <b>30</b>. In addition, the movement of the propeller <b>50</b> through the water at the speed of the marine vessel causes the blades <b>80</b> to exert torque on the propeller shaft <b>30</b> to induce its continued rotation at a speed which is greater than the rotational speed of the first gear <b>20</b>. When this occurs, the leading face <b>101</b> of each of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> can become disengaged from the associated first face <b>201</b> of the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b>. In marine transmissions known to those skilled in the art, the trailing face <b>102</b> of each of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> is configured to have no rake angle. In other words, the effective rake angle of each of these trailing faces <b>102</b> is generally equal to zero. As a result, disengagement between the leading faces <b>101</b> of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> and the first faces <b>201</b> of the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> can allow separation between the dog clutch <b>70</b> and the first gear <b>20</b> as a result of the tendency of the dog clutch <b>70</b> to move axially away from the first gear <b>20</b>. During these deceleration conditions, the rotational speed of the dog clutch <b>70</b> typically exceeds the rotational speed of the propeller shaft <b>30</b> because of the hydrodynamic effect of the blades <b>80</b> as they move through the water at the speed of the associated marine vessel. This resulting rotational speed of the propeller shaft <b>30</b> and the dog clutch <b>70</b> is greater than the rotational speed of the first gear <b>20</b> which is in meshing contact with the drive gear <b>18</b> that is attached to the driveshaft <b>14</b>. Since the trailing faces <b>102</b> of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> have a rake angle of essentially zero degrees in forward gears known to those skilled in the art, the dog clutch <b>70</b> can easily move axially away from the forward gear. This causes disengagement between the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> and the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> in transmissions known to those skilled in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref>, the trailing faces <b>102</b> of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b>, in a first gear made in accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention, the surface of each trailing face <b>102</b> is provided with a rake angle greater than zero degrees. In a particularly preferred embodiment of the present invention, this rake angle is approximately equal to five degrees. Since the second face <b>202</b> of each of the clutch projections <b>200</b> is normally provided with a rake angle because of the manufacturing efficiencies described above, the rotation of the dog clutch <b>70</b> at speeds greater than the rotation of the first gear <b>20</b> will tend to cause the second faces <b>202</b> of the clutch projections <b>200</b> to move into contact with the trailing faces <b>102</b> of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b>. Since both the trailing faces <b>102</b> and the second faces <b>202</b> have a rake angle of approximately five degrees, the dog clutch <b>70</b> will be retained in meshing association with the first gear <b>20</b> even though the propeller shaft <b>30</b> is rotating at a speed greater than the first gear <b>20</b> during periods of time when the marine vessel is rapidly decelerating. This retention of the dog clutch <b>70</b> in engagement with the first gear <b>20</b> provides a significant advantage by preventing the axial movement of the dog clutch <b>70</b> away from the first gear <b>20</b> when rapid deceleration occurs.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref> are developed views which show the relationship between the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> and the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b>. Arrows R are provided to show the directions of rotation of the components.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, the first gear <b>20</b> provides torque, through its connection with the drive gear <b>18</b>, to the dog clutch <b>70</b>. This results from the leading face <b>101</b> being in direct contact with the first face <b>201</b>. In a typical arrangement of first gear and dog clutch, both the leading face <b>101</b> and the first face <b>201</b> are provided with a rake angle θ of approximately five degrees. The rake angles θ of the leading face <b>101</b> and first face <b>201</b> help to retain the meshing relation between the first gear <b>20</b> and the dog clutch <b>70</b> when the first gear <b>20</b> is driving the dog clutch <b>70</b>. This relationship is generally known to those skilled in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> shows the relative positions of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> and plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> when, during periods of rapid deceleration of the marine vessel, the dog clutch <b>70</b> is in driving relation with the first gear <b>20</b>. As described above, this occurs when the hydrodynamic forces on the blades <b>80</b> of the propeller <b>50</b> cause the propeller shaft <b>30</b> to attempt to move at a rotational speed about the propeller axis <b>26</b> which is greater than the rotational speed of the first gear <b>20</b> about that same axis. As a result, each of the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> moves into driving relation with an associated one of the plurality of gear projections. This causes the second face <b>202</b> of each of these clutch projections <b>200</b> to move into contact with a trailing face <b>102</b> of the associated gear projection <b>100</b>. The provision of the rake angle θ, between the trailing face <b>102</b> of each of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> and the second face <b>202</b> of each of the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b>, maintains the relative axial positions of the dog clutch <b>70</b> and first gear <b>20</b> even during circumstances when the dog clutch is attempting to rotate faster than the first gear. As a result, the roles of the dog clutch <b>70</b> and the first gear <b>20</b> are reversed. Rather than a situation when the first gear <b>20</b> is driving the dog clutch <b>70</b>, the dog clutch <b>70</b> exerts a driving force on the first gear <b>20</b> when the marine vessel is rapidly decelerating and the blades <b>80</b> of the propeller <b>50</b> are subjected to hydrodynamic forces as described above. This beneficial result is caused by the provision of the rake angle θ of the trailing face <b>102</b> of the first gear. As described above, the second face <b>202</b>, of each of the plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> is normally provided in dog clutches <b>70</b> known to those skilled in the art. However, the trailing faces <b>102</b> of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> of the first gear <b>20</b> are provided with no such rake angle θ. Instead, these trailing faces <b>102</b> are generally parallel to the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">As a result of the provision of the rake angle θ, of approximately five degrees, of the trailing face <b>102</b> on each of the plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> of the first gear <b>20</b>, the dog clutch <b>70</b> is retained in its axial position relative to the first gear <b>20</b> even during periods of rapid deceleration. The rake angles θ of both the trailing faces <b>102</b> and second faces <b>202</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>, result in this beneficial axial retention of the dog clutch <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref>, <b>5</b>A and <b>5</b>B, it can be seen that a preferred embodiment of the present invention provides a transmission for a marine propulsion device that comprises a propeller shaft <b>30</b> supported for rotation about a propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>, a first gear <b>20</b> disposed for rotation about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>, a second gear <b>22</b> disposed for rotation about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>, a driveshaft <b>14</b> supported for rotation about a driveshaft axis <b>16</b>, a drive gear <b>18</b> attached for rotation with the driveshaft <b>14</b>, a dog clutch <b>70</b> attached for rotation with the propeller shaft <b>30</b>, a first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> and a first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b>. The driveshaft axis <b>16</b> is generally perpendicular to the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b>. The first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, are disposed in meshing relation with the drive gear <b>18</b> for rotation in opposite directions from each other about the propeller shaft <b>30</b>. The dog clutch <b>70</b> is attached for rotation with the propeller shaft <b>30</b> about the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b> and between the first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>. The dog clutch <b>70</b> is movable in a direction parallel to the propeller shaft axis <b>26</b> in a first direction toward the first gear <b>20</b> and away from the second gear <b>22</b> and also in a second direction toward the second gear <b>22</b> and away from the first gear <b>20</b>. The first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> extend from the dog clutch <b>70</b> in a direction toward the first gear <b>20</b>. The first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> extend from the first gear <b>20</b> in a direction toward the dog clutch <b>70</b>. Each of the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> has a leading face <b>101</b> and a trailing face <b>102</b>. The leading face and the trailing face are each disposed at a rake angle θ which is greater than one degree. In certain embodiments of the present invention, the rake angle θ is greater than three degrees and, in a particularly preferred embodiment of the present invention, the rake angle θ is generally equal to approximately five degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">A second plurality of gear projections <b>300</b> extend from the second gear <b>22</b> in a direction toward the dog clutch <b>70</b>. Each of the second plurality of gear projections <b>300</b> has a leading face and a trailing face. These leading and trailing faces aren't specifically identified by reference numerals in the figures, but are positioned in a manner that is generally similar to the leading and trailing faces of the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> described above. The second gear <b>22</b> provides torque to the propeller shaft <b>30</b> that is in a reverse direction than the first gear <b>20</b>. In other words, the first gear <b>20</b> is typically a forward gear and the second gear <b>22</b> is typically a reverse gear. The leading face can be disposed at a rake angle θ which is greater than one degree and the trailing face can be disposed at a rake angle θ which is generally equal to zero degrees. In other words, during periods of rapid deceleration, the advantages provided by the rake angle θ on the trailing face <b>102</b> of the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> is not necessary because the problems described above, which can occur during rapid deceleration from movement in a forward direction, typically do not induce axial separation between the dog clutch <b>70</b> and the second gear <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">With continued reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref>, <b>5</b>A and <b>5</b>B, the first face <b>201</b> of each of the first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b>, is disposable in contact relation with the leading face <b>101</b> of an associated one of the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> when the first gear <b>20</b> is in driving relation with the dog clutch <b>70</b> and, simultaneously, the leading face <b>101</b> of each of the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> is providing a driving force against the first face <b>201</b> of an associated one of the first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> to cause the dog clutch <b>70</b> and the propeller shaft <b>30</b> to rotate in synchrony with the first gear <b>20</b>. The second face <b>202</b> of each of the first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> is disposable in contact relation with the trailing face <b>102</b> of an associated one of the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> when the dog clutch <b>70</b> is in driving relation with the first gear <b>20</b> and the second face <b>202</b> of each of the first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b> is providing a driving force against the trailing face <b>102</b> of an associated one of the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> to cause the dog clutch <b>70</b> and the propeller shaft <b>30</b> to rotate in synchrony with the first gear <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">In a particularly preferred embodiment of the present invention, the dog clutch <b>70</b> is attached to the propeller shaft <b>30</b> by a plurality of spline teeth <b>210</b>. In a particularly preferred embodiment of the present invention, the first gear <b>20</b> is a forward gear which, when the first plurality of gear projections <b>100</b> is engaged in driving association with the first plurality of clutch projections <b>200</b>, a propeller <b>50</b> of the marine propulsion rotates in a direction which exerts a force on an associated marine vessel in a forward direction. The first and second gears, <b>20</b> and <b>22</b>, are bevel gears in a preferred embodiment of the present invention. Similarly, the drive gear <b>18</b> is also a bevel gear in a particularly preferred embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Although the present invention has been described in particular detail and illustrated to show a preferred embodiment, it should be understood that alternative embodiments are also within its scope.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A transmission for a marine propulsion device, comprising:
<claim-text>a propeller shaft supported for rotation about a propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first gear disposed for rotation about said propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second gear disposed for rotation about said propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driveshaft supported for rotation about a driveshaft axis, said driveshaft axis being generally perpendicular to said propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a drive gear attached for rotation with said driveshaft, said first and second gears being disposed in meshing relation with said drive gear for rotation in opposite directions from each other about said propeller shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dog clutch attached for rotation with said propeller shaft about said propeller shaft axis and between said first and second gears, said dog clutch being movable parallel to said propeller shaft axis in a first direction toward said first gear and away from said second gear and in a second direction toward said second gear and away from said first gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first plurality of clutch projections extending from said dog clutch in a direction toward said first gear; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first plurality of gear projections extending from said first gear in a direction toward said dog clutch, each of said first plurality of gear projections having a leading face and a trailing face, said leading face and said trailing face each being disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said leading face and said trailing face are each disposed at a rake angle which is greater than three degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said leading face and said trailing face are each disposed at a rake angle which is generally equal to five degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a second plurality of gear projections extending from said second gear in a direction toward said dog clutch, each of said second plurality of gear projections having a leading face and a trailing face, said leading face being disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree and said trailing face being disposed at a rake angle which is generally equal to zero degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>each of said first plurality of clutch projections has a first face and a second face, said first face and said second face each being disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections is disposable in contact relation with said leading face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections when said first gear is in driving relation with said dog clutch and said leading face of each of said first plurality of gear projections is providing a driving force against said first face of an associated one of said first plurality of clutch projections to cause said dog clutch and said propeller shaft to rotate in synchrony with said first gear.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said second face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections is disposable in contact relation with said trailing face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections when said dog clutch is in driving relation with said first gear and said second face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections is providing a driving force against said trailing face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections to cause said dog clutch and said propeller shaft to rotate in synchrony with said first gear.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said dog clutch is attached to said propeller shaft by a plurality of spline teeth.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first gear is a forward gear which, when said first plurality of gear projections is engaged in driving association with said first plurality of clutch projections, a propeller of said marine propulsion system rotates in a direction which exerts a force on an associated marine vessel in a forward direction.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first and second gears are both bevel gears.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said drive gear is a bevel gear.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A transmission for a marine propulsion device, comprising:
<claim-text>a propeller shaft supported for rotation about a propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first gear disposed for rotation about said propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second gear disposed for rotation about said propeller shaft axis, said first and second gears both being bevel gears;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driveshaft supported for rotation about a driveshaft axis, said driveshaft axis being generally perpendicular to said propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a drive gear attached for rotation with said driveshaft, said first and second gears being disposed in meshing relation with said drive gear for rotation in opposite directions from each other about said propeller shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dog clutch attached for rotation with said propeller shaft about said propeller shaft axis and between said first and second gears, said dog clutch being movable parallel to said propeller shaft axis in a first direction toward said first gear and away from said second gear and in a second direction toward said second gear and away from said first gear, said dog clutch being attached to said propeller shaft by a plurality of spline teeth;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first plurality of clutch projections extending from said dog clutch in a direction toward said first gear, each of said first plurality of clutch projections having a first face and a second face, said first face and said second face each being disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first plurality of gear projections extending from said first gear in a direction toward said dog clutch, each of said first plurality of gear projections having a leading face and a trailing face, said leading face and said trailing face each being disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections is disposable in contact relation with said leading face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections when said first gear is in driving relation with said dog clutch and said leading face of each of said first plurality of gear projections is providing a driving force against said first face of an associated one of said first plurality of clutch projections to cause said dog clutch and said propeller shaft to rotate in synchrony with said first gear.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said second face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections is disposable in contact relation with said trailing face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections when said dog clutch is in driving relation with said first gear and said second face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections is providing a driving force against said trailing face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections to cause said dog clutch and said propeller shaft to rotate in synchrony with said first gear.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said leading face and said trailing face are each disposed at a rake angle which is generally equal to five degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a second plurality of gear projections extending from said second gear in a direction toward said dog clutch, each of said second plurality of gear projections having a leading face and a trailing face, said leading face being disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree and said trailing face being disposed at a rake angle which is generally equal to zero degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first gear is a forward gear which, when said first plurality of gear projections is engaged in driving association with said first plurality of clutch projections, a propeller of said marine propulsion system rotates in a direction which exerts a force on an associated marine vessel in a forward direction.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A transmission for a marine propulsion device, comprising:
<claim-text>a propeller shaft supported for rotation about a propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first gear disposed for rotation about said propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second gear disposed for rotation about said propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driveshaft supported for rotation about a driveshaft axis, said driveshaft axis being generally perpendicular to said propeller shaft axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a drive gear attached for rotation with said driveshaft, said first and second gears being disposed in meshing relation with said drive gear for rotation in opposite directions from each other about said propeller shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dog clutch attached for rotation with said propeller shaft about said propeller shaft axis and between said first and second gears, said dog clutch being movable parallel to said propeller shaft axis in a first direction toward said first gear and away from said second gear and in a second direction toward said second gear and away from said first gear;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first plurality of clutch projections extending from said dog clutch in a direction toward said first gear, each of said first plurality of clutch projections having a first face and a second face, said first face and said second face each being disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first plurality of gear projections extending from said first gear in a direction toward said dog clutch, each of said first plurality of gear projections having a leading face and a trailing face, said leading face and said trailing face each being disposed at a rake angle which is greater than one degree, said first gear being a forward gear which, when said first plurality of gear projections is engaged in driving association with said first plurality of clutch projections, a propeller of said marine propulsion system rotates in a direction which exerts a force on an associated marine vessel in a forward direction, said second face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections being disposable in contact relation with said trailing face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections when said dog clutch is in driving relation with said first gear and said second face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections is providing a driving force against said trailing face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections to cause said dog clutch and said propeller shaft to rotate in synchrony with said first gear.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a second plurality of gear projections extending from said second gear in a direction toward said dog clutch, each of said second plurality of gear projections having a leading face and a trailing face, said leading face and said trailing face each being disposed at a rake angle which is generally equal to five degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first face of each of said first plurality of clutch projections is disposable in contact relation with said leading face of an associated one of said first plurality of gear projections when said first gear is in driving relation with said dog clutch and said leading face of each of said first plurality of gear projections is providing a driving force against said first face of an associated one of said first plurality of clutch projections to cause said dog clutch and said propeller shaft to rotate in synchrony with said first gear, said dog clutch being attached to said propeller shaft by a plurality of spline teeth, said first and second gears being bevel gears.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
