<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297079-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297079</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11635491</doc-number>
<date>20061208</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>67</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473473</main-classification>
<further-classification>273349</further-classification>
<further-classification>273459</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Game system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>906848</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Atwell</name>
<date>19081200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>1300972</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Janssen</name>
<date>19190400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3866916</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Clarke</name>
<date>19750200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>273338</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4573679</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Janszen</name>
<date>19860300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>473427</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4595155</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gough</name>
<date>19860600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4993719</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hernandez</name>
<date>19910200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5279151</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Coody et al.</name>
<date>19940100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5303932</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kessler</name>
<date>19940400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>473492</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5338044</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mazursky et al.</name>
<date>19940800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>273402</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5375849</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sabourin</name>
<date>19941200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>473466</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5462284</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Felsenthal</name>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>473473</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5586767</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bohland</name>
<date>19961200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>273349</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5611539</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Watterson et al.</name>
<date>19970300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6807999</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Bowen et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>2</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>273349</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>273459</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473473</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473490</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>473492</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Delauter</last-name>
<first-name>Keith H.</first-name>
<address>
<street>10257 Meadowridge Dr.</street>
<city>Myersville</city>
<state>MD</state>
<postcode>21773</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Greiner</last-name>
<first-name>Stephen R.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chiu</last-name>
<first-name>Raleigh W.</first-name>
<department>3711</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An outdoor game system includes a pole adapted for anchoring to the earth. A water-carrying conduit extends upwardly through the pole and is rotatable within the pole. A sprinkler is mounted atop the pole and is connected to the conduit. A reel is affixed to the conduit within the pole adjacent an opening in the pole. The reel is rotatable with the conduit. A net, capable of extension from the opening in the pole, is wound upon the reel. An elongated cover is provided for closing the opening in the pole. The cover is connected to the net for supporting the net above the earth, when the net is extended from the opening in the pole. A handgrip, for rotating the conduit to rewind the net upon the reel, is affixed to the conduit beneath the reel.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="216.92mm" wi="281.35mm" file="US07297079-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="282.11mm" wi="221.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297079-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="281.69mm" wi="222.08mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297079-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="281.94mm" wi="222.25mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297079-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to amusement devices and, more particularly, to court games and accessories therefor.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">For generations, kids have played volleyball and tetherball outdoors. To avoid interference from trees and houses, volleyball and tetherball courts were, and still are, set up in open, grassy areas. These areas, lacking significant shade, however, often prove too hot for extended periods of playing outdoor games, especially during summer months. Volleyball and tetherball games, then, are often short, being broken up by dips in a nearby pool or by play with a garden hose.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Since staying cool while playing volleyball and tetherball outdoors is often difficult, it is a principal object of the invention to provide a single game system that allows users to play games of either volleyball or tetherball and that sprinkles water on users as either game progresses. The sprinkling, coming from above the users, does not impede game play.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">It is another object of the invention to provide a game system of the type described that can be converted from a volleyball game to a tetherball game, and vise versa, in a matter of seconds and without the use of tools and without the need for prolonged training to accomplish the conversion.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is an object of the invention to provide improved features and arrangements thereof in a game system for the purposes described that is lightweight in construction, inexpensive to manufacture, and dependable in use.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Briefly, the game system in accordance with this invention achieves the intended objects by featuring a pole anchored to the earth. A rotatable, water-carrying conduit extends upwardly through the pole. A sprinkler is mounted atop the pole and is connected to the conduit. A reel is affixed to the conduit and is rotatable with the conduit. A net, capable of extension from an opening in the pole, is wound upon the reel. An elongated cover closes the opening in the pole and is connected to the net so as to support the net when the net is extended from the opening in the pole. A handgrip is affixed to the conduit for rotating the conduit to selectively rewind the net upon the reel. Also, a tetherball is secured by means of a tether to the top of the pole.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The foregoing and other objects, features, and advantages of the game system will become readily apparent upon further review of the following detailed description of the preferred embodiment as illustrated in the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention may be more readily described with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a game system in accordance with the present invention with the net thereof being fully extended for tetherball game play.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of the game system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with the net being retracted into the pole for tetherball game play</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a top view of the game system with the net retracted.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective view of the game system with the net retracted and the ground anchor being revealed.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the game system with the net being extended and portions thereof being broken away.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a front view of the pole cover of the game system that alternately serves as a net support.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a perspective view of the bottom portion of the pole cover showing the foothold feature.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Similar reference characters denote corresponding features consistently throughout the accompanying drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring now to the FIGS., a game system in accordance with the present invention is shown at <b>10</b>. Game system <b>10</b> includes a pole <b>12</b> adapted for anchoring at its bottom to the earth <b>14</b>. Extending upwardly through pole <b>12</b> is a conduit <b>16</b> for conveying water from a garden hose <b>18</b> to a sprinkler <b>20</b> mounted atop pole <b>12</b>. A reel <b>22</b> is affixed to the top of conduit <b>16</b> within pole <b>12</b>. Wound upon reel <b>22</b> is a net <b>24</b> that can be selectively extended from pole <b>12</b>. The opening <b>26</b> in pole <b>12</b> from which net <b>24</b> is extended is closed by an elongated cover <b>28</b> that also serves as a support for net <b>24</b> during the playing of volleyball games.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Pole <b>12</b> includes a hollow tube <b>30</b> upon the top of which is fitted a cap <b>32</b>. Tube <b>30</b> measures about 12 feet (3.66 m) in length and 1 foot (30.4 cm) in diameter. The side wall of tube <b>30</b> has a thickness of about 0.25 inches (0.64 cm) and has access openings <b>26</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>, respectively located at the top, bottom, and middle thereof. Cap <b>32</b>, however, has a circular, top plate <b>38</b> adhesively fastened to the top of tube <b>30</b>. From the periphery of top plate <b>38</b>, a tubular retaining wall <b>40</b> extends downwardly to snugly engage and reinforce tube <b>30</b>. Tube <b>30</b> and cap <b>32</b> are made from PVC, known for its light weight, great strength, durability, and water resistance, but can be formed from, and fastened together by, other suitable materials.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The bottom of pole <b>30</b> is slidably fitted within a ground anchor <b>42</b>. As shown, anchor <b>42</b> has a tubular sleeve <b>44</b> vertically affixed by a mass of cement <b>46</b> to earth <b>14</b>. The top of sleeve <b>44</b> is provided with an outwardly extending, peripheral lip <b>48</b> that sits atop cement <b>46</b> for reinforcing sleeve <b>44</b> and keeping soil out of sleeve <b>44</b>. Sleeve <b>44</b> measures about: 2 feet (61 cm) in length, 1 foot (30.4 cm) in diameter, and 0.25 inch (0.64 cm) in wall thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Although the most common sites for tetherball or volleyball courts are on a lawn, heavy use can make such an area muddy. Fortunately, cover <b>28</b> can be variably positioned around anchor <b>42</b> to reduce wear and tear on sod. Alternatively, extra driveway space can provide a good site for the positioning of anchor <b>42</b>, as can a graveled or mulched area, all of which make it somewhat easier to play games while the ground is wet. Falling should be rare for most players, so a hard surface should be reasonably safe.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">For tetherball play, it is best to have about 10 feet (3.04 m) of clear, level ground around anchor <b>42</b>. The only boundary needed is a line (not shown) radiating out from anchor <b>42</b> dividing the play area into two equal halves. Such a line can be provided in any suitable manner.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Volleyball play requires more space than tetherball play. A typical volleyball court measures 29.5 feet by 59 feet (18 m×9 m). Such a court is positioned so that anchor <b>42</b> is placed along one side of the court so as to divide the side in half. For play, cover <b>28</b> is extended to an opposing point on the other side of the court and is affixed there. The boundaries of the court can be delineated upon the earth in any suitable manner.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Conduit <b>16</b> extends longitudinally through pole <b>12</b>. The top of conduit <b>16</b> passes rotatably through an opening <b>50</b> in top plate <b>38</b>. The bottom of conduit <b>16</b> is positioned adjacent opening <b>34</b> in tube <b>30</b>. Conduit <b>16</b> measures about 11 feet (3.35 m) in length and has an outer diameter of about 1 inch (2.5 cm) and an inner diameter of about 0.75 inches (1.9 cm).</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">An L-shaped hose fitting <b>52</b> is connected to the bottom of conduit <b>16</b>. Fitting <b>52</b> provides for the threaded fastening of garden hose <b>18</b> to conduit <b>16</b>. So that hose <b>18</b> does not become tangled when conduit <b>16</b> is rotated to extend or retract net <b>24</b>, as will be explained more fully below, a swiveling pipe joint <b>54</b> is positioned between conduit <b>16</b> and fitting <b>52</b>. Thus, fitting <b>52</b> can always be extended from tube <b>30</b> regardless of the angular orientation of conduit <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Sprinkler <b>20</b> includes a base <b>56</b> that carries a rotatable hub <b>58</b>. As shown, base <b>56</b> is affixed to the top of conduit <b>16</b> so as to receive water therefrom and to hang conduit <b>16</b> from top plate <b>38</b> of cap <b>32</b>. Base <b>56</b> serves as a vertical axle upon which hub <b>58</b> rotates. A number of jetting arms <b>60</b> radiate outwardly from hub <b>58</b>. Arms <b>60</b> are hollow and their inner ends are in fluid communication with the interior of hub <b>58</b> and their outer ends are open so as to serve as spray nozzles. When water from a pressurized source, like hose <b>18</b>, is delivered to sprinkler <b>20</b> via conduit <b>16</b>, arms <b>60</b> jet water tangentially to hub <b>58</b> thereby causing hub <b>58</b> and arms <b>60</b> to rotate and spray water in all directions around pole <b>12</b> to the amusement of game players.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Reel <b>22</b> has a cylindrical core <b>62</b> with a pair of outwardly extending peripheral flanges <b>64</b> being respectively located at the top and bottom of core <b>62</b>. Core <b>62</b> is provided with an interior passageway (not shown) sized to snugly receive conduit <b>16</b>. Snap fasteners as at <b>66</b> are provided on the exterior of core <b>62</b> for the releasable attachment of net <b>24</b> to reel <b>22</b>. Flanges <b>64</b> ensure that net <b>24</b> is neatly wound upon core <b>62</b> and that conduit <b>16</b> remains centralized within tube <b>30</b> when conduit <b>16</b> is rotated for net winding purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The rotation of conduit <b>16</b> is manually accomplished. To facilitate rotation, a handgrip <b>68</b> is affixed to conduit <b>16</b> beneath reel <b>22</b> and adjacent opening <b>36</b> in tube <b>30</b>. Rotating handgrip <b>68</b> by hand causes conduit <b>16</b>, sprinkler <b>20</b>, and reel <b>22</b> to rotate about a vertical axis. Continued rotation of reel <b>22</b> draws net <b>24</b> onto core <b>62</b> of reel <b>22</b> for the storage of net <b>24</b> out of the weather and within pole <b>12</b> when it is not in use. Withdrawal of net <b>24</b> from pole <b>12</b> is accomplished merely by pulling cover <b>28</b> away from pole <b>12</b>, no manipulation of handgrip <b>68</b> is required.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Net <b>24</b> is conventional in size being about 31 feet (9.50 m) in length, 3.3 feet (1 m) in height, and is made from a rope mesh <b>70</b> with openings of about 3.9 inches (10 cm) square. The periphery of mesh <b>70</b> is reinforced with a webbing border <b>72</b>. The inner end of border <b>72</b> is provided with snap fasteners <b>74</b> adapted for releasable attachment to snap fasteners <b>66</b> affixed to reel <b>22</b>. The outer end of border <b>72</b> is provided with grommets <b>76</b> for tying net <b>24</b> to the top of cover <b>28</b>. The height of net <b>24</b> is about 8 feet (2.4 m) for tetherball game play.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Cover <b>28</b> includes an elongated bar <b>78</b> having a ground-penetrating spike <b>80</b> affixed to the bottom thereof. Bar <b>78</b>, formed of PVC, measures about 10 feet (3.04 m) in length and has a C-shaped cross section to nest snugly against pole <b>12</b>. Spike <b>80</b> is formed of metal and is sharpened so that it can be easily pushed into earth <b>14</b>. A foothold <b>82</b> extends outwardly from the top of spike <b>80</b> for the easy application of downward force to spike <b>80</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">A pair of pins <b>90</b> is affixed to the top of bar <b>78</b> for holding cover <b>28</b> against tube <b>30</b> when net <b>24</b> is being stored within pole <b>12</b>. Pins <b>90</b> fit snugly within a correspondingly positioned pair of holes <b>92</b> in the top of tube <b>30</b>. A light push or pull is all that is required to insert pins <b>90</b> into, or withdraw pins <b>90</b> from, holes <b>92</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Beneath pins <b>90</b>, openings <b>94</b> are provided in the top of bar <b>78</b> for the passage of ties as at <b>96</b>. Ties <b>96</b> extend through openings <b>94</b> and grommets <b>76</b> to attach net <b>24</b> to cover <b>28</b>. Ties <b>96</b> can be formed of rope, wire, nylon, or other suitable material.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">When cover <b>28</b> is positioned against tube <b>30</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-4</figref>, spike <b>80</b> and foothold <b>82</b> are positioned within opening <b>34</b>. Spike <b>80</b> extends downwardly into ground anchor <b>42</b> and prevents the bottom of cover <b>28</b> from being pulled away from tube <b>30</b>. Foothold <b>82</b>, being relatively short does not contact hose fitting <b>52</b> found adjacent opening <b>34</b> and does not impede in any way the flow of water through conduit <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">When it is desired that game system <b>10</b> be employed for volleyball play, cover <b>28</b> is moved away from pole <b>12</b> and secured with spike <b>80</b> to earth <b>14</b> at a desired location. To ensure that cover <b>28</b> not tip over, the center portion of a guide rope <b>84</b>, measuring perhaps 24 feet (7.3 m) in length, can be looped through a pair of slots <b>86</b> at the top of bar <b>78</b>. Then, the opposite ends of rope <b>84</b> are pulled taught and fastened to earth by pegs <b>88</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Volleyball is played in a traditional manner with system <b>10</b>. Game play proceeds with a ball <b>98</b> being first served, and later volleyed, over net <b>24</b> by players <b>100</b> formed into teams of four to six players on opposite sides of net <b>24</b>. The serving team scores a point when the receiving team fails to return the ball over net <b>24</b> in three or fewer attempts. The serve is lost, however, if the serving team misses a volley in three attempts. A volleyball game is played to twenty-one points.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Each team rotates when it wins the serve so that all players <b>100</b> get a turn playing adjacent net <b>24</b>. Ball <b>98</b> can be played off net <b>24</b> during a volley. A player <b>100</b> cannot hit ball <b>100</b> twice in succession nor can he: carry, palm or throw ball <b>98</b>. Hitting ball <b>98</b> toward sprinkler <b>20</b> so that water jetted therefrom diverts ball <b>98</b> from its original path is encouraged. Not only can water being sprayed from sprinkler <b>20</b> keep players <b>100</b> cool, but can add a new, strategic aspect to the game of volleyball.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">System <b>10</b> can be employed for tetherball game play. To this end, an eyebolt <b>102</b> is affixed to the top of tube <b>30</b>. A flexible cord or tether <b>104</b> is tied at its inner end to eyebolt <b>102</b>. A tetherball <b>106</b> is tied to the outer end of tether <b>104</b>. The length of tether <b>104</b> is set at 8 feet (2.4 m) so that the bottom of ball <b>106</b> ends up about 2 feet (61 cm) above earth <b>14</b> when tether <b>104</b> is not wrapped around pole <b>12</b> and ball <b>106</b> is at rest.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A tetherball game is won when one of a pair of players <b>108</b> has wrapped tether <b>104</b> as far as it can go around pole <b>12</b>. The usual game begins with one player <b>108</b> serving in a direction she chooses, after which either player can hit ball <b>106</b>. Under the best rules, the serving player <b>108</b> must wait until either the other player strikes ball <b>106</b>, or tether <b>104</b> has wrapped four times, before she can strike ball <b>106</b> again.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">During a game of tetherball, a player <b>108</b> cannot: 1) step off sides, 2) touch tether <b>104</b>, 3) carry or throw ball <b>106</b>, and 4) double hit ball <b>106</b>. If either player <b>108</b> commits one of these minor rules violations, ball <b>106</b> is stopped and returned to the place it was wrapped when the violation occurred. The other player <b>108</b> gets to serve, and either player can hit ball <b>106</b> from that point on. If a player <b>108</b> commits three of the minor violations listed above, in any combination, his opponent wins the game. If a player <b>108</b> commits a major rules violation, i.e., grabs pole <b>12</b>, he automatically loses the game.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Water sprayed from sprinkler <b>20</b> can affect tetherball game play and the outcome of a game. For example, hitting ball <b>106</b> so that its movement coincides with that of the sprayed water, clockwise or counterclockwise around pole <b>12</b>, receives a small benefit. The benefit is taken away, however, by an opponent who lofts ball <b>106</b> upwardly so as to cause the first player to look directly into the spray to make a hit—an added difficulty. Thus, the use of sprinkler <b>20</b> adds another dimension to the game of tetherball.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">While game system <b>10</b> has been described with a high degree of particularity, it will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that modifications can be made to it. Therefore, it is to be understood that the present invention is not limited merely to game system <b>10</b> described above, but encompasses any and all game systems within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A game system, comprising:
<claim-text>a hollow pole being adapted for anchoring at the bottom thereof to the earth, said pole having an opening therein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a water-carrying conduit extending upwardly through said pole past said opening, said conduit being rotatable within said pole;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sprinkler being mounted atop said pole and being connected to said conduit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a reel being affixed to said conduit within said pole adjacent said opening, said reel being rotatable with said conduit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a net, capable of extension from said opening in said pole, being wound upon said reel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an elongated cover for closing said opening in said pole, said cover being connected to said net for supporting said net above the earth when said net is extended from said opening in said pole; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a handgrip, for rotating said conduit to rewind said net upon said reel, being affixed to said conduit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The game system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a tether being affixed at its top to the top of said pole; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tetherball affixed to the bottom of said tether.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
