<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296783-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296783</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11073652</doc-number>
<date>20050308</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-026611</doc-number>
<date>20050202</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251327</main-classification>
<further-classification>251193</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Vacuum processing apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4381100</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schoenberg</name>
<date>19830400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>251368</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6390448</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kroeker et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>251167</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0129910</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ishigaki</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>251193</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-9125</doc-number>
<date>20020100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>15</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251327</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251167</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251193</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251195-204</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251296</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251302</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>414217</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060169939</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060803</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kihara</last-name>
<first-name>Hideki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kudamatsu</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tsubone</last-name>
<first-name>Tsunehiko</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hikari</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nagayasu</last-name>
<first-name>Nobuo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kudamatsu</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Antonelli, Terry, Stout &amp; Kraus, LLP.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hitachi High-Technologies Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Jacyna</last-name>
<first-name>J. Casimer</first-name>
<department>3754</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An inexpensive and reliable vacuum processing apparatus is provided. The vacuum processing apparatus comprises a sealed gate located between two vacuum vessels for allowing them to communicate with each other and a sample subjected to processing to be transferred from one of the vacuum vessels to the other therethrough; and a gate valve located on a path of the gate, the gate valve including a first and second valve body facing a first and second opening, respectively, and a shaft to which the valve bodies are coupled at one end thereof, the gate valve selectively opening and closing each of the openings. The gate valve includes an axial drive section coupled to the other end of the shaft for moving the shaft in the axial direction thereof, and a rotary drive section located between the one end and the other end of the shaft for rotating the shaft about a predetermined pivot crossing the axis of the shaft. The rotating force is transmitted to a spot on the shaft between the pivot and the other end along the axis of the shaft.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="108.37mm" wi="84.84mm" file="US07296783-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="231.65mm" wi="180.00mm" file="US07296783-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="164.85mm" wi="132.33mm" file="US07296783-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="140.46mm" wi="155.87mm" file="US07296783-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="127.25mm" wi="160.36mm" file="US07296783-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="144.78mm" wi="172.89mm" file="US07296783-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="203.03mm" wi="149.78mm" file="US07296783-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="137.75mm" wi="153.25mm" file="US07296783-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application is based on and claims priority of Japanese patent applications No. 2005-026611 filed on Feb. 2, 2005, the entire contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The invention relates to a vacuum processing apparatus such as, for example, a plasma processing apparatus for processing a sample with plasma, and more particularly to a vacuum processing apparatus having valves located between a plurality of chambers in which the sample is moved.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A known vacuum processing apparatus of the type described above comprises an atmospheric transfer chamber where at least one of the cassettes storing samples is installed and a sample is transferred and exchanged with the cassette under atmospheric pressure; a vacuum transfer chamber of a generally polygonal planar shape, having a reduced pressure and maintained at vacuum, where a robot arm for holding and transferring a sample is placed inside; a plurality of process vessels located around the periphery thereof; and a load lock chamber or unload lock chamber connected between the atmospheric transfer chamber and the vacuum transfer chamber and having an inner pressure that can be varied or configured between a reduced pressure (vacuum) equal to that in the vacuum transfer chamber and a pressure (atmospheric pressure) equal to that in the atmospheric transfer chamber, where a sample is exchanged with the atmospheric transfer chamber under atmospheric pressure and with the vacuum transfer chamber under vacuum pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In addition, a configuration including a gate and a gate valve for closing and opening the gate is located between the vacuum transfer chamber and the atmospheric transfer chamber, between the vacuum transfer chamber and the load lock chamber or unload lock chamber, or between the load lock (unload lock) chamber and the atmospheric transfer chamber. The gate partitions the connected chambers and has an opening through which a sample is transferred.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In general, a plurality of such vacuum processing apparatus are located in a user's room such as a clean room adjusted to a predetermined condition to simultaneously process a plurality of samples. To improve the overall efficiency in processing samples and the efficiency in manufacturing devices or other products obtained from the processed samples, it is important to note that many of such apparatus can be installed within a limited area of the room. Therefore, it has been required to reduce the size of the apparatus to decrease its footprint.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">To solve this problem, conventionally, the size of the gate valve has been reduced to decrease the footprint of the apparatus. In this conventional art, a plurality of gates with two valves for closing/opening the gate are provided between each pair of the chambers. These valves are connected to a single shaft, which is moved vertically, as well as rotated toward each gate, so that each gate can be selectively closed with the associated valve (see, for example, Japanese Laid-Open Patent Application 2002-009125).</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">However, the conventional art as described above has some problems because it does not fully take the following points into consideration. The apparatus according to the conventional art described above comprises, between two gates, a first pivotally supported cradle capable of rotating toward the gates, and a second pivotally supported cradle connected to the first cradle, capable of rotating toward the gates, to the second cradle being attached a cylinder for vertically moving a shaft having two valves mounted thereon. The configuration is thus complex, and bulky in the vertical direction.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In addition, the configuration of valves for closing or opening the two gates is complex, which increases time required for maintenance and other handling operations. Moreover, the housing for containing these valves and gates requires a large size, which leads to a larger footprint of the entire processing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Furthermore, the apparatus is more prone to vibration, by which wastes and dust are likely to occur from members contained in the housing. This leads to a problem that the wafer is prone to adhesion of foreign particles and contamination.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An object of the invention is to provide a vacuum processing apparatus that is inexpensive and reliable.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Another object of the invention is to provide a vacuum processing apparatus that has a small footprint.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Still another object of the invention is to provide a vacuum processing apparatus that has a high processing efficiency.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The foregoing object is achieved by a vacuum processing apparatus comprising a sealed gate located between two vacuum vessels for allowing the vacuum vessels to communicate with each other and a sample subjected to processing to be transferred from one of the vacuum vessels to the other therethrough; and a gate valve located on a path of the gate, the gate valve including a first valve body facing a first opening of the gate on one vacuum vessel side, a second valve body facing a second opening of the gate on the other vacuum vessel side, and a shaft to which the valve bodies are coupled at one end thereof, the gate valve selectively opening and closing each of the openings, the gate valve including an axial drive section coupled to the other end of the shaft for moving the shaft in the axial direction thereof, and a rotary drive section located between the one end and the other end of the shaft for rotating the shaft about a predetermined pivot crossing the axis of the shaft, and the rotating force is transmitted to a spot on the shaft between the pivot and the one end or the other end along the axis of the shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In an aspect of the invention, the vacuum processing apparatus further comprises a valve chamber located in the gate, the first valve body and the second valve body being moved inside the valve chamber with motion of the shaft, wherein the first valve body is attached and coupled to the second valve body. Preferably, in the vacuum processing apparatus, after a lid member sealing the valve chamber is opened, the first valve body can be detached through the opened portion out of the valve chamber.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In another aspect of the vacuum processing apparatus according to the invention, the first valve body can be attached to and detached from the second valve body while the second valve body closes the facing opening. Preferably, in the vacuum processing apparatus, the sample is processed in the one vacuum vessel with which the first opening communicates.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In still another aspect of the vacuum processing apparatus according to the invention, the shaft has a first and second shaft divided between the other end of the shaft and the axial drive section and coupled to each other, and the first shaft subjected to force from the rotary drive section can slide and rotate relative to the second shaft at a coupling section between the first and second shafts. Preferably, the vacuum processing apparatus further comprises a bellows attached around the first shaft outside the valve chamber for sealing between the valve chamber and the periphery of the shaft while the gate valve is attached to the vessel having the valve chamber, the bellows being compressed with motion of the shaft.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a plan view illustrating the configuration overview of the vacuum processing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a vertical cross section illustrating the configuration of a gate unit.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) is a vertical cross section illustrating the configuration of a gate valve section; and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>b</i>) is a vertical cross section as viewed laterally in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>a</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>4</b>(<i>b</i>) are vertical cross sections illustrating the operation of the gate unit.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a vertical cross section of a relevant part illustrating the closed state on the vacuum transfer chamber side of the gate unit.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a vertical cross section illustrating the detached state of the gate valve.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>7</b>(<i>b</i>) are perspective views illustrating the structure of the gate.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Embodiments of the invention will now be described in detail with reference to the drawings. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an overview schematically illustrating the configuration of an embodiment of the vacuum processing apparatus according to the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The vacuum processing apparatus <b>100</b> shown in this figure can be roughly divided into two parts: a vacuum block <b>101</b> located on the upper side of the figure, and an atmospheric block <b>102</b> connected thereto, located on the lower side of the figure.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The vacuum block <b>101</b> is primarily composed of a plurality of interconnected vacuum vessels having a reduced pressure and maintained at vacuum where a sample subjected to processing is transferred inside, including a vacuum transfer vessel <b>103</b> of a generally polygonal (hexagonal) planar shape depicted around the center of the figure, vacuum processing units <b>104</b><i>a</i>, <b>104</b><i>b</i>, <b>104</b><i>c</i>, and <b>104</b><i>d</i>, and load lock or unload lock chamber vessels <b>106</b>, <b>107</b> attached to respective edges around the generally polygonal shape. It is noted that each of the load lock or unload lock chamber vessels <b>106</b>, <b>107</b> in this embodiment is configured to be capable of both operations. For simplicity, they are hereinafter referred to as load lock chamber vessels.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Each of the vacuum processing units <b>104</b><i>a </i>to <b>104</b><i>d </i>and the load lock chamber vessels <b>106</b>, <b>107</b> comprises a vacuum vessel. The pressure inside the vacuum vessel can be reduced to and maintained at the degree of vacuum equal to that inside the vacuum transfer vessel <b>103</b>. Sample stages <b>105</b><i>a </i>to <b>105</b><i>d </i>are located in the vacuum vessels. The sample stage has a mounting surface on which a sample subjected to processing is mounted. In particular, samples are processed while being mounted on the sample stages <b>105</b><i>a </i>to <b>105</b><i>d </i>located in the vacuum processing units <b>104</b><i>a </i>to <b>104</b><i>d. </i></p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In the vacuum transfer vessel <b>103</b> is located a vacuum transfer robot <b>108</b> for transferring a sample between the sample stages <b>105</b><i>a </i>to <b>105</b><i>d </i>in the vacuum processing units <b>104</b><i>a </i>to <b>104</b><i>d</i>, and the sample stages <b>105</b><i>e</i>, <b>105</b><i>f </i>in the load lock chamber vessels <b>106</b>, <b>107</b>, respectively. The vacuum transfer robot <b>108</b> has two robot arms <b>109</b>, <b>109</b>′, each mounting a sample on its upper face to transfer and exchange the sample between the sample stages.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In addition, the vacuum processing units <b>104</b><i>a </i>to <b>104</b><i>d </i>and the load lock chamber vessels <b>106</b>, <b>107</b> are connected with the vacuum transfer vessel <b>103</b> via gate units <b>110</b><i>a </i>to <b>110</b><i>f</i>, each including a gate partitioning the connection therebetween with an opening through which a sample is transferred, and a gate valve for closing and opening the gate.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The atmospheric block <b>102</b> is primarily composed of an atmospheric transfer vessel <b>112</b> configured so that it has an inner pressure of about atmospheric pressure and that a plurality of cassettes <b>114</b> for enclosing samples can be attached to the front side thereof (lower side in the figure), and an atmospheric transfer robot <b>113</b> located in an atmospheric transfer chamber in the atmospheric transfer vessel <b>112</b> for exchanging a sample between the cassettes <b>114</b> and the load lock chamber vessels <b>106</b>, <b>107</b> in the atmospheric transfer chamber under atmospheric pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In addition, an aligner <b>115</b> is attached to the lateral side (left side in the figure) of the atmospheric transfer vessel <b>112</b>. The aligner <b>115</b> adjusts the orientation and position of the sample subjected to processing that has been taken out of the cassette <b>114</b> by the robot arm <b>113</b>′ of the atmospheric transfer robot <b>113</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The load lock chambers <b>106</b>, <b>107</b> are located on the rear side (upper side in the figure) of the atmospheric transfer vessel <b>112</b> and connected to the rear face of the atmospheric transfer vessel <b>112</b>. The load lock chamber vessels <b>106</b>, <b>107</b> are configured so that the pressure therein can be varied from the pressure equal to ambient pressure (atmospheric pressure) around the apparatus to the pressure equal to that inside the vacuum transfer vessel <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The load lock chamber vessels <b>106</b>, <b>107</b> are connected to the atmospheric transfer vessel <b>112</b> via gate units <b>111</b><i>a</i>, <b>111</b><i>b</i>, respectively. The atmospheric transfer chamber communicates with the load lock chamber vessel via a gate in the gate unit <b>111</b>. The gate can be closed/opened by driving a gate valve provided in the gate unit <b>111</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the gate unit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is described in detail. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a vertical cross section schematically illustrating the configuration of the gate unit of the vacuum processing apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In this embodiment, the gate unit <b>110</b> is generally identical to the gate unit <b>111</b> in the configuration of its gate section and gate valve. By way of example, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the gate 110<i>a </i>between the processing unit <b>104</b><i>a </i>and the vacuum transfer chamber <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The gate unit <b>110</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is located between and coupled to a vacuum vessel <b>201</b> constituting the vacuum processing unit <b>104</b>, and the vacuum transfer vessel <b>103</b>. The gate unit <b>110</b> functions as a sluice valve for opening or closing the gate that allows a process chamber <b>203</b> in the vacuum vessel <b>201</b> to communicate with a vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> in the vacuum transfer vessel <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Broadly, the gate unit <b>110</b> is vertically divided into two parts. The upper part is a gate vessel <b>202</b> and the lower part is a gate valve section <b>208</b>. The gate vessel <b>202</b> comprises a vacuum vessel clamp <b>202</b>′ and, as described above, is coupled to the vacuum vessel <b>201</b> and the vacuum transfer chamber <b>103</b> with bolts or the like. On its inside, the gate vessel <b>202</b> comprises gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b> that are openings with which the process chamber <b>203</b> and the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> communicate, respectively. The gate vessel <b>202</b> also includes a valve chamber <b>209</b> that is a space where the openings of the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b> are opened and a valve <b>210</b> for closing/opening the openings is located inside. The valve <b>210</b> can be moved vertically in the valve chamber <b>209</b> by a predetermined drive means as described later to be placed at a position where the valve <b>210</b> can cover the openings of the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b>. The valve <b>210</b> can also be moved toward each of the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b> (toward the process chamber <b>203</b> or the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b>) to selectively close the openings.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">More specifically, the gate <b>205</b> allows the process chamber <b>203</b> on the right side of the figure to communicate with the valve chamber <b>209</b>, and the gate <b>206</b> allows the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> on the left side of the figure to communicate with the valve chamber <b>209</b>. In this embodiment, the sample subjected to processing is a substrate such as a semiconductor wafer of a generally circular shape. The gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b> are shaped like a generally rectangular parallelepiped having a horizontally elongated cross section in conformity with the substrate, and their openings are located at a generally equal height in the vertical direction (top-bottom direction in the figure). Therefore, when the valve <b>210</b> is retracted to the lower portion of the valve chamber <b>209</b>, a sample mounted on the transfer robot <b>108</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) that has passed through one gate can enter and pass through the other gate without any significant change of the transfer path of the transfer robot <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The valve <b>210</b>, which closes/opens the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b>, has faces opposite to the openings of the gates, each face contacting the wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> where the associated opening is opened, when the valve <b>210</b> is raised to a height where it covers the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b>. Each of the faces is also provided with a sealing member such as an O-ring that can hermetically seal the associated opening. The valve <b>210</b> is coupled to a single shaft <b>211</b> located below so that the valve <b>210</b> is fixed in position. As the shaft <b>211</b> swings, the valve <b>210</b> selectively closes one of the gates. That is, the operation of the valve <b>210</b> of this embodiment allows one gate to be closed and the other gate to be opened at the same time.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">On top of the gate vessel <b>202</b> is located a top lid <b>214</b> that covers the top of, and can hermetically seal from outside, the valve chamber <b>209</b>. When the valve chamber <b>209</b> is opened to the atmosphere, the top lid <b>214</b> can be opened so that the inside of the valve chamber <b>209</b> communicates with outside. This configuration allows a user to access the inside of the valve chamber or the valve <b>210</b> for work of maintenance, inspection, and component replacement as needed.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the lower portion of the gate unit <b>110</b> is located a gate valve section <b>208</b> that includes the valve <b>210</b>, the shaft <b>211</b>, and a drive mechanism that is coupled to and drives the shaft <b>211</b>. The gate valve section <b>208</b> has a casing <b>212</b> that contains the drive mechanism inside. In the casing <b>212</b> are located a plurality of swing cylinders <b>213</b><i>a</i>, <b>213</b><i>b </i>for swinging the shaft <b>211</b> about a predetermined pivot <b>207</b> to move the valve <b>210</b> toward the gate <b>205</b> or gate <b>206</b>, thereby pressing the valve <b>210</b> against the wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Each of the two swing cylinders <b>213</b><i>a</i>, <b>213</b><i>b </i>is operable to push out a piston toward the gate <b>206</b> or <b>205</b> to press the piston against one end at the bottom of the shaft <b>211</b>, thereby rotating the shaft <b>211</b> and the valve <b>210</b> attached to the other end thereof toward the gate <b>205</b> or gate <b>206</b> about the pivot <b>207</b>. In particular, in this embodiment, the two swing cylinders <b>213</b><i>a</i>, <b>213</b><i>b </i>are located opposite to each other, and the spots on the shaft <b>211</b> pressed by the pistons-are located generally opposite to each other across the central axis of the shaft <b>211</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the configuration of the gate valve section is described in more detail. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a vertical cross section illustrating the configuration of the gate valve section shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is a vertical cross section as viewed laterally in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>. As described above, the gate valve section <b>208</b> includes the casing <b>212</b> that houses the drive section for the shaft <b>211</b>, the shaft <b>211</b>, and the valve <b>210</b> coupled thereto.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The gate valve section <b>208</b> includes, on both sides of the shaft <b>211</b> horizontally in the figure, drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>for vertically moving the shaft <b>211</b>. The drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>include drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b </i>inside, respectively, so that the axis of the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b </i>is generally parallel to the axis of the shaft <b>211</b>. As the pressure in the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>varies, the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b </i>are moved along the axis of the shaft <b>211</b>, respectively. The drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>are attached to the lower face of the flange <b>302</b>, the top end thereof being in contact with the gate vessel <b>202</b>, and constitute the upper portion of the gate valve section <b>208</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The casing <b>212</b> is attached to the outer wall of the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b</i>. The casing <b>212</b> has an inner space where the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b </i>are moved with the motion of the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Hence, in this embodiment, the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b </i>extend downward, or in the direction opposite to the valve <b>201</b>, for the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b</i>, respectively. That is, the top end of the drive shafts is coupled to the associated piston inside the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b</i>, and the bottom end is coupled to the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> of the shaft <b>211</b> via a coupling beam <b>204</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The shaft <b>211</b> in this embodiment is divided into an upper shaft <b>306</b> and a lower shaft <b>307</b>. The upper shaft <b>306</b> is coupled to the valve <b>210</b>, and the lower shaft <b>307</b> is coupled to the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b </i>and the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>via the coupling beam <b>304</b>. There is a coupling section <b>308</b> between the upper and lower shafts <b>306</b>, <b>307</b>, both of which are moved vertically as the shaft <b>211</b> with the motion of the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>and the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The coupling section <b>308</b> between the upper shaft <b>306</b> and the lower shaft <b>307</b> has a curved surface portion of a predetermined spherical shape recessed on the end face of one shaft, and a ball placed between the inside of this curved surface and the end of the other shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The upper shaft <b>306</b> is subjected to pressing force caused by the above-described motion of the swing cylinders <b>213</b><i>a</i>, <b>213</b><i>b </i>to swing about the pivot <b>207</b>. Therefore, at the coupling section <b>308</b>, the end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> slightly slides relative to the lower shaft <b>307</b> coupled via the coupling beam to the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>connected to the flange <b>302</b>. To facilitate this sliding movement, this embodiment includes the coupling section <b>308</b> having the above configuration of a curved surface and a ball.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">More specifically, the pressing force transmitted through the shaft due to the motion of the pistons in the swing cylinders <b>213</b><i>a</i>, <b>213</b><i>b </i>allows the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> to smoothly slide on the top end of the lower shaft <b>307</b> by slipping or rolling on the surface of the ball placed between the curved surface of the spherically recessed shape formed at the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> and the top end of the lower shaft <b>307</b>. Thus the upper shaft <b>306</b> can swing about the pivot <b>207</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The upper shaft <b>307</b> is fixed at an intermediate height on its vertically extending cylinder portion of a generally cylindrical shape by swaging the surface of the cylinder portion with a mechanical lock <b>310</b>. The mechanical lock <b>310</b> is surrounded by a cupped flange <b>311</b> having a bottom portion connected thereto and a sidewall portion located around the upper shaft <b>306</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">At the top end of the outer sidewall of the cupped flange <b>311</b> on the side opposite to the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>on the left and right of the shaft <b>211</b> are located pivots <b>312</b><i>a</i>, <b>312</b><i>b </i>of a generally cylindrical shape, which are attached to the side face of the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b</i>, respectively. The pivots <b>312</b><i>a</i>, <b>312</b><i>b </i>are engaged into and supported by grooves <b>305</b><i>a</i>, <b>305</b><i>b </i>formed vertically on the face of the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>opposite to the upper shaft <b>306</b>. Therefore, the cylindrical pivots <b>312</b><i>a</i>, <b>312</b><i>b </i>are capable of vertical movement and rotation in the grooves <b>305</b><i>a</i>, <b>305</b><i>b</i>, or the cupped flange <b>311</b> is capable of vertical movement and rotation relative to the pivots <b>312</b><i>a</i>, <b>312</b><i>b </i>fixed in position to and supported by the grooves <b>305</b><i>a</i>, <b>305</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As described above, the mechanical lock <b>310</b> is connected to the cupped flange <b>311</b> at the bottom thereof, and coupled and fixed in position to the upper shaft <b>306</b>. Directly above the mechanical lock <b>310</b> is located a vacuum seal <b>313</b> having sealing material for hermetically sealing the surface of the cylindrical shape of the upper shaft <b>306</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Furthermore, a bellows <b>314</b> extensible in the axial direction of the upper shaft <b>306</b> is connected to the top of the vacuum seal <b>313</b> for hermetic sealing between inside and outside. The bellows <b>314</b> surrounds the cylindrical sidewall of the upper shaft <b>306</b> above the vacuum seal <b>313</b>. The top end of the bellows <b>314</b> is connected to the lower face of the flange <b>302</b> to seal between the inside and outside of the bellows <b>314</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In this embodiment, the bellows <b>314</b> is made of metal. Its bottom end is connected to the vacuum seal <b>313</b>, so that hermetic sealing is made between the inside and outside of the bellows <b>314</b>. The valve chamber <b>209</b> and the inside of the bellows <b>314</b> communicating with each other via a gap between the flange <b>302</b> and the surface of the upper shaft <b>306</b> are thus in a vacuum condition at a high level. On the other hand, the inside of the gate valve section <b>208</b> outside the bellows <b>314</b> is under ambient pressure, which causes force based on the large difference of pressure to be acted on both of them. Upward motion of the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b </i>causes the upper shaft <b>306</b> constituting the shaft <b>211</b> to also move upward, and in turn the vacuum seal <b>313</b> connected and coupled thereto moves upward. As a result, the bellows <b>314</b> connected to the vacuum seal <b>313</b> and located above is compressed against the flange <b>302</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">When the upper shaft <b>306</b> is moved upward and reaches at a position where the valve <b>210</b> coupled thereto covers the openings of the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b>, the motion of the drive pistons <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>is stopped and the upward motion of the shaft <b>306</b> is also stopped. From this state, one of the swing cylinders <b>213</b><i>a</i>, <b>213</b><i>b </i>is driven so that the upper shaft <b>306</b> is swung about the pivot <b>207</b>, that is, the cylindrical pivot <b>312</b>. In this situation, the pivot <b>207</b> or pivot <b>312</b> is in the vicinity of the flange <b>302</b>. The shaft <b>211</b> (upper shaft <b>306</b>) can be rotated in this situation to reduce the gap between the upper shaft <b>306</b> and the flange <b>302</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">It is noted that in this embodiment, a spring <b>315</b> is placed in the vicinity of the location where the shafts of the swing cylinders <b>213</b><i>a</i>, <b>213</b><i>b </i>are pressed against the upper shaft <b>306</b>. The spring <b>315</b> is an elastic body for biasing the upper shaft <b>306</b> against the displacement due to the rotation or swing thereof. This applies force to the swung and slid upper shaft <b>306</b> to move it back opposite to its displacement when the pressing force of the piston of the swing cylinder <b>213</b><i>a </i>or <b>213</b><i>b </i>pressed against the upper shaft <b>306</b> is weakened or removed. While the spring <b>315</b> is placed only in the direction toward one gate in the figure, another spring is preferably attached in the other direction.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the operation of the gate valve section <b>208</b> in the gate unit <b>110</b> is described in detail. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a vertical cross section illustrating the operation of the gate valve of the vacuum processing apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> is a vertical cross section illustrating the state in which the valve is raised, where the valve closes neither left nor right gate. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> is a vertical cross section illustrating the state in which the raised valve closes the gate on the vacuum vessel side.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Referring initially to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>, the operation of closing the gate <b>205</b> on the process chamber <b>203</b> side is described. After this operation, the process chamber <b>203</b> is sealed from the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> and the valve chamber <b>209</b> by the valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>of the valve <b>210</b> facing the gate <b>205</b> on the process chamber side, and a sample mounted on the sample stage in the process chamber <b>203</b> is processed. Reaction products generated in this process, plasma, and gas are prevented from migrating to the side of vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> and the valve chamber <b>209</b> via the gate <b>205</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">First, the valve <b>210</b> is located below the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The valve <b>210</b> is then raised to a position where it can face and cover the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b>. To this end, the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>are operated to adjust their inner gas pressure and move the pistons in the cylinders, there by moving upward the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b </i>connected to the pistons. The lower shaft <b>307</b> coupled to the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b </i>via the coupling beam <b>304</b> coupled to the bottom end of the drive shafts <b>303</b><i>a</i>, <b>303</b><i>b</i>, and the upper shaft <b>306</b> coupled thereto via the coupling section <b>308</b> are moved upward. In this way, the valve <b>210</b> coupled to the top end of the shaft <b>211</b> is raised to a predetermined height where the valve <b>210</b> can cover the gates as described above, and maintained at this height.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">As the upper shaft <b>306</b> is raised, the mechanical lock <b>310</b> connected to the outer periphery of the upper shaft <b>306</b> and the vacuum seal <b>313</b> connected to the top of the upper shaft <b>306</b> are also raised. As the vacuum seal <b>313</b> is raised, the bellows <b>314</b> connected between the vacuum seal <b>313</b> and the overlying flange <b>302</b>, with the connection being sealed, are compressed.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">In addition, the flange <b>311</b> connected to the outer periphery of the mechanical lock <b>310</b> and the pivots <b>312</b><i>a</i>, <b>312</b><i>b </i>connected to the flange <b>311</b> are also raised. In particular, the pivots <b>312</b><i>a</i>, <b>312</b><i>b </i>are raised inside and along the associated engaging grooves <b>305</b><i>a</i>, <b>305</b><i>b </i>formed on the side face of the drive cylinders <b>301</b><i>a</i>, <b>301</b><i>b</i>. When the valve <b>210</b> reaches a predetermined height where it can cover the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b>, the pivots <b>312</b><i>a</i>, <b>312</b><i>b </i>reach immediately below the flange <b>302</b>. That is, the grooves <b>305</b><i>a</i>, <b>305</b><i>b</i>, in which the pivots <b>312</b><i>a</i>, <b>312</b><i>b </i>are moved, reach immediately below the flange <b>302</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">When the valve <b>210</b> is raised to a height where it can cover the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>and the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>are separated from the openings of the gates <b>205</b>, <b>206</b> by minute gaps. In this state, neither gate is in contact with, or closed by, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>or the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b</i>. Subsequently, the upper shaft <b>306</b> is swung to move one end thereof toward one of the gates, thereby moving the valve <b>210</b> coupled to the end toward the one gate so that the valve <b>210</b> covers the opening of the gate with pressure. At this time, the valve <b>210</b> moves away from the other gate. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> shows this state.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> shows the state in which the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>of the valve <b>210</b> is pressed against the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> having the opening of the process chamber gate <b>205</b> so that the opening is closed. That is, the upper shaft <b>306</b> is rotated or swung about the pivot <b>312</b> in the clockwise direction in the figure, thereby being moved toward and pressed against the gate <b>205</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">In this situation, first, out of the swing cylinders <b>213</b><i>a</i>, <b>213</b><i>b </i>with the pistons or shafts driven thereby located opposite to each other across the upper shaft <b>306</b> toward the gates at the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b>, the swing cylinder <b>213</b><i>a </i>located on the process chamber <b>203</b> side (with its piston or shaft directed to the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> on the opposite side) is driven. This driving allows the piston or shaft located in the swing cylinder <b>213</b><i>a </i>and coupled thereto to be pushed out toward the upper shaft <b>306</b>, and pressed against a flat portion provided on the process chamber side of the cylindrical portion at the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b>. As a result, the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> is slid at the coupling section <b>308</b> toward the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> side, the opposite side of the process chamber <b>203</b>, relative to the lower shaft <b>307</b>, and rotated about the pivot <b>312</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">With this motion, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>of the valve <b>210</b> attached to the top end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> is moved toward the process chamber gate <b>205</b>, and pressed against the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> around the opening of the gate <b>205</b>. On the face of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>in contact with the wall is placed sealing means such as an O-ring. This O-ring, for example, is pressed against the wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> and deformed with surrounding the outer periphery of the opening of the gate <b>205</b>, thereby sealing the opening and the inside of the gate <b>205</b> having the opening from the inside of the valve chamber <b>209</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Next, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is used to describe the state in which the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> is closed and sealed from the valve chamber <b>209</b> by the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b</i>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a vertical cross section illustrating the operation of the gate valve of the vacuum processing apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, and more particularly, an enlarged vertical cross section illustrating the state in which the valve closes the gate on the vacuum transfer chamber side.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">When the opening of the gate <b>206</b> on the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> side is closed, the valve <b>210</b> is moved opposite to the motion shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. First, out of the swing cylinders at the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b>, the swing cylinder <b>213</b><i>b </i>located on the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> side (with its piston or shaft directed to the process chamber <b>203</b> on the opposite side) is driven. This driving allows the piston or shaft located inside the swing cylinder <b>213</b><i>b </i>and coupled thereto to be pushed out toward the upper shaft <b>306</b>, and pressed against a flat portion provided on the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> side of the cylindrical portion at the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b>. As a result, the bottom end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> is slid at the coupling section <b>308</b> toward the process chamber <b>203</b> side, the opposite side of the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b>, relative to the lower shaft <b>307</b>, and rotated about the pivot <b>312</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows the state in which the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>of the valve <b>210</b> is pressed against the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> having the opening of the vacuum transfer chamber gate <b>206</b> so that the opening is closed. That is, the upper shaft <b>306</b> is rotated or swung about the pivot <b>312</b> in the counterclockwise direction in the figure, thereby being moved toward and pressed against the gate <b>206</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">With the motion of the swing cylinder <b>213</b><i>b </i>and the upper shaft <b>306</b>, the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>of the valve <b>210</b> attached to the top end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> is moved toward the vacuum transfer chamber gate <b>206</b>, and pressed against the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> around the opening of the gate <b>206</b>. As with the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a</i>, on the face of the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>in contact with the wall is placed sealing means such as an O-ring. This O-ring, for example, is pressed against the wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> and deformed with surrounding the outer periphery of the opening of the gate <b>206</b>, thereby sealing the opening and the inside of the gate <b>206</b> having the opening from the inside of the valve chamber <b>209</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">In this situation, the valve chamber <b>209</b> is in communication with the process chamber <b>203</b> via the gate <b>205</b>. When one of the chambers is opened to the atmosphere and its pressure is set equal to ambient pressure, the other is also allowed to have the same pressure. For example, the process chamber <b>203</b> may be allowed to have atmospheric pressure for component replacement, maintenance, and other services in the process chamber <b>203</b> of the vacuum processing unit <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">In this case, according to this embodiment, the gate <b>206</b> on the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> side is closed by the valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>so that the process chamber <b>203</b> can be opened to the atmosphere while the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> has a reduced pressure and is maintained at vacuum. There is no need to open the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> to the atmosphere. While the vacuum processing unit <b>104</b> (vacuum vessel <b>201</b>) is serviced, other processing units and load lock chambers connected to the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> and the vacuum transfer vessel <b>103</b> can be used to process samples. Therefore, the operating rate of the apparatus and working efficiency are increased, and thereby the sample throughput is enhanced.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">In addition, when the process chamber <b>203</b> is opened to the atmosphere, the valve chamber <b>209</b> is also opened to the atmosphere. An operator can access and work on the valve <b>210</b> and the inside of the valve chamber <b>209</b>. Therefore, the gate unit <b>110</b> can be serviced concurrently with services on the vacuum processing unit <b>104</b> side.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, operations for attaching/detaching the valve <b>210</b> of the gate unit <b>110</b> are described. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a vertical cross section illustrating, in the upper portion, the detached state of the valve <b>210</b> of the gate valve of the vacuum processing apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">In this embodiment, service for the valve <b>210</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> begins with the state shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. In this embodiment, the valve <b>210</b> is detachably configured so that it can be divided into the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>and the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b</i>. Furthermore, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is configured so that an operator can work for attachment/detachment while the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>closes and seals the gate <b>206</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, as with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, when the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>of the valve <b>210</b> is pressed against the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> on the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> side, that is, when the process chamber <b>203</b> is in communication with the valve chamber <b>209</b>, both of them are opened to the atmosphere and the pressure thereof is set approximately to atmospheric pressure. Subsequently, bolts <b>601</b><i>a</i>, <b>601</b><i>b </i>fastening the top lid <b>214</b> from above are detached, and then the top lid <b>214</b> located on top of the gate vessel <b>202</b> of the gate unit <b>110</b> is detached, thereby opening the valve chamber <b>209</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">At this time, the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>is fixed in position on the opening of the gate <b>206</b> by application of pressing force from the swing cylinder <b>213</b><i>b </i>via the upper shaft <b>306</b> toward the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> side in the valve chamber <b>209</b>, and pressing force of gas pressure due to the pressure difference between the pressure in the vacuum transfer chamber <b>204</b> and the pressure in the valve chamber <b>209</b>, which is now approximately atmospheric pressure. In this situation, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>can be detached.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">In this respect, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is coupled to the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>on top thereof. As viewed in the cross section at the coupling portion, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>has a flange portion of an inverted L-shape, and is coupled to the valve <b>210</b> or the top end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> with a bolt <b>602</b> inserted in a hole passing through the flange portion from above. The flange portion of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>has a shape that does not contact the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> when the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is attached to the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>to facilitate detachment and attachment of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a</i>. According to this configuration, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>can be pulled out upward with keeping the gap from the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> after the bolt <b>602</b> attaching and coupling the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>to the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>is detached.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">The process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>does not have any rotation mechanism for rotatably adapting its contact face to the wall around the opening of the gate <b>205</b> depending on the angle between the axis of the shaft <b>211</b> and the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b>. The valve body of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is attached to the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>or the top end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> and coupled to the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>with the bolt. Therefore, the configuration can be simplified as compared to having any rotation mechanism. Moreover, this configuration facilitates work from above, and reduces the possibility that the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>and the valve body thereof contact the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b>, and generation of foreign particles or dust. Furthermore, the distance between the valve <b>210</b> and the inner wall of the valve chamber <b>209</b> can be reduced to make them closer to each other. This can reduce the volume and footprint of the gate unit <b>110</b><i>a</i>, which leads to reduction of the footprint of the entire vacuum processing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">When the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is taken out, the O-ring or other sealing member and the valve body of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>for sealing the opening of the process chamber gate <b>205</b>, and the main body of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a</i>, may be subjected to maintenance, inspection, and replacement. The process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is attached to the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>or the top end of the upper shaft <b>306</b> by another attaching operation in the valve chamber <b>209</b>. In order to define the position of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>and the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>relative to each other to enhance sealing performance of the valve <b>210</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, positioning pins <b>603</b> are located on the upper face of the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b</i>, and on the corresponding lower face of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>are formed positioning holes <b>604</b> in which the positioning pins <b>603</b> are engaged. The valves <b>210</b><i>a</i>, <b>210</b><i>b </i>are coupled to each other with precision by matching the positioning pins <b>603</b> with the positioning holes <b>604</b>. This reduces leaks due to loss of sealing performance when the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is pressed against the gate <b>205</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">After the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is attached to the top end of the upper shaft <b>306</b>, the top lid <b>214</b> of the valve chamber <b>209</b> or gate section <b>202</b> is mounted on the gate section <b>202</b> and fastened with the bolts <b>601</b><i>a</i>, <b>601</b><i>b </i>so that the valve chamber <b>209</b> is sealed from outside. In this way, the top lid <b>214</b> is attached to the gate section.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">Next, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is used to describe the configuration of coupling between the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>and the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>constituting the valve <b>210</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a perspective view illustrating the configuration of the valve <b>210</b> of the gate valve of the vacuum processing apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">As shown in this figure, in this embodiment, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>constituting the valve <b>210</b> is provided with an O-ring <b>702</b> on its seal face <b>701</b> for closing the periphery of the opening of the associated gate <b>205</b>. The process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is attached to the top of the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>from above in the figure and coupled thereto with bolts <b>602</b><i>a</i>, <b>602</b><i>b</i>. In particular, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref>, the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>has a horizontally elongated, generally rectangular parallelepiped shape for closing the opening of the gate adapted to the shape of a transferred sample such as a semiconductor wafer subjected to processing. On top of the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>are a plurality of steps <b>710</b>, <b>711</b>, <b>712</b>. The lower face of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is formed to contact these steps in an adapted manner. The positioning pins <b>603</b> located on the step <b>710</b> of these steps are engaged in the positioning holes <b>604</b> located on the lower face of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>so that the valves are attached to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">The vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>is connected to a coupling flange <b>713</b> located on top of the upper shaft <b>306</b> via positioning protrusions <b>705</b> formed on the step <b>704</b> of the coupling flange <b>713</b> and positioning holes <b>706</b> of the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>at a recessed portion <b>709</b> having a flat surface for connection on the opposite side of the seal face. The coupling flange <b>713</b> is fastened to the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>with bolts <b>707</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">According to this configuration, the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is configured to be attached to and detached from the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>while the vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>closes the opening of the gate <b>206</b>. The vacuum transfer chamber valve <b>210</b><i>b </i>is coupled to the shaft <b>211</b> (<b>306</b>) at a planar flange portion, which enables uniform application of large force in closing the opening of the gate <b>205</b>, and thus its sealing performance for a valve is enhanced. The sealing performance of the process chamber valve <b>210</b><i>a </i>is enhanced as well.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A vacuum processing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a sealed gate located between two vacuum vessels for allowing the vacuum vessels to communicate with each other and a sample subjected to processing to be transferred from one of the vacuum vessels to the other therethrough; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate valve located on a path of the gate, the gate valve including a first valve body facing a first opening of the gate on one vacuum vessel side, a second valve body facing a second opening of the gate on the other vacuum vessel side, and a shaft to which the valve bodies are coupled at one end thereof, the gate valve selectively opening and closing each of the openings,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the gate valve including an axial drive section coupled to the other end of the shaft for moving the shaft in the axial direction thereof, and a rotary drive section located between the one end and the other end of the shaft for rotating the shaft about a predetermined pivot crossing the axis of the shaft,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the rotating force is transmitted to a spot on the shaft between the pivot and the one end or the other end along the axis of the shaft, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>further comprising a valve chamber located in the gate, the first valve body and the second valve body being moved inside the valve chamber with motion of the shaft, wherein the first valve body is attached and coupled to the second valve body and the first valve body can be attached to and detached from the second valve body while the second valve body closes the facing opening, the shaft has a first shaft and a second shaft divided between the other end of the shaft and the axial drive section and coupled to each other, the first shaft subjected to force from the rotary drive section can slide and rotate relative to the second shaft at a coupling section between the first and second shafts, and the sample is processed in the one vacuum vessel with which the first opening communicates.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A vacuum processing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a sealed gate located between two vacuum vessels for allowing the vacuum vessels to communicate with each other and a sample subjected to processing to be transferred from one of the vacuum vessels to the other therethrough; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate valve located on a path of the gate, the gate valve including a first valve body facing a first opening of the gate on one vacuum vessel side, a second valve body facing a second opening of the gate on the other vacuum vessel side, and a shaft to which the valve bodies are coupled at one end thereof, the gate valve selectively opening and closing each of the openings,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the gate valve including an axial drive section coupled to the other end of the shaft for moving the shaft in the axial direction thereof, and a rotary drive section located between the one end and the other end of the shaft for rotating the shaft about a predetermined pivot crossing the axis of the shaft,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the rotating force is transmitted to a spot on the shaft between the pivot and the one end or the other end along the axis of the shaft, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the shaft has a first shaft and a second shaft divided between the other end of the shaft and the axial drive section and coupled to each other, and the first shaft subjected to force from the rotary drive section can slide and rotate relative to the second shaft at a coupling section between the first and second shafts.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A vacuum processing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a sealed gate located between two vacuum vessels for allowing the vacuum vessels to communicate with each other and a sample subjected to processing to be transferred from one of the vacuum vessels to the other therethrough; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate valve located on a path of the gate, the gate valve including a first valve body facing a first opening of the gate on one vacuum vessel side, a second valve body facing a second opening of the gate on the other vacuum vessel side, and a shaft to which the valve bodies are coupled at one end thereof, the gate valve selectively opening and closing each of the openings,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the gate valve including an axial drive section coupled to the other end of the shaft for moving the shaft in the axial direction thereof, and a rotary drive section located between the one end and the other end of the shaft for rotating the shaft about a predetermined pivot crossing the axis of the shaft,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the rotating force is transmitted to a spot on the shaft between the pivot and the one end or the other end along the axis of the shaft, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the shaft has a first shaft and a second shaft divided between the other end of the shaft and the axial drive section and coupled to each other, and the first shaft subjected to force from the rotary drive section can slide and rotate relative to the second shaft at a coupling section between the first and second shafts, and further comprising a bellows attached around the first shaft outside the valve chamber for sealing between the valve chamber and the periphery of the shaft while the gate valve is attached to the vessel having the valve chamber, the bellows being compressed with motion of the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A vacuum processing apparatus with at least two vacuum vessels, comprising:
<claim-text>a sealed gate located between two vacuum vessels for allowing the vacuum vessels to communicate with each other and a sample subjected to processing to be transferred from one of the vacuum vessels to the other therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate valve located on a path of the gate, the gate valve including a first valve body facing a first opening of the gate on one vacuum vessel side, a second valve body facing a second opening of the gate on the other vacuum vessel side, and a shaft to which the valve bodies are coupled at one end thereof, the gate valve selectively opening and closing air-tightly each of the openings by the valve bodies according to a movement of the shaft; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driving device which drives the shaft to push the first valve body or the second valve body toward the first opening or the second opening, respectively,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first valve body comprises a plane portion disposed at an opposite side of a closing side and is coupled to the shaft by the plane portion and is connected to another plane portion of a member disposed at the one end of the shaft, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second valve body is coupled with respect to the first valve body so that the second valve body can be attached to and detached from the first valve body.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the second valve body is coupled to the first valve body so that the second valve body can be attached to and detached from the first valve body while the first valve body closes the first opening air-tightly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein, while the first valve body closes the first opening air-tightly, one chamber inside the one of the vacuum vessels can be maintained at its pressure different from that of another chamber inside the other vacuum vessel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the second valve body is coupled to the first valve body so that the second valve body can be attached to and detached from the first valve body while the first valve body closes the first opening air-tightly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the second valve body is directly coupled to the first valve body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said another plane portion is a coupling flange of said member, at the one end of the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A vacuum processing apparatus with at least two vacuum vessels, comprising:
<claim-text>a sealed gate located between two vacuum vessels for allowing the vacuum vessels to communicate with each other and a sample subjected to processing to be transferred from one of the vacuum vessels to the other therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate valve located on a path of the gate, the gate valve including a first valve body facing a first opening of the gate on one vacuum vessel side, a second valve body facing a second opening of the gate on the other vacuum vessel side, and a shaft to which the valve bodies are coupled at one end thereof, the gate valve selectively opening and closing air-tightly each of the openings by the valve bodies according to a movement of the shaft; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driving device which drives the shaft to push the first valve body or the second valve body toward the first opening or the second opening, respectively,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first valve body comprises a plane portion disposed at an opposite side of a closing side and is coupled to the shaft by the plane portion and is connected to another plane portion disposed on the one end portion of the shaft, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second valve body is coupled with respect to the first valve body and the second valve body can be attached to and detached from the first valve body.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the second valve body is coupled to the first valve body so that the second valve body can be attached to and detached from the first valve body while the first valve body closes the first opening air-tightly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein, while the first valve body closes the first opening air-tightly, one chamber inside the one of the vacuum vessels can be maintained at its pressure different from that of another chamber inside the other vacuum vessel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein, the second valve body is coupled to the first valve body so that the second valve body can be attached to and detached from the first valve body while the first valve body closes the first opening air-tightly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the second valve body is directly coupled to the first valve body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A vacuum processing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein, said another plane portion is a coupling flange at the one end of the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
