<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298097-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298097</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11245947</doc-number>
<date>20051006</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>CN</country>
<doc-number>2005 1 0102863</doc-number>
<date>20050913</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315291</main-classification>
<further-classification>315307</further-classification>
<further-classification>315224</further-classification>
<further-classification>315274</further-classification>
<further-classification>315276</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Driver system and method with multi-function protection for cold-cathode fluorescent lamp and external-electrode fluorescent lamp</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5365152</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ozawa et al.</name>
<date>19941100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>315291</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5384518</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kido et al.</name>
<date>19950100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>315225</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0024896</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Man-Ho</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>363 2104</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0038513</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Henry</name>
<date>20060200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>315291</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315291</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315307</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315297</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315308</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315312</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315324</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315323</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315322</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315224</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315225</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315274</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315276</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315279</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315287</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070057643</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070315</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zhang</last-name>
<first-name>Changshan</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ye</last-name>
<first-name>Jun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fang</last-name>
<first-name>Lieyi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Townsend and Townsend and Crew LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>On-Bright Electronics (Shanghai) Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Vo</last-name>
<first-name>Tuyet</first-name>
<department>2821</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">System and method for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. The system includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="141.05mm" wi="174.33mm" file="US07298097-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="80.18mm" wi="151.64mm" file="US07298097-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="86.70mm" wi="88.05mm" file="US07298097-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="154.94mm" wi="173.65mm" file="US07298097-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="86.36mm" wi="136.48mm" file="US07298097-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="78.91mm" wi="96.27mm" file="US07298097-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="77.64mm" wi="118.79mm" file="US07298097-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="114.55mm" wi="127.93mm" file="US07298097-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCES TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority to Chinese Patent Application No.200510102863.0, filed Sep. 13, 2005, commonly assigned, incorporated by reference herein for all purposes.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT AS TO RIGHTS TO INVENTIONS MADE UNDER FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR DEVELOPMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">NOT APPLICABLE</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">REFERENCE TO A “SEQUENCE LISTING,” A TABLE, OR A COMPUTER PROGRAM LISTING APPENDIX SUBMITTED ON A COMPACT DISK.</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">NOT APPLICABLE</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The present invention is directed to integrated circuits. More particularly, the invention provides a system and method with multi-function protection. Merely by way of example, the invention has been applied to driving one or more cold-cathode fluorescent lamps, and/or one or more external-electrode fluorescent lamps. But it would be recognized that the invention has a much broader range of applicability.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The cold-cathode fluorescent lamp (CCFL) and external-electrode fluorescent lamp (EEFL) have been widely used to provide backlight for a liquid crystal display (LCD) module. The CCFL and EEFL often each require a high alternate current (AC) voltage such as 2 kV for ignition and normal operation. Such a high AC voltage can be provided by a CCFL driver system or an EEFL driver system. The CCFL driver system and the EEFL driver system each receive a low direct current (DC) voltage and convert the low DC voltage to the high AC voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a simplified conventional driver system for CCFL and/or EEFL. The driver system <b>100</b> includes a control subsystem <b>110</b> and an AC power supply subsystem <b>120</b>. The control subsystem <b>110</b> receives a power supply voltage V<sub>DDA </sub>and certain control signals. The control signals include an enabling (ENA) signal and a dimming (DIM) signal. In response, the control subsystem <b>110</b> outputs gate drive signals to the AC power supply subsystem <b>120</b>. The AC power supply subsystem <b>120</b> includes MOSFET transistors and power transformers, and receives a low DC voltage V<sub>IN</sub>. The MOSFET transistors convert the low DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>to a low AC voltage in response to the gate drive signals. The low AC voltage is boosted to a high AC voltage V<sub>OUT </sub>by the power transformers, and the high AC voltage V<sub>OUT </sub>is sent to drive a system <b>190</b>. The system <b>190</b> includes CCFLs and/or EEFLs. The system <b>190</b> provides a current and voltage feedback to the control subsystem <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">As discussed above, the power transformers can boost the AC voltage. The increase in AC voltage is often accomplished by a high turn ratio between the secondary winding and the primary winding. The secondary winding usually is formed by a wire having a small diameter such as 0.05 mm. The wire can easily be damaged by bending in the manufacturing process. For example, a breakpoint may exist at the winding terminal that is connected to pins in the transformer bobbin. If the gap at the breakpoint is small, the high AC voltage can jump through the gap by arcing and still drive the system <b>190</b> including CCFLs and/or EEFLs. But the arcing process can produce a large amount of heat and even a visible fire. Under these conditions, the driver system <b>100</b> should be turned off to prevent any accidents.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a simplified conventional system for detecting breakpoint in transformer secondary winding. The secondary winding of a transformer T<b>1</b> includes pins <b>5</b> and <b>6</b>. The pin <b>6</b> is biased to the low DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>that is different from the ground voltage. Additionally, the DC voltage at the pin <b>5</b> is received by a high impedance voltage divider. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the voltage divider includes resistors R<b>1</b> and R<b>2</b> and outputs a voltage V<sub>DIV </sub>to a transistor Q<sub>1</sub>. If no breakpoint exists in the secondary winding, the voltage V<sub>DIV </sub>would be equal to a fraction of V<sub>IN</sub>. As a result, the transistor Q<sub>1 </sub>is turned on, and the control subsystem <b>110</b> is enabled. If a breakpoint exists in the secondary winding, the voltage V<sub>DIV </sub>would be equal to zero. As a result, the transistor Q<sub>1 </sub>is turned off, and the control subsystem <b>110</b> is disabled. The driver system <b>100</b> for CCFL and/or EEFL is thus protected. But the system as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> often cannot effectively detect breakpoints for multiple transformers.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Hence it is highly desirable to improve protection techniques for CCFL driver system and EEFL driver system.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention is directed to integrated circuits. More particularly, the invention provides a system and method with multi-function protection. Merely by way of example, the invention has been applied to driving one or more cold-cathode fluorescent lamps, and/or one or more external-electrode fluorescent lamps. But it would be recognized that the invention has a much broader range of applicability.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to one embodiment of the present invention, a system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is provided. The system includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to another embodiment, a system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is higher than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. The power supply subsystem includes a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding. If the DC input voltage is lower than a first predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. If the DC input voltage is higher than a second predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. If the secondary winding includes a breakpoint, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. The power supply subsystem includes a first resistor, a second resistor, a first capacitor, and a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding. The secondary winding, the first resistor, and the second resistor are in series. The second resistor is located between the first resistor and the secondary winding, and the secondary winding includes a first terminal biased to a ground voltage level. The first resistor includes a second terminal and a third terminal. The second terminal is biased to the DC input voltage, and the third terminal is coupled to the second resistor. The first resistor and the first capacitor are in parallel between the second terminal and the third terminal, and the third terminal is associated with a first detected voltage. The first detected voltage is compared to a first predetermined voltage for determining the one or more control signals.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to yet another embodiment, a method for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes receiving a DC input voltage, determining whether the DC input voltage is lower than a first predetermined threshold or higher than a second predetermined threshold, and generating one or more control signals based on at least information associated with the DC input voltage, the first predetermined threshold, and the second predetermined threshold. Additionally, the method includes receiving the one or more control signals, converting the DC input voltage into an AC output voltage in response to the one or more control signals, and sending the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than the first predetermined threshold, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero. If the DC input voltage is higher than the second predetermined threshold, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is higher than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. The power supply subsystem includes a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding. If the DC input voltage is lower than a first predetermined threshold, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. If the DC input voltage is higher than a second predetermined threshold, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. If the secondary winding includes a breakpoint, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. The power supply subsystem includes a first resistor, a second resistor, a first capacitor, and a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding. The secondary winding, the first resistor, and the second resistor are in series. The second resistor is located between the first resistor and the secondary winding, and the secondary winding includes a first terminal biased to a ground voltage level. The first resistor includes a second terminal and a third terminal. The second terminal is biased to the DC input voltage, and the third terminal is coupled to the second resistor. The first resistor and the first capacitor are in parallel between the second terminal and the third terminal. The third terminal is associated with a first detected voltage, and the first detected voltage is compared to a first predetermined voltage for determining the one or more control signals.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">According to yet another embodiment, a method for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes receiving a DC input voltage, determining whether the DC input voltage is lower than a first predetermined threshold or higher than a second predetermined threshold, and generating one or more control signals based on at least information associated with the DC input voltage, the first predetermined threshold, and the second predetermined threshold. Additionally, the method includes receiving the one or more control signals, converting the DC input voltage into an AC output voltage in response to the one or more control signals, and sending the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than the first predetermined threshold, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero. If the DC input voltage is higher than the second predetermined threshold, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Many benefits are achieved by way of the present invention over conventional techniques. For example, some embodiments of the present invention provide a driver system with one or more protection mechanisms. For example, the driver system is protected against under-voltage system power supply, over-voltage system power supply, and/or breaking of transformer secondary winding. In another example, the driver system is used to drive one or more cold-cathode fluorescent lamps and/or one or more external-electrode fluorescent lamp. Certain embodiments of the present invention provide protection against breaking of a secondary winding. The breaking of the secondary winding can cause arcing, which may damage the secondary winding. Arcing often is difficult to detect during the testing process, so it is very important to protect the driver system when the breaking of the secondary winding occurs. Some embodiments of the present invention provide protection against under-voltage system power supply. Such protection is very important because a low DC input voltage can cause current stress to a power MOSFET transistor. Certain embodiments of the present invention provide protection against over-voltage system power supply. Such protection is very important because a high DC input voltage can cause voltage stress between the drain and source of a power MOSFET transistor. Depending upon the embodiment, one or more of these benefits may be achieved. These and other benefits will be described in more detail throughout the present specification and more particularly below.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Various additional objects, features and advantages of the present invention can be more fully appreciated with reference to the detailed description and the accompanying drawings that follow.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a simplified conventional driver system for CCFL and/or EEFL;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a simplified conventional system for detecting breakpoint in transformer secondary winding;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a simplified driver system according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a simplified subsystem for protecting the driver system according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5</figref>, <b>6</b>, and <b>7</b> are simplified diagrams showing a subsystem for protecting the driver system according to another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The present invention is directed to integrated circuits. More particularly, the invention provides a system and method with multi-function protection. Merely by way of example, the invention has been applied to driving one or more cold-cathode fluorescent lamps, and/or one or more external-electrode fluorescent lamps. But it would be recognized that the invention has a much broader range of applicability.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a simplified driver system according to an embodiment of the present invention. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. The driver system <b>300</b> includes a control subsystem <b>310</b> and an AC power supply subsystem <b>320</b>. The control subsystem <b>310</b> includes a comparator <b>430</b>, a control logic component <b>440</b>, and a gate drive component <b>450</b>. The AC power supply subsystem <b>320</b> includes resistors <b>410</b>, <b>420</b>, <b>540</b>, <b>545</b>, <b>550</b>, <b>555</b> and <b>640</b>, transistors <b>510</b>, <b>515</b>, <b>520</b>, <b>525</b> and <b>710</b>, transformers <b>530</b> and <b>535</b>, capacitors <b>560</b>, <b>565</b>, <b>570</b>, <b>575</b> and <b>630</b>, and comparators <b>610</b> and <b>620</b>. Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the system <b>300</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. Depending upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with others replaced. For example, the system <b>300</b> is used to regulate one or more cold-cathode fluorescent lamps and/or external-electrode fluorescent lamps. Further details of these components are found throughout the present specification and more particularly below.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The control subsystem <b>310</b> receives a power supply voltage V<sub>DDA </sub>and certain control signals. For example, the power supply voltage V<sub>DDA </sub>is equal to 5 volts. In another example, the control signals include an enabling (ENA) signal and a dimming (DIM) signal. The control subsystem <b>310</b> outputs gate drive signals <b>312</b> and <b>314</b> to the AC power supply subsystem <b>320</b>. Additionally, the AC power supply subsystem <b>320</b> receives a DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>and generates AC voltages V<sub>OUT1 </sub>and V<sub>OUT2</sub>. For example, the DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>is equal to 12 volts. In another example, the peak-to-peak amplitude for each of the AC voltages V<sub>OUT1 </sub>and V<sub>OUT2 </sub>ranges from several hundred volts to several thousand volts. In yet another example, the AC voltages V<sub>OUT1 </sub>and V<sub>OUT2 </sub>are sent to drive cold-cathode fluorescent lamps and/or external-electrode fluorescent lamps.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a simplified subsystem for protecting the driver system <b>300</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. The subsystem <b>400</b> includes the comparator <b>430</b>, the control logic component <b>440</b>, the gate drive component <b>450</b>, and the resistors <b>410</b> and <b>420</b>. Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the subsystem <b>400</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. Depending upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with others replaced. For example, the subsystem <b>400</b> is used to protect the driver system <b>300</b> for one or more cold-cathode fluorescent lamps and/or one or more external-electrode fluorescent lamps. Further details of these components are found throughout the present specification and more particularly below.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The comparator <b>430</b>, the control logic component <b>440</b>, and the gate drive component <b>450</b> are parts of the control subsystem <b>310</b>. Additionally, the resistors <b>410</b> and <b>420</b> are parts of the AC power supply subsystem <b>320</b>. The resistor <b>410</b> has resistance R<sub>1</sub>, and the resistor <b>420</b> has resistance R<sub>2</sub>. The resistors <b>410</b> and <b>420</b> are connected in series through a node <b>411</b> to form a voltage divider and coupled between the ground voltage and the DC voltage V<sub>IN</sub>. The comparator <b>430</b> includes input terminals <b>431</b> and <b>432</b> and an output terminal <b>433</b>. The input terminal <b>431</b> is biased to a predetermined reference voltage V<sub>REF</sub>, and the input terminal <b>432</b> is biased to a detected voltage V<sub>DET</sub>, which is the voltage potential at the node <b>411</b>. The comparator <b>430</b> compares the reference voltage V<sub>REF </sub>and the detected voltage V<sub>DET</sub>, and in response outputs a comparison signal to the control signal component <b>440</b>. Based on at least the comparison signal, the control logic component <b>440</b> provides a control signal to the gate drive component <b>450</b>, which in response can turn on or off the driver system <b>300</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In one embodiment, if the comparison signal indicates the detected voltage V<sub>DET </sub>is lower than the reference voltage V<sub>REF</sub>, the control signal from the control logic component <b>440</b> instructs the gate drive component <b>450</b> to turn off the driver system <b>300</b>. For example,</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>V</mi>
          <mi>DET</mi>
        </msub>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mfrac>
            <msub>
              <mi>R</mi>
              <mn>2</mn>
            </msub>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
          </mfrac>
          <mo>×</mo>
          <msub>
            <mi>V</mi>
            <mi>IN</mi>
          </msub>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="1.1em" height="1.1ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>1</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mrow>
          <mi>If</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <msub>
            <mi>V</mi>
            <mi>DET</mi>
          </msub>
        </mrow>
        <mo>&lt;</mo>
        <msub>
          <mi>V</mi>
          <mi>REF</mi>
        </msub>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="1.1em" height="1.1ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>2</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>V</mi>
          <mi>IN</mi>
        </msub>
        <mo>&lt;</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
            <msub>
              <mi>R</mi>
              <mn>2</mn>
            </msub>
          </mfrac>
          <mo>×</mo>
          <msub>
            <mi>V</mi>
            <mi>REF</mi>
          </msub>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="1.1em" height="1.1ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>3</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Hence the driver system <b>300</b> is turned off if V<sub>IN </sub>is lower than a threshold voltage that is equal to</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">
<maths id="MATH-US-00002" num="00002">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mrow>
  <mfrac>
    <mrow>
      <msub>
        <mi>R</mi>
        <mn>1</mn>
      </msub>
      <mo>+</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>R</mi>
        <mn>2</mn>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
    <msub>
      <mi>R</mi>
      <mn>2</mn>
    </msub>
  </mfrac>
  <mo>×</mo>
  <mrow>
    <msub>
      <mi>V</mi>
      <mi>REF</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>.</mo>
  </mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
</maths>
<br/>
For example, R<sub>1 </sub>equals 91 kΩ, R<sub>2 </sub>equals 15 kΩ, and V<sub>REF </sub>equals 1.25 volts, so the threshold voltage is equal to about 8.8 volts. If V<sub>IN </sub>is lower than 8.8 volts, the driver system <b>300</b> is turned off.
</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5</figref>, <b>6</b>, and <b>7</b> are simplified diagrams showing a subsystem for protecting the driver system <b>300</b> according to another embodiment of the present invention. These diagrams are merely examples, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. The subsystem <b>500</b> includes the comparators <b>430</b> and <b>610</b>, the control logic component <b>440</b>, the gate drive component <b>450</b>, the resistors <b>540</b>, <b>550</b> and <b>640</b>, the transistors <b>510</b>, <b>520</b> and <b>710</b>, the transformer <b>530</b>, and the capacitors <b>560</b> and <b>630</b>. Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the subsystem <b>500</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. Depending upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with others replaced. For example, the subsystem <b>500</b> is used to protect the driver system <b>300</b> for one or more cold-cathode fluorescent lamps and/or one or more external-electrode fluorescent lamps. Further details of these components are found throughout the present specification and more particularly below.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The comparator <b>430</b>, the control logic component <b>440</b>, and the gate drive component <b>450</b> are parts of the control subsystem <b>310</b>. Additionally, the comparator <b>610</b>, the resistors <b>540</b>, <b>550</b> and <b>640</b>, the transistors <b>510</b>, <b>520</b> and <b>710</b>, the transformer <b>530</b>, and the capacitors <b>560</b> and <b>630</b> are parts of the AC power supply subsystem <b>320</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the transformer <b>530</b> includes a primary winding <b>531</b> and a secondary winding <b>532</b>. The secondary winding <b>532</b> has resistance R<sub>secondary</sub>, the resistor <b>540</b> has resistance R<sub>11</sub>, and the resistor <b>550</b> has resistance R<sub>12</sub>. The resistors <b>540</b> and <b>550</b> and the secondary winding <b>532</b> are connected in series and coupled between the ground voltage and the DC voltage V<sub>IN</sub>. Additionally, the resistor <b>540</b> and the capacitor <b>560</b> are in parallel between nodes <b>541</b> and <b>542</b>. At the node <b>542</b>, the voltage potential is equal to a detected voltage V<sub>1</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In one embodiment, an AC voltage exists at pin <b>7</b> of the transformer <b>531</b>. For example, the AC voltage has a frequency of 50 kHz. The AC voltage is filtered out by the resistors <b>540</b> and <b>550</b> and the capacitor <b>560</b>. For example, the capacitor <b>560</b> provides low impedance to the AC voltage. In another example, the capacitor <b>560</b> has a capacitance value of 27 nF. Accordingly, the AC component can be ignored for the detected voltage V<sub>1</sub>, and the detected voltage V<sub>1 </sub>is determined as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">
<maths id="MATH-US-00003" num="00003">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>V</mi>
          <mn>1</mn>
        </msub>
        <mo>≈</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>12</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mi>secondary</mi>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>11</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>12</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mi>secondary</mi>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
          </mfrac>
          <mo>×</mo>
          <msub>
            <mi>V</mi>
            <mi>IN</mi>
          </msub>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="1.1em" height="1.1ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>4</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the comparator <b>610</b> includes input terminals <b>611</b> and <b>612</b> and an output terminal <b>613</b>. The input terminal <b>611</b> is biased to a predetermined reference voltage V<sub>0</sub>, and the input terminal <b>612</b> is biased to the detected voltage V<sub>1</sub>. The comparator <b>610</b> compares the reference voltage V<sub>0 </sub>and the detected voltage V<sub>1</sub>, and in response generates a comparison signal at the output terminal <b>613</b>. For example, the reference voltage V<sub>0 </sub>is equal to 5 volts. In another example, the comparison signal is at the logic low level if the detected voltage V<sub>1 </sub>is higher than the reference voltage V<sub>0</sub>. In yet another example, the comparison signal <b>614</b> is at the logic high level if the detected voltage V<sub>1 </sub>is lower than the reference voltage V<sub>0</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In another embodiment, the subsystem <b>500</b> includes another comparator <b>620</b>. The comparator <b>620</b> includes input terminals <b>621</b> and <b>622</b> and an output terminal <b>623</b>. The input terminal <b>621</b> is biased to the predetermined reference voltage V<sub>0</sub>, and the input terminal <b>622</b> is biased to another detected voltage V<sub>2</sub>. The comparator <b>620</b> compares the reference voltage V<sub>0 </sub>and the detected voltage V<sub>2</sub>, and in response outputs a comparison signal at the output terminal <b>623</b>. For example, the reference voltage V<sub>0 </sub>is equal to 5 volts. In another example, the comparison signal is at the logic low level if the detected voltage V<sub>1 </sub>is higher than the reference voltage V<sub>0</sub>. In yet another example, the comparison signal is at the logic high level if the detected voltage V<sub>1 </sub>is lower than the reference voltage V<sub>0</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the output terminals <b>613</b> and <b>623</b> are directly connected at a node <b>631</b>. The node <b>631</b> is coupled to a node <b>641</b> through the resistor <b>640</b>, and is coupled to the ground voltage level through the capacitor <b>630</b>. For example, the resistor <b>640</b> has a resistance value of 10 kΩ. In another example, the capacitor <b>630</b> has a capacitance value of 100 pF. At the node <b>631</b>, a signal <b>614</b> is outputted to the transistor <b>710</b>. For example, the signal <b>614</b> is at the logic high level only if both the comparison signals at the output terminals <b>613</b> and <b>623</b> are at the logic high level. In another example, the signal <b>614</b> is at the logic low level if at least one of the comparison signals at the output terminals <b>613</b> and <b>623</b> is at the logic low level.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the signal <b>614</b> is used to turn on or off the transistor <b>710</b>. The transistor <b>701</b> serves as a switch. For example, the transistor <b>710</b> is closed or turned on if the signal <b>614</b> is at the logic low level. Hence, the input terminal <b>432</b> is biased to substantially the ground voltage level, which is lower than the reference voltage V<sub>REF</sub>. In another example, the transistor <b>710</b> is open or turned off if the signal <b>614</b> is at the logic high level. Hence the input terminal <b>432</b> is biased to the voltage at the node <b>411</b> as discussed above for <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The comparator <b>430</b> compares the voltage level at the input terminal <b>432</b> and the reference voltage V<sub>REF </sub>at the input terminal <b>431</b>, and in response outputs the comparison signal to the control signal component <b>440</b>. Based on at least the comparison signal, the control logic component <b>440</b> provides a control signal to the gate drive component <b>450</b>, which in response can turn on or off the driver system <b>300</b>. In one embodiment, if the comparison signal indicates the voltage level at the input terminal <b>432</b> is lower than the reference voltage V<sub>REF</sub>, the control signal from the control logic component <b>440</b> instructs the gate drive component <b>450</b> to turn off the driver system <b>300</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As discussed above, the detected voltage V<sub>1 </sub>can be determined according to Equation 4. In one embodiment,</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">
<maths id="MATH-US-00004" num="00004">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mrow>
          <mi>if</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <msub>
            <mi>V</mi>
            <mn>1</mn>
          </msub>
        </mrow>
        <mo>&lt;</mo>
        <msub>
          <mi>V</mi>
          <mn>0</mn>
        </msub>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="1.1em" height="1.1ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>5</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>V</mi>
          <mi>IN</mi>
        </msub>
        <mo>&gt;</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>11</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>12</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mi>secondary</mi>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>12</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mi>secondary</mi>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
          </mfrac>
          <mo>×</mo>
          <msub>
            <mi>V</mi>
            <mn>0</mn>
          </msub>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="1.1em" height="1.1ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>6</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Hence the comparison signal at the output terminal <b>613</b> is at the logic low level if V<sub>IN </sub>is larger than a threshold voltage that is equal to</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">
<maths id="MATH-US-00005" num="00005">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mrow>
  <mfrac>
    <mrow>
      <msub>
        <mi>R</mi>
        <mn>11</mn>
      </msub>
      <mo>+</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>R</mi>
        <mn>12</mn>
      </msub>
      <mo>+</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>R</mi>
        <mi>secondary</mi>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
      <msub>
        <mi>R</mi>
        <mn>12</mn>
      </msub>
      <mo>+</mo>
      <msub>
        <mi>R</mi>
        <mi>secondary</mi>
      </msub>
    </mrow>
  </mfrac>
  <mo>×</mo>
  <mrow>
    <msub>
      <mi>V</mi>
      <mn>0</mn>
    </msub>
    <mo>.</mo>
  </mrow>
</mrow>
</math>
</maths>
<br/>
For example, R<sub>11 </sub>equals 13 MΩ, R<sub>12 </sub>equals 6.2 MΩ, R<sub>secondary </sub>equals 600 Ω, and V<sub>0 </sub>equals 5 volts, so the threshold voltage is equal to about 15.5 volts. If V<sub>IN </sub>is higher than 15.5 volts, the comparison signal at the output terminal <b>613</b> is at the logic low level. If the comparison signal at the output terminal <b>613</b> is at the logic low level, the signal <b>614</b> is also at the logic low level. Hence, the driver system <b>300</b> is turned off if V<sub>IN </sub>is larger than the threshold voltage.
</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">In another embodiment, the secondary winding <b>532</b> includes one or more breakpoints, so R<sub>secondary </sub>of the secondary winding <b>532</b> becomes very large. Accordingly, the detected voltage V<sub>1 </sub>is substantially equal to the DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">
<maths id="MATH-US-00006" num="00006">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>V</mi>
          <mn>1</mn>
        </msub>
        <mo>≈</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>12</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mi>secondary</mi>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>11</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mn>12</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>R</mi>
                <mi>secondary</mi>
              </msub>
            </mrow>
          </mfrac>
          <mo>×</mo>
          <msub>
            <mi>V</mi>
            <mi>IN</mi>
          </msub>
        </mrow>
        <mo>≈</mo>
        <msub>
          <mi>V</mi>
          <mi>IN</mi>
        </msub>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="1.1em" height="1.1ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>7</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">For example, the DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>is higher than the reference voltage V<sub>0</sub>. Accordingly, the detected voltage V<sub>1 </sub>is also higher than the reference voltage V<sub>0 </sub>based on Equation 7. In another example, the DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>is equal to 12 volts, and the reference voltage V<sub>0 </sub>is equal to 5 volts. Hence the comparison signal at the output terminal <b>613</b> is at the logic low level, and the signal <b>614</b> is also at the logic low level. Accordingly, the driver system <b>300</b> is turned off if the secondary winding <b>532</b> includes one or more breakpoints.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Returning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the control subsystem <b>310</b> outputs the gate drive signals <b>312</b> and <b>314</b> to the AC power supply subsystem <b>320</b>. The control subsystem <b>310</b> includes the gate drive component <b>450</b>, and the AC power supply subsystem <b>320</b> includes the transistors <b>510</b> and <b>520</b>. The gate drive signals <b>312</b> and <b>314</b> are generated by the gate drive component <b>450</b> and received by the transistors <b>520</b> and <b>510</b> respectively. The transistors <b>510</b> and <b>520</b> are coupled to the primary winding <b>531</b> of the transformer <b>530</b>. Additionally, the secondary winding <b>532</b> of the transformer <b>530</b> is coupled to a terminal <b>571</b> of the capacitor <b>570</b>. Another terminal <b>572</b> of the capacitor <b>570</b> provides the AC voltage V<sub>OUT1</sub>. The gate drive signals <b>312</b> and <b>314</b> turns on or off the driver system <b>300</b> by controlling the AC voltage V<sub>OUT1</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The driver system <b>300</b> includes the transformers <b>530</b> and <b>535</b>. The transformer <b>530</b> is associated with the transistors <b>510</b> and <b>520</b>, the resistors <b>540</b> and <b>550</b>, the capacitors <b>560</b> and <b>570</b>, and the comparator <b>610</b>. The transformer <b>535</b> is associated with the transistors <b>515</b> and <b>525</b>, the resistors <b>545</b> and <b>555</b>, the capacitors <b>565</b> and <b>575</b>, and the comparator <b>620</b>. For example, the arrangement and operation principle for the transformer <b>535</b>, the transistors <b>515</b> and <b>525</b>, the resistors <b>545</b> and <b>555</b>, the capacitors <b>565</b> and <b>575</b>, and the comparator <b>620</b> are substantially the same as the arrangement and operation principle for the transformer <b>530</b>, the transistors <b>510</b> and <b>520</b>, the resistors <b>540</b> and <b>550</b>, the capacitors <b>560</b> and <b>570</b>, and the comparator <b>610</b>. In another example, the transformer <b>530</b> is used to generate the AC voltage V<sub>OUT1</sub>, and the transformer <b>535</b> is used to generate the AC voltage V<sub>OUT2</sub>. The AC voltages V<sub>OUT1 </sub>and V<sub>OUT2 </sub>can be the same or different.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">As discussed above and further emphasized here, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-7</figref> are merely examples, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. For example, one of the transformers <b>530</b> and <b>535</b> and certain associated components are removed. In another example, one or more additional transformers and some associated components are added to generate one or more additional AC voltages. As discussed above, the driver system <b>300</b> includes three protection mechanisms. Specifically, the driver system <b>300</b> is turned off if the DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>is lower than a threshold voltage, if the DC voltage V<sub>IN </sub>is larger than a threshold voltage, or if the secondary winding of anyone of the transformers <b>530</b> and <b>535</b> includes one or more breakpoints. In one embodiment, the driver system <b>300</b> is modified so that one of these three protection mechanisms is removed. In another embodiment, the driver system <b>300</b> is modified so that two of these three protection mechanisms are removed.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">According to another embodiment of the present invention, a system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. For example, the system is implemented according to the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>400</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">According to another embodiment, a system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is higher than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. For example, the system is implemented according to the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. The power supply subsystem includes a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding. If the DC input voltage is lower than a first predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. If the DC input voltage is higher than a second predetermined threshold, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. If the secondary winding includes a breakpoint, the system for driving the cold-cathode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. For example, the system is implemented according to the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>400</b> and the subsystem <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. The power supply subsystem includes a first resistor, a second resistor, a first capacitor, and a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding. The secondary winding, the first resistor, and the second resistor are in series. The second resistor is located between the first resistor and the secondary winding, and the secondary winding includes a first terminal biased to a ground voltage level. The first resistor includes a second terminal and a third terminal. The second terminal is biased to the DC input voltage, and the third terminal is coupled to the second resistor. The first resistor and the first capacitor are in parallel between the second terminal and the third terminal, and the third terminal is associated with a first detected voltage. The first detected voltage is compared to a first predetermined voltage for determining the one or more control signals. For example, the system is implemented according to the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">According to yet another embodiment, a method for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp includes receiving a DC input voltage, determining whether the DC input voltage is lower than a first predetermined threshold or higher than a second predetermined threshold, and generating one or more control signals based on at least information associated with the DC input voltage, the first predetermined threshold, and the second predetermined threshold. Additionally, the method includes receiving the one or more control signals, converting the DC input voltage into an AC output voltage in response to the one or more control signals, and sending the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than the first predetermined threshold, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero. If the DC input voltage is higher than the second predetermined threshold, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero. For example, the converting the DC input voltage into an AC output voltage is performed by at least a transformer. The transformer includes a primary winding and a secondary winding. Additionally, the method includes determining whether the secondary winding includes a breakpoint. If the secondary winding includes a breakpoint, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero. In another example, the method is performed by the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>400</b> and the subsystem <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. For example, the system is implemented according to the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>400</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is higher than a predetermined threshold, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. For example, the system is implemented according to the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. The power supply subsystem includes a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding. If the DC input voltage is lower than a first predetermined threshold, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. If the DC input voltage is higher than a second predetermined threshold, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. If the secondary winding includes a breakpoint, the system for driving the external-electrode fluorescent lamp is turned off in response to the one or more control signals. For example, the system is implemented according to the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>400</b> and the subsystem <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">According to yet another embodiment, a system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals, and a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. The power supply subsystem includes a first resistor, a second resistor, a first capacitor, and a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding. The secondary winding, the first resistor, and the second resistor are in series. The second resistor is located between the first resistor and the secondary winding, and the secondary winding includes a first terminal biased to a ground voltage level. The first resistor includes a second terminal and a third terminal. The second terminal is biased to the DC input voltage, and the third terminal is coupled to the second resistor. The first resistor and the first capacitor are in parallel between the second terminal and the third terminal. The third terminal is associated with a first detected voltage, and the first detected voltage is compared to a first predetermined voltage for determining the one or more control signals. For example, the system is implemented according to the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">According to yet another embodiment, a method for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp includes receiving a DC input voltage, determining whether the DC input voltage is lower than a first predetermined threshold or higher than a second predetermined threshold, and generating one or more control signals based on at least information associated with the DC input voltage, the first predetermined threshold, and the second predetermined threshold. Additionally, the method includes receiving the one or more control signals, converting the DC input voltage into an AC output voltage in response to the one or more control signals, and sending the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp. If the DC input voltage is lower than the first predetermined threshold, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero. If the DC input voltage is higher than the second predetermined threshold, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero. For example, the converting the DC input voltage into an AC output voltage is performed by at least a transformer. The transformer includes a primary winding and a secondary winding. Additionally, the method includes determining whether the secondary winding includes a breakpoint. If the secondary winding includes a breakpoint, the AC output voltage is substantially equal to zero. In another example, the method is performed by the system <b>300</b> including the subsystem <b>400</b> and the subsystem <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The present invention has various advantages. Some embodiments of the present invention provide a driver system with one or more protection mechanisms. For example, the driver system is protected against under-voltage system power supply, over-voltage system power supply, and/or breaking of transformer secondary winding. In another example, the driver system is used to drive one or more cold-cathode fluorescent lamps and/or one or more external-electrode fluorescent lamps. Certain embodiments of the present invention provide protection against breaking of a secondary winding. The breaking of the secondary winding can cause arcing, which may damage the secondary winding. Arcing often is difficult to detect during the testing process, so it is very important to protect the driver system when the breaking of the secondary winding occurs. Some embodiments of the present invention provide protection against under-voltage system power supply. Such protection is very important because a low DC input voltage can cause current stress to a power MOSFET transistor. Certain embodiments of the present invention provide protection against over-voltage system power supply. Such protection is very important because a high DC input voltage can cause voltage stress between the drain and source of a power MOSFET transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Although specific embodiments of the present invention have been described, it will be understood by those of skill in the art that there are other embodiments that are equivalent to the described embodiments. Accordingly, it is to be understood that the invention is not to be limited by the specific illustrated embodiments, but only by the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07298097-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="19.73mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298097-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00002" nb-file="US07298097-20071120-M00002.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00002" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298097-20071120-M00002.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00003" nb-file="US07298097-20071120-M00003.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00003" he="7.03mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298097-20071120-M00003.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00004" nb-file="US07298097-20071120-M00004.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00004" he="12.02mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298097-20071120-M00004.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00005" nb-file="US07298097-20071120-M00005.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00005" he="6.69mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298097-20071120-M00005.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00006" nb-file="US07298097-20071120-M00006.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00006" he="7.03mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298097-20071120-M00006.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A system for driving a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to a cold-cathode fluorescent lamp;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein:</claim-text>
<claim-text>the power supply subsystem includes a first resistor, a second resistor, a first capacitor, and a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the secondary winding, the first resistor, and the second resistor are in series, the second resistor being located between the first resistor and the secondary winding, the secondary winding including a first terminal biased to a ground voltage level;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first resistor includes a second terminal and a third terminal, the second terminal being biased to the DC input voltage, the third terminal being coupled to the second resistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first resistor and the first capacitor are in parallel between the second terminal and the third terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the third terminal is associated with a first detected voltage, the first detected voltage being compared to a first predetermined voltage for determining the one or more control signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>if the DC input voltage is higher than a predetermined threshold, the system is turned off in response to the one or more control signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the predetermined threshold is proportional to the first predetermined voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the power supply subsystem further includes a second capacitor including a fourth terminal and a fifth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the fourth terminal is coupled to the second resistor and the secondary winding;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the fifth terminal provides the AC output voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the power supply subsystem further includes a first comparator configured to compare the first detected voltage and the first predetermined voltage and generate a first comparison signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first comparison signal is at a logic low level if the first detected voltage is higher than the first predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first comparison signal is at a logic high level if the first detected voltage is lower than the first predetermined voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the first comparison signal is used to generate a logic signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the logic signal is at the logic low level if the first comparison signal is at the logic low level.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the control subsystem includes a second comparator and a gate drive device coupled to the second comparator, the second comparator including a fourth terminal and a fifth terminal, the fifth terminal being biased to a second predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the power supply subsystem further includes a switch configured to receive the logic signal and including a sixth terminal and a seventh terminal, the sixth terminal being coupled to the fourth terminal, the seventh terminal being biased to the ground voltage level;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second comparator is configured to compare a received voltage at the sixth terminal and the second predetermined voltage and generate a second comparison signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the gate drive device is configured to generate the one or more control signals in response to the second comparison signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the control subsystem further comprises a control logic device, the gate drive device being coupled to the second comparator through the control logic device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the one or more control signals includes one or more gate drive signals.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the power supply subsystem further includes a third resistor and a fourth resistor, the third resistor including an eighth terminal and a ninth terminal, the fourth resistor including a tenth terminal and an eleventh terminal, the eighth terminal being biased to the DC input voltage, the eleventh terminal being biased to the ground voltage level, the ninth terminal and the ten terminal both being coupled to the fourth terminal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>if the DC input voltage is lower than a second predetermined threshold, the system is turned off in response to the one or more control signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second predetermined threshold is proportional to the second predetermined voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the switch is closed if the logic signal is at the logic low level;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the switch is open if the logic signal is at the logic high level.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the switch includes a transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A system for driving an external-electrode fluorescent lamp, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a control subsystem configured to generate one or more control signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply subsystem configured to receive the one or more control signals and a DC input voltage, convert the DC input voltage to an AC output voltage, and send the AC output voltage to an external-electrode fluorescent lamp;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein:</claim-text>
<claim-text>the power supply subsystem includes a first resistor, a second resistor, a first capacitor, and a transformer including a primary winding and a secondary winding;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the secondary winding, the first resistor, and the second resistor are in series, the second resistor being located between the first resistor and the secondary winding, the secondary winding including a first terminal biased to a ground voltage level;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first resistor includes a second terminal and a third terminal, the second terminal being biased to the DC input voltage, the third terminal being coupled to the second resistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first resistor and the first capacitor are in parallel between the second terminal and the third terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the third terminal is associated with a first detected voltage, the first detected voltage being compared to a first predetermined voltage for determining the one or more control signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
