<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298012-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298012</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11307537</doc-number>
<date>20060211</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>76</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257384</main-classification>
<further-classification>257408</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Shallow junction semiconductor</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4692348</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Rubloff et al.</name>
<date>19870900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>437 82</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5395787</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lee et al.</name>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>437 57</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6136636</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wu</name>
<date>20001000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438231</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6326251</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Gardner et al.</name>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438197</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6555438</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wu</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438305</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6613623</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Tsai et al.</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438197</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6873057</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chen et al.</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257777</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7033916</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Pelella et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438558</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257382-384</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257408</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>14</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10770990</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040202</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7033916</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20060425</date>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11307537</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060180873</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060817</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Pelella</last-name>
<first-name>Mario M.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Mountain View</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>En</last-name>
<first-name>William George</first-name>
<address>
<city>Milpitas</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Paton</last-name>
<first-name>Eric</first-name>
<address>
<city>Morgan Hill</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Maszara</last-name>
<first-name>Witold P.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Morgan Hill</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ishimaru</last-name>
<first-name>Mikio</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Advanced Micro Devices, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Sunnyvale</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Prenty</last-name>
<first-name>Mark V.</first-name>
<department>2822</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An integrated circuit with a semiconductor substrate is provided. A gate dielectric is on the semiconductor substrate, and a gate is on the gate dielectric. A silicide layer is on the semiconductor substrate adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric. The silicide layer incorporates a substantially uniformly distributed and concentrated dopant therein. A shallow source/drain junction is beneath the salicide layer. An interlayer dielectric is above the semiconductor substrate, and contacts are in the interlayer dielectric to the salicide layer.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="72.90mm" wi="72.64mm" file="US07298012-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="194.99mm" wi="149.18mm" file="US07298012-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="218.86mm" wi="151.13mm" file="US07298012-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="216.24mm" wi="151.21mm" file="US07298012-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="169.50mm" wi="68.16mm" file="US07298012-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This is a divisional of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/770,990 filed Feb. 2, 2004, since issued on Apr. 25, 2006 as U.S. Pat. No. 7,033,916.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to semiconductor technology, and more specifically to shallow junctions in semiconductor integrated circuit devices.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">At the present time, electronic products are used in almost every aspect of life, and the heart of these electronic products is the integrated circuit. Integrated circuits are used in everything from airplanes and televisions to wristwatches.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Integrated circuits are made in and on silicon wafers by extremely complex systems that require the coordination of hundreds or even thousands of precisely controlled processes to produce a finished semiconductor wafer. Each finished semiconductor wafer has hundreds to tens of thousands of integrated circuits, each wafer worth hundreds or thousands of dollars.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Integrated circuits are made up of hundreds to millions of individual components. One common component is the semiconductor transistor. The most common and important semiconductor technology presently used is silicon-based, and the most preferred silicon-based semiconductor device is a Complementary Metal Oxide Semiconductor (“CMOS”) transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The principal elements of a CMOS transistor generally consist of a silicon substrate having shallow trench oxide isolation regions cordoning off transistor areas. The transistor areas contain polysilicon gates on silicon oxide gates, or gate oxides, over the silicon substrate. The silicon substrate on both sides of the polysilicon gate is slightly doped to become conductive. These lightly doped regions of the silicon substrate are referred to as “shallow source/drain junctions”, which are separated by a channel region beneath the polysilicon gate. A curved silicon oxide or silicon nitride spacer, referred to as a “sidewall spacer”, on the sides of the polysilicon gate allows deposition of additional doping to form more heavily doped regions of the shallow source/drain (“S/D ”) junctions, which are called “deep S/D junctions”. The shallow and deep S/D junctions together are collectively referred to as “S/D junctions”.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">To complete the transistor, a silicon oxide dielectric layer is deposited to cover the polysilicon gate, the curved spacer, and the silicon substrate. To provide electrical connections for the transistor, openings are etched in the silicon oxide dielectric layer to the polysilicon gate and the S/D junctions. The openings are filled with metal to form electrical contacts. To complete the integrated circuits, the contacts are connected to additional levels of wiring in additional levels of dielectric material to the outside of the dielectric material.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In operation, an input signal to the gate contact to the polysilicon gate controls the flow of electric current from one S/D contact through one S/D junction through the channel to the other S/D junction and to the other S/D contact.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Transistors are fabricated by thermally growing a gate oxide layer on the silicon substrate of a semiconductor wafer and forming a polysilicon layer over the gate oxide layer. The oxide layer and polysilicon layer are patterned and etched to form the gate oxides and polysilicon gates, respectively. The gate oxides and polysilicon gates in turn are used as masks to form the shallow S/D regions by ion implantation of boron or phosphorus impurity atoms into the surface of the silicon substrate. The ion implantation is followed by a high-temperature anneal above 700° C. to activate the implanted impurity atoms to form the shallow S/D junctions.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A silicon nitride layer is deposited and etched to form sidewall spacers around the side surfaces of the gate oxides and polysilicon gates. The sidewall spacers, the gate oxides, and the polysilicon gates are used as masks for the conventional S/D regions by ion implantation of boron or phosphorus impurity atoms into the surface of the silicon substrate into and through the shallow S/D junctions. The ion implantation is again followed by a high-temperature anneal above 700° C. to activate the implanted impurity atoms to form the S/D junctions.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">After formation of the transistors, a silicon oxide dielectric layer is deposited over the transistors and contact openings are etched down to the S/D junctions and to the polysilicon gates. The contact openings are then filled with a conductive metal and interconnected by formation of conductive wires in other interlayer dielectric (“ILD”) layers.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">As transistors have decreased in size, it has been found that the electrical resistance between the metal contacts and the silicon substrate or the polysilicon has increased to the level where it negatively impacts the performance of the transistors. To lower the electrical resistance, a transition material is formed between the metal contacts and the silicon substrate or the polysilicon. The best transition materials have been found to be cobalt silicide (CoSi2) and titanium silicide (TiSi2).</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The silicides are formed by first applying a thin layer of the cobalt or titanium on the silicon substrate above the S/D junctions and the polysilicon gates. The semiconductor wafer is subjected to one or more annealing steps at temperatures above 800° C. and this causes the cobalt or titanium to selectively react with the silicon and the polysilicon to form the metal silicide. The process is generally referred to as “siliciding”. Since the shallow trench oxide and the sidewall spacers will not react to form a silicide, the silicides are aligned over the S/D junctions and the polysilicon gates so the process is also referred to as “self-aligned siliciding”, or “saliciding”.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Salicidation technology is vital for improving the operating speed of modern semiconductor devices with sub-micron feature sizes. The salicide technology is widely use to increase the packing density of integrated circuits and to reduce the circuit interconnect resistance for high-speed operation. With the continuous decrease in device sizes (transistors becoming narrower and thinner and transistor channels becoming shorter), salicidation problems like junction punchthrough, current leakage, and contact resistance continue to reduce product yields and reliability.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In general, salicidation results in high junction leakage due to metal penetration into the silicon substrate. The penetration of the metal “spikes” the junction, causing the current leakage.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Residual metal from the salicidation process can also cause leakage. The silicide across the sidewall spacers may not be totally removed after the salicidation. The residual metal can cause a bridge between adjacent circuit features, like the gate and the S/D regions, causing current leakage.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Nevertheless, as device dimensions continue to be scaled to smaller and smaller dimensions, it is necessary to scale down extension junction depths as well. Furthermore, shallow junctions are increasingly needed to control adverse charge-sharing effects (two dimensional short channel effects) in advanced devices such as metal oxide field effect transistors. Extended ultra-shallow S/D junctions can improve such negative effects, can suppress the short channel effect, and can improve device operating speeds.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">However, existing shallow S/D junction fabrication technologies, such as ion implantation followed by rapid thermal annealing, have not succeeded in solving all the problems related to fabricating increasingly shallow S/D junctions, and to connecting metal contacts to them.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Solutions to these problems have been long sought but prior developments have not taught or suggested any solutions and, thus, solutions to these problems have long eluded those skilled in the art.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The present invention provides a method of forming an integrated circuit. A gate dielectric is formed on a semiconductor substrate, and a gate is formed on the gate dielectric. A super-saturated doped source silicide metallic layer is formed on the semiconductor substrate adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric. The silicide metallic layer incorporates a substantially uniformly distributed dopant therein in a substantially uniform super-saturated concentration. The silicide metallic layer is reacted with the semiconductor substrate therebeneath to form a salicide layer and outdiffuse the dopant from the salicide layer into the semiconductor substrate therebeneath. The outdiffused dopant in the semiconductor substrate is then activated to form a shallow source/drain junction beneath the salicide layer. An interlayer dielectric is then deposited above the semiconductor substrate, and contacts are formed in the interlayer dielectric to the salicide layer. This method significantly improves the formation of very shallow source/drain junctions for integrated circuits.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Certain embodiments of the invention have other advantages in addition to or in place of those mentioned above. The advantages will become apparent to those skilled in the art from a reading of the following detailed description when taken with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a view of an integrated circuit in an intermediate stage of fabrication in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with an insulating layer and silicide metallic layers formed thereon;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> following formation of salicide layers and shallow source/drain junctions;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> after formation of a sidewall spacer;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> during ion implantation to form deep source/drain junctions;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> after deposition of a dielectric layer over the silicide, the sidewall spacer, and shallow trench isolation;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> after formation of metal contacts;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a variation on the method for forming the shallow source/drain junctions;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9-11</figref> illustrate another variation on the method for forming the shallow source/drain junctions;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows a structure combining the variations illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8-11</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> illustrates still another variation on the method for forming the shallow source/drain junctions; and</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a simplified flow chart of the method of manufacturing the integrated circuit in accordance with the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In the following description, numerous specific details are given to provide a thorough understanding of the invention. However, it will be apparent to one skilled in the art that the invention may be practiced without these specific details. In order to avoid obscuring the present invention, some well-known configurations and process steps are not disclosed in detail. In addition, the drawings showing embodiments of the device are semi-diagrammatic and not to scale and, particularly, some of the dimensions are for the clarity of presentation and may be exaggerated in the drawing FIGS. The same numbers will be used in all the drawing FIGS. to relate to the same elements.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The term “horizontal” as used herein is defined as a plane parallel to a substrate or wafer. The term “vertical” refers to a direction perpendicular to the horizontal as just defined. Terms, such as “on”, “above”, “below”, “bottom”, “top”, “side” (as in “sidewall”), “higher”, “lower”, “over”, and “under”, are defined with respect to the horizontal plane.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, therein is shown a semiconductor integrated circuit, and in particular a transistor <b>100</b>, in an intermediate stage of fabrication in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">To form the intermediate stage, a gate dielectric layer, such as silicon oxide, and a conductive gate layer, such as polysilicon, have been deposited on a semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> of a material such as silicon. The layers are patterned and etched to form a gate dielectric <b>104</b> and a gate <b>106</b>. The semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> has been further patterned, etched, and filled with a silicon oxide material to form a shallow trench isolation (“STI”) <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, therein is shown the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> having an insulating layer <b>202</b> formed on the sides of the gate <b>106</b>. The insulating layer <b>202</b> is formed by depositing an insulating film over the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and anisotropically etching the horizontal surfaces. A deposition process <b>204</b> is then used to form silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> in accordance with the present invention. The silicide metallic layers <b>206</b> and <b>210</b> are formed on the surface of the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b>, and the silicide metallic layer <b>208</b> is formed on the gate <b>106</b>. Advantageously, the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b> and <b>210</b> can be formed adjacent the gate <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The silicide layer deposition process forms the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> by depositing silicide metal that is doped with a dopant species to be used for subsequently forming very shallow source/drain (“S/D”) junctions. For example, the silicide metallic layers may be cobalt (for forming cobalt silicide, CoSi<sub>2</sub>), nickel (for forming nickel silicide, NiSi<sub>2</sub>), or platinum (for forming platinum silicide, PtSi). The dopant impurity atoms that are incorporated in the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> as they are formed may be, for example, arsenic (As), boron (B), or phosphorus (P).</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The doped silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> may be formed, for example, by a sputtering process in which both the silicide metal and the dopant are incorporated into the sputter target. In one embodiment, the dopant concentration in the sputter target may be sufficiently high that the sputtered dopant is incorporated into the deposited silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> in a super-saturated concentration (i.e., the dopant concentration is higher than its solid solubility). Such a super-saturated dopant concentration in the deposited silicide metallic layer provides a super-saturated doped source. The super-saturated doped source facilitates subsequent solid-source outdiffusion of the dopant to form very shallow junctions, as further described herein. The use of sputtering to form the super-saturated doped source results in a uniform distribution and concentration of the dopant throughout the silicide metallic layers.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The doped silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> may alternatively be formed by other suitable means, such as, for example, deposition of undoped silicide metallic layers followed by ion implantation of the dopant in a concentration similarly sufficient to create a super-saturated dopant concentration in the silicide metallic layers.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, therein is shown the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> following a heating and annealing step that reacts the deposited silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) with the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> and the gate <b>106</b> therebeneath. The reaction forms salicide layers <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, and <b>306</b> and causes the dopant to outdiffuse from the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b> into the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> therebeneath as it incorporates the silicide metallic layers into the salicide layers. Since the solid solubility of dopants in silicide is very low, the dopants readily eject out of the silicide and go into the silicon substrate therebeneath. The dopant that remains behind in the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b> will also be uniformly distributed and concentrated therein as a residual result from the prior uniform distribution and concentration of the dopant throughout their predecessor silicide metallic layers.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The thermal outdiffusion of the dopant into the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> activates the outdiffused dopant atoms in the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> to form very shallow S/D junctions immediately beneath the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b>. The process forms shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b> that are directly beneath and follow the contour of the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b>. This advantageously reduces junction leakage.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, therein is shown the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> after formation of a sidewall spacer <b>402</b>. The sidewall spacer <b>402</b>, generally of silicon nitride, is a deposited layer that is etched in conventional manner to form a conventional curved shape as shown.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, therein is shown the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> during an ion implantation <b>502</b> to form deep S/D junctions <b>504</b> and <b>506</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The sidewall spacer <b>402</b>, the gate <b>106</b>, and the STI <b>108</b> act as masks for the formation of the deep S/D junctions <b>504</b> and <b>506</b> by the ion implantation <b>502</b> of arsenic, boron, or phosphorus impurity atoms into the surface of the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> and into and through the shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b>, respectively. The ion implantation <b>502</b> is followed by a high-temperature anneal above 700° C. to activate the implanted impurity atoms to form the deep S/D junctions <b>504</b> and <b>506</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, therein is shown the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> after deposition of a dielectric layer <b>602</b> over the salicide layers <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, and <b>306</b>, the sidewall spacer <b>402</b>, and the STI <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In various embodiments, the dielectric layer <b>602</b> is of dielectric materials such as silicon oxide (SiO<sub>x</sub>), tetraethylorthosilicate (TEOS), borophosphosilicate (BPSG) glass, etc., with dielectric constants from 4.2 to 3.9, or low dielectric constant dielectric materials such as fluorinated tetraethylorthosilicate (FTEOS), hydrogen silsesquioxane (HSQ), bis-benzocyclo-butene (BCB), tetramethylorthosil icate (TMOS), octamethyleyclotetrasi loxane (OMCTS), hexa-methyidisiloxane (HMDS), trimethylsilil borxle (SOB), diaceloxyditerliarybutosiloxane (DADBS), trimethylsilil phosphate (SOP), etc., with dielectric constants below 3.9 to 2.5. Available ultra-low dielectric constant dielectric materials, having dielectric constants below 2.5, include commercially available Teflon-AF, Teflon microemulsion, polimide nanofoams, silica aerogels, silica xerogels, and mesoporous silica. Stop layers and capping layers (where used) are of materials such as silicon nitride (Si<sub>x</sub>N<sub>x</sub>) or silicon oxynitride (SiON).</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, therein is shown the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> after formation of metal contacts <b>702</b>, <b>704</b>, and <b>706</b>. The metal contacts <b>702</b>, <b>704</b>, and <b>706</b> are respectively electrically connected to the salicide layers <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, and <b>306</b>, and respectively to the deep S/D junction <b>504</b>, the gate <b>106</b>, and the deep S/D junction <b>506</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">In various embodiments, the metal contacts <b>702</b>, <b>704</b>, and <b>706</b> are of metals such as tantalum (Ta), titanium (Ti), tungsten (W), alloys thereof, and compounds thereof. In other embodiments, the metal contacts <b>702</b>, <b>704</b>, and <b>706</b> are of metals such as copper (Cu), gold (Au), silver (Ag), alloys thereof, and compounds thereof with one or more of the above elements with diffusion barriers around them.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, therein is shown a variation on the method for forming the shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b>. The variation adds an additional step between the steps illustrated above for <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Thus, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, following formation of the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a metallic cap layer <b>802</b> is formed on the tops thereof by a deposition process <b>804</b>. The metallic cap layer <b>802</b> and the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> combine to form an alloyed metallic bi-layer that caps and deters outdiffusion of the super-saturated dopant through the top surfaces of the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">For example, the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> formed by sputtering Ni<sub>x</sub>As<sub>y</sub>, Ni<sub>x</sub>B<sub>y</sub>, or Ni<sub>x</sub>P<sub>y </sub>would be caped by a layer of Ni. The silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> formed by sputtering Co<sub>x</sub>As<sub>y</sub>, Co<sub>x</sub>B<sub>y</sub>, or Co<sub>x</sub>P<sub>y </sub>would be caped by a layer of Co. The silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> formed by sputtering Pt<sub>x</sub>As<sub>y</sub>, Pt<sub>x</sub>B<sub>y</sub>, or Pt<sub>x</sub>P<sub>y </sub>would be caped by a layer of Pt. Of course, other combinations of materials, including combinations of dissimilar silicide and capping metals, may be used as appropriate.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The method of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> then continues with the steps illustrated for <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-7</figref>, beginning with the heating and annealing step that reacts the deposited silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> to form the salicide layers <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, and <b>306</b>, and outdiffuses the dopant from the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b> into the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b>. The thermal outdiffusion of the dopant into the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> again activates the outdiffused dopant atoms to form the shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b>. The metallic cap layer <b>802</b> deters outdiffusion of the super-saturated dopant through the top surfaces of the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> during the heating and annealing process.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9-11</figref>, therein is shown another variation on the method for forming the shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b>. The variation adds an additional step between the steps illustrated above for <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Thus, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, following formation of the gate dielectric <b>104</b> and the gate <b>106</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a self-aligned amorphous layer <b>902</b> is formed in the surface of the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> on each side of and adjacent the gate <b>106</b> and the gate dielectric <b>104</b>. The amorphous layer <b>902</b> may be formed, for example, by a damaging ion implantation <b>904</b> of an inert species such as germanium (Ge), silicon (Si), or Argon (A). The implantation damage creates a disordered (amorphous) layer that presents much greater resistance to diffusion of dopants, thereby effectively limiting subsequent dopant diffusion to a very narrow penetration depth into the amorphous layer <b>902</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> corresponds to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, showing formation of the insulating layer <b>202</b> and deposition of the doped silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Alternatively, the doped silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> may be deposited prior to the formation of the amorphous layer <b>902</b> by the damaging ion implantation <b>904</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> corresponds to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, showing formation of the salicide layers <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, and <b>306</b> and outdiffusion of the dopant from the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b> into the amorphous layer <b>902</b> therebeneath. As before, the thermal outdiffusion of the dopant into the amorphous layer <b>902</b> activates the outdiffused dopant atoms in the amorphous layer <b>902</b> to form very shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b>′ and <b>310</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The method of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9-11</figref> then continues with the steps illustrated for <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-7</figref>, beginning with formation of the sidewall spacer <b>402</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, therein is shown a structure combining the metallic cap layer <b>802</b>, as taught in connection with the method and structure described in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, with the dopant diffusion depth-limiting properties of the amorphous layer <b>902</b>, as taught in connection with the method and structure described in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9-11</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">The combination of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> may be fabricated, for example, by forming the metallic cap layer <b>802</b> on the tops of the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> subsequent to the process steps illustrated in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>. The metallic cap layer <b>802</b> and the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> then combine to form an alloyed metallic bi-layer that caps and deters outdiffusion of the super-saturated dopant through the top surfaces of the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b>. This is followed, as before, with a heating and annealing step that reacts the deposited silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> (cf. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10-11</figref>). The heating and annealing reaction forms the salicide layers <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, and <b>306</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>), causes the dopant to outdiffuse from the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b> into the amorphous layer <b>902</b> therebeneath, and activates the outdiffused dopant atoms in the amorphous layer <b>902</b> to form the very shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b>′ and <b>310</b>′. The metallic cap layer <b>802</b> deters outdiffusion of the super-saturated dopant through the top surfaces of the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> during the heating and annealing process.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The fabrication of the transistor <b>100</b> according to the method described in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is then completed in the same manner as described previously in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-7</figref>, beginning with formation of the sidewall spacer <b>402</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, therein is shown a variation on the method for forming the shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>). The variation shown in (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>) replaces the steps illustrated above for <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-4</figref>, eliminating the heating and annealing step that formed the shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) at that stage of the process. By eliminating this heating and annealing step, heat cycles are preserved or saved, thereby reducing costs and improving operational efficiencies.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Thus, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, following formation of the silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a sidewall spacer <b>402</b> is formed in the same manner as described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The sidewall spacer <b>402</b>, generally of silicon nitride, is thus a deposited layer that is etched in conventional manner to form the conventional curved shape as shown.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The method of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> then continues with the steps illustrated for <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5-7</figref>. In this case, the high temperature anneal that follows the ion implantation <b>502</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) not only activates the implanted impurity atoms to form the deep S/D junctions <b>504</b> and <b>506</b>, but it also reacts the deposited silicide metallic layers <b>206</b>, <b>208</b>, and <b>210</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>) with the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> and the gate <b>106</b> therebeneath. The reaction forms the salicide layers <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, and <b>306</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) and outdiffuses the dopant from the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b> into the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b>. The thermal outdiffusion of the dopant from the salicide layers <b>302</b> and <b>306</b> into the semiconductor substrate <b>102</b> provides activated outdiffused dopant atoms that form the shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The method of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> thus saves energy and heat cycles by utilizing the single annealing step described in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> to form the salicide layers <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, and <b>306</b>, the shallow S/D junctions <b>308</b> and <b>310</b>, and activate and form the deep S/D junctions <b>504</b> and <b>506</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">It will be understood that the dopant can be expected to be activated immediately in the semiconductor substrate during the step of reacting the silicide metallic layer with the semiconductor substrate therebeneath to form the salicide layer and outdiffuse the dopant from the salicide layer into the semiconductor substrate therebeneath. This is due to the lack of damage to the semiconductor substrate crystalline structure that would have resulted from a dopant ion implantation (for which subsequent annealing is then conducted). Thus, the step of activating the outdiffused dopant in the semiconductor substrate to form shallow source/drain junctions beneath the salicide layer may be accomplished by the salicide formation process itself without the additional thermal annealing process, as well as by thermal annealing steps such as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>, therein is shown a simplified flow chart of a method <b>1400</b> in accordance with the present invention. The method <b>1400</b> includes: providing a semiconductor substrate in a step <b>1402</b>; forming a gate dielectric on the semiconductor substrate in a step <b>1404</b>; forming a gate on the gate dielectric in a step <b>1406</b>; forming at least one super-saturated doped source silicide metallic layer on the semiconductor substrate adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric, the silicide metallic layer incorporating a substantially uniformly distributed dopant therein in a substantially uniform super-saturated concentration, in a step <b>1408</b>; reacting the silicide metallic layer with the semiconductor substrate therebeneath to form a salicide layer and outdiffuse the dopant from the salicide layer into the semiconductor substrate therebeneath, in a step <b>1410</b>; activating the outdiffused dopant in the semiconductor substrate to form a shallow source/drain junction beneath the salicide layer in a step <b>1412</b>; depositing an interlayer dielectric above the semiconductor substrate in a step <b>1414</b>; and forming a contact in the interlayer dielectric to the salicide layer in a step <b>1416</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">While the invention has been described in conjunction with a specific best mode, it is to be understood that many alternatives, modifications, and variations will be apparent to those skilled in the art in light of the aforegoing description. Accordingly, it is intended to embrace all such alternatives, modifications, and variations that fall within the spirit and scope of the included claims. All matters hither-to-fore set forth or shown in the accompanying drawings are to be interpreted in an illustrative and non-limiting sense.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is: </us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An integrated circuit comprising:
<claim-text>a semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate dielectric on the semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate on the gate dielectric;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one salicide layer on the semiconductor substrate adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric, the salicide layer incorporating a substantially uniformly distributed and concentrated dopant therein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an amorphous layer in the surface of the semiconductor substrate beneath the salicide layer and adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shallow source/drain junction beneath the salicide layer, the shallow source/drain junction being formed in the amorphous layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interlayer dielectric above the semiconductor substrate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a contact in the interlayer dielectric to the salicide layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The integrated circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the contact to the salicide layer is at least one material selected from tantalum, titanium, tungsten, copper, gold, silver, an alloy thereof, a compound thereof, and a combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. An integrated circuit comprising:
<claim-text>a semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate dielectric on the semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate on the gate dielectric;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an amorphous layer in the surface of the semiconductor substrate adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one salicide layer on the semiconductor substrate adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric and over the amorphous layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shallow source/drain junction in the amorphous layer beneath the salicide layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interlayer dielectric above the semiconductor substrate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a contact in the interlayer dielectric to the salicide layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The integrated circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the contact to the salicide layer is at least one material selected from tantalum, titanium, tungsten, copper, gold, silver, an alloy thereof, a compound thereof, and a combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An integrated circuit comprising:
<claim-text>a semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate dielectric on the semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gate on the gate dielectric;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an amorphous layer in the surface of the semiconductor substrate adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one salicide layer on the semiconductor substrate adjacent the gate and the gate dielectric and over the amorphous layer, the salicide layer incorporating a substantially uniformiy distributed and concentrated dopant therein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shallow source/drain junction in the amorphous layer beneath the salicide layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interlayer dielectric above the semiconductor substrate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a contact in the interlayer dielectric to the salicide layer, the contact being at least one material selected from tantalum, titanium, tungsten, copper, gold, silver, an alloy thereof, a compound thereof, and a combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
