<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297995-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297995</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10923693</doc-number>
<date>20040824</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>308</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>062</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257291</main-classification>
<further-classification>257292</further-classification>
<further-classification>257510</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E27133</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Transparent metal shielded isolation for image sensors</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6229194</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lizotte</name>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257506</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6611037</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Rhodes</name>
<date>20030800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6888214</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Mouli et al.</name>
<date>20050500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257510</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0089004</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Rhodes</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0001059</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Mouli et al.</name>
<date>20060100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257292</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>D.L. Losee et al., “All-ITO gate, two phase CCD image sensor technology,” Proc. of IEDM, p. 397 (2003).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>26</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>26</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257291</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257292</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257510</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E27133</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>11</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060043437</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060302</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mouli</last-name>
<first-name>Chandra</first-name>
<address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Dickstein Shapiro LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Micron Technology, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Quach</last-name>
<first-name>T. N.</first-name>
<department>2826</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An isolation region formed in a substrate and lined with a transparent metal layer. The isolation region provides isolation between adjacent active areas of an integrated circuit structure, for example the inventive region may provide isolation between pixels of a pixel array. Utilizing a transparent material maintains high quantum efficiency of the pixels as photons are not blocked from penetrating into the substrate. In one exemplary embodiment, a shallow trench isolation region is formed in a substrate, lined with an oxide or other dielectric, and an indium-tin-oxide shielding layer is formed over the oxide. The lined trench may then be filled with either the transparent metal material or a transparent insulating material.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="136.14mm" wi="226.57mm" file="US07297995-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="205.99mm" wi="153.84mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297995-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="170.69mm" wi="146.22mm" file="US07297995-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="169.08mm" wi="151.81mm" file="US07297995-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="167.89mm" wi="158.33mm" file="US07297995-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="227.25mm" wi="150.54mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297995-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="170.18mm" wi="136.23mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297995-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="174.41mm" wi="132.84mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297995-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="168.91mm" wi="132.59mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297995-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="238.17mm" wi="134.37mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297995-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="197.53mm" wi="172.30mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297995-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="193.63mm" wi="165.78mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297995-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention relates generally to an improved isolation structure for high density integrated circuits and, in particular, to an improved isolation region for an image sensor and a process for its formation.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">CMOS (Complementary Metal-Oxide Semiconductor) imagers are increasingly being used as low cost imaging devices. A CMOS imager circuit includes a focal plane array of pixel cells, each one of the cells including a photosensor, for example, a photogate, photoconductor or a photodiode overlying a substrate for accumulating photo-generated charge in the underlying portion of the substrate. A readout circuit is connected to each pixel cell and includes at least pixel selecting field effect transistor formed in the substrate and a charge storage region formed on the substrate connected to the gate of a transistor coupled to the pixel selecting transistor. The charge storage region may be constructed as a floating diffusion region. The imager may include at least one electronic device such as a transistor for transferring charge from the photosensor to the storage region and one device, also typically a transistor, for resetting the storage region to a predetermined charge level prior to charge transference.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In a so-called four-transistor (4T) CMOS imager, the active elements of a pixel cell perform the necessary functions of: (1) photon to charge conversion; (2) accumulation of image charge; (3) resetting the storage region to a known state before the transfer of charge to it; (4) transfer of charge to the storage region accompanied by charge amplification; (5) selection of a pixel for readout; and (6) output and amplification of a signal representing a reset voltage and a signal representing pixel charge. Photo charge may be amplified when it moves from the initial charge accumulation region to the storage region. The charge at the storage region is typically converted to a pixel output voltage by a source follower output transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Exemplary CMOS imaging circuits, processing steps thereof, and detailed descriptions of the functions of various CMOS elements of an imaging circuit are described, for example, in U.S. Pat. No. 6,140,630, U.S. Pat. No. 6,376,868, U.S. Pat. No. 6,310,366, U.S. Pat. No. 6,326,652, U.S. Pat. No. 6,204,524, and U.S. Pat. No. 6,333,205, all assigned to Micron Technology, Inc. The disclosures of each of the foregoing are hereby incorporated by reference herein in their entirety.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Trench isolation regions are an essential part of current fabrication methods for CMOS and other microelectronic circuits. The decreasing dimensions of devices and the increasing density of integration in microelectronic circuits have required a corresponding reduction in the size of isolation structures. This reduction places a premium on reproducible formation of structures that provide effective isolation, while also occupying a minimum amount of the substrate surface.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">One isolation technique widely employed in semiconductor fabrication is the shallow trench isolation (STI) region. The STI technique forms trench isolation regions that electrically isolate the various active components formed in integrated circuits. In the STI technique, the first step is the formation of a plurality of trenches at predefined locations in the substrate. This occurs usually through anisotropic etching. After the etching is complete, the trenches are filled with an oxide to complete the STI structure. One major advantage of using the STI technique over the conventional LOCOS (Local Oxidation of Silicon) insulation technique is the high scalability to CMOS IC devices for fabrication at the sub-micron level of integration. Another advantage is that the STI technique helps prevent the occurrence of the so-called “bird's beak” encroachment, which is characteristic to the LOCOS technique.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In order to provide context for the present invention, a portion of a conventional CMOS image sensor cell <b>10</b> is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. As described in general terms above, incident light causes electrons to accumulate in an n-type region <b>26</b> of a photodiode <b>21</b>. An output signal, which is produced by the source follower transistor having gate <b>50</b>, is proportional to the number of electrons extracted from the n-type region <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Trench isolation regions <b>15</b> having sidewalls <b>16</b> and a bottom <b>17</b> are formed in a p-well active layer <b>94</b> and adjacent to the charge photodiode <b>21</b>, to isolate the cell <b>10</b> from adjacent pixel cells. Trench isolation regions <b>15</b> are formed using known STI techniques. Specifically, the trenches <b>15</b> are etched by employing a dry anisotropic or other suitable etching process, and are filled with a dielectric such as a chemical vapor deposited (CVD) silicon dioxide (SiO<sub>2</sub>) or other known oxide. The filled trenches <b>15</b> are then planarized so that the dielectric remains only in the trenches and their top surface remains level with that of the silicon substrate <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">As scaling continues to decrease the size of each device, such as pixel cell <b>10</b>, isolation techniques become increasingly important. Traditional STI fabrication methods have several drawbacks that are intensified by desired scaling. STI regions, such as trench <b>15</b>, have encountered processing problems such as void prevention, corner rounding, and gap fill. Several techniques have been devised in order to mitigate these negative effects which tend to reduce the isolation capabilities of the STI regions.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Another problem that pixel cells encounter due to scaling occurs when the spacing between the active areas of the pixels is decreased. The effect of the decrease in area is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A</figref>, <b>2</b>B, and <b>2</b>C. When adjacent active areas of a pixel cell, which can be multiple areas within a cell or of adjacent cells, are supplied with different voltages, an electric field is created between the two areas. These electric fields are generally shown in the accompanying drawings, which illustrates that the field may take on many forms depending on the voltage levels applied (see, e.g., Fields F<b>1</b>, F<b>2</b>, and F<b>3</b>). This field, in turn, may provide transportation of electrons between the two active areas. Electrons may even be carried through an isolation region, as typical isolation regions do not block this flow. This undesirably reduces the quantum efficiency of the pixel cell.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">There is needed, therefore, an isolation region for use in imager pixels that prevents an electric field penetration between active areas of adjacent pixels without reducing the quantum efficiency of the pixels. There is also a need for a simple method of fabricating the desired isolation regions in pixels.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Exemplary embodiments of the invention provide an isolation region formed in a substrate and lined with a transparent metal layer. The isolation region provides isolation between adjacent active areas of an integrated circuit structure, for example the inventive region may provide isolation between pixels of a pixel array. Utilizing a transparent material maintains high quantum efficiency of the pixels as photons are not blocked from penetrating into the substrate. In one exemplary embodiment, a shallow trench isolation region is formed in a substrate, lined with an oxide or other dielectric, and an indium-tin-oxide shielding layer is formed over the oxide. The lined trench may then be filled with either the transparent metal material or a transparent insulating material.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Additional advantages and features of the present invention will be apparent from the following detailed description and drawings which illustrate preferred embodiments of the invention, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a conventional four-transistor pixel cell;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A-2C</figref> are images of potential profiles in a silicon substrate during various bias conditions;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a portion of an exemplary imager pixel constructed in accordance with the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the exemplary imager pixel of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> during an initial stage of fabrication;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the exemplary imager pixel of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> during a stage of fabrication subsequent to that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the exemplary imager pixel of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> during a stage of fabrication subsequent to that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the exemplary imager pixel of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> during a stage of fabrication subsequent to that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a block diagram of an integrated circuit that includes a pixel array having exemplary imager pixels as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates a processor system incorporating a CMOS imager device containing one or more exemplary imager pixels according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In the following detailed description, reference is made to the accompanying drawings which form a part hereof, and in which is shown by way of illustration specific embodiments in which the invention may be practiced. These embodiments are described in sufficient detail to enable those skilled in the art to practice the invention, and it is to be understood that other embodiments may be utilized, and that structural, logical and electrical changes may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The term “substrate” is to be understood as a semiconductor-based material including silicon, silicon-on-insulator (SOI) or silicon-on-sapphire (SOS) technology, doped and undoped semiconductors, epitaxial layers of silicon supported by a base semiconductor foundation, and other semiconductor structures. Furthermore, when reference is made to a “substrate” in the following description, previous process steps may have been utilized to form regions or junctions in the base semiconductor structure or foundation. In addition, the semiconductor need not be silicon-based, but could be based on silicon-germanium, germanium, or gallium arsenide.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The term “pixel” refers to a picture element unit cell containing a photosensor and transistors for converting light radiation to an electrical signal. For purposes of illustration, a representative pixel is illustrated in the figures and description herein and, typically, fabrication of all pixels in an imager and will proceed simultaneously in a similar fashion.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The term “metal” is intended to include not only elemental metal, but can include metal with other trace metals or in various alloyed combinations with other metals as known in the semiconductor art, as long as such alloy retains the physical and chemical properties of a metal. The term “metal” is also intended to include conductive oxides of such metals when appropriate to the context in which the metal is used.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Although the invention is described herein with reference to the architecture and fabrication of one pixel, it should be understood that this is representative of a plurality of pixels in an array of an imager device such as array <b>240</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>) of an imager device <b>308</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>). In addition, although the invention is described below with reference to a CMOS imager, the invention has applicability to other solid state imaging devices having isolated pixels. The invention may also be employed more generally to isolated adjacent photosensitive structures in an integrated circuit device. The following detailed description is, therefore, not to be taken in a limiting sense, and the scope of the invention is defined only by the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Referring now to the drawings, where like elements are designated by like reference numerals, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> depicts a portion of an exemplary pixel <b>100</b> constructed in accordance with the invention. The pixel <b>100</b> contains a photosensitive element <b>188</b> which is illustratively a pinned photodiode. It should be understood, however, that the exemplary pixel <b>100</b> may include a photogate, photoconductor, or other photon-to-charge converting device, in lieu of a pinned photodiode. The photosensitive element <b>188</b> is formed of a p+ type surface region <b>124</b>, an n-type buried charge accumulation region <b>126</b> and the p-type substrate <b>110</b>. Adjacent either side of the photosensitive element <b>188</b> are doped p-wells <b>194</b>. The p-type wells <b>194</b> are formed by applying p-type dopants to selective areas of the substrate <b>110</b> up to a desired concentration.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The exemplary pixel <b>100</b> also has a transfer transistor <b>130</b> formed at a top surface of the substrate <b>110</b>. The transfer transistor <b>130</b> is adapted to transfer charges accumulated in the accumulation region <b>126</b> to a storage region <b>129</b>, which may be a floating diffusion region. The transfer transistor <b>130</b> is formed of a dielectric layer <b>133</b> over a conductive gate electrode layer <b>132</b> over a gate oxide layer <b>131</b>. Insulating sidewalls <b>134</b> are formed on the sides of the transistor gatestack. The gatestack materials may be any material known in the art and consistent with the materials specified for this invention.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The storage region <b>129</b> is doped n-type and is electrically connected to a gate of a source follower transistor <b>127</b> and a source/drain terminal of a reset transistor <b>135</b>. The source follower transistor <b>127</b> provides an output signal to a row select transistor <b>137</b> having a gate for selectively gating the output signal to a pixel array column line <b>142</b>. The reset transistor <b>135</b> resets the storage region <b>129</b> to a specified charge level V<sub>rst </sub>before each charge transfer from the accumulation region <b>126</b> of the photosensitive element <b>188</b>. Transistors <b>127</b>, <b>137</b> are coupled in series, source to drain, with the drain of the source follower transistor <b>127</b> also coupled to a voltage source V<sub>dd </sub>and the source of the row select transistor <b>137</b> that is used to selectively connect the pixel cell <b>100</b> to readout circuitry via output line <b>142</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Adjacent either side of the photosensitive element <b>188</b> is an isolation region <b>150</b>. Each isolation region <b>150</b> is an isolation trench having sidewalls <b>159</b> and a bottom <b>158</b> formed in the p-well <b>194</b> of the substrate <b>110</b>. Each isolation region <b>150</b> is illustratively a shallow trench isolation (STI) region. The isolation region <b>150</b> contains a dielectric layer <b>161</b>, which is illustratively lining both the sidewalls <b>159</b> and the bottom <b>158</b> of the trench. The dielectric layer <b>161</b> may be formed of any dielectric material, such as silicon dioxide (SiO<sub>2</sub>), and the layer <b>161</b> may be thin, within the range of about 30 to about 200 Angstroms, typically about 60 Angstroms. A transparent metal layer <b>162</b> is formed in the isolation region <b>150</b> over the dielectric layer <b>161</b>. The transparent metal layer <b>162</b> is illustrated as covering both the sidewalls <b>159</b> and the bottom <b>158</b> of the trench. It should be understood, however, that other embodiments of the transparent metal layer <b>162</b>, such as the transparent metal layer <b>162</b> only covering the sidewalls <b>159</b>, are also within the scope of the invention. In a preferred embodiment, the transparent metal layer <b>162</b> is formed of indium tin oxide, however, any conductive material that is transparent to photons is appropriate for use in the invention. The remainder of the isolation region <b>150</b> is a filler layer <b>149</b>. The filler layer <b>149</b> may be a transparent dielectric material, such as an oxide; or alternatively, the filler layer <b>149</b> may be the same material as the transparent conductive layer <b>162</b> or formed of a different transparent conductive material from that of layer <b>162</b>. The layers <b>149</b>, <b>161</b>, <b>162</b> of the isolation region <b>150</b> are planarized so that the layers are coplanar with a top surface of the substrate <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">A terminal contact <b>157</b> is connected to the transparent metal layer <b>162</b> of each isolation region <b>150</b>. The terminal contact <b>157</b> is used to apply a voltage to the transparent metal layer <b>162</b>, as desired. For example, for use with an NMOS transfer transistor <b>130</b>, it may be desirable to apply a slightly negative voltage to the transparent metal layer <b>162</b> in order to create a hole accumulation region surrounding the isolation region <b>150</b>. Alternatively, when used with a PMOS transfer transistor <b>130</b>, the voltage applied would be slightly positive. The applied voltages may be within the range of +/−300 mV, for example. In most instances, however, and especially when the isolation region <b>150</b> is incorporated into the periphery of a pixel array, the voltage applied to the transparent metal layer <b>162</b> will be used to maintain the isolation region <b>150</b> at ground potential. The voltage applied to the isolation region <b>150</b> could also be positive or negative when the region <b>150</b> is located in the periphery, depending again on whether it is in an NMOS or PMOS region. The appropriate voltage is determined by a mitigation of field lines (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A-2C</figref>) such that charges do not build up in one pixel <b>100</b> or flow into adjacent pixels.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-7</figref> depict an exemplary method of fabricating the isolation region <b>150</b> in accordance with the invention. Although <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-7</figref> illustrate only a portion of the substrate <b>110</b> with only two shallow trench isolation regions <b>150</b><i>a</i>, <b>150</b><i>b</i>, it must be understood that the present invention contemplates the simultaneous formation of a plurality of shallow trench structures at various locations on the substrate <b>110</b> to isolate all of the pixels from one another, and to provide isolation between other pixel array structures.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a portion of the pixel <b>100</b> is illustrated with a substrate <b>110</b> having various layers formed on its upper surface. A blanket layer <b>153</b> of a hard mask material, such as silicon nitride, silicon oxide, or other suitable material, is formed over a barrier oxide layer <b>156</b> over a top surface of the substrate <b>110</b>. The barrier oxide layer <b>156</b> is typically a grown oxide but can also be a deposited oxide, such as TEOS (tetra ethyl orthosilicate) or HDP (high density plasma) oxide, among others. A photoresist layer <b>155</b> is formed over the hard mask layer <b>153</b> and then patterned with a mask (not shown) and etched to obtain openings <b>152</b><i>a</i>, <b>152</b><i>b </i>in layers <b>156</b>, <b>153</b> and <b>155</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The silicon substrate <b>110</b> is then etched to form trenches <b>150</b><i>a </i>and <b>150</b><i>b</i>. Any suitable etching technique may be used to perform this step.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the photoresist layer <b>155</b> is stripped typically using an oxygen containing plasma. However, other suitable methods can be equally employed. Next, a thin layer <b>161</b> of dielectric material is formed in the trenches <b>150</b><i>a</i>, <b>150</b><i>b</i>. In one embodiment, the dielectric material is a high density plasma (HDP) oxide, a material which has a high ability to effectively fill narrow trenches. Alternatively, the dielectric layer <b>161</b> may be formed using other conventional formation techniques such as sputtering or CVD depositing. The dielectric layer <b>161</b> may be formed to a thickness of about 30 to about 200 Angstroms (typically about 60 Angstroms) by blanket depositing the dielectric material to this desired thickness over the surface of the cell <b>100</b>, thereby coating the sidewalls <b>159</b> and the bottom <b>158</b> of the trench.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a layer <b>162</b> of a transparent metal material is formed over the dielectric layer. The transparent metal material may be indium tin oxide, indium oxide, tin oxide, or any other conductive material compatible with the selected fabrication materials and transparent to photons. The selected materially should also serve as a shield to electrons within the substrate <b>110</b>. The transparent metal layer <b>162</b> may be formed to a thickness of about 100 to about 1500 Angstroms, preferably about 200 to about 300 Angstroms over the dielectric layer <b>161</b>, again, by blanket depositing the transparent conductive material over the dielectric layer <b>161</b> to the desired thickness. Other methods of forming the transparent metal layer <b>162</b> may also be employed. Alternatively, the transparent conductive material may be formed to fill the entire trench area <b>150</b><i>a</i>, <b>150</b><i>b </i>or a different transparent conductive material may be used to fill the trenches.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">If the transparent metal material does not fill the entire trench <b>150</b><i>a</i>, <b>150</b><i>b</i>, a filling step is necessary, and is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the trench <b>150</b><i>a</i>, <b>150</b><i>b </i>is filled with an insulator <b>149</b>, which may be a HDP oxide deposition or an SOD (spin-on dielectric) oxide, such that trench isolation regions <b>150</b><i>a</i>, <b>150</b><i>b </i>are completely filled. Preferably, the insulator <b>149</b> is also transparent to photons. The wafer is planarized with known techniques such as CMP, or by dry etch techniques such as resist etch-back to create a planar surface for the isolation regions <b>150</b><i>a</i>, <b>150</b><i>b </i>with the top of the substrate. Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the hard mask layer <b>153</b> is removed by conventional techniques, such as wet or dry etching, to complete the formation of trench isolation regions <b>150</b><i>a</i>, <b>150</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">At this stage, the isolation regions <b>150</b> are complete, and other processing steps are carried out to complete formation of the pixel <b>100</b>. For example, each of the transistors, <b>130</b>, <b>135</b>, <b>127</b>, and <b>127</b> may be formed using techniques as known in the art. Accumulation region <b>126</b> and charge storage region <b>129</b> may be formed by doping the region of the substrate <b>110</b> with n-type dopants. Additionally, p-wells <b>194</b> and p+ surface region <b>124</b> may be formed by doping the areas of the substrate <b>110</b> with an appropriate p- type dopant to a desired concentration.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a block diagram of an exemplary CMOS imager <b>308</b> having a pixel array <b>240</b> comprising a plurality of pixels arranged in a predetermined number of columns and rows, with each pixel cell <b>100</b> being constructed in accordance with the exemplary embodiments described above. Attached to the array <b>240</b> is signal processing circuitry, at least part of which may be formed in the substrate. The pixels of each row in array <b>240</b> are all turned on at the same time by a row select line, and the pixels of each column are selectively output by respective column select lines. A plurality of row and column lines are provided for the entire array <b>240</b>. The row lines are selectively activated by a row driver <b>245</b> in response to row address decoder <b>255</b>. The column select lines are selectively activated by a column driver <b>260</b> in response to column address decoder <b>270</b>. Thus, a row and column address is provided for each pixel.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The CMOS imager <b>308</b> is operated by the timing and control circuit <b>250</b>, which controls address decoders <b>255</b>, <b>270</b> for selecting the appropriate row and column lines for pixel readout. The control circuit <b>250</b> also controls the row and column driver circuitry <b>245</b>, <b>260</b> such that they apply driving voltages to the drive transistors of the selected row and column lines. The pixel column signals, which typically include a pixel reset signal (V<sub>rst</sub>) and a pixel image signal (V<sub>sig</sub>), are read by a sample and hold circuit <b>261</b>. V<sub>rst </sub>is read from a pixel <b>100</b> immediately after the charge storage region <b>115</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) is reset by the reset gate <b>117</b>. V<sub>sig </sub>represents the amount of charges generated by the photosensitive element <b>188</b> in response to applied light to the pixel <b>100</b>. A differential signal (V<sub>rst</sub>−V<sub>sig</sub>) is produced by differential amplifier <b>262</b> for each pixel, which is digitized by analog-to-digital converter <b>275</b> (ADC). The analog to digital converter <b>275</b> supplies the digitized pixel signals to an image processor <b>280</b> which forms and outputs a digital image.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates a processor system <b>1100</b> including an imaging device <b>308</b>, which has pixels constructed in accordance with the methods described herein. The processor system <b>1100</b> is exemplary of a system having digital circuits that could include image sensor devices. Without being limiting, such a system could include a computer system, camera system, scanner, machine vision, vehicle navigation, video phone, surveillance system, auto focus system, star tracker system, motion detection system, image stabilization system, and data compression system.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The processor-system <b>1100</b> , for example a camera system, generally comprises a central processing unit (CPU) <b>1102</b>, such as a microprocessor, that communicates with an input/output (I/O) device <b>1106</b> over a bus <b>1104</b>. Imaging device <b>308</b> also communicates with the CPU <b>1102</b> over the bus <b>1104</b>. The processor system <b>1100</b> also includes random access memory (RAM) <b>1110</b>, and can include removable memory <b>1115</b>, such as flash memory, which also communicates with CPU <b>1102</b> over the bus <b>1104</b>. Imaging device <b>308</b> may be combined with a processor, such as a CPU, digital signal processor, or microprocessor, with or without memory storage on a single integrated circuit or on a different chip than the processor.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The above description and drawings are only to be considered illustrative of exemplary embodiments which achieve the features and advantages of the invention. Modification of, and substitutions to, specific process conditions and structures can be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. Accordingly, the invention is not to be considered as being limited by the foregoing description and drawings, but is only limited by the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed as new and desired to be protected by Letters Patent of the United States is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An isolation structure comprising:
<claim-text>a trench region having sidewalls and a bottom formed in a semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dielectric layer lining at least the sidewalls of said trench region; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transparent conductive layer over said dielectric layer, wherein said transparent conductive layer comprises indium tin oxide and has a thickness of about 200 to about 300 Angstroms.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The isolation structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said dielectric layer lines the sidewalls and the bottom of the trench region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The isolation structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said dielectric layer comprises an oxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The isolation structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said dielectric layer comprises silicon dioxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The isolation structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said transparent conductive layer fills said trench region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An imager pixel comprising:
<claim-text>a photosensitive element formed in a substrate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an isolation region formed in the substrate and adjacent said photosensitive element, said isolation region comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a trench formed in the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dielectric layer lining said trench; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transparent conductive layer over the dielectric layer, wherein said transparent conductive layer has a thickness of about 200 to about 300 Angstroms.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The pixel of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising a terminal formed over the substrate adapted to apply a voltage to said transparent conductive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The pixel of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said dielectric layer comprises an oxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The pixel of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said dielectric layer has a thickness of about 100 to about 1000 Angstroms.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The pixel of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said dielectric layer comprises silicon dioxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The pixel of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising an oxide over the transparent conductive layer to fill said trench.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The pixel of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said transparent conductive layer comprises indium tin oxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The pixel of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said transparent conductive layer fills said trench region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. An array of pixels comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of pixel active areas formed in a substrate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of isolation regions formed in the substrate and adjacent the active areas, each isolation region comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>an oxide layer formed in a trench; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a layer of transparent conductive material having a thickness of about 200 to about 300 Angstroms located over said oxide layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The array of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein said oxide layer comprises any one of silicon dioxide and oxy-nitride.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The array of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein said oxide layer has a thickness of about 100 to about 1000 Angstroms.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The array of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising a layer of dielectric material over said transparent conductive layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The array of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein said transparent conductive layer comprises one of indium oxide, tin oxide, and indium tin oxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. An array of pixels comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of imager pixels formed in a substrate, wherein at least one of said pixel sensor cells comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a photosensitive element for converting photons into electrons; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an isolation trench adjacent said photosensitive element, said isolation trench comprising a transparent metal layer having a thickness of about 200 to about 300 Angstroms and an oxide layer lining sidewalls and a bottom of said isolation trench, wherein said oxide layer is formed beneath said transparent metal layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The array of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein said transparent metal layer fills said lined trench.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The array of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein said transparent metal layer comprises indium tin oxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A processing system comprising:
<claim-text>a processor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an imaging device comprising an array of pixels formed in a substrate, wherein a plurality of pixels of said array comprise:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a photosensitive element; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an isolation trench located adjacent said photosensitive element in the substrate and having sidewalls and a bottom, said isolation trench comprising a dielectric material lining the sidewalls and the bottom of the trench, and a transparent conductive layer having a thickness of about 200 to about 300 Angstroms and being located over said dielectric lining and at least one of the sidewalls and the bottom of the trench.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein said imager is a CMOS imager and said pixels are CMOS pixel cells.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein said dielectric layer comprises silicon dioxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein said transparent conductive layer comprises indium tin oxide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. A pixel imager cell comprising:
<claim-text>at least one active area formed in a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one isolation region formed in the substrate and adjacent the at least one active area, each isolation region comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a trench having sidewalls and a bottom;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an oxide layer formed on the sidewalls and bottom of said trench; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a layer of indium tin oxide formed over said oxide layer, said indium tin oxide having a thickness of about 200 to about 300 Angstroms; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a terminal contact connected to said layer of indium tin oxide for applying a voltage potential to said isolation region.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
