<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297964-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297964</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11311008</doc-number>
<date>20051219</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>64</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2504661</main-classification>
<further-classification> 40542</further-classification>
<further-classification> 522871</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Photoluminescent wall marker and method of making</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2387512</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hilberg</name>
<date>19451000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4401050</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Britt et al.</name>
<date>19830800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5415911</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Zampa et al.</name>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5724909</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Pitman et al.</name>
<date>19980300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5904017</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Glatz et al.</name>
<date>19990500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 522871</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6237266</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Tassey et al.</name>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 40542</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6253478</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kalavity</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6307207</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Burbank</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2504621</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6487802</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Suen</name>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6508900</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kendall et al.</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0106995</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kim</name>
<date>20050500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>446473</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>www.mss-int.com/space1.html.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2504661</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 40542</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 522871</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070138408</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070621</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Savagian</last-name>
<first-name>Michael D.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Germantown</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mess</last-name>
<first-name>Steven H.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Franklin</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Quarles &amp; Brady LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Brady Worldwide, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Milwaukee</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Porta</last-name>
<first-name>David</first-name>
<department>2884</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Sung</last-name>
<first-name>Christine</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A photoluminescent wall marker includes an elongated base having an upper edge and a lower edge. The lower edge of the base is integral with an upper edge of a photoluminescent panel. The upper edge of the photoluminescent panel is integral with the base lower edge and defined by a fold line extending longitudinally between the base and the photoluminescent panel. The base and photoluminescent panel are flexible in a transverse direction allowing the wall marker to be stored in roll form in an unassembled configuration.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="160.02mm" wi="105.07mm" file="US07297964-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="228.01mm" wi="118.53mm" file="US07297964-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="185.08mm" wi="105.33mm" file="US07297964-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="185.50mm" wi="106.17mm" file="US07297964-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="186.52mm" wi="112.95mm" file="US07297964-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCES TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Not Applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Not Applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">This invention relates to photoluminescent wall markers, and in particular to a roll up, fold up photoluminescent wall marker.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Photoluminescent marking of egress pathways has gained importance over the past ten years. This is the result of both the advent of high performance, long afterglow strontium aluminate pigments, and the recognition of the need for illuminated pathway markings in emergency, blackout conditions. In densely populated buildings, increasing safety cues can result in less hesitation during emergency exits. For these reasons, it is becoming common to require that emergency exits be marked with photoluminescent guidance systems. An example of a photoluminescent guidance sign is shown in U.S. Pat. No. 6,487,802.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Guidance cues can be provided by marking the edges of the egress pathway. This is usually done low to the ground, as in many emergencies there is the presence of smoke, and combustion by products, which rise due to heat. As a result the clearest view is of the lowest portions of a pathway. For this reason the optimum placement of egress markings is on either the floor, or the lowest portion of the wall. An example of this type of product is shown in U.S. Pat. No. 5,904,017, where a photoluminescent strip is extruded into a floor molding, or other attachable material.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Commercial, long afterglow photoluminescent signs, markers, and tapes are usually compounded from strontium aluminate pigments. Other pigments, such as zinc sulfide can also be used, however the performance isn't quite as long lasting. All of the pigments behave in the same general way by absorbing ultraviolet (UV) light radiation and discharging visible light. When the UV light source is removed, the afterglow of visible light discharge continues for some time, although it does decay eventually. The useful life of a photoluminescent sign, during a blackout, is dependant on this property. Without sufficient UV light to charge the sign, the afterglow is limited.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Emergency exits of many buildings are illuminated by fluorescent lighting. Fluorescent lighting works by the internal UV discharge causing the fluorescent coated layer to charge and give off visible light. This effect is not photoluminescent, because as soon as the UV charging is removed, the fluorescence ceases. The output of a fluorescent lamp is primarily visible light, however a small percentage of the UV light is emitted through the coated layer and the glass. This allows a fluorescent lamp to be used as a source for charging photoluminescent signs, markers, and tapes. While illumination levels in an office space may be high, to allow for efficient operations, illumination levels in emergency exit pathways is kept to a much lower level for energy efficiency. This level varies, depending upon the building code in effect and the building owner's preference. In one large metropolitan city, the minimum level can be as low as 2 foot-candles. Making the most efficient use of the illumination provided is an important factor in providing the most conspicuous egress marking.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Photoluminescent egress marking can be applied to the floor, providing a photoluminescent surface that is nearly perpendicular to overhead illumination and, depending upon observer position and height, at a close to perpendicular angle to viewing as well. This generally results in both good illumination of the photoluminescent tape as well as good, viewable brightness of the marker luminance in black-out conditions.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Sometimes the egress marking cannot be applied to the floor, either due to a difficult to bond surface, difficulty in cleaning or otherwise preparing the surface for bonding, or other obstacles. In this case the marking is applied along the lower portion of the wall, near the floor. If a flat tape-like material is used, with its photoluminescent surface parallel to the wall, the tape is at an acute angle to both illumination from overhead lighting and observation by an upright viewer. This angle can diminish the effectiveness of the marking and slow recognition by the viewer in a black-out, emergency situation.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A solution to the problem of the performance of wall mounted photoluminescent markings is to mount the marking at an angle to the wall. The greater the angle, the more illumination will be provided to it by the overhead lighting and the more observable it will be in a black-out by an upright viewer. This has been recognized by some providers of photoluminescent wall markings in the form of an angled mount for a photoluminescent tape or insert to be applied to. Angled mounts can be manufactured from either stamped or extruded metal or plastic.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The disadvantage of the current angled mounts is that they must be made in rigid lengths. Providing the angle feature requires the mount to have a significant third dimension, which adds greatly to its longitudinal stiffniess. This means that the length of the mounts is restricted to the greatest length that can be efficiently made, stored, transported, and installed. Even eight foot lengths present a challenge for convenient handling, especially when being transported up emergency exits on multi-story buildings. Flat tapes and flat mounts for tapes and markings can be provided and dispensed from convenient rolls in much greater lengths, but do not supply the angled display feature. Accordingly, a need exists for an effective photoluminescent wall marker that can be efficiently stored and transported.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present invention provides a photoluminescent wall marker including upwardly facing photoluminescent material and can be stored in roll form. In one embodiment, the wall marker includes an elongated base having an upper edge and a lower edge. The lower edge of the base is integral with an upper edge of a photoluminescent panel. The upper edge of the photoluminescent panel is integral with the base lower edge and defined by a fold line extending longitudinally between the base and the photoluminescent panel. The base and photoluminescent panel are flexible in a transverse direction allowing the wall marker to be stored in roll form in an unassembled configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A general objective of the present invention is to provide an effective wall marker that can be efficiently stored and transported. This objective is accomplished by providing a wall marker that can be stored in roll form and dispensed with an angled photoluminescent panel.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The foregoing and other objectives and advantages of the invention will appear from the following description. In the description, reference is made to the accompanying drawings which form a part hereof, and in which there is shown by way of illustration a preferred embodiment of the invention. Such embodiment does not necessarily represent the full scope of the invention, however, and reference is made therefore to the claims herein for interpreting the scope of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a plan view of a wall marker incorporating the present invention in an unassembled configuration;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an end view of the wall marker of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an end view of the wall marker of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in an assembled configuration;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an end view of another embodiment of a wall marker incorporating the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an end view of yet another embodiment of a wall marker incorporating the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A preferred embodiment of a photoluminescent wall marker <b>10</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref> can be stored and transported in an unassembled configuration (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>) in roll form and dispensed in an elongated strip that is folded to form a three-dimensional structure in an assembled configuration (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) for affixing to a wall <b>18</b>. The three-dimensional structure includes an upwardly facing photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> having a photoluminescent material <b>14</b> charged by ambient light.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The wall marker <b>10</b> includes an elongated substrate <b>16</b> on which strips <b>20</b>, <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material and the photoluminescent material <b>14</b> are affixed defining a base <b>32</b>, the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>, a support segment <b>34</b>, and an anchor <b>36</b>. Preferably, the base <b>32</b>, photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>, support segment <b>34</b>, and anchor <b>36</b> are separated from each other by fold lines <b>42</b>, <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> extending substantially the entire length, i.e. in a longitudinal direction, of the elongated substrate <b>16</b>. Advantageously, the stiffening material has sufficient flexibility along the transverse direction, i.e. transverse to the longitudinal direction, to be wound into a roll having an axis substantially transverse to the fold lines <b>42</b>, <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> which allows the wall marker <b>10</b> to be rolled into roll form for storage and shipping.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The substrate <b>16</b> is a length of elongated flexible material which integrally joins the base <b>32</b>, photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>, support segment <b>34</b>, and anchor <b>36</b> at their respective edges. The substrate <b>16</b> includes a top surface <b>52</b> and a bottom surface <b>54</b> defined between ends <b>56</b>, <b>58</b> and elongated upper and lower edges <b>62</b>, <b>64</b>. Preferably, the substrate <b>16</b> has a width (i.e. the distance between the edges <b>62</b>, <b>64</b>) substantially equal to the width of the wall marker <b>10</b> in the unfolded unassembled configuration. In a preferred embodiment, the substrate <b>16</b> is a tape material having an adhesive, such as a pressure sensitive adhesive, heat-activated adhesive, and the like, applied to the bottom surface <b>54</b>. The tape material can be any single or multi-layer material known in the art, such as paper, plastic, metal, a combination thereof, and the like, without departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The strip <b>20</b> of photoluminescent material <b>14</b> forming the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> having upper and lower edges <b>66</b>, <b>68</b> is fixed relative to the top surface <b>52</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> along the length of the substrate <b>16</b> between the substrate longitudinal edges <b>62</b>, <b>64</b>. Preferably, the strip <b>20</b> of photoluminescent material <b>14</b> is a photoluminescent tape including strontium aluminate pigments which absorb ultraviolet light radiation and discharge visible light. Of course, other photoluminescent materials can be used, such as zinc sulfide, without departing from the scope of the invention. A photoluminescent panel strip <b>22</b> of stiffening material interposed between the strip <b>20</b> of photoluminescent material <b>14</b> and substrate <b>16</b> stiffens the upwardly facing photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In the embodiment disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>, additional strips <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material are provided to increase the rigidity of the wall marker <b>10</b> when in the assembled configuration. A support segment strip <b>24</b> of stiffening material forming the support segment <b>34</b> having upper and lower edges <b>72</b>, <b>74</b> is fixed to the top surface <b>52</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> adjacent to the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>. Preferably, the support segment <b>34</b> is separated from the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> by the fold line <b>42</b> extending the length of the substrate <b>16</b> between the upper edge <b>72</b> of the support segment <b>34</b> and the lower edge <b>68</b> of the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>. In the assembled configuration, the wall marker <b>10</b> is folded along the fold line <b>42</b> to form the support segment <b>34</b> extending from the lower edge <b>68</b> of the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> toward the base <b>32</b> and stiffened by the stiffening material. The support segment <b>34</b> spaces the lower edge <b>68</b> of the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> from the base <b>32</b>, and thus the wall <b>18</b> when affixed thereto, to face the photoluminescent material <b>14</b> upwardly.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">A base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material forming the base <b>32</b> having upper and lower edges <b>76</b>, <b>78</b> is affixed to the top surface <b>52</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> between the upper edge <b>66</b> of the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> and upper edge <b>62</b> of the substrate <b>16</b>. In the assembled configuration, the wall marker <b>10</b> is folded along the fold line <b>44</b> between the base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material and photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> to form the base <b>32</b> affixable to the wall <b>18</b>. In the embodiment disclosed herein, a doubled sided pressure sensitive adhesive tape <b>86</b> affixed to a top surface <b>80</b> of the base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material adhesively fixes the base <b>32</b>, and thus the wall marker <b>10</b>, to the wall <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">An anchor strip <b>28</b> of stiffening material forming the anchor <b>36</b> having upper and lower edges <b>82</b>, <b>84</b> is fixed to the top surface <b>52</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> between the lower edge <b>74</b> of the support segment <b>34</b> and lower edge <b>64</b> of the substrate <b>16</b>. In the assembled configuration, the wall marker <b>10</b> is folded along the fold line <b>46</b> between the anchor strip <b>28</b> of stiffening material and support segment <b>34</b> to form the anchor <b>36</b> affixed, such as by the adhesive on the bottom surface <b>54</b> of the substrate <b>16</b>, to the base <b>32</b>. The anchor <b>36</b> fixes the height of the lower edge <b>74</b> of the support segment <b>34</b> relative to the base <b>32</b> to ensure the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> faces upwardly.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The strips <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material extend along substantially the entire length of the substrate <b>16</b>. Preferably, the strips <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material are sufficiently thin to allow a user to easily cut through the stiffening material when cutting the wall marker <b>10</b> to a desired length. However, the strips <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material can be discontinuous having transverse cut lines (not shown) void of stiffening material that allow a user to cut the wall marker <b>10</b> to predetermined lengths without having to cut through the stiffening material. Advantageously, a plurality of transverse cut lines can also be provided to increase the flexibility of the wall marker <b>10</b> in the transverse direction.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The stiffening material can be any material that adds rigidity to the wall marker <b>10</b> in the longitudinal direction. Preferably, the stiffening material is a metal, such as full hard aluminum foil having a thickness of approximately 0.008 inches which is joined to the substrate <b>16</b>. Advantageously, the metal foil provides sufficient rigidity to the wall marker <b>10</b> while allowing the wall marker <b>10</b> to be rolled up into a roll. Of course other stiffening materials, such as other metals, plastic, paper, and the like, can be used without departing from the scope of the invention. Moreover, the stiffening material can be joined to the substrate <b>16</b>, as described below, or formed as an integral part of the substrate, such as by extruding the substrate and strips <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material together as a single piece, without departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The wall marker <b>10</b> can be made starting with a 1.0 inch wide photoluminescent tape laminated to a first strip of metal foil of about the same width to form the strip <b>20</b> of photoluminescent material <b>14</b> affixed to the photoluminescent panel strip <b>22</b> of stiffening material. A second strip of metal foil approximately 1.5 inches wide is then affixed to one side of the double sided pressure sensitive adhesive tape <b>86</b> to form the base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material having an adhesive coated top surface <b>80</b>. A release liner (not shown) covering the adhesive on the other side of the double sided pressure sensitive adhesive tape <b>86</b> is left in place until the wall marker <b>10</b> is adhesively affixed to the wall <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material is then affixed to a non-adhesive side (top surface <b>52</b>) of a 3.5 inch wide strip of adhesive tape forming the substrate <b>16</b> having an adhesive side. Of course, a double-sided adhesive tape can be used as the substrate <b>16</b>, and the base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material can be affixed to an adhesive side of the tape without departing from the scope of the invention. One edge of the base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material is aligned with the upper edge <b>62</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> to form the base <b>32</b> of the wall marker <b>10</b> which can be adhesively fixed to the wall <b>18</b> using the outwardly facing side of the double sided pressure sensitive adhesive tape <b>86</b> affixed to the base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The 1.0 inch wide photoluminescent tape laminated to the photoluminescent panel strip <b>22</b> of stiffening material is then affixed to the top surface <b>52</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> adjacent to the base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material forming the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>. The support segment strip <b>24</b> of stiffening material, in the form of a 0.5 inch wide metal foil, is then affixed to the top surface <b>52</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> adjacent to the photoluminescent panel strip <b>22</b> of stiffening material on which the photoluminescent material <b>14</b> is affixed. Finally, the anchor strip <b>28</b> of stiffening material in the form of a 0.5 inch wide metal foil, is then affixed to the top surface <b>52</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> adjacent to the support segment strip <b>24</b> of stiffening material to form the anchor <b>36</b> and complete the wall marker <b>10</b> in the unassembled configuration, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Advantageously, following the application of the anchor strip <b>28</b> of stiffening material to the substrate <b>16</b>, the wall marker <b>10</b> in the unassembled configuration can be rolled up into roll form for easy storage and shipping.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Although the strips <b>20</b>, <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material and photoluminescent material <b>14</b> are described above as being affixed to the substrate <b>16</b> sequentially, the strips <b>20</b>, <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> can be applied to the substrate <b>16</b> simultaneously, as a single strip of foil having a width substantially equal to the substrate <b>16</b> followed by a strip of photoluminescent material <b>14</b>, or individually in a staggered fashion without departing from the scope of the invention. In addition, the widths of the strips <b>20</b>, <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b>, or spacing of the fold lines <b>42</b>, <b>44</b>, <b>46</b>, can be varied to change the angle A of the upwardly facing photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>, such that the angle of the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> ranges from nearly vertical to nearly horizontal without departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Preferably, the fold lines <b>42</b>, <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> are predetermined longitudinal lines formed by abutting the strips <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material, as disclosed above, to provide longitudinal lines between the strips <b>22</b>, <b>24</b>, <b>26</b>, <b>28</b> of stiffening material that are easy to fold. Alternatively, marks formed, such as by etching, embossing, printing, creasing, and the like, can be made on the wall marker <b>10</b> indicating where the user folds the wall marker <b>10</b> to transform the wall marker <b>10</b> from the unassembled configuration to the assembled configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In use, a length of the wall marker <b>10</b> is unrolled in the unassembled configuration from a roll and cut to the desired length. The base <b>32</b> of the wall marker <b>10</b> is folded back away from the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> along the fold line <b>44</b> between the base <b>32</b> and photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>. The support segment <b>34</b> is then folded back away from the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> along the fold line <b>42</b> between the support segment <b>34</b> and photoluminescent panel <b>12</b>. The anchor <b>36</b> is then folded downwardly from the support segment <b>34</b> and the release liner (not shown) is removed to expose the adhesive on the bottom surface <b>54</b> of the substrate <b>16</b>. The edges <b>62</b>, <b>64</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> are then aligned, and the anchor <b>36</b> is pressed against the adhesively coated bottom surface <b>54</b> of the substrate <b>16</b> to adhesively affix the anchor <b>36</b> to the base <b>32</b> and form the wall marker <b>10</b> in the assembled configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">A user affixes the wall marker <b>10</b> to the wall <b>18</b> by removing the release liner covering the adhesive on the top surface <b>80</b> of the base strip <b>26</b> of stiffening material forming the base <b>32</b> and positioning the wall marker <b>10</b>, such that the photoluminescent panel <b>12</b> faces upwardly. The base <b>32</b> of the wall marker <b>10</b> is then pressed against the wall <b>18</b> to adhesively fix the base <b>32</b>, and thus the wall marker <b>10</b>, to the wall <b>18</b>. Although adhesively fixing the wall marker <b>10</b> to the wall <b>18</b> is disclosed, the wall marker <b>10</b> can be fixed to the wall <b>18</b> using other methods, such as mechanical fasteners, without departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Another embodiment of a photoluminescent marker <b>110</b> disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, includes a photoluminescent panel <b>112</b> in which only a portion of the photoluminescent material <b>114</b> faces upwardly in an assembled configuration. This particular embodiment is suitable for use in an area in which sufficient light is reflected off of a floor to charge the downwardly facing photoluminescent material <b>114</b>, the marker <b>110</b> is placed on a horizontal surface, or the marker <b>110</b> is placed at a height on the wall <b>118</b> in which the downwardly facing photoluminescent material <b>114</b> receives sufficient light from other sources.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the wall marker <b>110</b> includes the photoluminescent panel <b>112</b> interposed between a base <b>132</b> and an anchor <b>136</b> integrally joined by an elongated substrate <b>116</b>. As in the embodiment disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>, the base <b>132</b> includes an adhesive tape <b>186</b> that affixes the wall marker <b>110</b> to the wall <b>118</b>. Likewise, the anchor <b>136</b> fixes a lower edge <b>168</b> of the photoluminescent panel <b>112</b> relative to the base <b>132</b>. In this embodiment, however, the photoluminescent panel <b>112</b> bows outwardly away from the base <b>132</b>. As a result, only a portion of photoluminescent material <b>114</b> faces upwardly when affixed to the wall <b>118</b> in the assembled configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In a third embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a wall marker <b>210</b> incorporating the present invention includes an elongated substrate <b>216</b> on which a strip <b>226</b> of stiffening material is affixed. The strip <b>226</b> of stiffening material is folded along a fold line <b>244</b> extending in the longitudinal direction along the strip <b>226</b> of stiffening material to support a photoluminescent panel <b>212</b> integrally joined to a base <b>232</b>. The photoluminescent panel <b>212</b> includes a strip of photoluminescent material <b>214</b>, as described above. Likewise, the base <b>232</b> includes an adhesive tape <b>286</b> that adhesively fixes the wall marker <b>210</b> to a wall <b>218</b>. Although, the stiffening material disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> extends laterally a distance between an upper edge <b>266</b> of the photoluminescent panel <b>212</b> toward an upper edge <b>262</b> of the substrate <b>216</b> to stiffen the base <b>232</b> fixed to the wall <b>218</b>, the stiffening material can be provided only across the fold line <b>244</b> to support the photoluminescent panel <b>212</b> at a desired angle in an upwardly facing position without departing from the scope of the invention. Of course, if the strip <b>226</b> of stiffening material extends across the entire width of the wall marker <b>210</b>, a separate substrate <b>216</b> is not required.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The present invention is not limited to the above described applications, and one skilled in the art will be able to incorporate the present invention into other applications that fall within the scope of the claims. Moreover, while there has been shown and described what is at present considered the preferred embodiment of the invention, it will be obvious to those skilled in the art that various changes and modifications can be made therein without departing from the scope of the invention defined by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A photoluminescent wall marker, said wall marker comprising:
<claim-text>an elongated substrate having a top surface and a bottom surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fold line formed in said substrate and extending along a length of said substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a strip of photoluminescent material affixed to said top surface extending along a length of said substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a strip of stiffening material affixed to said top surface adjacent said strip of photoluminescent material, wherein said marker is storable in roll form and upon being dispensed is folded along said fold line to face at least a portion of said strip of photoluminescent material upwardly when fixing said wall marker to a wall.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, in which said fold line is formed between said strip of stiffening material and said strip of photoluminescent material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, in which said strip of stiffening material extends across said fold line to support said portion of said strip of photoluminescent material upwardly when fixing said wall marker to a wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, including an adhesive applied to said top surface of said substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, in which said photoluminescent material is applied over a strip of stiffening material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, in which said stiffening material is metal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, in which said stiffening material is formed as an integral part of said substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A method of using a photoluminescent wall marker, said method comprising:
<claim-text>unrolling a length of wall marker from a roll, said wall marker including a strip of photoluminescent material affixed to an elongated substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>folding said substrate along a fold line extending the length of said length of wall marker adjacent said strip of photoluminescent material;</claim-text>
<claim-text>affixing said substrate to a wall with at least a portion of said photoluminescent material facing upwardly.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, in which affixing said substrate to said wall includes adhesively affixing said substrate to said wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, in which folding said substrate along a fold line includes folding said substrate along a fold line between a strip of stiffening material and said strip of photoluminescent material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, including affixing said stiffening material to said substrate adjacent to said strip of photoluminescent material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, in which said stiffening material is a metal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, in which said strip of photoluminescent material is fixed to a stiffening material affixed to said substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, including rolling said wall marker into a roll about an axis transverse to said fold line.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A photoluminescent wall marker, said wall marker comprising:
<claim-text>an elongated base having an upper edge and a lower edge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a photoluminescent panel having an upper edge and a lower edge, said upper edge of said photoluminescent panel being integral with said base lower edge and being defined by a fold line extending longitudinally between said base and said photoluminescent panel, said base and photoluminescent panel being flexible in a transverse direction allowing the wall marker to be stored in roll form in an unassembled configuration.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, including a strip of stiffening material extending across said fold line to support said photoluminescent panel facing upwardly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, including a support segment having an upper edge and a lower edge, said upper edge of said support segment being integral with said photoluminescent panel lower edge and being defined by a fold line extending longitudinally between said support segment and said photoluminescent panel, said support segment spacing said photoluminescent panel lower edge from said base in an assembled configuration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, including an anchor having an upper edge and a lower edge, said upper edge of said support segment being integral with one of said photoluminescent panel lower edge and said support segment and being defined by a fold line extending longitudinally between said support segment and said one of said photoluminescent panel lower edge and said support segment lower edge, said anchor anchoring said one of said photoluminescent panel lower edge and said support segment lower edge relative to said base in an assembled configuration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, in which photoluminescent panel includes a photoluminescent material applied over a strip of stiffening material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The wall marker as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, in which said stiffening material is metal.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
