<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296493-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296493</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10903667</doc-number>
<date>20040730</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>682</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 74470</main-classification>
<further-classification> 7447328</further-classification>
<further-classification> 7447335</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Offset transmission shift lever and isolator arrangement</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4811921</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Whitaker et al.</name>
<date>19890300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>244234</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5347881</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Watson et al.</name>
<date>19940900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7447329</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5452623</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Knight</name>
<date>19950900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7447329</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5845534</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kim</name>
<date>19981200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7447312</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6360627</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Buckingham et al.</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 744733</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 74470</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7447335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7447328</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060021459</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060202</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Buckingham</last-name>
<first-name>David G</first-name>
<address>
<city>Berkley</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Slifco</last-name>
<first-name>William</first-name>
<address>
<city>Macomb Township</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Schumacher</last-name>
<first-name>Michael</first-name>
<address>
<city>Royal Oak</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jurecko</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas A.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Chrysler LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Auburn Hills</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Fenstermacher</last-name>
<first-name>David M.</first-name>
<department>3682</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An offset transmission shift lever assembly and isolator arrangement is provided. The shift lever assembly includes an insert arranged to fit over a transmission shift stub. An isolator is provided that encircles the insert and is formed thereto. The isolator has a varying outside diameter such upon assembling the isolator into a canister that encircles the isolator, a portion of the isolator outside diameter is press fit into the canister and another portion of the isolator outside diameter does not contact the canister thereby leaving a gap between the canister and the isolator. The isolator also includes axial holes formed in a lower end thereof and extending axially for a portion of the isolator length. Affixed to the canister is a shift lever aligned parallel to and offset from the shift stub. A fastener is provided for securing the shift lever assembly via the insert to the shift stub.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="189.74mm" wi="161.04mm" file="US07296493-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="208.20mm" wi="161.46mm" file="US07296493-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="145.71mm" wi="149.78mm" file="US07296493-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to a shift lever arrangement for a transmission, and, more particularly, to an improved offset transmission shift lever and isolator arrangement for a motor vehicle.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Generally, there are known advantages for using an offset shift lever assembly arrangement that fastens to a transmission shift stub extending into a vehicle interior compartment. One primary advantage is being able to easily remove the shift lever assembly from the transmission by simply unfastening the shift lever assembly from the transmission shift stub. This and other advantages are described in commonly owned U.S. Pat. No. 6,360,627, which is hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Automotive vehicles of today are being continually refined to improve several areas of performance, such as noise, vibration and harshness (NVH) that would be potentially perceived by a vehicle occupant. These refinements include, among other things, improvements to existing isolation arrangements for a vehicle powertrain, such as improvements to transmission shift lever isolators. Vibrations from powertrain components, such as an engine or a driveline, can be potentially transmitted through a transmission to a shift lever via the transmission shift stub. These transmitted vibrations may result in a visible shaking motion of the transmission shift lever that would be apparent to a vehicle occupant.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Thus, while known transmission shift lever assemblies and known isolator arrangements work for their intended purpose, there is still a need for an improved offset transmission shift lever isolation arrangement capable of further reducing the potential for vibrations to be transmitted from the powertrain to the shift lever.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Accordingly, an improved offset transmission shift lever and isolator arrangement is provided. In accordance with one aspect of the present invention, an offset shift lever and isolator arrangement is provided that includes a shift stub connected to the transmission and extending into a vehicle compartment. The shift stub includes an axially threaded bore for receiving a fastener. An insert is provided and arranged to fit over the shift stub. The insert includes a partially closed upper end with a fastener shank extending therethrough. An isolator is provided that is formed over and encircles the insert. The isolator includes an upper end and a lower end and a plurality of axial holes formed in the lower end of the isolator and partially extending toward the upper end of the isolator. The isolator has an outside diameter at the upper end that is smaller than an outside diameter at the lower end. A canister is provided and encircles the isolator. The canister includes an inner surface and an outer surface, an open lower end for receiving the isolator and an upper end with an opening for receiving a fastener. The isolator is arranged to be press fit into the canister with the isolator lower end outside diameter being press fit against the canister inner surface and the isolator having a space between the canister inner surface and the isolator upper end outside diameter. A shift lever is provided and affixed to the canister outer surface, and the shift lever is aligned generally parallel and axially off center to the shift stub. A fastener is provided for securing the insert to the shift stub, and the fastener is arranged to threadably engage the threaded bore in the shift stub. The isolator is arranged to absorb powertrain excitations applied to the shift stub to isolate the excitations from the shift lever.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Other aspects, features, and advantages of the present invention will become more fully apparent from the following detailed description of the preferred embodiment, the appended claims, and in the accompanying drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a partial cross-sectional view of an offset transmission shift lever assembly and isolator arrangement showing a canister, an isolator and an insert in cross-section in accordance with the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a view along line A-A of the shift lever and isolator arrangement shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in accordance with the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Referring now to the drawings, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> illustrate an exemplary embodiment of an offset transmission shift lever and isolator arrangement. In accordance with one aspect of the present invention, an offset transmission shift lever and isolation assembly <b>10</b> is provided. Shift lever and isolation assembly <b>10</b> includes an insert <b>20</b> sized to fit securely over a manual transmission shift stub <b>50</b> that extends into a vehicle passenger compartment. Insert <b>20</b> is preferably made of steel and has an inner side <b>30</b>, an outer side <b>40</b> and a series of circular apertures <b>60</b>. Insert <b>20</b> also includes an upper end <b>25</b> with an opening <b>35</b> for receiving a fastener shank.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Formed to the outer side <b>40</b> of insert <b>20</b> is a preferably elastomeric isolator <b>70</b>. Isolator <b>70</b> is generally cylindrically shaped with an open lower end <b>80</b> and an upper end <b>90</b> molded over the upper end <b>25</b> of insert <b>20</b>. Isolator <b>70</b> also includes an opening <b>100</b> in upper end <b>90</b> arranged to provide clearance for a fastener. Isolator <b>70</b> has an inside diameter <b>110</b>, an upper end outside diameter <b>120</b> that is smaller than a lower end outside diameter <b>130</b>. Isolator <b>70</b> is preferably molded with insert <b>20</b> positioned within so as to allow isolator <b>70</b> to better grip insert <b>20</b> and allow elastomeric material to flow into apertures <b>60</b>. It should be appreciated that the isolator material can form around and to insert <b>20</b> without the use of apertures <b>60</b>. In addition, isolator <b>70</b> further includes a series of axial holes <b>125</b> positioned circumferentially around lower end <b>80</b> between inside diameter <b>110</b> and lower end outside diameter <b>130</b>. Axial holes <b>125</b> extend, along with lower end outside diameter <b>130</b>, from lower end <b>80</b> toward upper end <b>90</b> for a distance of one-third the axial length of isolator <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Encircling the isolator is a generally rigid canister <b>140</b>. Canister <b>140</b> includes axial serrations <b>150</b> that cut into isolator <b>70</b> during assembly when isolator <b>70</b> is press fit into canister <b>140</b>. Specifically, axial serrations <b>150</b> are arranged to cut into isolator <b>70</b> lower end outside diameter <b>130</b> during the assembly press fit operation. Canister <b>140</b> also includes an opening <b>155</b> for receiving a fastener <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Affixed to canister <b>140</b> is a shift lever <b>170</b>. Shift lever <b>170</b> is preferably welded to an outside diameter <b>180</b> of canister <b>140</b>. Shift lever <b>170</b> is positioned generally parallel to shift stub <b>50</b> and offset axially by the radial distance of the canister outside diameter <b>180</b> of canister <b>140</b> from a centerline of shift stub <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Shift stub <b>50</b> is provided with a machined flat section <b>190</b> to aid with assembly and orientation of shift lever assembly <b>10</b> to transmission shift stub <b>50</b>. Flat section <b>190</b> acts as an indexing feature and mates with a corresponding flat section <b>200</b> on insert <b>20</b>. The combination of indexing features <b>190</b> and <b>200</b> provide for orientation of the shift lever <b>170</b> during assembly of shift lever assembly <b>10</b> to transmission shift stub <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">To install isolator assembly <b>10</b> to the vehicle transmission stub <b>50</b>, insert <b>20</b> is inserted over shift stub <b>50</b> with insert indexing flat <b>200</b> aligning with shift stub flat <b>190</b>. Fastener <b>160</b> is then used to secure insert <b>20</b> to transmission shift stub <b>50</b>. Fastener shank <b>165</b> passes through canister opening <b>155</b>, isolator opening <b>100</b>, insert opening <b>35</b> and then into threaded bore <b>168</b> of transmission shift stub <b>50</b>. Fastener head <b>163</b> directly contacts insert upper end <b>25</b> and secures insert <b>20</b> and thereby isolator assembly <b>10</b> to shift stub <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Upon inserting isolator <b>70</b> into canister <b>140</b>, there is a designed gap <b>210</b> between isolator upper end outside diameter <b>120</b> and canister inside diameter <b>220</b>. In operation, gap <b>210</b> in combination with axial holes <b>125</b> provide isolation of powertrain vibrations and excitations applied to shift stub <b>50</b> from canister <b>140</b> and shift lever <b>170</b>. Although isolator <b>70</b> directly interfaces via a press fit with canister <b>140</b> at isolator lower end outside diameter <b>130</b>, axial serrations <b>150</b> provide for a minimum press fit while preventing movement of isolator lower end outside diameter <b>130</b> relative to canister <b>140</b>. In addition, axial holes <b>125</b> effectively reduce the stiffness of the rubber for the axial length of isolator lower end outside diameter <b>130</b> that contacts canister <b>140</b> via a press fit. The minimum press fit combined with axial holes <b>125</b> and gap <b>210</b> mentioned above, allow shift stub <b>50</b> to vibrate from powertrain excitations without transferring such vibrations to shift lever <b>170</b> thereby preventing a vehicle occupant from sensing a vibrating shift lever. Specifically, this combination acts as a predamper and allows the transmission shift stub <b>50</b> to move back and forth without exciting or moving the shift lever <b>170</b>. Incorporation of voids and varying diameters into isolator <b>70</b> provides for superior benefits to that of a multi-durometer isolator without the added cost and complexity in molding and assembling the isolator assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The foregoing description constitutes the embodiments devised by the inventors for practicing the invention. It is apparent, however, that the invention is susceptible to modification, variation, and change that will become obvious to those skilled in the art. Inasmuch as the foregoing description is intended to enable one skilled in the pertinent art to practice the invention, it should not be construed to be limited thereby but should be construed to include such aforementioned obvious variations and be limited only by the proper scope or fair meaning of the accompanying claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An offset shift lever and isolator arrangement for a vehicle transmission, the arrangement comprising:
<claim-text>a shift stub connected to the transmission and extending into a vehicle compartment, the shift stub having an axially threaded bore;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an insert arranged to fit over the shift stub, the insert having a partially closed upper end with a fastener shank extending therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an isolator encircling and formed over the insert, the isolator having an upper end and a lower end, the isolator having a plurality of axial holes formed in the lower end of the isolator and partially extending toward the upper end of the isolator, the isolator having an outside diameter at the upper end that is smaller than an outside diameter at the lower end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a canister encircling the isolator and having an inner surface and an outer surface, the canister having an open lower end for receiving the isolator and an upper end with an opening for receiving a fastener, wherein the isolator is arranged to be press fit into the canister with the isolator lower end outside diameter being press fit against the canister inner surface and the isolator having a space between the canister inner surface and the isolator upper end diameter;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shift lever affixed to the canister outer surface, the shift lever being aligned generally parallel and axially off center to the shift stub; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fastener for securing the insert to the shift stub, the fastener arranged to threadably engage the threaded bore in the shift stub;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the isolator is arranged to absorb powertrain excitations applied to the shift stub to isolate the excitations from the shift lever.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the insert further includes a plurality of apertures formed therein, and wherein the isolator is formed over the insert and into the apertures.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the canister further includes axial serrations on its inner surface for a portion of the inner surface that contacts the isolator lower end outside diameter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the isolator comprises an elastomeric isolator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the shift stub further includes a flat portion on an end of the stub extending into the vehicle interior compartment, and wherein the insert further includes a flat portion on an upper end thereof, the insert flat portion arranged to align with the shift stub flat portion during assembly of the insert onto the shift stub.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the shift stub comprises a manual transmission shift stub.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality axial holes in the isolator comprises twelve holes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the isolator upper end outside diameter extends axially from the isolator upper end toward the isolator lower end for a length of two-thirds of a total axial length of the isolator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the isolator lower end outside diameter extends axially from the isolator lower end toward the isolator upper end until mating with the isolator upper end outside diameter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The offset transmission shift lever and isolation arrangement of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the isolator further comprises an inside diameter, and wherein the plurality of axial holes are centered radially between the isolator inside diameter and the isolator lower end outside diameter.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
