<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298545-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298545</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11318234</doc-number>
<date>20051223</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>137</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>35</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>2</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359330</main-classification>
<further-classification>356301</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">High repetition rate visible optical parametric oscillator</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6108081</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Holtom et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6211999</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Gopalan et al.</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0154663</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Zhu et al.</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>372 22</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2007/0127107</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kitamura et al.</name>
<date>20070600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359238</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00005">
<othercit>L.E. Meyers et al., Multigrating quasi-phase-matched optical parametric oscillator in periodically poled LiNbO<sub>3</sub>, <i>Optics Letters</i>, vol. 21, No. 8 p. 591-593 (1996).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>J. Mes et al., Single-longitudinal-mode optical parametric oscillator for spectroscopic applications, <i>Optics Letters</i>, vol. 27, No. 16 p. 1442-1444 (2002).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>H. Liu et al., Aperiodic optical superlattices engineered for optical frequency conversion, <i>Applied Physics Letters</i>, vol. 79, No. 6 p. 728-730 (2001).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Kartaloglu et al., Simultaneous phase matching of optical parametric oscillation and second-harmonic generation in a periodically poled lithium niobate, <i>J. Opt. Soc. Am. B. </i>vol. 20, No. 2 (2003).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>25</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359326-330</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>372 21- 22</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356301</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>10</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070147443</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070628</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kung</last-name>
<first-name>Andrew H.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zhu</last-name>
<first-name>Shining</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nanjing</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tu</last-name>
<first-name>Shih-Yu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Xizhi</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gao</last-name>
<first-name>Zhida</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shen Yang</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Cohen Pontani Lieberman &amp; Pavane LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Academia Sinica</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Nankang, Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Sanghavi</last-name>
<first-name>Hemang</first-name>
<department>2874</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A tunable coherent light source includes a pump laser for generating a pump beam and an optical parametric oscillator including a crystal exhibiting an output curve for a pump beam of a defined wavelength, the output curve defining wavelengths of signal and idler outputs based on periodically poled grating periods of the crystal. The crystal has a plurality of segments associated with a plurality of grating periods of the output curve, each segment of the plurality of segments having a different crystal structure. At least one of the plurality of segments comprises a crystal structure combining at least two of the grating periods A heating device heats the crystal to an elevated operating temperature and is adjustable for adjusting the output wavelengths of each of the segments.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="96.77mm" wi="111.59mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="212.85mm" wi="126.15mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="122.43mm" wi="131.66mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="152.32mm" wi="160.19mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="173.57mm" wi="152.23mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298545-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="233.76mm" wi="158.07mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="109.90mm" wi="112.35mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="108.63mm" wi="139.95mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="115.99mm" wi="144.27mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="117.86mm" wi="152.82mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="178.73mm" wi="165.18mm" file="US07298545-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a tunable coherent light source comprising an optical parametric oscillator device for the visible and near infrared region based on stoichiometric ferroelectric crystal material as the parametric gain medium pumped by pulsed solid state lasers.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Optical Parametric Oscillators (OPOs) are used as sources of tunable coherent radiation. An OPO includes a non-linear optical crystal and an optical resonator cavity. The non-linear optical crystal converts an input laser wave (referred to as a “pump” beam) into two output waves called the signal beam and the idler beam. The wavelengths of the signal and idler beams are determined by the pump frequency, the angle the pump wave vector makes with respect to a crystal axis of the non-linear optical crystal, and the phase matching properties of the non-linear optical crystal. The optical resonator cavity resonates at least one of the signal and idler beams.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Electric field poling is used to fabricate periodically-poled quasi-phase-matched ferroelectric crystals which are used to produce efficient and compact all solid-state OPOs. However, ferroelectric material is known to be highly susceptible to photo refractive damage and visible-induced infrared absorption such that OPOs using ferroelectric material as the non-linear optical crystal are confined to operating in the infrared region. Near-infrared OPOs using LiNbO<sub>3 </sub>and LiTaO<sub>3 </sub>as the non-linear optical crystal are used for low power applications. However, refractive damage limits their further development in high power OPOs. Accordingly, compact high repetition-rate high power OPOs broadly tunable in the visible and near-infrared are still not available.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">U.S. Pat. No. 6,211,999 discloses the use of near-stoichiometric LiTaO<sub>3 </sub>(SLT) with an increased optical damage threshold. Periodically-poled near stoichiometric LiTaO<sub>3 </sub>(PPSLT) is applied in efficient second harmonic generation and sum frequency mixing to the blue and green regions. However, the devices described in U.S. Pat. No. 6,211,999 also suffer from photo refractive damage and light-induced absorption under intense radiation of &gt;15 MW/cm<sup>2</sup>. Similar ferroelectric crystals made of MgO doped SLT and MgO doped stoichiometric lithium niobate have similar problems.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">OPOs typically include a plurality of periodically poled inverted domain structures, each having a different period. Each section or segment is used to generate different signal and idler wavelengths. Another problem with known periodically-poled crystal devices is that many segments of slightly different periodicity are required to provide a broad continuously tunable range.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Commercially available high power tunable lasers include dye lasers and Ti: sapphire lasers. Dye lasers use chemicals that are potentially toxic and possible cancer agents. Ti: sapphire lasers have a limited tuning range and are difficult to time.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">An object of the present invention is to provide a high power, compact, environmentally friendly, and continuously tunable coherent light source for producing visible and near infrared light.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another object of the present invention is to provide an optical device comprising the light source of the present invention and an optical system for producing microscopic images by non-linear optical interaction of the light from the light source with an object sample.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The above objects are met by a tunable coherent light source comprising a pump laser for generating a pump beam, and an optical parametric oscillator including a crystal having a crystal structure exhibiting an output curve for a pump beam of a defined wavelength, the output curve defining wavelengths of signal and idler outputs based on periodically poled grating periods of the crystal structure. The crystal includes a plurality of segments associated with a plurality of grating periods of the output curve. Each of the segments has a different domain structure, wherein at least one of the plurality of segments comprises a domain structure combining at least two of the grating periods. The light source also includes a heating element for maintaining the crystal at an elevated temperature. The heating element is adjustable so that the operating temperature is adjustable between a minimum temperature and a maximum temperature. In a preferred embodiment, the crystal is periodically poled near-stoichiometric LiTaO<sub>3 </sub>(PPSLT) and the heating element heats the crystal to a temperature above approximately 373° K. The combination of grating periods may be effected by an aperiodic structure or a quasi-periodic structure.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The optical parametric oscillator comprises a resonator cavity having a first reflecting element arranged proximate a first side of the resonator cavity and a second reflecting element arranged proximate a second side of the resonator cavity, the crystal being arranged between the first and second reflecting elements.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In one embodiment, the pump beam is directed into the resonator cavity through the first reflecting element, the first reflecting element being a multiple layer dielectric mirror having a high transmissivity T&gt;99.5% at the wavelength of the pump beam and a high reflectivity R&gt;98.5% at the output wavelengths of at least one of the segments. In this embodiment, the second reflecting element is a multiple layer dielectric mirror having a reflectivity in the range of 30-70% at the output wavelengths.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In a further embodiment, the optical parametric oscillator has a third reflecting element arranged between the first reflecting element and the crystal for deflecting and guiding the pump beam through the crystal. The third reflecting element is highly transmitting for a broad range of output wavelengths. In this embodiment, the first reflecting elements may be a silver coated mirror having a very high reflectivity for all wavelengths of the output of the oscillator or a Littrow grating. The second reflecting element may be a crystal with a high refractive index and wavelength independent reflection.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The second reflecting element may alternatively comprise a grazing incidence grating. In this embodiment, the oscillator may further comprise a reflecting mirror arranged for receiving a first order reflection from the grazing incidence grating. A further reflecting element may be arranged so that the second reflecting element is arranged between the further reflecting element and the crystal, the further reflecting element guiding and deflecting the pump beam through the crystal via the second reflecting element.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The output of the optical parameter oscillator is continuously tunable within an output wavelength range of 640 nm to 3000 nm by switching between the plural segments and adjusting the operating temperature of the crystal. The plurality of grating periods includes first through seventeenth grating periods. In one embodiment, the crystal includes nine segments and eight of the nine segments include a combination of two consecutive grating periods. In another embodiment, the crystal include six segment and five of the six segments include a combination of three consecutive grating periods.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The objects of the present invention are also met by a device for obtaining microscopic images of an object including a light source generating an output beam which includes a signal beam and an idler beam, wherein a difference between wavelengths of the signal beam and the idler beam is approximately equal to the Raman wavelength of the object to be imaged, a means for directing the output of the light source to the object, and a detector arranged in front of or behind the object for receiving a signal produced by interaction of the output beam with the object. The light source includes a pump laser for generating a pump beam, and an optical parametric oscillator including a crystal having a crystal structure exhibiting an output curve for a pump beam of a defined wavelength, the output curve defining wavelengths of signal and idler outputs based on periodically poled grating periods of the crystal structure. The crystal includes a plurality of segments associated with a plurality of grating periods of the output curve. Each of the segments has a different crystal structure, wherein at least one of the plurality of segments comprises a crystal structure combining at least two of the grating periods. The light source also includes a heating element for adjustably maintaining the crystal at an elevated temperature.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Other objects and features of the present invention will become apparent from the following detailed description considered in conjunction with the accompanying drawings. It is to be understood, however, that the drawings are designed solely for purposes of illustration and not as a definition of the limits of the invention, for which reference should be made to the appended claims. It should be further understood that the drawings are not necessarily drawn to scale and that, unless otherwise indicated, they are merely intended to conceptually illustrate the structures and procedures described herein.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In the drawings:</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of a light source according to the present invention, having a basic optical parametric oscillator cavity with a PPSLT crystal embedded in a temperature-controlled oven;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a more detailed view of a crystal <b>10</b> from the light source of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a graph showing a tuning curve which illustrates the relationship between crystal temperature and inverted domain periodicity with output wavelength;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a table showing the signal and idler wavelengths of the segments of a crystal according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a segment of a crystal structure in which two grating periods are combined according to an aperiodic domain structure;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a segment of a crystal structure in which two grating periods are combined according to a quasi-periodic domain structure;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a portion of a poled crystal segment combining two consecutive periods of the table in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a portion of a poled crystal segment combining two consecutive periods of the table in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a schematic diagram of a compact OPO arrangement for broad tuning application;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a schematic diagram of an optical cavity according to the present invention that provides output with a medium resolution in a wavelength bandwidth;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a schematic diagram of a optical cavity according to the present invention that provides output with a high resolution in wavelength bandwidth;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a variation of the embodiment in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> to provide double passes of the pump beam to reduce the pump threshold; and</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a schematic diagram of a microscopic imaging device using a compact visible OPO light source.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PRESENTLY PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">An optical parametric oscillator (OPO) <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> includes a gain medium made from a periodically poled near-stoichiometric LiTaO<sub>3 </sub>(PPSLT) crystal <b>10</b> embedded in an oven <b>20</b> or other heating device in an OPO cavity <b>110</b>. The crystal may alternatively be mode from MgO doped PPSLT. A pump laser <b>16</b> generates a pump beam having high repetition rate solid state laser pulses of nano-second scale duration and a repetition rate in the range of 100 Hz-100 kHz. The pump beam generated by the pump laser <b>16</b> is directed into the OPO cavity <b>110</b> and is focused by coupling optics <b>18</b> to provide an intensity below the dielectric damage threshold of the crystal <b>10</b> which is approximately 55 MW/cm<sup>2</sup>. To overcome the problem of photo-induced damage, i.e., photorefractive damage, and visble-induced absorption, the heating device <b>20</b> is used to operate the crystal at an elevated temperature of above about 100° C. (for PPSLT).</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The OPO cavity <b>110</b> in the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> comprises an input mirror <b>12</b> arranged between the crystal <b>10</b> and the pump laser <b>16</b> and an output minor <b>14</b>. The input mirror <b>12</b> is highly transmitting at the wavelength of the pump laser <b>16</b> and preferably has a transmissivity of T&gt;99.5% at the pump laser wavelength. The input mirror <b>12</b> is also highly reflective at the output wavelengths (the signal and idler wavelength). The input mirror <b>12</b> preferably has a reflectivity of R&gt;98/5% at the output wavelengths. The output mirror <b>14</b> is partially reflecting at the output wavelengths. For the pump intensity of &lt;55 MW/cm<sup>2 </sup>and for an PPSLT crystal length of 2 cm, the reflectivity of the output mirror <b>14</b> is preferably in the range 30-70%. Both the input mirror <b>12</b> and the output mirror <b>14</b> may comprise multiple layer dielectric mirrors. Furthermore, the spacing between the input and output mirrors <b>12</b>,<b>14</b> is approximately 3 cm. The arrangement of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> can reach approximately 70% output efficiency in photon conversion. However, the mirrors <b>12</b>,<b>14</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> have a limited useful wavelength range.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Typical PPSLT crystals used for parametric gain devices include a plurality of sections of periodically poled inverted domain structures to produce tuned radiation, each section generating different idler and signal wavelengths. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a more detailed view of the crystal <b>10</b> showing sections <b>10</b><i>a</i>-<b>10</b><i>d</i>. Although four sections are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the crystal may have any number of sections and is limited only by convenience of operation and cost of production. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the second section <b>10</b><i>b </i>is aligned with the input and output mirrors <b>12</b>,<b>14</b> and produces the output wavelengths associated with that particular section. The OPO output is tuned by translating the crystal to align a different section <b>10</b><i>a</i>-<b>10</b><i>d </i>with the input and output mirrors <b>12</b>,<b>14</b>. As will be discussed in more detail below, the output wavelengths of each individual section <b>10</b><i>a</i>-<b>10</b><i>d </i>may also be adjusted by altering the operating temperature of the crystal <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a tuning curve for an PPSLT crystal for a pump wavelength of 0.532 nm. Each specific grating period has an associated signal and idler output wavelength for the pump wavelength. The signal wavelength is the upper portion of the curve and an idler wavelength is the lower portion of the curve. As indicated in the graph of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the signal wavelength and idler wavelength produced by each segment can be adjusted by adjusting the operating temperature of the crystal <b>10</b>. However, a large number of segments are required to provide a continuous tuning range.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a table listing <b>17</b> segments of periodically poled domain structures of a crystal which provide a continuous tuning range from 645 nm to 3029 nm with a temperature adjustment of 130° C. to 200° C. Each of the 17 segments includes a structure having a specific grating period. The large number of segments requires frequent switching between segments to achieve the desired output. According to the present invention, the number of domain segments is reduced by combining at least two adjacent grating periods. The method of combining periods in one segment is discussed in further detail below. The reduction in the number of segments facilitates the convenience of operation and reduces the manufacturing cost of the crystal. However, the combining of periods into one segment reduces the gain of the crystal. Accordingly, the amount of reduction in segments must be weighed against the amount of reduction in parametric gain which can be tolerated. Our experience in modeling crystals indicates that combining two or three consecutive periods into one segment provides the most optimal solution. In a first alternative embodiment, each consecutive pair of segments starting with segments <b>2</b> and <b>3</b> and ending with segments <b>16</b> and <b>17</b>, is combined into one segment to produce a crystal structure <b>100</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. Segment <b>1</b> is left alone in this case because it has sufficiently broad wavelength coverage (i.e., 909 nm to 1283 nm). The crystal structure <b>100</b> that has nine segments <b>100</b><i>a</i>-<b>100</b><i>i </i>instead of 17 segments of individual periods. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows another alternative embodiment of a crystal structure <b>110</b> in which three adjacent periods are combined. The total number of segments <b>110</b><i>a</i>-<b>110</b><i>f </i>is reduced to six in this embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">There are two methods which may be used to combine consecutive periods into one segment. The first method is referred to as aperiodic structure method and the second method is referred to as quasi-periodic structure method. The following discussion uses the combination of the second and third periods from the table in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> as an example. However, the same methods may be used to accomplish the other combinations. The first method is described in detail in the article by T. Kartaloglu, et al., “Simultaneous Phase Matching of Optical Parametric Oscillation and Second-Harmonic Generation in Aperiodically Poled Lithium Niobate”, <i>J. Opt. Soc. Am.</i>, Vol. 20, No. 2, page 343 (2003), the entire contents of which are incorporated herein by reference. The second and third periods in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> to be combined are 8.16 and 7.98 μm. According to Kartaloglu et al., reciprocal vectors Δk<sub>1</sub>=0.77=2p/L (L=8.16) and Δk<sub>2</sub>=0.787367=2p/L (L=7.98) are first determined. Fourier components G(Δk<sub>1</sub>) and G(Δk<sub>2</sub>) are then maximized. A segment width of 3.5 μm is selected based on experience and an aperiodic pattern of inverted domain distribution is obtained. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a segment of the distribution according to the aperiodic structure method.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The quasi-periodic structure method is described in H. Liu, et al., “Aperiodic Optical Superlattices Engineered for Optical Frequency Conversion”, Appl. Phys. Lett. 79, pages 728-730 (2001), the entire contents of which are incorporated herein by reference. According to that reference, the reciprocals for the quasi-periodic structure are</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mrow>
  <mrow>
    <msub>
      <mi>G</mi>
      <mrow>
        <mi>m</mi>
        <mo>,</mo>
        <mi>n</mi>
      </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mrow>
      <mn>2</mn>
      <mo>⁢</mo>
      <mi>π</mi>
      <mo>⁢</mo>
      <mstyle>
        <mspace width="0.3em" height="0.3ex"/>
      </mstyle>
      <mo>⁢</mo>
      <mfrac>
        <mrow>
          <mi>m</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mi>n</mi>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mstyle>
              <mspace width="0.3em" height="0.3ex"/>
            </mstyle>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mi>γ</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mi>D</mi>
      </mfrac>
    </mrow>
  </mrow>
  <mo>,</mo>
</mrow>
</math>
</maths>
<br/>
where D=γD<sub>A</sub>+D<sub>B</sub>, G<sub>1,1</sub>=Δk<sub>1</sub>, G<sub>1,2</sub>=Δk<sub>2</sub>, and Δk<sub>1</sub>=0.77, Δk<sub>2</sub>=0.787367 in our example of combining the second and third periods from the table in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. From this one can obtain the structure parameters: γ=0.023075, D=8.348272 μm, D<sub>A</sub>=12.13 μm, D<sub>B</sub>=8.068 μm, l=4.03 μm, upon maximizing the Fourier components G<sub>1,1 </sub>and G<sub>1,2</sub>. The corresponding quasi-periodic structure is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>.
</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows an OPO <b>300</b> according to a further embodiment of the present invention in which one set of optical mirrors is used for an entire tuning range of the PPSLT crystal <b>10</b>. The OPO <b>300</b> includes an OPO cavity <b>310</b> with a dichroic mirror <b>22</b> to deflect the pump beam by approximately 90° toward the PPSLT crystal <b>10</b>. Although the pump beam is deflected by approximately 90° in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the pump beam deflection angle may be any suitable angle that allows the pump beams to clear the components surrounding the OPO <b>300</b>. The dichroic mirror <b>22</b> is highly transmitting for a broad range of output wavelengths. In the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, a mirror <b>24</b> is arranged on one end, i.e., the input end of the OPO cavity <b>310</b> and has a silver coating. This mirror <b>24</b> has a reflectivity of R&gt;95% for all output wavelengths. In a preferred embodiment, the mirror has a reflectivity of R&gt;99%. At the output end, an output mirror <b>14</b>′ has a crystal with a highly refractive index such that the output mirror <b>14</b>′ has an essentially wavelength independent reflection of [(n−1)/(n+1)]<sup>2 </sup>on one surface and is broadband anti-reflection coated on a second surface. The arrangement of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is operable for all output wavelengths, i.e., 640 nm-3000 nm, with one set of optics. However, the output power is approximately half of that which is obtainable in the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> discloses an OPO <b>400</b> with an OPO cavity <b>410</b> according to an alternative embodiment in which the broadly reflecting mirror of the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is replaced by a grating <b>28</b>. A beam expander <b>26</b> is optionally-included between the dichroic mirror <b>22</b> and the grating <b>28</b>. In the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the grating <b>28</b> is set in a Littrow arrangement. The wavelength is set by the setting of the grating <b>28</b> and is not affected by the changes in the temperature of the crystal <b>10</b>. The grating <b>28</b> also facilitates a reduction in the bandwidth resolution of the output.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows another arrangement of an OPO <b>500</b> with an OPO cavity <b>510</b> in which the output mirror of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is replaced by a grazing incidence grating <b>30</b> and a high reflecting mirror <b>32</b>. The pump beam and output beam exiting the right side of the crystal <b>10</b> reflect off of the grating <b>30</b> and make an incident angle close to 90°. This arrangement is referred to as a grazing incidence and is described in more detail in U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/834,755, the entire contents of which are incorporated herein by reference. The beam that is reflected at the angle of incidence exits the OPO cavity <b>510</b>. Another beam, called the first order reflection, diffracts off the grating and is directed to a reflecting mirror <b>32</b>, which is adjusted so that the first order reflection reflects onto itself to produce an oscillating action for the OPO <b>500</b>. The arrangement of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is capable of producing an output having a narrow bandwidth having a width of less than 100 MHz.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a variation of the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>. A pump beam is fed into the OPO cavity <b>610</b> by way of the grazing incidence grating <b>30</b>. The dichroic mirror <b>32</b> is arranged outside of the grazing incidence grating <b>30</b> relative to the crystal <b>10</b>. The reflecting silver mirror <b>34</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is replaced by a mirror <b>36</b> that is highly reflective (reflectivity&gt;98% or more preferably reflectivity&gt;99%) at the pump wavelength and has a reflectivity R&gt;90% for the range of output wavelengths. In this embodiment, the pump beam passes through the crystal <b>10</b> twice which doubles the single pass gain. An advantage of this embodiment is that the pump power requirement is reduced. However, the optical alignment is more difficult than the previous embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The dual output of the OPO <b>100</b>, <b>300</b>, <b>400</b>, <b>500</b>, <b>600</b> is suitable for obtaining microscopic images of an object through non-linear optical interaction of the OPO output with the object to be imaged. In a specific embodiment, the pump laser <b>16</b>, coupling optics <b>18</b>, and the OPO cavity <b>110</b>, <b>310</b>, <b>410</b>, <b>510</b>, <b>610</b> according to the present invention is packaged in a single compact platform which is used as a light source for coherent anti-Stoke Raman spectroscopic microscopy (CARS microscopy). In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, an output (the signal and idler beams) of OPO <b>100</b>, <b>300</b>, <b>400</b>, <b>500</b>, <b>600</b> is directed into a microscope <b>700</b>. More specifically, the output of the OPO <b>100</b>, <b>300</b>, <b>400</b>, <b>500</b>, <b>600</b> enters a collimator <b>704</b> and reflects off of a dichroic beam splitter <b>706</b> toward an objective lens assembly <b>702</b> of the microscope which focuses the output beam onto an object <b>708</b> to be imaged. In this embodiment, the signal and idler beams are tuned so that the difference in wavelengths of the signal and idler beams is equal to the Raman wavelength of the object <b>708</b> to be imaged. An interaction of the output beam with the object <b>708</b> produces a CARS signal. The CARS signal reflected backward passes through collection optics <b>712</b> which focus the CARS signal onto a photon detector <b>710</b>. Alternatively or additionally, a photon detector <b>716</b> and collection optics <b>714</b> may be arranged behind the object <b>708</b>. By scanning the position of the light on the object <b>708</b>, a two-dimensional CARS image of the object can be recorded. This process can be repeated for different distances of the object from the objective lens to produce three-dimensional images.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Thus, while there have shown and described and pointed out fundamental novel features of the invention as applied to a preferred embodiment thereof, it will be understood that various omissions and substitutions and changes in the form and details of the devices illustrated, and in their operation, may be made by those skilled in the art without departing from the spirit of the invention. For example, it is expressly intended that all combinations of those elements which perform substantially the same function in substantially the same way to achieve the same results are within the scope of the invention. Moreover, it should be recognized that structures and/or elements shown and/or described in connection with any disclosed form or embodiment of the invention may be incorporated in any other disclosed or described or suggested form or embodiment as a general matter of design choice. It is the intention, therefore, to be limited only as indicated by the scope of the claims appended hereto.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07298545-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="5.67mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298545-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A tunable coherent light source, comprising:
<claim-text>a pump laser for generating a pump beam;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an optical parametric oscillator including a crystal exhibiting an output curve for a pump beam of a defined wavelength, said output curve defining wavelengths of signal and idler outputs based on periodically poled grating periods of said crystal, said crystal having a plurality of segments associated with a plurality of grating periods of said output curve, each segment of said plurality of segments having a different domain structure, wherein at least one of said plurality of segments comprises a domain structure combining at least two of said grating periods; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heating device for adjustably heating said crystal to an elevated operating temperature in a temperature range between a minimum temperature and a maximum temperature, said minimum temperature being greater than 100° C., said wavelengths of said signal and idler outputs of each of said segments being adjustable by adjusting said temperature within said temperature range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said optical parametric oscillator comprises a resonator cavity having a first reflecting element arranged proximate a first side of said resonator cavity and a second reflecting element arranged proximate a second side of said resonator cavity, said crystal being arranged between said first and second reflecting elements.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said pump beam is directed into said resonator cavity through said first reflecting element, said first reflecting element comprising a multiple layer dielectric mirror having a transmissivity T&gt;99.5% at the wavelength of said pump beam and a reflectivity R&gt;98.5% at the output wavelengths of at least one of said segments.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said second reflecting element is a multiple layer dielectric mirror having a reflectivity in the range 30-70% at the output wavelengths.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising a third reflecting element arranged between said first reflecting element and said crystal for deflecting and guiding said pump beam through said crystal, said third reflecting element being highly transmitting for a broad range of output wavelengths.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said first reflecting element is a silver coated mirror having a reflectivity R&gt;99% for all wavelengths of said output of said optical parametric oscillator and said second reflecting element comprises a crystal with a high refractive index having an essentially wavelength-independent reflection.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The tunable light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said first reflecting element comprises a grating.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The tunable light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said grating is set in a Littrow arrangement.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The tunable light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising a beam expander arranged between said grating and said third reflecting element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said first reflecting element is a silver coated mirror having a reflectivity R&gt;95% for all wavelengths of said output of said optical parametric oscillator and said second reflecting element comprises a grazing incidence grating.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising a reflecting mirror arranged for receiving a first order reflection from the grazing incidence grating and reflecting the first order reflection onto itself.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising a third reflecting element arranged so that said second reflecting element is between said third reflecting element and said crystal, said third reflecting element deflecting and guiding said pump beam through said crystal via said second reflecting element, said third reflecting element being highly transmitting for a broad range of output wavelengths.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said first reflecting element is a dielectric mirror having a reflectivity R&gt;98% at the wavelength of said pump beam and a reflectivity of R&gt;90% for wavelengths of said output of said optical parametric oscillator, said second reflecting element comprising a grazing incidence grating.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, further comprising a reflecting mirror arranged for receiving a first order reflection from the grazing incidence grating and reflecting the first order reflection onto itself.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein an output of said optical parametric oscillator is continuously tunable within an output wavelength range of 640 nm to 3000 nm by switching between said plurality of segments and adjusting the operating temperature of said crystal between the minimum temperature and the maximum temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein said plurality of grating periods of said output curve includes first through seventeenth grating periods, said first grating period being a shortest of said grating periods.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein said minimum temperature is approximately 130° C. and the maximum temperature is approximately 200° C.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein said plurality of segments comprises first through ninth segments associated with said seventeen grating periods, and eight segments of said nine segments each include a domain structure combining two successive grating periods.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein said first segment includes a domain structure associated with only said first grating period.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein said plurality of segments comprises six segments associated with said seventeen grating periods, five of the six segments each include a domain structure combining three successive grating periods and one segment of said six segments includes a domain structure combining two successive grating periods.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref>, wherein said first segment includes a domain structure combining only said first and second grating periods.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said crystal is made from periodically poled near-stoichiometric LiTaO<sub>3</sub>(PPSLT) or MgO doped PPSLT.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The tunable coherent light source of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said at least one of said plurality of segments combines said at least two of said grating periods using one of an aperiodic structure and a quasi-periodic structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A device for obtaining microscopic images of an object, comprising:
<claim-text>a light source generating an output beam including a signal beam and an idler beam, wherein a difference in wavelength between the signal beam and the idler beam is approximately equal to a Raman wavelength of the object to be imaged;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for directing the output of the light source to the object; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detector arranged in front of or behind the object relative to said output beam for receiving a signal produced by the interaction of the output beam with the object,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said light source comprises a pump laser for generating a pump beam, an optical parametric oscillator including a crystal exhibiting an output curve for a pump beam of a defined wavelength, said output curve defining wavelengths of signal and idler outputs based on periodically poled grating periods of said crystal, said crystal having a plurality of segments associated with a plurality of grating periods of said output curve, each segment of said plurality of segments having a different domain structure, wherein at least one of said plurality of segments comprises a domain structure combining at least two of said grating periods, and a heating device for adjustably heating said crystal to an elevated operating temperature in a temperature range between a minimum temperature and a maximum temperature, said minimum temperature being greater than 100° C., said wavelengths of said signal and idler outputs of each of said segments being adjustable by adjusting said temperature within said temperature range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref>, wherein said signal produced by the interaction of the output beam with the object comprises a coherent anti-Stokes Raman spectroscopic (CARS) signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
