<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299375-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299375</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10895933</doc-number>
<date>20040722</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-278684</doc-number>
<date>20030723</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>478</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714  4</main-classification>
<further-classification>709217</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Signal processing apparatus, remote operation system, and signal processing method</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5913034</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Malcolm</name>
<date>19990600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>709223</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6388658</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ahern et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345168</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6681250</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Thomas et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>709226</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7003563</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Leigh et al.</name>
<date>20060200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>709223</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0054029</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Glancy et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345173</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0268012</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ferguson</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710313</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-344189</doc-number>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714  4</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709217</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709223</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709219</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>14</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>14</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050033815</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050210</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nagao</last-name>
<first-name>Naoyuki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shinagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Staas &amp; Halsey LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fujitsu Component Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Le</last-name>
<first-name>Dieu-Minh</first-name>
<department>2114</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A signal processing device that is used for remotely operating a server via a network includes: a first input unit that inputs an operation screen image of the server; an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image; a first output unit that outputs the image data to the network; a second input unit that inputs operation information via the network, the operation information being required for operating the server; and a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="178.22mm" wi="243.84mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="231.82mm" wi="175.09mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299375-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="229.36mm" wi="173.82mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299375-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="231.82mm" wi="147.32mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299375-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="193.21mm" wi="166.71mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="246.30mm" wi="185.93mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299375-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="189.57mm" wi="170.26mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="218.52mm" wi="144.95mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="175.09mm" wi="146.13mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="233.00mm" wi="160.61mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="219.20mm" wi="174.75mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="231.82mm" wi="166.62mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="236.64mm" wi="166.71mm" file="US07299375-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00013" num="00013">
<img id="EMI-D00013" he="245.11mm" wi="136.48mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299375-20071120-D00013.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00014" num="00014">
<img id="EMI-D00014" he="249.94mm" wi="155.79mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299375-20071120-D00014.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a signal processing apparatus, a remote operation system, a signal processing method and a computer program product.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">There is a technique of directly remote-operating a server on a network, as disclosed in Japanese Patent Application Publication No. 2001-344189. A remote-operation system that employs the above technique is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A system configuration shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> has a plurality of server groups <b>910</b>, each of which has a housing in which multiple servers <b>911</b> are housed. Each of the servers <b>911</b> is connected to a server switching device <b>901</b>. The servers <b>911</b> and the server switching devices <b>901</b> may be connected together via connectors capable of transferring image data (for example, VGA (Video Graphics Array) connectors), keyboard connectors and mouse connectors (for example, PS/2® connectors).</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The server switching devices <b>901</b> are connected to a network <b>903</b> such as a LAN (Local Area Network) or Internet, and communicate with an information processing apparatus <b>920</b>, which may be a personal computer (hereinafter simply referred to as PC) or a workstation.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">More particularly, upon receiving a request from the information processing apparatus <b>920</b>, the server switching devices <b>901</b> selectively connect the information processing apparatus <b>920</b> with the servers <b>911</b> requested. The server switching devices <b>901</b> generate IP (Internet Protocol) packages on the basis of a display screen output via the VGA connectors from the servers <b>911</b>, and send the IP packages to the information processing apparatus <b>920</b>. The apparatus <b>920</b> receives the IP packages based on the IP address from the network <b>903</b>, and displays a display screen on a monitor <b>921</b>. The information processing apparatus <b>920</b> converts information on an operation entered using a keyboard or mouse on the display screen into IP packets, and sends these IP packets to the server switching devices <b>901</b>. The devices <b>901</b> receive the IP packets related to the operation information on the basis of the IP addresses from the network <b>903</b>, and extract the operation information therefrom. Then, the server switching devices <b>901</b> apply the operation information thus extracted to the keyboard connector or the mouse connector of the server <b>911</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The server switching devices <b>901</b> cause the information processing apparatus <b>920</b> to serve as an input/output device such as a monitor, keyboard and mouse connected to the selected servers <b>911</b>. This provides the operator with a circumstance such that the above input/output device is directly connected to the servers <b>911</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Generally, each of the servers <b>911</b> is connected directly to the network <b>903</b> without the server switching devices <b>901</b>. In this case, each of the serves <b>911</b> is equipped with a network adapter for making a connection with the network <b>903</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">However, the system configuration shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> needs a huge number of interconnection cables dependent on the number of servers <b>911</b>. Examples of those interconnection cables are to connect the servers <b>911</b> and the server switching devices <b>901</b>, and to connect the servers <b>911</b> and the network <b>903</b>. Nowadays, the mainstream configuration in a large-scale system employs a single housing in which multiple servers <b>911</b> are housed as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In this system configuration, a huge number of interconnection cables are gathered in a very narrow area, and has a difficulty in establishment and management.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">It is an object of the present invention to provide a signal processing device, a remote operation system, a signal processing method and a computer program product that may be a recording medium, capable of easily configuring and managing the system.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">This object of the present invention is achieved by a signal processing device that is used for remotely operating a server via a network, comprising: a first input unit that inputs an operation screen image of the server; an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image; a first output unit that outputs the image data to the network; a second input unit that inputs operation information via the network, the operation information being required for operating the server; and a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The above object of the present invention is also achieved by a remote operation system comprising: a signal processing device that is connected to a server; and an information processing apparatus that remotely operates the server through the signal processing device, the signal processing device and the information processing apparatus being connected to each other via a network, the signal processing device including: a first input unit that inputs an operation screen image of the server; an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image; a first output unit that outputs the image data to the information processing apparatus via the network; a second input unit that inputs operation information from the information processing apparatus via the network, the operation information being required for operating the server; and a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server, the information processing apparatus including: a third input unit that inputs the image data outputted from the first output unit; a display unit that displays the image data; and a third output unit that outputs operation information of the server to the signal processing device via the network, the operation information of the server being inputted in accordance with the display unit.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The above object of the present invention is also achieved by A remote operation system comprising: a first signal processing device that is connected to a server; a second signal processing device that is connected to the first signal processing device via a network; and a monitor that is connected to the second signal processing device, the first signal processing device including: a first input unit that inputs an operation screen image of the server; an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image; a first output unit that outputs the image data to the second signal processing device via the network; a second input unit that inputs operation information from the second signal processing device via the network, the operation information being required for operating the server; and a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server, the second signal processing device including: a third input unit that inputs the image data outputted from the first output unit; a display unit that displays the image data on the monitor; and a third output unit that outputs operation information of the server to the first signal processing device via the network, the operation information of the server being inputted in accordance with the display unit.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The above object of the present invention is also achieved by a remote operation system comprising: a plurality of servers; a signal processing device that processes a signal outputted from one of the plurality of servers; a switching device that selectively connects the signal processing device to one of the plurality of servers; and an information processing apparatus that remotely operates one of the plurality of servers through the signal processing device, the signal processing device including: a first input unit that selectively inputs an operation screen image of one of the plurality of servers via the switching device; an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image; a first output unit that outputs the image data to the information processing apparatus via the network; a second input unit that inputs operation information from the information processing apparatus via the network, the operation information being required for operating the server; and a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server via the switching device, the information processing apparatus including: a third input unit that inputs the image data outputted from the first output unit; a display unit that displays the image data; and a third output unit that outputs operation information of the server to the signal processing device via the network, the operation information of the server being inputted in accordance with the display unit.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The above object of the present invention is also achieved by a method of processing a signal in a device for remotely operating a server via a network, the method comprising the steps of: inputting an operation screen image from the server; generating image data in accordance with the operation screen image; outputting the image data to the network; inputting operation information via the network, the operation information being required for operating the server; and outputting the operation information to the server.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The above-mentioned object of the present invention is also achieved by a computer program product for causing a computer to remotely operate a server via a network, the computer program product comprising instructions to be executed by the computer to: generate image data in accordance with an operation screen image that is inputted from the server; output the image data to the network; input operation information via the network, the operation information being required for operating the server; and output the operation information to the server.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram illustrating a conventional remote operation system;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the structure of a remote operation system in accordance with a first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram schematically illustrating the structure of the remote operation system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a display screen that is displayed on the monitor of the PC shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the structure of the signal processing device in accordance with the first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a server operation screen that is displayed on the monitor locally connected to the signal processing device shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flowchart of an operation to be performed by the control unit of the signal processing device when an operation screen image of the server is transmitted to the PC in the first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a flowchart of an operation to be performed by the control unit of the signal processing device when an operation code of the server is entered from the PC in the first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a flowchart of an operation to be performed by the control unit when an operation screen image of the server is outputted to the monitor that is locally connected to the signal processing device in the first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a flowchart of an operation to be performed by the control unit when an operation code of the server is entered from the keyboard or the mouse that is locally connected to the signal processing device in the first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a flowchart showing the predetermined routine started in step S<b>135</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>, as well as an operation to be performed by the control unit when a console screen image of the signal processing device is displayed on the monitor that is locally connected to the signal processing device;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a flowchart showing the predetermined routine started in step S<b>135</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, as well as an operation to be performed by the control unit when a console screen image of the signal processing device is displayed on the monitor of the PC;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a block diagram schematically illustrating the structure of a remote operation system in accordance with a second embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a block diagram schematically illustrating the structure of a remote operation system in accordance with a third embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The following is a description of preferred embodiments of the present invention, with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">A first embodiment of the present invention will be first described in detail. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the structure of a remote operation system <b>1</b> that includes signal processing devices <b>12</b> in accordance with this embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the remote operation system <b>1</b> includes server groups <b>10</b> each having servers <b>11</b> housed in one housing. Each of the servers <b>11</b> is a server module that is called a “blade server”. The server groups <b>10</b> house the servers <b>11</b> in housings called “chassis”. However, the present invention is not limited to this structure, and may be applied to an information processing apparatus such as a personal computer or a server that has an independent structure.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The signal processing devices <b>12</b> of this embodiment are connected to the servers <b>11</b> one by one. As will be described later, each signal processing device <b>12</b> is connected to each corresponding server <b>11</b> through the connectors provided to the server <b>11</b> for connecting display units and input units such as a keyboard, a mouse, and a monitor (a keyboard connector, a mouse connector, and a video terminal), and a serial connector such as an RS-232C connector (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Each of the signal processing devices <b>12</b> has a function of connecting with a network such as a LAN (Local Area Network) and the Internet. Accordingly, an operator accesses the signal processing devices <b>12</b> through a personal computer (PC) <b>22</b> in the network, so as to remotely operate the servers <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the structure of the remote operation system <b>1</b> will be described in greater detail. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the remote operation system <b>1</b> includes the servers <b>11</b>, the signal processing devices <b>12</b>, and the PC <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Each of the servers <b>11</b> is designed to locally connect with a monitor, a keyboard, and a mouse. As described earlier, each of the signal processing devices <b>12</b> is connected to each corresponding server <b>11</b> through the connectors for a monitor, a keyboard, and a mouse. More specifically, each of the signal processing devices <b>12</b> is connected to the video terminal, the keyboard connector, the mouse connector, and the serial connector of each corresponding server <b>11</b> through cables.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The video terminal of each server <b>11</b> may be a DVI (Digital Visual Interface) connector or a RGB connector. More specifically, each server <b>11</b> may be connected to each corresponding signal processing device <b>12</b> through a DVI display connecting interface or by an output image signal technique utilizing RGB (Red, Green, and Blue) to output an operation image. The keyboard connector and the mouse connector of each server <b>11</b> may be PS/2 connectors or USB (Universal Serial Bus) connectors. The serial connector of each server <b>11</b> may be an RS-232C connector, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Each of the signal processing devices <b>12</b> is designed to be capable of locally connecting with display units and input units such as a monitor <b>13</b>, a keyboard <b>14</b>, and a mouse <b>15</b>. In this embodiment, using a console that is formed with the monitor <b>13</b>, the keyboard <b>14</b>, and the mouse <b>15</b> locally connected to each signal processing device <b>12</b>, input can be performed on the signal processing device <b>12</b> in a GUI (Graphical User Interface) environment, and input can also be performed on each server <b>11</b> through each corresponding signal processing device <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Each signal processing device <b>12</b> can also be accessed by an operator through the PC <b>22</b> over the network, as already mentioned. In the following, an example case where a signal processing device <b>12</b> is connected to the PC <b>22</b> via a HUB <b>21</b>, or where the network is a LAN (local Area Network) <b>20</b>, will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The monitor <b>23</b> as a display unit and the keyboard <b>24</b> and the mouse <b>25</b> as input units are connected to the PC <b>22</b>. The display unit and the input units are controlled by the PC <b>22</b>, and provide the GUI environment to operators.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">In the above described structure, an operator accesses the signal processing device <b>12</b> through the PC <b>22</b>, using identification information for identifying the IP (Internet Protocol) address of the signal processing device <b>12</b> or for identifying the signal processing device <b>12</b>. By doing so, the operator makes a request to the signal processing device <b>12</b> for a remote operation of the corresponding server <b>11</b>. Upon receipt of the request for a remote operation of the server <b>11</b> from the PC <b>22</b>, the signal processing device <b>12</b> generates image data (in the bitmap format, for example) of the display screen of the server <b>11</b> (hereinafter referred to as the “operation screen”), based on a video signal V (in the form of digital data or analog data in a DVI format; in the form of analog data in an RGB format) outputted from the server <b>11</b>. The signal processing device <b>12</b> then turns the image data into an IP packet, and outputs the IP packet to the LAN <b>20</b>. The PC <b>22</b> analyzes the IP packet received through the LAN <b>20</b>, and reconstructs the image data of the operation screen. The PC <b>22</b> then displays the reconstructed image data in a terminal window on the monitor <b>23</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the operation screen image <b>232</b> displayed in a terminal window on the display screen <b>231</b> of the monitor <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">When an input operation is performed with the operation screen image <b>232</b> through the keyboard <b>24</b> or the mouse <b>25</b>, the PC <b>22</b> also converts the inputted operation code into an IP packet P, and transmits the IP packet P to the signal processing device <b>12</b> via the LAN <b>20</b>. The signal processing device <b>12</b> analyzes the IP packet P received from the PC <b>22</b>, and reconstructs the operation code. The signal processing device <b>12</b> then inputs the reconstructed operation code into the server <b>11</b> through connectors such as the keyboard connector, the mouse connector, the USE connector, and the serial connector. The server <b>11</b> carries out a process in accordance with the operation code inputted from the signal processing device <b>12</b>. Here, the operation code is a signal that is generated from the keyboard based on the key matrix, or a signal that is generated from the mouse based on the amount of movement or the click. The operation code can also be regarded as operation information.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In this manner, the operation screen of the server <b>11</b> is displayed on the monitor <b>23</b> of the PC <b>22</b> via a network such as the LAN <b>20</b>, and the operation code entered from the operation screen is inputted into the server <b>11</b> via the network. Thus, the server <b>11</b> can be remotely operated by an operator through the PC <b>22</b> that is connected to the server <b>11</b> via the network.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the initial state of the operation screen image <b>232</b> when an access is made. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the operation screen image <b>232</b> in the initial state demands that an operator inputs a login name (Login&gt;) and a password (Password&gt;) that are part of the identification information. This is a normal login screen of a general server. The operator should input the login name and the password that are allotted to him/her, through the operation screen image <b>232</b> of the PC <b>22</b>. By doing so, the operator can log in with the server <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The operation screen image outputted from the server <b>11</b> is constantly updated. While the server <b>11</b> is accessed, the image data of the updated operation screen or the data of the difference between the updated operation screen and the previous operation screen are generated based on a monitor signal V, and are transmitted to the PC <b>22</b> via the LAN <b>20</b>. In this manner, the operation screen image <b>232</b> displayed on the monitor <b>23</b> of the PC <b>22</b> can be always synchronized with the latest screen image of the server <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the inner structure of the signal processing device <b>12</b> will be described in detail. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block diagram illustrating the structure of the signal processing device <b>12</b> in accordance with this embodiment. Described below is an example case where DVI-format and RGB-format display connecting interfaces are provided in the server <b>11</b>, a video signal to be inputted into a DVI processing unit <b>121</b> is a digital signal, and the monitor <b>13</b> locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b> is an analog RGB monitor.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the signal processing device <b>12</b> includes the DVI processing unit <b>121</b>, a RGB processing unit <b>122</b>, a video signal switching unit <b>123</b>, an image processing unit <b>124</b>, a K/M processing unit <b>125</b>, a local K/M processing unit <b>126</b>, a control unit <b>127</b>, and a communication processing unit <b>128</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The control unit <b>127</b> includes a CPU (Central Processing Unit), and controls the other components, which are the DVI processing unit <b>121</b>, the RGB processing unit <b>122</b>, the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>, the image processing unit <b>124</b>, the KIM processing unit <b>125</b>, the local KIM processing unit <b>126</b>, and the communication processing unit <b>128</b>. The control unit <b>127</b> also performs operations that will be described later.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The DVI processing unit <b>121</b> receives a DVI video signal V<sub>D </sub>that is outputted from a DVI terminal <b>111</b> of the server <b>11</b>. The digital video signal V<sub>D </sub>received by the DVI processing unit <b>121</b> is then inputted into the image processing unit <b>124</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In a case where the video signal V<sub>D </sub>inputted through the DVI processing unit <b>121</b> is to be outputted to the LAN <b>20</b>, the image processing unit <b>124</b> generates image data in the bitmap format or the GIF (Graphics Interchange Format) or JPEG (Joint Photographic Experts Group) format, based on the video signal V<sub>D</sub>. The image processing unit <b>124</b> then inputs the image data into the communication processing unit <b>128</b>. Based on the image data, the communication processing unit <b>128</b> generates an IP packet P, and transmits the IP packet P to the LAN <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The communication processing unit <b>128</b> is a structure that controls communication with a network such as the LAN <b>20</b>, and is equivalent to the MAC (Media Access Control layer) or the PHY (Physical layer) of a LAN, the SIE (Serial Interface Engine) of an USB, and an RS-232C transceiver.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In a case where the video signal V<sub>D </sub>inputted through the DVI processing unit <b>121</b> is to be outputted to the locally connected monitor <b>13</b>, on the other hand, the image processing unit <b>124</b> converts the video signal V<sub>D </sub>into an analog signal (a video signal V<sub>A</sub>; an analog video signal will be hereinafter denoted by V<sub>A</sub>), and inputs the analog signal into the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>. However, the conversion of the video signal V<sub>D </sub>into an analog signal may be carried out by the RGB processing unit <b>122</b>. In that case, the image processing unit <b>124</b> inputs the video signal V<sub>D </sub>directly into the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>. The video signal switching unit <b>123</b> in turn inputs the video signal V<sub>D </sub>into the RGB processing unit <b>122</b>. The RGB processing unit <b>122</b> converts the video signal V<sub>D </sub>into an analog signal (a video signal V<sub>A</sub>), and inputs the video signal V<sub>A </sub>into the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>. If the monitor <b>13</b> is a DVI monitor, the signal processing device <b>12</b> can input the video signal V<sub>D</sub>, which has been received through the DVI processing unit <b>121</b>, into the monitor <b>13</b> via the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>, without carrying out any conversion process.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">After receiving the video signal V<sub>A </sub>that is an analog signal converted from a digital signal, the video signal switching unit <b>123</b> outputs the video signal V<sub>A </sub>to the locally connected monitor <b>13</b>. By doing so, the operation screen image of the server <b>11</b> outputted from the DVI terminal <b>111</b> can be displayed on the monitor <b>13</b> locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Meanwhile, the RGB processing unit <b>122</b> receives a RGB video signal V<sub>A </sub>that is outputted from a RGB terminal <b>112</b> of the server <b>11</b>. The video signal V<sub>A </sub>that is an analog signal received by the RGB processing unit <b>122</b> is inputted into the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">In a case where the video signal V<sub>A </sub>inputted through the RGB processing unit <b>122</b> is to be outputted to the LAN <b>20</b>, the video signal switching unit <b>123</b> inputs the video signal V<sub>A </sub>into the image processing unit <b>124</b>. The image processing unit <b>124</b> converts the video signal V<sub>A </sub>into a digital signal (a video signal V<sub>D</sub>; each digital video signal will be hereinafter denoted by V<sub>D</sub>). Based on the video signal V<sub>D</sub>, the image processing unit <b>124</b> generates image data in a bitmap format or a GIF (Graphics Interchange Format) or a JPEG (Joint Photographic Experts Group) format. The image processing unit <b>124</b> then inputs the image data into the communication processing unit <b>128</b>. In the same manner as described earlier, the communication processing unit <b>128</b> converts the image data into an IP packet P, and transmits the IP packet P to the LAN <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">In a case where the video signal V<sub>A </sub>inputted through the RGB processing unit <b>122</b> is to be outputted to the locally connected monitor <b>13</b>, on the other hand, the video signal switching unit <b>123</b> inputs the video signal V<sub>A </sub>directly into the monitor <b>13</b>. By doing so, the operation screen image of the server <b>11</b> outputted from the RGB terminal <b>112</b> can be displayed on the monitor <b>13</b> that is locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Which one of the two different display connecting interfaces should be used is determined by a DIP (Dual Inline Package) switch <b>12</b>-<b>1</b> provided in the signal processing device <b>12</b> or which one of the terminals (the DVI terminal <b>111</b> and the RGB terminal <b>112</b>) is connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>. The DIP switch <b>12</b>-<b>1</b> is a switch for performing various setting operations in the signal processing device <b>12</b>. Other than the above, the various setting operations include switching between IPv4 and IPv6 in the communication function, switching on and off a PnP (Plug and Play) and PHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) automatic allocation function, switching between Half-Duplex communication and Full-Duplex communication, switching on and off an automatic negotiation function, and setting an operation mode.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The signal processing device <b>12</b> also includes DDCs (Display Data Channels) <b>122</b><i>a </i>and <b>122</b><i>b </i>for inputting the information as to the display capacity of the monitor <b>13</b> or the monitor <b>23</b> into the server <b>11</b>. The DDC <b>122</b><i>a </i>is connected to a DDC terminal <b>112</b><i>a </i>of the server <b>11</b>. Accordingly, the server <b>11</b> outputs a video signal V<sub>D</sub>/V<sub>A </sub>in accordance with the display capacity information inputted from the signal processing device <b>12</b>. Here, the DDCs <b>122</b><i>a </i>and <b>122</b><i>b </i>are compliant to any one of the following three standards: the DDC-1, the DDC-2B, and the DDC-2AB. The DDC <b>122</b><i>a </i>is to provide the server <b>11</b> with a virtual situation in which a monitor is directly connected to the server <b>11</b>. Therefore, the DDC <b>112</b><i>a </i>should be operated by power supplied from the server <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">So as to provide the image processing unit <b>124</b> with the above described processing capacity, the image processing unit <b>124</b> should be formed with a programmable operation processing unit, such as a field programmable gate array (FPGA). The image processing unit <b>124</b> that is a programmable operation processing unit can perform different operations. Accordingly, the structure can be simplified, and the production cost can be reduced. The image processing unit <b>124</b> may also be designed to perform image processing such as mosaic processing on image data.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The signal processing device <b>12</b> has the K/M processing unit <b>125</b> to provide the server <b>11</b> with a virtual situation in which the keyboard and/or the mouse are directly connected to the server <b>11</b>. The K/M processing unit <b>125</b> inputs an operation code that is entered through the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b> into a K/M port <b>113</b> (equivalent to the keyboard connector and the mouse connector) of the server <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The K/M processing unit <b>125</b> inputs the operation code, which is entered from the keyboard <b>14</b> or the mouse <b>15</b> locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>, directly into the K/M port <b>113</b> of the server <b>11</b>. The operation code entered through the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b> is the operation code of the PC <b>22</b> received from the LAN <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">As described earlier, the K/M processing unit <b>125</b> provides the server <b>11</b> with the situation in which the keyboard and/or the mouse are directly connected to the server <b>11</b>. Therefore, it is preferable to operate the K/M processing unit <b>125</b> by power supplied from the server <b>11</b>. The other components of the signal processing device <b>12</b> operate by virtue of power supplied from the power supply unit <b>12</b>-<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The local K/M processing unit <b>126</b> functions when an input operation is performed through the keyboard <b>14</b> and the mouse <b>15</b> locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>. More specifically, when an operation code is entered by pressing a predetermined key (a function key or a special key, for example) of the keyboard <b>14</b> or the mouse <b>15</b>, the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b> inputs the operation code into the control unit <b>127</b>. Receiving the operation code inputted by the predetermined key pressing, the control unit <b>127</b> reads out a predetermined routine that is stored beforehand in a ROM (Read Only Memory) or the like (not shown), and provides the local operator with a suitable environment for performing an input operation with the signal processing device <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">In doing so, the control unit <b>127</b> carries out the following process. When the predetermined key pressing is performed, the control unit <b>127</b> reads out the predetermined routine, which serves as a trigger. In accordance with the predetermined routine, the control unit <b>127</b> generates a screen image (such as an OSD (On Screen Display) image, which will be hereinafter referred to as the console screen image) for performing an input operation with the signal processing device <b>12</b>, and inputs the console screen image into the image processing unit <b>124</b>. In accordance with the console screen image, the image processing unit <b>124</b> generates an analog video signal V<sub>C</sub>, and inputs the video signal V<sub>C </sub>into the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>. Here, the image processing unit <b>124</b> generates the video signal V<sub>C </sub>that is to be used for displaying a console screen image <b>132</b> in a pop-up window on the operation screen <b>131</b> of the server <b>11</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The video signal switching unit <b>123</b> superimposes the video signal V<sub>A </sub>of the operation screen <b>131</b> on the video signal V<sub>C </sub>inputted from the image processing unit <b>124</b> in such a manner that the console screen image <b>132</b> is displayed in the front. The video signal switching unit <b>124</b> then outputs the superimposed signal to the monitor <b>13</b>. Accordingly, the console screen image <b>132</b> to be used for performing an input operation with the signal processing device <b>12</b> is displayed, in an overlaid fashion, on the monitor <b>13</b> that is locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows the operation screen <b>131</b> of the server <b>11</b> displayed on the monitor <b>13</b>, on which the console screen image <b>132</b> is displayed in an overlaid fashion.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The local K/M processing unit <b>126</b> also inputs an operation code that is entered from the keyboard <b>14</b> or the mouse <b>15</b> through the console screen image <b>132</b> displayed on the monitor <b>13</b>, into the control unit <b>127</b>. In accordance with the operation code, the control unit <b>127</b> performs various setting operations and processes. Thus, an environment suitable for performing an input operation with the signal processing device can be realized.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">The operation code of the PC <b>22</b> entered via the LAN <b>20</b> is also inputted into the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b>. More specifically, the communication processing unit <b>128</b> receives an IP packet P transmitted from the PC <b>22</b> via the LAN <b>20</b>. The communication processing unit <b>128</b> then analyzes the IP packet P and reconstructs the operation code. The reconstructed operation code is inputted into the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b> via the control unit <b>127</b>. The local K/M processing unit <b>126</b> inputs the operation code directly into the K/M processing unit <b>125</b>. The K/M processing unit <b>125</b> in turn inputs the operation code into the K/M port <b>113</b> of the server <b>11</b>. In this manner, the operator of the PC <b>22</b> can be provided with an environment suitable for performing an input operation on the server <b>11</b> from a remote place.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The server <b>11</b> and the signal processing device <b>12</b> are connected to each other via a serial port <b>114</b>. Serial data S that are outputted from the serial port S are converted into parallel data, and are then inputted into the control unit <b>127</b>. If the inputted data S are the image data of a BIOS (Basic Input/Output System) setting screen of the server <b>11</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> inputs the data S into the image processing unit <b>124</b>. In a case where the setting screen image is to be displayed on the monitor <b>13</b> locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> controls the image processing unit <b>124</b> to generate an analog video signal V<sub>S </sub>based on the setting screen image, and to input the video signal V<sub>S </sub>into the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>. Here, the video signal V<sub>S </sub>generated by the image processing unit <b>124</b> is to be used for displaying the setting screen image in a pop-up window on the operation screen <b>131</b> of the server <b>11</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>; however, the console screen image <b>132</b> should be replaced with the setting screen image). The video signal switching unit <b>123</b> superimposes the video signal V<sub>A </sub>of the operation screen <b>131</b> on the video signal V<sub>s </sub>inputted from the image processing unit <b>124</b> in such a manner that the setting screen image is displayed in the front. The video signal switching unit <b>123</b> then outputs the superimposed signal to the monitor <b>13</b>. Thus, the setting screen image to be used for setting the BIOS is displayed on the monitor <b>13</b> that is locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>. In a case where the setting screen image is to be displayed on the monitor <b>23</b> of the PC <b>22</b>, on the other hand, the control unit <b>127</b> controls the image processing unit <b>124</b> to generate the image data of the setting screen image, and superimposes the image data of the operation screen image <b>232</b> on the image data of the setting screen image. The superimposed image data are inputted into the communication processing unit <b>128</b>. The communication processing unit <b>128</b> converts the superimposed image data into an IP packet, and transmits the IP packet to the PC <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">It is also possible to input an operation code that is entered from a keyboard or a mouse into the server <b>11</b> via the serial port <b>114</b>. In such a case, an operation code entered from the PC <b>22</b>, for example, is reconstructed by the communication processing unit <b>128</b>, and is inputted into the control unit <b>127</b>. The operation code is then inputted from the control unit <b>127</b> into the serial port <b>114</b>. Meanwhile, an operation code that is entered from the local console <b>12</b><i>a </i>is inputted into the control unit <b>127</b> via the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b>, and is then inputted from the control unit <b>127</b> into the serial port <b>114</b>. In this manner, the serial port <b>114</b> can be used as a video terminal (a terminal that outputs video signals), a keyboard connector, or a mouse connector.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">In the above described structure, the control unit <b>127</b> should preferably be capable of transferring image data with efficiency in accordance with the band and the congestion level of the LAN <b>20</b>. More specifically, the control unit <b>127</b> should preferably be capable of transmitting unit blocks of image data at random, or compressing image data and then transmitting the compressed image data.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Next, the operation flow of a remote operation to be performed on the server <b>11</b> by the PC <b>22</b>, and the operation flow of an operation to be performed on the server <b>11</b> by the local console <b>12</b><i>a </i>connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>, will be described in detail, with reference to the accompanying drawings. The operations described below are performed under the control of the control unit <b>127</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">Referring to the flowcharts of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 and 8</figref>, a remote operation to be performed on the server <b>11</b> by the PC <b>22</b> via the LAN <b>20</b> will be described below.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the communication processing unit <b>128</b> receives a request for access to the server <b>11</b> from the PC <b>22</b>. When the request for access is inputted into the control unit <b>127</b> (step S<b>101</b>), the control unit <b>127</b> controls the image processing unit <b>124</b> to generate the image data of the operation screen image <b>232</b> in accordance with a video signal V that is inputted through the DVI processing unit <b>121</b> or the RGB processing unit <b>122</b> (step S<b>102</b>). For ease of explanation, any video signal will be hereinafter denoted by V, whether analog or digital. The generated image data are then inputted into the communication processing unit <b>128</b>. The communication processing unit <b>128</b> converts the image data into an IP packet P, and transmits the IP packet P to the PC <b>22</b> (step S<b>103</b>). If the image data generated in the previous operation still exist in step S<b>103</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> controls the image processing unit <b>124</b> to generate the difference data between the previously generated image data and the currently generated image data, and the IP packet P of the difference data is transmitted to the PC <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">The control unit <b>127</b> repeats the procedures of steps S<b>102</b> and S<b>103</b> as long as the server <b>11</b> is accessed by the PC <b>22</b>, or until the line between the PC <b>22</b> and the signal processing device <b>12</b> is disconnected (step S<b>104</b>). In this manner, the operation screen image of the server <b>11</b> displayed on the PC <b>22</b> is constantly updated with the latest image.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, if the control unit <b>127</b> receives an operation code from the PC <b>22</b> through the operation screen image <b>232</b> displayed in accordance with the above operation flow while the signal processing device <b>12</b> is in communication with the PC <b>22</b> (step S<b>111</b>), the control unit <b>127</b> inputs the operation code into the K/M port <b>113</b> of the server <b>11</b> (step S<b>112</b>). By doing so, the server <b>11</b> can be remotely operated. The procedures of steps S<b>111</b> and S<b>112</b> are repeated as long as the server <b>11</b> is accessed by the PC <b>22</b>, or until the line between the PC <b>22</b> and the signal processing device <b>12</b> is disconnected (step S<b>113</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">Referring now to the flowcharts of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9 through 11</figref>, the procedures to be carried out to operate the server <b>11</b> by the local console <b>12</b><i>a</i>, which is connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>, will be described in detail.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, when detecting the connection between the signal processing device <b>12</b> and the set of the monitor <b>13</b>, the keyboard <b>14</b>, and the mouse <b>15</b>, or when detecting the connection between the signal processing device <b>12</b> and the monitor <b>13</b> (“Yes” in step S<b>121</b>), the control unit <b>127</b> acquires information as to the display capacity of the monitor <b>13</b> through the DDC <b>122</b><i>b </i>(step S<b>122</b>), and inputs the display capacity information into the DDC terminal <b>112</b><i>a </i>via the DDC <b>122</b><i>a </i>(step S<b>123</b>). The control unit <b>127</b> then controls the video signal switching unit <b>123</b> to output a video signal V (an analog signal converted by the image processing unit <b>124</b>) inputted through the DVI processing unit <b>121</b>, or a video signal V inputted through the RGB processing unit <b>12</b>, to the monitor <b>13</b> (step S<b>124</b>). By doing so, the operation screen <b>131</b> of the server <b>11</b> can be displayed on the monitor <b>13</b> that is locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>. The procedure of step S<b>124</b> is repeated until the line between the monitor <b>13</b> and the signal processing device <b>12</b> is disconnected (step S<b>125</b>). Thus, the operation screen <b>131</b> displayed on the monitor <b>13</b> is constantly updated with the latest screen image.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, while the line is connected between the signal processing device <b>12</b> and the monitor <b>13</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> determines whether an operation code is entered from the keyboard <b>14</b> or the mouse <b>15</b> (of the local console <b>12</b><i>a</i>) that is locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b> (step S<b>131</b>). When an operation code is entered from the local console <b>12</b><i>a </i>(“Yes” in step S<b>131</b>), the control unit <b>127</b> determines whether the operation code is a predetermined operation code entered by pressing a predetermined key (step S<b>132</b>). If the operation code is the predetermined operation code (“Yes” in step S<b>132</b>), a predetermined routine that is stored beforehand in a ROM or the like is activated (step S<b>135</b>). The operation then returns to step S<b>131</b>, and the control unit <b>127</b> waits for an operation code to be entered from the local console <b>12</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">If the operation code entered in step S<b>131</b> is not the predetermined operation code (“No” in step S<b>132</b>), the control unit <b>127</b> inputs the operation code into the K/M port <b>113</b> of the server <b>11</b> from the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b> via the K/M processing unit <b>125</b> (step S<b>133</b>). The control unit <b>127</b> repeats the procedures of steps S<b>131</b> through S<b>133</b> and the procedure of step S<b>135</b> until the line between the local console <b>12</b><i>a </i>and the signal processing device <b>12</b> is disconnected (step S<b>134</b>). Thus, an environment suitable for performing an input operation on the server <b>11</b> through the local console <b>12</b><i>a </i>can be realized.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, the predetermined routine that is started in step S<b>135</b> in the flowchart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">When the predetermined routine is started, the control unit <b>127</b> first generates the console screen image <b>132</b> (step S<b>141</b>), and inputs the console screen image <b>132</b> into the image processing unit <b>124</b>. The control unit <b>127</b> controls the image processing unit <b>124</b> to generate the image data of the console screen image <b>132</b> (step S<b>142</b>). The control unit <b>127</b> then controls the image processing unit <b>124</b> to generate a video signal V<sub>C </sub>of the image data (step S<b>143</b>), and to superimpose the video signal V of the operation screen <b>131</b> on the video signal V<sub>C </sub>(step S<b>144</b>). Here, the video signal V is the video signal V inputted in step S<b>124</b> in the flowchart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. Accordingly, in step S<b>124</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the video signal V outputted to the monitor <b>13</b> is a video signal superimposed with the video signal V<sub>c</sub>. Thus, the monitor <b>13</b> can display the operation screen <b>131</b> on which the console screen image <b>132</b> is shown in an overlaid fashion. The control unit <b>127</b> then determines whether an instruction to exit from the predetermined routine (an exit command) has been issued (step S<b>145</b>). In a case where such an instruction has been issued (“Yes” in step S<b>145</b>), the operation exits from the predetermined routine. In a case where such an instruction has not been issued (“No” in step S<b>145</b>), the control unit <b>127</b> updates the console screen image <b>132</b> (step S<b>146</b>), and returns to step S<b>142</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">In a case where the console screen of the signal processing device <b>12</b> is to be displayed on the monitor <b>23</b> of the PC <b>22</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> first generates a console screen image (step S<b>151</b>), as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>. The control unit <b>127</b> inputs the console screen image into the image processing unit <b>124</b>, which in turn generates the image data of the console screen image (step S<b>152</b>). The control unit <b>127</b> then superimposes the image data of the operation screen image <b>232</b> on the image data of the console screen image (step S<b>153</b>), and inputs the superimposed data into the communication processing unit <b>128</b>. The communication processing unit <b>128</b> converts the image data of the operation screen image <b>232</b>, which are superimposed on the image data of the console screen image, into an IP packet P, and then transmits the IP packet P to the PC <b>22</b> via the LAN <b>20</b> (step S<b>154</b>). The control unit <b>127</b> then determines whether an instruction to exit from the predetermined routine (an exit command) has been issued (step S<b>155</b>). In a case where such an instruction has been issued (“Yes” in step S<b>155</b>), the operation exits from the predetermined routine. In a case where such an instruction has not been issued (“No” in step S<b>155</b>), the control unit <b>127</b> updates the console screen image (step S<b>156</b>), and then returns to step S<b>152</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">In the above manner, an environment suitable for performing a remote operation on the server <b>11</b> through the PC <b>22</b> that is connected to the server <b>11</b> via a network can be realized, and the signal processing device <b>12</b> that can provide such an environment can be obtained. Also, an environment suitable for performing a direct input operation on the server <b>11</b> through the local console <b>12</b><i>a</i>, which is locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>, can be realized.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">The above described first embodiment is merely one of the preferred embodiments of the present invention, and various changes and modifications can be made to it as follows.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, a second embodiment of the present invention will be described in detail. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> schematically illustrates the structure of a remote operation system <b>1</b>A in accordance with this embodiment. In the following description, the same components as those of the first embodiment are denoted by the same reference numerals as those of the first embodiment, and explanation of them will not be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">The remote operation system <b>1</b>A shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> differs from the remote operation system <b>1</b> of the first embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> in that the PC <b>22</b> locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b> via a network (the LAN <b>20</b>) is replaced with a signal processing device <b>12</b>A. Other than this aspect, the remote operation system <b>1</b>A of this embodiment has the same structure as the remote operation system <b>1</b> of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">The signal processing device <b>12</b>A has the same structure as the signal processing device <b>12</b>. Therefore, the operation of the signal processing device <b>12</b>A will be described, with reference to the block diagram of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. However, as the server <b>11</b> is not connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>A, the structure on the side of the server <b>11</b> will not be described below. For ease of explanation using the block diagram of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, the monitor, the keyboard, and the mouse, which are locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>A, are also denoted by reference numerals <b>23</b>, <b>24</b>, and <b>25</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">An operator on the side of the signal processing device <b>12</b>A uses a console that includes the monitor <b>23</b>, the keyboard <b>24</b>, and the mouse <b>25</b>, and makes a request to the signal processing device <b>12</b> for access to the server <b>11</b> through the signal processing device <b>12</b>A. At this point, the console screen image of the signal processing device <b>12</b>A is displayed on the monitor <b>23</b>, for example. An operation code that is entered from the keyboard <b>24</b> or the mouse <b>25</b> is inputted into the control unit <b>127</b> via the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b>, and is then converted into an operation code. When receiving an operation code that represents a request for access to the server <b>11</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> makes a request to the signal processing device <b>12</b> for access to the server <b>11</b> via the communication processing unit <b>128</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">When the communication processing unit <b>128</b> of the signal processing device <b>12</b>A receives an IP packet P that contains the image data of the operation screen image <b>232</b> from the signal processing device <b>12</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> of the signal processing device <b>12</b>A reconstructs the image data in the communication processing unit <b>128</b>, and inputs the reconstructed image data into the image processing unit <b>124</b>. In the image processing unit <b>124</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> converts the image data into an analog video signal VA, and inputs the video signal VA into the monitor <b>23</b> via the video signal switching unit <b>123</b>. Thus, the operation screen image <b>232</b> of the server <b>11</b> is displayed on the monitor <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">When an operation code is entered from the keyboard <b>24</b> or the mouse <b>25</b> through the displayed operation screen image <b>232</b>, the control unit <b>127</b> receives the operation code via the local K/M processing unit <b>126</b>, and generates an operation code based on the received operation code. The operation code is then converted into an IP packet P in the communication processing unit <b>128</b>, and the IP packet P is transmitted to the signal processing device <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">In the above manner, the server <b>11</b> can be remotely operated. The other aspects and operations of this embodiment are the same as those of the first embodiment, and therefore, explanation of them is omitted herein. The second embodiment is also merely one of the preferred embodiments of the present invention, and more changes and modifications can be made to it.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Third Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>, a third embodiment of the present invention will be described in detail. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> schematically illustrates the structure of a remote operation system <b>1</b>B in accordance with this embodiment. In the description below, the same components as those of the first embodiment are denoted by the same reference numerals as those of the first embodiment, and explanation of them will not be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">The remote operation system <b>1</b>B shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> differs from the remote operation system <b>1</b> of the first embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> in that the signal processing device <b>12</b> is connected to more than one server (three servers <b>11</b><i>a </i>through <b>11</b><i>c</i>, for example) via a switching device <b>40</b>. Each of the servers <b>11</b><i>a </i>through <b>11</b><i>c </i>has the same structure as the server <b>11</b> of the first embodiment. Other than this aspect, the remote operation system <b>1</b>B is the same as the remote operation system <b>1</b> of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">The switching device <b>40</b> is a structure for selectively connecting the signal processing device <b>12</b> to one of the servers <b>11</b><i>a </i>through <b>11</b><i>c</i>. When the signal processing device <b>12</b> makes a request for access to the server <b>11</b><i>a </i>via the serial port <b>114</b> or the K/M port <b>113</b>, for example, the switching device <b>40</b> forms a path that connects the server <b>11</b><i>a </i>and the signal processing device <b>12</b> to each other, thereby providing a virtual situation in which the signal processing device <b>12</b> and the server <b>11</b><i>a </i>are connected directly to each other. The request for access to the server <b>11</b><i>a </i>is generated in the control unit <b>127</b> in accordance with an operation code that is entered from the PC <b>22</b> via the LAN <b>20</b> or an operation code that is entered from the keyboard <b>14</b> or the mouse <b>15</b> locally connected to the signal processing device <b>12</b>. The request for access is then inputted into the switching device <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">In the above described manner, the signal processing device <b>12</b> is connected to more than one server via the switching device <b>40</b>. With this structure, only one signal processing device <b>12</b> is required for two or more servers, and it is not necessary to employ two or more signal processing devices <b>12</b>. The other aspects and operations of this embodiment are the same as those of the first embodiment, and therefore, explanation of them is omitted herein.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">The computer program product of the present invention may be a recording medium such as a hard disk, CD-ROM and an electronic memory.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">Although a few preferred embodiments of the present invention have been shown and described, it would be appreciated by those skilled in the art that changes may be made in these embodiments without departing from the principles and spirit of the invention, the scope of which is defined in the claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A signal processing device that is used for remotely operating a server via an IP network, comprising:
<claim-text>a first input unit that inputs an operation screen image of the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first output unit that outputs the image data to the IP network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second input unit that inputs operation information via the IP network, the operation information being required for operating the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface via which a keyboard, a mouse and a monitor are connected directly to the signal processing device so that the server can be operated locally in addition to the remotely operating via the IP network.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said interface further comprising:
<claim-text>a first terminal that connects with the monitor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second terminal that connects with the keyboard or the mouse;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third output unit that outputs the operation screen image to the monitor via the first terminal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third input unit that inputs operation information from the keyboard or the mouse via the second terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second output unit outputs the operation information, which is inputted through the third input unit, to the server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a determination unit that determines whether the operation information inputted through the third input unit is predetermined operation information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a console screen image generating unit that generates a console screen image of the signal processing device, when the operation information is determined to be the predetermined operation information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth output unit that outputs the console screen image to the monitor in such a manner that the console screen image is overlaid on the operation screen image; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a processing unit that performs predetermined processing in accordance with the operation information inputted from the second input unit through the console screen image displayed on the monitor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the second output unit outputs the operation information to a keyboard connector or a mouse connector of the server.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the second output unit outputs the operation information to a serial port of the server.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the first input unit inputs a video signal of the operation screen image via a display connector; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the image processing unit generates the image data in accordance with the video signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the IP network includes a local area network or the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said interface further comprising a first port via which the operation screen image of the server is output to the monitor connected to the signal processing device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said interface further comprising:
<claim-text>a first port via which the operation screen image of the server is output to the monitor connected to the signal processing device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second port via which local operation information are input to the server, including signals from the keyboard and mouse directly connected to the to the signal processing device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the operation information and said local operation information being sent to the server so that the server can selectively use the operation information and said local operation information.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The signal processing device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said image processing unit further generates a console screen image and superimposes the console screen image onto the operation screen image data that is input via the first input unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A remote operation system, comprising:
<claim-text>a signal processing device that is connected to a server; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an information processing apparatus that remotely operates the server through the signal processing device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the signal processing device and the information processing apparatus being connected to each other via an IP network</claim-text>
<claim-text>the signal processing device including:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first input unit that inputs an operation screen image of the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first output unit that outputs the image data to the information processing apparatus via the IP network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second input unit that inputs operation information from the information processing apparatus via the IP network, the operation information being required for operating the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface via which a keyboard, a mouse and a display are connected directly to the signal processing device so that the server can be operated locally in addition to the remotely operating via the IP network; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the information processing apparatus including:
<claim-text>a third input unit that inputs the image data outputted from the first output unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a display unit that displays the image data; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third output unit that outputs operation information of the server to the signal processing device via the network, the operation information of the server being inputted in accordance with the display unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A remote operation system, comprising:
<claim-text>a first signal processing device that is connected to a server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second signal processing device that is connected to the first signal processing device via an IP network; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a monitor that is connected to the second signal processing device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first signal processing device including:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first input unit that inputs an operation screen image of the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first output unit that outputs the image data to the second signal processing device via the IP network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second input unit that inputs operation information from the second signal processing device via the IP network, the operation information being required for operating the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface via which a keyboard, a mouse and a display are connected directly to the signal processing device so that the server can be operated locally in addition to the remotely operating via the IP network,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second signal processing device including:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third input unit that inputs the image data outputted from the first output unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a display unit that displays the image data on the monitor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third output unit that outputs operation information of the server to the first signal processing device via the network, the operation information of the server being inputted in accordance with the display unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A remote operation system, comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of servers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a signal processing device that processes a signal outputted from one of the plurality of servers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switching device that selectively connects the signal processing device to one of the plurality of servers; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an information processing apparatus that remotely operates one of the plurality of servers through the signal processing device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the signal processing device including:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first input unit that selectively inputs an operation screen image of one of the plurality of servers via the switching device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an image processing unit that generates image data in accordance with the operation screen image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first output unit that outputs the image data to the information processing apparatus via an IP network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second input unit that inputs operation information from the information processing apparatus via the IP network, the operation information being required for operating the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second output unit that outputs the operation information to the server via the switching device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface via which a keyboard, a mouse and a display are connected directly to the signal processing device so that the server can be operated locally in addition to the remotely operating via the IP network,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the information processing apparatus including:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third input unit that inputs the image data outputted from the first output unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a display unit that displays the image data; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third output unit that outputs operation information of the server to the signal processing device via the network, the operation information of the server being inputted in accordance with the display unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method of processing a signal in a device for remotely operating a server via an IP network, the method comprising:
<claim-text>inputting an operation screen image from the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating image data in accordance with the operation screen image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>outputting the image data to the IP network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>inputting operation information via the IP network, the operation information being required for operating the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>outputting the operation information to the server; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>interfacing with a keyboard, a mouse and a display so as to be connected directly to the device so that the server can be operated locally in addition to the remotely operating via the IP network.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, said interfacing further comprising:
<claim-text>outputting the operation screen image to the monitor that is connected to the device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>inputting operation information through the keyboard or the mouse that is connected to the device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the operation information, which is inputted through the keyboard or the mouse, is outputted to the server when outputting the operation information to the server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, said interfacing further comprising:
<claim-text>determining whether the operation information inputted through the keyboard or the mouse is predetermined operation information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating a console screen image of the device, when the operation information is determined to be the predetermined operation information</claim-text>
<claim-text>outputting the console screen image to the monitor in such a manner that the console screen image is overlaid on the operation screen image; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>performing predetermined processing in accordance with operation information inputted through the console screen image displayed on the monitor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A computer readable medium storing a program for causing a computer to remotely operate a server via an IP network via a signal processing device, the computer readable medium causing the computer to execute:
<claim-text>generating image data in accordance with an operation screen image that is inputted from the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>outputting the image data to the IP network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>inputting operation information via the IP network, the operation information being required for operating the server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>outputting the information the server; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>interfacing with a keyboard, a mouse and a display so as to be connected directly to the device so that the server can be operated locally in addition to the remote operation via the IP network.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The computer readable medium as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, said interfacing further comprising:
<claim-text>outputting the operation screen image to a monitor that is connected to the computer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>inputting operation information through a keyboard or a mouse that is connected to the computer,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the operation information, which is inputted through the keyboard or the mouse, is outputted to the server in accordance with the instruction for outputting the operation information to the server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The computer readable medium as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, said interfacing further comprising:
<claim-text>determining whether the operation information inputted through the keyboard or the mouse is predetermined operation information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating a console screen image of a signal processing device when the operation information inputted through the keyboard or the mouse is determined to be the predetermined operation information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>outputting the console screen image to the monitor in such a manner that the console screen image is overlaid on the operation screen image; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>performing predetermined processing in accordance with operation information inputted through the console screen image displayed on the monitor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
