<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296311-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296311</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11478764</doc-number>
<date>20060630</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>47</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>23</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  55071</main-classification>
<further-classification>  5659</further-classification>
<further-classification>108 49</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Mattress supported frame and tray</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3698328</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Weir</name>
<date>19721000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3894709</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Weir</name>
<date>19750700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4404698</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Koncelik et al.</name>
<date>19830900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>  55071</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4465255</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hill</name>
<date>19840800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4819568</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Coffrin</name>
<date>19890400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5009379</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sadler</name>
<date>19910400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>248174</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5038434</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Navarrette</name>
<date>19910800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5359741</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lang</name>
<date>19941100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5642541</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Corbin</name>
<date>19970700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6742204</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Barker</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>  55071</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6834403</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Elliott</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>  55051</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  55031</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  55071</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  5659</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  5426</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  5658</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>108 49</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>12</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Navarrette</last-name>
<first-name>Philip F.</first-name>
<address>
<street>12339 Dorland #A</street>
<city>Whittier</city>
<state>CA</state>
<postcode>90601</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Green</last-name>
<first-name>Kenneth L.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Averill, Jr.</last-name>
<first-name>Edgar W.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Trettel</last-name>
<first-name>Michael</first-name>
<department>3673</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A tray is supported by a tubular frame residing between a mattress and box spring. The frame is a single continuous loop of tubing having a substantially horizontally residing supported portion, a vertical center portion, and a substantially horizontal tray support portion. The tray is rectangular with a raised edge and includes clips residing on a tray bottom to snap onto the frame.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="140.63mm" wi="317.58mm" file="US07296311-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="211.24mm" wi="163.49mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296311-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="216.66mm" wi="164.68mm" file="US07296311-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="226.91mm" wi="174.67mm" file="US07296311-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a support frame and tray and in particular to a mattress supported tubular support frame and snap-on tray.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">There is often a need for a tray adjacent to a bed to hold various articles such as books, lamps, food, drinks, and the like. One solution is a tray with legs which support the tray above the floor. Unfortunately, such floor supported trays are often cumbersome and easily knocked over. Other solutions comprise trays supported by a frame residing between a mattress and box spring. Such frames generally comprise a flat plate residing horizontally when in use, and vertical members rising from the flat plate to support the tray. Unfortunately, such flat plates may slip between the mattress and box spring, and comprise several members raising production costs. Therefore, a need remains for a simple and stable mattress supported frame and tray.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention addresses the above and other needs by providing a tray supported by a tubular frame residing between a mattress and box spring. The frame is a single continuous loop of tubing having a substantially horizontally residing supported portion, a vertical center portion, and a substantially horizontal tray support portion. The tray is rectangular with a raised edge and includes clips residing on a tray bottom to snap onto the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In accordance with one aspect of the invention, there is provided a mattress supported frame and tray. The frame is a substantially round tubular frame having a supported portion, a center portion, and a tray support portion. The supported portion is substantially planar (i.e., may include some vertical variation, but not enough to affect the mattress) and has an inward end insertable under a mattress and an outward end opposite the inward end. The center portion is approximately orthogonal to the supported portion and has a lower end extending vertically from the outward end of the supported portion and a higher end opposite the lower end. The tray support portion is approximately parallel to the supported portion and extends horizontally from the higher end of the center portion, extending opposite the supported portion. The tray includes pairs of downwardly extending opposed clips configured to grasp the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In accordance with another aspect of the invention, there is provided a mattress supported frame and tray having a continuous tube frame.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWING</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The above and other aspects, features and advantages of the present invention will be more apparent from the following more particular description thereof, presented in conjunction with the following drawings wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a bed with a mattress supportable frame and tray according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is detailed perspective view of the mattress supportable frame and tray alone.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a detailed perspective view of the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> is a side view of the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> is a front view of the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> is a top view of the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a detailed perspective view of the tray.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> is a front view of the tray.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> is a side view of the tray.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref> is a top view of the tray.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref> is a bottom view of the tray.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> show fingers with concave inner opposing surfaces.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Corresponding reference characters indicate corresponding components throughout the several views of the drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The following description is of the best mode presently contemplated for carrying out the invention. This description is not to be taken in a limiting sense, but is made merely for the purpose of describing one or more preferred embodiments of the invention. The scope of the invention should be determined with reference to the claims.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">A perspective view of a bed <b>10</b> with a mattress supportable frame and tray <b>22</b> according to the present invention is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The bed includes a bed frame <b>16</b> supporting a mattress <b>12</b> and usually a box spring <b>14</b>. A frame <b>20</b> of the frame and tray <b>22</b> is inserted between the mattress <b>12</b> and the box spring <b>14</b> to support and secure the frame <b>20</b>. A tray <b>18</b> is attached to the frame <b>20</b> for convenient use.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">A detailed perspective view of the mattress supportable frame and tray <b>22</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, The frame includes a supported portion <b>24</b> which is inserted between the mattress <b>12</b> and the box spring <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">A detailed perspective view of the frame <b>20</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a side view of the frame <b>20</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>, a front view of the frame <b>20</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>, and a top view of the frame is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>. The frame <b>20</b> includes a substantially planar supported portion <b>24</b>, a center portion <b>26</b>, and a tray support portion <b>28</b>. The supported portion <b>24</b> has an inward end <b>24</b><i>a </i>insertable under the mattress <b>12</b> and an outward end <b>24</b><i>b </i>opposite the inward end <b>24</b><i>a</i>. The center portion <b>26</b> is preferably approximately orthogonal to the supported portion <b>24</b> and has a lower end <b>26</b><i>a </i>extending from the outward end <b>24</b><i>b </i>of the supported portion <b>24</b> and a higher end <b>26</b><i>b </i>opposite the lower end <b>26</b><i>a</i>. The center portion <b>26</b> is not necessarily orthogonal to the supported portion <b>24</b> but should have some vertical extent to raise the height of the tray <b>18</b> when in use. If the center portion <b>26</b> is sloped too much, the tray <b>18</b> may be displaced from the bed <b>10</b>, however, in an alternative embodiment, a center portion may slope away from the bed <b>10</b>, and the tray support portion <b>28</b> may be reversed and extend back towards the bed <b>10</b>. The tray support portion <b>28</b> is approximately parallel to the supported portion <b>24</b> and extends from the higher end <b>26</b><i>b </i>of the center portion <b>26</b>, extending opposite the supported portion <b>24</b>. The tray support portion <b>28</b> comprises longitudinal portions <b>28</b><i>a </i>and a lateral portion <b>28</b><i>b </i>running between the longitudinal portions <b>28</b><i>a</i>, and the longitudinal portions <b>28</b><i>a </i>are preferably approximately parallel.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The frame <b>20</b> has a width W<b>1</b> which is preferably between approximately ten inches and approximately fourteen inches, and more preferably approximately twelve inches. The frame <b>20</b> has a height H<b>1</b> which is preferably between approximately ten inches and approximately eighteen inches, and more preferably between approximately twelve inches and approximately sixteen inches. The supported portion <b>24</b> has a length L<b>3</b> of preferably between approximately ten inches and approximately sixteen inches, and more preferably between approximately twelve inches and approximately fourteen inches. The tray support portion <b>28</b> has a length L<b>2</b> of preferably between approximately six inches and approximately ten inches, and more preferably approximately eight inches.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The frame <b>20</b> is preferably made from tubing and more preferably from round tubing. The frame <b>20</b> is also preferably a continuous loop and more preferably a continuous loop of tubing, for example, a continuous length of bent tubing, and most preferably joined at one or two points along the frame, and more preferably joined by welding at two points along the frame. The tubing preferably has an outside diameter between approximately ½ inches and ¾ inches and more preferably approximately ⅝ inches.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">A detailed perspective view of the tray <b>18</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a front view of the tray <b>18</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, a side view of the tray <b>18</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, a top view of the tray <b>18</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref>, and a bottom view of the tray <b>18</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref>. The tray is approximately flat and has a top surface <b>18</b><i>a </i>which is preferably textured to reduce sliding. An edge <b>30</b> surrounds the tray <b>18</b> and provides stiffness. An upper edge portion <b>30</b><i>a </i>forms an edge around the top surface <b>18</b><i>a </i>to reduce the chance of items rolling or sliding off the tray top surface <b>18</b><i>a</i>. The edge <b>30</b> preferably includes a lower edge portion <b>30</b><i>b </i>extending downward to add stiffness.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Attaching features <b>32</b> for attaching the tray <b>20</b> to the frame <b>18</b> are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The attaching features reside on the a tray bottom surface <b>18</b><i>b</i>. The attaching features <b>32</b> are preferably spaced apart opposing clips or fingers which the tray support portion <b>28</b> of the frame <b>18</b> snaps into. More preferably, attaching features <b>32</b> are pairs of downwardly extending fingers with concave inner opposing surfaces <b>32</b><i>a </i>to retain the tray <b>20</b> once snapped onto the frame <b>18</b>. Most preferably, the attaching features <b>32</b> comprise three pairs of spaced apart pairs (a total of six pairs of fingers) of downwardly extending fingers which snap onto the longitudinal portions <b>28</b><i>a </i>and the lateral portion <b>28</b><i>b </i>of the tray support portion <b>28</b>. Alternatively, the three pairs of spaced apart pairs of fingers may be replaced by 3 pairs of continuous clips, one pair of clips for each of the longitudinal portions <b>28</b><i>a </i>and one pair of clips for the lateral portion <b>28</b><i>b</i>. In another instance, the attaching features may be screws or similar fasteners passing though holes in the tray support portion and into the tray, or adhesives to attach the tray to the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The tray <b>20</b> has a tray width W<b>2</b>, a tray length L<b>4</b>, and a tray thickness T. The tray length L<b>4</b> is preferably approximately equal to the frame width W<b>1</b> to facilitate packaging the frame and tray <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">While the invention herein disclosed has been described by means of specific embodiments and applications thereof, numerous modifications and variations could be made thereto by those skilled in the art without departing from the scope of the invention set forth in the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A mattress supported frame and tray comprising:
<claim-text>a single continuous bent tube tubular frame having:
<claim-text>a tubular substantially planar supported portion having an inward end insertable under a mattress and an outward end opposite the inward end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tubular center portion approximately orthogonal to the supported portion and having a lower end extending from the outward end of the supported portion and a higher end opposite the lower end; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tubular tray support portion approximately parallel to the supported portion and extending from the higher end of the center portion opposite the supported portion; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tray configured to attach to the tray support portion of the frame.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The frame and tray of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the tray has a bottom surface including clips which snap onto the tray support portion to attach the tray to the frame.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The frame and tray of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the clips comprise opposing pairs of downward protruding fingers to grasp the frame.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The frame and tray of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the opposing pairs of downward protruding fingers include concave inner opposing surfaces.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The frame and tray of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein;
<claim-text>the tray support portion comprises two longitudinal portions joined by a lateral portion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the clips comprise six pairs of opposing downward protruding fingers arranged to grasp the two longitudinal portions and the lateral portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The frame and tray of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the longitudinal portions are approximately parallel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The frame and tray of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the tray includes a tray edge to add stiffness to the tray.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The frame and tray of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the tray edge includes a downward extending edge and an upward extending edge.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The frame and tray of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the length of the tray is approximately equal to the width of the frame to facilitate packaging the frame and tray for shipping.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A mattress supported frame and tray comprising:
<claim-text>a continuous round tubular frame having:
<claim-text>a planar supported portion having an inward end insertable under a mattress and an outward end opposite the inward end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a center portion approximately orthogonal to the supported portion and having a lower end extending from the outward end of the supported portion and a higher end opposite the lower end; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tray support portion approximately parallel to the supported portion and extending from the higher end of the center portion opposite the supported portion; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tray including pairs of downwardly extending opposed clips configured to grasp the frame.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A mattress supported frame and tray comprising:
<claim-text>a continuous tubular frame having:
<claim-text>a substantially planar supported portion having an inward end insertable under a mattress and an outward end opposite the inward end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a center portion approximately orthogonal to the supported portion and having a lower end extending from the outward end of the supported portion and a higher end opposite the lower end; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tray support portion approximately parallel to the supported portion and extending from the higher end of the center portion opposite the supported portion;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tray configured to attach to the tray support portion of the frame; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>three pairs of two pairs of opposing fingers having concave inner opposing surface and residing on a bottom surface of the tray for attaching the tray to the frame.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
