<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299323-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299323</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11072870</doc-number>
<date>20050304</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2004-0015591</doc-number>
<date>20040308</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>341</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>12</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>711155</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Memory controller having a read-modify-write function</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5737744</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Callison et al.</name>
<date>19980400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>711114</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6718444</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hughes</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>711155</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6868486</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ward</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>711158</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>5298179</doc-number>
<date>19931200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>7129468</doc-number>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-003302</doc-number>
<date>20000700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>711155</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050198458</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050908</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cho</last-name>
<first-name>Sang-Yeun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>F. Chau &amp; Associates, LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung Electronics Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Suwon-Si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ellis</last-name>
<first-name>Kevin L.</first-name>
<department>2188</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Provided are a memory controller with data read-modify-write function, and a system-on-chip (SOC) having such a memory controller, where the memory controller is connected to a memory, the memory controller is connected to IP (intellectual property) blocks and a microprocessor via a system bus, and, in response to one of read, write, and modify request signals received from the one of the IP blocks or the microprocessor and an address signal, the memory controller reads a data signal from the memory, writes a write data signal to the memory, or modifies the data signal read from the memory and writes the modified data signal to the memory such that the memory controller and the SOC can reduce occupation time for the system bus and access time for the memory and additionally reduce unnecessary power consumption.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="157.31mm" wi="233.17mm" file="US07299323-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="178.65mm" wi="158.24mm" file="US07299323-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="178.05mm" wi="161.21mm" file="US07299323-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="234.02mm" wi="161.88mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299323-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="162.22mm" wi="142.83mm" file="US07299323-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims foreign priority under 35 U.S.C. ยง 119 to Korean Patent Application No. 2004-15591, filed on Mar. 8, 2004, in the Korean Intellectual Property Office, the disclosure of which is incorporated herein in its entirety by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present disclosure relates to memory controllers, and more particularly, to memory controllers for system-on-chip (SOC) operation.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In general, a system-on-chip (SOC) may include a memory controller for accessing an external memory. For example, the external memories accessed by the SOC may include non-volatile memories such as ROMs and Flash memories, used primarily to store programs, and volatile memories such as SRAMs and SDRAMs, used for various applications. An example of a conventional SOC is disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 6,526,462.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram showing a SOC <b>10</b> comprising a conventional memory controller <b>12</b> and an external memory <b>20</b>. The SOC <b>10</b> comprises the memory controller <b>12</b>, intellectual property (IP) blocks <b>13</b> and <b>14</b>, a microprocessor <b>15</b>, an internal memory <b>16</b>, and a direct memory access unit (DMA) <b>17</b>. The SOC <b>10</b> may further comprise additional IP blocks and others, which are omitted for the sake of simplification. The memory controller <b>12</b>, the IP blocks <b>13</b> and <b>14</b>, the microprocessor <b>15</b>, the internal memory <b>16</b>, and the DMA <b>17</b>, which are connected to a system bus <b>11</b>, are in communication with each other. In addition, in some cases, data stored in the external memory <b>20</b> needs to be error-corrected. An error correcting code (ECC) processor (not shown) of an optical disk system as known in the art is an example of an apparatus for error-correcting the data stored in the external memory and rewriting data. The ECC processor reads error correcting data out of the data stored in the external memory and performs an XOR operation on the read data and calculated error mask data, and rewrites the result of the XOR operation to the external memory. Similarly to the ECC processor, one of the IP blocks <b>13</b> and <b>14</b> in the SOC <b>10</b> reads data stored in the external memory <b>20</b>, modifies the read data, and rewrites the modified data to the external memory <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the aforementioned operations are performed by the IP block <b>13</b>. The IP block <b>13</b> requests the memory controller <b>12</b> to read data of the external memory <b>20</b> via the system bus <b>11</b>. Next, the IP block <b>13</b> receives data read from the external memory <b>20</b> via the system bus <b>11</b> from the memory controller <b>12</b>, as shown in line A. The IP block <b>13</b> modifies the read data and transmits the modified data to the memory controller <b>12</b> via the system bus <b>11</b>, as shown in line B. The memory controller <b>12</b> writes the modified data received from the IP block <b>13</b> via the system bus <b>11</b> to the external memory <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Here, in order to use the system bus <b>11</b>, the IP block <b>13</b> must acquire a privilege for the system bus <b>11</b> from an arbiter (not shown). In addition, in order to read the data stored in the external memory <b>20</b>, the IP block <b>13</b> must acquire the privilege for the system bus <b>11</b> from the arbiter, and transmit a read address signal to the memory controller <b>12</b>, and transmit a control data signal to the memory controller <b>12</b>. In addition, in order to write the modified data to the external memory <b>20</b>, the IP block <b>13</b> must acquire the privilege for the system bus <b>11</b> from the arbiter, transmit a write address signal to the memory controller <b>12</b>, and transmit the modified data signal to the memory controller <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">As described above, during an operation of modifying the data signal stored in the external memory <b>20</b>, the IP block <b>13</b> occupies the system bus <b>11</b> twice. Therefore, there is a problem in that the occupation time of the IP block <b>13</b> occupying the system bus <b>11</b> is long. As a result, until the data transmission between the IP block <b>13</b> and the memory controller <b>12</b> is completed, other devices in the SOC <b>10</b> cannot use the system bus <b>11</b>, so that overall performance of the SOC <b>10</b> may decrease. In addition, during the operation of modifying the data signal stored in the external memory <b>20</b>, the address signal transmission and the data signal transmission between the IP block <b>13</b> and the memory controller <b>12</b> are performed twice, such that efficiency may be reduced.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present disclosure provides an exemplary memory controller capable of reducing occupation time for a system bus by reading, modifying, and writing data stored in a memory.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The present disclosure also provides an exemplary SOC (system-on-chip) comprising a memory controller capable of reducing occupation time for a system bus by reading, modifying, and writing data stored in a memory.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to an aspect of the present disclosure, there is provided a memory controller, wherein the memory controller is connected to a memory, wherein the memory controller is connected to intellectual property (IP) blocks and a microprocessor via a system bus, and wherein, in response to one of read, write, and modify request signals received from the one of the IP blocks or the microprocessor and an address signal, the memory controller reads a data signal from the memory, writes a write data signal to the memory, or modifies the data signal read from the memory and writes the modified data signal to the memory.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to another aspect of the present disclosure, there is provided a SOC (system-on-chip) comprising a microprocessor connected to a system bus, the microprocessor controlling all devices connected to the system bus and executing a predetermined program; an internal memory storing the predetermined program or main data obtained in operations of the microprocessor; IP blocks connected to the system bus, each of the IP blocks performing a predetermined function; and a memory controller connected to an external memory and the system bus, wherein, in response to one of read, write, and modify request signals received from the one of the IP blocks or the microprocessor and an address signal, the memory controller reads a data signal from the external memory, writes a write data signal to the external memory, or modifies the data signal read from the external memory and writes the modified data signal to the external memory.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The above and other features of the present disclosure will become more apparent by describing in detail exemplary embodiments thereof with reference to the attached drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic block diagram showing a system-on-chip (SOC) comprising a conventional memory controller and an external memory;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic block diagram showing a SOC comprising a memory controller according to the present disclosure and an external memory;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic diagram showing the memory controller of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic diagram showing a data modification unit of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The present disclosure and operational advantages thereof may be more fully understood by referring to the accompanying drawings and explanations thereof. Exemplary embodiments of the present disclosure will be described with reference to the accompanying drawings to explain the present disclosure in detail. In the drawings, like reference numerals may be used to indicate like elements.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram showing a system-on-chip (SOC) <b>100</b> comprising a memory controller <b>120</b> according to the present disclosure, and an external memory <b>200</b>. The SOC <b>100</b> comprises the memory controller <b>120</b>, intellectual property (IP) blocks <b>130</b> and <b>140</b>, a microprocessor <b>150</b>, an internal memory <b>160</b>, and a direct memory access (DMA) unit <b>170</b>. The memory controller <b>120</b>, the IP blocks <b>130</b> and <b>140</b>, the microprocessor <b>150</b>, the internal memory <b>160</b>, and the DMA <b>170</b>, which are each connected to a system bus <b>110</b>, are in communication with each other via the system bus <b>110</b>. Detailed descriptions of devices in the SOC <b>100</b> that are not related to the present disclosure are omitted for brevity. The IP blocks <b>130</b> and <b>140</b> or the microprocessor <b>150</b> request the memory controller <b>120</b> to perform operations of reading, writing, or modifying data in the external memory <b>200</b>. The memory controller <b>120</b> performs a control operation on the external memory <b>200</b> requested by one of the IP blocks <b>130</b> and <b>140</b> or the microprocessor <b>150</b>. Detailed description of operations for reading and writing data in the external memory <b>200</b> is omitted because these operations are well known by those of ordinary skill in the related art. In this exemplary embodiment of the present disclosure, the operation of modifying the data stored in the external memory <b>200</b> under the control of the IP block <b>130</b> will be described in detail.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As shown in line C of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the IP block <b>130</b> requests via the system bus <b>110</b> that the memory controller <b>120</b> modify data. As shown in line D, in response to the data modification request of the IP block <b>130</b>, the memory controller <b>120</b> reads a data signal stored in the external memory <b>200</b> and modifies the read data signal. As shown in line E, the memory controller <b>120</b> rewrites the modified data signal to the external memory <b>200</b>. As described above, even if the IP block <b>130</b> requests the memory controller <b>120</b> to modify data, the memory controller <b>120</b> automatically performs the operations of reading, modifying, and writing the data stored in the external memory <b>200</b>. Therefore, during the operation of modifying the data stored in the external memory <b>200</b>, the IP block <b>130</b> occupies the system bus <b>110</b> just one time, such that the occupation time of the IP block <b>130</b> occupying the system bus <b>110</b> can be reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a detailed view showing the exemplary memory controller <b>120</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The memory controller <b>120</b> comprises a controller <b>121</b>, an address generation unit <b>122</b>, an address buffer <b>123</b>, an input buffer <b>124</b>, a data modification unit <b>125</b>, an input data processor <b>126</b>, an output data processor <b>127</b>, a selection unit <b>128</b>, and an output buffer <b>129</b>. In response to a transmission request signal REQ received from the IP block <b>130</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> via the system bus <b>110</b>, the controller <b>121</b> initiates communication with the IP block <b>130</b>. The controller <b>121</b> receives any one of read, write, and modify request signals READ, WRITE, and MDFY, respectively, from the IP block <b>130</b>. When the controller receives the read request signal READ or the write request signal WRITE, the controller <b>121</b> further receives size information SIZE or length information LENG of the to-be-transmitted data signal from the IP block <b>130</b>. The size information SIZE means the number of bits of a data signal transmitted at one time between the memory controller <b>120</b> and the IP block <b>130</b>. For example, the size information SIZE is represented with 8-bit, 16-bit, 32-bit, and so on. In a case where the size information SIZE is 8-bit, the data signal is transmitted in units of 8 bits between the memory controller <b>120</b> and the IP block <b>130</b>. The length information LENG means a length of burst transmitted at one time when the data signal is transmitted in a burst manner between the memory controller <b>120</b> and the IP block <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">When it receives the modify request signal MDFY, the controller <b>121</b> further receives an arithmetic information signal ARMC from the IP block <b>130</b>. The arithmetic information signal ARMC denotes types of arithmetic operations of modifying a data signal read form the external memory <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In response to one of the read, modify, and write request signals READ, MDFY, and WRITE, the controller <b>121</b> outputs control signals CTL<b>1</b> to CTL<b>9</b>. In addition, the controller <b>121</b> outputs a chip selection signal CS, a read command signal CMD_READ, or a write command signal CMD_WRITE to the external memory <b>200</b>. In addition, the controller <b>121</b> outputs a memory clock signal MCLK to the external memory <b>200</b> based on a system clock signal SCLK received from a clock generation unit (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In response to a transmission control signal WAIT received from the external memory <b>200</b>, the controller <b>121</b> transmits a transmission ready signal READY to the IP block <b>130</b> via the system bus <b>110</b>. In response to the transmission ready signal READY, the IP block <b>130</b> determines whether or not a read data signal RE_DATA received from the memory controller <b>120</b> via system bus <b>110</b> is in a valid state.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">On the other hand, the IP block <b>130</b> may transmit the read request signal READ together with the modify request signal MDFY to the controller <b>121</b>. This is because the IP block <b>130</b> may use the read data signal RDATA that the memory controller <b>120</b> reads from the external memory <b>200</b> to modify, if necessary. Therefore, in response to the read request signal READ received together with the modify request signal MDFY, the controller <b>121</b> generates the control signal CTL<b>8</b>. As a result, in response to the control signal CTL<b>8</b>, the input data processor <b>126</b> transmits the read data signal RE_DATA to the IP block <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The address generation unit <b>122</b> receives an address signal ADD from IP block <b>130</b> via the system bus <b>110</b>. In response to the control signal CTL<b>1</b>, the address generation unit <b>122</b> generates a read address signal RADD or a write address signal WADD based on the received address signal ADD and outputs the read address signal RADD or the write address signal WADD to the address buffer <b>123</b>. The address buffer <b>123</b> stores the read address signal RADD or the write address signal WADD received from the address generation unit <b>122</b>, and, in response to the control signal CTL<b>2</b>, outputs the read address signal RADD or the write address signal WADD to the external memory <b>200</b>. The input buffer <b>124</b> stores the read data signal RDATA received from the external memory <b>200</b>, and, in response to the control signal CTL<b>3</b>, outputs the stored read data signal RDATA to the data modification unit <b>125</b> and the input data processor <b>126</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The data modification unit <b>125</b> is enabled or disabled in response to the control signal CTL<b>4</b>. In addition, the data modification unit <b>125</b> selects a type of an arithmetic operation in response to the control signal CTL <b>5</b>. When it is enabled, the data modification unit <b>125</b> performs the arithmetic operation on the read data signal RDATA and the arithmetic data signal AR_DATA and outputs the result of the arithmetic operation as a modification data signal MO_DATA. The data modification unit <b>125</b> will be described later in detail.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In response to the control signal CTL<b>8</b>, the input data processor <b>126</b> stores the read data signal RDATA received from the input buffer <b>124</b>. The input data processor <b>126</b> constructs the stored read data signal RDATA in a predetermined format, and outputs the resultant signal as read data RE_DATA via the system bus <b>110</b>. Here, the predetermined format is, for example, a specific transmission order of the read data signal RDATA and a size thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In response to the control signal CTL<b>9</b>, the output data processor <b>127</b> receives one of the write data signal WR_DATA and the arithmetic data signal AR_DATA from the IP block <b>130</b> via system bus <b>110</b> and stores the received data signal. The output data processor <b>127</b> constructs the stored write data signal WR_DATA or arithmetic data signal AR_DATA in a predetermined format and outputs the resultant data signal to the data modification unit <b>125</b> and the selection unit <b>128</b>. Here, when the controller <b>121</b> receives the write request signal WRITE via the system bus <b>110</b>, the output data processor <b>127</b> receives the write data signal WR_DATA via the system bus <b>110</b>. On the other hand, when the controller <b>121</b> receives the modify request signal MDFY via system bus <b>110</b>, the output data processor <b>127</b> receives the arithmetic data signal AR_DATA. In response to the control signal CTL<b>6</b>, the selection unit <b>128</b> selects one of the modification data signal MO_DATA and the output signal of the output data processor <b>127</b> and outputs the selected signal. In response to the control signal CTL<b>7</b>, the output buffer <b>129</b> stores the modification data signal MO_DATA or the write data signal WR_DATA output from the selection unit <b>128</b> and outputs the stored modification data signal MO_DATA or write data signal WR_DATA to the external memory <b>200</b>. The selection unit <b>128</b> is preferably implemented with a multiplexer.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a detailed view showing the data modification unit <b>125</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The data modification unit <b>125</b> comprises input gating circuits <b>181</b> and <b>182</b>, first to third arithmetic units <b>183</b> to <b>185</b>, and a multiplexer <b>186</b>. Although the data modification unit <b>125</b> comprises three arithmetic units <b>183</b> to <b>185</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the data modification unit <b>125</b> may further comprise additional arithmetic units, for example. In response to the control signal CTL<b>4</b>, the input gating circuits <b>181</b> and <b>182</b> outputs or holds the input signals. More specifically, in response to the control signal CTL <b>4</b>, the input gating circuit <b>181</b> outputs or holds the input arithmetic data signal AR_DATA. In addition, in response to the control signal CTL<b>4</b>, the input gating circuit <b>182</b> outputs or holds the input read data signal RDATA. The input gating circuits <b>181</b> and <b>182</b> may be implemented with, for example, AND gates. The first to third arithmetic units <b>183</b> to <b>185</b> performs arithmetic operations on the arithmetic data signal AR_DATA received from the input gating circuits <b>181</b> and <b>182</b> and the read data signal RDATA, and outputs the resultant signals FR_DAT, SR_DAT, and TR_DAT of the arithmetic operations. Here, the first to third arithmetic units <b>183</b> to <b>185</b> perform different arithmetic operations. For example, the first to third arithmetic units <b>183</b> to <b>185</b> perform an XOR operation, an addition operation, and a multiplication, respectively. In response to the control CTL<b>5</b>, the multiplexer <b>186</b> selects one of the resultant signals FR_DAT, SR_DAT, and TR_DAT of the arithmetic operations and outputs the selected signal as the modification data signal MO_DATA.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">On the other hand, although the data modification unit <b>125</b> performs various arithmetic operations in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the data modification unit <b>125</b> might perform only one arithmetic operation, for example. In this case, the data modification unit <b>125</b> can be implemented with two input gating circuits and one arithmetic unit.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Next, operations of the aforementioned memory controller <b>120</b> for reading, modifying, and writing the data signal stored in the external memory <b>200</b> in response to the modify request signal MDFY will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Firstly, the IP block <b>130</b> transmits the modify request signal MDFY, the arithmetic information signal ARMC, the address signal ADD, and arithmetic data signal AR_DATA to the memory controller <b>120</b> via system bus <b>110</b>. In response to the modify request signal MDFY, the controller <b>121</b> of the memory controller <b>120</b> outputs the control signals CTL<b>1</b>, CTL<b>2</b>, and CTL<b>9</b>. The controller <b>121</b> outputs the chip selection signal CS, the memory clock signal MCLK, and the read command signal CMD_READ to external memory <b>200</b>. In response to the control signal CTL <b>1</b>, the address generation unit <b>122</b> stores the address signal ADD received via system bus <b>110</b>, generates the read address signal RADD based on the stored address signal ADD, and outputs the read address signal RADD to the external memory <b>200</b>. In response to the control signal CTL<b>2</b>, the address buffer <b>123</b> stores the read address signal RADD, and outputs the stored read address signal RADD to the external memory <b>200</b>. In response to the control signal CTL<b>9</b>, the output data processor <b>127</b> receives and stores the arithmetic data signal AR_DATA, constructs the stored arithmetic data signal AR_DATA in a predetermined format, and outputs the resultant signal. Next, the controller <b>121</b> outputs the control signals CTL<b>3</b> to CTL<b>6</b>. In response to the control signal CTL<b>3</b>, the input buffer <b>124</b> stores read data signal RDATA received from the external memory <b>200</b>, and outputs the stored read data signal RDATA. On the other hand, when the controller <b>121</b> receives the read request signal READ together with the modify request signal MDFY from the IP block <b>130</b>, the controller <b>121</b> further generates the control signal CTL<b>8</b> in response to the read request signal READ. As a result, in response to the control signal CTL<b>8</b>, the input data processor <b>126</b> stores the read data signal RDATA received from the input buffer <b>124</b>. The input data processor <b>126</b> constructs the stored read data signal RDATA in a predetermined format, and outputs the resultant signal as the read data RE_DATA to the IP block <b>130</b> via system bus <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">When the data modification unit <b>125</b> is enabled in response to the control signal CTL<b>4</b>, the data modification unit <b>125</b> receives the read data signal RDATA from the input buffer <b>124</b> and the arithmetic data signal AR_DATA from the output data processor <b>127</b>. In response to the control signal CTL<b>5</b>, the data modification unit <b>125</b> performs arithmetic operations on the read data signal RDATA and arithmetic data signal AR_DATA, and outputs the results of the arithmetic operations as the modification data signal MO_DATA. In response to the control signal CTL <b>6</b>, the selection unit <b>128</b> selects and outputs the modification data signal MO_DATA.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Next, the controller <b>121</b> outputs the control signals CTL<b>1</b>, CTL<b>2</b>, and CTL<b>7</b>. In addition, the controller <b>121</b> outputs the write command signal CMD_WRITE to the external memory <b>200</b>. In response to the control signal CTL <b>1</b>, the address generation unit <b>122</b> generates the write address signal WADD based on the stored address signal ADD and outputs the write address signal WADD to the external memory <b>200</b>. Here, the read address signal RADD and the write address signal WADD may be identical or different to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">On the other hand, in a case where the read address signal RADD and the write address signal WADD are identical and the external memory <b>200</b> is a dynamic memory such as an SDRAM, the data modification operation of the memory controller <b>120</b> modifying the data in the external memory <b>200</b> can be more simplified. That is, in order that the memory controller <b>120</b> reads a data signal, after one bank is enabled before the bank is disabled, the modified data signal can be written. As a result, it is possible to reduce the access time of the memory controller <b>120</b> accessing the external memory <b>200</b>. It is possible to reduce unnecessary power consumption.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In response to the control signal CTL<b>2</b>, the address buffer <b>123</b> stores the write address signal WADD, and outputs the stored write address signal WADD to the external memory <b>200</b>. In response to the control signal CTL<b>7</b>, the output buffer <b>129</b> stores the modification data signal MO_DATA received from the selection unit <b>128</b> and outputs the stored modification data signal MO_DATA to the external memory <b>200</b>. As a result, the modification data signal MO_DATA is written to storage cells of the external memory <b>200</b> corresponding to the write address signal WADD.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In a memory controller and an SOC having the memory controller according to the present disclosure, since the memory controller reads, modifies, and writes data stored in a memory, it is possible to reduce occupation time for a system bus.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In addition, in a memory controller and an SOC having the memory controller according to the present disclosure, in a case where a read address and a write address are identical in a dynamic memory such as an SDRAM, in a state that an associated bank is enabled, the data signal is read, modified and written, so that it is possible to reduce access time for the memory. In addition, it is possible to reduce unnecessary power consumption.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">While the present invention has been particularly shown and described with reference to exemplary embodiments thereof, it will be understood by those of ordinary skill in the art that various changes in form and details may be made therein without departing from the spirit and scope of the present invention as defined by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A memory controller,
<claim-text>wherein the memory controller is connected to a memory,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the memory controller is connected to intellectual property (IP) blocks and a microprocessor via a system bus, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, in response to one of read, write, and modify request signals received from the one of the IP blocks or the microprocessor and an address signal, the memory controller reads a data signal from the memory, writes a write data signal to the memory, or modifies the data signal read from the memory and writes the modified data signal to the memory,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the memory controller comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller, in response to the read, write, and modify request signals, outputting first to ninth control signals, and outputting a read command signal or a write command signal together with a chip selection signal and a memory clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an address generation unit, in response to the first control signal, storing the address signal received via the system bus, and generating a read address signal or a write address signal based on the stored address signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an address buffer, in response to the second control signal, storing the read address signal or the write address signal, and outputting the stored read address signal or write address signal to the memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an input buffer, in response to the third control signal, storing a read data signal received from the memory, and outputting the stored read data signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data modification unit being enabled or disabled in response to the fourth control signal,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, when the data modification unit is enabled, in response to the fifth control signal, the data modification unit performs an arithmetic operation on the read data signal and an arithmetic data signal, and outputs the result of the arithmetic operation as a modify data signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The memory controller according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein, when the memory controller receives the write request signal, the memory controller further receives the write data signal via the system bus, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, when the memory controller receives the modify request signal, the memory controller further receives an arithmetic data signal via the system bus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The memory controller according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the memory controller comprises:
<claim-text>a selection unit, in response to the sixth control signal, selecting and outputting one of the modify data signal and the write data signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output buffer, in response to the seventh control signal, storing the modify data signal or the write data signal, and outputting the stored modify data signal or write data signal to the memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an input data processor, in response to the eighth control signal, storing the read data signal received from the input buffer, constructing the stored read data signal in a predetermined first format, and outputting the resultant data signal via the system bus; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output data processor, in response to the ninth control signal, storing the write data signal or the arithmetic data signal, constructing the stored write data signal or arithmetic data signal in a predetermined second format, and outputting the resultant data signal to the data modification unit and the selection unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The memory controller according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein, when the controller receives the modify request signal, the controller further receives an arithmetic information signal, and generates the fifth control signal in response to the arithmetic information signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The memory controller according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein, when the controller receives the modify request signal, the controller outputs the read command signal to the memory, and, after a predetermined time interval, outputting the write command signal to the memory.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The memory controller according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the data modification unit comprises:
<claim-text>input gating circuits, in response to the fourth control signal, outputting or holding the arithmetic data signal and the read data signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an arithmetic unit performs arithmetic operations on the arithmetic data signal and the read data signal received from the input gating circuits, and outputting the results of the arithmetic operations as the modify data signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The memory controller according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the data modification unit comprises:
<claim-text>input gating circuits, in response to the fourth control signal, outputting or holding the arithmetic data signal and the read data signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first to N-th arithmetic units performing different arithmetic operations on the arithmetic data signal and the read data signal received from the input gating circuits, and outputting the results of the arithmetic operation as first to N-th arithmetic result signals, wherein N is integer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a multiplexer, in response to the fifth control signal, selecting one of the first to N-th arithmetic result signals and outputting the selected arithmetic result signal as the modify data signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The memory controller according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the memory is an SDRAM, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, when the read address signal and the write address signal are identical to each other, in a state that a predetermined bank of the SDRAM is enabled, the memory controller reads the data signal from the SDRAM, modifies the read data signal, and writes the modified data signal to the SDRAM.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A system-on-chip (SOC) comprising:
<claim-text>a microprocessor connected to a system bus, the microprocessor controlling all devices connected to the system bus and executing a predetermined program;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an internal memory storing the predetermined program or main data obtained in operations of the microprocessor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>intellectual property (IP) blocks connected to the system bus, each of the IP blocks performing a predetermined function; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a memory controller connected to an external memory and the system bus,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, in response to one of read, write, and modify request signals received from the one of the IP blocks or the microprocessor and an address signal, the memory controller reads a data signal from the external memory, writes a write data signal to the external memory, or modifies the data signal read from the external memory and write the modified data signal to the external memory,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the memory controller comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller, in response to the read, write, and modify request signals, outputting first to ninth control signals, and outputting a read command signal or a write command signal together with a chip selection signal and a memory clock signal to the external memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an address generation unit, in response to the first control signal, storing the address signal received via the system bus, and generating a read address signal or a write address signal based on the stored address signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an address buffer, in response to the second control signal, storing the read address signal or the write address signal, and outputting the stored read address signal or write address signal to the external memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an input buffer, in response to the third control signal, storing a read data signal received from the external memory, and outputting the stored read data signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a data modification unit being enabled or disabled in response to the fourth control signal, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, when the data modification unit is enabled, in response to the fifth control signal, the data modification unit performs an arithmetic operation on the read data signal and an arithmetic data signal, and outputs the result of the arithmetic operation as a modify data signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The SOC according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein, when the memory controller receives the write request signal, the memory controller further receive the write data signal via the system bus, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, when the memory controller receives the modify request signal, the memory further receives an arithmetic data signal via the system bus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The SOC according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the memory controller comprises:
<claim-text>a selection unit, in response to the sixth control signal, selecting and outputting one of the modify data signal and the write data signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output buffer, in response to the seventh control signal, storing the modify data signal or the write data signal, and outputting the stored modify data signal or write data signal to the external memory;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an input data processor, in response to the eighth control signal, storing the read data signal received from the input buffer, constructing the stored read data signal in a predetermined first format, and outputting the resultant data signal via the system bus; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output data processor, in response to the ninth control signal, storing the write data signal or the arithmetic data signal, constructing the stored write data signal or arithmetic data signal in a predetermined second format, and outputting the resultant data signal to the data modification unit and the selection unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The SOC according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein, when the controller receives the modify request signal, the controller further receives an arithmetic information signal, and generates the fifth control signal in response to the arithmetic information signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The SOC according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein, when the controller receives the modify request signal, the controller outputs the read command signal to the external memory, and, after a predetermined time interval, outputting the write command signal to the external memory.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The SOC according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the data modification unit comprises:
<claim-text>input gating circuits, in response to the fourth control signal, outputting or holding the arithmetic data signal and the read data signal; and an arithmetic unit performs arithmetic operations on the arithmetic data signal and the read data signal received from the input gating circuits, and outputting the results of the arithmetic operations as the modify data signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The SOC according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the data modification unit comprises:
<claim-text>input gating circuits, in response to the fourth control signal, outputting or holding the arithmetic data signal and the read data signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first to N-th arithmetic units performing different arithmetic operations on the arithmetic data signal and the read data signal received from the input gating circuits, and outputting the results of the arithmetic operation as first to N-th arithmetic result signals, wherein N is integer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a multiplexer, in response to the fifth control signal, selecting one of the first to N-th arithmetic result signals and outputting the selected arithmetic result signal as the modify data signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The SOC according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the external memory is an SDRAM, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, when the read address signal and the write address signal are identical to each other, in a state that a predetermined bank of the SDRAM is enabled, the memory controller reads the data signal from the SDRAM, modifies the read data signal, and writes the modified data signal to the SDRAM.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A memory controller comprising:
<claim-text>control means responsive to an address signal and read, write and modify request signals received from at least one IP block or microprocessor for outputting a plurality of control signals and outputting a read command signal or a write command signal together with a chip selection signal and a memory clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>address generation means in signal communication with the control means for storing the address signal and generating a read address signal or a write address signal based on the stored address signal in response to a first of the plurality of control signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>address buffer means in signal communication with the control means for storing the read address signal or the write address signal and outputting the stored read address signal or write address signal in response to a second of the plurality of control signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>input buffer means in signal communication with the control means for storing a read data signal and outputting the stored read data signal in response to a third of the plurality of control signals; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>data modification means in signal communication with the control means for performing an arithmetic operation on the read data signal and an arithmetic data signal and outputting the result of the arithmetic operation as a modify data signal in response to a fourth of the plurality of control signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A system-on-chip (SOC) comprising a memory controller as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, the SOC further comprising:
<claim-text>a microprocessor in signal communication with the bus means for controlling devices connected to the bus means and executing a predetermined program;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an internal memory in signal communication with the bus means for storing at least one of the predetermined program and data obtained in operations of the microprocessor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an intellectual property (IP) block in signal communication with the bus means for performing a predetermined function.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
