<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298990-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298990</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11061876</doc-number>
<date>20050222</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-053105</doc-number>
<date>20040227</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>177</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>18</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399113</main-classification>
<further-classification>399111</further-classification>
<further-classification>399119</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Process cartridge and image forming apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6075957</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Batori et al.</name>
<date>20000600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399114</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6647227</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Yokoi et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6751428</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Okabe</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2003-084645</doc-number>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2003-107975</doc-number>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>22</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399110-114</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399119</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>10</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>16</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050191090</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050901</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nishimura</last-name>
<first-name>Soichiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Handa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Oliff &amp; Berridge, PLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Brother Kogyo Kabushiki Kaisha</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Nagoya</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Gray</last-name>
<first-name>David M.</first-name>
<department>2852</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Walsh</last-name>
<first-name>Ryan D.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A developing cartridge includes an engagement device that is capable of being engaged with an engaging member associated with a frame, wherein: the engagement device can be placed in a restricting state where the engagement device is engaged with the engaging member, the engagement device can be placed in an unrestricting state where the engagement device is disengaged from the engaging member, and the engagement device is automatically placed in the unrestricting state when the developing cartridge is placed in an image forming device.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="112.10mm" wi="191.43mm" file="US07298990-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="195.24mm" wi="130.05mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298990-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="208.87mm" wi="90.17mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298990-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="203.28mm" wi="127.25mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298990-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="221.32mm" wi="99.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298990-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="239.44mm" wi="96.60mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298990-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="225.72mm" wi="150.11mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298990-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="159.43mm" wi="123.61mm" file="US07298990-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="221.74mm" wi="146.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298990-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="235.88mm" wi="99.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298990-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="224.62mm" wi="119.97mm" file="US07298990-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">INCORPORATION BY REFERENCE</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority from JP 2004-053105, filed Feb. 27, 2004, the subject matter of which is incorporated herein in its entirety by reference thereto.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The disclosure relates to a process cartridge and an image forming apparatus equipped with the process cartridge.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Conventionally, a process cartridge is loaded into an image forming apparatus, such as a laser printer. The process cartridge includes a photosensitive drum on which an electrostatic latent image is formed and a developing cartridge that develops the electrostatic latent image formed on the photosensitive drum into a toner image.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The developing cartridge is mounted to a drum cartridge supporting the photosensitive drum. The developing cartridge includes a developing roller that supplies toner onto a surface of the photosensitive drum. As the developing roller rotates in a state where the developing cartridge is mounted to the drum cartridge and the developing roller faces the photosensitive drum, toner is supplied to the surface of the photosensitive drum from the developing roller. An electrostatic latent image is thus developed into a toner image. The developed toner image is then transferred onto a sheet, which is fed between the photosensitive drum and the transfer roller, by the transfer roller disposed opposite the photosensitive drum.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">For example, U.S. Pat. No. 6,751,428 discloses such a process cartridge including a locking device for maintaining a state where the developing cartridge is attached to the drum cartridge. In the process cartridge, the drum cartridge includes a shaft that extends along an upstream end face in a developing cartridge attaching direction, and a locking lever that is rotatably supported by the shaft. The developing cartridge includes a locking protrusion that protrudes therefrom toward the upstream side in the developing cartridge mounting direction. The locking lever is rotated about the shaft to engage the locking protrusion in order to prevent the developing cartridge from becoming detached from the drum cartridge. By doing so, the attachment of the developing cartridge to the drum cartridge is maintained.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">However, the locking lever is manually switched between a locked state where the locking lever is engaged with the locking protrusion and an unlocked state where the locking lever is disengaged from the locking protrusion. Therefore, to remove the developing cartridge from the image forming apparatus in the state where the process cartridge is mounted to the image forming apparatus, the locking lever needs to be manually disengaged from the locking protrusion and then the developing cartridge is pulled out of the image forming apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The disclosure thus provides, among other things, a process cartridge that achieves an improvement in operability when a developing cartridge is detached from an image forming apparatus and an image forming apparatus including the process cartridge.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">An exemplary developing cartridge includes an engagement device that is capable of being engaged with an engaging member associated with a frame, wherein: the engagement device can be placed in a restricting state where the engagement device is engaged with the engaging member, the engagement device can be placed in an unrestricting state where the engagement device is disengaged from the engaging member, and the engagement device is automatically placed in the unrestricting state when the developing cartridge is placed in an image forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">An exemplary process cartridge includes a frame; and an engaging member that is provided to the frame, wherein: the engaging member includes an engagement portion and a disengagement portion, the disengagement portion automatically moves the engaging member to a first position when the process cartridge is placed in an image forming device, and the engagement portion automatically moves the engaging member to a second position when the process cartridge is removed from the image forming device.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Exemplary embodiments of the disclosure will be described in detail with reference to the following figures wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side sectional view showing essential parts of a laser beam printer, as an image forming apparatus, of an exemplary embodiment of the disclosure;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a side view of a process cartridge for the laser printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, wherein the process cartridge is attached to a body casing;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, wherein the process cartridge is separated from the body casing;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> with a developing cartridge removed therefrom;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> of another exemplary embodiment, wherein the process cartridge has a manual engaging member, which is in an unrestricting state;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>, wherein the manual engaging member is in a restricting state;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> of another exemplary embodiment, wherein the process cartridge has a movable developing-cartridge-side handle, which is located at an unrestricting position;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, wherein the developing-cartridge-side handle is located at a restricting position;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a side sectional view showing essential parts of the laser beam printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> of another exemplary embodiment, wherein pressure is applied to and released from the developing cartridge in conjunction with opening and closing of a front cover;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a partially enlarged side view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, wherein the pressure on the developing cartridge is released by opening the front cover;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a side view of the laser beam printer of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> of another exemplary embodiment, wherein the front cover has a pressing member;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> of another exemplary embodiment, wherein the developing cartridge has an engaging member, which is located at an unrestricting position;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref>, wherein the engaging member is located at a restricting position;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> of another exemplary embodiment, wherein an engaging member is interposed between the developing cartridge and the frame and the engaging member is located at an unrestricting position;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10B</figref> is a side view of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>, wherein the engaging member is located at a restricting position; and</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10C</figref> is an enlarged view of an engagement device, including the engaging member of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>, of the process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Exemplary embodiments of the disclosure will be described with reference to the accompanying drawings. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a laser beam printer <b>1</b> as an image forming apparatus includes a body casing <b>2</b>, a sheet feeding portion <b>4</b> that feeds a sheet <b>3</b> as a recording medium, and an image forming portion <b>5</b> that forms an image onto the fed sheet <b>3</b>. The sheet feeding portion <b>4</b> and the image forming portion <b>5</b> are provided in the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The body casing <b>2</b> has an opening <b>44</b>, through which a process cartridge <b>19</b> (described later) is mounted to the laser beam printer <b>1</b>, at its one side wall. For opening and closing the opening <b>44</b>, a front cover <b>45</b> as a cover member is provided to the one side wall of the body casing <b>2</b>. The front cover <b>45</b> is rotatably attached to the body casing <b>2</b> via a hinge <b>46</b> at its lower end. When the front cover <b>45</b> is closed by rotating about the hinge <b>46</b>, the opening <b>44</b> is closed. When the front cover <b>45</b> is opened by rotating about the hinge <b>46</b>, the opening <b>44</b> is open, so that the process cartridge <b>19</b> can be mounted to the laser beam printer <b>1</b> therethrough.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In the body casing <b>2</b>, a mounting path <b>47</b> is provided extending substantially in parallel with a sheet conveying direction so as to communicate with the opening <b>44</b>. The process cartridge <b>19</b> is mounted to and removed from the body casing <b>2</b> through the mounting path <b>47</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Hereinafter, in the laser beam printer <b>1</b> and the process cartridge <b>19</b>, a side on which the front cover <b>45</b> is provided is defined as the front and an opposite side on which a fixing portion <b>13</b> (described later) is provided is defined as the rear, in a state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b>, throughout the description.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The sheet feeding portion <b>4</b> is provided at the bottom of the body casing <b>2</b> and includes a sheet feeding tray <b>6</b>, which can hold a stack of sheets <b>3</b> therein, a sheet supply roller <b>7</b> and a sheet supply pad <b>8</b>, which are disposed above a front end of the sheet feeding tray <b>6</b>, a paper dust removing roller <b>9</b>, which is provided downstream of the sheet supply pad <b>8</b> in the sheet conveying direction, and a pair of resist rollers <b>10</b>, which is provided downstream of the paper dust removing roller <b>9</b> in the sheet conveying direction.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The sheet supply roller <b>7</b> and the sheet supply pad <b>8</b> are disposed so as to be opposite each other. The sheet supply pad <b>8</b> is pressed against the sheet supply roller <b>7</b> by a spring (not shown) provided below the sheet supply pad <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">A topmost sheet <b>3</b> in the stack placed in the sheet feeding tray <b>6</b> is pressed against the sheet supply roller <b>7</b>. The topmost sheet <b>3</b> is then pinched by the sheet supply roller <b>7</b> and the sheet supply pad <b>8</b> and is separated and supplied from the stack, one by one, by a rotation of the sheet supply roller <b>7</b>. The fed sheet <b>3</b> then passes the paper dust removing roller <b>9</b>, so that paper dust adhering to the sheet <b>3</b> is removed therefrom. After that, the sheet <b>3</b> is further conveyed to the resist rollers <b>10</b>. The resist rollers <b>10</b> resist the conveyance of the sheet <b>3</b> and then further feed the sheet <b>3</b> to an image transfer position (which is provided between a photosensitive drum <b>21</b> (described later) and a transfer roller <b>34</b> (described later) and at which a toner image formed on the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is transferred onto the sheet <b>3</b>) in an image forming portion <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The image forming portion <b>5</b> includes a scanning portion <b>11</b>, a process portion <b>12</b>, and the fixing portion <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The scanning portion <b>11</b> provided at the upper portion of the body casing <b>2</b>, includes a laser emitting portion (not shown), a rotatable polygon mirror <b>14</b>, a lens <b>15</b> and three reflectors <b>16</b>, <b>17</b>, <b>18</b>. In the scanning portion <b>11</b>, a laser beam, which is emitted from the laser emitting portion based on image data, passes or is reflected off the polygon mirror <b>14</b>, the lens <b>15</b>, the reflector <b>16</b>, the reflector <b>17</b> and the reflector <b>18</b> in this order, and is finally applied to a surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> of the process cartridge <b>19</b> by high-speed scanning, as indicated by a dashed line.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The process portion <b>12</b> includes the process cartridge <b>19</b> mounted to the body casing <b>2</b> and the transfer roller <b>34</b> as a transfer device provided to the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b>, below the scanning portion <b>11</b>. The process cartridge <b>19</b> includes a frame <b>50</b>, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> to be accommodated in the frame <b>50</b>, the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> as an image holding body, a scorotron charging device <b>22</b>, and a cleaning brush <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the frame <b>50</b> includes a pair of side plates <b>51</b> provided opposite to each other at a predetermined distance from each other, a front plate <b>91</b> connecting the side plates <b>51</b> at their front edges, a bottom plate <b>121</b> connecting the side plates <b>51</b> at their lower edges, a rear plate <b>122</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) connecting the side plates <b>51</b> at their rear edges, and a top plate <b>123</b> connecting the side plates <b>51</b> at their upper edges.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Each of the side plates <b>51</b> includes a rear side-plate-portion <b>52</b> having a substantially rectangular shape and a front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> having an elongated plate shape, which are integrated with each other. The front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> extends forward from a lower end portion of a front edge of the rear side-plate-portion <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The front plate <b>91</b> connects the side plates <b>51</b> at the front edges of the front side-plate-portions <b>53</b>. The front plate <b>91</b> includes a drum handle <b>56</b>, as a frame-side operating portion, having a horizontal portion <b>54</b> and a pendent portion <b>55</b>. The horizontal portion <b>54</b> extends forward from the front plate <b>91</b>. The pendent portion <b>55</b> extends downward from a front end of the horizontal portion <b>54</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Each of the rear side-plate-portions <b>52</b> has a semi-circular engaging portion <b>57</b> at its front edge. The engaging portion <b>57</b> can be engaged with a roller shaft <b>49</b> (described later) of the developing roller <b>26</b>. In each rear side-plate-portion <b>52</b>, a lower edge of the engaging portion <b>57</b> continuously extends to an upper edge of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The bottom plate <b>121</b> connects the front side-plate-portions <b>53</b> of the side plates <b>51</b> at their lower edges. The bottom plate <b>121</b> is provided from the front edges to the midway portions of the front side-plate-portions <b>53</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The rear plate <b>122</b> connects the rear side-plate-portions <b>52</b> of the side plates <b>51</b> at their rear edges. The top plate <b>123</b> connects the rear side-plate-portions <b>52</b> of the side plates <b>51</b> at their upper edges.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">In the frame <b>50</b>, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is mounted to a cartridge mount portion <b>124</b> defined by the side plates <b>51</b>, the bottom plate <b>121</b> and the front plate <b>91</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> includes a housing <b>48</b>, a toner storage chamber <b>24</b>, a toner supply roller <b>25</b>, the developing roller <b>26</b> and a layer thickness regulating blade <b>27</b>. The toner storage chamber <b>24</b>, the toner supply roller <b>25</b>, the developing roller <b>26</b> and the layer thickness regulating blade <b>27</b> are accommodated in the housing <b>48</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>, the housing <b>48</b> includes side walls <b>58</b> provided on opposite sides of the toner storage chamber <b>24</b>, a front wall <b>92</b> connecting the side walls <b>58</b> at their front edges, a bottom wall <b>125</b> connecting the side walls <b>58</b> at their lower edges, and a top wall <b>130</b> connecting the sides walls <b>58</b> at their upper edges. The side walls <b>58</b>, the front wall <b>92</b>, the bottom wall <b>125</b> and the top wall <b>130</b> are integrated with each other. With this structure, the housing <b>48</b> has a box shape with a rear open structure.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Each of the side walls <b>58</b> includes a front side-wall-portion <b>59</b> having a substantially rectangular shape and a projecting portion <b>60</b> projecting rearward from a lower end portion of a rear edge of the front side-wall-portion <b>59</b>, when viewed from the side.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The front wall <b>92</b> connects the side walls <b>58</b> at front edges of the front side-wall-portions <b>59</b>. The front wall <b>92</b> includes a developing cartridge handle <b>63</b>, as a developing-cartridge-side operating portion, having a horizontal portion <b>61</b> and a pendent portion <b>62</b>. The horizontal portion <b>61</b> extends forward from an upper end of the front wall <b>92</b>. The pendent portion <b>62</b> extends downward from a front end of the horizontal portion <b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The bottom wall <b>125</b> connects the side walls <b>58</b> at lower edges of the front side-wall-portions <b>59</b>. The top wall <b>130</b> connects the side walls <b>58</b> at upper edges of the front side-wall-portions <b>59</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the toner storage chamber <b>24</b> is achieved by an internal space provided at the front part of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> divided by a partition <b>28</b>. A toner discharge opening <b>29</b> is provided under the partition <b>28</b> so as to communicate the divided spaces with each other in the front and rear direction. The toner storage chamber <b>24</b> stores positively charged non-magnetic single-component toner, as developing agent. The toner is a polymerized toner obtained through co-polymerization of styrene-based monomers, such as styrene, and acryl-based monomers, such as acrylic acid, alkyl(C1-C4)acrylate, alkyl (C1-C4)methacrylate, using a known polymerization method, such as suspension polymerization. The polymerized toner has a substantially spherical shape and has excellent fluidity. Thus, a high quality image can be formed.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">A coloring agent, such as carbon black, and wax are added to the polymerized toner. An external additive, such as silica, is also added to the polymerized toner to improve its fluidity. The particle size of the polymerized toner is approximately 6-10 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">An agitator <b>30</b> is provided in the toner storage chamber <b>24</b>. The toner stored in the toner storage chamber <b>24</b> is agitated by the agitator <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The toner supply roller <b>25</b> is rotatably supported by the developing cartridge <b>20</b>, next to and behind the toner discharge opening <b>29</b>. The toner supply roller <b>25</b> includes a metal roller shaft covered with a roller portion made of a conductive foam material. The toner supply roller <b>25</b> is driven and rotated by the power from the motor (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The developing roller <b>26</b> is disposed behind the toner supply roller <b>25</b>. The developing roller <b>26</b> is rotatably supported between the projecting portions <b>60</b> of the side walls <b>58</b> of the housing <b>48</b> while being in contact with the toner supply roller <b>25</b> so that they are press-deformed against each other to an appropriate extent. Therefore, the developing roller <b>26</b> is partially exposed to the outside from the rear of the housing <b>48</b>. The developing roller <b>26</b> includes the metal roller shaft <b>49</b> covered with a roller portion made of a conductive rubber material. More specifically, the roller portion of the developing roller <b>26</b> is made of a conductive urethane or silicone rubber containing carbon particles and its surface is covered with a coating layer made of a urethane or silicone rubber containing fluorine. A predetermined developing bias is applied to the developing roller <b>26</b> at the time of development. The developing roller <b>26</b> is driven and rotated in the same direction as the rotation of the toner supply roller <b>25</b> by the power from the motor (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>, both end portions of the roller shaft <b>49</b> outwardly protrude from the respective projecting portions <b>60</b> of the side walls <b>58</b> in a width direction (in a direction in which the side walls <b>58</b> are opposite to each other).</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The layer thickness regulating blade <b>27</b> includes a blade body <b>31</b> made of a metal leaf spring and a pressing portion <b>32</b> made of an insulative silicone rubber. The pressing portion <b>32</b> having a semi-circular shape in cross section is provided at a free end of the blade body <b>31</b>. The layer thickness regulating blade <b>27</b> is situated near the developing roller <b>26</b>. The pressing portion <b>32</b> provided at the free end of the blade body <b>31</b> presses the developing roller <b>26</b> by an elastic force of the blade body <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the cartridge mount portion <b>124</b> of the frame <b>50</b> such that both end portions, outwardly protruding from the projecting portions <b>60</b> in the width direction, of the roller shaft <b>49</b> of the developing roller <b>26</b> are engaged with the respective engaging portions <b>57</b> of the rear side-plate-portions <b>52</b> of the side plates <b>51</b>. When the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the cartridge mount portion <b>124</b> of the frame <b>50</b>, the partially exposed portion of the developing roller <b>26</b> opposingly contacts the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">In the toner storage chamber <b>24</b>, the toner agitated by the agitator <b>30</b> is discharged toward the toner supply roller <b>25</b> through the toner discharge opening <b>29</b> provided under the partition <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The toner discharged from the toner discharge opening <b>29</b> is then supplied to the developing roller <b>26</b> by the rotation of the toner supply roller <b>25</b>. At that time, the toner is positively charged by friction caused between the toner supply roller <b>25</b> and the developing roller <b>26</b>. The toner supplied onto the developing roller <b>26</b> is further supplied between the pressing portion <b>32</b> of the layer thickness regulating blade <b>27</b> and the developing roller <b>26</b> by the rotation of the developing roller <b>26</b>, so that the toner becomes a thin layer having a uniform thickness and is held on the developing roller <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is disposed behind the developing cartridge <b>20</b> so as to be opposite the developing roller <b>26</b>. The photosensitive drum <b>21</b> has a cylindrical body and a drum shaft <b>33</b> provided at the center of an axis of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>. The photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is rotatably supported between the rear side-plate-portions <b>52</b> of the side plates <b>51</b> of the frame <b>50</b>, via the drum shaft <b>33</b>. The surface of the conductive cylindrical body, made of, for example, aluminum, of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is covered with a positively-charged photosensitive layer. The cylindrical body of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is connected to a ground.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>, the drum shaft <b>33</b> is provided such that its end portions outwardly protrude from the respective side plates <b>51</b> in the width direction.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The scorotron charging device <b>22</b> is located above the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>, at a predetermined distance, so as not to contact the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>, while being supported by the top plate <b>123</b>. The scorotron charging device <b>22</b> is a charging device that generates corona discharge from charging wires, such as tungsten wires, in order to uniformly positively charge the surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">The cleaning brush <b>23</b> is supported by the rear plate <b>122</b>, behind the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>, so as to be opposite to the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> and be in contact with the surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The process cartridge <b>19</b> having the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b> through the mounting path <b>47</b> from the opening <b>44</b> by opening the front cover <b>45</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The transfer roller <b>34</b> is provided in the body casing <b>2</b>. In the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b>, the transfer roller <b>34</b> is in contact with the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> so as to be opposite to each other in the up and down direction and forms (provides) a nip portion therebetween. Because the transfer roller <b>34</b> is provided in the body casing <b>2</b>, the process cartridge <b>19</b> can be downsized. The transfer roller <b>34</b> includes a metal roller shaft covered with a roller portion made of a conductive rubber material.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">A predetermined transfer bias is applied to the transfer roller <b>34</b> at the time of transfer. The transfer roller <b>34</b> is driven and rotated by the power from a motor (not shown). The surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is uniformly positively charged by the scorotron charging device <b>22</b> in accordance with the rotation of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>. Then, the surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is exposed to a laser beam emitted from the scanning portion <b>11</b> by a high-speed scanning and an electrostatic latent image, which corresponds to an image to be transferred onto the sheet <b>3</b>, is formed onto the surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">After that, when the electrostatic latent image on the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> faces and contacts the developing roller <b>26</b>, the positively charged toner held on the developing roller <b>26</b> is supplied onto and held by the electrostatic latent image formed on the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>, i.e., a portion whose potential is lowered by the exposure by the laser beam. Thus, the latent image formed on the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is visualized, and thus, an toner image is formed on the surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> by a reversal phenomenon.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Then, the toner image held by the surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is transferred onto the sheet <b>3</b> while the sheet <b>3</b> passes between the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> and the transfer roller <b>34</b> (the transfer position), by a transfer bias applied to the transfer roller <b>34</b>. The sheet <b>3</b> onto which the toner image is transferred is then conveyed to the fixing portion <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">The residual toner remaining on the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> after the transfer is collected by the developing roller <b>26</b>. The paper dust adhered to the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> from the sheet <b>3</b> after the transfer is collected by the cleaning brush <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">The fixing portion <b>13</b> is provided behind the process cartridge <b>19</b> and includes a fixing frame <b>35</b>, a heat roller <b>36</b>, a pressing roller <b>37</b> and a pair of conveyor rollers <b>38</b>. The heat roller <b>36</b>, the pressing roller <b>37</b> and the pair of conveyor rollers <b>38</b> are provided in the fixing frame <b>35</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The heat roller <b>36</b> includes a metal base tube and a halogen lamp in the base tube to generate heat. The heat roller <b>36</b> is driven and rotated by the power from the motor (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">The pressing roller <b>37</b> is opposingly disposed below the heat roller <b>36</b> so as to press the heat roller <b>36</b>. The pressing roller <b>37</b> includes a metal roller shaft covered with a roller portion made of rubber material. The pressing roller <b>37</b> rotates by following the rotation of the heat roller <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">The pair of conveyor rollers <b>38</b> is disposed behind the heat roller <b>36</b> and the pressing roller <b>37</b>, that is, downstream of the heat roller <b>36</b> and the pressing roller <b>37</b> in the sheet conveying direction.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">At the fixing portion <b>13</b>, the toner transferred onto the sheet <b>3</b> at the transfer position is thermally fixed onto the sheet <b>3</b> while the sheet <b>3</b> passes between the heat roller <b>36</b> and the pressing roller <b>37</b>. The sheet <b>3</b> on which the toner is fixed is further conveyed to a sheet discharge path <b>39</b> extending toward the top of the body casing <b>2</b>. The sheet <b>3</b> conveyed to the sheet discharge path <b>39</b> is then discharged onto a sheet discharge tray <b>41</b> provided at the top of the body casing <b>2</b> by a pair of sheet discharge rollers <b>40</b>, which is provided above the discharge path <b>39</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">In the laser beam printer <b>1</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, the process cartridge <b>19</b> includes a support shaft <b>64</b>, an engaging member <b>65</b>, and an engagement boss <b>66</b> as an engaged portion, on each side. The support shafts <b>64</b>, the engaging members <b>65</b>, and the engagement bosses <b>66</b> function as an engagement device. Although explanations will be given for each one of the support shafts <b>64</b>, the engaging members <b>65</b> and the engagement bosses <b>66</b> only, they have the same structure and function on each side.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">The support shaft <b>64</b> is provided to the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> of the side plate <b>51</b> of the frame <b>50</b>. More specifically, the support shaft <b>64</b> outwardly protrudes in the width direction from a forward portion of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> in the front and rear direction.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">The engaging member <b>65</b> is rotatably supported by the support shaft <b>64</b>. The engaging member <b>65</b> includes a shaft insertion portion <b>67</b>, into which the support shaft <b>64</b> is inserted, an engaging portion <b>68</b>, which is connected with the shaft insertion portion <b>67</b> at its one end and has a substantially C-shape, a disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> as a release member and an engagement operating portion <b>70</b> as a retuning member, both of which linearly extend in predetermined respective directions from the shaft insertion portion <b>67</b>. The shaft insertion portion <b>67</b>, the engaging portion <b>68</b>, the disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> and the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> are integrated with each other. The engaging member <b>65</b> can rotate about the support shaft <b>64</b> within a range of predetermined angles, between an unrestricting position where the engaging portion <b>68</b> faces the support shaft <b>64</b> substantially in the horizontal direction (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>) and a restricting position where the engaging portion <b>68</b> faces the support shaft <b>64</b> in the up and down direction (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">In the engaging member <b>65</b>, the disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> and the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> are provided so as to form a substantially V-shape having an angle that the engaging member <b>65</b> can rotate (the above-described predetermined angle). The disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> extends in the up and down direction substantially perpendicular to the axial direction of the support shaft <b>64</b> and downwardly protrudes from the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b>, in a state where the engaging portion <b>68</b> is located at the restricting position (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>). The engagement operating portion <b>70</b> extends in the up and down direction substantially perpendicular to the axial direction of the support shaft <b>64</b> and downwardly protrudes from the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b>, in a state where the engaging portion <b>68</b> is located at the unrestricting position (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>). When the disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> downwardly protrudes from the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b>, the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> downwardly extends at an incline toward the rear (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>). When the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> downwardly protrudes from the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b>, the disengagement operating portion <b>70</b> downwardly extends at an incline toward the front (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">The engagement boss <b>66</b> protrudes from the side wall <b>58</b> of the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b>, so as to extend substantially in parallel with the support shaft <b>64</b> toward the restricting position, in the state where the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b>. The engagement boss <b>66</b> has a cylindrical shape and has a diameter so that the engaging portion <b>68</b> can engage a periphery of the engagement boss <b>66</b>. With this structure, when the engaging member <b>65</b> rotates to move the engaging portion <b>68</b> to the restricting position in the state where the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b>, the engaging portion <b>68</b> is engaged with the engagement boss <b>66</b> to establish a restricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is restricted. When the engaging member <b>65</b> rotates in the reverse direction to move the engaging portion <b>68</b> to the unrestricting position, the engaging portion <b>68</b> is disengaged from the engagement boss <b>66</b> to establish an unrestricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is permitted.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The process cartridge <b>19</b> further includes a support shaft <b>71</b> as a second support shaft, a manual engaging member <b>72</b> as a second engaging member, and an engagement member <b>73</b> as a second engaged member. The support shaft <b>71</b>, the manual engaging member <b>72</b> and the engagement member <b>73</b> function as a manual engagement device.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">The support shaft <b>71</b> is provided to extend from the outer surface of the horizontal portion <b>54</b> of the drum handle <b>56</b>, in the width direction substantially in parallel to the front plate <b>91</b> of the frame <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">The manual engaging member <b>72</b> includes a hook portion <b>74</b> and a manual operating portion <b>76</b>, which are integrated with each other. The hook portion <b>74</b> has a substantially C-shape at its free end when viewed from the side. The manual operating portion <b>76</b> extends in a direction substantially perpendicular to the hook portion <b>74</b>. The support shaft <b>71</b> is inserted into a joint portion of the hook portion <b>74</b> and the manual operating portion <b>76</b>. Thus, the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is supported by the support shaft <b>71</b> so as to be rotatable between a restricting position and an unrestricting position by manually operating the manual operating portion <b>76</b> to rotate the manual engaging member <b>72</b> about the support shaft <b>71</b>. When the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is located at the restricting position, the manual operating portion <b>76</b> extends substantially in the horizontal direction along the horizontal portion <b>54</b> of the drum handle <b>56</b>. When the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is located at the unrestricting position, the manual operating portion <b>76</b> extends in the up and down direction along the pendent portion <b>55</b> of the drum handle <b>56</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">The engagement member <b>73</b> includes a horizontal portion <b>77</b>, which extends forward from the front wall <b>92</b> of the housing <b>48</b>, and a projecting portion <b>78</b>, which is upwardly bent from a front end of the horizontal portion <b>77</b>, in the state where the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b>. The horizontal portion <b>77</b> and the projecting portion <b>78</b> are integrated with each other.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">The projecting portion <b>78</b> is designed so as to enter a space of the substantially C-shaped free end portion of the hook portion <b>74</b> of the manual engaging member <b>72</b> when the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is located at the restricting position. With this structure, when the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is rotated to the restricting position in the state where the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b>, the hook portion <b>74</b> is engaged with the projecting portion <b>78</b>, so that the restricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is restricted is established. When the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is rotated to the unrestricting position from the restricting position, the hook portion <b>74</b> is disengaged from the projecting portion <b>78</b>, so that the unrestricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from detached from the frame <b>50</b> is permitted is established, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>, in the body casing <b>2</b>, a pillar member <b>79</b>, as a first contact portion, is provided on each side so as to extend from below and toward the mounting path <b>47</b>. The pillar member <b>79</b> is disposed such that its tip portion is located in a path through which the disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> and the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> of the engaging member <b>65</b> passes during the attachment and detachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b>. More specifically, when the engaging member <b>65</b> is located at the restricting position, the disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> faces the tip portion of the pillar member <b>79</b> substantially in the horizontal direction and the engagement operating portions <b>70</b> are positioned above the pillar members <b>79</b> without facing the pillar members <b>79</b>. When the engaging member <b>65</b> is located at the unrestricting position, the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> faces the pillar member <b>79</b> and the disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> is positioned above the pillar member <b>79</b> without facing the pillar member <b>79</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">The restricted state of the process cartridge <b>19</b> is established at the engaging members <b>65</b> and the manual engaging member <b>72</b> by which the engaging portion <b>68</b> of the engaging member <b>65</b> is engaged with the engagement boss <b>66</b> and the hook portion <b>74</b> of the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is engaged with the projecting portion <b>78</b> while the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b>. Thus, the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is restricted (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>). To attach the process cartridge <b>19</b> in the restricted state to the body casing <b>2</b>, as described above, first, the front cover <b>45</b> is opened to open the opening <b>44</b>. After that, the process cartridge <b>19</b> is inserted into the body casing <b>2</b> through the opening <b>44</b> and is moved rearward along the mounting path <b>47</b> by operating the drum handle <b>56</b> from the front. Then, the disengagement operation member <b>69</b> contacts the pillar member <b>79</b> after the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> passes above the pillar member <b>79</b>. In accordance with the movement of the process cartridge <b>19</b>, the lower end portion of the disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> is pushed upward by the pillar member <b>79</b>, so that the engaging member <b>65</b> rotates about the support shaft <b>64</b> to disengage the engaging portion <b>68</b> of the engaging member <b>56</b> from the engagement boss <b>66</b>. Accordingly, the unrestricted state is established at the engaging member <b>65</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>) in the laser beam printer <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b> as described above, in conjunction with the attachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b> to the body casing <b>2</b>, the engaging member <b>65</b> moves from the restricting position to the unrestricting position, so that the restriction on the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is removed at the engaging member <b>65</b>. Therefore, it is unnecessary to change the position of the engaging members <b>65</b> when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, so that the operability can be improved when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is removed from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">To remove the process cartridge <b>19</b> from the body casing <b>2</b>, the drum handle <b>56</b> is operated from the front to move the process cartridge <b>19</b> forward along the mounting path <b>47</b>. Then, the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> contacts the pillar member <b>79</b> after the disengagement operating portion <b>69</b> passes above the pillar member <b>79</b>, and the lower end portion of the engagement operating portion <b>70</b> is pushed upward by the pillar member <b>79</b> in accordance with the movement of the process cartridge <b>19</b>. Thus, the engaging member <b>65</b> rotates about the support shaft <b>64</b> to engage the engaging portion <b>68</b> of the engaging member <b>65</b> with the engagement boss <b>66</b>, so that the restricted state is established at the engaging member <b>65</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is removed from the body casing <b>2</b> as described above, in conjunction with the detachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b> from the body casing <b>2</b>, the position of the engaging member <b>65</b> returns to the restricting position from the unrestricting position, so that the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is restricted at the engaging members <b>65</b>. Therefore, it is unnecessary to change the position of the engaging members <b>65</b> when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, for example, in order to clear a paper jam, so that the operability can be improved when the process cartridge <b>19</b> is removed from the body casing <b>2</b>. In addition, in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is separated from the body casing <b>2</b>, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be prevented from being easily detached from the frame <b>50</b>. As a result, the exposure of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> caused by the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> can be prevented, so that damage to the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> can be prevented in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is separated from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">To remove the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the process cartridge <b>19</b> while leaving the process cartridge <b>19</b> in the body casing <b>2</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> is operated from the front to move the developing cartridge <b>20</b> forward after the hook portion <b>74</b> of the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is disengaged from the projecting portion <b>78</b> to release the restricted state at the manual engaging member <b>72</b>. As should be appreciated, when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is removed from the process cartridge <b>19</b>, the engaging member <b>65</b> is in the unrestricting position. To attach the developing cartridge <b>20</b> to the process cartridge <b>19</b> while the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b>, the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> is operated from the front to move the developing cartridge <b>20</b> rearward. Then, the hook portion <b>74</b> of the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is engaged with the projecting portion <b>78</b> to establish the restricted state at the manual engaging member <b>72</b>. In the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is separated from the body casing <b>2</b>, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be attached to and detached from the process cartridge <b>19</b> in a similar fashion to the above.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">In the above-described process cartridge <b>19</b>, the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> can be restricted by the engagement of the hook portion <b>74</b> of the manual engaging member <b>72</b> with the projecting portion <b>78</b>. Thus, the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> can be further restricted in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is separated from the body casing <b>2</b>. As a result, the exposure of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> and damage to the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> can be further prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">The hook portion <b>74</b> can be engaged with and disengaged from the projecting portion <b>78</b> by the simple manual operation that the manual engaging member <b>72</b> is rotated. Accordingly, in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be restricted from being detached from the frame <b>50</b> without loss of the operability during the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">In the laser beam printer <b>1</b>, because the transfer roller <b>34</b> is provided to the body casing <b>2</b>, the portion of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> facing the transfer roller <b>34</b> is exposed when the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>. Therefore, when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is separated from the frame <b>50</b> in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, the portion of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> facing the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is further exposed and the exposed portion of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> is expanded. When the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is restricted by the engagement of the engaging members <b>65</b> with the engagement bosses <b>66</b> and the engagement of the manual engaging member <b>72</b> with the projecting portion <b>78</b> in the state where the process cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, the expansion of the exposed portion of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> can be prevented. Accordingly, a possibility of damage to the exposed portion of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> can be reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">Because the drum handle <b>56</b> and the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> are separately provided, the drum handle <b>56</b> is operated when the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to and detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, and the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> is operated when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to and detached from the frame <b>50</b>. That is, the drum handle <b>56</b> and the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> can be used as situation demands. Thus, the operability can be further improved during the attachment and detachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b> and the developing cartridge <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">In addition, because the drum handle <b>56</b> and the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> are provided so as to be operated from the front, it is easier to operate the drum handle <b>56</b> and the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> through the opening <b>44</b> of the body casing <b>2</b>. Therefore, the operability can be further improved when the process cartridge <b>19</b> and the developing cartridge <b>20</b> are attached to and detached from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">In this embodiment, instead of having the engagement device on each side, the process cartridge <b>19</b> may have the engagement device on only one side. In addition, the process cartridge <b>19</b> may have a plurality of manual engagement devices.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref> represent the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> of another exemplary embodiment. In the description below, the same parts or portions of the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref> as those of the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> are designated by the same reference numerals, and explanations for the those parts or portions will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">The process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref> includes a slidable engaging member <b>80</b> as a third engaging member, and an engagement boss <b>81</b> as a third engaged portion, on each side wall <b>58</b> of the frame <b>50</b>. The slidable engaging members <b>80</b> and the engagement bosses <b>81</b> function as a manual engagement device. Although explanations will be given for one of the slidable engaging members <b>80</b> and one of the engagement bosses <b>81</b> only, they have the same structure and function on each side.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">The slidable engaging member <b>80</b> has a substantially L-shape and includes an engaging plate portion <b>82</b>, which extends in the up and down direction, and an operating plate portion <b>83</b>, which extends forward from a lower end portion of the engaging plate portion <b>82</b> in the process cartridge attaching/detaching direction. The engaging plate portion <b>82</b> and the operating plate portion <b>83</b> are integrated with each other.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">In the slidable engaging member <b>80</b>, an upper end portion of the engaging plate portion <b>82</b> is cut away in a substantially rectangular shape from the front edge toward the rear to provide an engaging recess <b>84</b> that can be engaged with the engagement boss <b>81</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0100">A joint portion of the engaging plate portion <b>82</b> and the operating plate portion <b>83</b> has a slot <b>85</b> extending in the process cartridge attaching/detaching direction. The frame <b>50</b> has a shaft <b>86</b> outwardly extending in the width direction from the front end portion of the rear side-plate-portion <b>52</b>. The shaft <b>86</b> is inserted into the slot <b>85</b> of the slidable engaging member <b>80</b>. With this structure, the slidable engaging member <b>80</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b> so as to be slidable in the process cartridge attaching/detaching direction with respect to the frame <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0101">The engagement boss <b>81</b> is provided to the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b>. More specifically, each of the side walls <b>58</b> of the housing <b>48</b> has a projecting portion <b>87</b> forwardly projecting from its front edge of the lower end portion. The engagement boss <b>81</b> is provided to the projecting portion <b>87</b> so as to outwardly extend in the width direction. In addition, the engagement boss <b>81</b> is provided to a position where the engaging recess <b>84</b> is engaged therewith when the slidable engaging member <b>80</b> slides to the foremost position with respect to the shaft <b>86</b> in the state where the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0102">In the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b>, when the operating plate portion <b>83</b> is pulled in the process cartridge detaching direction to remove the process cartridge <b>19</b> from the body casing <b>2</b> the slidable engaging member <b>80</b> slides in the detaching direction to engage the engaging recess <b>84</b> of the slidable engaging member <b>80</b> with the engagement boss <b>81</b>. Thus, the restricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is restricted is established. Therefore, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be detached from the body casing <b>2</b> together with the process cartridge <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0103">When the operating plate portion <b>83</b> is pressed in the process cartridge attaching direction to attach the process cartridge <b>19</b> to body casing <b>2</b>, the slidable engaging member <b>80</b> slides in the attaching direction and thus the engaging recess <b>84</b> of the slidable engaging member <b>80</b> is disengaged from the engagement boss <b>81</b>. Thus, the unrestricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is allowed is established. Therefore, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be separated from the developing cartridge <b>19</b> and pulled out of the body casing <b>2</b>. In the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref>, in conjunction with the attachment and detachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b> with respect to the body casing <b>2</b>, the developing cartridge <b>19</b> is changed between the restricted state and the unrestricted state with respect to the frame <b>50</b>. Accordingly, the operability can be further improved during the attachment and detachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b> with respect to the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0104">In this embodiment, instead of having the manual engagement device on each side, the process cartridge <b>19</b> may have the manual engagement device on only one side.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0105"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref> represent the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> of another exemplary embodiment. In the description below, the same parts or portions of the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref> as those of the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A</figref> and <b>2</b>B are designated by the same reference numerals, and explanations for the those parts or portions will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0106">In this process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref>, the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> is provided on each side so as to extend along each side wall <b>58</b> of the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b>. The developing cartridge handles <b>63</b> are movable between a standby position where the developing cartridge handles <b>63</b> are on standby for operation (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>) and an operable position where the developing cartridge handles <b>63</b> can be operated (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0107">More specifically, the process cartridge <b>19</b> includes a rotating shaft <b>88</b>, a rotating member <b>89</b>, a boss <b>94</b> and a torsion spring <b>95</b>, on each side. Although explanations will be given for one of the rotating shafts <b>88</b>, the rotating members <b>89</b>, the bosses <b>94</b> and the torsion springs <b>95</b> only, they have the same structure and function on each side. The rotating shaft <b>88</b> outwardly extends from the front end portion of the side wall <b>58</b> of the housing <b>48</b> in the width direction. The rotating member <b>89</b> has the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> at its one end, and is rotatably supported by the rotating shaft <b>88</b> at its other end. The boss <b>94</b> outwardly extends in the width direction from a substantially middle position of the rotating member <b>89</b>. The torsion spring <b>95</b> as an urging device urges the rotating member <b>89</b> at all times so that the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> is oriented toward the standby position.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0108">The torsion spring <b>95</b> has a coil-like wound portion <b>96</b> and linear engagement portions <b>97</b> extending from both sides of the wound portion <b>96</b> in respective directions. The wound portion <b>96</b> and the engagement portions <b>97</b> are integrated with each other. One of the engagement portions <b>97</b> is engaged with a cutaway portion provided to a front of the rotating member <b>89</b> and another is fixed by a spring fixing portion <b>98</b> provided at a diagonally front lower position with respect to the rotating shaft <b>88</b> while the wound portion <b>96</b> of the torsion spring <b>95</b> is wound around the rotating shaft <b>88</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0109">In the body casing <b>2</b>, contact members <b>99</b>, as a second contact portion, are located in a path over which the bosses <b>94</b> move during the attachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0110">When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is moved in the attaching direction along the mounting path <b>47</b>, the boss <b>94</b> contacts the contact member <b>99</b> and the boss <b>94</b> is pressed forward by the contact member <b>99</b> in accordance with the movement of the process cartridge <b>19</b> in the attaching direction after the contact occurs. As a result, the rotating member <b>89</b> rotates forward about the rotating shaft <b>88</b> against urging force from the torsion spring <b>95</b>, so that the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> is moved to the operable position at which the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> protrudes forward from the developing cartridge <b>20</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>). Thus, in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b>, the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> can be located at the operable position in conjunction with the attaching operation of the process cartridge <b>19</b>. Accordingly, the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> can be easily operated and the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be easily detached from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0111">When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, the rotating member <b>89</b> rotates rearward about the rotating shaft <b>88</b> by the urging force from the torsion spring <b>95</b> so that the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> returns to the standby position from the operable position (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>). Therefore, it is unnecessary to return the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> to the standby position from the operable position when the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, so that the operability can be further improved when the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0113" num="0112">In this embodiment, instead of having the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> on each side, the process cartridge <b>19</b> may have the developing cartridge handle <b>63</b> on only one side.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0113"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates the laser beam printer <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> of another exemplary embodiment. In the description below, the same parts or portions of the laser beam printer <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> as those of the laser beam printer <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> are designated by the same reference numerals, and explanations for the those parts or portions will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0114">The process cartridge <b>19</b> to be attached to the laser beam printer <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> includes a protruding member <b>100</b> protruding forward from the front plate <b>91</b> of the frame <b>50</b>. In addition, the process cartridge <b>19</b> includes lever rotating shafts <b>101</b>, which outwardly extends from the side surfaces of the protruding member <b>100</b> in the width direction, a pressing lever <b>102</b>, which is rotatably supported by the lever rotating shaft <b>101</b>, and a pressing member <b>103</b> as an urging device, which is attached to the pressing lever <b>102</b>. The lever rotating shafts <b>101</b>, the pressing lever <b>102</b> and the pressing member <b>103</b> function as a pressure release device.</p>
<p id="p-0116" num="0115">The pressing lever <b>102</b> extends along the side surface of the protruding member <b>100</b> and is rotatably supported by the lever rotating shafts <b>101</b> at its one end. The other end of the pressing lever <b>102</b> is bent substantially at a right angle toward the front so as to extend substantially along the front wall <b>92</b> of the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b>. When the front cover <b>45</b> is closed, the front cover <b>45</b> contacts the front surface of the other end of the pressing lever <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0117" num="0116">The pressing member <b>103</b> includes a fixed portion <b>104</b>, which is fixed to the pressing lever <b>102</b>, a pressing portion <b>105</b>, which is engaged so as to be movable in a direction to become closer to and away from the fixed portion <b>104</b>, and a compression spring <b>106</b>, which is interposed between the fixed portion <b>104</b> and the pressing portion <b>105</b>. The pressing member <b>103</b> contacts the front wall <b>92</b> of the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> to press the housing <b>48</b> by the urging force from the compressing spring <b>106</b>, in the state where the pressing lever <b>102</b> extends along the front wall <b>92</b> of the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0118" num="0117">In the state where the front cover <b>45</b> is closed, the front cover <b>45</b> contacts the other end of the pressing lever <b>102</b>, so that the pressing portion <b>105</b> of the pressing member <b>103</b> contacts the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> to press the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> toward the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> by the urging force from the compression spring <b>106</b> of the pressing member <b>103</b>. Thus, the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> can hold a toner image by which toner is surely supplied to the surface of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0119" num="0118">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, when the front cover <b>45</b> is open, the front cover <b>45</b> is separated from the pressing lever <b>102</b>, so that the pressing lever <b>102</b> rotates forward about the lever rotating shafts <b>101</b> by the urging force from the compression spring <b>106</b> so that the pressing member <b>103</b> moves away from the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b>. As a result, the pressure on the housing <b>48</b> applied by the pressing member <b>103</b> is removed, so that the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be unforcedly detached from the frame <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0120" num="0119">With this structure, in conjunction with the opening and closing of the front cover <b>45</b>, the pressure can be applied to and removed from the developing cartridge <b>20</b> by the pressing member <b>103</b>. Particularly, the pressure on the housing <b>48</b> applied by the pressing member <b>103</b> is removed in conjunction with the opening of the front cover <b>45</b>, so that the operability can be further improved when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the frame <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0121" num="0120">In this embodiment, instead of the single pressure release device, the process cartridge <b>19</b> may have a plurality of pressure release devices.</p>
<p id="p-0122" num="0121"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates the laser beam printer <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> of another exemplary embodiment. In the description below, the same parts or portions of the laser beam printer <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> as those of the laser beam printer <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> are designated by the same reference numerals, and explanations for the those parts or portions will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0123" num="0122">In the laser printer <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the front cover <b>45</b> is provided with the pressing member <b>103</b> (having the same structure as that provided to the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>). When the front cover <b>45</b> is closed, the pressing member <b>103</b> contacts the protruding portions <b>107</b>, which protrude forward from the front wall <b>92</b> of the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b>, to press the developing cartridge <b>20</b> toward the photosensitive drum <b>21</b>. When the front cover <b>45</b> is open, the pressing member <b>103</b> is separated from the protruding portions <b>107</b> to remove the pressure on the housing <b>48</b> applied by the pressing member <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0124" num="0123">With this structure, the effect that is the same as that obtained by the structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> can be obtained. That is, in conjunction with the opening and closing of the front cover <b>45</b>, the pressure can be applied to and removed from the developing cartridge <b>20</b> by the pressing member <b>103</b>. Particularly, the pressure on the housing <b>48</b> applied by the pressing member <b>103</b> is released in conjunction with the opening of the front cover <b>45</b>, so that the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be unforcedly detached from the frame <b>50</b>. In addition, the operability can be further improved during the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0125" num="0124">In this embodiment, instead of having the single pressing member <b>103</b>, the front cover <b>45</b> may have a plurality of pressing members <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0126" num="0125"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A and 9B</figref> represents the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> of another exemplary embodiment. In the description below, the same parts or portions of the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A and 9B</figref> as those of the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> are designated by the same reference numerals, and explanations for the those parts or portions will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0127" num="0126">The process cartridge of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A and 9B</figref> includes a support shaft <b>108</b>, an engaging member <b>109</b>, and an engagement boss <b>110</b> as an engaged portion, on each side. The support shafts <b>108</b>, the engaging members <b>109</b> and the engagement bosses <b>110</b> function as an engagement device. Although explanations will be given for one of the support shafts <b>108</b>, the engaging members <b>109</b> and the engagement bosses <b>110</b> only, they have the same structure and function on each side.</p>
<p id="p-0128" num="0127">The support shaft <b>108</b> outwardly extends in the width direction from the forward part of the side wall <b>58</b> of the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0129" num="0128">The engaging member <b>109</b> has a substantially rectangular shape and is rotatably supported by the support shaft <b>108</b> at a position slightly above a middle position of the engaging member <b>109</b>. A lower end portion of the engaging member <b>109</b> is cut away in a substantially rectangular shape from a front edge toward the rear to provide an engagement recess <b>117</b> engageable to the engagement boss <b>110</b>. The engaging member <b>109</b> has a boss <b>115</b> extending in the width direction, at its upper end. The engaging member <b>109</b> is supported by the support shaft <b>108</b> so as to be able to rotate about the support shaft <b>108</b> between a position where the engaging member <b>109</b> extends in the up and down direction and an inclined position where the engaging recess <b>117</b> and the boss <b>115</b> are located at the rear side and the front side, respectively. The engaging member <b>109</b> is urged at all times by a torsion spring <b>111</b> so that the engaging recess <b>117</b> and the boss <b>115</b> are oriented toward the front and the rear, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0130" num="0129">That is, the torsion spring <b>111</b> has a coil-like wound portion <b>112</b> and linear engagement portions <b>113</b> extending from both sides of the wound portion <b>112</b> in respective directions. The wound portion <b>112</b> and the engagement portions <b>113</b> are integrated with each other. One of the engagement portions <b>113</b> is engaged with a step portion provided to a forward portion of the engaging member <b>109</b> and another is fixed at the side wall <b>58</b> of the housing <b>48</b> by a spring fixing portion <b>114</b> provided at a diagonally front lower position with respect to the support shaft <b>108</b> while the wound portion <b>112</b> of the torsion spring <b>111</b> is wound around the support shaft <b>108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0131" num="0130">The engagement boss <b>110</b> inwardly extends from the front side-plate portion <b>53</b> of the frame <b>50</b> in the width direction. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref>, the engagement boss <b>110</b> is provided at a position where the engaging member <b>109</b> engages the engagement boss <b>110</b> when the engaging member <b>109</b> extends in the up and down direction in the state where the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b>. When the engaging recess <b>117</b> is engaged with the engagement boss <b>110</b>, the restricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is restricted is established. When the engaging recess <b>117</b> is disengaged from the engagement boss <b>110</b>, the unrestricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is unrestricted is established.</p>
<p id="p-0132" num="0131">In the body casing <b>2</b>, contact members <b>116</b>, as a third contact portion, are provided in a path over which the bosses <b>115</b> move during the attachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0133" num="0132">When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is moved in the attaching direction, the boss <b>115</b> contacts the contact member <b>116</b> and the boss <b>115</b> is pressed forward by the contact member <b>116</b> in accordance with the movement of the process cartridge <b>19</b> in the attaching direction after the contact occurs. Then, the engaging member <b>109</b> rotates about the support shaft <b>108</b> against the urging force from the torsion spring <b>111</b>. The engaging recess <b>117</b> of the engaging member <b>109</b> is disengaged from the engagement boss <b>110</b>, so that the restriction on the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is released (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref>). Therefore, it is unnecessary to change the position of the engaging members <b>109</b> when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b> in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b>, so that the operability can be improved when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is removed from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0134" num="0133">When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, the engaging member <b>109</b> rotates about the support shaft <b>108</b> by the urging force from the torsion spring <b>111</b>, so that the engaging recess <b>117</b> is engaged with the engagement boss <b>110</b>. Thus, the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> of the frame <b>50</b> is restricted (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref>). Therefore, it is unnecessary to change the position of the engaging member <b>109</b> when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, so that the operability can be improved when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>. In addition, in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is separated from the body casing <b>2</b>, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be prevented from being easily detached from the frame <b>50</b>. As a result, the exposure of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> caused by the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> can be prevented, so that damage to the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> can be prevented in the state where the process cartridge <b>19</b> is separated from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0135" num="0134">In this embodiment, although having the engagement device is on each side, the process cartridge <b>19</b> may have the engagement device on only one side.</p>
<p id="p-0136" num="0135"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10A and 10B</figref> represent the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> of another exemplary embodiment. In the description below, the same parts or portions of the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10A and 10B</figref> as those of the process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> are designated by the same reference numerals, and explanations for the those parts or portions will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0137" num="0136">The process cartridge <b>19</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10A and 10B</figref> includes a support shaft <b>140</b>, an engaging member <b>141</b>, and an engagement boss <b>142</b> as an engagement portion, on each side. The support shafts <b>140</b>, the engaging members <b>141</b> and the engagement bosses <b>142</b> function as an engagement device (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10C</figref>). Although explanations will be given for one of the support shafts <b>140</b>, the engaging members <b>141</b> and the engagement bosses <b>142</b> only, they have the same structure on each side.</p>
<p id="p-0138" num="0137">The support shaft <b>140</b> is provided to the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> of the side plate <b>51</b> of the frame <b>50</b>. More specifically, the support shaft <b>140</b> inwardly protrudes in the width direction from the middle portion of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> in the front and rear direction.</p>
<p id="p-0139" num="0138">The engaging member <b>141</b> has a plate-shape extending in parallel with the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> and is rotatably supported by the support shaft <b>140</b> at the inner surface of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b>. The engaging member <b>141</b> includes a shaft insertion portion <b>143</b>, into which the support shaft <b>140</b> is inserted, a guided portion <b>144</b> as a release member, which downwardly protrudes from a lower edge of a rear end portion of the engaging member <b>141</b> and has a substantially semi-circular shape, and an engaging portion <b>145</b>, which has a substantially C-shaped portion upwardly opened at a front end portion of the engaging member <b>141</b>. The shaft insertion portion <b>143</b> upwardly protrudes from an upper edge of the engaging member <b>141</b> at a substantially central portion in its longitudinal direction and has a substantially semi-circular shape. The shaft insertion portion <b>143</b>, the guided portion <b>144</b> and the engaging portion <b>145</b> are integrated with each other. The engaging member <b>141</b> is disposed so as to be swingable about the support shaft <b>140</b> between a position where the engaging member <b>141</b> extends in the longitudinal direction of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> and the guided portion <b>144</b> stays within the frame <b>50</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>) and a position where the engaging member <b>141</b> inclinatory extends with respect to the longitudinal direction of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> and the guided portion <b>144</b> protrudes from the lower edge of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10B</figref>). The engaging member <b>141</b> is urged at all times by a torsion spring <b>146</b> in a direction so that the guided portion <b>144</b> protrudes from the lower edge of the frame <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0140" num="0139">In the engaging member <b>141</b>, the torsion spring <b>146</b> has a coil-like wound portion <b>147</b> and linear engagement portions <b>148</b> extending from both sides of the wound portion <b>147</b> in respective directions. The wound portion <b>147</b> and the engagement portions <b>148</b> are integrated with each other. One of the engagement portions <b>147</b> is engaged with a step portion provided behind the shaft insertion portion <b>143</b> and another is fixed at the inner surface of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> of the frame <b>50</b> by a spring fixing portion <b>149</b> provided at a diagonally front upper position with respect to the support shaft <b>140</b> while the wound portion <b>147</b> of the torsion spring <b>146</b> is wound around the support shaft <b>140</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0141" num="0140">The engagement boss <b>142</b> outwardly protrudes from the side wall <b>58</b> of the housing <b>48</b> of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> in the width direction. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10B</figref>, the engagement boss <b>142</b> is provided at a position where the engaging member <b>141</b> inclinatory extends with respect to the longitudinal direction of the front side-plate-portion <b>53</b> of the frame <b>50</b> when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is attached to the frame <b>50</b> and the engaging portion <b>145</b> of the engaging member <b>141</b> is engaged with the engagement boss <b>142</b> when the guided portion <b>144</b> protrudes from the lower edge of the frame <b>50</b>. When the engaging portion <b>145</b> is engaged with the engagement boss <b>142</b>, the restricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is restricted is established. When the engaging portion <b>145</b> is disengaged with the engagement boss <b>142</b>, the unrestricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is permitted is established.</p>
<p id="p-0142" num="0141">In the body casing <b>2</b>, a guiding member <b>150</b> as a first contact portion is provided in order to guide the guided portion <b>144</b> of the engaging member <b>141</b> during the attachment and detachment of the process cartridge <b>19</b> with respect to the body casing <b>2</b>. The guiding member <b>150</b> includes an inclined plane <b>151</b>, which ascends rearward, and a horizontal plane <b>152</b>, which extends substantially in the horizontal direction from an upper end (a rear end) of the inclined plane <b>151</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0143" num="0142">The inclined plane <b>151</b> of the guiding member <b>150</b> is disposed at a position where the guided portion <b>144</b> of the engaging member <b>141</b> protruding from the lower edge of the engaging member <b>141</b> contacts the included plane <b>151</b> when the process cartridge <b>19</b> is attached to the body casing <b>2</b>. When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is further moved in the attaching direction after the guided portion <b>144</b> of the engaging member <b>141</b> contacts the inclined plane <b>151</b>, the guided portion <b>144</b> is moved over the inclined plane <b>151</b> toward the horizontal plane <b>152</b>. In accordance with this movement, the engaging member <b>141</b> rotates in a direction to accommodate the guided portion <b>144</b> in the frame <b>50</b> against the urging force from the torsion spring <b>146</b>. Thus, the engaging portion <b>145</b> of the engaging member <b>141</b> is disengaged from the engagement boss <b>142</b>, so that the restriction on the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the casing <b>50</b> is removed (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>). Therefore, it is unnecessary to change the position of the engaging member <b>141</b> when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, so that operability can be improved when the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0144" num="0143">When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, the guided portion <b>144</b> of the engaging member <b>141</b> is moved over the horizontal plane <b>152</b> of the guiding member <b>150</b> toward the inclined plane <b>151</b> in accordance with the movement of the process cartridge <b>19</b> in the detaching direction. When the process cartridge <b>19</b> is further moved in the detaching direction after the guided portion <b>144</b> reaches the inclined plane <b>151</b>, the engaging member <b>141</b> rotates in the direction to allow the guided portion <b>144</b> to protrude from the lower edge of the frame <b>50</b> by the urging force from the torsion spring <b>111</b> while the guided portion <b>144</b> is guided by the inclined plane <b>151</b>. Therefore, the engaging portion <b>145</b> is engaged with the engagement boss <b>142</b>, so that the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> is restricted (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10B</figref>). Accordingly, it is unnecessary to change the position of the engaging member <b>141</b> when the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, for example, in order to clear a paper jam, so that the operability can be improved when the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0145" num="0144">In the state whew the process cartridge <b>19</b> is detached from the body casing <b>2</b>, the engaging member <b>141</b> almost stays between the developing cartridge <b>20</b> and the frame <b>50</b>, so that it is difficult to manually operate the engaging member <b>141</b>. Accordingly, the developing cartridge <b>20</b> can be further prevented from being easily detached from the frame <b>50</b>. As a result, the exposure of the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> caused by the detachment of the developing cartridge <b>20</b> from the frame <b>50</b> can be prevented, so that damage to the photosensitive drum <b>21</b> can be prevented in the state where the developing cartridge <b>20</b> is detached.</p>
<p id="p-0146" num="0145">In this embodiment, instead of having the engagement device on each side, the process cartridge <b>19</b> may have the engagement device on only one side.</p>
<p id="p-0147" num="0146">Although, in the above described embodiments, the explanations have been made as to the operation performed at one side only, the same operation is performed at the other side of the process cartridge <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0148" num="0147">According to the above embodiments, when the process cartridge is attached to the image forming apparatus while the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame is restricted by the engagement device, the engagement device is changed from the restricting state to the unrestricting state by the release device, so that the restriction on the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame is released. Therefore, it is unnecessary to change the state of the engagement device. Thus, the operability can be improved when the developing cartridge is removed from the image forming apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0149" num="0148">When the process cartridge is attached to the image forming apparatus, the release member contacts the first contact member and then the engaging member rotates about the support shaft in a direction to disengage from the engaged portion in accordance with the movement of the process cartridge in the attaching direction. Therefore, in conjunction with the attachment of the process cartridge to the image forming apparatus, the restriction on the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame imposed by the engagement device can be surely removed.</p>
<p id="p-0150" num="0149">When the process cartridge is attached to the image forming apparatus, the second release portion contacts the third contact portion and then the engaging member rotates about the support shaft in a direction to disengage from the engaged portion in accordance with the movement of the process cartridge in the attaching direction. Therefore, in conjunction with the attachment of the process cartridge to the image forming apparatus, the restriction on the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame imposed by the engagement device can be surely removed.</p>
<p id="p-0151" num="0150">When the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus, the engagement device returns to the restricting state from the unrestricting state, so that the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame is restricted. Therefore, it is unnecessary to change the state of the engaging device when the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus, for example, in order to clear a paper jam, so that the operability can be improved when the process cartridge is removed from the image forming apparatus. In addition, the developing cartridge can be prevented from being easily detached from the frame in the state where the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus. As a result, the exposure of the image forming apparatus caused by the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame can be prevented, thereby preventing damage to the image forming apparatus in the state where the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0152" num="0151">When the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus, the retuning member contacts the first contact portion and then the engaging member rotates about the support shaft in a direction to engage the engaged portion in accordance with the movement of the process cartridge in the detaching direction. Therefore, in conjunction with the detachment of the process cartridge from the image forming apparatus, the restricted state where the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame is restricted can be surely established.</p>
<p id="p-0153" num="0152">The process cartridge includes the manual engagement device that can change between the restricting state where the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame is restricted and the unrestricting state where the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame is permitted. Therefore, the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame can be restricted. Thus, the developing cartridge can be further surely prevented from being detached from the frame, so that damage to the image holding body can be further prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0154" num="0153">By manual operation, the second engaging member is rotated to engage the second engaging member with the second engaged member for restricting the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame and to disengage the second engaging member from the second engaged member for removing the restriction on the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame. Accordingly, the detachment of the developing cartridge can be restricted and permitted by the simple manual operation.</p>
<p id="p-0155" num="0154">When the process cartridge is attached to and detached from the image forming apparatus by operating the frame-side operating portion, the third engaging member slides in the process cartridge attaching/detaching direction, so that the third engaging member is engaged with and disengaged from the third engaged portion. Thus, the manual engagement device can change between the restricting state and the unrestricting state.</p>
<p id="p-0156" num="0155">The frame-side operating portion and the developing-cartridge-side operating portion are separately provided. That is, the frame-side operating portion and the developing-cartridge-side operating portion can be used as situation demands. That is, the frame-side operating portion is operated when the process cartridge is attached to and detached from the image forming apparatus, and the developing-cartridge-side operating portion is operated when the developing cartridge is attached to and detached from the frame. Thus, the operability can be further improved when the process cartridge and the developing cartridge are attached to and detached from the image forming apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0157" num="0156">The frame-side operating portion and the developing-cartridge-side operating portion can be operated from the same side, so that the operability can be further improved when the process cartridge and the developing cartridge are attached to and detached from the image forming apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0158" num="0157">In the state where the process cartridge is attached to the image forming apparatus, the developing-cartridge-side operating portion protrudes from the developing cartridge, so that the usability of the developing-cartridge-side operating portion can be increased. Therefore, the operability can be improved when the developing cartridge is removed from the image forming apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0159" num="0158">When the process cartridge is attached to the image forming apparatus, the boss of the rotating member contacts the second contact portion and then the rotating member rotates about the support shaft in accordance with the movement of the process cartridge in the attaching direction. Then, the developing-cartridge-side operating portion protrudes from the developing cartridge. Accordingly, in conjunction with the attachment of the process cartridge to the image forming apparatus, the developing-cartridge-side operating portion can be surely positioned at the operable position where the developing-cartridge-side operating portion protrudes from the developing cartridge.</p>
<p id="p-0160" num="0159">In the state where the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus, the urging member urges the developing-cartridge-side operating portion toward the standby position. Accordingly, when the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus, the developing-cartridge-side operating portion returns to the standby position from the operable position, so that the operability can be further increased.</p>
<p id="p-0161" num="0160">In the state where the process cartridge is attached to the image forming apparatus, the developing cartridge is urged toward the image holding body by the pressing device. Therefore, the image holding body can hold a developing agent image by which developing agent is surely supplied to the surface of the image holding body. In addition, when the developing cartridge is removed from the frame, the pressure on the developing cartridge applied by the pressing device can be removed by the pressure release device, so that the developing cartridge can be unforcedly removed from the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0162" num="0161">In conjunction with the opening of the cover member, the pressure on the developing cartridge applied by the pressing device can be removed. Therefore, the operability can be improved when the developing cartridge is removed from the image forming apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0163" num="0162">When the cover member is open, the cover member and the pressing lever are out of contact with each other, so that the pressure on the developing cartridge applied by the pressing device is removed. When the cover member is closed, the cover member and the pressing lever are in contact with each other, so that the developing cartridge is pressed by the pressing device. Accordingly, in conjunction with the opening and closing of the cover member, the pressure by the pressing device can be surely applied to and removed from the developing cartridge.</p>
<p id="p-0164" num="0163">In the state where the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus, the portion, facing the transfer device, of the image holding body is exposed. Therefore, when the developing cartridge is separated from the frame in the state where the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus, the portion, facing the developing cartridge of the image holding device is further exposed and the exposed portion of the image holding body is expanded. When the detachment of the developing cartridge is restricted in the state where the process cartridge is detached from the image forming apparatus, the expansion of the exposed portion of the image holding body can be prevented. Accordingly, a possibility of damage to the exposed portion of the image holding body can be reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0165" num="0164">While the disclosure has been described in detail with reference to the specific embodiments thereof, it would be apparent to those skilled in the art that various changes, arrangements and modifications may be applied therein without departing from the spirit and scope of the disclosure.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A process cartridge, comprising:
<claim-text>a developing cartridge;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a frame that detachably mounts the developing cartridge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an engaging member, provided on the frame, that engages the developing cartridge, wherein:
<claim-text>the engaging member includes an engagement portion and a disengagement portion,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the disengagement portion automatically moves the engaging member to a first position when the process cartridge is placed in an image forming device, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the engagement portion automatically moves the engaging member to a second position when the process cartridge is removed from the image forming device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the developing cartridge, further comprises:
<claim-text>an engagement device that is capable of being engaged with the engaging member associated with the frame, wherein:
<claim-text>in the second postion the engagement device is placed in a restricting state where the engagement device is engaged with the engaging member,</claim-text>
<claim-text>in the first position the engagement device is placed in an unrestricting state where the engagement device is disengaged from the engaging member, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the engagement device is automatically placed in the unrestricting state when the developing cartridge is placed in an image forming device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The developing cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a manual engagement device that is capable of being manually engaged with a manual engaging member associated with the frame, wherein:
<claim-text>the manual engagement device can be placed in a second restricting state where the manual engagement device is engaged with the manual engaging member, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the manual engagement device can be placed in a second unrestricting state where the manual engagement device is disengaged from the manual engaging member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The developing cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a pressing device that is capable of pressing the developing cartridge toward an image forming body when the developing cartridge is attached to the image forming device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The developing cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the pressing device is capable of pressing the developing cartridge in conjunction with an opening of a cover member associated with the image forming device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The developing cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a developing-cartridge-side operating portion that is operated when the developing cartridge is attached to and detached from the frame.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The developing cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the developing-cartridge-side operating portion is movable between a standby position where the developing-cartridge-side operating portion is on standby for operation and is disposed so as to extend along the developing cartridge, and an operable position where the developing-cartridge-side operating portion is in an operable state and is disposed so as to protrude from the developing cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The developing cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a rotating shaft that is provided to the developing cartridge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotating member that has the developing-cartridge-side operating portion at one end and is rotatably supported by the rotating shaft at another end, the rotating member having a boss between the one end and the another end, wherein the developing-cartridge-side operating portion is located at the standby position when the frame is detached from the image forming device and is located at the operable position by which the boss contacts a first contact portion provided to the image forming apparatus and the rotating member rotates about the rotating shaft because of the pressing of the boss by the first contact portion when a process cartridge is attached to the image forming apparatus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The developing cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising an urging device that urges the rotating member so that the developing-cartridge-side operating portion is oriented toward the standby position in the state where the boss is separated from the first contact portion and the frame is detached from the image forming device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. An image forming device, comprising:
<claim-text>the process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The image forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a pressing device that presses the developing cartridge toward an image holding body in the state where the process cartridge is attached to the image forming apparatus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>when the engaging member is moved to the first position and a developing cartridge is placed on the frame, the engaging member is placed in an unrestricting state where the engaging member is disengaged from an engagement device of the developing cartridge, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the engaging member is moved to the second position and a developing cartridge is placed on the frame, the engaging member is placed in a restricting state where the engaging member is engaged with the engagement device of the developing cartridge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the engaging member has a support shaft that is provided to the frame,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the engaging member is rotatably supported by the support shaft and is capable of being engaged with and disengaged from the engagement device of the developing cartridge by rotating about the support shaft, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the disengagement portion contacts a first contact portion of the image forming device during attachment of the process cartridge to the image forming device and the first contact portion rotates the engaging member in a direction to disengage the engaging member from the engagement device in accordance with a movement of the process cartridge in an attaching direction.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the engagement portion contacts the first contact portion of the image forming device during detachment of the process cartridge from the image forming device and the first contact portion rotates the engaging member in a direction to engage the engaging member with the engagement device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a manual engaging device that can manually change between a second restricting state where the detachment of a developing cartridge from the frame is restricted and a second unrestricting state where the detachment of the developing cartridge from the frame is permitted, by manual operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the manual engaging device includes a support shaft that is provided to the frame,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second engaging member that is rotatably supported by the support shaft and is capable of being engaged with and disengaged from a second engagement device of the developing cartridge by rotating about the support shaft by manual operation, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second restricting state is established by the engagement of the second engaging member and the second engagement device and the second unrestricting state is established by the disengagement of the second engaging member and the second engagement device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the manual engaging member includes a second engaging member that is provided to the frame so as to be slidable, the second engaging member is capable of being engaged with and disengaged from a second engagement device of the developing cartridge by sliding relative to the frame, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second restricting state is established by the engagement of the second engaging member and the second engagement device and the second unrestricting state is established by the disengagement of the second engaging member and the second engagement device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a frame-side operating portion that is operated when the process cartridge is attached to and detached from the image forming apparatus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a pressing device that is capable of pressing a developing cartridge attached to the frame toward an image forming body in the state where the process cartridge is attached to the image forming device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the process cartridge is attached to and detached from the image forming device by opening a cover member provided to the image forming apparatus so as to be able to be open and closed, and a pressure release device releases the pressure on the developing cartridge applied by the pressing device in conjunction with the opening of the cover member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref>, wherein the pressure release device includes a lever rotating shaft, which is provided to the frame, a pressing lever, which is rotatably supported by the lever rotating shaft and is provided with the pressing device, the pressing lever not contacting the cover member when the cover member is open and contacting the cover member to press the pressing device in a direction to contact the urging device with the developing cartridge when the cover member is closed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. An image forming device, comprising:
<claim-text>the process cartridge according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
