<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296732-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296732</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11445381</doc-number>
<date>20060601</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>47</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>232 19</main-classification>
<further-classification>232 45</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Magnetically sealing mail slot flap</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>746906</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wimer</name>
<date>19031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>232 45</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2437319</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gable et al.</name>
<date>19480300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>232 45</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2595535</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nowakowski</name>
<date>19520500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>232 45</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4545522</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kerzner</name>
<date>19851000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>232 45</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5382945</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Novak</name>
<date>19950100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340569</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0065705</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Plappert</name>
<date>20060300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>232 19</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>232 19</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>232 45</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>232 44</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>232  1 E</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>109 64</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>109 66</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 49168</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 494781</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 49402</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60686121</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20050601</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060273146</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061207</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Roddy</last-name>
<first-name>Steven T.</first-name>
<address>
<street>20622 Wedgewood</street>
<city>Grosse Pointe Woods</city>
<state>MI</state>
<postcode>48236</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fildes &amp; Outland, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Miller</last-name>
<first-name>William L.</first-name>
<department>3677</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An assembly for a door or wall having a mail slot therein includes a mounting portion and a flap portion. The flap portion is sized to cover the mail slot. A connector is mountable on the door or wall around the slot. A cooperable connector is integral with the flap portion for releasably connecting with the connector. The connector includes one of a ferrous material containing portion and a magnetic portion. The cooperable connector includes the other of the ferrous material containing portion and the magnetic portion. The flap portion is magnetically connectable to the door or wall around the mail slot opening.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="160.53mm" wi="240.20mm" file="US07296732-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="257.81mm" wi="200.83mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296732-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="206.08mm" wi="163.49mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296732-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the priority of U.S. Provisional Application No. 60/686,121 filed Jun. 1, 2005.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to mail slots in entry doors and in walls, and more particularly to sealing the opening forming the mail slot thereby to conserve energy.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A mail slot is often provided or disposed in an entry door or an outer wall of a residence or business through which mail is delivered. For example, an entry door may include a rectangular aperture that defines the mail slot and also a flap disposed about the outward facing side of the door. Such flaps are usually hinged along a top edge and closed by gravitational force. Alternatively, the mail slot may be disposed in on an outer wall and may be located near to an entry door.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Often the flap used to close the opening is quite energy inefficient. It may be part of a trim pack designed for aesthetic purposes but not to prevent heat/cold transfer. Typically the flap is made of thin sheet material, often a metallic material that is highly conductive and aids in undesirable heat transfer. Further, the flap may not, and typically does not, seal around the opening to prevent air movement through the opening.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is desirable to have provided a mail slot closing structure that aids in the conservation of energy.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The present invention provides a magnetic mail slot flap assembly for magnetically sealing around the opening on the interior side of a mail slot in an entry door or outside wall of a residence or commercial building. The magnetic sealing of the door flap inhibits heat transfer and prevents air movement, such as drafts, through the mail slot, resulting in energy savings when heating and cooling a building on which the entry door is disposed. The interior mail slot flap also provides a cover for the often unsightly interior opening of a mail slot.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">More particularly, an assembly for a surface of a structural member such as a door or wall having a mail slot therein includes a mounting portion and a flap portion. The flap portion is sized to cover the mail slot. A connector is mountable on the surface around the slot. A cooperable connector is integral with the flap portion for releasably connecting with the connector. The connector includes one of a ferrous portion and a magnetic portion. The cooperable connector includes the other of the ferrous portion and the magnetic portion. The flap portion is magnetically connectable to the surface around the mail slot opening.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In a specific embodiment, the cooperable connector may comprise a flexible magnetically susceptible material. Alternatively, the cooperable connector may comprise a rigid material. The mounting portion may be mountable to the surface of the door or wall by one of an adhesive or one or more mechanical fasteners. The mounting portion may be integral with the flap portion. Alternatively, the mounting portion may be connected to the flap portion by a hinge.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In another embodiment of the present invention, a mail slot assembly is provided for a structural member such as a door or wall having an interior side, an exterior side, a slot extending from the exterior side to the interior side, and a connector portion surrounding the slot on the interior side of the door or wall. The assembly includes a cover sheet. The cover sheet is sized to cover the slot and includes a magnetically susceptible face. The cover sheet is mountable to the interior side of the door or wall such that the magnetically susceptible face is juxtaposed the interior side of the door or wall. The magnetically susceptible face is cooperable with the connector portion of the door or wall for releasable connection to the connector portion. Connecting the magnetically susceptible face to the connector portion of the door or wall seals the slot.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In this embodiment, the cover sheet may comprise a flexible material or alternatively may comprise a rigid material. The connector portion of the door or wall may be a thin ferrous material containing sheet mounted to the interior side of the door or wall and having an opening corresponding in size to the slot. The door or wall may be made of a non-ferrous material such as wood, a composite material, or another similar non-ferrous building material. The connector portion may then be mountable to the door or wall by an adhesive. Alternatively, the door or wall may be made of a ferrous material wherein the connector portion is integral with the door or wall. It should be understood, however, that the door or wall may be made of any material known in the art as a material for making doors or walls. The cover sheet may be mountable to the door or wall along an upper edge. The cover sheet may also be mountable to the door or wall by an adhesive, one or more mechanical fasteners, or other similar mounting means.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">These and other features and advantages of the invention will be more fully understood from the following detailed description of the invention taken together with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In the drawings:</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an exploded perspective view of a magnetic mail slot flap assembly in accordance with the invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the mail slot assembly taken along the line <b>2</b>-<b>2</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Referring now to the drawings in detail, numeral <b>10</b> generally indicates a magnetically sealing mail slot flap assembly in accordance with the present invention. The magnetically sealing mail slot assembly <b>10</b> provides a tight seal between the flap and the opening on the interior side of a mail slot in a door or outside wall of a residence or commercial building. The magnetically sealing mail slot assembly <b>10</b> thereby reduces heat transfer through the mail slot and in turn improves the efficiency of energy use for heating/cooling the area inside of the door or wall, which may be used as a living space or business. The magnetically sealing mail slot assembly <b>10</b> is also universally mountable on any entranceway door or outside wall having a mail slot, or even an angled surface having a mail slot. It should be understood that the present invention may be used to seal any mail slot disposed in a door, a wall, or other similar structural member. For simplicity, the following description will relate to mail slots in doors, although the invention is not limited solely to this example.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">More particularly, an assembly <b>10</b> for a door <b>12</b> having a mail slot <b>14</b> therein includes a mounting portion <b>16</b> and a flap portion <b>18</b>. The flap portion <b>18</b> is sized to cover the mail slot <b>14</b>. A connector <b>20</b> is mountable on the door <b>12</b> around the slot <b>14</b>. A cooperable connector <b>22</b> is integral with the flap portion <b>18</b> for releasably connecting with the connector <b>20</b>. The connector <b>20</b> comprises one of a ferrous portion and a magnetic portion. The cooperable connector <b>22</b> comprises the other of the ferrous portion and the magnetic portion. If the connector <b>20</b> is the ferrous portion, then the cooperable connector <b>22</b> is the magnetic portion, or if the connector <b>20</b> is the magnetic portion, then the cooperable connector <b>22</b> is the ferrous portion. The ferrous portion and magnetic portion cooperate to form a magnetic connection between the connector <b>20</b> and the cooperable connector <b>22</b> in order to magnetically connect the flap portion <b>18</b> to the door <b>12</b> around the mail slot opening <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The mounting portion <b>16</b> may be mountable to the door <b>12</b> by an adhesive, one or more mechanical fasteners <b>24</b> such as screws or nails, or any other suitable, known mounting means. The assembly <b>10</b> may further include a mounting bar <b>26</b> that is placed on top of the mounting portion <b>16</b> prior to fastening the mounting portion to the door <b>12</b>. The mounting bar <b>26</b> may include receiver(s) <b>28</b> for receiving and retaining a decorative strip <b>30</b>. After mounting the mounting portion <b>16</b> to the door <b>12</b>, the decorative strip <b>30</b> may be either slid or pressed into the receivers <b>28</b>. The decorative strip <b>30</b> covers and hides the fasteners <b>24</b> to improve the appearance of an installed mail slot assembly <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The connector <b>20</b> may be integral with the door <b>12</b>. For example, if the door is made of a ferrous metal material, the connector <b>20</b> may simply be the portion of the door <b>12</b> that surrounds the mail slot <b>14</b> on the interior surface of the door. Alternatively, if the door is made of wood or any other non-ferrous material, the connector <b>20</b> may be a thin sheet of a ferrous or magnetic material that is mountable around the mail slot opening <b>14</b> by an adhesive or other mounting means.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The cooperable connector <b>22</b> may comprise a flexible magnetically susceptible material and may be generally lightweight. The mounting portion <b>16</b> may then be integral with the flap portion <b>18</b>. For example, the mounting portion <b>16</b> and flap portion <b>18</b> may be formed from a sheet of flexible magnetic material that may be laminated with a colored decorative layer <b>32</b>. The decorative layer <b>32</b> is preferably the same color as the decorative strip <b>30</b>. Further, the color of the decorative strip <b>30</b> and decorative layer <b>32</b> preferably are chosen to match the color of the door <b>12</b>. The decorative layer <b>32</b> may also include decorative art. Alternatively, the cooperable connector <b>22</b> may comprise a rigid material. The mounting portion <b>16</b> may then be connected to the flap portion <b>18</b> by a hinge so that the flap portion <b>18</b> may open and close. The cooperable connector <b>22</b> may be contiguous with the entire flap portion <b>18</b> or may only be disposed along a peripheral edge of the flap portion.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In a specific embodiment of the present invention, the mail slot assembly <b>10</b> is provided for a door <b>12</b> having an interior side <b>34</b>, an exterior side <b>36</b>, a slot <b>14</b> extending from the exterior side <b>36</b> to the interior side <b>34</b>, and a connector portion <b>20</b> surrounding the slot <b>14</b> on the interior side <b>34</b> of the door <b>12</b>. The assembly <b>10</b> includes a flexible cover sheet <b>40</b> integrally comprising the mounting portion <b>16</b> and flap portion <b>18</b>. The cover sheet <b>40</b> is sized to cover the slot <b>14</b> in the door <b>12</b> and includes a magnetically susceptible face that forms the cooperable connector <b>22</b>. The cover sheet <b>40</b> is mountable to the interior side <b>34</b> of the door <b>12</b> such that the magnetically susceptible face is juxtaposed, i.e. face to face with, the interior side <b>34</b> of the door <b>12</b>. The magnetically susceptible face <b>22</b> is cooperable with the connector portion <b>20</b> of the door <b>12</b> for releasable connection to the connector portion <b>20</b>. Connecting the magnetically susceptible face <b>22</b> to the connector portion <b>20</b> of the door <b>12</b> seals the slot <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In this embodiment, the connector portion <b>20</b> of the door <b>12</b> may be a thin ferrous material containing sheet mounted to the interior side <b>34</b> of the door <b>12</b> and having an opening <b>42</b> corresponding in size to the slot <b>14</b> in the door <b>12</b>. The door <b>12</b> may be made of a wood material, a composite material, or other non-metallic, non-ferrous material. The connector portion <b>20</b> may then be provided as part of the assembly <b>10</b> and may be mountable to the door <b>12</b> by an adhesive or other suitable, known mounting means. Prior to mounting the connector portion <b>20</b> to the door <b>12</b>, a release liner or backing sheet may cover the adhesive side of the connector portion to protect the connector portion from premature sticking to other objects. It is necessary to mount the connector portion <b>20</b> to the door prior to mounting the cover sheet <b>40</b>. Alternatively, if the door <b>12</b> is made of a ferrous material, the connector portion <b>20</b> is an integral portion of the door surrounding the mail slot <b>14</b>. The cover sheet <b>40</b> may then be directly mounted to the door <b>12</b>. It should be understood that the door may be made of any material known in the art as a material for making doors. The cover sheet <b>40</b> may be mountable to the door <b>12</b> along an upper edge <b>44</b> of the cover sheet <b>40</b>. The cover sheet <b>40</b> may also be mountable to the door <b>12</b> by an adhesive, one or more mechanical fasteners <b>24</b>, or other similar mounting means.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">To mount the mail slot assembly <b>10</b> to a door <b>12</b>, any existing mail slot assembly must be removed from the interior surface <b>34</b> of the door. The surface <b>34</b> should also be clean and dry. Next, if a separate connector portion <b>20</b> sheet must be used (i.e., for a door that is non-ferrous), the connector portion <b>20</b> sheet may be centered about the slot <b>14</b> and then mounted to the interior surface <b>34</b> of the door <b>12</b>. If the connector portion <b>20</b> includes an adhesive surface, any backing sheet present on the adhesive side should be removed to mount the connector portion <b>20</b>. The connector portion <b>20</b> may have a pre-sized opening <b>42</b> made to match the size of the slot <b>14</b>. Alternatively, part of the connector portion <b>20</b> may need to be removed in order to match the size of the opening <b>42</b> with the slot <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Next, the mounting bar <b>26</b> is aligned with the mounting portion <b>16</b> of the cover sheet <b>40</b> and the cover sheet is aligned with the connector portion <b>20</b>. The location of holes <b>46</b> in the mounting bar <b>26</b> are marked on the cover sheet <b>40</b>. The mounting bar <b>26</b> is removed and, with the cover sheet <b>40</b> aligned with the connector portion <b>20</b>, holes are driven through the cover sheet <b>40</b> and connector portion <b>20</b>, and into the door <b>12</b>. The holes <b>46</b> in the mounting bar are realigned with the holes in the cover sheet <b>40</b> and connector portion <b>20</b>, and the cover sheet <b>40</b> is mounted to the door by driving fasteners <b>24</b> through the aligned holes. The decorative strip <b>30</b> may then be placed in the receiver(s) <b>28</b> in the mounting bar <b>26</b> to cover the fasteners <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In use, the magnetic mail slot door flap <b>10</b> is opened by applying force against the flap portion <b>18</b> from the exterior side <b>36</b> of the door such as by a mail carrier inserting mail through the mail slot <b>14</b>. When the mail or other object passes all the way through the mail slot <b>14</b>, gravity closes the flap portion <b>18</b> and a magnetic seal is effected between the connector portion <b>20</b> and the cooperable connector <b>22</b>. The mail slot assembly <b>10</b> thereby creates an airtight seal between the flap portion <b>18</b> and the door <b>12</b>. The mail slot assembly <b>10</b> also improves the appearance of the interior side <b>36</b> of the door <b>12</b> by covering over the open slot <b>14</b> in the door.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Although the invention has been described by reference to a specific embodiment, it should be understood that numerous changes may be made within the spirit and scope of the inventive concepts described. Accordingly, it is intended that the invention not be limited to the described embodiment, but that it have the full scope defined by the language of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A mail slot assembly for a surface having a mail slot therein, the mail slot assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a cover sheet including a mounting portion mountable to said surface and a flap portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said flap portion being sized to cover said mail slot;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a connector mountable on said surface around said slot;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cooperable connector integral with said flap portion for releasably connecting with said connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said connector including one of a ferrous portion and a magnetic portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said cooperable connector including the other of said ferrous portion and magnetic portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>whereby said flap portion is magnetically connectable to said surface around said mail slot opening.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said cooperable connector comprises a flexible material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said cooperable connector comprises a rigid material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said mounting portion is mountable to said surface by one of an adhesive and a mechanical fastener.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said mounting portion is connected to said flap portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said mounting portion is integral with said flap portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A mail slot assembly for a structural member having an interior side, an exterior side, a slot extending from the exterior side to the interior side, and a connector portion surrounding the slot on the interior side of the structural member, the mail slot assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a cover sheet sized to cover the slot and including a magnetically susceptible face;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said cover sheet being mountable to the interior side of said structural member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said magnetically susceptible face being cooperable with said connector portion of said structural member for releasable connection to said connector portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein connecting said magnetically susceptible face to said connector portion of said structural member seals said slot.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said cover sheet comprises a rigid material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said cover sheet comprises a flexible material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said connector portion of said structural member is a thin ferrous material containing sheet mounted to the interior side of said structural member and having an opening corresponding in size to the slot.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said structural member comprises a non-ferrous material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said structural member comprises a ferrous material and said connector portion is integral with said structural member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said cover sheet is mountable to said structural member along an upper edge.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said cover sheet is mountable to said structural member by an adhesive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said cover sheet is mountable to said structural member by one or more mechanical fasteners.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The mail slot assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said connector portion is mountable to said structural member by an adhesive.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
