<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298448-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298448</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10708330</doc-number>
<date>20040224</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>92108283 A</doc-number>
<date>20030410</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>1335</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349155</main-classification>
<further-classification>349156</further-classification>
<further-classification>349157</further-classification>
<further-classification>349106</further-classification>
<further-classification>349110</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Liquid crystal display with a uniform common voltage and method thereof</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5748266</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kodate</name>
<date>19980500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349 39</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5917572</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kurauchi et al.</name>
<date>19990600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349156</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6275280</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kajita et al.</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349155</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6795141</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Yamada</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349106</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6862050</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Rho et al.</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349 44</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6930747</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lee</name>
<date>20050800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349155</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6965419</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Nishida et al.</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349106</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0026347</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Sawasaki et al.</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349156</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0060771</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Sumino et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349156</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0075441</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Fujimori et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349155</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0109815</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hirakata et al.</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349155</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0171800</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Miyazaki et al.</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349156</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0027529</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Sasaki</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349156</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>8</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349106</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349107</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349108</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349155-157</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349110</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040201813</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20041014</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wu</last-name>
<first-name>Yang-En</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hsu</last-name>
<first-name>Winston</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>AU Optronics Corp.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Hsin-Chu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nelms</last-name>
<first-name>David</first-name>
<department>2871</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>(Nancy) Thanh-Nhan P</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An LCD with a uniform common voltage and a method thereof. The present invention method includes providing a lower substrate, forming scan lines and data lines, then forming common electrodes and common electrode pads electrically connecting the common electrodes. The method also includes providing an upper substrate, forming photo spacers corresponding to each of the electrode pad, then forming a conductive material layer covering each photo spacer, combining the two substrates and connecting the conductive material layer on the photo spacers to the common electrode pads, and sealing the two substrates.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="111.93mm" wi="162.31mm" file="US07298448-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="115.32mm" wi="138.26mm" file="US07298448-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="115.32mm" wi="150.03mm" file="US07298448-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="115.32mm" wi="124.38mm" file="US07298448-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="115.32mm" wi="162.90mm" file="US07298448-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="221.83mm" wi="149.69mm" file="US07298448-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention relates to a liquid crystal display (LCD), and more particularly, to a LCD with a uniform common voltage and a method thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Since the LCD has the advantages of portability, low power consumption, and low radiation, the LCD has been widely used in various portable information products, such as notebooks, personal digital assistants (PDA), video cameras, and etc. Furthermore, the LCD even has a potential to replace the CRT monitor or the television gradually.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the conventional TFT-LCD process, spacers, such as plastic beads, glass beads, or glass fibers, are positioned by spraying, and tend to be mal-distributed, for maintaining the thickness of the cell gap between two substrates of the TFT-LCD and controlling the cell gap to a specific value to ensure the display performance. Consequently, the contrast of the TFT-LCD is affected due to light scattering by the spacers that are positioned in the light transmitting regions, generating white point defects and reducing yield rates and the display performance. For this reason, photo spacers formed by a photolithographic process have been developed to replace the conventional plastic beads to control the dimensions and positions of the spacers and the uniformity of the cell gap accurately to raise the display performance.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of a LCD <b>10</b> according to the prior art, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a section view of the structure of the LCD <b>10</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the LCD <b>10</b> has a display area <b>12</b> and a non-display area <b>14</b> surrounding the display area <b>12</b>. The display area <b>12</b> contains a plurality of data lines <b>16</b> and a plurality of scan lines <b>18</b> arranged perpendicular to the data lines <b>16</b> to form a pixel matrix (comprising a plurality of pixels <b>20</b>), and a plurality of pixel drivers comprising a plurality of electrical elements, such as thin film transistors (TFTs) and capacitances, positioned on each intersection of the scan lines <b>18</b> and the data lines <b>16</b>. The non-display area <b>14</b> contains package testing materials, signal transmitting wires, such as periphery circuit elements, repair lines, and tape carrier packages (TCPs) <b>26</b>, and a plurality of silver paste points uniformly positioned in the non-display area <b>14</b>. In the viewpoint of structure, the LCD <b>10</b> comprises a lower substrate <b>22</b>, an upper substrate <b>24</b>, and a plurality of liquid crystal molecules (not shown) filled between the lower substrate <b>22</b> and the upper substrate <b>24</b>. The upper surface of the lower substrate <b>22</b> contains the data lines <b>16</b>, the scan lines <b>18</b>, the TCPs <b>26</b> (in the non-display area <b>14</b>), and the TFTs (not shown). Each data line <b>16</b> and scan line <b>18</b> are electrically connected to their corresponding TCPs <b>26</b> for transmitting signals to the lower substrate <b>22</b> so that the LCD <b>10</b> can show an image. Each of the TFTs is positioned in an intersection of the data lines <b>16</b> and the scan lines <b>18</b> as a switch element of the pixel <b>20</b>. The lower substrate <b>22</b> further contains a plurality of pixel electrodes <b>28</b> formed by a transparent conductive material layer electrically connected to the TFTs, and an alignment film (not shown) covering the TFTs and the pixel electrodes <b>28</b> for aligning the arranging direction of the liquid crystal molecules.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the bottom surface of the upper substrate <b>24</b> contains a plurality of black matrixes <b>32</b>, a plurality of color filters <b>34</b>, a transparent conductive material layer as a counter electrode <b>36</b> of the LCD <b>10</b>, and a plurality of photo spacers <b>38</b>. There are three kinds of color filters <b>34</b>: red color filters <b>34</b><i>a</i>, green color filters <b>34</b><i>b</i>, and blue color filters <b>34</b><i>c</i>. Each of the pixels <b>20</b> comprises all three kinds of the color filters <b>34</b>. The black matrixes <b>32</b> are set on the border between each of the color filters <b>34</b> and the upper substrate <b>24</b>. The counter electrode <b>36</b> covers over the surface of the color filters <b>34</b> to provide a voltage for the operation of the LCD <b>10</b>. The photo spacers <b>38</b> are transparent or nontransparent minute columns, and they are used for replacing the spacers in the conventional LCD. The distribution density of the photo spacers <b>38</b> varies according to different manufacturing designs. The main consideration of the design of the distribution density is to make the photo spacers <b>38</b> arrange uniformly in the whole plane of the LCD <b>10</b> to support the cell gap between the upper substrate <b>24</b> and the lower substrate <b>22</b>, and maintain the thickness of the cell gap. The process of fabricating the LCD <b>10</b> according to the prior art is to form the photo spacer <b>38</b> on the counter electrode <b>36</b> by lithography process after depositing the counter electrode <b>36</b> on the bottom surface of the upper substrate <b>24</b>. Besides, the bottom surface of the upper substrate <b>24</b> can further comprise an alignment film covering the surface of the counter electrode <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The driving method of the conventional LCD <b>10</b> is described as follows. When showing an image, the counter electrode <b>36</b> provides a stable common voltage. And the TCPs <b>26</b> on the non-display area <b>14</b> transmits data signals to the data lines <b>16</b> to provide pixel voltages to each pixel electrode <b>28</b> through the TFT in each of the pixels <b>20</b>, and then the electric field between the common voltage and the pixel voltage in each pixel affects the liquid crystal molecules in the pixel to turn to a certain direction so that a certain amount of light beams are allowed to pass through the liquid crystal material layer to display an image on the LCD <b>10</b>. Therefore having a stable common voltage or stable pixel voltages is one of the key points of the LCD <b>10</b> for presenting a high quality image.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">According to the conventional method for providing the common voltage, the common voltage is transmitted by wires to the lower substrate <b>22</b>, and then to the counter electrode <b>36</b> of the upper substrate <b>24</b> by the silver paste points to diffuse the common voltage to the whole plane of the LCD <b>10</b> to make the LCD <b>10</b> have a same common voltage. However, the counter electrode <b>36</b> of the LCD <b>10</b> according to the prior art is usually composed of indium tin oxide (ITO), which has a high impedance of about 90Ω per unit area. Furthermore, silver paste points for transmitting the common voltage are only positioned in the periphery of the LCD <b>10</b> (in the non-display area <b>14</b>). Therefore as the common voltage is transmitted through the silver paste points and the counter electrode <b>36</b> in the periphery portion of the LCD <b>10</b> to the counter electrode <b>36</b> in the middle portion of the LCD <b>10</b>, the common voltage will have a voltage drop because of the high impedance of the counter electrode <b>36</b> composed of ITO, especially when the LCD <b>10</b> is a large-size LCD. When the size of the LCD <b>10</b> is large, the voltage drop problem will be more serious so that the common voltage of the upper substrate <b>24</b> will be so non-uniform that the LCD <b>10</b> cannot accurately maintain the turning directions of the liquid crystal molecules. Thus the LCD <b>10</b> will fail to present the best images. As a result, to provide a LCD with a uniform common voltage and the method thereof is still an important issue in LCD manufacturing and industry.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">It is therefore a primary objective of the claimed invention to provide a LCD with a uniform common voltage and a method thereof to solve the above-mentioned problem.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to the claimed invention, a method for fabricating a LCD with a uniform common voltage is provided. The method comprising: providing a lower substrate; forming a plurality of scan lines and a plurality of data lines on an upper surface of the lower substrate, wherein the scan lines are arranged perpendicular to the data lines to form a pixel matrix comprising a plurality of pixels; then forming a plurality of common electrodes for transmitting a common voltage and a plurality of common electrode pads electrically connected to the common electrodes on the lower substrate; providing an upper substrate; forming a plurality of photo spacers on the bottom surface of the upper substrate to make each of the photo spacers correspond to one of the common electrode pads; forming a conductive material layer on the bottom surface of the upper substrate to make the conductive material layer cover the surface of the photo spacers; combining the upper substrate and the lower substrate face to face by using the photo spacers to support the space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate and electrically connecting the conductive material layer covering the surface of each of the photo spacers to the common electrode pads corresponding to each of the photo spacers; and filling a plurality of liquid crystal molecules in the space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate and sealing the space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">It is an advantage of the claimed invention that the photo spacers are first formed on the upper substrate of the LCD, then the conductive material layer is formed on the surface of the photo spacer for electrically connecting the conductive material layer directly to the common electrode pads of the lower substrate and the common electrodes, so that the common voltage can be transmitted from the common electrodes on the lower substrate directly to the conductive material layer covering photo spacer on the upper substrate. Furthermore, since the photo spacers are uniformly arranged on the whole plane of the LCD, the conductive material layer can have a uniform common voltage. Therefore the claimed invention can effectively solve the problem in the prior art that the common voltage is transmitted only by the silver paste points in the non-display area to the periphery portion of the conductive material layer of the upper substrate but with a voltage drop results in the conventional LCD panel having an non-uniform common voltage because of the high impedance of the conductive material layer.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">These and other objectives of the present invention will no doubt become obvious to those of ordinary skill in the art after reading the following detailed description of the preferred embodiment that is illustrated in the various figures and drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of a LCD according to the prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a section view of the structure of the LCD shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic diagram of a LCD according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a section view of the structure of the LCD shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flow diagram of a method for fabricating a LCD with a uniform common voltage according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic diagram of a LCD <b>50</b> according to the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a section view of the structure of the LCD <b>50</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The present invention LCD <b>50</b> with a uniform common voltage comprises a lower substrate <b>52</b>, an upper substrate <b>54</b> positioned on the lower substrate oppositely, and a plurality of liquid crystal molecules (not shown) filled between the lower substrate <b>52</b> and the upper substrate <b>54</b>. The lower substrate <b>52</b> of the LCD <b>50</b> defines a display area <b>56</b> and a non-display area <b>58</b>. The lower substrate <b>52</b> has a plurality of scan lines <b>60</b>, a plurality of data lines <b>62</b>, a plurality of pixels <b>64</b> defined by the scan lines <b>60</b> and the data lines <b>62</b> with intersection in the display area <b>56</b>, a plurality of TFTs (not shown) positioned in each of the pixels <b>64</b>, a plurality of common electrodes <b>66</b>, a plurality of common electrode pads <b>68</b>, and an alignment film <b>80</b> thereon. The common electrodes <b>66</b> and the common electrode pads <b>68</b> are composed of a metal material with a high conductivity, such as aluminum.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, on the bottom surface of the upper substrate <b>54</b> contains a plurality of photo spacers <b>70</b> and a conductive material layer <b>72</b> covering the photo spacers <b>70</b>. The photo spacers <b>70</b> are used for maintaining the cell gap between the upper substrate <b>54</b> and the lower substrate <b>52</b>. And the photo spacers <b>70</b> are arranged uniformly on the surface of the upper substrate <b>54</b> in the display area <b>56</b>. For example, each of the pixels <b>20</b> contains a photo spacer <b>70</b>. The conductive material layer <b>72</b> is used as a counter electrode of the LCD <b>50</b> similar to the counter electrode of a conventional LCD for supplying a stable common voltage on the whole plane of the surface of the upper substrate <b>54</b> to ensure the effect of the turning performance of the liquid crystal molecules. The upper substrate <b>54</b> further comprises a plurality of color filters <b>74</b>, a plurality of black matrixes <b>76</b>, and an alignment film (not shown), wherein the color filters <b>74</b> contains red color filters <b>74</b><i>a</i>, green color filters <b>74</b><i>b</i>, and blue color filters <b>74</b><i>c</i>. Each of the pixels <b>64</b> comprises a red color filter <b>74</b><i>a</i>, a green color filter <b>74</b><i>b</i>, and a blue color filter <b>74</b><i>c</i>. The black matrixes <b>76</b> are set on the border between each of the color filters <b>74</b> and the upper substrate <b>54</b> to prevent the color from being mixed up and to raise the contrast of the LCD <b>50</b>. The present invention LCD <b>50</b> further comprises two polarizers (not shown) on the upper surface of the upper substrate <b>54</b> and the bottom surface of the lower substrate <b>52</b> respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Since the conductive material layer <b>72</b> covering the photo spacers <b>70</b> corresponding to the common electrode pads <b>68</b> are electrically connected to the common electrode pads <b>68</b>, and the common electrode pads <b>68</b> are arranged uniformly in the display area <b>56</b>, thus the conductive material layer <b>72</b> covering the photo spacers <b>70</b> are electrically connected to the common electrodes <b>66</b>. Therefore the common voltage from the common electrodes <b>66</b> can be transmitted to the conductive material layer <b>72</b> covering the photo spacers <b>70</b> directly. In another aspect for the consideration to the circuit arrangement of the lower substrate, some portions of the common electrodes <b>66</b> can serve as the common electrode pads <b>68</b>. Therefore the conductive material layer <b>72</b> on the photo spacers <b>70</b> are directly electrically connected to each of the common electrodes <b>66</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">It should be noticed that the present invention method could be applied to other LCD products, for example, a LCD with the color filter on a TFT (COT) structure or with the color filters directly on the substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, which is a flow diagram of a method for fabricating a LCD with a uniform common voltage according to the present invention. The method comprises providing a lower substrate; forming a plurality of scan lines, a plurality of common electrodes for transmitting a common voltage, and a plurality of common electrode pads electrically connected to the common electrodes on the upper surface of the lower substrate; and then forming a plurality of data lines, a plurality of pixel electrodes, and electrical elements, such as TFTs, wherein the data lines are arranged perpendicular to the scan lines to form a plurality of pixels. The present invention method also comprises providing an upper substrate, forming a plurality of photo spacers corresponding to the common electrode pads of the lower substrate on the bottom surface of the upper substrate, and then forming a conductive material layer on the surface of the photo spacers. The present invention method further comprises combining the upper substrate and the lower substrate face to face by using the photo spacers on the bottom surface of the upper substrate to support the space between the two substrates, meanwhile electrically connecting the conductive material layer covering the photo spacers to each of the common electrode pads corresponding to each of the photo spacers; filling liquid crystal molecules between the substrates; and finally sealing the space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate. The present invention also comprises forming a plurality of color filters, two alignment films, and two polarizers with 90 degree differences on the surface of the upper substrate or the lower substrate, which are technologies known by those skill in the art, and thus more detailed information is not needed.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In contrast to the prior art, the present invention LCD uses the common electrodes on the lower substrate to transmit the common voltage to reach the goal of making the LCD have a uniform common voltage. The common electrodes on the surface of the lower substrate can be formed by a material with low impedance. In the embodiment of the present invention, the common electrodes are formed by aluminum, which has an impedance of 3-4Ω per unit area. The process of forming the common electrodes can be performed together with the scan lines by a same photo-etching-process (PEP), so that the common voltage can be transmitted to the conductive material layer on the surface of each of the photo spacers effectively, thus the common voltage on the surface of the upper substrate is uniform. As a result, the display performance and quality of the present invention LCD can be improved substantially. When applying the present invention, no new complicated processes are needed, and the present invention can be applied to the fabrication of a LCD with a large size to raise the yield rate of product.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Those skilled in the art will readily observe that numerous modifications and alterations of the device may be made while retaining the teachings of the invention. Accordingly, the above disclosure should be construed as limited only by the metes and bounds of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for fabricating a liquid crystal display (LCD) with a uniform common voltage, the method comprising:
<claim-text>providing a lower substrate having a display area and a non-display area;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a plurality of scan lines, a plurality of common electrodes, and a plurality of common electrode pads on an upper surface of the lower substrate simultaneously, wherein the common electrodes are adapted to transmit a common voltage and are positioned at the same plane as a plane where the common electrode pads are positioned on the lower substrate, and the common electrode pads are electrically connected to the common electrodes;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a plurality of data lines on the upper surface of the lower substrate, wherein the data lines are arranged substantially perpendicular to the scan lines to form a pixel matrix in the display area, the pixel matrix comprising a plurality of pixels;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing an upper substrate having a plurality of color filters, and black matrices disposed between adjacent color filters, the black matrices being covered by the color filters, and each color filter having a lower surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a plurality of photo spacers on the upper substrate, each photo spacer being in direct contact with the lower surfaces of adjacent color filters, and corresponding to one of the black matrices and one of the common electrode pads on the lower substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a conductive material layer on the upper substrate and covering the surface of the photo spacers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>combining the upper substrate and the lower substrate face to face by the photo spacers to support a space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate, and electrically connecting the conductive material layer covering the surface of each of the photo spacers to the common electrode pads corresponding to each of the photo spacers; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>filling a plurality of liquid crystal molecules in the space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate, and sealing the space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising forming a plurality of thin film transistors (TFTs) on the upper surface of the lower substrate, wherein the TFTs are positioned on each intersection of the scan lines and the data lines as switching elements of the pixels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the lower substrate further comprises an alignment film having a plurality of openings disposed on the common electrodes, and the dimension of each photo spacer plus the dimension of the conductive material layer covering the photo spacer substantially equal to the dimension of each opening so that the alignment film is in contact with the conductive material layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the color filters comprise red color filters, green color filters, and blue color filters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising forming a polarizer on a bottom surface of the lower substrate and forming a polarizer on an upper surface of the upper substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each of the pixels contains one of the photo spacers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the conductive material layer is a transparent indium tin oxide (ITO) layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A LCD with a uniform common voltage, the LCD comprising:
<claim-text>a lower substrate having a display area and a non-display area on an upper surface thereof the lower substrate comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of scan lines and a plurality of data lines, wherein the data lines are arranged substantially perpendicular to the scan lines to form a pixel matrix in the display area, the pixel matrix comprising a plurality of pixels;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of common electrodes adapted to transmit a common voltage; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of common electrode pads electrically connected to the common electrodes, the common electrode pads and the common electrodes are positioned at a same plane on the lower substrate;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>an upper substrate positioned on the lower substrate oppositely, the upper substrate comprising:
<claim-text>a plurality of color filters, and black matrices disposed between adjacent color filters, the black matrices being covered by the color filters, and each color filter having a lower surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of photo spacers positioned on the upper substrate for supporting a space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate, wherein each of the photo spacers is in direct contact with the lower surfaces of adjacent color filters and corresponding to one of the black matrices and one of the common electrode pads of the lower substrate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a conductive material layer positioned on the upper substrate covering the photo spacers, wherein the conductive material layer covering the photo spacers is connected to each of the common electrode pads corresponding to each of the photo spacers; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of liquid crystal molecules filled in the space between the upper substrate and the lower substrate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The LCD of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the lower substrate further  comprises a plurality of TFTs positioned on each intersection of the scan lines and the data lines as switching elements of the pixels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The LCD of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the lower substrate further comprises an alignment film having a plurality of openings disposed on the common electrodes, and the dimension of each photo spacer plus the dimension of the conductive material layer covering the photo spacer substantially equal to the dimension of each opening so that the alignment film is in contact with the conductive material layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The LCD of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the color filters comprise red color filters, green color filters, and blue color filters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The LCD of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> further comprising a polarizer positioned on the upper surface of the upper substrate and a polarizer positioned on the bottom surface of the lower substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The LCD of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein each of the pixels contains one of the photo spacers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The LCD of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the conductive material layer is a transparent ITO layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
