<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296530-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296530</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11311760</doc-number>
<date>20051212</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>163</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>8</main-group>
<subgroup>41</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114322</main-classification>
<further-classification>114 51</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Unmanned system for underwater object inspection, identification and/or neutralization</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3880103</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Talkington</name>
<date>19750400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>405185</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4010619</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hightower et al.</name>
<date>19770300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>405191</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5235931</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nadolink</name>
<date>19930800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>114321</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114 51</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114321</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114322</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114258</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bernstein</last-name>
<first-name>Charles</first-name>
<address>
<city>Panama City</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Dudinsky</last-name>
<first-name>John</first-name>
<address>
<city>Panama City</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Moser</last-name>
<first-name>Paul</first-name>
<address>
<city>Panama City</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kucik</last-name>
<first-name>Daniel</first-name>
<address>
<city>Panama City</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Freeman</last-name>
<first-name>Doug</first-name>
<address>
<city>Panama City</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="006" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jennings</last-name>
<first-name>David</first-name>
<address>
<city>Panama City</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Shepherd</last-name>
<first-name>James T.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>United States of America as represented by the Secretary of the Navy</orgname>
<role>06</role>
<address>
<city>Washington</city>
<state>DC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Sotelo</last-name>
<first-name>Jesús D</first-name>
<department>3617</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An unmanned system performs inspection, identification and/or neutralization of underwater objects. An unmanned vehicle that operates at a water's surface stows underwater crawling and/or swimming vehicles that can operate underneath a water's surface. A winch associated with each robotic vehicle is mounted on the unmanned vehicle. An electro-mechanical tether electrically and mechanically couples a corresponding robotic vehicle to the unmanned vehicle, and is mechanically coupled to a corresponding winch for control of the paying out and reeling in thereof.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="158.58mm" wi="170.35mm" file="US07296530-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="235.12mm" wi="170.52mm" file="US07296530-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="246.97mm" wi="173.14mm" file="US07296530-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="146.56mm" wi="149.35mm" file="US07296530-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?GOVINT description="Government Interest" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">ORIGIN OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention described herein was made in the performance of official duties by an employee of the Department of the Navy and may be manufactured, used, licensed by or for the Government for any governmental purpose without payment of any royalties thereon.</p>
<?GOVINT description="Government Interest" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention relates generally to the inspection, identification and neutralization of underwater objects, and more particularly to an unmanned system for underwater object inspection, identification and/or neutralization.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Current Navy methods for reacquisition, identification and neutralization (RIN) of mines in very shallow water (i.e., 10-40 feet) and surf zone (i.e., 0-10 feet) utilize divers and/or marine mammals (e.g., dolphins and sea lions) to relocate contacts found by mine search sonars and to deploy countercharges to destroy the mines. These approaches risk personnel who must enter the minefields and endanger themselves by being visible on the surface from enemy shores, and by having to work around mines while in moving currents and waves.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Recently, unmanned vehicles have been used to search for and neutralize mines. Unmanned underwater vehicles (UUVs) that swim in the water column are currently in the fleet for performing search, classify and mapping (SCM) missions. These swimming vehicles are ideal for carrying side-scan sonar to perform wide area reconnaissance of minefields. They can efficiently scan large areas and map mine-like sonar contacts. Under ideal conditions, UUVs can identify sonar contacts using cameras or specialized imaging sonars. However, it is difficult for UUVs to place countercharges on the mines or to identify them under poor optical or acoustic conditions. In addition, UUVs generally rely on acoustic navigation aids which must be pre-positioned within the minefield before the vehicles can function. The UUVs must be delivered near to or into the minefields by personnel in boats thereby endangering the delivery personnel.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Bottom-crawling robots (i.e., “crawlers”) provide a stable base for identifying and prosecuting mines that were contacted by a UUV and are thus ideal for performing the RIN mission. A crawling robot can approach an object and apply sensors (e.g., image the object) at contact range. The natural stability of the crawler and the fact that it moves along the bottom offers the opportunity to exploit new target features for identification of mine-like contacts. The crawler can neutralize mines easily by dropping a countercharge or by serving as a sacrificial, mobile countercharge.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">However, crawlers cannot transit long distances. Further, they can easily become stuck while transiting over rough bottoms. Still further, because of their limited energy, personal in boats must deliver the crawlers into or close to the minefields. For these reasons, crawlers have been considered only for limited use for performing mine neutralization missions.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Vehicles that can both swim and crawl have limited payload, speed, and range capabilities. The limitations derive mostly from the physics of buoyancy since it is necessary for the vehicle to release either ballast or buoyancy material to enable it to swim or to be heavy enough to navigate along the bottom and stay in place to neutralize a mine.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Accordingly, it is an object of the present invention to provide an unmanned system that can efficiently and effectively perform one or more of inspection, identification and neutralization of underwater objects.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Other objects and advantages of the present invention will become more obvious hereinafter in the specification and drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In accordance with the present invention, an unmanned system performs inspection, identification and/or neutralization of underwater objects. At least one remotely-operated robotic vehicle is provided that can operate underneath a water's surface. Each robotic vehicle has a slave controller, electrical propulsion system, underwater sensors, and is equipped for explosive charge deployment. An unmanned vehicle that operates at a water's surface includes a mother controller, self-propulsion, navigation, wireless communication, electrical energy generation systems as well as the ability to stow each robotic vehicle. A winch associated with each robotic vehicle is mounted on the unmanned vehicle. An electro-mechanical tether electrically and mechanically couples a corresponding robotic vehicle to the unmanned vehicle. Each tether is also mechanically coupled to a corresponding winch for control of the paying out and reeling in thereof. Each tether electrically couples the unmanned vehicle's to the robotic vehicle for electrical energy and control signal transfer thereto.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will become apparent upon reference to the following description of the preferred embodiments and to the drawings, wherein corresponding reference characters indicate corresponding parts throughout the several views of the drawings and wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of the systems maintained onboard an unmanned surface vehicle in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of the systems maintained in each of the surface vehicle's hold regions;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram of the systems maintained onboard an unmanned bottom crawling vehicle transported and deployed by the unmanned surface vehicle in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of the systems maintained onboard an unmanned swimming vehicle transported and deployed by the unmanned surface vehicle in accordance with the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a plan view of multiple pontoon boat embodiment of the unmanned surface vehicle.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The present invention is an unmanned system that can be used to inspect, identify and/or neutralize a variety of underwater objects (e.g., underwater mines, unexploded ordnance, pipelines, or other underwater objects). In general, the unmanned system can deploy from a remote location and travel relatively long distances on the water, deploy one or more robotic vehicles therefrom to perform underwater operations as controlled from the water's surface, and retrieve the robotic vehicle(s) for return travel to a remote location. More specifically, the present invention includes an unmanned surface vehicle or boat that can stow one or (typically) more robotic vehicles while in transit to an area of interest, deploy and control the robotic vehicles using systems maintained on the boat, and ultimately retrieve and stow the robotic vehicles. Accordingly, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref> depict block diagrams of the boat's capabilities (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) and the capabilities of two different types of robotic vehicles (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>). By way of example, the present invention will be described for its use in the inspection, identification, and neutralization of underwater mines.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Referring first to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a boat <b>10</b> and its various functional systems are illustrated in block diagram form. Boat <b>10</b> can be realized by a variety of different designs, one of which will be described later herein. At the heart of the functional capability of boat <b>10</b> is its control, piloting and navigation computer <b>12</b> that supports and/or controls the various systems coupled thereto. Since boat <b>10</b> must be capable of relatively long-distance navigated travel on the water, a GPS antenna and receiver system <b>14</b> provide GPS location data to computer <b>12</b>. The GPS location data could be used by computer <b>12</b> to automatically implement a pre-determined navigation plan. Additionally or alternatively, the GPS location data can be provided to a communications transceiver <b>16</b> for wireless transmission over the airwaves by a communications antenna <b>18</b>. In this way, the GPS location data could be monitored at a remote location or used by an operator at a remote location to pilot boat <b>10</b> from the remote location. That is, the operator could wirelessly transmit navigation control signals to boat <b>10</b> (i.e., via antenna <b>18</b> and transceiver <b>16</b>) based on the GPS location data.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Boat <b>10</b> must be able to propel itself to and from locations of interest, and further provide operational power to the one or more robotic vehicles that it supports. Accordingly, boat <b>10</b> must be capable of generating its own mechanical and electrical power as well as operational power for its robotic vehicles. One way of achieving this is for boat <b>10</b> to have a conventional air-breathing engine/propulsion system <b>20</b> onboard, a fuel tank <b>22</b> supplying fuel to engine <b>20</b>, and a generator <b>24</b> coupled to engine/propulsion system <b>20</b>. In this way, engine/propulsion system <b>20</b> provides mechanical power for propulsion of boat <b>10</b> and for generator <b>24</b> which converts mechanical power to electrical power. A battery <b>26</b> could be coupled to generator <b>24</b> to store excess electrical power and/or to provide regulated power for those systems onboard boat <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In addition to engine/propulsion system <b>20</b>, boat <b>10</b> will be equipped with steering mechanisms <b>30</b> controlled by computer <b>12</b>. Such mechanisms <b>30</b> would typically include both macro steering mechanisms <b>30</b>A (e.g., rudders) and micro steering mechanisms <b>30</b>B (e.g., side thrusters). Macro steering control is implemented when boat <b>10</b> is traveling to and from an area of interest. Micro steering control is implemented when boat <b>10</b> is “on station” at an area of interest with its robotic vehicle(s) deployed in the water as will be explained further below.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As previously mentioned, boat <b>10</b> is equipped to stow one or more robotic vehicles during travel to and from an area of interest. The robotic vehicles can be “bottom crawling” vehicles capable of traversing the bottom of a body of water, and/or “swimming vehicles” capable of controlled movement under the water's surface. Accordingly, boat <b>10</b> has hold region(s) <b>40</b>, each of which can stow, deploy and retrieve one robotic vehicle. Control signals for hold regions <b>40</b> are provided by computer <b>12</b> while electrical power is supplied by one or both of generator <b>24</b> and battery <b>26</b>. Since each hold region <b>40</b> will be similarly equipped, only one such hold region <b>40</b> will be described with the aid of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, an interface <b>42</b> in hold region <b>40</b> receives both control signals and electrical power as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. An electro-mechanical tether <b>44</b> is coupled on one end thereof to interface <b>42</b> and is coiled about a winch <b>46</b>. The other end of tether <b>44</b> is coupled to a robotic vehicle <b>48</b>. Upon reaching an area of interest, boat <b>10</b> can deploy robotic vehicle <b>48</b> by paying out tether <b>44</b> using winch <b>46</b>, power and control robotic vehicle <b>48</b> during its mission, and then reel in tether <b>44</b> using winch <b>46</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Robotic vehicle <b>48</b> can be either a bottom crawling or swimming vehicle. The drive system associated with a bottom crawling vehicle will be different from that of a swimming vehicle. Accordingly, the systems maintained onboard a (robotic) bottom crawling vehicle and swimming vehicle will be explained with the aid of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a bottom crawling vehicle <b>50</b> has an interface <b>52</b> to which tether <b>44</b> is coupled. Electrical power provided via tether <b>44</b> is directed to power converters/regulators <b>54</b> which, in turn, provides the necessary electrical power for the systems onboard vehicle <b>50</b>. Operational and navigation control signals can be provided by computer <b>12</b> (onboard boat <b>10</b>) and directed to a control computer <b>56</b>. In this scenario, computer <b>12</b> functions as a “mother controller” to computer <b>56</b> while computer <b>56</b> functions as a “slave controller” to computer <b>12</b>. Optionally, onboard navigation systems <b>58</b> (e.g., long baseline navigation, local navigation sensors such as gyros, inclinometers, odometers, compass, etc.) can be provided and coupled to computer <b>56</b> to supplement the navigation control received from boat <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Computer <b>56</b> provides local control signal distribution to an electrically-driven traction drive system <b>60</b>, an explosive charge control system <b>62</b>, and a sensing system <b>64</b>. For controlled movement on the water's bottom, traction drive system <b>60</b> would typically include individually-controllable left and right traction drives <b>60</b>A and <b>60</b>B. A variety of such systems are known in the art of ground traversing vehicles. Sensing system <b>64</b> would typically include one or more sonar sensors <b>64</b>A and a video camera <b>64</b>B. Outputs from sensor system <b>64</b> are provided to computer <b>56</b> for use thereby or for ultimate wireless transmission by boat <b>10</b> to a remote operator.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Once bottom crawling vehicle <b>50</b> is on the sea floor, sensing system <b>64</b> is activated/used to (i) acquire/reacquire an object of interest, and (ii) provide inspection information (e.g., sonar data, video data) to one or more of computer <b>56</b>, computer <b>12</b> or a remotely-located operator so that an object of interest can be identified. If it is determined that the identified object should be neutralized, the appropriate control signals are issued to explosive charge control system <b>62</b> which maintains one or more explosive charge(s) <b>62</b>A. Explosive charges <b>62</b>A could be deployed from vehicle <b>50</b> by means of a release mechanism <b>62</b>B coupled to explosive charges <b>62</b>A. Another option would be for some or all of vehicle <b>50</b> to be left on the sea floor with charges <b>62</b>A. In this case, interface <b>52</b> could include a disconnection mechanism <b>52</b>A so that tether <b>44</b> can be uncoupled from vehicle <b>50</b> if vehicle <b>50</b> is to be made expendable. Disconnection mechanism <b>52</b>A can be actuated via a control signal received from boat <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a (robotic) swimming vehicle <b>70</b> would be equipped in a fashion similar to bottom crawling vehicle <b>50</b>. Accordingly, common reference numerals have been used for those systems that would be identical or nearly identical as would be understood by one of ordinary skill in the art. In contrast, swimming vehicle <b>70</b> has an electrically-driven propulsion system <b>80</b> which could be realized by any conventional underwater vehicle propulsion system. Once on station, swimming vehicle <b>70</b> would be able to perform the same functions as bottom crawling vehicle <b>50</b> albeit in the water depths.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">By way of example, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates a design for the present invention's surface vehicle that would be useful for carrying out the functions of the present invention. Specifically, a pontoon boat <b>100</b> has two or more pontoons <b>102</b> (e.g., three are illustrated) that provide for floatation thereof on the water's surface. In general, pontoon boats have a low profile which is advantageous for covert operations. A deck structure <b>104</b> is used to couple pontoons <b>102</b> to one another and is used to define hold regions <b>40</b> between pontoons <b>102</b>. In this way, vehicles <b>50</b> and/or <b>70</b> are stowed between pontoons <b>102</b> during travel to and from an area of interest.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The advantages of the present invention are numerous. The system is entirely unmanned thereby insuring that all operational personnel remain safe. By making multiple robotic crawling and swimming vehicles available for a given mission, the system can adapt to a wide variety of changing mission scenarios and operational environments.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Although the invention has been described relative to a specific embodiment thereof, there are numerous variations and modifications that will be readily apparent to those skilled in the art in light of the above teachings. It is therefore to be understood that, within the scope of the appended claims, the invention may be practiced other than as specifically described.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed as new and desired to be secured by Letters Patent of the United States is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An unmanned system for performing one or more of inspection, identification and neutralization of underwater objects, comprising:
<claim-text>at least one remotely-operated robotic vehicle for operation underneath a water's surface, each said robotic vehicle having a slave controller, electrical propulsion means, underwater sensing means and explosive charge deploying means;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an unmanned vehicle for operation at a water's surface, said unmanned vehicle having a mother controller, self-propulsion means, navigation means, wireless communication means, electrical energy generation means and means for stowing each said robotic vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one winch mounted on said unmanned vehicle, each said winch being associated with one said robotic vehicle; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electro-mechanical tether for electrically and mechanically coupling a corresponding one said robotic vehicle to said unmanned vehicle, each said tether mechanically coupled to a corresponding one said winch for control of the paying out and reeling in thereof, each said tether electrically coupling said mother controller to said slave controller and electrically coupling said electrical energy generation means to said electrical propulsion means.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least one robotic vehicle comprises a plurality of vehicles that can traverse the sea bottom.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least one robotic vehicle comprises a plurality of swimming vehicles.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least one robotic vehicle comprises:
<claim-text>at least one vehicle that can traverse the sea bottom; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one swimming vehicle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said unmanned vehicle has a multiple pontoon hull, and wherein each said robotic vehicle is stowed within said multiple pontoon hull when said tether associated therewith is reeled in on said winch associated therewith.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said navigation means includes a GPS receiver system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said underwater sensing means includes at least one sonar sensor and a video camera.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said self-propulsion means is coupled to and supplies mechanical power for said electrical energy generation means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An unmanned system for performing one or more of inspection, identification and neutralization of underwater objects, comprising:
<claim-text>at least one first type of vehicle having explosive charges maintained thereon, each of said first type of vehicle equipped for traveling on the bottom of a body of water;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one second type of vehicle having explosive charges maintained thereon, each of said second type of vehicle equipped for swimming in a body of water under the surface thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an unmanned boat having multiple pontoons for the floatation thereof, said boat equipped for navigated travel on water and for control of each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electro-mechanical tethering system mounted on said boat for (i) controlling the individual paying out of each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle from between said pontoons of said boat, (ii) controlling the individual reeling in of each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle to stowed positions between said pontoons of said boat, and (iii) electrically coupling said boat to each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle for the supply of electrical power and control signals thereto.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said boat includes:
<claim-text>a GPS receiver system for determining the location of said boat; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a wireless communication system coupled to said GPS receiver system for transmitting the location of said boat and for receiving navigation control signals for said boat from a remote location.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said boat includes:
<claim-text>a self-propulsion system that generates mechanical power for said navigated travel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a generator system coupled to said self-propulsion system for converting a portion of said mechanical power to said electrical power supplied to each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An unmanned system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle includes means for releasing said explosive charges maintained thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle includes means for disconnecting from said electro-mechanical tethering system when commanded by one of said control signals received from said boat.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle includes means for sensing and imaging underwater objects.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. An unmanned system for performing one or more of inspection, identification and neutralization of underwater objects, comprising:
<claim-text>at least one first type of vehicle having explosive charges maintained thereon, each of said first type of vehicle equipped for traveling on the bottom of a body of water;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one second type of vehicle having explosive charges maintained thereon, each of said second type of vehicle equipped for swimming in a body of water under the surface thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an unmanned boat having multiple pontoons for the floatation thereof, said boat equipped for navigated travel on water and for control of each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a GPS receiver system mounted on said boat for determining the location of said boat;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a wireless communication system mounted on said boat and coupled to said GPS receiver system for transmitting the location of said boat and for receiving navigation control signals for said boat from a remote location;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a self-propulsion system mounted on said boat that generates mechanical power for said navigated travel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a generator system mounted on said boat and coupled to said self-propulsion system for converting a portion of said mechanical power to electrical power; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electro-mechanical tethering system mounted on said boat for (i) controlling the individual paying out of each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle from between said pontoons of said boat, (ii) controlling the individual reeling in of each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle to stowed positions between said pontoons of said boat, and (iii) electrically coupling said boat to each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle for the supply of said electrical power and control signals thereto.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. An unmanned system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle includes means for releasing said explosive charges maintained thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle includes means for disconnecting from said electro-mechanical tethering system when commanded by one of said control signals received from said boat.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. An unmanned system as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein each of said first type of vehicle and said second type of vehicle includes means for sensing and imaging underwater objects. </claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
