<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298340-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298340</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11499558</doc-number>
<date>20060804</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-230298</doc-number>
<date>20050809</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>Q</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>24</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>343702</main-classification>
<further-classification>343700 MS</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Antenna device and radio apparatus capable of multiband operation</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0246179</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chen et al.</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>343700 MS</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0050007</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Min</name>
<date>20060300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>343876</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0152419</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Sato et al.</name>
<date>20060700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>343702</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0262015</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Thornell-Pers et al.</name>
<date>20061100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>343702</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-136019</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-46318</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-40596</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Sekine, S. and Shoki, H., “Characteristics of T-type Monopole Antenna with Parallel Resonance Mode”, IEICEJ, Trans. vol. J86-B, No. 2, pp. 200-208, Feb. 2003 (in Japanese).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>343702</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>343700 MS</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>343876</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>12</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>24</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070035458</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070215</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ohba</last-name>
<first-name>Isao</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Frishauf, Holtz, Goodman &amp; Chick, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Kabushiki Kaisha Toshiba</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Hoang V.</first-name>
<department>2821</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An antenna device and a radio apparatus are provided. The antenna device is configured to be coupled to a feeding point of the radio apparatus. The antenna device has a first antenna element and a second antenna element. The first antenna element is configured to be an unbalanced-fed antenna fed at the feeding point to resonate at a first frequency. The second antenna element is configured to be a monopole antenna having an open end and to be fed at the feeding point. The first antenna element and the second antenna element have a common portion from the feeding point to a branching point. The second antenna element is configured to be ungrounded in a first state to resonate at a second frequency lower than the first frequency and to be grounded in a second state at a switch point between the branching point and the open end.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="101.94mm" wi="107.10mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="235.63mm" wi="130.13mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="249.26mm" wi="144.53mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="212.34mm" wi="143.93mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="249.09mm" wi="130.13mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="240.88mm" wi="144.44mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="189.65mm" wi="123.27mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="201.08mm" wi="123.11mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="208.11mm" wi="116.16mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="205.57mm" wi="116.16mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="172.97mm" wi="156.38mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="237.57mm" wi="136.91mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="241.22mm" wi="155.19mm" file="US07298340-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is based upon and claims the benefit of priority from the prior Japanese Patent Application No. 2005-230298 filed on Aug. 9, 2006; the entire contents of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an antenna device and a radio communication apparatus capable of multiband operation, and in particular to those adapted for mobile use.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">As radio apparatus like mobile phones, etc. come into wide use and have a wider range of application, antennas having a broader frequency range are required more than ever for radio apparatus. For instance, it is thought that an ultra-high frequency (UHF) band as broad as a couple of hundred megahertz (MHz) is required for receiving terrestrial digital television broadcast. In order that a radio apparatus using a single antenna for downsizing is adapted for two or more standards of wireless local area networks (WLAN) of different frequencies, the antenna has to cover both 2.4 gigahertz (GHz) and 5.2 GHz bands.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A multi-resonant antenna applicable to WLANs is disclosed in Japanese Patent Publication (Kokai), No. 2003-46318. The multi-resonant antenna includes an antenna element formed by a linear or band-shaped conductor one end of which is fed at a feeding point on and surrounded by a ground plane and another end of which is grounded on the ground plane. The antenna element is loaded with an impedance element so that the multi-resonant antenna resonates at a frequency determined by a length of the linear or band-shaped conductor and resonates at another frequency determined by a value of the impedance element.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">An antenna including an antenna element formed by a linear or plate-shaped conductor loaded with a reactance element for multi-resonance is disclosed in Japanese Patent Publication (Kokai), No.2004-40596, and is called here a reactance-loaded antenna. The antenna element of the reactance-loaded antenna is divided by the reactance element by a ratio that determines a resonant frequency of the reactance-loaded antenna.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A majority of radio apparatus adopt built-in antennas these days. In order to select a type of built-in antennas, it is necessary to examine candidates of built-in antennas from viewpoints of size, inefficiency of radiation caused by return currents, necessity of balance-to-unbalance transformation, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">As one of the candidates that may somehow satisfy the necessity from the above viewpoints, known is a half-wavelength T-type monopole antenna. One example of that type of antenna is disclosed in:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0008">Sekine, S. and Shoki, H., “Characteristics of T-type monopole antenna with parallel resonance mode”, IEICEJ. Trans. Vol. J86-B, No. 2, pp. 200-208, February 2003 (in Japanese).</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0009">The above example of the T-type monopole antenna is configured that lengths of a left half and a right half thereof are unequal so that the antenna may be resonant in a parallel resonance mode and may cope with both downsizing and efficiency of radiation by increasing input impedance.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0010">The multi-resonant antenna or the reactance-loaded antenna described above may be multi-resonant by being loaded with a reactance element located at a middle portion of the antenna element, i.e., somewhere between both ends of the antenna element. In a case where a resonant frequency needs to be changed or tuned, however, a value of the reactance has to be adjusted. Hence, there is a problem that the above antennas may not be suitable for an application that needs a significant change of the resonant frequency, e.g., WLANs.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0011">The parallel resonance mode of the T-type monopole antenna described above may be effective depending on a configuration of radio apparatus. The T-type monopole antenna, however, may not be suitable for a radio apparatus a feeder system of which is designed to match the input impedance of the antenna at a series resonant frequency of the antenna, as the increase of the input impedance in the parallel resonant mode is likely to cause a mismatch.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0012">Accordingly, an advantage of the present invention is that a resonant frequency of an antenna device may be significantly changed while causing little mismatch of the antenna's input impedance.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0013">To achieve the above advantage, one aspect of the present invention is to provide an antenna device and a radio apparatus capable of multiband operation. The antenna device is configured to be coupled to a feeding point of the radio apparatus. The antenna device has a first antenna element and a second antenna element. The first antenna element is configured to be an unbalanced-fed antenna fed at the feeding point to resonate at a first frequency. The second antenna element is configured to be a monopole antenna having an open end and to be fed at the feeding point. The first antenna element and the second antenna element have a common portion from the feeding point to a branching point. The second antenna element is configured to be ungrounded in a first state to resonate at a second frequency lower than the first frequency and to be grounded in a second state at a switch point between the branching point and the open end.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus and an antenna device of a first embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows how to represent a length of each portion and a total length of each of antenna elements included in the antenna device of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is equivalent to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> except for a state of a switch included in the antenna device of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a condition of a simulation for examining an effect of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a simulated characteristic of a voltage standing wave ratio (VSWR) over a frequency range of the antenna device of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is equivalent to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> except that an extra VSWR characteristic after a change of a switch point is added.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus and an antenna device of a second embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows how to represent a length of each portion and a total length of each of antenna elements included in the antenna device of the second embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows how to represent a length of each portion and a total length of each of antenna elements included in a variation of the antenna device of the second embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is equivalent to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> except for a state of a switch included in the antenna device of the second embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is equivalent to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> except for a state of a switch included in the antenna device of the second embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows a simulated VSWR characteristic over a frequency range of the antenna device of the second embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> shows a first configuration of an antenna device of a third embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> shows a second configuration of an antenna device of a third embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> shows a third configuration of an antenna device of a third embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> shows a fourth configuration of an antenna device of a third embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus of a fourth embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref> shows a configuration of a variation of the radio apparatus of a fourth embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref> shows a condition of a simulation for examining an effect of the fourth embodiment corresponding to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 20</figref> shows a condition of a simulation for examining an effect of the fourth embodiment corresponding to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 21</figref> shows a simulated VSWR characteristic over a frequency range of the antenna device of the fourth embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 22</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus and an antenna device of a fifth embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> shows a configuration of a switch included in the antenna device of the fifth embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 24</figref> shows a measured characteristic of the antenna device of the fifth embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">1. First Embodiment of the Present Invention</heading>
<p id="p-0038" num="0038">A first embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 6</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus <b>1</b>, including an antenna device, of the first embodiment. The radio apparatus <b>1</b> of the first embodiment has a case <b>10</b> indicated by a dot-and-dash line. The radio apparatus <b>1</b> has a printed board <b>11</b> and an antenna device <b>12</b> contained in the case <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0039">The antenna device <b>12</b> includes a first antenna element <b>13</b> indicated as encircled by a dashed ellipse on a right hand side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and a second antenna element <b>14</b> encircled by another dashed ellipse on a left hand side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The first antenna element <b>13</b> and the second antenna element <b>14</b> are fed in common at a feeding point <b>15</b> located on the printed board <b>11</b>. The first antenna element <b>13</b> is located near an end of the printed board <b>11</b>, and so is the second antenna element <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0040">The antenna device <b>12</b> includes a switch element <b>16</b> located at a middle location of the second antenna element <b>14</b>, i.e., somewhere between both ends of the antenna element <b>14</b> and called a switch point of the antenna device <b>12</b>. The switch element <b>16</b> has at least three terminals, <b>16</b><i>h</i>, <b>16</b><i>j </i>and <b>16</b><i>k</i>. In one state of the switch element <b>16</b>, the terminals <b>16</b><i>h </i>and <b>16</b><i>j </i>are shorted and the terminal <b>16</b><i>k </i>is open. In another state of the switch element <b>16</b>, the terminals <b>16</b><i>h </i>and <b>16</b><i>k </i>are shorted and the terminal <b>16</b><i>j </i>is open. The switch element <b>16</b> may be located on the printed board <b>11</b>, but preferably apart from a ground pattern of the printed board <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0041">The terminal <b>16</b><i>h </i>is coupled to a portion of the second antenna element coupled to the feeding point <b>15</b>. The terminal <b>16</b><i>j </i>is coupled to a portion of the second antenna element including an open end <b>17</b> of the second antenna element <b>14</b>. The terminal <b>16</b><i>k </i>is coupled to the ground pattern of the printed board <b>11</b> and is thus grounded. Due to these couplings of the terminals <b>16</b><i>h</i>, <b>16</b><i>j </i>and <b>16</b><i>k</i>, the second antenna element <b>14</b> is grounded in one state (called a grounded state), and is not grounded in another state (called an ungrounded state).</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0042">How to represent a length of each portion and a total length of the first antenna element <b>13</b> and the second antenna element <b>14</b> will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Each portion of the first antenna element <b>13</b> and the second antenna element <b>14</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a same as the corresponding one given the same reference numeral shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and its explanation is omitted. Each of small alphabet letters a to f shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> represents a length of each portion of the first antenna element <b>13</b> and the second antenna element <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0043">The first antenna element <b>13</b> has a starting portion of a length of a starting and going up from the feeding point <b>15</b>, a following portion of a length of b going right, and an end portion of a length of c going downward. The first antenna element <b>13</b> is a monopole antenna having an open end, and has a total length of a+b+c. Hence, the first antenna element <b>13</b> has a resonant frequency on which the length of a+b+c corresponds to a quarter wavelength. Here and hereafter, the term “resonant frequency” means a series resonant frequency unless otherwise noted.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0044">The second antenna element <b>14</b> has, in the ungrounded state, the starting portion of the length of a in common with the first antenna element <b>13</b>, a following portion of a length of d going left, a switch portion between the terminals <b>16</b><i>h </i>and <b>16</b><i>j </i>of the switch element <b>16</b> (the reference numeral “16” is not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) and an end portion of a length e between the terminal <b>16</b><i>j </i>and an open end <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0045">The second antenna element <b>14</b> is, in the ungrounded state, a monopole antenna having the open end <b>17</b>, and has a length of a+d+e if an electric length between the terminals <b>16</b><i>h </i>and <b>16</b><i>j </i>of the switch element <b>16</b> is neglected. Hence, the second antenna element <b>14</b> has a resonant frequency on which the length of a+d+e corresponds to a quarter wavelength in the ungrounded state. The resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>14</b> in the ungrounded state is lower than that of the first antenna element <b>13</b> if a following inequality is true, i.e., b+c&lt;d+e.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0046">A configuration of the antenna device <b>12</b> in the grounded state of the second antenna element <b>14</b> will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> that is different from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> only in the state of the switch element <b>16</b> (the reference numeral “16” is not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). Each portion or its length of the first antenna element <b>13</b> and the second antenna element <b>14</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a same as the corresponding one given the same reference numeral or the same small alphabet shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, and its explanation is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0047">In the grounded state of the second antenna element <b>14</b>, the starting portion of the length of a, the following portion of the length of d, a switch portion between the terminals <b>16</b><i>h </i>and <b>16</b><i>k </i>of the switch element <b>16</b>, and an end portion of a length of f going down from the terminal <b>16</b><i>k </i>are coupled in series one by one to form a line. The end portion of the length of f is grounded on the ground pattern of the printed board <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0048">The line formed in the grounded state of the second antenna element <b>14</b> has a length of a+d+f, if an electric length between the terminals <b>16</b><i>h </i>and <b>16</b><i>k </i>of the switch element <b>16</b> is neglected. The line formed in the grounded state has an end coupled to the feeding point <b>15</b>, and has another end that is grounded. As is known, the line formed in the grounded state performs as an antenna equivalent to a loop antenna twice as long as the line except for a value of input impedance. Hence, the line formed in the grounded state is an equivalent loop antenna having a resonant frequency on which the length of a+d+f corresponds to a half wavelength.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0049">The resonant frequency of the equivalent loop antenna is nearly twice as high as the resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>14</b> in the ungrounded state, if a following condition is true, i.e., e ≅f. The resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>14</b> may thus be changed up to twice as high as its value of the ungrounded state if the switch element <b>16</b> is switched to the grounded state, and may be changed even higher if a following condition is true, i.e., f&lt;e.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0050">An effect of the first embodiment examined by simulation will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a condition of the simulation. Each portion given a reference numeral <b>11</b> to <b>15</b> or <b>17</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a same as the corresponding one given the same reference numeral in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, though, the end portion including the open end <b>17</b> of the second antenna element <b>14</b> is further turned to go downward. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a length of each portion is indicated in millimeters (mm).</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0051">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the feeding point <b>15</b> is located at a right upper corner of the printed board <b>11</b>. The first antenna element <b>13</b> includes a portion 4 mm long going upward from the feeding point <b>15</b>, a following portion 2 mm long going right, and an ending portion 39 mm long going downward. The second antenna element <b>14</b> includes the portion going upward from the feeding point <b>15</b>, a following portion 42 mm long going left, and the ending portion 39 mm long going downward.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0052">In the simulation, there is assumed a switch element (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) corresponding to the switch element <b>16</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> to be located at a switch point-<b>1</b>, i.e., a middle location of the second antenna element <b>14</b> and 20 mm apart from the open end <b>17</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a frequency characteristic of a voltage standing wave ratio (VSWR) of the antenna device <b>12</b> simulated under the condition shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a horizontal axis represents the frequency in MHz, and a vertical axis represents the VSWR.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0053"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a solid curve and a dashed curve. The solid curve represents a VSWR characteristic in a case where the second antenna element <b>14</b> is in the ungrounded state and has a full length including the open end <b>17</b>. The dashed curve represents a VSWR characteristic in a case where the second antenna element <b>14</b> is grounded at the switch point-<b>1</b> to form equivalently a loop antenna and the portion including the open end <b>17</b> is separated.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0054">On the solid curve, i.e., the VSWR characteristic in the ungrounded state, a peak at a frequency of nearly 850 MHz is a resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>14</b> (here and hereafter, a peak that looks down is simply called a peak). On the solid curve, a peak at a frequency of nearly 1600 MHz is a resonant frequency of the first antenna element <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0055">On the dashed curve, i.e., the VSWR characteristic in the grounded state, a peak at a frequency of nearly 2300 MHz is a resonant frequency of the loop antenna equivalently formed by the second antenna element <b>14</b>. On the dashed curve, a peak at a frequency of nearly 1600 MHz is the resonant frequency of the first antenna element <b>13</b>. As the switch point-<b>1</b> is 20 mm apart from the open end <b>17</b> and the condition f&lt;e is true as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the resonant frequency of the equivalent loop antenna is more than twice as high as the resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>14</b> in the ungrounded state.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0056">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the VSWR characteristic on the dashed curve is better than that on the solid curve over a frequency range 1200 to 1600 MHz. That is because the second antenna element <b>14</b> grounded at the switch point-<b>1</b> works as a stub for the first antenna element <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0057">In the simulation, there may be assumed a switch element (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) corresponding to the switch element <b>16</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> to be located not at the switch point-<b>1</b> but at a switch point-<b>2</b>, i.e., the open end <b>17</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a horizontal axis, a vertical axis, a solid curve and a dashed curve, each of which is a same as the corresponding one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. In addition, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a dot-and-dash curve, i.e., a VSWR characteristic of the antenna device <b>12</b> simulated under the condition where the switch element is assumed to be located not at the switch point-<b>1</b> but at the switch point-<b>2</b>, and the second antenna element <b>14</b> is in the grounded state.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0058">As the switch point-<b>2</b> coincides with the open end <b>17</b>, the equivalent loop antenna formed in the grounded state has a resonant frequency that is nearly twice as high as the resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>14</b> in the ungrounded state. Depending on where the switch element <b>16</b> is located on the second antenna element <b>14</b>, a high/low relationship of the resonant frequencies may be adjusted between the second antenna element <b>13</b> and the equivalent loop antenna formed in the grounded state of the second antenna element <b>14</b>. The antenna device <b>12</b> may thus broaden its frequency characteristic as a whole.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0059">The present invention may be applied as long as the second antenna element <b>14</b> is a monopole antenna having an open end and a portion thereof may be grounded as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 3</figref>. Hence, the first antenna element <b>13</b> may not be a monopole antenna having an open end as long as being unbalanced-fed. In that case, the condition explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, i.e., b+c&lt;d+e, is replaced by a condition that a total length of the second antenna element <b>14</b> in the ungrounded state is greater than the quarter wavelength of the resonant frequency of the first antenna element <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0060">According to the first embodiment described above, a built-in antenna device of a radio apparatus may significantly change or broaden its frequency characteristic by locating a switch element at a middle location of an antenna element of the antenna device and by turning the switch element on and off.</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">2. Second Embodiment of the Present Invention</heading>
<p id="p-0061" num="0061">A second embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 to 12</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus <b>2</b>, including an antenna device, of the second embodiment. The radio apparatus <b>2</b> of the second embodiment has a case <b>20</b> indicated by a dot-and-dash line. The radio apparatus <b>2</b> has a printed board <b>21</b> and an antenna device <b>22</b> contained in the case <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0062">The antenna device <b>22</b> includes a first antenna element <b>23</b> indicated as encircled by a dashed ellipse on a right hand side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, and a second antenna element <b>24</b> on a left hand side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The first antenna element <b>23</b> and the second antenna element <b>24</b> are fed in common at a feeding point <b>25</b> located on the printed board <b>21</b>. The first antenna element <b>23</b> is located near an end of the printed board <b>21</b>, and so is the second antenna element <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0063">The antenna device <b>22</b> has a switch point <b>26</b> which is a middle location of the second antenna element <b>24</b>. The antenna device <b>22</b> includes a switch element <b>27</b> coupled to the switch point <b>26</b>. The second antenna element <b>24</b> is a monopole antenna having an open end <b>28</b> formed by a line between the feeding point <b>25</b> and the open end <b>28</b>. The switch element <b>27</b> has at least two terminals, <b>27</b><i>h </i>and <b>27</b><i>j</i>. In one state of the switch element <b>27</b>, the terminals <b>27</b><i>h </i>and <b>27</b><i>j </i>are shorted. In another state of the switch element <b>27</b>, the terminals <b>27</b><i>h </i>and <b>27</b><i>j </i>are open. The switch element <b>27</b> may be located on the printed board <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0064">The terminal <b>27</b><i>h </i>is coupled to the switch point <b>26</b>. The terminal <b>27</b><i>j </i>is coupled to the ground pattern of printed board <b>21</b> and is thus grounded. Due to these couplings of the terminals <b>27</b><i>h </i>and <b>27</b><i>j</i>, the second antenna element <b>24</b> is grounded at the switch point <b>26</b> in one state (called a grounded state), and is not grounded in another state (called an ungrounded state).</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0065">How to represent a length of each portion and a total length of the first antenna element <b>23</b> and the second antenna element <b>24</b> will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 9</figref>. Each portion of the first antenna element <b>23</b> and the second antenna element <b>24</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a same as the corresponding one given the same reference numeral shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, and its explanation is omitted. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the switch element <b>27</b> is being open. Each of small alphabet letters p to u shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> represents a length of each portion of the first antenna element <b>23</b> and the second antenna element <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0066">The first antenna element <b>23</b> has a starting portion of a length of p starting and going up from the feeding point <b>25</b>, a following portion of a length of q going right, and an end portion of a length of r going downward. The first antenna element <b>23</b> is a monopole antenna having an open end, and has a total length of p+q+r. Hence, the first antenna element <b>23</b> has a resonant frequency on which the length of p+q+r corresponds to a quarter wavelength.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0067">The second antenna element <b>24</b> has the starting portion of the length of p in common with the first antenna element <b>23</b>, a following portion of a length of s going left and reaching the switch point <b>26</b>, and an end portion of the length of t between the switch point <b>26</b> and the open end <b>28</b>. The second antenna element <b>24</b> has a total length of p+s+t.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0068">Hence, the second antenna element <b>24</b> has a resonant frequency on which the length of p+s+t corresponds to a quarter wavelength. The resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>24</b> is lower than that of the first antenna element <b>23</b> if a following inequality is true, i.e., q+r&lt;s+t. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows a variation of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, in which the switch point <b>26</b> coincides with the open end <b>28</b>, i.e., t=0.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0069">A configuration of the antenna device <b>22</b> in the grounded state of the second antenna element <b>24</b> will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> that is different from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> only in the state of the switch element <b>27</b> (the reference numeral “27” is not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>). Each portion or its length of the first antenna element <b>23</b> and the second antenna element <b>24</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a same as the corresponding one given the same reference numeral or the same small alphabet shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, and its explanation is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0070">In the grounded state of the second antenna element <b>24</b>, the starting portion of the length of p, the following portion of the length of s, a switch portion between the terminals <b>27</b><i>h </i>and <b>27</b><i>j </i>of the switch element <b>27</b> and a portion between the switch point <b>26</b> and the ground pattern of the printed board <b>21</b> are coupled in series one by one to form a line. Let a length of the portion between the switch point <b>26</b> and the ground pattern of the printed board <b>21</b> be u.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0071">The line formed in the grounded state of the second antenna element <b>24</b> has a length of p+s+u, if an electric length between the terminals <b>27</b><i>h </i>and <b>27</b><i>j </i>of the switch element <b>27</b> is neglected. As described regarding the first embodiment, the line formed in the grounded state performs as an antenna equivalent to a loop antenna twice as long as the line except for a value of input impedance.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0072">The equivalent loop antenna has a resonant frequency on which the length of p+s+u corresponds to a half wavelength. The resonant frequency of the equivalent loop antenna is nearly twice as high as the resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>24</b> in the ungrounded state, if a following condition is true, i.e., t≅u. The resonant frequency of the second antenna element <b>24</b> may thus be changed up to twice as high as its value in the ungrounded state if the switch element <b>27</b> is switched to the grounded state, and may be changed even higher if a following condition is true, i.e., u&lt;t.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0073">If the antenna device <b>22</b> is configured according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the antenna device <b>22</b> has a VSWR characteristic which is a same as the solid curve shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. A frequency characteristic of the antenna device <b>22</b> in the grounded state of the second antenna element <b>24</b> is determine by resonant frequencies of the first antenna element <b>23</b>, the equivalent loop antenna mentioned above and an antenna element of a length of t between the switch point <b>26</b> and the open end <b>28</b> performing as a quarter wavelength monopole antenna.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0074">Assume that q+r&lt;s+t and the resonant frequency of the first antenna element <b>23</b> is higher than that of the second antenna element <b>24</b> in the ungrounded state. In that case, a portion of the first antenna element <b>23</b> of a length of q+r and a portion of the second antenna element <b>24</b> of a length of s+t cause, as a whole, parallel resonance at a frequency on which a length of q+r+s+t corresponds to a half wavelength. The parallel resonant frequency is lower than the resonant frequency of the first antenna element <b>23</b> and higher than that of the second antenna element <b>24</b> (refer to p. 201 of Sekine and Shoki previously mentioned). At the parallel resonant frequency, the input impedance of the antenna device <b>22</b> may increase and may cause a mismatch.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0075">In a case where the radio apparatus <b>2</b> operates in a frequency range between the resonant frequencies of the first antenna element <b>23</b> and the second antenna element <b>24</b>, the parallel resonant frequency in the ungrounded state of the second antenna element <b>24</b> may be included in the above frequency range. By closing the switch element <b>27</b> and forming the equivalent loop antenna, the antenna device <b>22</b> may cover the frequency range while avoiding the parallel resonance.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0076">In a case where q+r&lt;t, though, a frequency of parallel resonance caused by the first antenna element <b>23</b> and the antenna element of the length of t between the switch point <b>26</b> and the open end <b>28</b> may be lower than the resonant frequency of the first antenna element <b>23</b>, and may be included in the above frequency range. The antenna device <b>22</b> may avoid the parallel resonant frequency from remaining in the above frequency range by letting t&lt;q+r. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows a variation of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, in which the switch point <b>26</b> coincides with the open end <b>28</b>, i.e., t=0.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0077"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows a simulated frequency characteristic of a voltage standing wave ratio (VSWR) of the antenna device <b>22</b> configured to avoid the parallel resonant frequency from remaining between two resonant frequencies in the ungrounded state of the second antenna element <b>24</b> by switching that to the grounded state. In that simulation, the antenna device <b>22</b> is assumed to have a meander element and to operate in an UHF band.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0078">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, a solid curve shows a VSWR characteristic indicating two separate resonant frequencies in the ungrounded state. A dashed curve shows a VSWR characteristic indicating that an interval between the two separate frequencies is covered by a resonant frequency generated in the grounded state and the parallel resonance is avoided.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0079">The first antenna element <b>23</b> may not be a monopole antenna having an open end as long as being unbalanced-fed, as the first antenna element <b>13</b> of the first embodiment may not either. In that case, the condition explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, i.e., q+r&lt;s+t, is replaced by a condition that a total length of the second antenna element <b>24</b> in the ungrounded state is greater than the quarter wavelength of the resonant frequency of the first antenna element <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0080">According to the second embodiment described above, obtained is an effect similar to that of the first embodiment while avoiding parallel resonance.</p>
<heading id="h-0009" level="1">3. Third Embodiment of the Present Invention</heading>
<p id="p-0081" num="0081">A third embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 13 to 16</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 13 and 14</figref> show configurations of antenna devices <b>12</b><i>a </i>and <b>12</b><i>b</i>, respectively, of the third embodiment. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 15 and 16</figref> show configurations of antenna devices <b>22</b><i>a </i>and <b>22</b><i>b</i>, respectively, of the third embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0082">The antenna device <b>12</b><i>a </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is configured in such a way that the antenna device <b>12</b> of the first embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is loaded with a reactance element <b>18</b> between the switch point of the antenna device <b>12</b> (or the terminal <b>16</b><i>j </i>of the switch element <b>16</b>) and the open end <b>17</b>. Each of remaining portions of the antenna device <b>12</b><i>a </i>is a same as the corresponding one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> given the same reference numeral, and its explanation is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0083">The antenna device <b>12</b><i>b </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is configured in such a way that the antenna device <b>12</b> of the first embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is loaded with a reactance element <b>19</b> between the switch point of the antenna device <b>12</b> (or the terminal <b>16</b><i>k </i>of the switch element <b>16</b>) and the ground pattern of the printed board <b>11</b>. Each of remaining portions of the antenna device <b>12</b><i>b </i>is a same as the corresponding one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> given the same reference numeral, and its explanation is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0084">The antenna device <b>22</b><i>a </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is configured in such a way that the antenna device <b>22</b> of the second embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is loaded with a reactance element <b>29</b> between the switch point <b>26</b> of the antenna device <b>22</b> and the open end <b>28</b>. Each of remaining portions of the antenna device <b>22</b><i>a </i>is a same as the corresponding one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> given the same reference numeral, and its explanation is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0085">The antenna device <b>22</b><i>b </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> is configured in such a way that the antenna device <b>22</b> of the second embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is loaded with a reactance element <b>30</b> between the terminal <b>27</b><i>j </i>of the switch element <b>27</b> and the ground pattern of the printed board <b>21</b>. Each of remaining portions of the antenna device <b>22</b><i>b </i>is a same as the corresponding one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> given the same reference numeral, and its explanation is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0086">Being loaded with the reactance element <b>18</b>, the antenna device <b>12</b><i>a </i>may change an effective length of the second antenna element <b>14</b> so that the resonant frequency or the input impedance of the antenna device <b>12</b><i>a </i>may be adjusted. So may the resonant frequency or the input impedance of each of the antenna devices <b>12</b><i>b</i>, <b>22</b><i>a </i>and <b>22</b><i>b </i>loaded with the reactance elements <b>19</b>, <b>29</b> and <b>30</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0087">If values of the reactance elements <b>18</b>, etc., are variable, the above adjustment may be made in a broader range. For the adjustment, the conditions of the lengths of the antenna elements explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 8</figref> need to be satisfied with the effective lengths of the antenna elements.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0088">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, the antenna device <b>12</b><i>a </i>may further be loaded with the reactance element <b>19</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> between the terminal <b>16</b><i>k </i>of the switch element <b>16</b> and the ground pattern of the printed board <b>11</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>, the antenna device <b>22</b><i>a </i>may further be loaded with the reactance element <b>30</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> between the terminal <b>27</b><i>j </i>of the switch element <b>27</b> and the ground pattern of the printed board <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0089">The switch element <b>16</b> may be located on the printed board <b>11</b>, and so may the reactance elements <b>18</b> and <b>19</b>. The switch element <b>27</b> may be located on the printed board <b>21</b>, and so may the reactance elements <b>29</b> and <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0090">According to the third embodiment described above, obtained is an additional effect that a resonant frequency or input impedance of an antenna device may be more easily adjusted.</p>
<heading id="h-0010" level="1">4. Fourth Embodiment of the Present Invention</heading>
<p id="p-0091" num="0091">A fourth embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 17 to 21</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus <b>4</b>, including an antenna device, of the fourth embodiment. The radio apparatus <b>4</b> has a case <b>40</b> formed by a first case <b>40</b><i>a </i>and a second case <b>40</b><i>b </i>connected to each other by a connection (not shown). The first case <b>40</b><i>a </i>and the second case <b>40</b><i>b </i>are indicated by a dot-and-dash line in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>. The first case <b>40</b><i>a </i>and the second case <b>40</b><i>b </i>contain a printed board <b>41</b><i>a </i>and a printed board <b>41</b><i>b</i>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0092">The first case <b>40</b><i>a </i>contains an antenna device <b>42</b> indicated as encircled by a dashed ellipse. The antenna device <b>42</b> has a same configuration as that of the antenna device <b>12</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and its explanation is omitted. The antenna device <b>42</b> is fed from a feeding point <b>43</b> located on the printed board <b>41</b><i>a</i>. A relationship among the first case <b>40</b><i>a</i>, the printed board <b>41</b><i>a</i>, the antenna device <b>42</b> and the feeding point <b>43</b> is a same as a relationship among the case <b>10</b>, the printed board <b>11</b>, the antenna device <b>12</b> and the feeding point <b>15</b> of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0093">The printed boards <b>41</b><i>a </i>and <b>41</b><i>b </i>are coupled to each other by a flexible printed board <b>44</b>. The printed board <b>41</b><i>a </i>has a ground pattern that is coupled to a ground pattern of the printed board <b>41</b><i>b </i>via a conductor pattern printed on the flexible printed board <b>44</b>. The antenna device <b>42</b> then provides a return current from the feeding point <b>43</b> along a current path formed on the ground pattern of the printed board <b>41</b><i>a</i>, the conductor pattern of the flexible printed board <b>44</b> and the ground pattern of the printed board <b>41</b><i>b</i>. As, more often than not, the current path is longer than an antenna element included in the antenna device <b>42</b>, the return current acts on the antenna device <b>42</b> so as to decrease a lower resonant frequency thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0094"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus <b>5</b> of the fourth embodiment. The radio apparatus <b>5</b> differs from the radio apparatus <b>4</b> in that the radio apparatus <b>5</b> has a flexible printed board <b>45</b> that is right-left reversed against the flexible printed board <b>44</b> of the radio apparatus <b>4</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>. The flexible printed board <b>45</b> is coupled to the printed board <b>41</b><i>a </i>on an end nearer to the printed board <b>41</b><i>b </i>and farther from the feeding point <b>43</b>. Each of remaining portions of the radio apparatus <b>5</b> is a same as the corresponding one given the same reference numeral shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>, and its explanation is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0095">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref>, the antenna device <b>42</b> provides a return current from the feeding point <b>43</b> along a current path formed on the ground pattern of the printed board <b>41</b><i>a</i>, the conductor pattern of the flexible printed board <b>45</b> and the ground pattern of the printed board <b>41</b><i>b</i>. As the current path formed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref> is longer than the current path formed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>, the return current acts on the antenna device <b>42</b> so as to moreover decrease the lower resonant frequency thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0096">An effect of the fourth embodiment examined by simulation will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 19 to 21</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref> corresponds to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>, and shows a condition of the simulation regarding a relative position between the printed boards <b>41</b><i>a </i>and <b>41</b><i>b</i>, and regarding a relationship between an orientation of the flexible printed board <b>44</b> and a location of the feeding point <b>43</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0097">Each portion shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref> represents the corresponding one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> and given the same reference numeral, <b>41</b><i>a</i>, <b>41</b><i>b</i>, <b>43</b> or <b>44</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref>, lengths are indicated in millimeters (mm). The printed boards <b>41</b><i>a </i>and <b>41</b><i>b </i>are separated 10 mm apart and arranged in a direction of their long sides. The printed boards <b>41</b><i>a </i>and <b>41</b><i>b </i>are coupled to each other along a diagonal line representing the flexible printed board <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0098"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 20</figref> corresponds to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref>, and shows a condition of the simulation as well as <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref>. Each portion shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 20</figref> represents the corresponding one shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> and given the same reference numeral, <b>41</b><i>a</i>, <b>41</b><i>b</i>, <b>43</b> or <b>45</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 20</figref>, the printed board <b>41</b><i>a </i>is coupled to the printed board <b>41</b><i>b </i>from the farther end along a right-left reversed diagonal line representing the flexible printed board <b>45</b>. There is no difference between <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 19 and 20</figref> other than that.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0099"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 21</figref> shows a VSWR characteristic of the antenna device <b>42</b> simulated under the condition shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 19 and 20</figref> in comparison with the VSWR characteristic of the antenna device <b>12</b> of the first embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 21</figref> shows same horizontal and vertical axes as those shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0100"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 21</figref> shows a solid curve, a dot-and-dash curve and a dashed curve. The solid curve represents the VSWR characteristic of the antenna device <b>12</b> of the first embodiment being in the ungrounded state. The dot-and-dash curve represents the VSWR characteristic of the antenna device <b>42</b> included in the radio apparatus <b>4</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>, simulated under the condition shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref>. The dashed curve represents the VSWR characteristic of the antenna device <b>42</b> included in the radio apparatus <b>5</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref>, simulated under the condition shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 20</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0101">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 21</figref>, the lower peak moves left, i.e., the lower resonant frequency decreases, in an order of the solid curve, the dot-and-dash curve and the dashed curve. The solid curve represents a case where the printed board <b>41</b><i>b </i>is not present. The dot-and-dash curve represents a case where the printed board <b>41</b><i>b </i>is present. The dashed curve represents a case where the printed board <b>41</b><i>b </i>is present and a connection between the printed board <b>41</b><i>a </i>and the flexible printed board <b>45</b> is kept away from the feeding point <b>43</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0102">As described above, the antenna device <b>42</b> is assumed to have a same configuration as that of the antenna device <b>12</b> of the first embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The antenna device <b>42</b> may have a same configuration as that of the antenna device <b>22</b> of the second embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0103">According to the fourth embodiment described above, obtained is an additional effect that a lower resonant frequency of an antenna device may further be decreased depending on a configuration of a radio apparatus having a plurality of cases.</p>
<heading id="h-0011" level="1">5. Fifth Embodiment of the Present Invention</heading>
<p id="p-0104" num="0104">A fifth embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 22 to 24</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 22</figref> shows a configuration of a radio apparatus <b>6</b>, including an antenna device, of the fifth embodiment. The radio apparatus <b>6</b> of the fifth embodiment has a case <b>60</b> indicated by a dot-and-dash line. The radio apparatus <b>6</b> has a printed board <b>61</b> and an antenna device <b>62</b> contained in the case <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0105">The radio apparatus <b>6</b> may be, e.g., a mobile phone having the case <b>60</b>. The radio apparatus <b>6</b> may have an extra case (not shown) connected to the case <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0106">The antenna device <b>62</b> includes a first antenna element <b>63</b> and a second antenna element <b>64</b>. The first antenna element <b>63</b> is arranged in parallel with a short side of the printed board <b>61</b>. The second antenna element <b>64</b> is arranged in parallel with a long side of the printed board <b>61</b>. The first antenna element <b>63</b> and the second antenna element <b>64</b> are fed in common at a feeding point <b>65</b> located on the printed board <b>61</b>. The first antenna element <b>63</b> is located near an end of the printed board <b>61</b>, and so is the second antenna element <b>64</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0107">The antenna device <b>62</b> includes a switch element <b>67</b> having two terminals. One of the terminals is coupled to an end of the second antenna element <b>64</b>. Another one of the terminals is coupled to a ground pattern of the printed board <b>61</b> and is thus grounded. Due to these couplings of the terminals of the switch element <b>67</b>, the second antenna element <b>64</b> is grounded at the end to which the switch element <b>67</b> is coupled in one state (called a grounded state), and is not grounded in another state (called an ungrounded state).</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0108"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> shows a configuration of the switch element <b>67</b>. The switch element <b>67</b> includes a substrate <b>69</b> and a semiconductor switch <b>70</b>. The semiconductor switch <b>70</b> is formed by, e.g., a metal semiconductor field effect transistor (MESFET) having a gate portion <b>71</b> and a source-drain portion <b>72</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0109">The gate portion <b>71</b> is located on a ground pattern <b>74</b> of the substrate <b>69</b>. To the gate portion <b>71</b>, coupled is a control line (not shown) to turn on and off the switch element <b>67</b>. The source-drain portion <b>72</b> has an electrode shown on a left lower side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> and coupled to the ground pattern <b>74</b>. The source-drain portion <b>72</b> has another electrode shown on a right side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> and coupled to the end of the second antenna element <b>64</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0110">A portion of the substrate <b>69</b> shown on a right side of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> has no ground pattern. If that portion has a ground pattern, the end of the second antenna element <b>64</b> and the ground pattern are electrostatically coupled to each other so that it may become difficult that a resonant frequency is adjusted or input impedance is matched as designed in a case where the end of the second antenna element <b>64</b> is grounded.</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0111"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 24</figref> shows a characteristic of the antenna device <b>62</b> configured as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 22 and 23</figref>, that is measured in an UHF band. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 24</figref> shows a Smith chart in an upper half thereof and a VSWR characteristic over a frequency range in a lower half thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0112">The VSWR characteristic includes a curve noted as “OPEN” measured while the switch element <b>67</b> is being open, and includes a curve noted as “SHORT” measured while the switch element <b>67</b> is being closed. The former curve shows two distinct resonances of the first antenna element <b>63</b> and the second antenna element <b>64</b>. That indicates a same effect as that of the second embodiment as described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0113" num="0113">According to the fifth embodiment described above, a switch is coupled to an antenna element at a location apart from a ground pattern of a printed board so that an effect of switching the antenna element between grounded and ungrounded may surely be obtained.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0114">In the above embodiments, the switch elements <b>16</b> and <b>27</b> may be implemented as a mechanical switch, a semiconductor switch, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0115">The particular hardware or software implementation of the present invention may be varied while still remaining within the scope of the present invention. It is therefore to be understood that within the scope of the appended claims and their equivalents, the invention may be practiced otherwise than as specifically described herein.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An antenna device configured to be coupled to a feeding point of a radio apparatus, comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first antenna element configured to be an unbalanced-fed antenna being fed at the feeding point to resonate at a first frequency; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second antenna element configured to be a monopole antenna having an open end and to be fed at the feeding point, the first antenna element and the second antenna element having a common portion from the feeding point to a branching point,
<claim-text>the second antenna element configured to be ungrounded in a first state to resonate at a second frequency lower than the first frequency and to be grounded in a second state at a switch point between the branching point and the open end.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch element located at the switch point and included in the second antenna element,
<claim-text>the switch element configured to switch the second antenna element between the first state and the second state.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch element located at the switch point and included in the second antenna element,
<claim-text>the switch element configured to switch the second antenna element between the first state and the second state,</claim-text>
<claim-text>two portions of the second antenna element on both sides of the switch point coupled to each other by the switch element in the first state, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the two portions uncoupled to each other by the switch element in the second state.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch element located at the switch point and included in the second antenna element,
<claim-text>the switch element configured to switch the second antenna element between the first state and the second state,</claim-text>
<claim-text>two portions of the second antenna element on both sides of the switch point coupled to each other by the switch element in the first state, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>one of the two portions coupled to the feeding point is grounded via the switch element to the radio apparatus in the second state.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch element located at the switch point and included in the second antenna element,
<claim-text>the switch element configured to switch the second antenna element between the first state and the second state, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a summed length of two portions of the second antenna element on both sides of the switch point is greater than a quarter wavelength of the first frequency.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch element having two terminals,
<claim-text>one of the two terminals coupled to the switch point, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>another one of the two terminals grounded to the radio apparatus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch element having two terminals,
<claim-text>one of the two terminals coupled to the switch point,</claim-text>
<claim-text>another one of the two terminals grounded to the radio apparatus, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a portion of the second antenna element between the switch point and the open end having a length less than a quarter wavelength of the first frequency.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch element having two terminals,
<claim-text>one of the two terminals coupled to the switch point,</claim-text>
<claim-text>another one of the two terminals grounded to the radio apparatus,</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the switch point coincides with the open end.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a reactance element loaded between the switch point and the open end.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The antenna device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a reactance element,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second antenna element is grounded through the reactance element to the radio apparatus in the second state.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A radio apparatus, comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a case;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a printed board contained in the case, the printed board including a feeding point and a ground pattern thereof; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an antenna device contained in the case, the antenna device including a first antenna element and a second antenna element,
<claim-text>the first antenna element configured to be an unbalanced-fed antenna being fed at the feeding point to resonate at a first frequency, the second antenna element being a monopole antenna having an open end and to be fed at the feeding point, the first antenna element and the second antenna element having a common portion from the feeding point to a branching point,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second antenna element configured to be ungrounded in a first state to resonate at a second frequency lower than the first frequency and to be grounded in a second state at a switch point between the branching point and the open end.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The radio apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising</claim-text>
<claim-text>an extra case connected to the case by a connection,</claim-text>
<claim-text>an extra printed board contained in the extra case, the extra printed board including a ground pattern thereof, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coupling member coupling the extra printed board to the printed board through the connection,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the coupling member couples a portion of the printed board to a portion of the extra printed board so as to extend a length of a return current path formed by the ground pattern of the printed board, the coupling member and the ground pattern of the extra printed board.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
