<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298363-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298363</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10901143</doc-number>
<date>20040729</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>608</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>09</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345168</main-classification>
<further-classification>400488</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Innovated keyboard for personal digital assistant</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5574481</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lee</name>
<date>19961100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345168</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6552281</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Katakami et al.</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>200  5 A</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6793421</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Baldwin et al.</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>400488</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>1</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345168</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>400488</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>400472</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>341 22</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>200  5 A</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060022946</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060202</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Huang</last-name>
<first-name>Chin-Lang</first-name>
<address>
<street>No. 70-13 Hsichow, Changhsing Village</street>
<city>Luchu Hsiang, Taoyuan Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Rosenberg, Klein &amp; Lee</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hjerpe</last-name>
<first-name>Richard</first-name>
<department>2629</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Kevin M</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An innovated design of keyboard for keying in commands to a PDA, particularly a collapsible type that can be folded for storage and convenient carrying purposes, and its two sides can be unfolded and compressed to a fixed status to minimize measurements, which comprising a left keyboard and a right keyboard, and a connecting board to enable connection of the left keyboard with a mobile track plate, forming a foldable and movable joint. Furthermore, provided on one side of the mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard and between two recesses is a formation of a protruded insert, thereby when the right keyboard and the left keyboard are pushed and inserted in position, the protruded insert on the mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard is inserted into the insert groove on the bottom plate of the left keyboard.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="136.57mm" wi="145.03mm" file="US07298363-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="145.80mm" wi="138.85mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298363-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="193.72mm" wi="95.33mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298363-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="192.96mm" wi="153.67mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298363-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="174.24mm" wi="153.25mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298363-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an innovative keyboard for a personal digital assistant, particularly a PDA key-in keyboard that can be folded for storage and convenient carrying, and unfolded for ready use, designed to reduce its measurements to enhance integrity and perfection.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The personal digital assistant, PDA, has become a modern-day star in our information industry. It has the function and characteristics to provide uses with convenient use in different occasions, space and time, which is quite suitable for processing personal affairs or jobs.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Wherein, the interior system provides functions almost similar to those of a miniature personal computer, for communication and other purposes, including consumer electronics, word processing, information transmission, etc., all of which are functions of a desk-top computer. Therefore, it was quite welcome to the public. The word key-in system provides a word identification function, by writing directly on a PDA panel with a touch pen, which is identified by the system and automatically keyed into the computer.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Due to the slow speed when a touch-pen is used to key in on a PDA panel, a user would choose to use a keyboard for better efficiency when trying to key in a large amount of text. The keyboard comes in either an elongated rectangular shape or a foldable type for convenient carrying with the user. The foldable keyboard consists of two main keyboard units that are connected by a connecting board to form a mobile joint. The two keyboard units can be folded to facilitate carrying, or unfolded for ready use. The connecting board between the two keyboard units forms a distance, causing the user some difficulty in manual operation. Another shortcoming is its larger measurements, occupying a larger space when it is unfolded.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The present invention relates to an innovated keyboard for personal digital assistant, an innovated design of keyboard for keying in commands to a PDA, particularly a collapsible type that can be folded for storage and convenient carrying purposes, and its two sides can be unfolded and compressed to a fixed status to minimize measurements, which comprising a left keyboard and a right keyboard, and a connecting board connecting with the left keyboard with a mobile track plate, forming a foldable and movable joint, wherein, provided on an upper and lower edges of a mobile track plate is a protruded guide strip, and on an upper and lower position is a protruded track, accommodating insertion of a track groove on a mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard for to-and-fro movement, there being a protruded guide strip guiding the mobile bottom plate and keep it from wobbling, provided at a specified position on a bottom plate of the left keyboard being a recoil device, and on one side of the bottom plate being an insert groove; wherein, provided respectively on an upper and lower position of the mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard being a track groove, the track groove having an inlet, a track strip and a guide incline, permitting insertion of the protruded track on the mobile bottom plate through the inlet, the guide incline guiding the protruded track to join smoothly with the track strip for to-and-fro movement.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Furthermore, provided on one side of the mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard and between two recesses is a formation of a protruded insert, thereby when the right keyboard and the left keyboard are pushed and inserted in position, the protruded insert on the mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard is inserted into the insert groove on the bottom plate of the left keyboard.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an exploded view of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a partially blow-up view of the mobile bottom plate of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exterior view of the present invention of keyboard when unfolded.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an exterior view of the invention of keyboard when two sides are compressed and joined.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic view of the present invention of keyboard when unfolded.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic view of the invention of keyboard when two sides are compressed and joined.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The present invention is an innovated keyboard for personal digital assistant (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), consisting of a left keyboard <b>10</b> and a right keyboard <b>20</b>, and a connecting board <b>30</b> to enable connection of the left keyboard <b>10</b> with a mobile track plate <b>40</b>, forming a foldable joint; wherein, provided on the upper and lower edges of the mobile track plate <b>40</b> are protruded guide strips <b>402</b> and on the upper and lower positions are protruded tracks <b>401</b>, permitting insertion in a track groove <b>202</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 1A</figref>) on a mobile bottom plate <b>201</b> of the right keyboard <b>20</b> for reciprocal movement (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>), and a protruded guide strip <b>402</b> guiding the mobile bottom plate <b>201</b> and preventing it from wobbling. Provided on a bottom plate <b>101</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>4</b> and <b>5</b>) of the left keyboard <b>10</b> is a recoil device <b>50</b>, and provided on a side of the bottom plate <b>101</b> is an insert groove <b>102</b>; (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 1A</figref>) wherein, the mobile bottom plate <b>201</b> of the right keyboard <b>20</b> has a track groove <b>202</b> respectively on an upper and a lower position, (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>), the track groove <b>202</b> has an inlet <b>202</b><i>a</i>, a track strip <b>202</b><i>c </i>and a guide incline <b>202</b><i>b </i>to accommodate the insertion by compression of the protruded track <b>401</b> of the mobile track plate <b>40</b> through the inlet <b>202</b><i>a </i>(<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>1</b>A, <b>2</b>, <b>3</b>, <b>4</b> and <b>5</b>), the guide incline <b>202</b><i>b </i>guiding smooth insertion of the protruded track <b>401</b> and the track strip <b>202</b><i>c </i>to move to and fro.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Furthermore, on one side of the mobile bottom plate <b>201</b> of the right keyboard <b>20</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>4</b> and <b>5</b>) and between two recesses <b>203</b> is the formation of a protruded insert <b>203</b><i>a</i>, when the right keyboard <b>20</b> and the left keyboard <b>10</b> are inserted to each other in position, the protruded insert <b>203</b><i>a </i>on the mobile bottom plate <b>201</b> of the right keyboard <b>20</b> is inserted into the insert groove <b>102</b> on the bottom plate <b>101</b> of the left keyboard <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> illustrate the schematic view of the present invention of keyboard in operation. As shown, after the left and right keyboards <b>10</b>,<b>20</b> are unfolded, the right keyboard <b>20</b> is pressed to join the left keyboard <b>10</b> (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>). After the protruded track <b>401</b> of the mobile track plate <b>40</b> is moved into position in the track groove <b>202</b> on the mobile bottom plate <b>201</b> of the right keyboard <b>20</b>, the protruded insert <b>203</b><i>a </i>on the mobile bottom plate <b>201</b> of the right keyboard <b>20</b> is inserted into the insert groove <b>102</b> on the bottom plate <b>101</b> of the left keyboard <b>10</b>, thereby the two parts of keyboard are fastened to reduce measurements.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">As evidenced above, the structure of the present invention is capable of moving the left and right parts of keyboard and inserting them into each other to reduce measurements. That characteristic has not yet been used or disclosed in public. Therefore, this application is filed for a patent right. Your favorable consideration shall be appreciated.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">While the particular embodiment of the present invention has been illustrated and described, it would be obvious to those skilled in the art that various other changes and modifications can be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. It is therefore intended to cover in the appended claims all such changes and modifications that are within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What the invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An innovative keyboard for personal digital assistant comprising:
<claim-text>a left keyboard;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a right keyboard;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a connecting board connecting with the left keyboard with a mobile track plate forming a foldable and movable joint;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a protruded guide strip is provided on upper and lower edges of the mobile track plate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a protruded track is disposed on an upper and lower portion of the mobile track plate, accommodating insertion of a track groove on a mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard for to-and-fro movement, the protruded guide strip guiding the mobile bottom plate and preventing it from wobbling;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a recoil device provided at a predetermined position on a bottom plate of the left keyboard; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an insert groove disposed on one side of the bottom plate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a track groove provided respectively on an upper and lower position of the mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard, the track groove including;
<claim-text>an inlet;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a track strip;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a guide incline, permitting insertion of the protruded track on the mobile bottom plate through the inlet, the guide incline guiding the protruded track to join smoothly with the track strip for to-and-fro movement; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a formation of a protruded insert is disposed on one side of the mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard between two recesses, whereby when the right keyboard and the left keyboard are pushed and inserted in position, the protruded insert on the mobile bottom plate of the right keyboard is inserted into the insert groove on the bottom plate of the left keyboard.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
