<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296763-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296763</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11119941</doc-number>
<date>20050503</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>211</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>18</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>241293</main-classification>
<further-classification> 298951</further-classification>
<further-classification> 2989521</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Keyless frictional shaft/hub locking device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2097982</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kist et al.</name>
<date>19371100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>403272</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2651241</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hornbostel</name>
<date>19530900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 2989521</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3501183</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Stratienko</name>
<date>19700300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>403370</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3752004</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hanssen</name>
<date>19730800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 74443</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2411012</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>241293</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>241294</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>241295</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>241236</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 298951</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 2989521</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060249610</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061109</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bliss</last-name>
<first-name>Theron J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Granville</city>
<state>MA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Case</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey A.</first-name>
<address>
<city>East Granby</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tobiasz</last-name>
<first-name>Robert R.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suffield</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Antonelli, Terry, Stout &amp; Kraus</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>ALSTOM Technology Ltd</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<country>CH</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Rosenbaum</last-name>
<first-name>Mark</first-name>
<department>3725</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A grinder roll assembly (<b>500</b>) is provided herein. The grinder roll assembly (<b>500</b>) includes a grinder roll (<b>505</b>), a shaft (<b>510</b>) in a through bore of the grinder roll, a first tapered sleeve (<b>615</b>A), and a second tapered sleeve (<b>615</b>B). The first tapered sleeve (<b>615</b>A) fits between the shaft (<b>510</b>) and the grinder roll (<b>505</b>) in one direction, and the second tapered sleeve (<b>615</b>B) fits between the shaft (<b>510</b>) and the grinder roll (<b>505</b>) in an opposite direction to form at least one friction lock that mounts the grinder roll (<b>505</b>) to the shaft (<b>510</b>).</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="102.62mm" wi="130.39mm" file="US07296763-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="191.85mm" wi="145.37mm" file="US07296763-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="195.58mm" wi="160.70mm" file="US07296763-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="170.60mm" wi="114.89mm" file="US07296763-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="175.43mm" wi="137.84mm" file="US07296763-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="194.48mm" wi="125.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296763-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="186.10mm" wi="144.36mm" file="US07296763-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="180.68mm" wi="131.23mm" file="US07296763-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="171.62mm" wi="138.43mm" file="US07296763-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention is related to clinker grinders, and more particularly to an improved technique for attaching a grinder roll to a shaft.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a portion of a typical coal-burning utility electrical power generation plant <b>20</b>. Coal is loaded into hopper <b>22</b> and gravity fed as shown at arrow <b>24</b> to inlet duct <b>26</b> of ball tube mill <b>28</b>. The mill includes a rotary drum with a charge or plurality of balls therein which pulverize the coal as the drum rotates to produce pulverized coal. The pulverized coal is discharged as shown at arrow <b>34</b> to outlet duct <b>36</b> for introduction to the burner of boiler <b>38</b>. Incoming combustion air is supplied as shown at arrow <b>40</b> from fan <b>42</b>. The heat of combustion of the air and pulverized coal is supplied as shown at arrow <b>44</b> through a plurality of heat exchangers <b>46</b>, <b>48</b>, to generate steam to in turn drive electrical power generating turbines, as is standard. After giving up heat for the noted steam generation, exhaust including fly ash flows as shown at arrow <b>50</b> to exhaust outlet <b>52</b>. An air preheater <b>54</b> is connected between combustion air inlet duct <b>56</b> and exhaust outlet duct <b>58</b> for transferring heat from the exhaust flow at <b>50</b> to the incoming combustion air flow at <b>40</b> to pre-heat the latter. The spent pulverized coal, after ignition and burning, fuses as hardened chunks called bottom ash clinkers, and are collected and ground at clinker grinder <b>60</b> for discharge and disposal. Of course, as will be understood by one of ordinary skill in the art, clinkers are also produced by other type coal-fired furnaces, beyond that depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A typical clinker grinder <b>60</b> includes two grinder roll assemblies that intermesh with knurls to grind the bottom ash clinkers. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> depicts a conventional and well known grinder roll assembly <b>200</b>. Included in assembly <b>200</b> is a cast Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b> that is mounted on a stainless steel shaft <b>210</b>. As shown, the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b> has multiple knurls, though for simplicity's sake only a single knurl is labeled <b>220</b>, formed on the outer surface thereof. The Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b> cannot be directly welded to the stainless steel shaft <b>210</b> because of differences in material properties. In lieu of welding, pentagonal shaped insert <b>225</b> is used to mount the grinding roll <b>205</b> to the stainless steel shaft <b>210</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Insert <b>225</b> is hand fitted into the bore of the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the insert <b>225</b> is then welded to the stainless steel shaft <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A clinker grinder <b>60</b> is subject to extensive wear. In addition to wear to the knurls and other parts of the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b>, there is frequent failure of the weld between the insert <b>225</b> and the shaft <b>210</b>. Also, it is known for insert <b>225</b> to fail and spin within the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b>. Because of the use of insert <b>225</b>, both the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b> and the stainless steel shaft <b>210</b> must be replaced together, even if only the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b> is worn. That is, the welding of the insert <b>225</b> to the stainless steel shaft <b>210</b> causes stress concentrations to the shaft <b>210</b> that make it undesirable to reuse the stainless steel shaft <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The forced replacement of stainless steel shaft <b>210</b> is not economical, as each stainless steel shaft <b>210</b> costs approximately $1,200.00. Also, labor costs associated with machining the bore of the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b> and the shaft <b>210</b> for fitting to the insert <b>225</b>, and with the actual mounting of the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b> on the shaft <b>210</b>, are high. Furthermore, the mounting procedure itself is prone to crack the Ni-hard grinding roll <b>205</b>, making it unusable.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Accordingly, a need exists for a grinder roll assembly which overcomes deficiencies of existing grinder roll assemblies. Thus, a need exists for a grinder roll assembly with an improved way of mounting a grinding roll to a shaft. A need also exists for a grinder roll assembly in which a welded insert is not required to mount the grinding roll to the shaft. A need also exists for a grinder roll assembly in which it is only necessary to replace worn parts. Also, a need exists for a grinder roll assembly which can be rebuilt using a previously used shaft, as well as a grinder roll assembly which is not subject to cracking during assembly. And, a need also exists for a grinder roll assembly which is economical to assemble.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">OBJECTS OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It is an object of the present invention to provide a grinder roll assembly that overcomes the deficiencies of existing grinder roll assemblies.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is also an object of the present invention to provide a grinder roll assembly which includes an improved way of mounting the grinding roll to the shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">It is yet another object of the present invention to provide a grinder roll assembly in which a welded insert is not required to mount the grinding roll to the shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Still another object of the present invention is to provide a grinder roll assembly in which it is only necessary to replace worn parts.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Yet another object of the present invention is to provide a grinder roll assembly having a shaft that can be reused.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Another object of the present invention is to provide a grinder roll assembly that is not subject to cracking during assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">It is still another object of the present invention to provide a grinder roll assembly that is economical to assemble.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The above-stated objects, as well as other objects, features, and advantages, of the present invention will become readily apparent from the following detailed description which is to be read in conjunction with the appended drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A grinder roll assembly, a locking mechanism for a grinder roll, and a method for locking a grinder roll and a shaft are provided. The grinder roll assembly includes a grinder roll, such as, but not limited to, a Ni-hard grinder roll, that has a through bore that extends from one end of the roll to the other, a shaft is disposed within the through bore, and first and second tapered sleeves.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The first tapered sleeve fits over the shaft and into the grinder roll bore such that a first end of this first tapered sleeve is positioned nearer to a first end of the bore. This first end of the first tapered sleeve is narrower than a second end of the first tapered sleeve. In other words, the first tapered sleeve is inserted into the bore thick end first.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The second tapered sleeve also fits over the shaft and into the grinder roll bore. However, the second tapered sleeve is inserted into the bore with the thin end of the second tapered sleeve inserted first so as to fit against the first tapered sleeve to form multiple friction locks which prevent movement. A first friction lock is between the first and second tapered sleeves, a second friction lock is between the one tapered sleeve and the grinder roll, i.e., the inside of the bore, and a third friction lock is between the other tapered sleeve and the shaft. Because of these friction locks, the grinder roll and the shaft become interconnected.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In one aspect, the grinder roll assembly is for use in a clinker grinder that is associated with a coal-fired furnace. The clinker grinder pulverizes the clinkers, which are produced as a byproduct of burning coal, into smaller particles.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">According to another aspect, the grinder roll assembly also includes a locking ring that fits over the shaft and is in contact with the second tapered sleeve. When installed the locking ring causes the second tapered sleeve to draw against the first tapered sleeve. Still further, the grinder roll assembly also includes at least one connector, such as, but not limited to, a bolt, for securing the locking ring to the grinder roll. In a still further aspect, the grinder roll assembly also includes at least one connection for securing the locking ring to either or both of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In yet another aspect, the grinder roll assembly also includes a third tapered sleeve and a fourth tapered sleeve. The third tapered sleeve fits over the shaft and into the grinder roll bore such that a first end of the third tapered sleeve is nearer to a second end of the bore. Similar to the first tapered sleeve, the first end of the third tapered sleeve is narrower than a second end of the third tapered sleeve, i.e., the thick end of the third tapered sleeve is inserted into the bore first.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The fourth tapered sleeve also fits over the shaft and into the grinder roll bore such that a fourth friction lock between the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, a fifth friction lock between the grinder roll and one of the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, and a sixth friction lock between the shaft and the other one of the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, are formed.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In a further aspect, the grinder roll assembly includes another locking ring that fits over the shaft and is in contact with the fourth tapered sleeve, causing the fourth tapered sleeve to draw against the third tapered sleeve. Still further, at least one connector may be utilized to secure the second locking ring to at least one of grinder roll, the third tapered sleeve, and the fourth tapered sleeve.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The locking mechanism for a grinder roll assembly disclosed herein includes a first tapered sleeve and a second tapered sleeve. The first tapered sleeve is adapted to fit between a grinder roll shaft and a grinder roll surface that defines a through bore such that a first end of the first tapered sleeve is positioned near to a first end of the through bore. Similar to the discussion above, the first end of the first tapered sleeve has a first thickness and a second end of the first tapered sleeve has a second thickness greater than the first thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The second tapered sleeve is adapted to fit over the shaft and into the through bore such that a first friction lock between the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, a second friction lock between the grinder roll and one of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, and a third friction lock between the shaft and the other one of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, are formed.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The method of the present invention for locking a grinder roll and a shaft will be understood with reference to the grinder roll assembly and locking mechanism described above.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In order to facilitate a fuller understanding of the present invention, reference is now made to the appended drawings. These drawings should not be construed as limiting the present invention, but are intended to be exemplary only.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic illustration of a portion of a coal-burning utility electrical power generation plant, including a clinker grinder.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> depicts a conventional grinder roll assembly for use in a clinker grinder depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is another view of the grinder roll assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is yet another view of the grinder roll assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is depicts a grinder roll assembly in accordance with certain aspects of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is another view of the grinder roll assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is yet another view of the grinder roll assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is still another view of the grinder roll assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF A PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> depicts a new and improved grinder roll assembly <b>500</b> in accordance with the present invention. Included in assembly <b>500</b> is a grinding roll <b>505</b> and shaft <b>510</b>. Preferably, the grinding roll <b>505</b> is a Ni-hard grinding roll. However, other suitable materials, as desired, may be utilized for the grinding roll <b>505</b> without departing from the essence of the present invention. Also preferably, the shaft <b>510</b> is stainless steel shaft. However, as with the grinding roll <b>505</b>, other suitable materials, as desired, may be utilized for the shaft <b>510</b> without departing from the essence of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The grinding roll <b>505</b> is mounted to the shaft <b>510</b> using a keyless frictional shaft/hub locking mechanism <b>520</b>. Of course, it will be recognized by one of ordinary skill in the art that two keyless frictional shaft/hub locking mechanisms will be used to mount the grinding roll <b>505</b> to the shaft <b>510</b>, one at either end of the grinding roll <b>505</b>. A first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and a second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B, with respective tapered ends facing opposite directions along the longitudinal axis of the shaft <b>510</b>, are fitted into the bore of the grinding roll <b>505</b> and over the shaft <b>510</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B are fitted into the bore such that the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B overlap.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B are drawn tight over one another by a locking hub <b>620</b>. Preferably, though not necessarily, the locking hub <b>620</b> is affixed to, and perhaps a part of, the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the locking hub <b>620</b> is secured by tightening fasteners to draw the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B over one another. For simplicity's sake, only a single fastener is designated by the reference numeral <b>730</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. It should be understood, however, that while <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> depicts twelve fasteners, a greater number or a lesser number of fasteners, as desired, could be utilized without departing from the essence of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Locking hub <b>620</b>, as it is fastened, pushes the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B together. It should be understood that while <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> depicts the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A being pushed underneath the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B by the locking hub <b>620</b>, if so desired, the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B can be placed onto shaft <b>510</b> in the opposite directions without departing from the essence of the present invention such that the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B is pushed underneath the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A by the locking hub <b>620</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a further depiction of the locking hub <b>620</b>, with a bolt <b>805</b> serving as a fastener. As will be understood from the above, preferably multiple bolts are utilized, though only a single bolt <b>805</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. In the alternative depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> the bolt <b>805</b> itself does not tap into the grinding roll <b>505</b>. Rather, the bolt <b>805</b> passes through the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and into a tapped hole on the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B. By tightening on the bolt <b>805</b>, the bolt <b>805</b> pulls the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B together. As the tapered sleeves slide over one another, the tapered sleeve closest to the shaft <b>510</b> (the inner tapered sleeve) exerts a pressure on the shaft <b>510</b> and the other tapered sleeve (the outer tapered sleeve) exerts a pressure on the grinder roll <b>505</b>, locking the grinder roll <b>505</b> to the shaft <b>510</b>. As the bolt <b>805</b> is further tightened, the tapered sleeves are further pulled up on each other, increasing the pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">No welding is required when mounting the grinding roll <b>505</b> to shaft <b>510</b> using the keyless frictional shaft/hub locking mechanism <b>520</b>. To this end, the friction generated by the pressure of the first tapered sleeve <b>615</b>A and the second tapered sleeve <b>615</b>B pushing off of one another interlocks the shaft <b>510</b> to the grinding roll <b>505</b> such that when the shaft <b>510</b> rotates about its longitudinal axis the grinding roll <b>505</b> also rotates. Also the mounting of the grinding roll <b>505</b> to the shaft <b>510</b> using the keyless frictional shaft/hub locking mechanism requires less time to complete than is required with the prior art mounting approaches.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Mentioned above, the present invention does not require welding for purposes of mounting the grinding roll <b>505</b> to the shaft <b>510</b>. Because of the lack of welding, the risk of failure of a weld is nonexistent in the present invention, and the possibility of a stress concentration occurring on the shaft <b>510</b> as a result of welding is also eliminated. Thus, because of the lack of welding, the locking hub <b>620</b> and the shaft <b>510</b> are capable of being reused in a rebuild, if so desired.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The present invention is not to be limited in scope by the specific embodiments described herein. Indeed, various modifications of the present invention in addition to those described herein will be apparent to those of skill in the art from the foregoing description and accompanying drawings. Thus, such modifications are intended to fall within the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A grinder roll assembly, comprising:
<claim-text>a grinder roll having a through bore defined by a surface of the grinder roll;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shaft disposed within the through bore;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first tapered sleeve disposed between the shaft and the grinder roll surface such that a first end of the first tapered sleeve is proximate to a first end of the through bore, wherein the first end of the first tapered sleeve has a first thickness and a first locking ring flange extending therefrom, and a second end of the first tapered sleeve has a second thickness greater than the first thickness;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second tapered sleeve disposed between the shaft and the grinder roll surface such that a first end of the second tapered sleeve is proximate to the first end of the through bore, wherein the first end of the second tapered sleeve has a first thickness and a second locking ring flange extending therefrom, and a second end of the second tapered sleeve has a second thickness less than the first thickness;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one connector for fastening together the first and the second locking ring flanges to thereby form a first friction lock between the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, a second friction lock between the grinder roll and one of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, and a third friction lock between the shaft and the other one of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The grinder roll assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the grinder roll assembly is for use in a grinder operative to pulverize into smaller particles clinkers that are produced by a coal-fired furnace.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The grinder roll assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the at least one connector functions to fasten together the first and the second locking ring flanges so as to apply a force to the second tapered sleeve, this applied force causing one of the first and the second tapered sleeves to move against the other of the first and the second tapered sleeves.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The grinder roll assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the at least one connector includes a fastener having member with a threaded portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>one of the first and the second locking ring flanges includes a threaded portion configured for coupling to the threaded portion of the fastener member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the other of the first and the second locking ring flanges includes an opening configured such that the threaded portion of the fastener member is passable through the opening in the other locking ring flange in order to couple the threaded portion of the fastener member to the threaded portion of the one locking ring flange.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The grinder roll assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a third tapered sleeve disposed between the shaft and the grinder roll surface such that a first end of the third tapered sleeve is proximate to a second end of the through bore distal to the first end of the through bore, wherein the first end of the third tapered sleeve has a third thickness and a second end of the third tapered sleeve has a fourth thickness greater than the third thickness; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth tapered sleeve disposed between the shaft and the grinder roll surface such that a fourth friction lock between the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, a fifth friction lock between the grinder roll and one of the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, and a sixth friction lock between the shaft and the other one of the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, are formed.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The grinder roll assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein (i) the first end of the third tapered sleeve has a third locking ring flange extending therefrom, (ii) a first end of the fourth tapered sleeve is proximate to the second end of the through bore, has a first thickness, and has a second locking ring flange extending therefrom, and (iii) a second end of the fourth tapered sleeve has a second thickness less than the first thickness, and further comprising:
<claim-text>at least one other connector for fastening together the third and the fourth locking ring flanges to thereby form the fourth, the fifth and the sixth friction locks;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the at least one other connector functions to fasten together the third and the fourth locking ring flanges so as to apply a force to the fourth tapered sleeve, this applied force causing the fourth tapered sleeve to move against the third tapered sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The grinder roll assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>at least one other connector including a fastener having a member with a threaded portion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>one of the third and the fourth locking ring flanges includes a threaded portion configured for coupling to the threaded portion of the fastener member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the other of the third and the fourth locking ring flanges includes an opening configured such that the threaded portion of the fastener member is passable through the opening in the other of the third and the fourth locking ring flanges in order to couple the threaded portion of the fastener member to the threaded portion of the one of the third and the forth locking ring flanges.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A locking mechanism for a grinder roll assembly including a grinder roll having a through bore defined by a surface of the grinder roll and a shaft disposed within the through bore, comprising:
<claim-text>a first tapered sleeve adapted to be disposed between the shaft and the grinder roll surface such that a first end of the first tapered sleeve is proximate to a first end of the through bore, wherein the first end of the first tapered sleeve has a first thickness and a first locking ring flange extending therefrom, and a second end of the first tapered sleeve has a second thickness greater than the first thickness;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second tapered sleeve adapted to be disposed over the shaft and into the through bore such that a first end of the second tapered sleeve is proximate to the first end of the through bore, wherein the first end of the second tapered sleeve has a first thickness and a second locking ring flange extending therefrom, and a second end of the second tapered sleeve has a second thickness less than the first thickness; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one connector for fastening together the first and the second locking ring flanges to thereby form a first friction lock between the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, a second friction lock between the grinder roll and one of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, and a third friction lock between the shaft and the other one of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The locking mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the grinder roll assembly is for use in a grinder operative to pulverize into smaller particles clinkers that are produced by a coal-fired furnace.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The locking mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein the at least one connector functions to fasten together the first and the second locking ring flanges so as to apply a force to the second tapered sleeve causing the second tapered sleeve to move against the first tapered sleeve when the first tapered sleeve is disposed over the shaft and in contact with the second tapered sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The locking mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the at least one connector includes a fastener having a member with a threaded portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>one of the first and the second locking ring flanges includes a threaded portion configured for coupling to the threaded portion of the fastener; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the other of the first and the second locking ring flanges includes an opening configured such that the threaded portion of the fastener member is passable through the opening in the other locking ring flange in order to couple the threaded portion of the fastener member to the threaded portion of the one locking ring flange.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The locking mechanism of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a third tapered sleeve adapted to be disposed between the shaft and the grinder roll surface such that a first end of the third tapered sleeve is proximate to a second end of the through bore distal to the first end of the through bore, wherein the first end of the third tapered sleeve has a third thickness and a second end of the third tapered sleeve has a fourth thickness greater than the third thickness; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth tapered sleeve adapted to be disposed over the shaft and into the through bore such that a fourth friction lock between the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, a fifth friction lock between the grinder roll and one of the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, and a sixth friction lock between the shaft and the other one of the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, are formed.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method for locking a grinder roll having a through bore extending from a first end to an opposing second end of the grinder roll and a shaft disposed within the through bore, comprising:
<claim-text>inserting a first tapered sleeve over the shaft and into a first end of the through bore such that a first end of the first tapered sleeve is proximate to the first end of the grinder roll, wherein the first end of the first tapered sleeve has a first thickness and a first locking ring flange extending therefrom, and a second end of the first tapered sleeve end has a second thickness greater than the first thickness; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>inserting a second tapered sleeve over the shaft and into the first end of the through bore such that a first end of the second tapered sleeve is proximate to the first end of the through bore, wherein the first end of the second tapered sleeve has a first thickness and a second locking ring flange extending therefrom, and a second end of the second tapered sleeve has a second thickness less than the first thickness; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>fastening together the first and the second locking ring flanges to thereby form a first friction lock between the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, a second friction lock between the grinder roll and one of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve, and a third friction lock between the shaft and the other one of the first tapered sleeve and the second tapered sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein fastening together the first and the second locking ring flanges applies a force to move the second tapered sleeve against the first tapered sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein fastening together the first and the second locking ring flanges includes passing a threaded portion of a fastener through an opening in one of the first and the second locking ring flanges and bolting the threaded portion of the fastener into a threaded portion of the other of the first and the second locking ring flanges.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>inserting a third tapered sleeve over the shaft and into a second end of the through bore distal to the first end of the through bore such that a first end of the third tapered sleeve is proximate to the second end of the grinder roll, wherein the first end of the third tapered sleeve has a third thickness and a second end of the third tapered sleeve has a fourth thickness greater than the third thickness; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>inserting a fourth tapered sleeve over the shaft and into the second end of the through bore to form a fourth friction lock between the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, a fifth friction lock between the grinder roll and one of the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve, and a sixth friction lock between the shaft and the other one of the third tapered sleeve and the fourth tapered sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein (i) the first end of the third tapered sleeve has a third locking ring flange extending therefrom, (ii) a first end of the fourth tapered sleeve is proximate to the second end of the through bore, has a first thickness, and has a second locking ring flange extending therefrom, and (iii) a second end of the fourth tapered sleeve has a second thickness less than the first thickness, and further comprising:
<claim-text>fastening together the third and the fourth locking ring flanges so as to apply another force to move the fourth tapered sleeve against the third tapered sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein (i) the first end of the third tapered sleeve has a third locking ring flange extending therefrom, (ii) a first end of the fourth tapered sleeve is proximate to the second end of the through bore, has a first thickness, and has a second locking ring flange extending therefrom, and (iii) a second end of the fourth tapered sleeve has a second thickness less than the first thickness, and further comprising:
<claim-text>fastening together the third and the fourth locking ring flanges by passing a threaded portion of a fastener through an opening in one of the third and the fourth locking ring flanges and bolting the threaded fastener into a threaded portion of the other of the third and the fourth locking ring flanges.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
