<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296964-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296964</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11235124</doc-number>
<date>20050927</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>87</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415108</main-classification>
<further-classification>415144</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Apparatus and methods for minimizing solid particle erosion in steam turbines</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4615734</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Spriggs</name>
<date>19861000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4704336</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Spriggs</name>
<date>19871100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4776765</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sumner et al.</name>
<date>19881000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4853014</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bloch</name>
<date>19890800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4921546</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bloch</name>
<date>19900500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4922937</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bloch</name>
<date>19900500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4986309</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bellanca</name>
<date>19910100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5249918</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Knorowski</name>
<date>19931000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5295301</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Knorowski</name>
<date>19940300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5363603</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Miller et al.</name>
<date>19941100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6288000</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hebsur</name>
<date>20010900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6391811</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hebsur</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6605648</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Johnson et al.</name>
<date>20030800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6644917</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Zhao et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6679681</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Burnett et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0194312</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Burnett et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00017">
<document-id>
<country>CA</country>
<doc-number>1273538</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19900900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00018">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>61031602</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19860200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00019">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>0524806</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>19930900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00020">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>9207849</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>19920900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415116</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415108</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>415144</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070071594</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070329</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Montgomery</last-name>
<first-name>Michael Earl</first-name>
<address>
<city>Niskayuna</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nixon &amp; Vanderhye, PC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>General Electric Company</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Schenectady</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Look</last-name>
<first-name>Edward K.</first-name>
<department>3745</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>White</last-name>
<first-name>Dwayne J</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Solid particle erosion in a steam turbine is minimized by diverting through holes in appendages of outer rings of the diaphragms, a portion of the steam from the steam flow path thereby bypassing downstream rotating components. The hole through the first stage appendage lies in communication with a passage through a downstream outer ring of a following stage such that the diverted solid particle containing steam may be extracted from the steam flow path and passed to the feed water heater of the turbine. The hole in the second stage appendage diverts steam from between the first and second stages and about the second stage. Solid particle erosion in various regions, i.e., the trailing edge of the stator vanes, along the surfaces of the buckets and in the regions of the cover and its connection with the buckets as well as the sealing devices are thereby minimized.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="136.91mm" wi="153.92mm" file="US07296964-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="188.81mm" wi="164.34mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296964-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="210.06mm" wi="162.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296964-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="154.52mm" wi="147.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296964-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="230.80mm" wi="126.75mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296964-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="98.47mm" wi="107.44mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296964-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to apparatus and methods for minimizing solid particle erosion in steam turbine components and particularly relates to apparatus and methods for removing solid particles from the steam flow path to minimize damage to the turbine components.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Solid particle erosion of the components of a steam turbine occurs due to carryover of particles from the steam boiler and piping upstream of the turbine. The solid particles become entrained in the steam flow path. As they pass through the steam turbine, the particles cause damage to both the stationary and rotating parts of the turbine that degrade steam turbine performance and mechanical reliability. The solid particles may be deposited throughout the steam path or may exit the steam path into steam extractions that feed the feed water heaters of the cycle. However, since the particles are transported by the main steam flow through the steam turbine steam path, they have the opportunity to inflict considerable damage to the steam path before they are deposited or expelled from the main steam flow. This damage can include erosion of the rotating and stationary buckets and partitions respectively, erosion of the rotating tip covers or tenons, erosion of tip sealing devices such as spill strips and erosion of stationary structures over the tips of the rotating buckets.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Various apparatus and methods have been proposed and utilized to minimize the impact of the solid particles on the rotating and stationary parts of steam turbines. For example, in U.S. Pat. No. 4,776,765 a protective device is disposed over a portion of the suction side of the partition to prevent solid particle erosion of the trailing edge of the partition due to rebound of particles from the leading edge of the buckets. Other apparatus and methods for minimizing or eliminating solid particle erosion in steam turbines include solid particle erosion resistant coatings such as disclosed in U.S. Pat. Nos. 4,704,336 and 4,615,734. While many of these and other efforts to minimize or eliminate solid particle erosion have been tried in the past, solid particle erosion in steam turbines remains a continuing problem for the various parts along the steam path. Accordingly there has developed a further need for apparatus and methods to minimize solid particle erosion of steam turbine components.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In a preferred embodiment of the present invention there is provided a steam turbine comprising: a stage of the steam turbine including a diaphragm having an inner web, an outer ring and a plurality of stator vanes therebetween; the outer ring having an axially downstream appendage overlying tips of buckets forming part of the turbine stage; and at least one hole through the appendage for diverting a portion of the steam in a steam flow path upstream of the buckets of the turbine stage and bypassing the buckets of the turbine stage.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In a further preferred embodiment of the present invention there is provided a method of minimizing solid particle erosion in a steam turbine stage comprising the step of diverting a portion of the steam in a steam flow path through a hole in an appendage of an outer ring overlying bucket tips of the turbine stage and bypassing the buckets of the turbine stage.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic illustration of a typical stage geometry of and function for a steam turbine;</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with areas denoted by the numbered ovals indicating typical damage caused by solid particle erosion in the turbine;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrating devices for diverting solid particles in the steam path in accordance with a preferred aspect of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an enlarged fragmentary schematic illustration of a diaphragm appendage, e.g., a first stage diaphragm appendage and sealing device illustrating a diverted portion of the steam flow;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a fragmentary schematic illustration of a second stage of a steam turbine illustrating the diverted steam portions from the first and second stages; and</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an enlarged schematic illustration of a diaphragm appendage of a second stage of the steam turbine showing the exit path of the diverted steam.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, there is illustrated typical steam turbine stages of a steam turbine generally designated <b>10</b>. Two stages of the steam turbine <b>10</b> are illustrated, for example, a first stage generally designated <b>12</b> and a second stage generally designated <b>14</b>. The first stage <b>12</b> includes a diaphragm <b>16</b> having an inner web <b>18</b>, an outer ring <b>20</b>, and a plurality of circumferentially spaced stator vanes or partitions <b>22</b> therebetween. The first stage also includes buckets <b>24</b> secured to a rotor <b>26</b>. The tips of the buckets <b>24</b> rotate past sealing devices <b>28</b> formed on an axially extending appendage <b>30</b> of the outer ring <b>20</b>. The inner web <b>18</b> of the first stage diaphragm includes sealing segments <b>32</b>, in this instance, mounting labyrinth seal teeth <b>34</b> for sealing about the rotor <b>26</b>. The second stage <b>14</b> is similar and includes a diaphragm <b>36</b>, an inner web <b>38</b>, an outer ring <b>40</b>, partitions <b>42</b> circumferentially spaced one from the other and disposed between the inner web and outer ring, the outer ring <b>40</b> having an appendage <b>44</b> overlying tips of buckets <b>46</b> mounted on the rotor <b>26</b>. It will be appreciated that the steam flows through the illustrated stages in the direction of the arrow <b>48</b> rotating the rotor <b>26</b>, enabling useful work to be derived from the steam turbine <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">As noted previously, solid particles flowing in the steam path tend to erode the various components of the turbine with consequent degradation in performance and efficiency. The region denoted {circle around (<b>1</b>)} in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> constitutes the trailing edge of the partitions. Solid particle erosion in region {circle around (<b>1</b>)} can seriously effect the mechanical integrity of the stationary vanes, potentially impact the mechanical integrity of the rotating vanes due to forced response phenomena and degrades stage performance due to the increase in stationary vane area, throat shape and flow angle degradation. Region {circle around (<b>2</b>)} in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> denotes an area of increased tip leakage of steam due to solid particle erosion to the tip sealing devices, e.g., devices <b>28</b>. Region {circle around (<b>3</b>)} in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> denotes areas where solid particles are deposited by centrifugal action under the covers of the rotating buckets. Such deposits can degrade mechanical integrity of the rotating buckets by changing the response of the rotating structure. They may also degrade performance by blockage of the rotating steam path near the tip. Region {circle around (<b>4</b>)} in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> denotes solid particle erosion in the area of the connection between the tenons and covers which can seriously effect the mechanical integrity of the covers and tenons at their connections. For example, over extended periods of time and being subject to solid particle erosion, the tenon or cover or both can be eroded to the extent that their mechanical integrity is degraded such that mechanical failure may occur. Also, cover and tenon erosion combined with tip sealing device erosion in region {circle around (<b>3</b>)} can decrease stage performance and efficiency due to increased tip leakage. In region {circle around (<b>5</b>)} of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, solid particle erosion causes damage to the typical outer ring cutback region which can effect the mechanical integrity of the tip sealing device retention. Solid particle erosion can also cause damage to the bucket surfaces per se as denoted in region {circle around (<b>6</b>)} in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. This can degrade stage performance due to increases in rotating vane surface roughness. From the foregoing, it will be appreciated that solid particle erosion may significantly damage the performance and efficiency of the steam turbine and seriously affect part life.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, wherein like reference numerals are applied to like parts as in the conventional steam turbine construction illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the present invention provides for the removal of a portion of the solid particles from the main steam flow so as to minimize damage to downstream steam path components. Another function is to minimize erosion damage to the tip sealing device retention. Generally, holes and passageways are provided in the component parts to divert a portion of the steam and hence the solid particles carried by the steam about the rotating parts. As used herein, the term “passageway(s)” or “passage(s)”, embraces slots, grooves, openings and the like for performing the function of diverting a portion of the steam and solid particles about the rotating parts. Thus, passages are provided through the outer ring of the first stage to bypass a portion of the steam about the first stage buckets and sealing devices. The diverted steam also flows through a passageway in a downstream stage, bypassing the stationary and rotating parts of the downstream stage. Another set of holes and passages are provided in the downstream stage such that residual solid particles in the steam are able to bypass the downstream stage rotating parts. The diverted steam portions are then discharged from the steam path to the extraction or heater.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">More particularly, and referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, an aspect of the present invention provides one or more holes <b>60</b> in the appendage <b>30</b> for diverting a portion of the steam flowing through the steam path through the hole <b>60</b>. It will be appreciated that the appendage <b>30</b> may be integral with or a separate part affixed to the ring <b>20</b>. The hole <b>60</b> includes an inlet opening <b>64</b> upstream of the buckets <b>24</b> of the stage, e.g., the first stage. The hole <b>60</b> is divided into two portions <b>64</b> and <b>66</b> on opposite sides of the sealing device <b>68</b>. The sealing device may comprise a spring or steam biased sealing segment carrying labyrinth seal teeth for sealing about the tip of the rotating buckets <b>24</b>. Thus, a passage <b>70</b> extends through the sealing segment <b>68</b> in communication with the hole portions <b>64</b> and <b>66</b>, thereby constituting a through passageway in appendage <b>30</b> for bypassing steam about the rotating parts, i.e., the buckets <b>24</b> of the stage. As illustrated, the hole portion <b>66</b> exits into a passageway <b>72</b> extending through the outer ring <b>40</b> of the next, e.g., second stage. The passage <b>72</b> exits to a steam extraction passage indicated by the arrow <b>73</b> to a feed water heater or other external connection, not shown, to which the solid particles will be expelled. It will be appreciated that the drawing <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-5</figref> as well as <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, by standard convention, are inverted such that the holes, passages and passageways are located in the bottom of the steam turbine to facilitate concentration of the solid particles and their removal and diversion from the steam path and about the rotating parts.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>, a similar arrangement for the downstream, e.g., second stage of the steam turbine is provided for diverting solid particles in the steam flow path about the rotating part of the second stage <b>14</b>. Specifically, the appendage <b>44</b> of the downstream, e.g., second stage, includes a hole <b>80</b> having an entrance aperture <b>82</b> and an exit aperture <b>84</b>. Similarly, as in the first stage diversion, the sealing device <b>86</b> in the downstream stage includes a passage, i.e., a hole <b>88</b> in communication with the hole <b>80</b> whereby residual solid particle containing steam in the steam path may flow into the entrance aperture <b>82</b> through hole <b>80</b> and <b>88</b> for egress through exit <b>84</b> to the extraction passage <b>73</b> to a feed water heater or other external connection. By providing the extraction holes, passages and passageways and locating them in the bottom of the turbine, a significant portion of the solid particles in the steam path can be diverted around the rotating parts of the stages as well as certain of the stationary components, minimizing solid particle erosion of the turbine parts.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">While the invention has been described in connection with what is presently considered to be the most practical and preferred embodiment, it is to be understood that the invention is not to be limited to the disclosed embodiment, but on the contrary, is intended to cover various modifications and equivalent arrangements included within the spirit and scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A steam turbine comprising:
<claim-text>a stage of the steam turbine including a diaphragm having an inner web, an outer ring and a plurality of stator vanes therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the outer ring having an axially downstream appendage overlying tips of buckets forming part of the turbine stage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one passage through the appendage for diverting a portion of the steam in a steam flow path upstream of the buckets of the turbine stage and bypassing the buckets of said turbine stage; and a sealing device carried by said appendage for sealing about the bucket tips, and a passage through the sealing device in communication with the passage in the appendage to bypass the diverted portion of the steam about the buckets of said turbine stage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A steam turbine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the sealing device lies intermediate the axial extent of the appendage, the passage through the appendage being divided into two portions on respective opposite sides of the passage through the sealing device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A turbine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the passage through the appendage is located adjacent a bottom of the first stage of the turbine.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A steam turbine comprising:
<claim-text>a first stage of the steam turbine including a diaphragm having an inner web, an outer ring and a plurality of stator vanes therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the outer ring of the first stage having a first axially downstream appendage overlying tips of buckets forming part of the first turbine stage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one passage through the appendage for diverting a portion of the steam in a steam flow path upstream of the buckets of the first turbine stage and bypassing the buckets of said first turbine stage; a second stage of the turbine downstream of the first stage and including a diaphragm having an inner web, an outer ring and a plurality of stator vanes therebetween, said second stage including a passage through the outer ring thereof in communication with the passage through the first stage appendage to flow the diverted steam portion outside of the steam path bypassing the second stage; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said outer ring of said second stage includes a second axially downstream appendage overlying tips of buckets forming part of the second stage, at least one passage through the second stage appendage for diverting a second portion of the steam from the steam path at a location upstream of the stator vanes and buckets of the second stage thereby bypassing the second diverted steam portion about the second stage buckets.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A turbine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> including an extraction passage for receiving the steam diverted from the steam path and flowing through said second stage passage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A turbine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> including a second sealing device carried by the second stage appendage and a passage through the second sealing device in communication with the passage through the second appendage to flow the second diverted portion of the steam to bypass the second stage buckets.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A turbine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the second diverted steam portion is extracted from the steam path at a location between said first and second stages.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A method of minimizing solid particle erosion in a steam turbine stage comprising diverting a portion of the steam in a steam flow path through a passage in an appendage of an outer ring overlying bucket tips of the turbine stage and bypassing the buckets of the turbine stage; and
<claim-text>providing a sealing device carried by said appendage for sealing about the bucket tips, and flowing the diverted portion of the steam through a passage in the sealing device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> including locating the passage through the appendage adjacent a bottom of the turbine.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> including diverting a second portion of the steam in the steam flow path downstream of the first mentioned stage through a passage in an appendage of an outer ring of a second turbine stage overlying bucket tips of the second stage and bypassing the buckets of the second stage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> including providing a sealing device carried by said appendage of the second stage for sealing about the bucket tips, and flowing the second diverted portion of the steam through a passage in the sealing device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A turbine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> including providing a second turbine stage including an outer ring downstream of the first mentioned stage and a passage in the second outer ring in communication with the passage through the first stage appendage.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
