<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296679-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296679</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11135917</doc-number>
<date>20050523</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>248</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>65</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>85</main-group>
<subgroup>68</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>65</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>54</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206477</main-classification>
<further-classification>206335</further-classification>
<further-classification>206775</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Multi-purpose fixing insert for toy containers and method of packaging</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3481453</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Beichler et al.</name>
<date>19691200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206778</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4185739</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wilford</name>
<date>19800100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206477</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4261466</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wilford</name>
<date>19810400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206335</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4925025</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Anten et al.</name>
<date>19900500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206335</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5411138</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Klawiter</name>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206335</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-exemplary-claim>6</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206477-483</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206775-783</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206488-489</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60574360</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040524</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050269235</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051208</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lam</last-name>
<first-name>Terry</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kowloon</city>
<country>HK</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>HK</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>HK</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Anten</last-name>
<first-name>Lewis</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Ying</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Funrise Toys, Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kowloon</city>
<country>HK</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Gehman</last-name>
<first-name>Bryon P.</first-name>
<department>3728</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A multi-purpose insert designed to be used in conjunction with a conventional toy container or box for packaging, shipping and displaying a toy item. The insert includes a base piece, a cover piece and a holding piece, as well as a locking mechanism. The base piece has a main section with a raised platform and two end sections that are hingeably connected to the main section so that they can be folded up in a right angle relative to the main section. The insert also includes a cover piece which is placed over the toy item placed on the main section of the base piece, and a holder piece placed above the cover piece for keeping the two end sections in the upright position for retaining the toy item for packaging and shipping purposes. When the holding piece is removed, the two end sections of the base piece can be folded down for displaying the toy item on the raised platform of the main section of the base piece.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="210.31mm" wi="164.42mm" file="US07296679-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="247.73mm" wi="179.49mm" file="US07296679-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="231.65mm" wi="166.54mm" file="US07296679-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This is a regular patent application based on U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 60/574,360 filed on May 24, 2004.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention generally relates to the field of packaging and shipping containers, and more particularly relates to the field of packaging and shipping containers used for toy merchandise.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Packaging and shipping containers are widely used in the toy industry. Conventional packaging and shipping containers for toys typically consist of preformed boxes made of plastic or cardboard materials.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">There are numerous problems associated with shipping toy merchandise that are fragile. The most obvious problem is that during shipment the product tends to move within the packaging container which often causes damage to the product. Another significant problem is the damage to the external container which also often results damage to the product inside of the container.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The above problems have traditionally been addressed by surrounding the product being shipped with fabric, foam pellets or formed polystyrene. In addition, heavy damage resistant packaging, such as wood or thick cardboard has also been employed.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, for most toy merchandise, simple and light weight packaging structures are still mostly desired. In addition, toy merchandise are often displayed in shop shelves or by private collectors where a display platform is often desirable.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Therefore, there exists a need to provide an insert of simple and lightweight construction that can be used in regular cardboard containers for packaging and shipping toy merchandise, which insert can also be used for easy handling and displaying of the toy merchandise once they are removed from the containers.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention discloses a multi-purpose insert for toy containers.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In a preferred embodiments of the present invention, the multi-purpose insert is designed to be used in conjunction with a conventional toy container or box for packaging, shipping and displaying a toy item. The insert includes a base piece, a cover piece and a holding piece. The base piece has a main section and two end sections. The main section of the base piece has a raised platform surrounded by beveled sidewalls. The two end sections of the base piece each also has a raised center portion surrounded by beveled sidewalls.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The main section and two end sections of the base piece are hingeably connected, where the two end sections can be folded up in a right angle position relative to the main section with the toy item placed on the main section of the base piece. The insert also includes a transparent cover piece which is placed over the toy item, and a holder piece for keeping the two end sections of the base piece at the upright position for retaining the toy item for packaging and shipping purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">When removed from the toy container, the present invention insert can also be opened with the holding and cover pieces removed and the two end sections of the base piece folded down in flat alignment with the main section of the base piece for displaying the toy item on the raised platform of the main section of the base piece.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The present invention multi-purpose insert also includes a locking mechanism which secures the toy item in position on the platform of the base piece while it is being packaged, shipped or displayed.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The present invention multi-purpose toy container insert has a simple, easy and durable construction and can be made of plastic, cardboard or other suitable materials.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">OBJECTS OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">It is an object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved device for packaging toy merchandise.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">It is also an object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved device for shipping toy merchandise.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">It is another object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved device for displaying toy merchandise.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">It is also another object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved packaging, shipping and shipping combination device for toy merchandise.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">It is yet another object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved packaging insert that can be used in conjunction with conventional toy boxes or containers.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">It is still another object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved shipping insert that can be user in conjunction with conventional toy boxes or containers.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">It is an additional object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved insert for conventional toy boxes or containers that can be used for displaying toy merchandise after a toy merchandise is removed from its container or box.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">It is also an additional object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved insert for conventional toy boxes or containers that can serve multiple purposes of packaging, shipping and displaying toy merchandise.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">It is a further object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved multi-purpose insert for conventional toy boxes or containers that has a lightweight construction.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">It is also a further object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved multi-purpose insert for conventional toy boxes or containers that has a simple and easy construction.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">It is still a further object of the present invention to provide a novel, unique and improved multi-purpose insert for conventional toy boxes or containers that is made of durable, lightweight and fire-retardant materials.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">These and other objects of the present invention will become apparent from a review of the accompanying drawings and the detailed description of the drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a prospective view of one of the preferred embodiments of the present invention multi-purpose insert for a toy merchandise to be used in conjunction with a conventional toy container or box;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded prospective view showing the component parts of the preferred embodiment of the present invention multi-purpose insert shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a prospective view showing the present invention multi-purpose insert used for displaying a toy merchandise; and</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view showing the locking mechanism of the preferred embodiment of the present invention multi-purpose insert for toy containers.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 through 3</figref>, one of the preferred embodiments of the present invention multi-purpose insert to be used in conjunction with a conventional toy container or box for packaging, shipping and displaying a toy merchandise is shown and generally referred to by the numeral <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a toy item <b>2</b> (in this example a fire truck) packaged inside the insert <b>10</b> in a generally rectangular shaped configuration for insertion into a similarly shaped cardboard container or box (not shown) for packaging and shipping purposes, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the insert <b>10</b> opened up and unpacked to show the component parts of the insert <b>10</b>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the insert <b>10</b> used as a base for displaying and exhibition purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The preferred embodiment of the present invention insert <b>10</b> includes a base piece <b>12</b>, a cover piece <b>14</b> and a holding piece <b>16</b>. The base piece <b>12</b> has a main section <b>22</b>, and two end sections <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> hingeably connected to the opposite ends of the main section <b>22</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The main section <b>22</b> of the base piece <b>12</b> has a raised platform <b>32</b> surrounded by beveled sidewalls <b>34</b>. On the platform <b>32</b> there are multiple pegs <b>36</b> strategically located for securing the position of the toy item <b>2</b> on the platform <b>32</b>, and one or more key holes <b>38</b> which use will be described below.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The two end sections <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> of the base piece <b>12</b> each also has a raised center portion <b>42</b> which, when the main section <b>22</b> and the end sections <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> are all laid flat (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>), has the same height as the platform <b>32</b> of the main section <b>22</b> of the base piece <b>12</b>, and which is surrounded by beveled sidewalls <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The beveled sidewalls <b>34</b> at the opposite ends of the main section <b>22</b> and the adjacent beveled sidewalls <b>44</b> of the end sections <b>24</b> and <b>26</b>, respectively, of the base piece <b>12</b>, are hingeably connected such that the two end sections <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> can be folded up in a right angle relative to the main section <b>22</b> for retaining and protecting the front and rear ends of the toy item <b>2</b> for packaging and shipping purposes, or alternatively be folded down in flat alignment with the main section <b>22</b> of the base piece <b>12</b> to serve as a raised display base for the purpose of exhibiting the toy item <b>2</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">One or both of the end sections <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> may be provided with an opening <b>48</b> which can serve the purpose of accommodating extended portions of the toy item <b>2</b> (such as the hood or front bumper of the fire truck shown in this example) and can also serve the purpose of allowing the features of the toy item <b>2</b> be viewed while contained in the container which optionally may have a transparent window at corresponding position.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The present invention insert <b>12</b> also includes a locking mechanism for locking the toy piece <b>2</b> in position while it is being packaged or shipped inside a container or box, or displayed on the base piece <b>12</b>. The locking mechanism includes one or more keys <b>18</b> and a matching number of key holders <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 4</figref>, each locking key <b>18</b> has a knob <b>52</b>, a stem <b>54</b> and a key pin <b>56</b>. Each key holders <b>20</b> has a plate <b>62</b> with a key knob slot <b>64</b> and a pair of positioning pegs <b>66</b>. The size of the plate <b>62</b> and the locations of the key knob slot <b>64</b> and the pegs <b>66</b> of the key holder <b>20</b> are made to match the locations of the pegs <b>36</b> and key holes <b>38</b> of the main section <b>22</b> of the base piece <b>12</b>. The size of the key knob slot <b>64</b> also matches the key knob <b>52</b> of the locking key <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">As the key pin <b>56</b> and stem <b>54</b> of the locking key <b>18</b> is inserted through the key knob slot <b>64</b> of the key holder <b>20</b> and the pegs <b>66</b> of the key holder <b>20</b> are inserted into the small holes underneath the corresponding pegs <b>38</b> of the main section <b>22</b> of the base piece <b>12</b>, the key pin <b>52</b> and stem <b>54</b> of the locking key <b>18</b> is further inserted through the key hole <b>38</b> of the main section <b>22</b> of the base piece <b>12</b> and finally inserted into a bottom lock of the toy item <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The key <b>18</b> is designed such that by turning the key knob <b>52</b> of the locking key <b>18</b> to a direction aligned with the key knob slot <b>64</b> of the key holder <b>20</b>, the key pin <b>56</b> is locked with the bottom lock of the toy item <b>2</b>, so that the key knob <b>52</b> of the locking key <b>18</b> can be inserted in the key knob slot <b>64</b> of the key holder <b>20</b> which prevents further turning of the key <b>18</b> so that the toy item <b>2</b> remains locked by the key <b>18</b> while being packaged, shipped or displayed.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the cover piece <b>14</b> f the present invention insert <b>10</b> is placed over the toy item <b>2</b> when the toy item <b>2</b> is packaged. The cover piece <b>14</b> has two opposite sidewalls <b>72</b> and two opposite end walls <b>74</b> all integrally formed and connected together with a top cover <b>76</b>. The whole cover piece may be made of transparent plastic material.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The holder piece <b>16</b> has an elongated body <b>82</b> with two opposite end hooks <b>84</b>. As the cover piece <b>14</b> is placed over the toy item <b>2</b> and the two end sections <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> of the base piece <b>12</b> folded up, the holder piece <b>16</b> is placed above the cover piece <b>14</b> with the two end hooks <b>84</b> of the holder piece inserted into and engaged with respectively the slot openings <b>46</b> at the beveled sidewalls <b>44</b> at the respective distal far end of the end section <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> of the base piece <b>12</b> to thereby prevent the two end sections <b>24</b> and <b>26</b> from unfolding such that they are kept at an upright angle relative to the main section <b>22</b> of the base piece <b>12</b> to retain the toy item <b>2</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> for packaging and shipping purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The present invention insert <b>12</b> serves many important purposes for packaging, shipping and displaying the toy item <b>2</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, when the insert <b>12</b> is configured to retain the toy item <b>2</b>, it provides impact protection on all sides of the toy item <b>2</b>. It also provides a locking mechanism to secure the toy item <b>2</b> in position so it cannot move around inside a packaging container or box while being handled or shipped. On the other hand, when the insert <b>12</b> is opened as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, it serves as a raised exhibition platform for displaying the toy item <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">It is appreciated that while an insert that is suitable to be used in conjunction with a generally rectangular shaped packaging container or box is described hereinabove, the present invention multi-purpose insert may be configured to suit packaging containers or boxes of other configurations, without departing from the scope and spirit of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The method used in preparing the package comprises the steps of aligning the openings in the product and in the packaging so that the keys can be inserted through the aligned openings and the key can then be turned by the handle so as to fix the product to the packaging. The packaging can be used to substantially cover the entire product or only a portion of the product.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In the preferred embodiment at least one slot formed in the product is oriented parallel to the axis of the product and at least one second slot is at a different orientation, preferably 90 degrees to the first slot.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">While the present invention has been described in detail with regards to the preferred embodiments, it is appreciated that other variations of the present invention may be devised which do not depart from the inventive concept of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A combination package and product comprising:
<claim-text>a product having a first opening;</claim-text>
<claim-text>packaging material disposed adjacent said product and having a first opening in alignment with said first opening in said product;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a key having a first end, a second end and an intermediate shaft, the first end configured to be insertable through said first opening in said packaging material and into said first opening in said product, the key capable of being rotated whereby said first end engages an interior of said product, the second end of said key having a handle portion and being accessible from an outer side of the packaging material away from the product so as to rotate the key thereby fixing said product to said packaging material; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a key holder disposed on the outer side of the packaging material, the key holder having a plate with a slot for receiving the handle portion of the key and a positioning peg,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the packaging material further includes a peg receiving hole for receiving the positioning peg.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The combination package and product of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a second opening in said product and a second opening in said packaging material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The combination package and product of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the first opening in the product is elongated in a first direction and the second opening in the product is elongated in a second direction different from the first direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The combination package and product of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first end of the key is in the form of a T and the first opening in said product has an elongated shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The combination package and product of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said packaging material substantially encloses said product.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A method for packaging a product with a packaging material, said product having an opening, said packaging material having an opening, the method comprising:
<claim-text>aligning the opening in the packaging material with the opening in said product;</claim-text>
<claim-text>placing a key through said opening in said packaging material into said opening in said product;</claim-text>
<claim-text>rotating the key to engage an interior of the opening of the product, whereby said key fixes said packaging material to said product; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>placing a key holder on an outer side of the packaging material to engage the key to prevent the key from turning further.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said packaging material substantially encloses said product.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said key has a T-shaped portion at one end and a handle portion at another end and wherein said opening in said product has an elongated shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the key holder has a plate with a slot and a positioning peg, wherein the packaging material has a peg receiving hole, and wherein the key holder is placed by inserting the handle portion of the key into the slot of the key holder and inserting the positioning peg of the key holder into the peg receiving hole of the packaging material.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
