<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296683-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296683</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11236118</doc-number>
<date>20050926</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>179</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209224</main-classification>
<further-classification>2092231</further-classification>
<further-classification>209215</further-classification>
<further-classification>209636</further-classification>
<further-classification>340551</further-classification>
<further-classification>324234</further-classification>
<further-classification>324239</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Ferrous metal detector with alarm</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3826973</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Pflaum</name>
<date>19740700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324329</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4279744</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Antonwitsch</name>
<date>19810700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>209214</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4367138</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kustas</name>
<date>19830100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>209224</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4494657</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Oldenkamp</name>
<date>19850100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>209636</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4875567</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fitton</name>
<date>19891000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>194318</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5001425</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Beling et al.</name>
<date>19910300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324239</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5659247</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Clements</name>
<date>19970800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324239</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6833789</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Carmen et al.</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340551</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0067163</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Goldberg et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324234</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209224</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2092231</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209215</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209636</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation-in-part>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10334847</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20021230</date>
</document-id>
<parent-status>ABANDONED</parent-status>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11236118</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation-in-part>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60382448</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20020522</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Vallelonga, Sr.</last-name>
<first-name>Kenneth M.</first-name>
<address>
<street>412 S. Virginia Ave.</street>
<city>Bridgeport</city>
<state>WV</state>
<postcode>26330</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Haddix</last-name>
<first-name>Derick J.</first-name>
<address>
<street>Route 1 Box 299-35</street>
<city>Mount Clare</city>
<state>WV</state>
<postcode>26408</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Mackey</last-name>
<first-name>Patrick</first-name>
<department>3654</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Matthews</last-name>
<first-name>Terrell</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electronic ferrous metal detector with an alarm includes a non-ferrous core positioned circumferentially about an opening in an object, such as a hole in a garbage can lid. A pick-up coil having a sufficient number of windings is wound about the non-ferrous core for detecting magnetized objects passing therethrough and generating a voltage. The voltage is passed through an op-amp and into a comparator/detector, where a preset reference point is compared to the voltage from the op-amp. Once the voltage passes the preset reference point, the comparator goes to a high output and powers a switch, such as a SCR or Triac, which is gated on and carries the current and feeds the voltage to an alarm that provides an audible or visual signal that a magnetized piece of ferrous material has passed through the metal detector.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="169.16mm" wi="135.55mm" file="US07296683-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="84.75mm" wi="140.12mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296683-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="230.46mm" wi="196.68mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296683-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="149.86mm" wi="119.89mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296683-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="154.86mm" wi="124.29mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296683-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="212.68mm" wi="169.59mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296683-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="133.10mm" wi="178.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296683-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="241.47mm" wi="169.42mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296683-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This is a Continuation-in-Part of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/334,847 filed Dec. 30, 2002, now abandoned.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This is a non-provisional patent application claiming the benefit of the filing date of provisional U.S. patent application Ser. No. 60/382,448 filed May 22, 2002, now abandoned.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The invention relates to metal detectors and, more particularly, to a detector that detects ferrous magnetic metal objects and generates a signal indicating the presence of the ferrous objects.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In a restaurant, many times eating utensils, such as silverware or stainless steel flatware, are accidentally thrown away and discarded unknowingly into the trash, thus costing many hundreds of dollars in loss. The problem results from the restaurant employees inadvertently tossing the silverware or flatware into the garbage while cleaning food and other waste from the restaurant's clientele's used plates.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Some restaurant kitchens use automatic means for rinsing and removing food and garbage from the plates. Also, food scrapers may be used to clean debris from the plates. The eating utensils may be inadvertently disposed of without the kitchen help being aware of the problem.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A flatware recover food scraper is disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 4,367,138 to Kustas and includes a cylindrically shaped rubber food scraper mounted to a table over a refuse container, which is located below the table. Food and waste is scraped from the dishes and the stainless steel flatware is attracted to and held by magnets located within the scraper.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">U.S. Pat. No. 4,494,657 to Oldenkamp discloses an integral housing member for removing magnetic articles from a flow of loosely packed material. The housing includes a magnetic article assembly which attracts and removes magnetic articles responsive to the magnetic field from a loosely packed material flow which is directed through the housing.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">U.S. Pat. No. 4,279,744 to Antonwitsch discloses an apparatus for removing magnetic articles from a flow of loosely packed material. The apparatus includes an elongated shaft attached to a plurality of magnetic members for attracting, removing, and holding the magnetic articles.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">However, these devices which attract and remove magnetic articles may miss silverware or flatware which is wrapped within napkins or positioned behind other non-magnetic articles. These devices do not detect the presence of eating utensils or signal a person that the eating utensil is being thrown away. Therefore, if the device does not actually attract and remove the eating utensil, then the eating utensil remains in the garbage.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">U.S. Pat. No. 6,833,789 to Carmen discloses a detector having a coil detect the presence of magnetized ferrous metal objects. However, Carmen uses an oscillator to generate a voltage on the coil, which requires FCC approval. Additionally, Carmen does not use a non-ferrous core, the use of which would enhance the detection of the metal object.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">U.S. Pat. No. 5,001,425 to Beling discloses a detector using a pair of detection coils and an oscillator. Beling does not use a non-ferrous core.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">U.S. Application 2002/0067163 to Goldberg discloses a detector having two separate non-ferrous cores, having a coil wound about the outside surface of each solid core. The object passes between the two cores, but not through the cores, reducing the dependability of the detector.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Therefore, what is needed is an apparatus for detecting ferrous metal eating utensils that eliminates the inadvertent disposal of the eating utensils into garbage cans by utilizing a pick-up coil wound about a non-ferrous core that generates a voltage when a magnetized object passes through the coil and signals, either audibly and/or visually, a person that the eating utensil has been thrown into the garbage can. A person can then retrieve the eating utensil from the garbage.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">An electronic ferrous metal detector for detecting a magnetized ferrous metal material or eating utensil passing through an opening in an object includes a coil wound on a non-ferrous core positioned circumferentially about the opening in the object or a garbage can for the passage of the ferrous metal material therethrough. The pick-up coil is positioned circumferentially about the opening and about the non-ferrous core for generating a voltage as the magnetic ferrous metal material is passed through the coil wound on the non-ferrous core and through the pick-up coil for detecting any ferrous metal material passing through the pick-up coil.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">An electronic compartment houses electronic circuitry electrically connected to the pick-up coil for receiving the voltage generated by the pick-up coil and for producing an output. An alarm is electrically coupled to the electronic circuitry for receiving the output of the electronic circuitry housed with the electronic compartment and for signaling a person that the magnetized ferrous metal material has passed through the pick-up coil and through the opening in the object.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The pick-up coil has a sufficient number of wire windings wound about the non-ferrous core to produce the voltage. A power supply is electrically coupled to the electronic circuitry for providing power to the electronic ferrous metal detector. A reset switch is electrically coupled to the signaling device for resetting the signaling device. An on/off switch may be electrically coupled to the power supply for turning on and off the metal detector. A microprocessor may be coupled to the metal detector for controlling various functions of the metal detector, such as warning when the batteries are low, turning off the alarm if the alarm is not tended to in one minute, extending the life of the battery by turning the power supply on and off, for example, every 10 milliseconds, or by controlling any other desired function of the metal detector. Also, a solar panel may be added to trickle charge the batteries.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">While the specification concludes with claims particularly pointing out and distinctly claiming the subject matter of the invention, it is believed the invention will be better understood from the following description, taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an isometric view of a garbage can having an electronic ferrous metal detector;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a plan view of the electronic ferrous metal detector positioned in a garbage can lid of the garbage can with associated electronic components;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side view of the electronic ferrous metal detector positioned in the garbage can lid of the garbage can with associated electronic components;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of the electronic ferrous metal detector without a microprocessor;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block diagram of the electronic ferrous metal detector with a microprocessor;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a view of a pick-up detector coil wound clockwise about a non-ferrous core of the electronic ferrous metal detector;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a side view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> showing the position of the clockwise wound detector coil and showing an electronic compartment positioned within the garbage can lid and having a DC voltage power supply;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a partial isometric view of the detector coil wound about the non-ferrous core for forming a detector coil loop: and</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a schematic representation of the electronic ferrous metal detector.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The invention described herein provides a metal detector positioned within a lid of a garbage can which can detect when ferrous metals are passed through the lid, such as knives, forks, spoons, and the like. An alarm is sounded or lit to alert a person that a ferrous metal piece has accidentally been thrown away so that it can be retrieved.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-5</figref>, an electronic ferrous metal detector <b>10</b> is attached to a garbage can lid <b>12</b> for detecting ferrous metal. A ferrous metal is any metal that a magnet is attracted to. The garbage can lid <b>12</b> has a hole <b>14</b> for the disposal of garbage therethrough and a handle <b>15</b>. The metal detector <b>10</b> may be positioned on various types of garbage cans, or may be used in various other applications, such as in areas other than the restaurant industry, for the detection and warning of ferrous metal objects.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The metal detector <b>10</b> can be used to detect the passage of ferrous metal objects through the metal detector <b>10</b>, such as to detect the inadvertent disposal of ferrous metal into a garbage can <b>16</b>. For the restaurant industry, the ferrous metal may be silverware, stainless steel flatware, or any other type of eating utensil <b>18</b>. For the metal detector <b>10</b> to detect the eating utensils, the eating utensils <b>18</b> must be slightly magnetized, which most silverware is.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The metal detector <b>10</b> will not detect non-ferrous material, such as aluminum cans, aluminum foil, non-magnetized objects, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The electronic ferrous metal detector <b>10</b> with alarm includes a ferrous metal pick-up coil <b>20</b> positioned about the hole <b>14</b> of the garbage can lid <b>12</b>. The pick-up coil <b>20</b> includes a wire wound around a non-ferrous, non-magnetic core <b>24</b>. The pick-up coil <b>20</b> is wound with the correct type of wire and enough wire sufficient for a strong enough signal when the magnetized ferrous metal passes through the pick-up coil <b>20</b> to produce a voltage in the coils <b>20</b>. As one example, the wire of the coil <b>20</b> may be a 30 gauge piece of wire which is approximately 3000 feet long and should have a sufficient number of windings and turnings to provide enough gain or induction for the coil <b>20</b> to be sensitive enough to detect a slightly magnetized object.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The core <b>24</b> may be brass, plastic, or any other suitable piece of non-ferrous, non-magnetic material. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, which illustrates one example of the shape of the core <b>24</b>, the core <b>24</b> may be a ring shaped material having an opening <b>23</b> therethrough. The core <b>24</b> may be a solid non-ferrous rod bent into a circular configuration, may be a continuous piece of material, or may have any other suitable configuration. Preferably, the opening <b>23</b> of the core <b>24</b> has a shape conforming to the shape of the hole <b>14</b> of the garbage can lid <b>12</b>. The non-ferrous core <b>24</b> is positioned circumferentially about the hole <b>14</b> of the garbage can lid <b>12</b>, thereby aligning the opening <b>23</b> of the core <b>24</b> and the hole <b>14</b> of the garbage can lid <b>12</b>, so that the garbage passes through the opening <b>23</b> in the core <b>24</b> and through the opening <b>14</b> of the garbage can lid <b>12</b> into the garbage can <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-8</figref>, the wire of the coil <b>20</b> is wrapped clockwise around the non-ferrous core <b>24</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the core <b>24</b> may be a solid circular member having the wire of the coil <b>20</b> wrapped around the longitudinal axis of the core <b>24</b>, thereby positioning the coil <b>20</b> about both the inside and outside diameters of the annularly shaped core <b>24</b>. The positioning of the coil <b>20</b> in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-8</figref> is merely for illustrative purposes. The actual windings may be closer together, may be tighter, may have a greater number of windings, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The coil <b>20</b>, including multiple windings about the core <b>24</b>, forms a detector loop, having a top portion <b>25</b> and a center <b>27</b> for providing an optimum location for detecting the passage of silverware therethrough, and through the hole <b>14</b> of the garbage can. The clockwise wrapping of the coil <b>20</b> directs the sensitivity toward the top portion <b>25</b> and toward the center <b>27</b> of the detector coil loop <b>20</b>, which in effect directs the sensitivity toward the top and center <b>14</b> of the opening or hole in the garbage can lid <b>12</b> for enhancing detection of the ferrous metal as the object or flatware passes through the hole <b>14</b>. The clockwise wrapping gives the detector coil <b>20</b> more sensitivity in the direction needed to detect the flatware or object going though the opening <b>14</b> in the lid <b>12</b>, thus lessening missed flatware.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-8</figref>, in combination with the schematic representation of the electronic ferrous metal detector in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, pick-up coil connection wire <b>30</b> is attached to the pick-up coil <b>20</b> and is electronically coupled to an electronic compartment <b>32</b>. The electronic compartment <b>32</b> houses all of the electronic circuitry <b>34</b>, such as a printed circuit board (PCB) <b>36</b>, an operational amplifier (op-amp) <b>46</b>, capacitors, resistors, diodes, switching devices, or other electronic components. A reset switch <b>40</b> is attached to the electronic compartment <b>32</b> and is coupled to the PCB <b>36</b> and/or to an alarm <b>44</b> for resetting the circuitry of the ferrous metal detector <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">A signaling device or alarm <b>44</b> is attached to the garbage can lid <b>12</b> and electronically coupled to the electronic components or circuitry <b>34</b> housed within the electronic compartment <b>32</b>. The alarm <b>44</b> may be a peizo type of alarm, may be a buzzer, or the like to audibly alert a person, or alternatively, may be a light, such as a LED, or the like to visually alert a person, or may be combinations thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the electronic compartment <b>32</b> further houses a DC voltage source <b>45</b>, such as a battery. The DC voltage source <b>45</b> provides a small DC (direct current) Bias voltage through wire <b>30</b> to the coil <b>20</b> to increase the sensitivity to the magnetic field. The use of DC voltage eliminates the need to use an oscillator. The DC Bias voltage provides sensitivity to the incoming magnetized ferrous metal flatware or other object. The combination of the clockwise winding and the use of the DC Bias voltage causes the detection of the magnetic ferrous material to be more to the top and to the center of the detector coil <b>20</b> and more to the center <b>14</b> of the opening of the garbage can lid <b>12</b> as well as more sensitive. The DC Bias voltage also stabilizes the detector coil <b>20</b> at a preset voltage level, thus eliminating possible false triggering from other magnetic fields.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The detector coil <b>20</b> wound around the non-ferrous core <b>24</b> produces the pick-up detector loop for the slightly magnetized ferrous metals passing through the windings of the coil <b>20</b> and through the core <b>24</b>. When the magnetic ferrous metal object passes through the windings of the pick-up detector loop, a small voltage is generated in the detector coil <b>20</b>. The voltage output of the coil <b>20</b> is transferred to an amplifying circuit, such as the op-amp <b>46</b>, that is then passed to a comparator <b>48</b> where it is compared to a reference to produce a sensitivity range. The output of the comparator <b>48</b> can switch the gate of a switch <b>50</b>, such as a silicone controlled rectifier (SCR), Triac, or the like for turning on the alarm <b>44</b> to alert a person in the event that a piece of magnetized ferrous metal has been accidentally discarded. The alarm <b>44</b> can be turned off with a push-button, such as the reset switch <b>40</b>, that resets the alarm <b>44</b> and the circuit. The comparator/detector <b>48</b>, the op-amp <b>46</b> and the switch <b>50</b> may be housed within the compartment <b>32</b>, along with batteries.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The metal detector <b>10</b> further includes an ON-OFF button <b>52</b> attached to the garbage can lid <b>12</b> and coupled to the electronic circuitry <b>34</b> housed within the electronic compartment <b>32</b> for enabling a person to manually turn on and shut off the power of the metal detector <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The metal detector <b>10</b> may include a power supply <b>54</b>, such as a disposable battery, a rechargeable battery such as nickel cadmium, solar power, may be electrically powered, or may be powered by any other suitable type of power. As one example, the op-amp <b>46</b> may be powered by a 9V battery, a buzzer of the alarm <b>44</b> may be powered by a 15V supply, and a microprocessor may be powered by a 5V supply. As an alternative, if the metal detector <b>10</b> is electrically powered, the AC power will be changed to DC and stepped down with a transformer. The power supply <b>54</b> may be housed within the electronic compartment <b>32</b> and coupled to the electronic circuitry <b>34</b> of the metal detector <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">For the various embodiments of this invention, the same reference characters will be used to designate like parts. In addition, like functions and like interactions of the parts among the various embodiments of this invention will not be repeated for each embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">As an alternative, the efficiency and logic can be enhanced using a microprocessor and/or a switching power supply to extend the life of the batteries and to add options. As an example, the microprocessor <b>56</b> may be housed within the electronic compartment <b>32</b> and electrically coupled to the components in the compartment <b>32</b>. As an example of some of the options that the microprocessor <b>56</b> may provide include putting the electronic circuitry <b>34</b> to sleep or turning the circuitry <b>34</b> off via the microprocessor <b>56</b> to conserve batteries, add timers, customize how the circuit works via the microprocessor, supply power to all of the circuits, or other improvements, which would be cost effective and efficient. With the microprocessor <b>56</b>, the power supply <b>54</b> can be put to sleep or turned off or on by using the microprocessor or a timer <b>60</b> to turn the power supply off, for example, 10 times a second, decreasing the total length of time that the batteries are on, thus conserving battery life considerably. With the microprocessor <b>56</b>, a warning can be provided if the batteries are low, thus telling when to change battery packs, for example, by using a battery low LED <b>62</b>. Preferably, two battery packs will be used with AA batteries, one battery pack to power the alarm <b>44</b> or LEDs, and the other battery pack to power the amplifier <b>46</b> and comparator-detector <b>48</b>. LEDs could be used to warn when to change the batteries. With the microprocessor <b>56</b>, the alarm <b>44</b> or LEDs can be turned off by switch <b>64</b> in the event that the person fails to push the reset button <b>40</b> after a preset length of time, for example, a minute.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">As yet another alternative, the power supply <b>54</b> may be replaced with an oscillator or switching power supply, which can extend the life or useful range of the batteries thus allowing the metal detector <b>10</b> to operate even when the battery voltage gets low, for example, 3 volts. The metal detector <b>10</b> using a switching power supply could still produce the needed 5 volts to run the amplifier <b>46</b>, the comparator/detector <b>48</b>, and the switches even when the batteries go as low as 2-3 volts, thus extending the useful life of the batteries.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">In operation, the silverware or eating utensils <b>18</b> are slightly magnetized. If an eating utensil <b>18</b> is thrown into the garbage can <b>16</b>, the alarm <b>44</b> signals a person that a piece of magnetized ferrous metal has passed through the detector <b>10</b> and the person can retrieve the utensil <b>18</b>. The whole circuit uses an on/off switch <b>52</b> to turn the power on or off. The pick-up coil <b>20</b> is wound with enough turns and the correct type of wire to achieve the proper gain or induction that is needed when a piece of slightly magnetized ferrous metal passes by or through the coil <b>20</b> to generate or induce enough voltage and current to activate the input of the first stage of the op-amp <b>46</b>. When the power is on, the pick-up coils <b>20</b> are slightly energized due to the DC Bias voltage from the voltage source <b>45</b> and detect when a piece of magnetized ferrous metal passes through the opening in the garbage can lid <b>12</b>, or other device, generating a small electric current in the coil <b>20</b> which passes to the amplifying stage. Then, the op-amp <b>46</b> amplifies the voltage or small electric current from the coils <b>20</b> and passes the voltage to a comparator or detector <b>48</b> that is set to a preset reference point or threshold to control the sensitivity of the output of the comparator or detector <b>48</b>. Once the voltage goes past the preset reference point, the comparator/detector <b>48</b> sends a signal or the output to the gate of the switch <b>50</b>, such as a Triac or a SCR (silicone controlled rectifier), which in turn will power or carry the current to the alarm <b>44</b>. The voltage fed into the alarm <b>44</b> will activate the alarm <b>44</b>, for example, sound the buzzer or illuminate the Warning LEDs. The reset button <b>40</b> breaks the current to the switch <b>50</b> and shuts the alarm <b>44</b> off. The cycle starts over again unless the main power switch <b>52</b> is turned off.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Therefore, when a piece of magnetized ferrous metal, such as an eating utensil <b>18</b>, is passed through the pick-up coil <b>20</b>, a voltage is generated which goes to the second stage of the op-amp <b>46</b>. The voltage is amplified in the op-amp <b>46</b> and is compared to a threshold in the second stage of the op/amp <b>46</b> and the output of the comparator <b>48</b> goes high at the presence of the eating utensil <b>18</b> and powers the switch <b>50</b>, which is housed within the electronic compartment <b>32</b>, which turns on the alarm <b>44</b>. A person may retrieve the inadvertently disposed of eating utensil <b>18</b> from the garbage can <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">An advantage of the electronic ferrous metal detector <b>10</b> is that the detector can be used to prevent the loss of eating utensils, such as knives, forks, spoons, etc. By detecting the eating utensils as the utensils <b>18</b> drop into the garbage can, the eating utensils can be retrieved from the garbage can.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Another advantage of the electronic ferrous metal detector <b>10</b> is that the detector only works on magnetized ferrous metals. Non-ferrous material will not set off the alarm <b>44</b>, and therefore will not be falsely activated by aluminum foil, damp paper, etc. This is advantageous for the restaurant industry because they only want to detect and warn when eating utensils, i.e. spoons, forks, knives, etc. are accidentally discarded. Also, the metal detector <b>10</b> will still detect and warn of an accidental loss of ferrous metal even if they are wrapped in paper towels or other debris since magnetic lines of flux will go through any material.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Yet another advantage of the electronic ferrous metal detector <b>10</b> is that the metal detector <b>10</b> is an electric generator which generates a small voltage. There is no power in the coil <b>20</b> until a magnet or magnetized piece of material is passed through the coil <b>20</b>. A slight current may pass through the coil <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Another advantage of the metal detector <b>10</b> is that it can be used in many other applications to detect and warn in the event that a magnetized ferrous metal object has passed through the metal detector.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Yet another advantage of the metal detector <b>10</b> is that the use of a DC Bias voltage source eliminates the need for FCC approval, reducing the overall cost of the detector.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Thus there has been shown and described a novel electronic ferrous metal detector with an alarm which fulfills all the objects and advantages sought therefor. Many changes, modifications, variations and other uses and applications of the subject invention will, however, become apparent to those skilled in the art after considering this specification together with the accompanying drawings and claims. All such changes, modifications, variations and other uses and applications which do not depart from the spirit and scope of the invention are deemed to be covered by the invention which is limited only by the claims which follow.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electronic ferrous metal detector for detecting magnetized ferrous metal material passing through an opening in an object, the opening in the object having a center therethrough, comprising:
<claim-text>one non-ferrous core positioned circumferentially about the opening in the object for the passage of the magnetized ferrous metal material therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the magnetized ferrous metal material providing a magnetic field in the opening of the object as the magnetized ferrous metal material passes through the opening in the object;</claim-text>
<claim-text>one continuous pick-up detector coil having a top portion, the detector coil positioned circumferentially about the opening in the object and wound clockwise about the one non-ferrous core for detecting the magnetic field provided by the magnetized ferrous metal material with only the one pick-up detector coil and generating a voltage as the magnetized ferrous metal material is passed through both the non-ferrous core and through the one clockwise wound pick-up detector coil for detecting the presence of the magnetized ferrous metal material within the opening of the object;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a DC Bias voltage source electrically connected to the pick-up detector coil for providing a DC Bias voltage on the pick-up detector coil for increasing sensitivity of the detector coil and adding stability;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the clockwise winding of the detector coil and the DC Bias voltage increasing sensitivity to the magnetic field, adding stability, and directing the sensitivity toward the top portion of the detector coil and to the center of the opening in the object; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an alarm electrically coupled to the one pick-up detector coil for receiving the voltage from the one pick-up detector coil and for signaling a person that the magnetized ferrous metal material has passed through the one pick-up detector coil and through the opening in the object for detecting any magnetized ferrous metal material passing through the one pick-up detector coil.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising an electronic compartment housing electronic circuitry electrically connected to the pick-up detector coil for receiving the voltage generated by the pick-up detector coil and for producing an output, and electrically connected to the alarm for transferring the output to the alarm for controlling the alarm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the pick-up detector coil has a sufficient number of wire windings wound about the non-ferrous core.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a power supply electrically coupled to the alarm for providing power to the electronic ferrous metal detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a reset switch electrically coupled to the alarm for resetting the alarm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the alarm further comprises a light for visually signaling a person that ferrous metal material has passed through the pick-up detector coil.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the alarm includes a buzzer for audibly signaling a person that ferrous metal material has passed through the pick-up detector coil.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a microprocessor coupled to the metal detector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a timer coupled to the microprocessor for automatically resetting the alarm; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a battery low indicator coupled to the microprocessor for providing a signal when power is low.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, further comprising an on/off switch electrically coupled to the power supply for turning on and off the metal detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. An electronic ferrous metal detector for detecting a magnetized ferrous metal eating utensil that is disposed of into a garbage can by passing through a hole, having a center, in a garbage can lid, comprising:
<claim-text>a non-ferrous core having an opening therethrough, the opening conforming to a shape of the hole in the garbage can lid, the non-ferrous core positioned circumferentially about the hole in the garbage can lid;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the magnetized ferrous metal eating utensil providing a magnetic field in the hole of the garbage can lid as the magnetized ferrous metal eating utensil passes through the hole in the garbage can lid;</claim-text>
<claim-text>one pick-up detector coil wound in a clockwise direction about the non-ferrous core forming a pick-up detector loop for detecting the magnetic field provided by the magnetized ferrous metal eating utensil passing through the one pick-up detector coil, the detector loop having a top portion, passage of the magnetized ferrous metal eating utensil through the one pick-up detector coil generating a voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the clockwise winding of the detector coil around the non-ferrous core directs detection of magnetic field sensitivity to the top portion of the detector coil loop and to the center of the garbage can lid hole;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a DC Bias voltage source electrically connected to the pick-up detector coil for providing a DC Bias voltage on the pick-up detector coil for increasing sensitivity of the detector coil and adding stability;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operational amplifying circuit connected to the one pick-up detector coil for receiving the voltage generated by the one pick-up detector coil and passing the voltage therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a comparator connected to the operational amplifying circuit for receiving the voltage passed through the operational amplifying circuit, for controlling sensitivity, and for producing an output; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a signaling device connected to the comparator for receiving the output from the comparator and producing a signal to alert a person that the magnetized ferrous material eating utensil has passed through the one pick-up detector coil and into the garbage can.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising a switch electrically coupled between the comparator and the signaling device for carrying the voltage from the comparator to the signaling device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising a reset switch connected to the signaling device for resetting the signaling device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the pick-up detector coil has a sufficient number of wire windings wound about the non-ferrous core for detecting the magnetized eating utensil and producing the voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising a power supply electrically coupled to the electronic circuitry for providing power to the electronic ferrous metal detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising a microprocessor coupled to the electronic ferrous metal detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising an on/off switch electrically coupled to the power supply for turning on and off the metal detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. An electronic ferrous metal detector for detecting magnetized ferrous metal material passing through an opening in an object, comprising:
<claim-text>a non-ferrous core positionable on the object having the opening for the passage of the magnetized ferrous metal material therethrough;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the magnetized ferrous metal material providing a magnetic field in the opening of the object as the magnetized ferrous metal material passes through the opening in the object;</claim-text>
<claim-text>one pick-up detector coil having a sufficient number of wire windings wound about the non-ferrous core for detecting the magnetic field provided by the magnetized ferrous metal material and generating a voltage as the magnetized ferrous metal material passes through the one pick-up detector coil, through the non-ferrous core and through the opening of the object;</claim-text>
<claim-text>electronic circuitry electrically connected to the one pick-up detector coil for receiving the voltage generated by the one pick-up detector coil and for producing an output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a DC Bias voltage source electrically connected to the pick-up detector coil for providing a DC Bias voltage and passing the DC Bias voltage through the detector coil for increasing sensitivity and adding stability of the pick-up detector coil to the magnetic field;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a signaling device electrically coupled to the electronic circuitry for receiving the output of the electronic circuitry and for signaling a person that magnetized ferrous metal material has passed through the one pick-up detector coil and through the opening in the object; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply coupled to the electronic circuitry for supplying power to the electronic ferrous metal detector.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein the signaling device includes a light for visually signaling a person that ferrous metal material has passed through the pick-up detector coil.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein the signaling device audibly signals a person that ferrous metal material has passed through the pick-up detector coil.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The electronic ferrous metal detector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, further comprising a reset switch electrically coupled to the signaling device for resetting the signaling device.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
