<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298213-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298213</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11224557</doc-number>
<date>20050912</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2004-0078161</doc-number>
<date>20041001</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>242</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330283</main-classification>
<further-classification>330302</further-classification>
<further-classification>330307</further-classification>
<further-classification>327314</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Input impedance matching circuit for low noise amplifier</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4658220</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Heston et al.</name>
<date>19870400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330277</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6204608</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Song et al.</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3151693</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6400204</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Davis</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6674337</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hashemi et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>333 32</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6917815</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hajimiri et al.</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4555521</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7123899</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Chen et al.</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>455341</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7157972</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hajimiri et al.</name>
<date>20070100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330277</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0107056</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chin et al.</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0117206</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ohnakado</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>KO0004338</doc-number>
<date>19920600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11067486</doc-number>
<date>19990900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>English Abstract of Korean Publication No.: 1992-0004338.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00013">
<othercit>English Abstract***.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330283</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330302</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330307</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327314</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060071735</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060406</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kang</last-name>
<first-name>Sang-Hoon</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>F. Chau &amp; Assoc., LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung Electronics Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Patricia</first-name>
<department>2817</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An input impedance matching circuit for a low noise amplifier includes a source pad, a gate pad, an input transistor, a source degeneration inductor and a matching capacitor. The gate pad receives an input signal and the input transistor amplifies the input signal transmitted from the gate pad. The source degeneration inductor electrically coupled to an external ground voltage is adapted for input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier. The source pad is coupled to a source electrode of the input transistor and the matching capacitor is formed between the gate pad and the source pad extending the source pad to be disposed under the gate pad. Accordingly, impedance matching of the low noise amplifier may be facilitated and the gain and noise figure of the low noise amplifier may be improved.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="133.35mm" wi="199.73mm" file="US07298213-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="143.09mm" wi="129.12mm" file="US07298213-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="152.82mm" wi="141.90mm" file="US07298213-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="148.17mm" wi="117.01mm" file="US07298213-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="218.27mm" wi="154.35mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298213-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="123.61mm" wi="125.90mm" file="US07298213-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="242.82mm" wi="167.98mm" file="US07298213-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="252.98mm" wi="166.12mm" file="US07298213-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="254.08mm" wi="177.80mm" file="US07298213-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CLAIM FOR PRIORITY</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority under 35 USC § 119 to Korean Patent Application No. 2004-78161, filed on Oct. 1, 2004, the contents of which are herein incorporated by reference in its entirety.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a receiving end of a low noise amplifier, and more particularly to a circuit for electrostatic discharge protection and input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Generally, a low noise amplifier having improved noise characteristics is used at a radio frequency (RF) receiver end to amplify a received RF signal. In addition, the low noise amplifier is used for impedance matching between internal elements of the low noise amplifier and an external circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A degeneration inductor is widely used for impedance matching of a low noise amplifier. However, when a degeneration inductor is used for impedance matching of a low noise amplifier, noise figure may be deteriorated due to parasitic capacitance of an electrostatic discharge protection circuit and a bonding pad of the low noise amplifier so that implementing an impedance matching low noise amplifier becomes difficult.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> show equivalent circuit diagrams illustrating a receiving end of a conventional low noise amplifier <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the conventional low noise amplifier <b>10</b> includes a gate pad PG<b>1</b>, parasitic capacitors C<b>1</b> and C<b>2</b>, an electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>1</b>, an input transistor M<b>1</b>, a source pad PS<b>1</b> and a source degeneration inductor L<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A received RF signal is input to the input transistor M<b>1</b> through the gate pad PG<b>1</b> and buffered by the input transistor M<b>1</b> to be amplified. The electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>1</b> is used to protect an RF receiver chip RFIC from an external electro-static discharge. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the parasitic capacitor C<b>1</b> may be formed between the gate pad PG<b>1</b> and a substrate SUBSTRATE of the chip RFIC. In addition, the parasitic capacitor C<b>2</b> may also be formed between a source electrode and a gate electrode of the input transistor M<b>1</b> during the manufacturing process of a semiconductor.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The source degeneration inductor L<b>1</b> is used to remove a capacitance component of an impedance value (imaginary impedance) so that only a real impedance component will remain. The source degeneration inductor L<b>1</b> may be implemented using a bonding wire to couple the source pad PS<b>1</b> to an external circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The input impedance of the RF receiver chip RFIC seen by the gate pad PG<b>1</b> may be represented as a function of the capacitance of capacitor C<b>2</b>, the inductance of the source degeneration inductor L<b>1</b> and the transconductance of the input transistor M<b>1</b>. To provide a target (desired) impedance value having only a real component required by a system, for example, 50 Ω, the capacitance value of the capacitor and the inductance value of the source degeneration inductor L<b>1</b> may be adjusted to cancel each other. In addition, a matching inductor L<b>2</b>, which may be implemented in a separate chip and coupled to the gate pad PG<b>1</b>, may be used for ease of impedance matching.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">As described above, except the capacitance C<b>2</b> formed between the gate and source electrodes of the input transistor M<b>1</b>, the parasitic capacitance C<b>1</b> between the substrate and the gate pad PG<b>1</b> and the parasitic capacitance (not shown) between the substrate and the electrostatic discharge protection unit D<b>1</b> are not used for impedance matching of the low noise amplifier, causing difficulty in the impedance matching. Moreover, the parasitic capacitance may lower the gain of the low noise amplifier and result in degradation of the noise figure.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Example embodiments of the present invention provide a low noise amplifier in which parasitic capacitance at a receiving end of the low noise amplifier is used for input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier so that impedance matching may be easily performed and both gain and noise figures of the low noise amplifier may be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In some embodiments of the present invention, there is provided an input impedance matching circuit for a low noise amplifier that includes a source pad, a gate pad, an input transistor, a source degeneration inductor and a matching capacitor. The gate pad receives an input signal and the input transistor amplifies the input signal transmitted from the gate pad. The source degeneration inductor coupled to an external ground voltage is adapted for input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier. The source pad is coupled to a source electrode of the input transistor and the matching capacitor is formed between the gate pad and the source pad by extending the source pad to be disposed under the gate pad. Accordingly, impedance matching of the low noise amplifier may be facilitated and the gain and noise figure of the low noise amplifier may be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In one embodiment, the input impedance matching circuit may further include an electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the gate pad and an internal ground voltage, configured to protect the low noise amplifier from an external electro-static discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In another embodiment, the input impedance matching circuit may further include a first electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the gate pad and the source pad, for protecting the low noise amplifier from an external electro-static discharge protection and for input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier; and a second electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the source pad and an internal ground voltage and configured to protect the low noise amplifier from an external electro-static discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In other embodiments of the present invention, there is provided a low noise amplifier that includes a source pad, a gate pad, an input transistor, a load, a source degeneration inductor and a matching capacitor. The gate pad receives an input signal. The input transistor amplifies the input signal transmitted from the gate pad. The load is coupled to a drain electrode of the input transistor. The source degeneration inductor coupled to an external power supply voltage is adapted for input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier. The source pad is coupled to a source electrode of the input transistor. The matching capacitor is formed between the gate pad and the source pad by extending the source pad to be disposed under the gate pad.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In yet another embodiment, the low noise amplifier may further include an electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the gate pad and an internal ground voltage, which is adapted for protecting the low noise amplifier from an external electro-static discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In still another embodiment, the low noise amplifier may further include a first electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the gate pad and the source pad, which is adapted for protecting the low noise amplifier from an external electrostatic discharge and input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier; and a second electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the source pad and an internal ground voltage, configured to protect the low noise amplifier from an external electrostatic discharge.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The present invention will become more apparent by describing in detail exemplary embodiments thereof with reference to the attached drawings, wherein like elements are represented by like reference numerals, which are given by way of illustration only and thus do not limit the exemplary embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> show equivalent circuit diagrams illustrating a receiving end of a conventional low noise amplifier.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows an equivalent circuit diagram illustrating a receiving end of a low noise amplifier according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating the receiving end of the low noise amplifier in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows an equivalent circuit diagram illustrating a receiving end of a low noise amplifier according to another exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a plan view illustrating a structure of a pad according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a cross sectional view taken along a line I-I′ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows a plan view illustrating a structure of a pad according to another exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows a cross sectional view taken along a line II-II′ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a graph showing the noise figure of a low noise amplifier according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a graph showing the reflection coefficient of a low noise amplifier according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE EXEMPLARY EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Hereinafter, the present invention will be explained in detail with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">It will be understood that when an element is referred to as being “connected” or “coupled” to another element, it can be directly connected or coupled to the other element or intervening elements may be present. In contrast, when an element is referred to as being “directly connected” or “directly coupled” to another element, there are no intervening elements present. Other words used to describe the relationship between elements should be interpreted in a like fashion (i.e., “between” versus “directly between”, “adjacent” versus “directly adjacent”, etc.).</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The terminology used herein is for the purpose of describing particular embodiments only and is not intended to be limiting of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows an equivalent circuit diagram illustrating a receiving end of a low noise amplifier <b>30</b> according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the low noise amplifier <b>30</b> includes a gate pad PG<b>31</b>, a matching capacitor C<b>31</b>, first and second electrostatic discharge protection units D<b>31</b> and D<b>32</b>, an input transistor M<b>31</b>, a source pad PS<b>31</b> and a source degeneration inductor L<b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">A received RF signal is input to the input transistor M<b>31</b> through the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and buffered by the input transistor M<b>31</b> to be amplified. Various types of load (not shown) may be coupled to a drain terminal of the input transistor M<b>31</b> to configure the low noise amplifier.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Compared with the prior art shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the matching capacitor C<b>31</b> and the first electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b> are disposed between the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and the source pad PS<b>31</b> and used for impedance matching together with a parasitic capacitance C<b>32</b> generated during a manufacturing process of the input transistor M<b>31</b>. Because the parasitic capacitance C<b>32</b> and the transconductance of the input transistor M<b>31</b> are relevant to the characteristics of the input transistor M<b>31</b>, using only the transconductance of the input transistor M<b>31</b> and the parasitic capacitor C<b>32</b> for the impedance matching has some limitations. Therefore, according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention, the parasitic capacitance C<b>31</b> and the impedance of the first electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b> may be used to perform more precise impedance matching.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The first electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b> may be implemented as a junction diode using a transistor. The first electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b> transmits an external electro-static discharge to the second electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>32</b>. Additionally, the first electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b> provides a junction capacitance between the gate and source electrodes of the input transistor M<b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The second electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>32</b> may also be implemented as a junction diode and coupled to a ground voltage of the substrate to protect the RF receiver chip RFIC from the electro-static discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The source degeneration inductor L<b>31</b> is used to remove a capacitance component of an impedance value (imaginary impedance) so that only a real impedance component may remain. The source degeneration inductor L<b>31</b> may be implemented using a bonding wire to couple the source pad PS<b>31</b> to an external circuit. In addition, a matching inductor L<b>32</b> having a large inductance and exterior to the RF receiver chip RFIC may be coupled to the gate pad PG<b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Since the matching inductor L<b>32</b> has an inductance much larger than the inductance of the source degeneration inductor L<b>31</b>, an inductor formed between the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and the matching inductor L<b>32</b> by a wire bond is omitted throughout <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 to 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In addition, a third electro-static discharge protection unit (not shown) coupled to the gate pad PG<b>31</b> as a supply voltage may further be included in the low noise amplifier <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating the receiving end of the low noise amplifier <b>30</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the source pad P<b>31</b> may extend under the gate pad PG<b>31</b> via, for example, a metal line, so that the matching capacitor C<b>31</b> may be positioned between the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and the source pad P<b>31</b>. The first electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b> is also positioned between the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and a portion of the source pad extension PS<b>31</b> under the gate pad PG<b>31</b>. The second electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>32</b> is formed between the source pad PS<b>31</b> and a substrate SUBSTRATE.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In addition, to ensure the proper operation of each circuit device that has an impedance value including a capacitance component, a shielding and grounding voltage line (not shown) may be disposed under the first electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b>, the matching capacitor C<b>31</b>, the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and the source pad PS<b>31</b> for securing an insulation from the substrate SUBSTRATE.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows an equivalent circuit diagram illustrating a receiving end of a low noise amplifier <b>50</b> according to another exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Comparing the low noise amplifier <b>50</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> with the low noise amplifier <b>30</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> reveals a single difference, i.e., the configuration relevant to the electro-static discharge protection.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Whereas both the matching capacitor C<b>31</b> and the first electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b> are used for the input impedance matching in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, only the matching capacitor C<b>31</b> is used for input impedance matching in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>33</b> is disposed between the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and the substrate that is coupled to the ground so as to protect the gate pad PG<b>31</b> from the electro-static discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Thus, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 5</figref>, the capacitance of the electro-static discharge protection unit D<b>31</b> or D<b>33</b> may be selectively used or may not be used for impedance matching in addition to the capacitance C<b>31</b> between the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and the source pad PS<b>31</b> so that the efficiency in the input impedance matching and in a layout area may be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a plan view illustrating a structure of a pad according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a cross sectional view taken along a line I-I′ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The structure of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> may be commonly applied to both of the exemplary embodiments of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the source pad PS<b>31</b> extends under the gate pad PG<b>31</b> via, for example, a metal line PM<b>31</b> so that the matching capacitor C<b>31</b> may be formed between the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and the source pad PS<b>31</b>. In addition, the gate pad PG<b>31</b> may be positioned on the source pad extension PM<b>31</b> that is larger than an area of the gate pad PG<b>31</b> to increase the capacitance of the matching capacitor C<b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In addition, in order to shield each component of the low noise amplifier (e.g., the gate pad PG<b>31</b> or the source pad PS<b>31</b>) from the substrate SUBSTRATE, a shielding and grounding voltage line G<b>31</b> may be disposed under the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and the source pad PS<b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows a plan view illustrating a structure of a pad according to another exemplary embodiment of the present invention and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows a cross sectional view taken along a line II-II′ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 9</figref>, the source pad PS<b>31</b> extends under the gate pad PG<b>31</b> and also a signal transmission line CS<b>31</b>, through which the gate pad PG<b>31</b> is electrically coupled to the input transistor M<b>31</b> to increase the capacitance of the matching capacitor C<b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10 and 11</figref> are graphs showing the noise figure and the reflection coefficient of a low noise amplifier, respectively, according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10 and 11</figref>, the low noise amplifier according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention exhibits a lower noise figure and has relatively uniform reflection coefficients. For example, under an available certain reflection coefficient such as −16 dB, the reflection coefficients of the low noise amplifier according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention are more uniform than the prior art. Therefore, the low noise amplifier according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention may stably operate over a wide frequency band.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">As described above, by using the parasitic capacitance for input impedance matching at the receiving end of the low noise amplifier according to the exemplary embodiments of the present invention, the impedance matching of the low noise amplifier may be easily carried out. In addition, the gain and noise figure of the low noise amplifier may be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Having thus described exemplary embodiments of the present invention, it is to be understood that the invention defined by the appended claims is not to be limited by particular details set forth in the above description as many apparent variations thereof are possible without departing from the spirit or scope thereof as hereinafter claimed.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An input impedance matching circuit for a low noise amplifier, comprising:
<claim-text>a gate pad configured to receive an input signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an input transistor configured to amplify the input signal transmitted from the gate pad;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a source degeneration inductor, electrically coupled to an external ground voltage, for matching input impedance of the low noise amplifier;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a source pad coupled to a source electrode of the input transistor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a matching capacitor formed between the gate pad and the source pad by extending the source pad to be disposed under the gate pad.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising an electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the gate pad and an internal ground voltage, configured to protect the low noise amplifier from an external electro-static discharge.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the gate pad is disposed above the source pad and is insulated from the source pad.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the source pad extends under the gate pad and a signal transmission line, through which the gate pad is electrically coupled to the input transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising a shielding and grounding voltage line for shielding the source pad and the gate pad from a substrate, wherein the shielding and grounding voltage line is disposed between the source and gate pads and the substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a first electrostatic discharge protection unit disposed between the gate pad and the source pad, for input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier and protecting the low noise amplifier from an external electrostatic discharge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the source pad and an internal ground voltage and configured to protect the low noise amplifier from an external electro-static discharge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the gate pad is disposed above the source pad, and insulated from the source pad.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the source pad extends under the gate pad and a signal transmission line, through which the gate pad is electrically coupled to the input transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the first and second electrostatic discharge protection units include a junction diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising a shielding and grounding voltage line for shielding the source pad and the gate pad from a substrate, wherein the shielding and grounding voltage line is disposed between the source and gate pads and the substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A low noise amplifier comprising:
<claim-text>a gate pad configured to receive an input signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an input transistor configured to amplify the input signal transmitted from the gate pad;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a load coupled to a drain electrode of the input transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a source degeneration inductor coupled to an external power supply voltage, adapted for input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a source pad coupled to a source electrode of the input transistor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a matching capacitor formed between the gate pad and the source pad by extending the source pad to be disposed under the gate pad.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising an electro-static discharge protection unit for electro-static discharge protection, disposed between the gate pad and an internal ground voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the gate pad is disposed above the source pad and is insulated from the source pad.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein the source pad extends under the gate pad and a signal transmission line, through which the gate pad is electrically coupled to the input transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, further comprising a shielding and grounding voltage line for shielding the source pad and the gate pad from a substrate, wherein the shielding and grounding voltage line is disposed between the source and gate pads and the substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a first electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the gate pad and the source pad, for the input impedance matching of the low noise amplifier and protecting the low noise amplifier from an external electro-static discharge; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second electro-static discharge protection unit disposed between the source pad and an internal ground voltage, configured to protect the low noise amplifier from an external electro-static discharge.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the gate pad is disposed above the source pad, and is insulated from the source pad.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein the source pad extends under the gate pad and a signal transmission line, through which the gate pad is electrically coupled to the input transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the first and second electro-static discharge protection units include junction diodes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The low noise amplifier of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, further comprising a shielding and grounding voltage line for shielding the source pad and the gate pad from a substrate, wherein the shielding and grounding voltage line is disposed under the source pad and the gate pad for electro-static discharge protection.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
