<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298237-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298237</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11490325</doc-number>
<date>20060720</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>14</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>335215</main-classification>
<further-classification> 7386269</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Magnetostrictive stress wave sensor</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3945459</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Oishi et al.</name>
<date>19760300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4284863</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Breed</name>
<date>19810800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4308474</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Savage et al.</name>
<date>19811200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4342228</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Savage</name>
<date>19820800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5275049</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schiessle et al.</name>
<date>19940100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5580084</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gioutsos</name>
<date>19961200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5767766</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kwun</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5983724</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yoshida</name>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6037682</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Shoop et al.</name>
<date>20000300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6329910</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Farrington</name>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6389911</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Aoki</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6587048</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Bomya</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00013">
<othercit>“Back in Style: Magnetostrictive Sensors”, by Dr. Hegeon Kwun, Technology Today, Sep. 1991, 9pp.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00014">
<othercit>“Terfenol Basics”, web page printout, http//www.terfenoltruth.com/basics/, Oct. 13, 2003, 1p.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00015">
<othercit>“RDP Electronics &amp; MTS Temposonics Transducers Principle of Operation”; RDP Group, website printout, no date provided.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>335205-207</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>335215</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>335302-306</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7386269</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340436</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10792739</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040305</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7081801</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11490325</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060261918</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061123</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Stuve</last-name>
<first-name>Steven R.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lake Mills</city>
<state>WI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Drayer</last-name>
<first-name>Lonnie</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Steinnon</last-name>
<first-name>Patrick</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Key Safety Systems, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Sterling Heights</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Enad</last-name>
<first-name>Elvin</first-name>
<department>2832</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Rojas</last-name>
<first-name>Bernard</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A shock sensor has a housing with a Terfenol-D type sensing element positioned inside a sensing coil. A permanent biasing magnet is positioned in engagement with the Terfenol-D sensing element, and a spacer engages the Terfenol-D sensing element and extends from the housing. The housing has a beam with one or two mounting holes through which fasteners extend to mount the shock sensor to a structural member. The housing places the spacer in compression against the structural member. In an alternative embodiment a DC current can be supplied to the sensing coil to provide the biasing magnetic field. A high frequency filter separates the shock sensing signal from the applied DC biasing current.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="74.93mm" wi="111.59mm" file="US07298237-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="240.28mm" wi="177.80mm" file="US07298237-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="241.89mm" wi="166.88mm" file="US07298237-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="225.13mm" wi="166.88mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298237-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This is a Divisional of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/792,739 filed Mar. 05, 2004 now U.S. Pat. No. 7,081,801.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to shock sensors for monitoring vehicle crashes in general, and to shock sensors utilizing the magnetostrictive effect in particular.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The modern automobile is equipped with many active safety systems, from seat belt tensioners, to air bags and fuel cutoff valves. To properly trigger the activation of the various active safety systems, crash sensors are used to detect the onset of a crash and to determine the severity of a crash. To optimize the use of active safety systems it is important to know as soon as possible the likely severity of the crash. Better results can be achieved by early detection of crash severity and early deployment of active safety systems. At the same time, considerable cost can be saved if safety systems are not deployed in less severe crashes where passive restraints such a seat belts are likely to be sufficient to prevent serious injury. As automobiles employ larger numbers of air bags and other deployable safety systems, the cost of replacing deployed safety systems becomes a considerable portion of the cost of repairs following a crash. Of course, in a severe crash, when deployment of all safety systems is desired, the automobile may have little residual value due to the extensive damage caused by the crash. This tension between the benefits of early deployment versus the cost of unnecessary deployment focuses attention on sensors that can give an indication of crash severity early in a crash. One type of known shock sensor that employs the inverse magnetostrictive effect or the Villari effect, can detect shock waves in ferrous structural members. Shock waves can be signal processed to give an indicator of crash severity early in the crash sequence. However, the ability to detect shock waves in non-ferrous structural members, and a sensor having a larger output voltage are desirable to increase the utility of sensors that detect shock waves in structural members an automobile during a crash.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The shock sensor of this invention employs a Terfenol-D sensing element positioned inside a sensing coil. A permanent biasing magnet is positioned in engagement with the Terfenol-D sensing element, and a spacer engages the Terfenol-D sensing element and extends from a housing that surrounds the biasing magnet, the Terfenol-D sensing element, and the sensing coil. The housing has a beam with two spaced-apart mounting holes through which fasteners extend to mount the shock sensor to a vehicle structural member. The mounting of the beam places the spacer in compression against the vehicle structural member. The spacer, the Terfenol-D sensing element, and the biasing magnet are packaged in a sleeve that is positioned in a cylindrical portion of the beam that extends perpendicular to the beam. The beam is mounted by the fasteners to the vehicle structural member. A bobbin about which the sensing coil is wound is positioned over the Terfenol-D sensing element and the biasing magnet, and the bobbin is over-molded to the beam. Compressive waves introduced in the vehicle structural member to which the shock sensor is mounted travel through the spacer which is held in engagement with the structural member, and from the spacer to the Terfenol-D sensing element. The strain in the Terfenol-D sensing element under the influence of the magnetic field of the biasing magnet, produces a substantial change in magnetic field strength that results in the generation of voltage in the output leads of the coil.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the preferred embodiment the sensor is passive and has a large voltage output that is easily detected and digitized. In an alternative embodiment, a DC current can be supplied to the sensing coil to provide the biasing magnetic field. The voltage produced by shock traveling through the Terfenol-D sensing element can be detected by a high frequency filter that separates the shock sensing signal from the applied DC biasing current. A simple series-connected capacitor in the sensing output of the shock sensor can function as the high frequency filter.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">It is a feature of the present invention to provide a shock sensor that detects shock waves in the structural elements of a vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It is another feature of the present invention to provide a shock sensor that detects shock waves in the nonferrous structural elements of a vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is a further feature of the present invention to provide a shock sensor for early detection of crash severity.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Further features and advantages of the invention will be apparent from the following detailed description when taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an exploded isometric view of the crash sensor of this invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an isometric view of the crash sensor of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with the over-molding of the coil shown in phantom view.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an alternative embodiment of the crash sensor of this invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a side elevation, somewhat schematic view, of an automobile cut away to show the mounting of the crash sensor of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a circuit diagram a further alternative embodiment of the crash sensor of this invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref>, wherein like numbers refer to similar parts, a crash sensor <b>20</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The crash sensor <b>20</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, has three functional elements: a Terfenol-D (Tb0.3 Dy0.7 Fe1.92) sensing element <b>22</b>, a biasing magnet <b>24</b>, and a sensing coil <b>26</b> mounted on a housing <b>27</b>. The housing <b>27</b> has a cylindrical portion <b>32</b> that projects from a beam <b>34</b>. The shock sensor <b>20</b> incorporates a bobbin <b>28</b> on which the sensing coil <b>26</b> is wound. The bobbin <b>28</b> has a central aperture <b>30</b> that fits over the cylindrical housing portion <b>32</b>. The sensing coil <b>26</b> can have for example, around 1,000 turns of thirty-six gauge wire. The beam <b>34</b> extends on either side of the cylindrical housing portion <b>32</b> and has two apertures <b>36</b>, one formed in each end <b>38</b> of the beam. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a sleeve <b>40</b> is loaded with a cylindrical biasing magnet <b>24</b>, a cylindrical Terfenol-D sensing element <b>22</b> and a cylindrical spacing element <b>42</b> that protrudes from the sleeve <b>40</b>. The biasing magnet <b>24</b>, the Terfenol-D sensing element <b>22</b> and the cylindrical spacing element <b>42</b> can be press fit or bonded to the sleeve <b>40</b>. The sleeve <b>40</b> is positioned within the cylindrical housing <b>32</b> so that the spacing element <b>42</b> protrudes beyond a land <b>44</b>, on the bottom surface <b>46</b> of the beam <b>34</b>. The sleeve <b>40</b> can be press fit or bonded within the cylindrical housing <b>32</b>. The bobbin <b>28</b> about which the sensing coil <b>26</b> is wound is surrounded by an over molded enclosure <b>48</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">End bosses or lands <b>50</b> surround the apertures <b>36</b> and define a mounting plane. Fasteners <b>52</b> extend through the end apertures <b>36</b> of the beam <b>34</b> and mount the crash sensor <b>20</b> to a structural element <b>54</b> of an automobile <b>56</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The cylindrical spacing element <b>42</b> extends beyond the mounting plane so that when the end bosses <b>50</b> are brought into contact with a portion of a structural element <b>54</b>, the spacing element <b>42</b> is resiliently compressed by the flexure of portions <b>57</b> of the housing <b>27</b> between the fasteners <b>52</b> and the Terfenol-D sensing element. This resilient flexure of housing portions <b>57</b> in turn compresses the Terfenol-D sensing element against the structural element <b>54</b> of the automobile <b>56</b>. This compressive loading assures good transmission of shock waves from the structural element <b>54</b> to the Terfenol-D sensing element <b>22</b>. To improve the transmission of shock from the spacing element <b>42</b> to the Terfenol-D, the spacing element <b>42</b> is preferably bonded with an adhesive to the sensing element.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The output from the coil may be from about 0.2 to 2.0 volts or greater, depending on the number of turns in the sensing coil <b>26</b>, the biasing field of the biasing magnet <b>24</b>, the composition of the structural member to which the crash sensor <b>20</b> is mounted, the force of the pre-load on the spacing element <b>42</b> and other factors affecting coupling between the Terfenol-D sensing element <b>22</b> and the structural material to which the crash sensor <b>20</b> is mounted.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">An alternative embodiment shock sensor <b>58</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The shock sensor <b>58</b> is similar to the shock sensor <b>20</b>, but has only one mounting aperture <b>60</b> in an end <b>62</b> of a cantilever beam <b>64</b>, rather than the two apertures <b>36</b> on the opposite ends of the beam <b>34</b> of the shock sensor <b>20</b>. The shock sensor <b>58</b> has a housing <b>59</b> with a cantilever beam <b>64</b> that forms a biasing member that resiliently compresses the sensing element by way of a spacing element <b>66</b> against the structural element <b>54</b> of the automobile <b>56</b>. The spacing element <b>66</b>, as in the device <b>20</b>, engages a biasing magnet that extends within the sensing coil <b>26</b> formed on a bobbin.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The shock sensor <b>58</b> housing has a boss <b>68</b> that surrounds the opening into which the spacing element <b>66</b> is fitted. A mounting boss <b>70</b> projects from the housing around a mounting aperture <b>60</b>, and a mounting plane is defined by the mounting boss <b>70</b>. The spacing element <b>66</b> extends from the housing beyond the mounting plane. Flexure of the cantilever beam <b>64</b> caused by the spacing element <b>66</b> extending beyond the mounting plane causes the compressive loading between the spacing element <b>66</b> and the structural element <b>54</b> of the automobile <b>56</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">It should be understood that the spacing element <b>42</b> could be omitted and the Terfenol-D sensing element extended to engage the automobile structural element <b>54</b>. A second biasing magnet could also be used between the spacing element <b>42</b> and the Terfenol-D sensing element <b>22</b>, or instead of the spacing element <b>42</b> to increase the strength of the biasing magnetic field. The magnet will preferably be of a high-strength type such as those fabricated with a rare earth metal, for example neodymium-iron-boron magnets.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The biasing magnet <b>24</b> can be replaced with a DC voltage <b>72</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> which is applied to the sensing coil <b>74</b> that contains a Terfenol-D sensing element <b>76</b>. The output of the coil <b>74</b> may be applied to a high frequency filter such as formed by capacitor <b>78</b>. The high frequency filter separates the voltage produced by the shock wave passing through the Terfenol-D sensing element from the supplied DC biasing voltage <b>72</b>. The output of the high frequency filter can be supplied to a safety system <b>80</b> or other processing circuit for characterizing an automobile crash</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Terfenol-D is an alloy of Tb0.3 Dy0.7 Fe1.92 but the term giant magnetostrictive material is defined to include Terfenol-D and various alloys of highly magnetostrictive rare earths such as Tb and Dy, as claimed in U.S. Pat. No. 4,308,474 which is incorporated herein by reference. A sensing assembly is defined which include the sensing element <b>22</b> alone or the sensing element plus the spacing element <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">It is understood that the invention is not limited to the particular construction and arrangement of parts herein illustrated and described, but embraces all such modified forms thereof as come within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A shock wave sensor in an automobile comprising:
<claim-text>a housing, the housing having a portion providing a mounting surface for attachment to an automobile structural element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a giant magnetostrictive sensing element mounted to the housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coil mounted to the housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a DC power source connected to the coil to form a biasing magnet, the coil being positioned to provide a biasing magnetic field to the giant magnetostrictive sensing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electronic filter connected across the coil for sensing a change in magnetic field produced by a shock wave in the giant magnetostrictive sensing element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fastener extending between the housing and an automobile structural element to hold the mounting surface of the housing against the automobile structural element, wherein the giant magnetostrictive sensing element is directly, or through a spacer in engagement with and located between the giant magnetostrictive sensing element and the automobile structural element, loaded against the automobile structural element when the portion of the housing providing a mounting surface is held by the fastener against the automobile structural element; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the housing has a portion that extends between the mounting surface and the giant magnetostrictive sensing element, that resiliently biases the giant magnetostrictive sensing element or the spacer against the automobile structural element thereby compressively loading the giant magnetostrictive sensing element against the spacer or the automotive structural element directly to improve shock wave transmission to the giant magnetostrictive sensing element.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the giant magnetostrictive sensing element is bonded to the spacer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the giant magnetostrictive sensing element is composed of Terfenol-D.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the housing has two mounting surfaces, and wherein the giant magnetostrictive sensing element is located between the mounting surfaces, and wherein the housing has a portion between each mounting surface and the giant magnetostrictive sensing element that resiliently biases the giant magnetostrictive sensing element or the spacer against the automobile structural element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a second biasing magnet between the spacing element and the giant magnetostrictive element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the spacer is a second biasing magnet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein each of the magnetostrictive sensing elements, the biasing magnet and the spacer are cylindrical.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further comprises a cylindrical sleeve, having the cylindrical biasing magnet, the cylindrical giant magnetostrictive sensing element and the cylindrical spacing element loaded therein and wherein the spacing element protrudes from the sleeve and the sleeve is press fit or bonded within a cylindrical portion of the housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the giant magnetostrictive sensing element, the biasing magnet and the spacer are press fit or bonded to the sleeve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The shock wave sensor of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the giant magnetostrictive sensing element has one of either the biasing magnet or the spacer bonded to the giant magnetostrictive sensing element at each end.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
