<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297603-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297603</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11093381</doc-number>
<date>20050331</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>315</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>336</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438289</main-classification>
<further-classification>257E21135</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Bi-directional transistor and method therefor</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4847522</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fuller et al.</name>
<date>19890700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6084264</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Darwish</name>
<date>20000700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6351009</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kocon et al.</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6573562</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Parthasarathy et al.</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257338</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6624469</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Harada</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6661277</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Dabral</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6674305</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Sheng et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>326 81</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6777745</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hshieh et al.</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6916712</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kocon et al.</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6943408</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Wu et al.</name>
<date>20050900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>Data Sheet “NTLTD7900ZR2 Power MOSFET 9A, 20 V, Logic Level, N-Channel Micro-8 Leadless”, Semiconductor Components Industries, LLC, Aug. 2004—Rev. 4, pp. 1-7.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438270</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438289</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>738271</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21135</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060226439</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061012</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Robb</last-name>
<first-name>Stephen P.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fountain Hills</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Robb</last-name>
<first-name>Francine Y.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fountain Hills</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hightower</last-name>
<first-name>Robert F.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Scottsdale</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hightower</last-name>
<first-name>Robert F.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Semiconductor Components Industries, L.L.C.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Phoenix</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Geyer</last-name>
<first-name>Scott B.</first-name>
<department>2812</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Ullah</last-name>
<first-name>Elias</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">In one embodiment, a transistor is formed to conduct current in both directions through the transistor.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="134.79mm" wi="249.51mm" file="US07297603-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="131.57mm" wi="95.17mm" file="US07297603-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="197.95mm" wi="157.48mm" file="US07297603-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="250.61mm" wi="155.19mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297603-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="221.74mm" wi="172.30mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297603-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="256.88mm" wi="160.61mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297603-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="252.56mm" wi="160.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297603-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is related to an application entitled “METHOD OF FORMING AN INTEGRATED POWER DEVICE AND STRUCTURE” that is filed concurrently herewith having at least one common inventor, a common assignee, and an Ser. No. of 11/095,135.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates, in general, to electronics, and more particularly, to methods of forming semiconductor devices and structure.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In the past, portable electronic systems often were powered by multiple power sources such as one of two batteries or from a battery and an AC wall outlet via an ac/dc converter or battery charger. A network of switches generally was used to control the flow of power depending on the mode of operation. For instance, if the portable device was powered from a primary battery while a secondary battery was charged, some switches were closed while other switches were open. In another mode, the switches may have been reversed. To be effective in all modes, the switches should have conducted and blocked in both directions. However, power metal oxide semiconductor field effect transistors (power MOSFETs) could only block voltage in one direction. In the reverse direction the body diode of the MOSFET conducted current, thus, two power MOSFETs typically were connected in series to function as one switch. The two power MOSFETS typically were used with their drains tied together so that when the gate voltage was zero, one of the devices would always block the voltage applied across the two transistors regardless of the polarity. One example of such a switch was the NTLTD7900 offered by ON Semiconductor of Phoenix Ariz. Because such switches used two transistors, the switches used twice as much silicon as one transistor which increased the costs. Additionally, the on-resistance was high because the two transistors were in series.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Accordingly, it is desirable to have a method of forming a bi-directional switch that reduces costs, and that reduces the resistance of the bi-directional switch.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> schematically illustrates a circuit representation of a portion of an embodiment of a bi-directional transistor in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> schematically illustrates an enlarged plan view of a portion of an embodiment of the bi-directional transistor of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional portion of the embodiment of the bi-directional transistor of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> schematically illustrates an enlarged plan view of a portion of an alternate embodiment of the bi-directional transistor of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1-FIG</figref>. <b>3</b> in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional portion of the embodiment of the bi-directional transistor of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> in accordance with the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional portion of an alternate embodiment of the bi-directional transistor of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> in accordance with the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">For simplicity and clarity of illustration, elements in the figures are not necessarily to scale, and the same reference numbers in different figures denote the same elements. Additionally, descriptions and details of well-known steps and elements are omitted for simplicity of the description. As used herein current carrying electrode means an element of a device that carries current through the device such as a source or a drain of an MOS transistor or an emitter or a collector of a bipolar transistor or a cathode or anode of a diode, and a control electrode means an element of the device that controls current through the device such as a gate of an MOS transistor or a base of a bipolar transistor. Although the devices are explained herein as certain N-channel or P-Channel devices, a person of ordinary skill in the art will appreciate that complementary devices are also possible in accordance with the present invention. For clarity of the drawings, doped regions of device structures are illustrated as having generally straight line edges and precise angular corners. However, those skilled in the art understand that due to the diffusion and activation of dopants the edges of doped regions are generally not straight lines and the corners are not precise angles.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> schematically illustrates a circuit representation of a bi-directional transistor <b>10</b> that can conduct current in both directions through transistor <b>10</b> and block reverse voltages in both directions across transistor <b>10</b>. Transistor <b>10</b> includes a first MOS transistor <b>11</b>, a first switch or first switch transistor <b>14</b>, and a second switch or second switch transistor <b>17</b>. Transistor <b>10</b> also includes a control electrode or gate <b>21</b> and current carrying electrodes <b>22</b> and <b>23</b> that can function as the source and drain of transistor as will be seen further hereinafter. Although transistors <b>10</b>, <b>11</b>, <b>14</b>, and <b>17</b> are illustrated and described herein as N-channel transistors, transistor <b>10</b> and transistors <b>11</b>, <b>14</b>, and <b>17</b> may also be implemented as P-channel transistors. As will be seen further hereinafter, transistor <b>11</b> includes a body region or body <b>12</b> that is isolated from both current carrying electrodes of transistor <b>11</b>. In order to facilitate the bi-directional current conduction through transistor <b>10</b>, body <b>12</b> is not directly connected to either current carrying electrode of transistor <b>11</b> but is selectively coupled to either of current carrying electrodes <b>22</b> and <b>23</b> by transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> responsively to the signals that are applied on the first current carrying electrode and the second current carrying electrode of transistor <b>10</b>. The source of a transistor typically is the electrode connected to the body of the transistor. Because body <b>12</b> is not directly connected to either the source or the drain of transistor <b>11</b>, it is not clear in the circuit schematic representation of transistor <b>10</b> which current carrying electrode of transistor <b>10</b> is identified as the source or the drain of transistor <b>10</b>. A parasitic source-drain diode of transistor <b>14</b> is illustrated by a diode <b>15</b>, and a parasitic source-drain diode of transistor <b>17</b> is illustrated by a diode <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In operation, if the voltage of the signal applied to current carrying electrode <b>22</b> is greater than the voltage of the signal applied to current carrying electrode <b>23</b>, then electrode <b>22</b> functions as the drain and electrode <b>23</b> functions as a source of transistors <b>10</b> and <b>11</b>. If the voltage applied to gate <b>21</b> relative to the voltage applied to electrode <b>23</b> is less than the threshold voltage of transistor <b>11</b>, transistor <b>11</b> is in an off state. The gate of transistor <b>14</b> is at a low voltage, thus, transistor <b>14</b> is also off. The gate of transistor <b>17</b> is at the voltage that is applied to electrode <b>22</b>. Assuming that the voltage applied to electrode <b>22</b> is greater than the threshold of transistor <b>17</b>, transistor <b>17</b> is turned on and couples body <b>12</b> to current carrying electrode <b>23</b> thereby ensuring that body <b>12</b> is connected to the lowest voltage that is applied to transistor <b>10</b>. This facilitates transistor <b>10</b> withstanding the voltage applied between electrodes <b>22</b> and <b>23</b>. If the voltage applied to gate <b>21</b> is changed to be greater than the threshold voltage of transistor <b>11</b>, transistor <b>11</b> is on, thus, the voltage on electrode <b>22</b> is substantially the same as the voltage applied to electrode <b>23</b> (minus the Vds-on of transistor <b>11</b>). Consequently, the voltage applied to the gate of transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> is also low and both of transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> are off. Body <b>12</b> is floating but, due to diode <b>18</b>, will never be more that about 0.6 V greater than the voltage on electrode <b>23</b>. Since transistor <b>11</b> is on, current can flow from electrode <b>22</b> through transistor <b>11</b> to electrode <b>23</b>. Because transistor <b>10</b> is on, transistor <b>11</b> does not have to block voltages applied between electrodes <b>22</b> and <b>23</b> thus the connection of body <b>12</b> is not important.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">If these signals applied to electrodes <b>22</b> and <b>23</b> are reversed such that the highest voltage is applied to electrode <b>23</b> and the lower voltage is applied to electrode <b>22</b>, then electrode <b>22</b> functions as the source and electrode <b>23</b> functions as the drain of transistors <b>10</b> and <b>11</b>. If the voltage applied to gate <b>21</b> is again less than the threshold voltage of transistor <b>11</b> relative to the voltage applied to electrode <b>22</b>, then transistor <b>11</b> is off. The gate of transistor <b>17</b> receives the low voltage from electrode <b>22</b>, thus transistor <b>17</b> is off. The gate of transistor <b>14</b> receives the high voltage from electrode <b>23</b> which enables transistor <b>14</b> to connect body <b>12</b> to electrode <b>22</b> and to the lowest voltage applied to transistor <b>10</b>. This connection facilitates transistor <b>10</b> withstanding the voltage applied between electrodes <b>22</b> and <b>23</b>. If the voltage applied to gate <b>21</b> is changed to be greater than the threshold voltage of transistor <b>11</b>, transistor <b>11</b> is on and current flow is enabled from electrode <b>23</b> through transistor <b>11</b> to electrode <b>22</b>. Because transistor <b>11</b> is on, the voltage on electrode <b>23</b> is substantially the same as the voltage applied to electrode <b>22</b> (minus the Vds-on of transistor <b>11</b>). Consequently the voltage applied to the gate of transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> is also low and both of transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> are off. Body <b>12</b> is floating but, due to diode <b>15</b>, will never be more that about 0.6 V greater than the voltage on electrode <b>22</b>. Since transistor <b>11</b> is on, transistor <b>11</b> does not have to block voltages thus the connection of body <b>12</b> is not important.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In order to assist in providing this functionality for transistor <b>10</b>, a drain of transistor <b>14</b> is commonly connected to the gate of transistor <b>17</b> and current carrying electrode <b>22</b> of transistors <b>10</b> and <b>11</b>. A source of transistor <b>14</b> is commonly connected to body <b>12</b> and to the source of transistor <b>17</b>. A drain of transistor <b>17</b> is commonly connected to the gate of transistor <b>14</b> and to current carrying electrode <b>23</b> of transistors <b>10</b> and <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates an enlarged plan view of a portion of an embodiment of transistor <b>10</b> that is described in the description of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional portion of the embodiment of transistor <b>10</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> along section line <b>3</b>-<b>3</b>. For clarity of the drawings, section <b>3</b>-<b>3</b> is drawn through transistor <b>10</b> at an angle in order to show a maximum of underlying features. Those skilled in the art will realize that using an angle cross-section will show underlying features as distorted from a right angle cross-section line, however such distortion is not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> for clarity of the drawings and clarity of the explanation. This description has references to both <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. In one embodiment, transistor <b>11</b> is an N-channel vertical power MOSFET that has trench gates and transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> are lateral N-channel transistors. In this embodiment, transistor <b>11</b> has multiple trench gates that typically extend parallel to each other laterally across a semiconductor substrate <b>35</b>. Substrate <b>35</b> typically includes a bulk N-type substrate <b>30</b> and an N-type epitaxial layer <b>32</b> that is formed on a surface of bulk substrate <b>30</b>. Transistors <b>11</b>, <b>14</b>, and <b>17</b> are formed on a first surface of substrate <b>35</b>. A conductor <b>31</b> is formed on a second surface of substrate <b>30</b> and functions as a portion of electrode <b>23</b> of transistor <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Transistor <b>11</b> includes a first doped region <b>47</b> that is formed on the first surface of substrate <b>35</b>. Region <b>47</b> functions as body <b>12</b> of transistor <b>11</b> and has a conductivity type that is opposite to the conductivity type of layer <b>32</b>. The doping concentration of region <b>47</b> generally is greater than the doping concentration of layer <b>32</b> in order to provide a channel region and to block voltages applied to transistor <b>10</b>. Regions <b>47</b> and layer <b>32</b> assist in blocking reverse voltages applied to transistor <b>10</b> such as when the voltage applied to electrode <b>23</b> is greater than the voltage applied to electrode <b>22</b>. Region <b>47</b> may be doped with boron at a peak concentration between about 1E16to 1E18 atoms/cm<sup>3</sup>. Region <b>47</b> often is referred to as a pHV region. A doped region <b>48</b> and a doped region <b>49</b> are formed within region <b>47</b> in order to facilitate making electrical contact to region <b>47</b>. Regions <b>48</b> and <b>49</b> typically are the same conductivity as region <b>47</b> and have a higher doping concentration. Trenches are formed extending from the surface of substrate <b>35</b> through region <b>47</b> into layer <b>32</b> in order to form trench type gates <b>26</b>, <b>27</b>, and <b>28</b> for transistor <b>11</b>. Gates <b>26</b>, <b>27</b>, and <b>28</b> are identified in general by arrows. Section line <b>3</b>-<b>3</b> only cuts through gates <b>26</b>, <b>27</b>, and <b>28</b> so only these gates are illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> even though the illustration of transistor <b>11</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows more gates that gates <b>26</b>, <b>27</b>, and <b>28</b>. An insulator <b>51</b>, such as silicon dioxide, is formed along the side walls and bottom of each trench. The remainder of the trench is filled with a gate conductor <b>52</b>, such as polysilicon, in order to form gates <b>26</b>, <b>27</b>, and <b>28</b>. Conductor <b>52</b> typically is covered with another portion of insulator <b>51</b>. A doped region <b>56</b> is formed on the surface of substrate <b>35</b> and disposed between each trench gate in order to function as a first current carrying electrode (CCE1) for transistor <b>11</b>. Regions <b>56</b> are opposite in conductivity to region <b>47</b>. Regions <b>56</b> may be doped with arsenic to a peak doping concentration between about 5E19 and 1E21 atoms/cm<sup>3</sup>. Regions <b>56</b> typically extend from the surface of substrate <b>35</b> a first distance into region <b>47</b>, typically about 0.15 microns. High voltage regions are formed to assist in blocking forward voltages such as when the voltage applied to electrode <b>22</b> is greater than the voltage applied to electrode <b>23</b>. High voltage regions, also referred to as an nHV region, are formed as doped regions <b>55</b> that extend from the surface of substrate <b>35</b> a second distance into region <b>47</b>, typically about 0.5 microns, that is greater than the first distance of region <b>56</b> in order to underlie regions <b>56</b>. Regions <b>55</b> may be formed before regions <b>56</b> and a portion of regions <b>55</b> may be over doped to form regions <b>56</b>. Regions <b>55</b> generally have a doping concentration that is less than the doping concentration of regions <b>56</b> in order to provide a high forward breakdown voltage between region <b>47</b> and regions <b>55</b>. A transistor without regions <b>55</b> would be able to sustain only a very small reverse voltage, typically less than about eight volts (8 V). However, because of regions <b>55</b> transistor <b>10</b> can sustain a large forward voltage. Regions <b>55</b> may have a peak doping concentration of about 1E16 to 1E18 atoms/cm<sup>3 </sup>to facilitate transistor <b>10</b> sustaining a forward breakdown voltage of at least about fifteen to fifty volts (15-50 V). The forward breakdown voltage can be increased by changing other parameters of transistor <b>10</b> such as the thickness of the gate insulator or the depth of the gates of transistor <b>11</b>. The P-N junction formed at the interface between region <b>47</b> and layer <b>32</b> forms a parasitic diode that is illustrated as a diode <b>19</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and the P-N junction formed at the interface between regions <b>55</b> and <b>47</b> forms another parasitic diode that is illustrated as a diode <b>20</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Transistor <b>17</b> is formed on the surface of substrate <b>35</b> and adjacent one side of transistor <b>11</b>. In the preferred embodiment, transistor <b>17</b> includes a doped region <b>34</b> that extends across the first surface of substrate <b>35</b> parallel to region <b>47</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Region <b>34</b> functions as the body of transistor <b>17</b> and typically has a conductivity that is opposite to layer <b>32</b>. A doped region <b>36</b> is formed within region <b>34</b> and has an opposite conductivity type in order to function as the drain of transistor <b>17</b>. A doped region <b>37</b> is formed within region <b>36</b> and has the same conductivity at a higher doping concentration than region <b>36</b> in order to facilitate forming electrical contact to region <b>36</b>. A doped region <b>38</b> having a conductivity type and doping concentration similar to region <b>37</b> is formed within region <b>34</b> and spaced apart from region <b>36</b> in order to function as the source of transistor <b>17</b>. A doped region <b>39</b> which has the same conductivity type as region <b>34</b> is formed abutting region <b>38</b> to assist in forming electrical contact to region <b>34</b>. A gate of transistor <b>17</b> includes a gate insulator <b>42</b> that is formed on the surface of substrate <b>35</b> and overlying a portion of at least regions <b>37</b> and <b>38</b>, a gate conductor <b>43</b> that is formed overlying insulator <b>42</b>, and a dielectric <b>44</b> that covers conductor <b>43</b> to insulate conductor <b>43</b> from other conductors.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A doped region <b>33</b> is formed on the surface of substrate <b>35</b> adjacent to region <b>34</b> and typically extending parallel to region <b>34</b>. Region <b>33</b> has a conductivity type that is the same as layer <b>32</b> and a higher doping concentration and extends into layer <b>32</b> in order to form electrical contact to layer <b>32</b>. Region <b>33</b> facilitates forming electrical contact between the drain of transistor <b>17</b> and current carrying electrode <b>23</b> of transistor <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Transistor <b>14</b> includes a doped region <b>60</b> that is similar to doped region <b>34</b> except that doped region <b>60</b> extends parallel to a different side of transistor <b>11</b>. A doped region <b>63</b> is formed to extend from the first surface of substrate <b>35</b> into region <b>60</b> similarly to region <b>36</b> and forms the drain of transistor <b>14</b>. A doped region <b>64</b> is formed within region <b>63</b> similarly to region <b>37</b> to facilitate forming electrical contact to region <b>63</b>. A doped region <b>62</b>, that is similar to doped region <b>38</b>, is form within region <b>60</b> and spaced apart from region <b>63</b> to function as the source of transistor <b>14</b>. A doped region <b>61</b>, that is similar to region <b>39</b>, is formed abutting region <b>62</b> and facilitates forming low resistance electrical contact to region <b>60</b>. The doping type and concentration of regions <b>61</b>, <b>62</b>, <b>63</b>, and <b>64</b> are similar to respective regions <b>39</b>, <b>38</b>, <b>36</b>, and <b>37</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">A conductor <b>76</b> is formed to make electrical contact to region <b>33</b> and to the drain of transistor <b>17</b> through an electrical contact to region <b>37</b>. A portion of a dielectric <b>75</b>, such as an inter-layer dielectric, insulates conductor <b>76</b> from portions of the surface of substrate <b>35</b>. Conductor <b>76</b> connects the drain of transistor <b>17</b> to electrode <b>23</b> of transistor <b>11</b>. A conductor <b>78</b> is formed to make electrical contact to region <b>47</b> through region <b>48</b> and to region <b>38</b> in order to connect body <b>12</b> to the source of transistor <b>17</b>. Another portion of dielectric <b>75</b> insulates conductor <b>78</b> from portions of the surface of substrate <b>35</b>. Conductors <b>76</b> and <b>78</b> are illustrated by dashed boxes in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> in order to illustrate some of the underlying portions of transistor <b>10</b>. A conductor <b>79</b> extends to overlie and make electrical contact to all regions <b>56</b> in order to form electrode <b>22</b> of transistor <b>11</b>. Other portions of dielectric <b>75</b> insulate conductor <b>79</b> from gates <b>26</b>, <b>27</b>, and <b>28</b>. A conductor <b>81</b> is formed to make electrical contact to region <b>49</b> and regions <b>61</b> and <b>62</b> in order to form an electrical contact between body <b>12</b> and the source of transistor <b>14</b>. Another portion of dielectric <b>75</b> insulates conductor <b>81</b> from other portions of transistors <b>11</b> and <b>14</b>. A conductor <b>82</b> is formed to make electrical contact to region <b>64</b> in order to form an electrical connection to the source of transistor <b>14</b>. Conductors <b>79</b>, <b>81</b>, and <b>82</b> are illustrated by a dashed box in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> in order to illustrate some of the underlying portions of transistor <b>10</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a portion of conductor <b>82</b> may extend across substrate <b>35</b> as a conductor <b>72</b> in order to electrically connect conductor <b>82</b> to conductor <b>79</b>, thus to electrode <b>22</b> and the first current carrying electrode (CCE1) of transistor <b>11</b>, and to the gate of transistor <b>17</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Additionally, a portion of conductor <b>76</b> may extend across substrate <b>35</b> to form a conductor <b>71</b> in order to connect the drain of transistor <b>17</b> to the gate of transistor <b>14</b>. Conductors <b>71</b> and <b>72</b> are illustrated by dashed lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> in order to illustrate the underlying regions of transistor <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">As will be understood by those skilled in the art, the on-resistance of transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> should be low in order to support a high dv/dt. The on-resistance of transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> typically is less than approximately twenty-five ohms and preferably is less than about five ohms.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates an enlarged plan view of a portion of an embodiment of a bi-directional transistor <b>85</b> that is an alternate embodiment of transistor <b>10</b> described in the description of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> though <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional portion of the embodiment of transistor <b>85</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> along section line <b>5</b>-<b>5</b>. This description has references to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. Transistor <b>85</b> is similar to transistor <b>10</b> with lateral MOS transistor <b>17</b> replaced by a vertical MOS transistor <b>86</b>. A vertical transistor can usually be formed to have a lower on-resistance that a lateral transistor. Transistor <b>86</b> is formed on a surface of substrate <b>35</b>. A doped region <b>94</b> functions as the body of transistor <b>86</b>. Region <b>94</b> is formed on the surface of substrate <b>35</b> substantially the same as region <b>47</b> but is spaced apart from region <b>47</b>. Trench gates <b>88</b>, <b>89</b>, and <b>90</b> of transistor <b>86</b> are formed in a manner similar to gates <b>26</b>, <b>27</b>, and <b>28</b> of transistor <b>11</b>. A trench is formed through region <b>94</b> and is lined with an insulator similar to insulator <b>51</b>. A gate conductor similar to conductor <b>52</b> is formed within the trench and to be surrounded by insulator <b>51</b>. Doped regions <b>93</b> are formed between gates <b>88</b> and <b>89</b> and between <b>89</b> and <b>90</b> to extend from the first surface of substrate <b>35</b> into region <b>94</b> to facilitate making electrical contact to the body of transistor <b>86</b>. Region <b>93</b> typically has the same conductivity as region <b>94</b> but a higher doping concentration. Doped regions <b>92</b> are formed between gates <b>88</b> and <b>89</b> and between gates <b>89</b> and <b>90</b> to function as the source of transistor <b>86</b>. Regions <b>92</b> generally are formed abutting an adjacent gate and extend to abut an adjacent region <b>93</b>. Regions <b>92</b> usually are doped opposite in conductivity to region <b>94</b> and may have a doping concentration of approximately 5E19 to 5E20 atoms/cm<sup>3</sup>. Conductor <b>78</b> is extended to electrically contact regions <b>92</b> and region <b>93</b> in order to connect the body and the source of transistor <b>86</b> to body <b>12</b> of transistors <b>11</b> and <b>85</b>. Conductor <b>82</b> typically extends across substrate <b>35</b> to make electrical contact to the gate of transistor <b>85</b> as illustrated in a general manner by dashed lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Additionally, a doped region <b>96</b> is formed on the surface of substrate <b>35</b> and extending into substrate <b>35</b> to facilitate forming a low resistance electrical contact to the second current carrying electrode (CCE2) of transistors <b>85</b> and <b>11</b>. Region <b>96</b> is formed adjacent to and extending parallel to region <b>60</b> and spaced apart from region <b>60</b>. A conductor <b>97</b> is formed to electrically contact region <b>96</b> and to extend across substrate <b>35</b> to make electrical contact to the gate of transistor <b>14</b> as illustrated in a general manner by dashed lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Those skilled in the art will appreciate that the placement of transistor <b>86</b> is only illustrative and that transistor <b>86</b> may be place differently relative to the placement of transistor <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates a cross-sectional portion of an embodiment-of a bi-directional transistor <b>100</b> that is another alternate embodiment of transistor <b>10</b> that was explained in the description of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Transistor <b>100</b> includes a buried layer <b>101</b> that assists in reducing the on-resistance of transistor <b>100</b>. In some embodiments the doping concentration of layer <b>32</b> may be light in order to form transistors <b>14</b> and <b>17</b> in addition to other types of active and passive elements on substrate <b>35</b>. The light doping could increases the on-resistance of transistor <b>11</b>. However, buried layer <b>101</b> is formed to have a high doping concentration and to underlie the channel region of transistor <b>11</b> in order to reduce the on-resistance. The peak doping concentration of layer <b>32</b> may be no greater than about 1E16 atoms/cm<sup>3 </sup>and preferably is no greater than about 1E15 atoms/cm<sup>3 </sup>and the peak doping concentration of layer <b>101</b> may be greater than about 4E16 atoms/cm<sup>3 </sup>and preferably is greater than about 1E16 atoms/cm<sup>3</sup>. Buried layer <b>101</b> generally is formed along the interface of and extending into both of substrate <b>30</b> and layer <b>32</b>. Layer <b>101</b> can be formed by a varied of methods including doping the surface of substrate <b>30</b> prior to forming layer <b>32</b>, forming layer <b>32</b> on substrate <b>30</b>, and annealing substrate <b>35</b> to diffuse the dopants into both substrate <b>30</b> and layer <b>32</b>. Layer <b>101</b> typically has a length sufficient to at least underlie regions <b>47</b>. Layer <b>101</b> may also extend to underlie a portion of the outermost gates of transistor <b>11</b>, gates <b>26</b> and <b>28</b>, and may even extend past the innermost edges and to the distal edges of gates <b>26</b> and <b>28</b> as illustrated by dashed lines.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In view of all of the above, it is evident that a novel device and method is disclosed. Included, among other features, is selectively coupling body <b>12</b> to different electrodes of transistor <b>10</b> in order to facilitate bi-directional blocking of voltages applied to transistor <b>10</b>. Forming the nHV region underlying the region <b>56</b> facilitates sustaining voltages across transistor <b>10</b>. Using one transistor instead of two series connected transistors reduces the cost of the bi-directional transistor and systems that use the bi-directional transistor. Using one transistor also reduces the on-resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">While the invention is described with specific preferred embodiments, it is evident that many alternatives and variations will be apparent to those skilled in the semiconductor arts. More specifically the invention has been described for a particular N-channel MOS transistor structure, although the method is directly applicable to P-channel transistors as well as to BiCMOS, metal semiconductor FETs (MESFETs), HFETs, and other transistor structures. Also transistors <b>11</b> and <b>86</b> may be formed as a vertical transistor with traditional surface gates instead of trench gates. Regions <b>55</b> would still be used to assist in blocking reverse voltages. Those skilled in the art will realize that other metal layers may be used to assist in forming more electrical contacts to the body regions in order to reduce resistance. Those skilled in the art will appreciate that the placement of the transistors relative to each other is only illustrative and that the transistors may be place differently relative to the placement of other transistors of the bi-directional transistor. Additionally, the word “connected” is used throughout for clarity of the description, however, it is intended to have the same meaning as the word “coupled”. Accordingly, “connected” should be interpreted as including either a direct connection or an indirect connection.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of forming a bi-directional transistor comprising:
<claim-text>forming a first MOS transistor on a semiconductor substrate of a first conductivity type;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a body region of the first MOS transistor as a first doped region of a first conductivity and a first doping concentration on a surface of the semiconductor substrate and isolated from a first current carrying electrode region of the first MOS transistor by a first P-N junction and isolated from a second current carrying electrode region of the first MOS transistor by a second P-N junction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a source region of the first MOS transistor as a second doped region of a second conductivity type and a second doping concentration that is overlying a portion of the body region;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a third doped region of the second conductivity type between the source region and the body region; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second MOS transistor coupled to selectively couple the body region of the first MOS transistor to the first current carrying electrode of the first MOS transistor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including forming the second MOS transistor electrically coupled between the body region of the first MOS transistor and the first current carrying electrode region of the first MOS transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first MOS transistor is a vertical transistor and the second MOS transistor is a lateral MOS transistor formed on the semiconductor substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first MOS transistor is a vertical transistor and the second MOS transistor is a vertical MOS transistor formed on the semiconductor substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including a third MOS transistor coupled to selectively couple the body region of the first MOS transistor to a second current carrying electrode of the first MOS transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein forming the third doped region of the second conductivity type includes forming the third doped with a third doping concentration that is less than the second doping concentration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A method of forming a bi-directional transistor comprising:
<claim-text>providing a semiconductor substrate of a first conductivity type;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first doped region of a second conductivity type on a surface of the semiconductor substrate as a body region of a first transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second doped region of the first conductivity type within the first doped region and extending a first distance into the first doped region as a first current carrying electrode region of the first transistor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a third doped region of the first conductivity type and extending from the second doped region a second distance into the first doped region.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further including forming a fourth doped region of the second conductivity type on the surface of the semiconductor substrate and spaced apart from the first doped region; forming a source and a drain of a second transistor in the fourth doped region; and coupling the second transistor electrically between the first doped region and the semiconductor substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein forming the source and the drain of the second transistor in the fourth doped region includes forming a fifth doped region within the fourth doped region; forming a sixth doped region within the fourth doped region and spaced apart from the fifth doped region; electrically coupling the fifth doped region to the first doped region; and coupling the sixth doped region to the semiconductor substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further including forming a fourth doped region of the second conductivity type on the surface of the semiconductor substrate and spaced apart from the first doped region; forming a source and a drain of a second transistor in the fourth doped region; and coupling the second transistor electrically between the first doped region and the second doped region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein forming the source and the drain of the second transistor in the fourth doped region includes forming a fifth doped region within the fourth doped region; forming a sixth doped region within the fourth doped region and spaced apart from the fifth doped region; electrically coupling the fifth doped region to the first doped region; and coupling the sixth doped region to the second doped region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein forming the first doped region of the second conductivity type on the surface of the semiconductor substrate as the body region of the first transistor includes forming the first transistor as a vertical transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method of forming a bi-directional transistor comprising:
<claim-text>providing a semiconductor substrate of a first conductivity type;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first doped region of a second conductivity type on a surface of the semiconductor substrate as a body region of a first transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second doped region of the first conductivity type having a first doping concentration within the first doped region and extending a first distance into the first doped region as a first current carrying electrode region of the first transistor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a third doped region of the first conductivity type having a second doping concentration that is less than the first doping concentration and extending from the second doped region a second distance into the first doped region wherein the second distance is greater than the first distance.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
