<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299271-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299271</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10314227</doc-number>
<date>20021209</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-377593</doc-number>
<date>20011211</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>670</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709219</main-classification>
<further-classification>709218</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">System for automatically downloading content from a server to a home system based on user's command from a remote terminal</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6826581</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Moslander et al.</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>707203</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6885809</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Asada</name>
<date>20050400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>386 46</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0031120</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Rakib</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370386</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0040475</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Yap et al.</name>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>725 39</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0100044</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Daniels</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>725 39</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0198991</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Gopalakrishnan et al.</name>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>709225</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0009537</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wang</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>709219</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>7-143170</doc-number>
<date>19950600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-259532</doc-number>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-331426</doc-number>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>22</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709219</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709218</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709225</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709203</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709 18</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709 19</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370386</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>725 39</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386 46</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>707203</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20030110214</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20030612</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sato</last-name>
<first-name>Shinobu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Young &amp; Thompson</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>NEC Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Luu</last-name>
<first-name>Le Hien</first-name>
<department>2141</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A content obtaining system automatically downloads desired content from a communication network to a home system based on a command from a remote terminal. The content obtaining system includes a communication network, a content server which stores content, a terminal which can access the content server via the communication network and which transmits a command to the communication network under a user's operation, and a home system which receives the command via the communication network and automatically downloads content stored in the content server and designated by the command sent via the communication network.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="148.34mm" wi="147.83mm" file="US07299271-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="169.50mm" wi="147.91mm" file="US07299271-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="204.55mm" wi="137.33mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299271-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="127.85mm" wi="146.22mm" file="US07299271-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="190.58mm" wi="138.85mm" file="US07299271-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a content obtaining system, and, more particularly, to a content obtaining system for downloading content automatically to a home system based on a command from a remote terminal.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Hitherto, when a user downloads desired content from a server on the Internet, the downloaded data is directly stored in the user's personal computer (PC) via the Internet.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Recently, there are mobile terminals such as a mobile telephone and a personal digital assistant (a PDA) that can access the Internet. By the mobile terminals, the user can browse homepages, download desired content and store the downloaded data in the user's mobile terminal via the Internet.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">It should be noted that, in conventional system, the downloaded content can be stored only in the terminal which the user operates.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Consequently, there is a possibility that a mobile terminal cannot download all the desired content because of its limited storage capacity, a time constraints, and the like. That is, the storage capacity of a mobile terminal is normally smaller than that of a PC. Therefore, all the desired data cannot be stored in the mobile terminal if the desired content is large. Moreover, the data transfer speed of a communication line which the mobile terminal uses is normally lower than a communication line which a PC uses, for example, DSL, LAN, and the like. Therefore, more time for storing data is required.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The present invention has an object to provide a content obtaining system for automatically downloading desired content from a communication network such as the Internet to a home system, based on a command from a remote terminal.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to one embodiment of the present invention, the content obtaining system includes a communication network, a content server which stores content, a terminal which can access the content server via the communication network and which transmits a command to the communication network under a user's operation, and a home system which receives the command via the communication network and automatically downloads content stored in the content server and designated by the command via the communication network.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">These and other objects, features and advantages of the invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description when taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram showing the structure of a content obtaining system according to preferred embodiments of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a sequence diagram showing the operation of a content obtaining system according to a first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a sequence diagram showing the operation of a content obtaining system according to a second embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flowchart showing the operation of a content obtaining system according to a third embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The present invention will be now explained in detail below with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a content obtaining system includes the Internet <b>10</b>, a mobile terminal <b>20</b> such as a PDA or a mobile phone, a home system <b>30</b>, a content server <b>40</b>, and an Internet service provider system (an “ISP”) <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The mobile terminal <b>20</b> is connected to the Internet <b>10</b> by radio signal and can communicate with the home system <b>30</b>, the content server <b>40</b>, and the ISP <b>50</b> via the Internet <b>10</b>. The mobile terminal <b>20</b> can browse a homepage (web page) on the Internet <b>10</b> by a communication unit <b>21</b>. Alternatively, the communication between the mobile terminal <b>20</b> and the Internet <b>10</b> may be connected not only by radio but also by wiring.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The home system <b>30</b> in this embodiment includes a first PC <b>31</b>, a second PC <b>32</b>, and a router <b>33</b>. The first PC <b>31</b> and the second PC <b>32</b> are connected to the Internet <b>10</b> via the router <b>33</b>. The first PC includes a hard disk <b>311</b>, a communication unit <b>312</b>, a storage checking unit <b>313</b>, a control unit <b>314</b>, a compression unit <b>315</b> and a dividing unit <b>316</b>. The control unit <b>314</b> controls each unit in the first PC <b>31</b>. The second PC includes a hard disk <b>321</b>, a communication unit <b>322</b>, a control unit <b>324</b> and a compression unit <b>325</b>. The control unit <b>324</b> controls each unit in the second PC.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The content server <b>40</b> stores home pages and various content such as document files, music files, still image files (e.g. photographs and illustrations) and moving images (e.g. movies). A user refers to the homepage which carries, for example, a list of the content.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The ISP <b>50</b> provides access services for permitting the user's terminal (the mobile terminal <b>20</b>, the first PC <b>31</b> and the second PC <b>32</b>) to access the Internet <b>10</b> and storage services for temporarily storage information described later. In the case of the access services, logically, the ISP <b>50</b> exists between the Internet <b>10</b> and the user's terminal. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, attention is paid to only the function of the ISP <b>50</b> for the storage services and the user's terminals are directly connected to the Internet <b>10</b>. The ISP <b>50</b> includes a temporary storage area <b>51</b> for temporarily storage information from each user or addressed to each user.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In above-described structure, in the content obtaining system, the home system <b>30</b> automatically downloads content on the content server <b>40</b> based on a command from the mobile terminal <b>20</b> operated by the user. The detailed operation of embodiments of the content obtaining system will now be described.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In operation of the first embodiment of the content obtaining system, referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the user browses the homepage of the content server <b>40</b> from the mobile terminal via the Internet <b>10</b>, out of his home or office (step S<b>1</b>). If the user finds content that he wishes to view later at the home system <b>30</b> during the browsing operation, the mobile terminal obtains a Uniform Resource Locator (URL) of the homepage and the content from the content server <b>40</b> via the Internet <b>10</b> under a user's operation (step S<b>2</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Under the user's operation, the mobile terminal <b>20</b> sends “content obtain” information to the ISP <b>50</b> via the Internet (step S<b>3</b>). The ISP <b>50</b> stores the received information in the temporary storage area <b>51</b> corresponding to the user who sends the information.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The content obtain information includes the URLs of the homepage and the content, time information, and storage information. The time information is for designating whether the download is started immediately or the download is started at a designated time.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The storage information is for designating “the hard disk <b>311</b> incorporated in the first PC <b>31</b> (e.g., C drive, D drive, . . . )” or “the hard disk <b>321</b> incorporated in the second PC <b>32</b> (e.g., C drive, D drive, . . . )”. By the storage information, the user can store the desired content in different disks depending on content genres. Thus, the adjustment which will be performed later is easy. Moreover, since the user can designate the hard disk with a large free capacity, when a file size of the downloaded content is large, the possibility that the content cannot be stored during the downloading operation is prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The first PC <b>31</b> is periodically connected to the ISP <b>50</b> and checks to see whether the content obtain information exists in the temporary storage area of the ISP <b>50</b> by a communication unit <b>312</b> (steps S<b>4</b><sub>1</sub>, S<b>4</b><sub>2</sub>, S<b>4</b><sub>3</sub>, . . . ). If the first PC <b>31</b> detects that the content obtain information exists, the first PC <b>31</b> receives the content obtain information (step S<b>5</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Next, the first PC <b>31</b> connects to the content server <b>40</b> based on the URL in the content obtain information and obtains information on file size of the content designated by the content obtain information, via the communication unit <b>312</b> (step S<b>6</b>). That is, in the case of using, for example, a Hyper Text Transfer Protocol (HTTP) as a protocol, the first PC <b>31</b> can recognize in advance and obtain the file size of the content.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Next, the first PC <b>31</b> obtains information on a first disk capacity including “current capacity value of the hard disk <b>311</b>”, “free capacity value of the hard disk <b>311</b>”, and “alarm information indicating the shortage of the capacity of the hard disk <b>311</b>” by a storage checking unit <b>313</b>. The PC <b>31</b> checks whether the second PC <b>32</b> is running, via the communication unit <b>312</b>. If the second PC <b>32</b> is not running, the first PC <b>31</b> turns the second PC <b>32</b> on, via the communication unit <b>312</b>. The first PC <b>31</b> obtains the information on the second disk capacity including the “current capacity value of the hard disk <b>321</b>”, the “free capacity value of the hard disk <b>321</b>”, and the “alarm information indicating the shortage of the capacity of the hard disk <b>321</b>” via the storage checking unit <b>313</b> and the communication unit <b>312</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Next, the communication unit <b>312</b> of the first PC <b>31</b> transmits to the mobile terminal <b>20</b> by, e.g., an email, the above-obtained file size information, the information on the first disk capacity, and the information on the second disk capacity, as “status information” indicating the current status of the home system <b>30</b> (step S<b>7</b>). Thus, the user of the mobile terminal <b>20</b> can check in advance whether his designated content can be stored in the home system <b>30</b>. If the content can be stored, the user feels safe.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In case the homepage of the content server <b>40</b> displays the file size of the content, the user can know the file size of the content when the homepage is browsed from the mobile terminal <b>20</b>. Therefore, the above-mentioned processing step S<b>6</b> (for checking the downloaded file size) can be omitted. In this case, in the processing for transmitting the status information in step S<b>7</b>, the information on the first and second disk capacities except for the file size information is transmitted to the mobile terminal <b>20</b> as the status information.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Next, the control unit <b>314</b> of the first PC <b>31</b> checks whether the download is commence without delay, based on the time information included in the content obtain information. If it is instructed that the operation for downloading the content is to be promptly started, the first PC <b>31</b> accesses the content server <b>40</b> based on the content obtain information, and requests the operation for downloading the content via the communication unit <b>312</b> (step S<b>8</b>). Thus, the designated content is downloaded from the content server <b>40</b> and is stored in the hard disk which is designated by the storage information included in the content obtain information.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In the case of storage, the free capacity value included in the above-obtained first or second disk capacity information is compared with the file size of the downloaded content. As a result, if the content cannot be stored in the designated storage destination, the content is automatically compressed by the compression unit <b>315</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The compressing operation is performed by thinning data or by changing a compression ratio. The thinning operation is performed, for example, by changing a moving picture comprising an image having 30 frames per second to a moving picture comprising an image having 15 frames per second. When the content for downloading and browsing includes a video image such a TV commercial image, the thinning operation is performed, for example, by omitting the TV commercial image. Further, when the content for downloading and browsing includes a video image such as a concert, the thinning operation is performed, for example, by omitting a video image of a break time of the concert.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The compression ratio is changed by downscaling for reducing the image size. Downscaling is a compression method in which a video image comprising, e.g., 720×480 pixels is converted into a video image comprising 320×240 pixels. The compression ratio may be changed by trans-coding for converting an encoding method. For example, an MPEG (Motion Picture Except Group) 2 having an arbitrary bit rate for converting MPEG2 data into MPEG4 data is converted into MPEG<b>2</b> data having another bit rate (that is, the compression ratio is changed) or the like. Incidentally, the trans-coding method can use various methods, other than the above-mentioned methods. The most simple method is a method whereby target data is temporarily decoded and is encoded again by using another bit rate and another compression method.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As mentioned above, in the case of a limitation for the number of downloading and browsing times, that is, when only one operation for downloading and browsing, e.g., live play, is permitted, and when the content must promptly be downloaded because the time is too short to adjust the hard disk having term-limited content, the user can obtain the desired content without fail by compressing and storing the downloaded content.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Although the downloaded content is compressed and stored in the hard disk in the above-mentioned structure, the file which has already been stored in the storage destination can automatically be compressed. The compressing of the file enables the expansion of the capacity of the hard disk. Further, both the downloaded content and the file which has already been stored in the storage destination can be compressed. The content is automatically compressed upon downloading operation and the user can designate whether the content is automatically compressed from the mobile terminal <b>20</b>. In this case, the user sends information for instructing the compression, and that information is included in the content obtain information from the mobile terminal <b>20</b>. With the above-mentioned structure, when the user knows that the downloaded content cannot be stored in the hard disk by viewing the status information sent from the home system <b>30</b> from the mobile terminal <b>20</b>, the user can instruct that the content is compressed and stored again. Therefore, as compared with the automatic compressing operation, compression can be stopped when downloading picture quality due to the compression would be unacceptable.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">After completing the downloading operation in step S<b>9</b>, subsequently, the first PC <b>31</b> sends the file size information of the downloaded content, the first disk capacity information, and the second disk capacity information, as the status information indicating the current status of the home system <b>30</b>, to the mobile terminal <b>20</b> by, e.g., an email (step S<b>10</b>). Thus, the user of the mobile terminal <b>20</b> can check whether his designated content is downloaded to the home system <b>30</b> and can check the file size of the content. Further, the user can determine whether another content can be downloaded by viewing the first disk capacity information and the second disk capacity information.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">After completing the processing for sending the status information in step S<b>10</b> to the mobile terminal <b>20</b>, the first PC <b>31</b> may disconnect from the Internet <b>10</b>. By the above-mentioned operation, the user can view in detail later the content which cannot be viewed away from home.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">If the content obtain information indicates that the content should be downloaded at a later designated time, the first PC <b>31</b> sends only the status information to the mobile terminal <b>20</b> (step S<b>7</b>). Thereafter, the first PC <b>31</b> disconnects from the Internet <b>10</b>. Later, the first PC <b>31</b> again accesses the Internet <b>10</b> at the time designated by the time information, and downloads the content which is designated by the above-mentioned sequence. When the downloading operation is completed, the first PC <b>31</b> disconnects from the Internet <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">With the above-mentioned structure, the user can select a time frame that is convenient for the user such as a time frame in which traffic of the Internet <b>10</b> is not heavy, and/or a time frame in which the access charge is cheap, and can download the content. By sending the content obtain information, the user can know the status of the home system <b>30</b> at the time. Therefore, the user can designate a different hard disk where the downloaded content will be stored and can change the designation of the compression with time allowance.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As mentioned above, in the content obtaining system according to the first embodiment of the present invention, when the user is not at home, he can nevertheless download the desired content via the Internet to the PC in the user's home at any desired time.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The first PC <b>31</b> may access the Internet <b>10</b> only for checking whether the ISP <b>50</b> has content obtain information, and if so, for downloading the content. Therefore, the access charge is cheap and the first PC <b>31</b> does not need a security function for preventing the danger caused by continuous Internet access. Alternatively, the first PC <b>31</b> can be set up with continuous Internet access. In this case, the above-mentioned access and disconnection to the Internet <b>10</b> are not performed and therefore, preferably, the first PC <b>31</b> or the router <b>33</b> has a security function.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The content obtaining system according to the first embodiment can be modified with a structure in which the mobile PC <b>20</b> can be instructed that the content is downloaded directly to the home system <b>30</b>, not via the ISP <b>50</b>. Hereinbelow, a description is given of the operation of the content obtaining system according to the modification of the first embodiment (a second embodiment) with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The user browses the homepage on the content server <b>40</b> out of the home or office via the Internet <b>10</b> from the mobile terminal <b>20</b> (step S<b>20</b>). If the content to be viewed in detail later is provided in the homepage during the browsing operation, the mobile terminal <b>20</b> obtains the URL address of the homepage and the desired content via the Internet <b>10</b> from the content server <b>40</b> (step S<b>21</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">On the other hand, upon external access, the router <b>33</b> in the home system <b>30</b> previously sets the access which is routed to the first PC <b>31</b>. Therefore, the mobile terminal <b>20</b> can directly access the first personal computer <b>31</b> via the Internet <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The mobile terminal <b>20</b> which obtains the URL sends the content obtain information to the first PC <b>31</b> via the Internet <b>10</b> (step S<b>22</b>). The operation for sending the content obtain information is performed as follows. That is, an access method from the mobile terminal <b>20</b> to the first PC <b>31</b> is established by browsing the homepage provided on the first PC <b>31</b> by the mobile terminal <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The homepage on the first PC <b>31</b> is browsed on the mobile terminal <b>20</b> and the homepage includes a URL address describing column, a content designating column, a download start designating column, and a storage destination designating column. The user inputs necessary indexes in these columns by operating a key of the mobile terminal <b>20</b>. Further, the homepage includes a sending button and the designation of the sending button from the mobile terminal <b>20</b> causes the transmission of the information inputted to the columns to the first personal computer <b>31</b>. Alternatively, the content obtain information can be formed in advance on the mobile terminal <b>20</b> and can be sent, similarly to the case according to the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The first PC <b>31</b> accesses the content server <b>40</b> which is designated by the URL in the content obtain information and obtains the file size information of the content (step S<b>23</b>). Subsequently, the first PC <b>31</b> obtains the first disk capacity information of the hard disk incorporated therein and the second disk capacity information of the hard disk incorporated in the second PC <b>32</b>. A free capacity and the like can be displayed in realtime by using a Common Gateway Interface (CGI) or an Active Server Pages (ASP) for the homepage on the first PC <b>31</b>. Thus, the mobile terminal <b>20</b> can obtain the first and second disk capacities by the access to the homepage on the first personal computer <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Hereinbelow, similarly to the first embodiment, the first PC <b>31</b> sends to the mobile terminal <b>20</b> by an email, the file size information, the first disk capacity information, and the second disk capacity information, as the “status information” indicating the current status of the home system <b>20</b> (step S<b>24</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">When the time information included in the content obtain information indicates that the downloading operation should be started promptly, the first PC <b>31</b> requests the operation for downloading the content designated by the content obtain information (step S<b>25</b>). Thus, the content is downloaded and is stored in the storage destination designated by the storage information in the content obtain information (step S<b>26</b>). In the case of storage, if the content cannot be stored in the designated storage destination, the file which has already been stored in the content or/and storage destination is automatically compressed. The file compression enables the expansion of the capacity of the storage destination. Alternatively or in addition, the user can designate whether the compression should be performed from the mobile terminal <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">After completing the downloading operation in step S<b>26</b>, next, the first PC <b>31</b> sends to the mobile terminal <b>20</b> by an email, information indicating the end of the downloading operation, the file size information of the downloaded content, the first disk capacity information, and the second disk capacity information, as the status information indicating the current status of the home system <b>30</b> (step S<b>27</b>). After completing the transmission, the first personal computer <b>31</b> disconnects from the Internet <b>10</b>. Thus, the user can view content that cannot be viewed in detail away from the home or office.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">On the other hand, if it is instructed by the content obtain information that the downloading operation should be started at the designated time, the first PC <b>31</b> only sends the status information to the mobile terminal <b>20</b> (step S<b>24</b>). Thereafter, the first personal computer <b>31</b> disconnects from the Internet <b>10</b>. The first PC <b>31</b> accesses the Internet <b>10</b> at the time designated by the time information, and downloads the content. After completing the downloading operation, the first PC <b>31</b> disconnects from the Internet <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Thus, the user can download content to a home system <b>30</b> instead of the mobile terminal <b>20</b>. For example, the user can select a time frame that is convenient for the user such as a time frame in which the Internet <b>10</b> is not heavy and a time frame in which access charge is cheap, and can download the content.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">As mentioned above, in the content obtaining system according to the second embodiment, advantageously, the first PC <b>31</b> can be accessed from the mobile terminal <b>20</b> without using the ISP <b>50</b>. It will be noted that, in the content obtaining system according to the second embodiment, the first PC <b>31</b> needs continuous access to the Internet <b>10</b>. Therefore, in the content obtaining system according to the second embodiment, the first PC <b>31</b> can be accessed externally and directly. Thus, preferably, the router <b>33</b> has a security function.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">According to the first and second embodiments, a description is given of the operation in which the PC <b>31</b> accesses the Internet <b>10</b> via the router <b>33</b>. However, the operation, in which the second PC <b>32</b> or both the first PC <b>32</b> and the second PC <b>32</b> access the Internet <b>10</b> via the router <b>33</b>, is the same as the above-mentioned operation.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Next, according to a third embodiment of the present invention, a plurality of personal computers distributes and stores downloaded content.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In the content obtaining system according to the third embodiment, the operation of the first PC <b>31</b> and the second PC <b>32</b> in the home system <b>30</b> is different from that according to the first embodiment. According to the third embodiment, the compression is not performed when the downloaded content is stored.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In the above-mentioned content obtaining system according to the first and second embodiments, as described above with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>, the user browses the homepage from the mobile terminal <b>20</b> and sends the content obtain information to the first PC <b>31</b> via the ISP <b>50</b> or directly. Thus, the first PC <b>31</b> downloads the content designated by the content obtain information via the Internet <b>10</b> from the content server <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Hereinbelow, a description is given of the operation of the first PC <b>31</b> and the second PC <b>32</b> upon storing the content downloaded to the home system <b>30</b> from the content server <b>40</b> with reference to a flowchart shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The content is downloaded to the home system <b>30</b> from the content server <b>40</b> in accordance with a predetermined communication protocol. The downloading operation is started. Then, the first PC <b>31</b> displays reception data on a display, and simultaneously and sequentially stores the reception data in a temporary memory provided in the first PC <b>31</b> (step S<b>30</b>). The reception data may be displayed on the display of the second PC <b>32</b>. In this case, it is confirmed in advance by the same sequence in steps S<b>35</b> and S<b>36</b>, which will be described later, whether power of the second PC <b>32</b> is ON. The reception data may be displayed on both the first PC <b>31</b> and the second PC <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Next, the first PC <b>31</b> checks whether the data temporarily stored in the memory reaches a predetermined capacity (step S<b>31</b>). Herein, a storage capacity unit of the hard disk is used as the predetermined capacity. The storage capacity of the hard disk is the remaining size when the data is written to the hard disk once. If it is determined in step S<b>31</b> that the data does not reach the predetermined capacity, the sequence returns step S<b>30</b> whereupon the reception data is repeatedly temporarily stored.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">If it is determined in step S<b>31</b> in the repeating processing in steps S<b>30</b> and S<b>31</b> that the data reaches the predetermined capacity, next, it is checked whether there is a free capacity for storing the data which is temporarily stored in the hard disk of the first PC <b>31</b> (step S<b>32</b>). This is performed for purpose of determining that there is no capacity, when the free capacity of the hard disk is 10% of the entire capacity or less, or when the free capacity of the hard disk is less than a preset value (e.g., 100 MB).</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">If it is determined in step S<b>32</b> that the hard disk of the first PC <b>31</b> has a free capacity, the data which is temporarily stored in the memory is stored in the hard disk (step S<b>33</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Next, the first PC <b>31</b> checks whether the downloading operation has ended (step S<b>34</b>). This is performed by checking whether an end code is present in the downloaded content. If it is determined in step S<b>34</b> that the downloading operation has not ended, the sequence returns to step S<b>30</b>. Then, the above-mentioned operation is repeated again.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">If the first PC <b>31</b> determines in step S<b>32</b> in the repeating processing that there is no free capacity in the hard disk, next, the first PC <b>31</b> checks whether the second PC <b>32</b> is started (step S<b>35</b>) This is performed by checking whether a response to a predetermined command is returned from the second PC <b>32</b> to the first PC <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">If the first PC <b>31</b> determines in step S<b>35</b> that the second PC <b>32</b> is not started, the first PC <b>31</b> starts the second PC <b>32</b> (step S<b>36</b>). The starting operation is performed by sending a command for instructing the on-operation of the power to the second PC <b>32</b> from the first personal computer <b>31</b>. If the first PC determines in step S<b>35</b> that the second PC <b>32</b> is started, the processing in step S<b>36</b> is skipped.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">The first PC <b>31</b> checks whether the second PC <b>32</b> has a free capacity for storing the data which is temporarily stored in the first PC <b>31</b> (step S<b>37</b>). This is performed similarly to the above-mentioned processing in step S<b>32</b>. If the first PC <b>31</b> determines in step S<b>37</b> that the hard disk of the second PC <b>32</b> has the free capacity, next, the data which is temporarily stored in the memory of the first PC <b>31</b> is sent to the hard disk of the second PC <b>32</b> in accordance with a preset condition (step S<b>38</b>) Thereafter, the sequence branches to step S<b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Preferably, in the above-mentioned processing, in the case where the downloaded content is a file having a well-known structure, e.g., an MPEG file, the downloaded content is divided in accordance with the structure, and is distributed and stored into the hard disk of the first PC <b>31</b> and the hard disk of the second PC <b>32</b> by the dividing unit <b>316</b>. The MPEG file is divided before a sequence header thereof or by a GOP unit. Thus, an MPEG moving picture can be read intact, despite the file thereof having been divided. As mentioned above, the file is stored by the storage capacity unit of the hard disk as mentioned above. The above division is performed by the storage capacity unit of the hard disk.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">If it is determined in step S<b>37</b> that the hard disk of the second personal computer <b>32</b> has no free capacity, an alarm is generated by the first PC <b>31</b> (step S<b>39</b>). In this case, the downloading operation is canceled upon generating the alarm and a series of processing ends.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">If it is determined in step S<b>34</b> in the repeating processing in steps S<b>30</b> to S<b>38</b> that the downloading operation ends, the storage information is subsequently generated and stored (step S<b>40</b>). That is, the first PC <b>31</b> generates an information management file which stores the downloaded content and data on the storage destination thereof, and stores the generated information management file in a predetermined folder of the first PC <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Specifically, when the downloaded data is stored only in the hard disk <b>311</b> of the first PC <b>31</b>, the information management file includes an original file name of the downloaded content, a name of the first PC <b>31</b> as the storage destination, a file name on the first PC <b>31</b>, a file name and a file size.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">On the other hand, the downloaded data is divided and stored into the hard disk <b>311</b> of the first PC <b>31</b> and the hard disk <b>322</b> of the second PC <b>32</b>, the information management file includes the original file name of the downloaded content, the name of the first PC <b>31</b> as the storage destination, the folder name on the first personal computer <b>31</b>, the file name, the file size, a name of the second PC <b>32</b>, a folder name on the second PC <b>32</b>, a file name, and a file size.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Therefore, the user refers to the information management file stored in the first PC <b>13</b>, thereby knowing the storage place of the downloaded content. When the downloaded data is stored only in the hard disk <b>311</b> of the first PC <b>31</b>, the user can directly view the content. When the downloaded data is divided and stored in the hard disk <b>311</b> of the first PC <b>31</b> and the hard disk <b>321</b> of the second PC <b>32</b>, the user can view the downloaded content by using an application program for viewing a plurality of files as one file and an application program for combining a plurality of files to one file.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">As mentioned above, in the content obtaining system according to the third embodiment of the present invention, when the free capacity of the hard disk of one PC is low, the content is stored in the hard disk of another PC and therefore the downloading operation is not stopped. As a result, the user can store the desired content from the Internet <b>10</b> in the user's PC without fail.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">According to the third embodiment, the downloaded content is divided according to the storage capacity unit of the hard disk. However, in the case of the MPEG file, the downloaded content can be divided just before the sequence header or by the GOP unit as an editing unit. The second and subsequent divided files can individually be viewed (read) after the above-mentioned division, despite the divided file.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">In the case of using an HTTP as a protocol, the file size can be known before transferring the data. Thus, prior to the start operation of the data transfer, the free capacity of the hard disk is compared with the size of the downloaded file. If the free capacity of the hard disk <b>311</b> of the first PC <b>31</b> is smaller than the file size but the free capacity of the hard disk <b>321</b> of the second PC <b>32</b> is larger than the file size, the data can be stored in the hard disk of the second PC <b>32</b> starting from the first data.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">In this case, the sum of the free capacity of the hard disk <b>311</b> of the first PC <b>31</b> and the free capacity of the hard disk <b>321</b> of the second PC <b>32</b> is larger than the file size but each of the free capacity of the hard disk <b>311</b> of the first PC <b>31</b> and the free capacity of the hard disk <b>321</b> of the second PC <b>32</b> is smaller than the file size, the downloading operation is impossible. However, according to the above-mentioned method for dividing and storing the file, even in the above-mentioned case, the content can be downloaded.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">According to the third embodiment, the description is given of the storage of the downloaded content without compression. However, similarly to the case according to the first embodiment, the downloaded content can be compressed and stored. In this case, in step S<b>30</b>, the first PC <b>31</b> sequentially stores the reception data in the temporary memory provided in the first PC <b>31</b> while displaying the reception data on the display and compressing the data. With the above-mentioned structure, if the content has a file size larger than each of the free capacities of the hard disk of the first PC <b>31</b> and the hard disk of the second PC <b>32</b>, the content can be downloaded and stored.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">According to the embodiments described above, not only the above-mentioned content but also the content associated with content on the homepage can be downloaded. With the above-mentioned structure, advantageously, the user can also view information associated with the content and therefore the user can promptly view a series of associated information.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">As mentioned above, according to the embodiments, the home system <b>30</b> has two PCs and the downloaded content is divided into two sections, is distributed to two places, and is stored. However, the home system <b>30</b> may include three or more PCs. The downloaded content may be divided into three sections, may be distributed to three or more places, and may be stored.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">Further, in the embodiments, the mobile terminal <b>20</b> can be replaced by a PC. In this case, the downloading operation can be instructed from away from home. The status information indicating the current status of the home system <b>30</b> is sent to the PC as homepage information.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">As described in detail above, according to the present invention, the content obtaining system for storing the desired content from the Internet without fail can be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">While this invention has been described in connection with the preferred embodiments described above, it will now be possible for those skilled in the art to put this invention into practice in various other manners.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A content obtaining system comprising:
<claim-text>a communication network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first server which stores content;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an information processing system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a terminal remote from said first server and remote from said information processing system,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said information processing system and said terminal being separately and independently connected to the communication network,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said terminal, independently from said information processing system, i) accessing said first server via said communication network and, ii) after said accessing, under a user's operation, transmitting a command, via said communication network, instructing the information processing system to download specific content from said first server, wherein,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said information processing system receives said command, via said communication network, and automatically downloads, via said communication network, the specific content stored in said first server and designated by said received command.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a second server on said communication network which receives said command from said terminal via said communication network and stores said command;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said information processing system receives said command from said second server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said information processing system periodically accesses said second server to check whether said command is present.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said information processing system comprises a first information processing device and a second information processing device, wherein said first information processing devices comprises a storage checking unit which checks a free storage capacity of each of said first and second information processing devices, and wherein said content is downloaded in said second information processing device if said storage checking unit determines that there is not enough storage capacity for said content in said first information processing device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said information processing system compresses said content while downloading said content.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said information processing system compresses previously-stored while downloading said content.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said information processing system comprises a first information processing device and a second information processing device, wherein said first information processing device comprises a dividing unit which divides said content while downloading said content, and wherein said first information processing device stores one part of said divided content and said second information processing device stores another part of said divided content.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said first information processing device first stores said one part of said content, and wherein said second information processing device start to store said second part of said divided content when said first information processing unit determines that a free storage capacity of said first information processing device achieves a predetermined capacity.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said command includes time information, and wherein said information processing system starts to download at a time designated by said time information.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said information processing system comprises a first information processing device and a second information processing device, wherein said command includes storage information, and wherein said content is stored in said first and/or second information processing devices based on said storage information.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The content obtaining system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein,
<claim-text>the communication network is the Internet;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the information processing system is a personal computer and the content is downloaded, from the Internet, onto the personal computer,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the terminal is configured for the user to browse, via the Internet, a homepage of the first server and to obtain Uniform Resource Locators of the homepage and of the content to be downloaded, the command comprises the obtained Uniform Resource Locators and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the command is transmitted by the terminal under the user's operation and received by the personal computer via the Internet so that said received command causes said personal computer to automatically download the content stored in said first server as designated by said command.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The communication terminal of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein,
<claim-text>said personal computer is part of a home computer network comprising a router, and said personal computer is connected to the Internet via the router,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said second server is an Internet Service Provider server,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said second server, upon receiving said command from said terminal via the Internet, stores said command in an area for temporary storage of information from the user, said command further comprising storage information indicating a size of a file to be downloaded by the personal computer and designating a hard disk of the personal computer to which the file is to be downloaded,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said second server responses to a periodic inquiry from said personal computer by sending, over the Internet, said stored command to said personal computer, said inquiry asking for any commands sent from said terminal and stored on said second server,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said terminal connects directly to the Internet by radio signal for accessing said first server, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said terminal is configured to communicate via the Internet with said home network, said personal computer, with said first server, and with said second server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The communication terminal of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein,
<claim-text>said home network comprises an additional personal computer, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said terminal is configured to allow the user to form said command to designate storing the file is to be downloaded either one of the personal computer and the additional personal computer, thus allowing the user to store files of a first content genre on the personal computer and files of a second content genre on the another personal computer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A communication terminal comprising:
<claim-text>a communication unit which accesses a content server connected to the Internet, the communication unit being connected to the Internet at a first Internet connection; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transmitting unit which transmits a command to said communication unit based on a prior access of the content server by the transmitting unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said command is transmitted from said communication unit to a remote information processing system connected to the Internet at a second Internet connection; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said information processing system automatically downloads content stored in said content server, responsive to said command.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. An information processing system comprising:
<claim-text>a communication unit which receives a command generated by a remote terminal under a user's operation via a communication network, and automatically downloads content on said communication network designated by said command; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a storage unit which stores said content, wherein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the communication unit and the terminal are independently connected to the communication network, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the communication unit and the terminal separately connected to the communication network independently of each other.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The information processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further comprising a first information processing device and second information processing device, wherein said first information processing devices comprises a storage checking unit which checks a free storage capacity of each of said first and second information processing devices, and wherein said content is downloaded in said second information processing device if said storage checking unit determines that there is not enough storage capacity for said content in said first information processing device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The information processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein said information processing system compresses said content while downloading said content.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The information processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein said information processing system compresses previously-stored data while downloading said content.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The information processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further comprising a first information processing device and a second information processing device, wherein said first information processing devices comprises a dividing unit which divides said content while downloading said content, and wherein said first information processing device stores one part of said divided content and said second information processing device stores another part of said divided content.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The information processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein said first information processing device begins to store said content, and wherein said second information processing device commences storing said divided content when said first information processing unit determines that a free storage capacity of said first information processing device drops below a predetermined capacity.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The information processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein said command includes time information, and wherein said information processing system starts to download at a time designated by said time information.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The information processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further comprising a first information processing device and a second information processing device, wherein said command includes storage information, and wherein said content is stored in said first and/or second information processing devices based on said storage information.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
