<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298063-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298063</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10281039</doc-number>
<date>20021028</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>345</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>20</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>310112</main-classification>
<further-classification>310268</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Quantum disk armature electric generator</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3431638</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Burr</name>
<date>19690300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 29598</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5184040</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lim</name>
<date>19930200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>310114</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6130493</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nitschke et al.</name>
<date>20001000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>310 89</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>310112</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>310113</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>310114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>310 89</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>310268</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040080238</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040429</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cunningham</last-name>
<first-name>Sydney A.</first-name>
<address>
<street>1368 New York Ave.</street>
<city>Brooklyn</city>
<state>NY</state>
<postcode>11203</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Schuberg</last-name>
<first-name>Darren</first-name>
<department>2834</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Hanh</last-name>
<first-name>Nguyen N.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Plurality of discs shaped permanent magnet polefaces are disposed on a armature shaft, plurality of discs shape armatures are also disposed on said armature shaft. Each armature is situated between two polefaces with endframes supporting each end of said shaft, elongated support strut are fixedly attached between both endframes and also secured each poleface. The shaft and its armatures rotate on bearing in each endframe.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="176.36mm" wi="240.45mm" file="US07298063-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="241.13mm" wi="179.66mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298063-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="222.50mm" wi="175.34mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298063-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="187.79mm" wi="157.73mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298063-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="176.11mm" wi="137.24mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298063-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="241.30mm" wi="188.38mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298063-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="230.89mm" wi="190.42mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298063-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relate to an apparatus for the generating of electricity. But more specifically, the invention relate to discs shape poleface made from permanent magnet, reacting with discs shape armature or multiple armatures. Where a armature may be placed between two polefaces and disposed on a armature shaft and rotate to produce electricity, the number of armature and poleface may be increase as required.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The prior art electric generator, a device which resist rotation; this resistance cause losses which reduce efficiency. This device generally incorporate a single cylindrical rotor per unit which is not cost effective, and is therefore inadequate; for the generating of electricity with respect to the growing energy consumption in general.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Accordingly, the desire and need exists to develop a new form of generator on a format which will produce large amount of electricity at a low cost. My present innovation was designed to fulfill that need as its objective.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">This innovation present a new format on which to build electric generator for the present and distance future. This device incorporate plurality of permanent magnet discs used as polefaces are disposed on a armature shaft. Plurality of discs with windings form the armature which are also disposed on said armature shaft, with each armature situated between two permanent magnet polefaces. The armatures are attach to the shaft, said shaft is supported at each end by endframe and rotate there-between. elongated support struts are placed between both endframes and fixedly attach thereto, said struts are part of the framework which support the endframes and also each poleface in the unit attach thereto. The wiring from the armature is taken along a duct cut in the length of the shaft, to a commutator and brush assembly at the output end of said shaft. When a torque is applied to the input shaft, said shaft and all its connected armatures rotate between each set of poleface; current is generated in each armature and is also available at the output.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Unlike the prior art device with its single armature, it is the object of this invention to produce an electric generator having any required number of armature rotating on a single shaft as a unit.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another object of this invention is to provide an electric generator, so configured to supply electricity to all form of electric powered transportation.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Still another object of this invention is to provide an electric generator which can be constructed to meet the need of Residential, Commercial, and Industrial consumer.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Preferably, the endframes and polefaces are substantially the same size. Preferably, the endframes and polefaces are substantially circular and situated substantially in the same plane. Preferably, the support struts are substantially curve to the contour of both the endframes and polefaces.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Preferably, the duct section of the armature shaft is substantially square.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF-DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an isometric view showing the preferred embodiment of the disk armature electric generator with four armatures of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a said isometric view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> but with three armatures;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a said isometric view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> but with two armatures;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a said isometric view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> but with one armature;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a isometric view of a magnetic poleface with opening throughout which the armature shaft intersect;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a isometric view of the disk type armature with windings and opening from which armature shaft is attach;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a isometric view showing one of two endframes with opening for armature shaft;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a isometric view of the elongated support strut with brace attach to each end;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a isometric view of the poleface sleeve;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a isometric view showing the armature shaft having two different section and also a duct.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The quantum disk armature is part of a new type of electric generator, while its configuration is different in many ways to that of the prior art, its operating principle remain the same. The way in which energy is been used will be profoundly change by the new and simple device shown in the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. This is an isometric view of an electric generator having four disk type armatures <b>30</b> with armature windings <b>36</b>, a opening <b>35</b> is provided in the center of each said armature to receive the armature shaft, said opening <b>35</b> is shown at <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> and the center is taken as half the diameter.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Each magnetic poleface <b>40</b> is also of disk form and have opening <b>34</b> cut in the center, said holes are large enough from which armature shaft intersect and rotate therethrough without touching said poleface. The center of each poleface is taken as half the diameter, and each said opening is shown at <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Two endframes <b>43</b> and <b>44</b> are located one at each end of the generator and have opening <b>47</b> and <b>48</b> cut in the center of each said endframe where bearings <b>41</b> and <b>42</b> are fitted. Each endframe <b>43</b> and <b>44</b> are substantially the same size as poleface <b>40</b>, and the centerpoint of said endframes are obtained by using half the length of its diameter. The armature shaft <b>31</b> is shown at <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> with a square section <b>45</b> which carry armature <b>30</b>,</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Each armature <b>30</b> is fitted to the shaft <b>31</b> and fix in place one poleface <b>40</b> is place on each side of armature <b>30</b> on the said shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Duct <b>46</b> is provided along said armature shaft which carry wiring from each armature <b>30</b> to the commutator <b>37</b> shown at <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Said commutator <b>37</b> is attach to the end of shaft <b>31</b> where duct <b>46</b> exit, sleeves <b>39</b> are made to fit the contour of poleface <b>40</b> and serve to secure sleeve <b>39</b> to same.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Elongated support strut <b>32</b> is fashioned to the contour of endframes <b>43</b>,<b>44</b>, and also to sleeve <b>39</b>, the support strut <b>32</b> is shown at <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>; the concave curve along its length give additional strength to the strut. Attach to the end of said struts are braces <b>33</b> which provide support and anchoring for each endframe, and help to strengthen strut <b>32</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> show brush assembly <b>38</b> around commutator <b>37</b> and attach to the inside of endframe <b>43</b>, wiring from each armature <b>30</b> to commutator <b>37</b> via duct <b>46</b> is not shown.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">To produce and assemble such a device is very simple for anyone verse in the art of electric generator and motors.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">With all parts for assemble the armature shaft <b>31</b> is position with commutator <b>37</b> attach to that end from which the duct <b>46</b> exit, each poleface <b>40</b> and armature <b>30</b> are placed on said shaft <b>31</b> in such a way that there is always one armature <b>30</b> between two polefaces <b>40</b>. Said polefaces are of permanent magnet with the sleeves <b>39</b> already attach to poleface <b>40</b> each endframe <b>43</b> and <b>44</b> is place on armature shaft <b>31</b> through bearings <b>41</b> and <b>42</b>, with brush assembly <b>38</b> in position around commutator <b>37</b>, and said shaft extend beyond the second endframe <b>44</b>. wiring from armature windings <b>36</b> is taken to commutator <b>37</b> via duct <b>46</b> and connected thereto, each support strut <b>32</b> is fixedly attach to each endframe <b>43</b> and <b>44</b> mainley with brace <b>33</b> which defined the perimeter of the device. Armature and polefaces are fixed at designated position, which maintain the air-gap required by electric generator and motors. Each poleface <b>40</b>, is situated between supporting struts <b>32</b> and means for fixedly mounting said polefaces between said supporting struts, and armature shaft <b>31</b> rotate through said opening <b>34</b> in poleface <b>40</b>. The length of the device is determine by the number of armatures used, an increase in said armature require an increase in the number of polefaces, the length of armature shaft, and supporting strut.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Assembling is now finish and a torque is applied which rotate shaft <b>31</b> and the armatures attach to it, this rotating armature windings cut the magnetic field set up between the polefaces, and in so doing generate current into the armature windings; this current is available at the output of the generator.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Consideration and appreciation to the present invention relating to a disk type armature electric generator, wherein any required number of disk armature can be design to rotate on a single armature shaft which will vastly increases the output current generated, while reducing the size, weight, and input energy requirement; compare to the prior art generatots.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Any required number of armature can be utilize without significant modification to the overall design of the device, these are a few of the many advantage that accompany this new application.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">There are a limited number of preferred embodiments been disclosed for the purpose of illustration, modification dimensional variations can be readily envisioned to achieve an equivalent result, it is therefore intended to cover all of these variations and modifications which fall within the scope of this invention; and define by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A disk shape armature electric generator, comprising: a armature shaft with duct along said shaft which carry armature wiring, associated with said armature shaft are two or more disks shape magnetic polefaces and one or more disk shape armature winding, each said poleface and armature winding having center aperture from which said shaft intersect and rotate therethrough; polefaces and armature are disposed on said armature shaft in a configuration which position said armature between two polefaces, sleeve means are fastened to the poleface contour and envelops part of said poleface, sleeves attachment secured each poleface in a space apart position which maintain the required airgap between poleface and armature winding; elongated supporting struts also designed to the poleface contour and work in conjunction with each sleeve to support polefaces by fixedly attach said struts to each poleface which also define the perimeter of the device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said armature shaft rotate through center aperture in each poleface without touching said poleface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein any required number of two or more disk shaped armature windings may be disposed on a single armature shaft and rotate between polefaces as a single unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein brace is attached to each end of each supporting strut.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein any required number of two or more disk shape poleface may be disposed on a single shaft to work with the required number of armature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the disk shaped armature, the path taken by each winding is from the center of said armature to any point along its circumference.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the section of armature shaft carrying the armature is square.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> comprising one armature winding.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> comprising two armature windings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> comprising three armature windings.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The generator of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> comprising four armature windings.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
