<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296434-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296434</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11157155</doc-number>
<date>20050620</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>140</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>25</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 624577</main-classification>
<further-classification> 62530</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Cooler</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4286440</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Taylor</name>
<date>19810900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4655052</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Garcia</name>
<date>19870400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4662188</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hullihan</name>
<date>19870500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5230450</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mahvi et al.</name>
<date>19930700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>224153</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5257509</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Harris</name>
<date>19931100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5329787</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Friday</name>
<date>19940700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 62389</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5509279</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Brown et al.</name>
<date>19960400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 624575</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6116045</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hodosh et al.</name>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 624574</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6698230</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Brusky</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 62371</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 624575</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 624577</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 62530</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60581906</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040622</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060021376</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060202</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Scroggs</last-name>
<first-name>Donald T.</first-name>
<address>
<street>200 S. Banana River Dr. B-18</street>
<city>Merrit Island</city>
<state>FL</state>
<postcode>32952</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Beusse Wolter Sanks Mora &amp; Maire, P.A.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Jones</last-name>
<first-name>Melvin</first-name>
<department>3744</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A cooler comprising a first compartment defining an interior region and a portion of the first compartment extending into an interior region of a second compartment. The interior region of the second compartment carries a cooling material that cools the interior region thereof. Heat flow from the interior region of the first compartment into the interior region of the second compartment cools the interior region of the first compartment.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="82.72mm" wi="95.59mm" file="US07296434-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="170.18mm" wi="181.78mm" file="US07296434-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="129.88mm" wi="188.98mm" file="US07296434-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="207.09mm" wi="184.49mm" file="US07296434-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="200.91mm" wi="168.74mm" file="US07296434-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the benefit of the provisional application filed on Jun. 22, 2004, assigned application No. 60/581,906 and entitled Cooler.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an apparatus for cold storage of ice, drinks and food items.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Portable enclosures for cold-temperature storage of ice, drinks and food items are well known. Referred to as “coolers”, they are available in various shapes and sizes, most commonly circular or rectangular in cross section with capacities ranging from one gallon to 75 gallons. Certain embodiments further comprise wheels and/or handles for portability and transportability. Ice (e.g., “dry” ice, ice packs) in the cooler maintains the food and drinks at a sufficiently low temperature to preserve freshness and retard spoilage.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Certain coolers referred to as “water jugs” filled with a water and ice mixture maintain the drinking water at a refreshingly cool temperature. Generally cylindrical in shape, the water jug comprises insulated upstanding sidewalls and a base that cooperate to define an open interior region. An openable or removable lid provides access to the interior region. The ice and water within the open region are insulated from ambient temperature and thus maintained at a lower temperature. Drinking water is withdrawn from the water jug by opening a manually operated valve disposed proximate the base.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The water jug also protects its ice and water contents from environmental contaminants, as access to the interior region is not required to dispense the water. The potable water remains clean and cold. Therefore it is generally not advisable to store containered drinks (cans and bottles) or food items in the water jug cooler, as contaminants on a container surface may contaminate the potable water. The act of placing an item in or removing an item from the water jug by reaching one's hand into the water jug may also contaminate the water. Water jugs are therefore best suited for a single function of storing only water.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Ice chest type coolers also have a single function. Generally rectangular in cross section, the ice chest comprises insulated upstanding sidewalls and a base that cooperate to define an open interior region. Ice, food (e.g., packaged food items) and/or containered drink items to be maintained at a low temperature are stored within the interior region. The beverage containers and packaged food items are typically placed above and in contact with exposed ice. A hinged or removable cooler door permits access to the stored items. Because dirt and contaminants may be present on the beverage containers and food packages, the water formed by ice melting within the container is generally not considered potable. Although an ice chest may include a valved nozzle or a drain, such is intended for draining water from the ice chest, not for providing access to clean drinking water.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to one embodiment, the invention comprises a cooler further comprising a first enclosed volume having a first controllable opening to provide access to an interior region thereof, a second enclosed volume surrounding a portion of the first enclosed volume, the second enclosed volume having a second controllable opening to provide access to an interior region thereof and wherein a material within the second enclosed volume cools the first enclosed volume.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The foregoing and other features of the invention will be apparent from the following more particular description of the invention, as illustrated in the accompanying drawings, in which like reference characters refer to the same parts throughout the different figures. The drawings are not necessarily to scale, emphasis instead being placed upon illustrating the principles of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> illustrate two configurations of a cooler of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a top view of the cooler of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> illustrate cross-sectional interior views of another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-8</figref> illustrate additional embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates a door-open configuration for the cooler embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Before describing in detail the particular cooler in accordance with the present invention, it should be observed that the present invention resides primarily in a novel combination of elements. Accordingly, the elements have been represented by conventional elements in the drawings, showing only those specific details that are pertinent to the present invention, so as not to obscure the disclosure with structural details that will be readily apparent to those skilled in the art having the benefit of the description herein.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A cooler constructed according to the teachings of the present invention offers advantages of both the water jug and ice chest type prior art coolers, but avoids their disadvantages. As illustrated in the various views of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>, a cooler <b>10</b> comprises an enclosed volume <b>12</b> (e.g., a cold water or water jug type storage enclosure) having an interior region in which is disposed a portion of an enclosed volume <b>16</b> (e.g., an ice chest type storage enclosure).</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The enclosed volume <b>12</b> in one embodiment comprises a cooled vessel containing water and ice cubes (where “ice cubes” is intended to encompass any of the various known cooling elements, solids, or mechanisms, including ice rectangles, crescents, particles, chips, pieces, ice packs and “dry” ice and refrigerant-based mechanical cooling systems). The enclosed volume <b>16</b> in one embodiment stores packaged items, such as packaged food or drink containers that are desired to be kept in a relatively cool environment.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">A wall <b>17</b> provides a physical barrier between the interior region of the enclosed volume <b>12</b> and the interior region of the enclosed volume <b>16</b> prevents physical contact between the contents of each. But since the interior regions are in a heat-exchange relationship, heat flows from the warmer enclosed volume to the colder enclosed volume to cool the contents of the former. Thus the coolant material or mechanism of the enclosed volume <b>12</b> cools the contents of the enclosed volume <b>16</b> as well as the contents of the enclosed volume <b>12</b>. Specifically, the ice cubes and cold water within the enclosed volume <b>12</b> provide a cooling source for the packaged items stored within the enclosed volume <b>16</b>, permitting the packaged items to be maintained at a cold temperature without requiring the use of ice within the enclosed volume <b>16</b>. By avoiding the use of ice within the enclosed volume <b>16</b>, an external surface of the packaged and containered items remains in a relatively dry condition.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">A door <b>18</b> pivotally affixed to the enclosed volume <b>16</b> is illustrated in an opened position in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> the door <b>18</b> is illustrated in a closed position. The enclosed volume <b>12</b> comprises a removable lid <b>20</b>. Preferably one or both of the enclosed volumes <b>12</b> and <b>16</b> comprises one or more handles <b>21</b> for transporting the cooler <b>10</b> and/or for controlling a position of the door <b>18</b> and/or the lid <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Each of the enclosed volumes <b>12</b> and <b>16</b> comprises a plurality of insulated wall surfaces that provide a thermal barrier to the ambient atmosphere, which is generally warmer than the desired temperature of the interior region of the enclosed volumes <b>12</b> and <b>16</b>. Specifically, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the volume <b>12</b> is defined in part by an interior surface <b>26</b><i>a </i>along an insulated wall section <b>26</b>, and the volume <b>16</b> is defined in part by an interior surface <b>28</b><i>a </i>along an insulated wall section <b>28</b>. As is known by those skilled in the art, the insulated wall surfaces can be constructed from various materials, including molded plastics. Typically each wall surface comprises an inner wall surface in parallel relationship with an outer wall surface, defining an interspace therebetween, wherein the interspace is preferably filled with an insulating material. The shape and size of the enclosed volumes <b>12</b> and <b>16</b> are not critical to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As can also be seen clearly in the top view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> with the lid <b>20</b> removed, a portion <b>24</b> of the enclosed volume <b>16</b> extends into an interior region of the enclosed volume <b>12</b>. In one embodiment, the wall surfaces of the enclosed volume <b>16</b> disposed within the interior region of the enclosed volume <b>12</b> are not insulated, as are the other wall surfaces, to maximize heat flow from the interior region of the enclosed volume <b>16</b> to the interior region of enclosed volume <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Thus the ice and water within the enclosed volume <b>12</b> provide cooling for the interior of the enclosed volume <b>16</b> and the beneficial effects of each cooler type are achieved. There is no melting ice within the enclosed volume <b>16</b> to soak or damage the packaged items stored there, and the cold water in the enclosed volume <b>12</b> is isolated from any contamination sources, permitting potable water to be dispensed from a valve, not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>, affixed to the enclosed volume <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> are cross-sectional interior views of another embodiment of a combination cooler <b>30</b> taken through a plane parallel to a front surface (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) and through a plane parallel to a side surface (FIG. <b>5</b>) of the combination cooler <b>30</b>, respectively. The cooler <b>30</b> comprises an insulating material <b>31</b> within an enclosure defining external wall and base surfaces <b>32</b>. Food and beverage items are stored in an interior region <b>33</b> defined by a wall <b>17</b> substantially surrounded by a water/ice storage region <b>36</b>. Clean water is dispensed from the water/ice storage region <b>36</b> via a valve <b>38</b>. The water/ice within the region <b>36</b> is physically separated from and therefore not contaminated by the food and beverage items stored within the interior region <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">A lid <b>40</b> closes a top surface <b>41</b> of the combination cooler <b>30</b>, providing access to the water/ice region <b>36</b> when removed. In one embodiment, the lid <b>40</b> is received by an annular ring within the top surface <b>39</b>. In another embodiment a hinge <b>42</b> pivotally attaches the lid <b>40</b> to one of the wall surfaces <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Access to the interior region <b>33</b> is provided through a door <b>44</b> disposed in one of the wall surfaces <b>32</b>. The door <b>44</b> may be hinged or otherwise removable according to known techniques. The door <b>44</b> is held in the closed position with a latch <b>45</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In one embodiment, an insulating layer <b>50</b> (not shown) may be included in the wall <b>17</b> between the interior region <b>33</b> and the water/ice storage region <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-8</figref> illustrate additional embodiments of the present invention, including an embodiment with handles <b>60</b> disposed on opposing side wall surfaces of the cooler <b>30</b>, an embodiment <b>30</b>A comprising wheels <b>62</b> and a handle <b>66</b>, and an embodiment <b>30</b>B comprising straps <b>70</b>. These embodiments, which are merely illustrative, depict different structural features and transportation modes for the various cooler embodiments according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> illustrates the cooler <b>30</b> with the door <b>44</b> in the open position. The door <b>44</b> is attached to the cooler <b>30</b> with hinges <b>76</b> for pivotal displacement to expose the interior region <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">As can be seen in the various presented embodiments of the combination cooler <b>30</b>, the water/ice storage region surrounds the region <b>33</b>, creating a “refrigerator like” cooling function for the packaged or containered items stored within the region <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">While the invention has been described with reference to preferred embodiments, it will be understood by those skilled in the art that various changes may be made and equivalent elements may be substituted for elements thereof without departing from the scope of the present invention. The scope of the present invention further includes any combination of the elements from the various embodiments set forth herein. In addition, modifications may be made to adapt a particular situation to the teachings of the present invention without departing from its essential scope thereof For example, different sized and shaped components can be employed to form a cooler according to the teachings of the present invention. Therefore, it is intended that the invention not be limited to the particular embodiment disclosed as the best mode contemplated for carrying out this invention, but that the invention will include all embodiments falling within the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A cooler comprising:
<claim-text>a first enclosure of a first shape including a first enclosed volume and including a first controllable opening to provide access to an interior region thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second enclosure of a second shape including a second enclosed volume partly defined by an insulated wall portion providing a thermal barrier relative to an ambient condition,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first and second shapes both defined in part with a wall portion common to each, a portion of the second volume extending about a portion of the first volume, so that the portion of the first volume is disposed within a region defined by the second shape,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second enclosure including a second controllable opening to provide access to an interior region thereof; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first and second enclosed volumes are separated from one another by a single wall common to each through which the first and second enclosed volumes are in a heat exchange relationship so that when a cooling material is placed within the second enclosed volume the first enclosed volume is cooled by heat exchange through the single common wall.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The cooler of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the cooling material may be taken from the group including ice, dry ice and water.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The cooler of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the second enclosed volume is connected to a valve for dispensing a liquid from the second enclosed volume.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The cooler of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein external surfaces defining the first enclosed volume bounds the interior region thereof, and wherein one external surface defines the first controllable opening, and wherein a closure structure received within the first controllable opening has a first position for providing access to the interior region and a second position for closing the first controllable opening.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The cooler of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein external surfaces defining the second enclosed volume bound the interior region thereof, and wherein one external surface defines the second controllable opening, and wherein a closure structure received within the second controllable opening has a first position for providing access to the interior region and a second position for closing the second controllable opening.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An insulated structure comprising:
<claim-text>first wall surfaces cooperating to define a first interior region, wherein one of the first wall surfaces defines a first closable opening therein through which access is gained to the first interior region; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>insulated second wall surfaces cooperating to define a second interior region, wherein at least a portion of the first interior region extends into the second interior region, and wherein one of the insulated second wall surfaces defines a second closable opening therein through which access is gained to the second interior region, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first and second interior regions are separated from one another by a single wall common to each through which the first and second interior regions are in a heat exchange relationship so that when a cooling agent is placed within the second enclosed volume the first enclosed volume is cooled by heat exchange through the single common wall.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The insulated structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the cooling agent comprises ice cubes and the contents of the second interior region may comprise water.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The insulated structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further comprising a valve for dispensing water from the second interior region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An insulated structure comprising
<claim-text>first surfaces cooperating to define a first closed interior region, wherein a side surface of the first surfaces defines a first closable opening providing access to the first closed interior region; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>second insulated surfaces cooperating to define a second closed interior region, wherein the first closed interior region is disposed wholly within the second closed interior region, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein an externally disposed upper surface of the second insulated surfaces defines a second closable opening providing access to the second closed interior region, and wherein, when the second interior region carries a cooling agent, heat is drawn from the first interior region.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The insulated structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the cooling agent comprises ice cubes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The insulated structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> further comprising a valve for dispensing water from the second interior region.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An insulated structure comprising:
<claim-text>a first closed volume defined by a first container including a first closable opening providing access to the first closed volume; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second closed volume positioned along the first closed volume and separated from the first closed volume by a single wall having first and second opposing surfaces, the first wall surface providing an interior wall of the first closed volume and the second wall surface providing an interior wall of the second closed volume,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second closed volume is defined by a second container including the second wall surface and a second closable opening providing access to the second closed volume, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, when a cooling agent is present in, or acts on, the second closed volume, heat can be withdrawn from the first closed volume by a heat transfer through the wall.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The insulated structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the second closed volume has a shape defined by a combination comprising said single wall and an insulated wall surface, and a portion of the first closed volume is positioned within the shape of the second closed volume.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The insulated structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the cooling agent comprises ice cubes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The insulated structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising a valve for dispensing a liquid from the second closed volume.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The structure of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the single wall common to the first and second interior regions includes at least some of the first surfaces.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
