<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298480-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298480</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11315334</doc-number>
<date>20051223</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>104</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>J</subclass>
<main-group>4</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356364</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Broadband ellipsometer / polarimeter system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5396329</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kalawsky</name>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>356364</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5706212</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Thompson et al.</name>
<date>19980100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6141069</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sharp et al.</name>
<date>20001000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349 98</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6552836</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Miller</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>359237</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0122514</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Jang</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>356365</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>Bennett, “A critical evaluation of Rhomb-type quarterwave retarders,” <i>Applied Optics</i>, vol. 9, No. 9, Sep. 1970, pp. 2123-2129.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>Collins et al., “Advances in multichannel ellipsometric techjniques for in-situ and real-time characterization of thin films,” <i>Thin Solid Films</i>, vol. 38, No. 46, 2004, pp. 469-470.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Filinski et al., “Achromatic phase retarders constructed from right-angle prisms: design,” <i>Applied Optics</i>, vol. 23, No. 16, Aug. 15, 1984, pp. 2747-2751.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>Compain et al., “Broadband division-of-amplitude polarimeter based on uncoated prisms,” <i>Applied Optics</i>, vol. 37, No. 25, Sep. 1, 1998, pp. 5938-5944.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00010">
<othercit>Compain et al., “General and self-consistent method for the calibration of polarization modulators, polarimeters, and Mueller-matrix ellipsometers,” <i>Applied Optics</i>, vol. 38, No. 16, Jun. 1, 1999, pp. 3490-3502.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>Goldstein, “Mueller matrix dual-rotating retarder polarimeter,” <i>Applied Optics</i>, vol. 31, No. 31, Nov. 1, 1992, pp. 6676-6683.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>De Martino et al., “Optimized Mueller polarimeter with liquid crystals,” <i>Optics Letters</i>, vol. 28, No. 8, Apr. 15, 2003, pp. 616-618.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00013">
<othercit>Nagib et al., “Optimization of a rhomb-type quarter-wave phase retarder,” <i>Applied Optics</i>, vol. 34, No. 16, Jun. 1, 1995, pp. 2927-2930.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00014">
<othercit>Rochford et al., “Design and performance of a stable linear retarder,” <i>Applied Optics</i>, vol. 36, No. 25, Sep. 1, 1997, pp. 6458-6465.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00015">
<othercit>Tyo, “Design of optimal polarimeters: maximization of signal-to-noise ratio and minimization of systematic error,” <i>Applied Optics</i>, vol. 41, No. 4, Feb. 1, 2002, pp. 619-630.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00016">
<othercit>Sabatke, D.S. et al., “Optimization of retardance for a complete Stokes polarimeter”, Optics Letters, vol. 25, No. 11, Jun. 1, 2000, pp. 802-804, XP-02412779.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>26</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070146706</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070628</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Garcia-Caurel</last-name>
<first-name>Enric</first-name>
<address>
<city>Paris</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>De Martino</last-name>
<first-name>Antonello</first-name>
<address>
<city>Massy</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Drevillon</last-name>
<first-name>Bernard</first-name>
<address>
<city>Clamart</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Young &amp; Thompson</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ecole Polytechnique</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Palaiseau</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Stafira</last-name>
<first-name>Michael P.</first-name>
<department>2886</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system for analyzing a sample includes an illumination source emitting a polychromatic light beam, a polarization state generator (PSG) including a fixed linear polarizer and a substantially achromatic retarder mounted on a rotating holder, a sample holder, a polarization state analyser (PSA) including a fixed linear polarizer and a substantially achromatic retarder mounted on a rotating holder, a primary detection system measuring the intensities at each wavelength of the light beam transmitted through the PSA, optics to collimate the beam into the PSG and into the PSA and to focus the beam into the sample surface and the detector. The linear polarizer and achromatic retarder in the PSA are identical to those of the PSG but mounted in a reverse order.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="103.97mm" wi="167.64mm" file="US07298480-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="217.93mm" wi="167.13mm" file="US07298480-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="205.32mm" wi="125.48mm" file="US07298480-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="201.93mm" wi="114.13mm" file="US07298480-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="192.11mm" wi="165.27mm" file="US07298480-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="178.22mm" wi="176.95mm" file="US07298480-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="88.73mm" wi="166.96mm" file="US07298480-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="211.75mm" wi="173.48mm" file="US07298480-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention concerns a broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system and a method of polarimetric measurement of Mueller matrices.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Ellipsometry is a non-destructive characterization technique that measures the change in polarization state of light reflected (or transmitted) by a sample.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present ellipsometric/polarimetric system contains an excitation section emitting a light beam. Said light beam passes through a polarisation state generator (PSG) and is focused on the sample. After being transmitted, reflected or scattered by the sample, the beam goes through an analysis section containing a polarisation state analyser (PSA) and a detection means.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Such PSG and PSA (which is also called PSD (polarisation state detector)) are described in the document US2004130717.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In a PSG, the light polarization can be modulated by a variety of devices such as discrete components inserted and then removed from the light path {Bickel W. S. et al.; Am. J. Phys 53 (1984) 468}, rotating retardation plates {Goldstein D. H.; Appl. Opt. 31 (1992) 6676}, rotating compensators {Collins R. W. and Koh J.; J. Opt. Soc. A 16, (1999) 1997}, Pockels cells {Delplancke F.; Appl. Opt. 36 (1997) 5388 and Compain E. and Drévillon B.; Rev. Sci. Instrum. 68 (1997) 2671} or photoacoustic modulators {Compain E. and Drévillon B.; Rev. Sci. Instrum. 69, (1998) 1574}.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">For PSA, one can use the same devices and a single detector, or a “parallel” analysis of light polarization through polarization-sensitive beamsplitters and simultaneous measurement of the separated beams by several detectors {Azzam R. M. A., Opt. Acta 29 (1982) 685, Brudzewski K.; J. Modern Optics 38 (1991) 889, Khrishnan S.; J. Opt. Soc. Am A 9 (1992) 1615, Compain E. et al., Thin Solid Films 313 (1998)}.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The optical set-up is completed with appropriate optics to collimate the beam into the PSG and into the PSA, and to focus the beam onto the sample surface and on the detector. The PSG generates a set of four independent states of polarization, which after being transformed by the sample, are projected over the PSA to be analyzed. The PSA produces a set of four independent optical configurations to analyze the polarization of the light emerging from the sample for each state that was previously created by the PSG. As a result, a complete measurement run yields a set of 16 independent values that eventually, allows the calculation of the sample Mueller matrix or ellipsometric angles.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">To date, several ellipsometers/polarimeters have been described, most of them working in the ultraviolet—visible (UV-VIS) wavelength range (250 to 900 nm) and only a small number working in the mid infrared (IR) (4 to 20 microns) or in the far ultraviolet (FUV) (140 nm-250 nm). This fact can be roughly explained because typically optical elements perform better in the UV-VIS than in the IR of the FUV and also because even though the visible spectral range is relatively narrow, it appears to be sufficient for some applications. However, there is an increasing interest in expanding the measured spectra because FUV and IR have particular advantages. The IR gives unique information about the chemical bonding within a sample, which is inaccessible to the sole UV-VIS. Moreover, because of its longer wavelengths, the IR, is less sensitive than the UV-VIS to surface structures (roughness, inhomogeneity among others). It is also better suited to the analysis of thick films (&gt;several microns) that usually make the interpretation of conventional measurements difficult. On the other hand, the shortness of the FUV wavelengths make it ideal to measure the thickness of very thin films (&lt;a few nm), in addition, the enhanced sensitivity of FUV to small defects and structures in the surface of samples is used for surface state quality control. Finally, it is of general agreement that the wider the measured spectral range, the better is the reliability of the final results.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The preceding arguments prove the necessity for an apparatus providing ellipsometric/polarimetric measurements in spectral ranges as wide as possible. Two particular interesting ranges are the IR range from 4 to 20 microns, and the FUV-NIR from 140 nm to 2 microns.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Briefly, the disclosed apparatus uses polarizers and retarders to create and to analyze the polarization state of a radiation beam. This apparatus is operated by placing the retarders at a set of 16 different orientations with respect to the polarizers, which are kept still.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In order to work in optimal conditions over all the measured spectral range, the polarizers and the retarders used in the instrument must be as much achromatic as possible. The operation mode of the disclosed ellipsometer/polarimeter system imposes an additional constraint to the design of the retarders. They must not deviate the beam even when they are rotated about an axis defined by the direction of the beam. Even if substantially achromatic polarizers can eventually be found commercially this is not always the case for substantially achromatic retarders.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An article of Benett et al. {Appl. Opt., (1970)}, has been used as a reference to select the most adapted types and characteristics of the retarders to be used in the disclosed ellipsometer/polarimeter system. In said article, Bennett et al., compare the optical performances of low order, zero order and total internal reflection (TIR) based retarders. The conclusion is that, even though TIR retarders are more sensitive to the beam alignment and aperture than the low order and zero order plates, they seem to be the optimum choice to be integrated into wide range spectroscopic systems because of their enhanced achromatism.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Concerning achromatic retarders, an article of Oxley {Phil. Mag., (1911)} has been considered because it gives some insight on the manufacture of two types of TIR based quarter wave retarders that do not deviate the beam when they are rotated. One of them is a V-shaped retarder made of two Fresnel rhombs, called bi-prism. The bi-prism geometry has become popular because of the easiness of construction and high achromaticity.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A patent of Thomson et al. {U.S. Pat. No 5,706,212}, describes an infrared ellipsometer/polarimeter system using pseudo-achromatic retarders. Each one of said retarders consists of a bi-prism cut to a given angle in order to create a total retardation of ¾λ. In a preferred embodiment, the ellipsometer has two retarders located respectivelly before and after the sample. During current operation of the ellipsometer/polarimeter, each retarder is rotated to a minimum of nine 9 azimuthal angle settings leading to at least eighty one 81 different raw data acquisitions. These acquisitions are then decomposed in terms of a double discrete Fourier series. From the coefficients of the said Fourier series, it is possible to calculate the characteristic Mueller matrix of the sample and of the optical components of the ellipsometer/polarimeter.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">One aim of the present invention consists to provide an ellipsometer/polarimeter system allowing simpler data analysis with less parameters for the calculation of the Mueller matrix, and without a signal processing based on a series expansion, such as a Fourier series. As a result, the time needed for measurements and data treatment are then reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Another aim of the invention is to provide a ellipsometer/polarimeter system comprising substantially achromatic retarders with optimized retardation to guarantee a uniform quality of the measurements for all the wavelengths in the light beam, and an optimization of the system performance by minimizing the propagation of noise and errors in the calculation of the Mueller matrix.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">To this end, the invention concerns a broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system for analysing a sample comprising:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0018">an illumination source emitting a polychromatic light beam,</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0019">a polarisation state generator (PSG) including a fixed linear polarizer and a substantially achromatic retarder mounted on a rotating holder, said light beam passing through said PSG,</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0003" num="0020">a sample holder, on which the sample can be mounted, the light beam being focused on the sample,</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0004" num="0021">a polarisation state analyser (PSA) including a fixed linear polarizer and a substantially achromatic retarder mounted on a rotating holder, the beam going through said PSA, after being transmitted, reflected or scattered by the sample.</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0005" num="0022">a primary detection system measuring the intensity of the light beam transmitted through said PSA at each wavelength,</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0006" num="0023">optics to collimate the beam into the PSG and into the PSA and to focus the beam into the sample surface.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0024">According to the invention:
<ul id="ul0003" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0003-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0004" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0004-0001" num="0025">said linear polarizer and said substantially achromatic retarder in the PSA are identical to the linear polarizer and the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSG and inverted according to the sense of propagation of the light. Here, “identical” means either “the same elements”, or “equivalent elements with the same optical properties”,</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0002" num="0026">said rotating holders run in a stepper mode allowing a set of only four selected orientation angles for the retarders, said set of four selected orientation angles being optimized in order to maintain the condition numbers of the modulation and analysis matrices associated respectively with the PSG and the PSA over 0.2.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0027">According to various embodiments, the present invention also concerns the characteristics below, considered individually or in all their technical possible combinations:
<ul id="ul0005" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0005-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0006" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0006-0001" num="0028">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSG is a total internal reflection based retarder providing a phase-shift of either {132°±30°+n360°} or {227°±30°+n360°}, for all the wavelength light beam, with “n” being any integer,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0002" num="0029">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSA is a total internal reflection based retarder providing a phase-shift of either {132°±30°+n360°} or {227°±30°+n360°}, for all the wavelengths of the light beam, with “n” being any integer,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0003" num="0030">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSG is placed at a set of four selected orientation angles θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3 </sub>and θ<sub>4</sub>, said θ<sub>1 </sub>being either {38±20°+n360°} or {218±20°+n360°}, said θ<sub>2</sub>, being either {75±20°+n360°} or {255±20°+n360°}, said θ<sub>3 </sub>being either {104±20°+n360°} or {284±20°+n360°}, and said θ<sub>4 </sub>being {142±20°+n360°} or {322±20°+n360°}, with “n” being any integer,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0004" num="0031">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSA is placed at a set of four selected orientation angles θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3 </sub>and θ<sub>4</sub>, said θ<sub>1 </sub>being either {38±20°+n360°} or {218±20°+n360°}, said θ<sub>2</sub>, being either {75±20°+n360°} or {255±20°+n360°}, said θ<sub>3 </sub>being either {104±20°+n360°} or {284±20°+n360°}, and said θ<sub>4 </sub>being {142±20°+n360°} or {322±20°+n360°}, with “n” being any integer,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0005" num="0032">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSG and the PSA comprises at least two prisms, each substantially achromatic retarder causing at least four internal reflections to the light beam entering on it and said beam is not deviated,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0006" num="0033">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSG is a “V” shaped bi-prism, consisting of two rhombs having an identical shape, optically assembled by one of their sides,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0007" num="0034">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSA is a “V” shaped bi-prism, consisting of two rhombs having an identical shape, optically assembled by one of their sides,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0008" num="0035">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSG comprises three triangular prisms from which, at least two have an identical shape,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0009" num="0036">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSA comprises three triangular prisms from which, at least two have an identical shape,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0010" num="0037">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSG comprises three prisms, two prisms of said three prisms are triangular and one prism is trapezoidal,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0011" num="0038">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSA comprises three prisms, two prisms of said three prisms are triangular and one prism is trapezoidal,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0012" num="0039">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSG comprises four trapezoidal prisms having an identical shape,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0013" num="0040">the substantially achromatic retarder of the PSA comprises four trapezoidal prisms having an identical shape,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0014" num="0041">each prism is made of a material with an index of refraction greater than that of the surrounding media,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0015" num="0042">the entrance and exit faces of the retarders comprise an antireflection treatment (coating) to minimise light insertion losses,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0016" num="0043">the faces of the prisms wherein total internal reflection takes place, are uncoated,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0017" num="0044">the prisms of the substantially achromatic retarders are made of a material presenting a low index of refraction like the BaF<sub>2</sub>,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0018" num="0045">the primary detection system measures simultaneously the intensity of all the wavelengths of the light beam transmitted through said PSA,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0019" num="0046">the primary detection system measures simultaneously and separately the intensity of each wavelength of the light beam transmitted through said PSA,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0020" num="0047">the system includes a holder for reference samples, said holder is placed between the PSG and the sample holder, said holder introduce a set of reference samples in the beam path during calibration, and remove them during measurement process,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0021" num="0048">the system includes a holder for reference samples, said holder is placed between the sample holder and the PSA, said holder introduce a set of reference samples in the beam path during calibration, and remove them during measurement process,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0022" num="0049">said system includes a secondary detection system to monitor the power given by the illumination source including a beam-splitter located between the illumination source and the PSG and a secondary detector,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0023" num="0050">said system operates in a spectral range from 4 to 20 microns,</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0024" num="0051">said system operates in a FUV-NIR spectral range from 140 nm to 2000 nm.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0052">To facilitate the description of the invention, the following drawings are provided in which:</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0053"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a functional block diagram of the ellipsometer/polarimeter system in transmission configuration, according to a particular embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0054"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a functional block diagram of the ellipsometer/polarimeter system in reflection configuration, according to a particular embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0055"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> displays the condition number of the PSG as a function of the phase-shift of a retarder for a given set of four optimal azimuth orientations;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0056"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the values of the condition number calculated as a function of the retarder azimuth θ<sub>1</sub>, with the other three azimuths and the retardation kept constant to their optimum value;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows the values of the condition number calculated as a function of the retarder azimuth θ<sub>2 </sub>with the other three azimuths and the retardation kept constant to their optimum value;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0058"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows the values of the condition number calculated as a function of the retarder azimuth θ<sub>3 </sub>with the other three azimuths and the retardation kept constant to their optimum value;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0059"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows the values of the condition number calculated as a function of the retarder azimuth θ<sub>4 </sub>with the other three azimuths and the retardation kept constant to their optimum value;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0060"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> displays a substantially achromatic retarder consisting of a bi-prism made of two identical Fresnel rhombs disposed symmetrically and optically assembled giving to the retarder a “V” shape;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0061"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> displays a particular embodiment of a substantially achromatic retarder made of a set of three triangular prisms optically assembled;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0062"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> displays another particular embodiment of a substantially achromatic retarder made of two triangular prisms and a third trapezoidal one optically assembled;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0063"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> displays another particular embodiment of a substantially achromatic retarder made of four identical trapezoidal prisms optically assembled;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0064"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a schematic representation of a possible embodiment of the ellipsometer/polarimeter system optimized for the infrared, set in transmission;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0065"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a schematic representation of another possible embodiment of the ellipsometer/polarimeter system optimized for the infrared, set in reflection configuration;</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0066"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> represent a functional block diagram of the disclosed ellipsometer/polarimeter system mounted respectively in transmission configuration and in reflection configuration according to two particular embodiments of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0067">Said systems include an entrance arm <b>1</b>, a sample holder system <b>3</b> to fix the studied sample <b>8</b>, and an exit arm <b>2</b>. The entry arm <b>1</b> includes an illumination source <b>5</b>, a polarization state generator or PSG <b>6</b> and a holder for reference samples <b>7</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0068">The PSG <b>6</b> includes a linear polarizer <b>13</b> and a substantially achromatic retarder <b>21</b>. The retarder of the PSG <b>21</b> is mounted on a rotating holder <b>14</b> that allows it to be placed at different orientations.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0069">The exit arm <b>2</b> includes a second holder for reference samples <b>9</b>, a polarisation state analyser or, PSA <b>10</b>, and a primary detection system <b>11</b> measuring the intensity of the light beam transmitted through said PSA (<b>10</b>) at each wavelength.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0070">The PSA <b>10</b> has the same elements that the PSG <b>6</b>, a linear polarizer <b>20</b> and a substantially achromatic retarder <b>22</b>, but located in reverse order (inverted according to the sense of propagation of the light).</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0071">The retarder of the PSA <b>22</b> is mounted on a rotating holder <b>19</b> allowing it to be set at different orientations. The holders for the reference samples <b>7</b> and <b>9</b>, introduce a set of specific samples <b>15</b>, <b>16</b>, <b>17</b> and <b>18</b> in the beam path during calibration, and remove them during measurement process. The optical path starts with the beam <b>12</b> emitted by the illumination source <b>5</b>. Said light beam <b>12</b> passes through the PSG <b>6</b> and is focused on the sample <b>8</b> on the sample holder system <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0072">After reflection on the sample surface, the beam goes through the analysis section <b>2</b>, containing the PSA <b>10</b>, and is finally focused into the sensitive area of the primary detection system <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0073">The optical set-up is completed with the appropriate optics to collimate the beam into the PSG <b>6</b> and into the PSA <b>10</b>, and to focus the beam into the sample <b>8</b> surface and the sensitive area of the primary detection system <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0074">In one embodiment of the invention, the primary detection system <b>11</b> measures simultaneously the intensity of all the wavelengths of the light beam transmitted through the PSA <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0075">In another embodiment of the invention, the primary detection system <b>11</b> measures simultaneously and separately the intensity of each wavelength of the light beam transmitted through the PSA <b>10</b></p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0076">The primary detection system <b>11</b> is linked to a computer or a data acquisition and processing system <b>4</b>. The computer <b>4</b>, or an equivalent tool, allows to monitor the detection systems <b>11</b>, <b>32</b> signals, to store raw data and to perform pertinent mathematical treatment of the raw data to obtain Mueller matrices, ellipsometric Ψ and Δ angles, as well as other derived data. The computer <b>4</b> also controls the position of the rotating holders <b>14</b>, <b>19</b> and the holders for the reference samples <b>7</b>, <b>9</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0077">The system can also include, as an option, a secondary detection system <b>32</b> made of a beam-splitter <b>23</b> and a secondary detector <b>24</b>. The beam-splitter <b>23</b> is located between the illumination source <b>5</b> and the PSG <b>6</b> and it sends a small portion of the beam power towards the secondary detector <b>24</b>. The signal measured by the secondary detector <b>24</b> can be used, among others, as a reference to normalize the signals measured by the primary detection system <b>11</b>. Data normalization prevents errors due to power fluctuations of the beam <b>12</b> emitted by the source <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0078">The use of substantially achromatic optical elements (polarizers <b>13</b>, <b>20</b> and retarders <b>21</b>, <b>22</b>) guarantees a uniform quality of the measurements through the studied spectral range.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0079">The advantage of rotating the retarders <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> instead of the polarizers <b>13</b>, <b>20</b> is to prevent the influence of the original polarization of the beam <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0080">The PSG <b>6</b> generates four polarization states by placing sequentially the retarder of the PSG <b>21</b> at four selected orientations respect to the transmission axis of the PSG polarizer <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0081">The rotation motion of the retarder <b>21</b> is not continuous; the rotating holder <b>14</b>, runs in a stepper mode, thus making a key difference with respect to other reported rotating compensator ellipsometers/polarimeters.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0082">Indeed, the small number of states produced by the PSG <b>6</b>, (four instead of nine), in comparison with a previously described apparatus of the document U.S. Pat. No. 5,706,212, makes its operation faster and simpler.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0083">Like in the PSG <b>6</b>, the retarder of the PSA <b>22</b> is mounted in a rotating holder <b>19</b> that allows it to be oriented at four different angles with respect to the transmission axis of the polarizer of the PSA <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0084">The four selected orientation angles for the two retarders <b>21</b> and <b>22</b> are optimized in order to maintain the condition numbers of the modulation and the analysis matrices associated respectively with the PSG <b>6</b> and the PSA <b>10</b> over 0.2.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0085">Optionaly, the four selected orientation angles for the two retarders <b>21</b> and <b>22</b> are approximately identical.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0086">After reflection or transmission by the sample <b>8</b>, each one of the polarization states that had been originally generated by the PSG <b>6</b>, is successively analyzed four times by the PSA <b>10</b>, giving as a result <b>16</b> independent intensity measurements (raw data) necessary for the determination of the Mueller matrix.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0087">The four polarization states generated in the PSG <b>6</b>, as well of the optical configurations of the PSA <b>10</b>, are not obvious or intuitive; they have been selected according to an objective criterion (condition numbers) that allows the minimization of the propagation of errors from the measurement to the computed Mueller matrix.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0088">In the following, the mathematical description of the PSG <b>6</b> used to define the criterion for instrument optimization is reviewed. Because the PSA <b>10</b> is identical to the PSG <b>6</b>, the physical principles, the mathematical description and the technological parameters giving rise to the optimization of the PSG <b>6</b> are also applicable to the PSA <b>10</b>. It is common to use a 4×4 matrix, W, called modulation matrix, to represent the PSG <b>6</b> and an analysis matrix, A, to represent the PSA <b>10</b>. The columns of the W matrix correspond to the four Stokes vectors generated by the PSG <b>6</b>. Reciprocally, for each state generated by the PSG <b>6</b>, the corresponding polarization state of the emerging light is projected over four optical configurations generated by the PSA <b>10</b>. The four dimensional signal vector D, eventually delivered by the PSA <b>10</b>, is related to each Stokes vector S<sub>out </sub>generated by the PSG by a linear relation D=AS<sub>out</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0089">The result of a complete polarimetric measurement, consists of sixteen independent raw intensity measurements that can be expressed by a matrix B=AMW, where A and W are respectively the analysis and modulation matrices defined above, and M the Mueller matrix of the sample. If A and W are known, then M can be extracted from the raw data B as M=A<sup>−1</sup>BW<sup>−1</sup>. The determination of A and W is called calibration of the polarimeter.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0090">Obviously, the instrument must be designed in such a way that A and W are non singular. Moreover, in order to minimize the error propagation from the raw measurement B to the final result M, the analysis and modulation matrices A and W must be “as close as possible” to unitary matrices.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0091">The best criterion in this respect is to optimize their condition numbers c(A) and c(W), which are the ratios of the smallest over the largest of their singular values, see for example W. H. Press et al. {Numerical Recipes in PASCAL, p <b>53</b>}, who actually define the condition number as the reciprocal of that defined here.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0092">In order to find the values of the azimuths and the retardation of the retarder <b>21</b> that optimize c(W), a convenient approach is to simulate the optical behaviour of PSG <b>6</b> treating the polarizer <b>13</b> and the retarder <b>21</b> as ideal. The ideal Mueller matrix for the polarizer <b>13</b> is:</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0093">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mi>P</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <msub>
            <mi>τ</mi>
            <mi>P</mi>
          </msub>
          <mo>⁡</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mtable>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
            </mtable>
            <mo>)</mo>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
<br/>
with τ<sub>P </sub>being the polarizer <b>13</b> transmittance. The matrix of an ideal retarder <b>21</b> with transmittance τ<sub>R</sub>, a retardation δ, set at an azimuth “θ” is:
</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0094">
<maths id="MATH-US-00002" num="00002">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mrow>
          <mi>C</mi>
          <mo>⁡</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mi>θ</mi>
              <mo>,</mo>
              <mi>δ</mi>
            </mrow>
            <mo>)</mo>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <msub>
            <mi>τ</mi>
            <mi>R</mi>
          </msub>
          <mo>⁡</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mtable>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <msup>
                        <mi>cos</mi>
                        <mn>2</mn>
                      </msup>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                          <mo>⁢</mo>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>+</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mrow>
                        <mi>cos</mi>
                        <mo>⁡</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mo>(</mo>
                          <mi>δ</mi>
                          <mo>)</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>⁢</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msup>
                          <mi>sin</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </msup>
                        <mo>⁡</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mo>(</mo>
                          <mrow>
                            <mn>2</mn>
                            <mo>⁢</mo>
                            <mi>θ</mi>
                          </mrow>
                          <mo>)</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <msup>
                        <mi>sin</mi>
                        <mn>2</mn>
                      </msup>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mfrac>
                          <mi>δ</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </mfrac>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>sin</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mn>4</mn>
                          <mo>⁢</mo>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>-</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mi>sin</mi>
                        <mo>⁡</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mo>(</mo>
                          <mi>δ</mi>
                          <mo>)</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>sin</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                          <mo>⁢</mo>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <msup>
                        <mi>sin</mi>
                        <mn>2</mn>
                      </msup>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mfrac>
                          <mi>δ</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </mfrac>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>sin</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mn>4</mn>
                          <mo>⁢</mo>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <msup>
                        <mi>cos</mi>
                        <mn>2</mn>
                      </msup>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                          <mo>⁢</mo>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>+</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mrow>
                        <mi>cos</mi>
                        <mo>⁡</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mo>(</mo>
                          <mi>δ</mi>
                          <mo>)</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>⁢</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msup>
                          <mi>sin</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </msup>
                        <mo>⁡</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mo>(</mo>
                          <mrow>
                            <mn>2</mn>
                            <mo>⁢</mo>
                            <mi>θ</mi>
                          </mrow>
                          <mo>)</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>sin</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>cos</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                          <mo>⁢</mo>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>sin</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>sin</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                          <mo>⁢</mo>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>-</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mi>sin</mi>
                        <mo>⁡</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mo>(</mo>
                          <mi>δ</mi>
                          <mo>)</mo>
                        </mrow>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>cos</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                          <mo>⁢</mo>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
                <mtd>
                  <mrow>
                    <mi>cos</mi>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mi>δ</mi>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
            </mtable>
            <mo>)</mo>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>2</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0095">Assuming that the light entering the PSG <b>6</b> is completely depolarized, the Stokes vector of the vector leaving the PSG <b>6</b> is given by the following expression:</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0096">
<maths id="MATH-US-00003" num="00003">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mrow>
          <msub>
            <mi>S</mi>
            <mi>out</mi>
          </msub>
          <mo>⁡</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mi>θ</mi>
              <mo>,</mo>
              <mi>δ</mi>
            </mrow>
            <mo>)</mo>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mrow>
            <mi>C</mi>
            <mo>⁡</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mo>(</mo>
              <mrow>
                <mi>θ</mi>
                <mo>,</mo>
                <mi>δ</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mo>)</mo>
            </mrow>
          </mrow>
          <mo>·</mo>
          <mi>P</mi>
          <mo>·</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mtable>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
              <mtr>
                <mtd>
                  <mn>0</mn>
                </mtd>
              </mtr>
            </mtable>
            <mo>)</mo>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>3</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0097">Finally, a complete W matrix can be built by taking the four Stokes vectors obtained for the azimuths θ<sub>i </sub>i=1 to 4, and for a common value for the retardation “δ”:</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0098">
<maths id="MATH-US-00004" num="00004">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mrow>
          <mi>W</mi>
          <mo>⁡</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mrow>
              <msub>
                <mi>θ</mi>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>,</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>θ</mi>
                <mn>2</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>,</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>θ</mi>
                <mn>3</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>,</mo>
              <msub>
                <mi>θ</mi>
                <mn>4</mn>
              </msub>
              <mo>,</mo>
              <mi>δ</mi>
            </mrow>
            <mo>)</mo>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mo>(</mo>
          <mtable>
            <mtr>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>1</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>3</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>4</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
            </mtr>
            <mtr>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>1</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>2</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>2</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>3</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>2</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>4</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>2</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
            </mtr>
            <mtr>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>1</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>3</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>3</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>3</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>3</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>4</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>3</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
            </mtr>
            <mtr>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>1</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>4</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>2</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>4</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>3</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>4</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
              <mtd>
                <msub>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>S</mi>
                      <mi>out</mi>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁡</mo>
                    <mrow>
                      <mo>(</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <msub>
                          <mi>θ</mi>
                          <mn>4</mn>
                        </msub>
                        <mo>,</mo>
                        <mi>δ</mi>
                      </mrow>
                      <mo>)</mo>
                    </mrow>
                  </mrow>
                  <mn>4</mn>
                </msub>
              </mtd>
            </mtr>
          </mtable>
          <mo>)</mo>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>4</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0099">Sub-indexes <b>1</b> to <b>4</b> placed next to the parentheses refer to the components of each one of Stokes vectors generated by the PSG <b>6</b>. Under the above representation, the condition number of the matrix W can be understood as a function of five parameters, the retardation δ and the four azimuth angles of the retarder <b>21</b>. In an article, Tyo et al. {Appl. Opt., (2002)} has shown that for a PSG or a PSA made essentially with polarizers and retarders, the theoretical value of the condition number can vary between “0” and “3<sup>−1/2</sup>”. Accordingly, the values of the five parameters, retardation and azimuths, used to design the PSG <b>6</b>, must be those that optimize the value of the condition number.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0100">Finding the value of the parameters that maximize the condition number is a numerical problem that can be solved by means of a standard optimization routine such as the Simplex or the Levenberg-Marquardt {Numerical Recipes in PASCAL, p. 326}. As a result, two optimal values for the retardation and two values for each one of the azymuts θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3 </sub>and θ<sub>4 </sub>can be found. Once the optimal values are determined, the sensitivity of the PSG <b>6</b> or the PSA <b>10</b> to fluctuations of retardation and orientation angles can be estimated using the condition number, again, as a criterion. In fact, even though the condition number can be theoretically very small, it is commonly accepted that a minimum value of 0.2 is needed to obtain measurements with acceptable quality. Accordingly, the tolerances of the retardation, and the four azimuths of the retarder around their respective optimum value, are specified in order to maintain the condition number over 0.2.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0101">The values for the retardation are:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>δ<sub>1</sub>=132°+n360° and<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>δ<sub>2</sub>=227°+n360°,<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<ul id="ul0007" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0007-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0008" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0008-0001" num="0102">with “n” being any integer.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0103"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the values of the condition number calculated as function of the retardation for one set of optimal values of the azimuths.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0104">The two maxima <b>40</b> and <b>41</b>, correspond respectively to the values for the retardation δ<sub>1 </sub>(132°) and δ<sub>2 </sub>(227°).</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0105">From this figure, and in accordance with the former definition, it can be seen that the tolerance for the retardation can be evaluated to about ±30°.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0106">The optimal values for the azimuths are are:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>θ<sub>1</sub>=38°+n360° or 218°+n360°<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>θ<sub>2</sub>=74°+n360° or 254°+n360°<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>θ<sub>3</sub>=106°+n360° or 286°+n360°<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>θ<sub>4</sub>=142°+n360° or 322°+n360°<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<ul id="ul0009" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0009-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0010" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0010-0001" num="0107">with “n” being any integer.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0108"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 to 7</figref> show the values of the condition number calculated as a function of the azimuths θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3</sub>, and θ<sub>4 </sub>respectively. From those figures, and in accordance with the former definition, it can be seen that the tolerance for the angles θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3</sub>, and θ<sub>4 </sub>can be evaluated to about ±20°.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0109">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the two maxima <b>42</b> and <b>43</b> correspond respectively to the two possible values of azimuths θ<sub>1 </sub>(38°+n360° and 218°+n360°) with n being any integer. These values have been calculated assuming the optimum values for the retardation and the azimuths θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3</sub>, and θ<sub>4</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0110">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the two maxima <b>44</b> and <b>45</b> correspond respectively to the two possible values of azimuths θ<sub>2 </sub>(74°+n360° and 254°+n360°) with n being any integer. These values have been calculated assuming the optimum values for the retardation and the azimuths θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>3</sub>, and θ<sub>4</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0111">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the two maxima <b>46</b> and <b>47</b> correspond respectively to the two possible values of azimuths θ<sub>3 </sub>(106°+n360° and 286°+n360°) with n being any integer. These values have been calculated assuming the optimum values for the retardation and the azimuths θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, and θ<sub>4</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0112">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the two maxima <b>48</b> and <b>49</b> correspond respectively to the two possible values of azimuths θ<sub>4 </sub>(142°+n360° and 322°+n360°) with n being any integer These values have been calculated assuming the optimum values for the retardation and the azimuths θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, and θ<sub>3</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0113">In view of the constraints imposed by the condition number of the PSG <b>6</b> and the PSA <b>10</b>, a broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter intended to perform optimally over all the spectral range, must include a retarder <b>21</b> as much achromatic as possible providing a retardation close to 132° for all the wavelengths. To achieve this objective, three TIR based achromatic retarders are proposed.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0114">The first retarder shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, consists of a bi-prism <b>51</b> made of two identical Fresnel rhombs disposed symmetrically and joined by optical contact, giving to the retarder a “V” shape. We mean with “identical” that the Fresnel rhombs present the same form. The two identical Fresnel rhombs are not necessarily made of the same material.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0115">In more detail, the bi-prism <b>51</b> includes a first <b>50</b> and a second <b>50</b>′ rhombs which, as viewed in side elevation, have each a top TF<b>1</b>/TF<b>2</b>, and bottom BF<b>1</b>/BF<b>2</b> faces oriented at an angle (90°−α) respect to the horizontal.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0116">Said first <b>50</b> and second <b>50</b>′ rhombs have right RF<b>1</b>/RF<b>2</b> and left LF<b>1</b>/LF<b>2</b> faces parallel respect to each other and oriented vertically. Said first <b>50</b> and second <b>50</b>′ rhombs are made of a material with an index of refraction greater than the surrounding medium (usually air, but not mandatory). A rightmost vertically oriented face RF<b>1</b> of the first rhomb <b>50</b> is in contact with the leftmost face LF<b>2</b> of the second rhomb <b>50</b>′. The input beam IB penetrates into the first rhomb <b>50</b> through its leftmost side LF<b>1</b> at normal incidence, then reaches a locus in the bottom face BF<b>1</b> at an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a first total internal reflection IR<b>1</b>, then, said beam reaches the top face TF<b>1</b> with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a second total internal reflection IR<b>2</b>. After said second internal reflection IR<b>2</b>, the beam reaches at normal incidence the interface between the first <b>50</b> and second <b>50</b>′ rhombs defined by the leftmost face LF<b>1</b> of the first rhomb <b>50</b> and the rightmost face RF<b>2</b> of the second rhomb <b>50</b>′. Once the beam is inside the second rhomb <b>50</b>′, it reaches a locus in the top face TF<b>2</b> with an angle of incidence α, where it undergoes a third total internal reflection IR<b>3</b>. Finally, said beam reaches the bottom face BF<b>2</b> with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a fourth total internal reflection IR<b>4</b>. After said fourth internal reflection IR<b>4</b> the beam reaches at normal incidence the rightmost face RF<b>2</b> and it exits the bi-prism <b>51</b>. As a result, the output beam OB is not deviated respect to the input beam IB even in the case of rotation of the bi-prism <b>51</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0117">This configuration induces four total internal reflections and prevents the beam emerging from the bi-prism <b>51</b> to be deviated from its original direction. The total amount of retardation created by a bi-prism in contact with the air is the sum of retardations caused by each one of the internal reflections. When the bi-prism <b>51</b> is in contact with the air, the most general case, the retardation introduced by each total internal reflection can be expressed as:</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0118">
<maths id="MATH-US-00005" num="00005">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msub>
          <mi>δ</mi>
          <mi>oneTIR</mi>
        </msub>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mn>2</mn>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mrow>
            <msup>
              <mi>tan</mi>
              <mrow>
                <mo>-</mo>
                <mn>1</mn>
              </mrow>
            </msup>
            <mo>⁡</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mo>(</mo>
              <mfrac>
                <mrow>
                  <mi>cos</mi>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <mstyle>
                    <mspace width="0.3em" height="0.3ex"/>
                  </mstyle>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <msup>
                    <mrow>
                      <mi>ϕ</mi>
                      <mo>⁡</mo>
                      <mrow>
                        <mo>(</mo>
                        <mrow>
                          <mrow>
                            <msup>
                              <mi>n</mi>
                              <mn>2</mn>
                            </msup>
                            <mo>⁢</mo>
                            <msup>
                              <mi>sin</mi>
                              <mn>2</mn>
                            </msup>
                            <mo>⁢</mo>
                            <mi>ϕ</mi>
                          </mrow>
                          <mo>-</mo>
                          <mn>1</mn>
                        </mrow>
                        <mo>)</mo>
                      </mrow>
                    </mrow>
                    <mrow>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                      <mo>/</mo>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </mrow>
                  </msup>
                </mrow>
                <mrow>
                  <mi>n</mi>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <mstyle>
                    <mspace width="0.3em" height="0.3ex"/>
                  </mstyle>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <msup>
                    <mi>sin</mi>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                  </msup>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <mi>ϕ</mi>
                </mrow>
              </mfrac>
              <mo>)</mo>
            </mrow>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>5</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0119">where φ is the angle of incidence for the internal reflection and “n” is the index of the material where the TIR takes place. The normal incidence of the beam at the interface between the rhombs <b>50</b>, <b>50</b>′, prevents it to be deviated, even if the rhombs are not built of the same material. This is an advantage that allows the combination of different materials in order to enhance the achromaticity of the bi-prism. The entrance and exit faces of the bi-prism <b>51</b> are perpendicular to the propagation direction of the beam in order to make insertion losses independent of the polarization. From geometrical considerations, it is easy to show that the angle of incidence φ in the expression 5 corresponds to the angle α mentioned previosly, that determines the shape of the bi-oprism. According to expression 5 and for a given value of the total retardation, high values of “n” allow small angles of incidence, thus leading to short and compact retarders.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0120">However, the use of high index materials to build the bi-prism <b>51</b> can create some optical drawbacks. First, the high contrast of index between the surrounding medium and the prism can induce important insertion losses if the entrance (exit) faces do not have an adequate antireflection coating. Secondly, in the absence of an antireflection coating, the transmission faces, which are parallel to each other, can generate multiple-internal reflected secondary beams inside the prism. Those multiple-reflected beams have performed multiple travels in the interior of the prisms, thus cumulating a phase-shift different from that of the principal beam. When the contrast of index is high, the relative intensity of the secondary beams cannot be neglected, and their superposition with the principal beam causes non-idealities, such as depolarization, in the behaviour of the retarder that can not be predicted by a simple addition of the retardations given by expression 5.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0121">Consequently, with uncoated high index materials, the performance, i.e. the condition number, of the PSG <b>6</b> can be considerably decreased. If there are no constraints on the size of the bi-prisms <b>51</b>, one possible solution to those drawbacks is to build them with low index, “n”, materials such as BaF<sub>2 </sub>(1.51 @ 265 nm, 1.39 @ 10 micron) among others because insertion losses and intensity of multiple-reflected beams are minimized. Materials like BaF<sub>2 </sub>have also the advantage of being transparent over a wide spectral range from the ultraviolet to the infrared, so they are the ideal candidates to be used in the construction of bi-prisms. BaF<sub>2 </sub>is mentioned here for illustrative purposes only and should not be used to unduly limit the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0122"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a schematic frontal view of a second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′ according to another embodiment of the invention. Said second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′ is made of three triangular prisms <b>24</b>, <b>25</b> and <b>26</b>, joined by optical contact.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0123">According to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the first prism <b>25</b> has a vertically oriented left face LF<b>1</b> that makes an angle α with its right face RF<b>1</b> and a right angle with its top face TF<b>1</b>. Similarly, the third prism <b>26</b> has a vertically oriented right face RF<b>3</b> that makes an angle α with its left face LF<b>3</b> and a right angle with its top face TF<b>3</b>. First <b>25</b> and third <b>26</b> triangular prisms are identical and are placed symmetrically with respect to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0124">The second prism has a horizontally oriented bottom face BF<b>2</b> that is in contact with the first <b>25</b> and the third prism <b>26</b> through their respective top TF<b>1</b> and TF<b>3</b> faces. Said second prism <b>24</b> has a right face RF<b>2</b> and a left face LF<b>2</b> oriented at an angle of α with respect to the horizontal. The input beam IB reaches the second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′ through the left face LF<b>1</b> of the first prism <b>25</b> at normal incidence. Once the said beam is in the first triangular prism <b>25</b>, it reaches a locus in the right face RF<b>1</b> with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a first total internal reflection IR<b>1</b>. Then, said beam reaches the second triangular prism <b>24</b>, through the interface defined by the BF<b>2</b> and TF<b>1</b>, and reaches its left face LF<b>2</b> with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a second total internal reflection IR<b>2</b>. Then, said beam follows a trajectory parallel to the horizontal and reaches a locus in the right face RF<b>2</b> with an angle of incidence α, before undergoing a third IR<b>3</b> total internal reflection and to be sent to the third prism <b>26</b> through the interface defined by BF<b>2</b> and TF<b>3</b>. On the third prism <b>26</b>, said beam reaches its left face LF<b>3</b> with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a fourth total internal reflection IR<b>4</b>. Finally, said beam reaches the right face RF<b>3</b> at normal incidence, and exits the system OB with a direction that is not deviated nor shifted respect to that of the initial input beam IB, even in the case of rotation of the substantially achromatic device <b>23</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0125">Again, like in the bi-prism <b>51</b>, the transmitting faces are perpendicular to the beam direction in order to avoid polarization dependant insertion loses.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0126">Because the beam is perpendicular to the input face of the prism, from geometrical considerations it is possible to show that the incidence angle in the first <b>25</b> and third <b>26</b> prisms is equal to α. Again, some simple geometrical considerations allow to show that if the direction of the beam must be preserved by the full device, the incidence angle of the two internal reflections on the second prism <b>24</b> must be equal to α. This implies that LF<b>2</b> (resp. RF<b>2</b>) must be parallel to RF<b>1</b> (resp. LF<b>3</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0127">The total retardation of the second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′ is the sum of the retardations suffered by the beam after the four total internal reflections, which are, in turn functions of the internal angle of incidence α, according to expression 5. As in the case of the bi-prism <b>51</b>, retardation can be defined by the manufacture of the device if the refraction index is known.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0128">Again, like in the case of the bi-prism <b>51</b> the expression 5 shows that for a given retardation, the use of materials of high index for the prisms results in small and compact devices, however, they can be affected by the same drawbacks caused by beam insertion losses and generation of multiple-reflected beams as in the case of the bi-prism <b>51</b>. For this reason, low index materials, such as BaF<sub>2 </sub>are preferred to build the second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0129"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a schematic frontal view of a third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″. Said third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″ is made of two triangular prisms <b>27</b>, <b>29</b> and a trapezoidal prism <b>28</b>, joined by optical contact, according to another embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0130">According to the schematic view shown in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the first prism <b>27</b> has a vertical left face LF<b>1</b>, a horizontal top face TF<b>1</b>, and a tilted right face RF<b>1</b>. The left face LF<b>1</b> defines an angle α with the right face RF<b>1</b>, and a right angle with the top face TF<b>1</b>. Similarly, the third prism <b>29</b> has a vertical right face RF<b>3</b>, a horizontal top face TF<b>3</b>, and a tilted left face LF<b>3</b>. The right face RF<b>3</b> defines an angle α with the left face LF<b>3</b>, and a right angle with the top face TF<b>3</b>. First <b>27</b> and third <b>29</b> triangular prisms are identical and are located symmetrically with respect to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0131">We mean with “identical” that the first <b>27</b> and third <b>29</b> triangular prisms present the same form.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0132">The second prism <b>28</b> has horizontally oriented top TF<b>2</b> and bottom BF<b>2</b> faces, and right RF<b>2</b> and left faces LF<b>2</b> oriented at an angle of β respect to the horizontal. Said bottom face BF<b>2</b> is in contact with the first <b>27</b> and the third prism <b>29</b> through their respective top (TF<b>1</b> and TF<b>3</b>) faces. The input beam IB penetrates into the third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″ through the left face LF<b>1</b> of the first prism <b>27</b> at normal incidence. Once said beam is in the first triangular prism <b>27</b>, it reaches the right face RF<b>1</b> with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a first total internal reflection IR<b>1</b>. Then, said beam reaches the second triangular prism <b>28</b> through the interface defined by the BF<b>2</b> and TF<b>1</b>, and reaches its left face LF<b>2</b> with an angle of incidence φ, which is a function of α and β, and undergoes a second total internal reflection IR<b>2</b>. Then, said beam reaches the top face TF<b>2</b> with an angle of incidence χ where it undergoes a third total internal reflection IR<b>3</b>. Said angle χ is a function of the angles α and β and is different from angle φ. Next, said beam reaches the right face RF<b>2</b> with an angle of incidence φ and undergoes a fourth IR<b>4</b> total internal reflection that sends it to the third prism <b>29</b> through the interface defined by BF<b>2</b> and TF<b>3</b>. On the third prism <b>29</b>, said beam reaches its left face LF<b>3</b> with an angle of incidence α and undergoes a fifth total internal reflection IR<b>5</b>. Finally, said beam reaches the right face RF<b>3</b> at normal incidence, and exits the system OB with a direction that is not deviated nor shifted respect to that of the initial input beam, even in the case of rotation of the substantially achromatic device.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0133">The light beam undergoes five total internal reflections, and the outgoing beam propagates along the optical axis in the same direction as the incoming beam. Like in the previously described second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′, the transmitting faces are perpendicular to the beam direction in order to avoid insertion loses depending on the polarization.</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0134">Because the beam is perpendicular to the entrance (exit) face of the first <b>27</b> (third <b>29</b>) prism, the incidence angle of the first and fifth internal reflections are equal to α.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0135">The trapezoidal prism <b>28</b> can be defined by an angle β that can be different from α. By convention, β is defined as the angle between the face in contact with the triangular prisms <b>27</b>, <b>29</b>, and the face where takes place the second total internal reflection IR<b>2</b>. The angle of incidence of the second and fourth total internal reflection IR<b>2</b>, IR<b>4</b> in the trapezoidal prism <b>28</b> is a function of the angles α and β. The angle of incidence of the third internal reflection IR<b>3</b>, χ, is different from the angle of incidence of the second and the fourth total internal reflections IR<b>2</b>, IR<b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0136">The total retardation of the third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″ is the sum over the retardations undergone by the beam after the five total internal reflections, which are in turn functions of each angle of incidence. An appropriate choice of α, β allows optimizing the value and the achromatism of the third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0137"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a schematic frontal view of a fourth substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b> according to another embodiment of the invention. Said second substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b> is made of four identical trapezoidal prisms <b>31</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>33</b> and <b>34</b>, joined by optical contact, and cut in order to the beam reaches their respective input and output interfaces at normal incidence.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0138">We mean with “identical” that the four identical trapezoidal prisms <b>31</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>33</b> and <b>34</b> present the same form but not necessarily made of the same material.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0139">This last condition imposes that all the prisms must be symmetric respect to the axis normal to the surface where the internal reflection takes place (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>). Accordingly, the prisms <b>31</b> and, <b>34</b> have a leftmost face LF<b>1</b>, LF<b>4</b>, that makes an angle α with their respective bottom face BF<b>1</b>, and BF<b>4</b>. The prism <b>32</b> and <b>33</b> have a leftmost face LF<b>2</b> and LF<b>3</b> that makes an angle α with their respective top faces TF<b>2</b> and TF<b>3</b>. In addition, because of symmetry, prisms <b>31</b> and <b>34</b> have a rightmost face RF<b>1</b>, and RF<b>4</b> respectivelly, that makes an angle α with the corresponding bottom face BF<b>1</b> and BF<b>4</b>, and prisms <b>32</b> and <b>33</b> have a rightmost face RF<b>2</b> and RF<b>3</b> that makes and angle α with the corresponding top faces TF<b>2</b> and TF<b>3</b>. The right face RF<b>1</b> of the first prism <b>31</b>, is in contact with the left face LF<b>2</b> of the second prism <b>32</b>. The right face RF<b>2</b> of the second prism <b>32</b>, is in contact with the left face LF<b>3</b> of the third prism <b>33</b>. Finally, the right face RF<b>3</b> of the third prism <b>33</b>, is in contact with the left face LF<b>4</b> of the fourth prism <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0140">The input beam IB reaches the fourth substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b> through the left face LF<b>1</b> of the first prism <b>31</b> at normal incidence. Once said beam is in the first prism <b>31</b>, it reaches a locus in its bottom face BF<b>1</b> with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a first total internal reflection IR<b>1</b>. Then, said beam reaches the interface between the first <b>31</b> and the second prism <b>32</b> at normal incidence and arrives to the top face TF<b>2</b> of the second prism <b>32</b>, with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a second total internal reflection IR<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0141">Then, said beam follows a trajectory parallel to the horizontal, crosses the interface between the second <b>32</b> and the third <b>33</b> prisms at normal incidence, and reaches a locus in the top face TF<b>3</b> of the third prism <b>33</b> with an angle of incidence α, before undergoing a third IR<b>3</b> total internal reflection and to be sent towards the fourth prism. After traversing the interface between the third <b>33</b> and the fourth <b>34</b> prism at normal incidence, said beam reaches its bottom face BF<b>4</b> with an angle of incidence α, and undergoes a fourth total internal reflection IR<b>4</b>. Finally, said beam reaches the right face RF<b>4</b> at normal incidence, and exits the system OB with a direction that is not deviated nor shifted respect to that of the initial input beam IB, even in the case of rotation of the substantially achromatic device <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0142">The transmitting faces LF<b>1</b> and RF<b>4</b> of the retarder <b>30</b> are perpendicular to the beam direction in order to avoid polarization dependent insertion losses. Because the beam reaches the three interfaces between prisms (RF<b>1</b>/LF<b>2</b>, RF<b>2</b>/LF<b>3</b>, RF<b>3</b>/LF<b>4</b>) at normal incidence, its trajectory is not deviated, even if different materials are used to build two adjoining prisms. This fact allows the combination of different materials to build the retarder <b>30</b> with enhanced achromaticity respect to an equivalent retarder built of only one material.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0143">The total retardation of the fourth substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b> is the sum of the retardations suffered by the beam after the four total internal reflections, which are, in turn, functions of the refraction index of each prism as well as the internal angle of incidence α, according to expression 5.</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0144">Again, like in the case of the bi-prism <b>51</b>, the expression 5 shows that the use of materials of high index for the prisms results in small and compact devices, however, they can be affected by the same drawbacks caused by beam insertion losses and generation of multiple-reflected beams as in the case of the bi-prism <b>51</b>. For this reason, low index materials, such as BaF<sub>2 </sub>are preferred to build the fourth substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0145">Each prism <b>51</b>, <b>23</b>′, <b>23</b>″ and <b>30</b> is made of a material with an index of refraction greater than that of the surrounding media.</p>
<p id="p-0113" num="0146">The entrance and exit faces of the prisms <b>51</b>, <b>23</b>′, <b>23</b>″ and <b>30</b> comprise an antireflection treatment (coating) to minimise light insertion losses.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0147">The faces of the prisms <b>51</b>, <b>23</b>′, <b>23</b>″ and <b>30</b> wherein total internal refection takes place, are uncoated.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0148">The prisms <b>51</b>, <b>23</b>′, <b>23</b>″ and <b>30</b> are made of a material presenting a low index of refraction like the BaF<sub>2</sub>. BaF<sub>2 </sub>is mentioned here for illustrative purposes only and should not be used to unduly limit the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0116" num="0149">The disclosed broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system is general and the spectral range is limited by the transmittance and other optical properties of the optical devices used to build it.</p>
<p id="p-0117" num="0150">Accordingly, the disclosed system can lead to multiple implementations. The following are two examples of possible embodiments for the present invention. Those examples are presented here for illustration purposes only and should not be used to unduly limit the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0118" num="0151">The first example of a possible embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, previously described, includes a broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system working from the far ultraviolet (around 140 nm) to the near infrared (2000 nm).</p>
<p id="p-0119" num="0152">The illumination source <b>5</b> is an ultraviolet-visible source. The illumination source <b>5</b> provides a continuous beam <b>12</b> in a wide spectral range from the ultraviolet to the near infrared. Some examples of those kinds of sources <b>5</b> could be high pressure Hg—Xe discharge lamps or Deuterium-Halogen lamps</p>
<p id="p-0120" num="0153">The reratarder holders <b>14</b>, <b>19</b> can be rotated, manually or automatically, following a predetermined sequence controlled by the computer <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0121" num="0154">In a preferred embodiment, the rotating holders <b>14</b>, <b>19</b> are driven automatically by a motor running in stepper mode, connected to the computer <b>4</b> to ensure fast and repetitive movements.</p>
<p id="p-0122" num="0155">Reference-sample-holders <b>7</b>, <b>9</b> placed respectively after the PSG <b>6</b> and before the PSA <b>10</b>, introduce reference samples <b>15</b>, <b>16</b>, <b>17</b>, <b>18</b> in the beam path during calibration and remove them during current measurement process.</p>
<p id="p-0123" num="0156">The computer <b>4</b> is intended to monitor the sequence of movements of the retarders <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> either directly, or assisted by secondary specific controllers.</p>
<p id="p-0124" num="0157">In addition, the computer <b>4</b> is also in charge of the acquisition of raw data from the detection unit and its subsequent treatment. The primary detector system <b>11</b> can be one or a combination of the types described in the following list:
<ul id="ul0011" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0011-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0012" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0012-0001" num="0158">a single photodiode for a sequential detection of radiation resolved in wavelength coming from a spectrograph,</li>
        <li id="ul0012-0002" num="0159">a group of photodiodes to detect in parallel a group of selected wavelengths coming from a spectrograph,</li>
        <li id="ul0012-0003" num="0160">a single CCD array coupled to a spectrograph,</li>
        <li id="ul0012-0004" num="0161">a group of CCD arrays coupled to a spectrograph.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0125" num="0162">The best suited polarizers <b>13</b>, <b>20</b> to work in the FUV-VIS range are those of either Rochon type or Glan type. Both retarders, <b>21</b> and <b>22</b> must be substantially achromatic, and provide a retardation close to 132°. In a preferred embodiment, retarder <b>21</b> must be either:
<ul id="ul0013" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0013-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0014" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0014-0001" num="0163">a bi-prism <b>51</b> or,</li>
        <li id="ul0014-0002" num="0164">a retarder according to the description of the second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′, or</li>
        <li id="ul0014-0003" num="0165">a retarder according to the description of the third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″, or</li>
        <li id="ul0014-0004" num="0166">a retarder according to the description of the fourth substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b>′,
<br/>
and the the retarder <b>22</b> must be:
</li>
        <li id="ul0014-0005" num="0167">a bi-prism <b>51</b> or,</li>
        <li id="ul0014-0006" num="0168">a retarder according to the description of the second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′, or</li>
        <li id="ul0014-0007" num="0169">a retarder according to the description of the third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″, or</li>
        <li id="ul0014-0008" num="0170">a retarder according to the description of the fourth substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b>′.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0126" num="0171">According to the present invention, during the data acquisition, the retarder <b>21</b> in the PSG <b>6</b> is successively oriented at four defined angles θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3</sub>, and θ<sub>4</sub>, with θ<sub>1 </sub>being either 38° or 218°, θ<sub>2 </sub>being either 74° or 254°, θ<sub>3 </sub>being either 106° or 286° and θ<sub>4 </sub>being either 142° or 322°, to generate different polarization states that are sent to the sample. Each one of the four polarization states, after interacting with the sample, is projected against four optical configurations of the PSA <b>10</b>, made by orienting retarder <b>22</b> at four different angles, θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3</sub>, and θ<sub>4</sub>, with θ<sub>1 </sub>being either 38° or 218°, θ<sub>2 </sub>being either 74° or 254°, θ<sub>3 </sub>being either 106° or 286° and θ<sub>4 </sub>being either 142° or 322°.</p>
<p id="p-0127" num="0172">As a result, a set of sixteen S<sub>i,j </sub>measurements are obtained. The Mueller matrix of the sample <b>8</b> is obtained by multiplying the matrix S by the inverse of the matrices W and A corresponding to the PSG <b>6</b> and the PSA <b>10</b> respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0128" num="0173">If the measured sample <b>8</b> corresponds to a non-depolarizing dichroic retarder, the ellipsometers angles Ψ and Δ can be derived directly from the corresponding Mueller matrix because for this type of sample the following relations are always satisfied:</p>
<p id="p-0129" num="0174">Upper diagonal block:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>M<sub>11</sub>=M<sub>22</sub>=τ<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>M</i><sub>12</sub><i>=M</i><sub>21</sub>=−τ cos(2Ψ)  (6)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0130" num="0175">Lower diagonal block:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>M</i><sub>33</sub><i>=M</i><sub>44</sub>=τ sin(2Ψ)cos(Δ)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>M</i><sub>34</sub><i>=−M</i><sub>43</sub>=τ sin(2Ψ)sin(Δ)  (7)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0131" num="0176">The remaining elements are null.</p>
<p id="p-0132" num="0177">Alternatively, Ψ and Δ can be evaluated directly from the eigenvalues of the Mueller matrix of a dichroic retarder, which can be written as:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>λ<sub>R1</sub>=2τ sin<sup>2</sup>(Ψ)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>λ<sub>R2</sub>=2τ cos<sup>2</sup>(Ψ)  (8)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>λ<sub>R3</sub>=τ sin(2Ψ)exp(<i>i</i>Δ)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>λ<sub>R4</sub>=τ sin(2Ψ)exp(−<i>i</i>Δ)  (9)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0133" num="0178">In order to minimize the errors due to intensity fluctuations of the illumination source <b>5</b>, a reference measurement can be taken by splitting a part of the beam, and to measure it with the second detector <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0134" num="0179">A second possible embodiment, represented in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12 and 13</figref>, includes a broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system working in the infrared that can be for example from 4 to 20 microns, but is not necessarily limited to this range.</p>
<p id="p-0135" num="0180">According to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12 and 13</figref>, the system, which can be used in transmission (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>) or in reflection (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>) mode, includes an input arm <b>1</b>, a sample holder <b>3</b>, an exit arm <b>2</b> and a computer <b>4</b>. The input arm <b>1</b> includes an illumination source <b>5</b>, a PSG <b>6</b> and a reference-sample-holder means <b>7</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0136" num="0181">The exit arm <b>2</b> includes a reference-sample-holder means <b>9</b>, a PSA <b>10</b> and a primary detector system <b>11</b>. The illumination source <b>5</b>, such as a standard FTIR interferometer, provides a continuous infrared beam in a wide spectral range.</p>
<p id="p-0137" num="0182">The PSG <b>6</b> comprises a fixed polarizer <b>13</b> located after the illumination source <b>5</b>, and a substantially achromatic retarder <b>21</b>. A preferred embodiment for the polarizer is the well known grid type, even if other types, like prisms, are also possible. Both retarders, <b>21</b> and <b>22</b> must be substantially achromatic, and provide a retardation close to 132°. In a preferred embodiment, retarder <b>21</b> must be either:
<ul id="ul0015" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0015-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0016" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0016-0001" num="0183">a bi-prism <b>51</b> or,</li>
        <li id="ul0016-0002" num="0184">a retarder according to the description of the second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′, or</li>
        <li id="ul0016-0003" num="0185">a retarder according to the description of the third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″, or</li>
        <li id="ul0016-0004" num="0186">a retarder according to the description of the fourth substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b>′,
<br/>
and the the retarder <b>22</b> must be:
</li>
        <li id="ul0016-0005" num="0187">a bi-prism <b>51</b> or,</li>
        <li id="ul0016-0006" num="0188">a retarder according to the description of the second substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>′, or</li>
        <li id="ul0016-0007" num="0189">a retarder according to the description of the third substantially achromatic retarder <b>23</b>″, or</li>
        <li id="ul0016-0008" num="0190">a retarder according to the description of the fourth substantially achromatic retarder <b>30</b>′.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0138" num="0191">The retarder <b>21</b> is mounted in a rotating holder <b>14</b>, that allows it to be placed at four consecutive orientations respect to the plane of incidence. The rotating holder <b>14</b> can be rotated, manually or automatically, following a predetermined sequence controlled by the computer <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0139" num="0192">In a preferred embodiment, the rotating holder <b>14</b>, is driven automatically by a motor connected to the computer <b>4</b> to ensure fast and repetitive movements. Holders <b>7</b>, <b>9</b> for reference samples <b>15</b>, <b>16</b>, <b>17</b>, <b>18</b>, respectively, located after the PSG <b>6</b> and before the PSA <b>10</b>, can introduce calibration samples <b>8</b> in the beam path during calibration, and remove them during current measurement process.</p>
<p id="p-0140" num="0193">The PSA <b>10</b> include a fixed linear polarizer <b>20</b> and a substantially achromatic retarder <b>22</b> mounted on a rotating holder <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0141" num="0194">The beam goes through said PSA <b>10</b>, after being transmitted, reflected or scattered by the sample <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0142" num="0195">The PSA <b>6</b> is identical to the PSG <b>10</b>, but with its optical elements, (retarder and polarizer) set in reverse order.</p>
<p id="p-0143" num="0196">We mean with “identical” that the PSG <b>6</b> and the PSA <b>10</b> comprise the same elements or equivalent elements having the same optical properties.</p>
<p id="p-0144" num="0197">The rotating holders <b>14</b>, <b>19</b> run in a stepper mode.</p>
<p id="p-0145" num="0198">The computer <b>4</b> is intended to monitor the sequence of movements of the retarders <b>21</b>, <b>22</b>, either directly, or assisted by secondary specific controllers. In addition, the computer <b>4</b> has also in charge the control the FTIR source <b>5</b>, the acquisition of raw data from the detection unit and its subsequent treatment.</p>
<p id="p-0146" num="0199">According to the present invention, during the data acquisition, the retarder <b>21</b> in the PSG <b>6</b> is successively oriented at four defined angles θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3</sub>, and θ<sub>4</sub>, with θ<sub>1 </sub>being either 38° or 218°, θ<sub>2 </sub>being either 74° or 254°, θ<sub>3 </sub>being either 106° or 286° and θ<sub>4 </sub>being either 142° or 322°, to generate different polarization states that are sent to the sample. Each one of the four polarization states, after interacting with the sample, is projected against four optical configurations of the PSA <b>10</b>, made by orienting retarder <b>22</b> at four different angles, θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3</sub>, and θ<sub>4</sub>, with θ<sub>1 </sub>being either 38° or 218°, θ<sub>2 </sub>being either 74° or 254°, θ<sub>3 </sub>being either 106° or 286° and θ<sub>4 </sub>being either 142° or 322°. The set of four selected orientation angles are optimized in order to maintain the condition numbers of the modulation and the analysis matrices associated respectively with the PSG <b>6</b> and the PSA <b>10</b> over 0.2.</p>
<p id="p-0147" num="0200">As a result a set of sixteen S<sub>i,j </sub>measurements are obtained. The Mueller matrix of the sample <b>8</b> is obtained multiplying the matrix S by the inverse of the matrices W and A (M=A<sup>−1</sup>SW<sup>−1</sup>) corresponding the PSG <b>6</b> and the PSA <b>10</b> respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0148" num="0201">The method chosen to calibrate the broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system is based in the eigenvalue method described in the article of E. Compain {Appl. Opt., (1999)} because of its robustness. Apart from Compain et al, other authors like Drévillon et al. {U.S. Pat. No. 6,175,412 B1 and the Pub. No.: US 2004/0130717 A1} have already successfully applied the eigenvalue method to many kinds of polarimetric systems.</p>
<p id="p-0149" num="0202">The eigenvalue method for calibration can be applied at the spectroscopic broadband systems according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0150" num="0203">As stated previously, the raw data given by the disclosed ellipsometer/polarimeter are equivalent to the matrix product AMW. To obtain M it is necessary to know a priori A and W. Even if the hypothesis of ideal elements can give a first approach, a calibration procedure is necessary in order to determine the real values of A and W that account for the effect of possible multiple-reflected beams, small defects, misalignment or imprecise orientation of the optical elements among other instrumental non-idealities.</p>
<p id="p-0151" num="0204">The present calibration procedure is general and is valid for the calibration of the ellipsometer/polarimeter system set either in reflection or in transmission mode. According to the method and for clarity purposes, the experimental measurements are written in lower case, and the theoretical or ideal mathematical elements representing physical objects are noted in upper case. For two samples with Mueller matrices M<sub>1 </sub>and M<sub>2</sub>, the raw data resulting from their respective measurements are (am<sub>1</sub>w) and (am<sub>2</sub>w) and their respective theoretical raw data equivalents are AM<sub>1</sub>W and AM<sub>2</sub>W. In absence of errors or noise, those expressions are related by:</p>
<p id="p-0152" num="0205">
<maths id="MATH-US-00006" num="00006">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mtable>
          <mtr>
            <mtd>
              <mrow>
                <mrow>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>AM</mi>
                    <mn>1</mn>
                  </msub>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <mi>W</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mrow>
                  <mo>(</mo>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>am</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <mi>w</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mo>)</mo>
                </mrow>
              </mrow>
            </mtd>
          </mtr>
          <mtr>
            <mtd>
              <mrow>
                <mrow>
                  <msub>
                    <mi>AM</mi>
                    <mn>2</mn>
                  </msub>
                  <mo>⁢</mo>
                  <mi>W</mi>
                </mrow>
                <mo>=</mo>
                <mrow>
                  <mo>(</mo>
                  <mrow>
                    <msub>
                      <mi>am</mi>
                      <mn>2</mn>
                    </msub>
                    <mo>⁢</mo>
                    <mi>w</mi>
                  </mrow>
                  <mo>)</mo>
                </mrow>
              </mrow>
            </mtd>
          </mtr>
        </mtable>
        <mo>}</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>10</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0153" num="0206">Considering that M<sub>1 </sub>and W are invertible, it is possible to obtain A:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>A</i>=(<i>am</i><sub>1</sub><i>w</i>)<i>W</i><sup>−1</sup><i>M</i><sub>1</sub><sup>−1</sup><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0154" num="0207">The substitution of the last expression in (10) results in the following:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>M</i><sub>1</sub><sup>−1</sup><i>M</i><sub>2</sub><i>W−W</i>(<i>am</i><sub>1</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup>(<i>am</i><sub>2</sub><i>w</i>)=0  (11)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0155" num="0208">After a similar mathematical manipulation, but with W instead of A, one obtains:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>AM</i><sub>2</sub><i>M</i><sub>1</sub><sup>−1</sup>−(<i>am</i><sub>2</sub><i>w</i>)(<i>am</i><sub>1</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup><i>A</i>=0  (12)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0156" num="0209">Equations 11 and 12 form a system of linear equations where A and W are the unknowns. However, up to this point nothing is known about the theoretical expressions M<sub>1</sub><sup>−1</sup>M<sub>2 </sub>and M<sub>2</sub>M<sub>1</sub><sup>−1</sup>. The eigenvalue method provides an original way to solve this apparent difficulty with the use of a simple set of calibration samples. For example, let's take a polarizer oriented to zero degree as a reference sample. The measurement of raw data without the polarizer gives B<sub>0</sub>=AM<sub>0</sub>W, where M<sub>0 </sub>can correspond either to a mirror located in the sample-holder if the ellipsometer is set in reflection, or to the unit matrix if the polarimeter is set in transmission without a sample between the PSG and the PSA. To obtain W, the polarizer must be located between the PSG and the sample-holder, thus, giving a raw matrix B<sub>P</sub>=AM<sub>0</sub>PW, with P given by the expression 1. Multiplication of the inverse of B<sub>0 </sub>by B<sub>P </sub>gives: C<sub>P</sub>=B<sub>0</sub><sup>−1</sup>B<sub>P</sub>=W<sup>−1</sup>PW. In theory, the eigenvalues of C<sub>P </sub>and P are the same. Knowing that P has only one non-zero eigenvalue λ<sub>1</sub>=2τ<sub>p</sub>, then it is possible to perform a direct measurement of τ<sub>P </sub>which is the sole parameter needed to characterize completely the matrix P. Back to expression 11, assuming that M<sub>1 </sub>equals M<sub>0</sub>, and that M<sub>2 </sub>equals M<sub>0</sub>P, the expression can be rewritten as:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>PW−W</i>(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup>(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>pw</i>)=0  (13)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0157" num="0210">To obtain A, a similar operation must be done. Continuing with the example of the polarizer as a reference sample, it is now necessary to locate it between the sample-holder and the PSA. Again, two measurements have to be performed, one without the polarizer giving B<sub>0</sub>=AM<sub>0</sub>W, and another with the polarizer giving B<sub>P</sub>=APM<sub>0</sub>W. The product of B<sub>P </sub>by the inverse of B<sub>0 </sub>gives: C<sub>P</sub>=B<sub>P</sub>B<sub>0</sub><sup>−1</sup>=A PA<sup>−1</sup>. Because the eigenvalues of C<sub>P </sub>and P are the same, it is possible to determine completely the matrix P. Now identifying M<sub>1 </sub>with M<sub>0 </sub>and M<sub>2 </sub>with PM<sub>0</sub>, it is possible to write the expression 12 in terms of P as follows:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>AP−</i>(<i>apm</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup><i>A</i>=0  (14)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0158" num="0211">Expressions 13 and 14 are now well defined equations. One of the possible ways to solve 13 and 14 consists of using an algebraic method. First, let's to create two linear mappings or applications, H<sup>W </sup>and H<sup>A</sup>, from the space of four-dimensional real matrices, {R<sup>4×4</sup>} to itself {R<sup>4×4</sup>}, having the following expressions:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>H</i><sup>W</sup>(<i>X</i>)=<i>PX−X</i>(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup>(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>pw</i>)  (15)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>H</i><sup>A</sup>(<i>X</i>)=<i>XP−</i>(<i>apm</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup><i>X</i>  (16)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0159" num="0212">As any linear mapping, H<sup>W </sup>and H<sup>A </sup>have a defined kernel and they can be represented by a matrix. Briefly, the kernel of a mapping is defined as the set of elements mapped towards the null element. The dimension of the kernel corresponds to the number of linearly independent elements in the set. By virtue of expressions 11 and 12, the matrix W belongs to the kernel of H<sup>W </sup>and the matrix A to the kernel of H<sup>A</sup>. When singular value decomposition (SVD) is performed on the matrix associated to a given mapping, a diagonal matrix can be obtained with a number of null diagonal elements equal to the dimension of the kernel. Further, it is known that each null singular value has an associated singular vector that turns out to be proportional to one of the elements of the kernel. Accordingly, if the kernel of H<sup>W </sup>and that of H<sup>A </sup>are of dimension 1, each of the corresponding associated matrices will have a unique null singular value with an associated singular vector being proportional to the desired solution W and A respectively, and the calibration problem will be solved. However, in practice, two difficulties arise. Firstly, W and A are matrices and not vectors, and secondly, if a polarizer or a retarder is used alone as unique reference sample, the dimension of the kernel cannot be one. The first difficulty is only apparent because the difference between vectors and matrices is only formal. In fact, the 4×4 matrices appearing in expressions 15 and 16 can be rewritten in the form of 16-dimensional vectors by taking the four columns of the matrix and writing them, one below the other, under the form a column that can be manipulated like a vector. Using 16-dimensional vectors, the mappings H<sup>W </sup>and H<sup>A </sup>can be represented by the 16×16 associate matrices H<sup>W </sup>and H<sup>A </sup>respectively. On the other hand, the dimension of the kernel of H<sup>W </sup>and H<sup>A </sup>can be reduced to one if a set of reference samples are used instead of only a single sample. In the most general case, where a number “n” of samples have to be used, the following “n” mappings can be built for the PSG and the PSA respectively:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>H</i><sub>i</sub><sup>W</sup>(<i>X</i>)=<i>M</i><sub>i</sub><i>X−X</i>(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup>(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>m</i><sub>i</sub><i>w</i>)  (17)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>H</i><sub>i</sub><sup>A</sup>(<i>X</i>)=<i>XM</i><sub>i</sub>−(<i>am</i><sub>i</sub><i>m</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup><i>X</i>  (18)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0160" num="0213">Where M<sub>i </sub>(i=1 . . . n) are the Mueller matrices of the n reference samples. Finding W or A is equivalent to find the solution of the following over-determined systems of equations:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>H</i><sub>i</sub><sup>W</sup>(<i>W</i>)=<i>M</i><sub>i</sub><i>W−W</i>(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup>(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>m</i><sub>i</sub><i>w</i>)=<i>H</i><sub>i</sub><sup>W</sup><i>W</i>=0  (19)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>H</i><sub>i</sub><sup>A</sup>(<i>A</i>)=<i>AM</i><sub>i</sub>−(<i>am</i><sub>i</sub><i>m</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)(<i>am</i><sub>0</sub><i>w</i>)<sup>−1</sup><i>A=H</i><sub>i</sub><sup>A</sup><i>A</i>=0  (20)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0161" num="0214">The solution of an over-determined linear system by least-squares method is given by the well-know relation {W. H. Press, B. P. Flannery, Numerical recipes in PASCAL}:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>K</i><sub>i</sub><sup>W</sup><i>W</i>=0  (21)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>K</i><sub>i</sub><sup>A</sup><i>A</i>=0  (22)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Where:
</p>
<p id="p-0162" num="0215">
<maths id="MATH-US-00007" num="00007">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msubsup>
          <mi>K</mi>
          <mi>i</mi>
          <mi>W</mi>
        </msubsup>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mrow>
            <msup>
              <mrow>
                <mo>(</mo>
                <mtable>
                  <mtr>
                    <mtd>
                      <msubsup>
                        <mi>H</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                        <mi>W</mi>
                      </msubsup>
                    </mtd>
                  </mtr>
                  <mtr>
                    <mtd>
                      <mi>⋮</mi>
                    </mtd>
                  </mtr>
                  <mtr>
                    <mtd>
                      <msubsup>
                        <mi>H</mi>
                        <mi>n</mi>
                        <mi>W</mi>
                      </msubsup>
                    </mtd>
                  </mtr>
                </mtable>
                <mo>)</mo>
              </mrow>
              <mi>T</mi>
            </msup>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mo>(</mo>
              <mtable>
                <mtr>
                  <mtd>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>H</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                      <mi>W</mi>
                    </msubsup>
                  </mtd>
                </mtr>
                <mtr>
                  <mtd>
                    <mi>⋮</mi>
                  </mtd>
                </mtr>
                <mtr>
                  <mtd>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>H</mi>
                      <mi>n</mi>
                      <mi>W</mi>
                    </msubsup>
                  </mtd>
                </mtr>
              </mtable>
              <mo>)</mo>
            </mrow>
          </mrow>
          <mo>=</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mrow>
              <mrow>
                <msup>
                  <mrow>
                    <mo>(</mo>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>H</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                      <mi>W</mi>
                    </msubsup>
                    <mo>)</mo>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>T</mi>
                </msup>
                <mo>⁢</mo>
                <msubsup>
                  <mi>H</mi>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                  <mi>W</mi>
                </msubsup>
              </mrow>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <mi>⋯</mi>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <mrow>
                <msup>
                  <mrow>
                    <mo>(</mo>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>H</mi>
                      <mi>n</mi>
                      <mi>W</mi>
                    </msubsup>
                    <mo>)</mo>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>T</mi>
                </msup>
                <mo>⁢</mo>
                <msubsup>
                  <mi>H</mi>
                  <mi>n</mi>
                  <mi>W</mi>
                </msubsup>
              </mrow>
            </mrow>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mn>0</mn>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>23</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <msubsup>
          <mi>K</mi>
          <mi>i</mi>
          <mi>A</mi>
        </msubsup>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mrow>
            <msup>
              <mrow>
                <mo>(</mo>
                <mtable>
                  <mtr>
                    <mtd>
                      <msubsup>
                        <mi>H</mi>
                        <mn>1</mn>
                        <mi>A</mi>
                      </msubsup>
                    </mtd>
                  </mtr>
                  <mtr>
                    <mtd>
                      <mi>⋮</mi>
                    </mtd>
                  </mtr>
                  <mtr>
                    <mtd>
                      <msubsup>
                        <mi>H</mi>
                        <mi>n</mi>
                        <mi>A</mi>
                      </msubsup>
                    </mtd>
                  </mtr>
                </mtable>
                <mo>)</mo>
              </mrow>
              <mi>T</mi>
            </msup>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mrow>
              <mo>(</mo>
              <mtable>
                <mtr>
                  <mtd>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>H</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                      <mi>A</mi>
                    </msubsup>
                  </mtd>
                </mtr>
                <mtr>
                  <mtd>
                    <mi>⋮</mi>
                  </mtd>
                </mtr>
                <mtr>
                  <mtd>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>H</mi>
                      <mi>n</mi>
                      <mi>A</mi>
                    </msubsup>
                  </mtd>
                </mtr>
              </mtable>
              <mo>)</mo>
            </mrow>
          </mrow>
          <mo>=</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mrow>
              <mrow>
                <msup>
                  <mrow>
                    <mo>(</mo>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>H</mi>
                      <mn>1</mn>
                      <mi>A</mi>
                    </msubsup>
                    <mo>)</mo>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>T</mi>
                </msup>
                <mo>⁢</mo>
                <msubsup>
                  <mi>H</mi>
                  <mn>1</mn>
                  <mi>A</mi>
                </msubsup>
              </mrow>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <mi>⋯</mi>
              <mo>+</mo>
              <mrow>
                <msup>
                  <mrow>
                    <mo>(</mo>
                    <msubsup>
                      <mi>H</mi>
                      <mi>n</mi>
                      <mi>A</mi>
                    </msubsup>
                    <mo>)</mo>
                  </mrow>
                  <mi>T</mi>
                </msup>
                <mo>⁢</mo>
                <msubsup>
                  <mi>H</mi>
                  <mi>n</mi>
                  <mi>A</mi>
                </msubsup>
              </mrow>
            </mrow>
            <mo>=</mo>
            <mn>0</mn>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mn>24</mn>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0163" num="0216">The matrices K<sub>i</sub><sup>W </sup>and K<sub>i</sub><sup>A </sup>are symmetrical and definite positive so, they can be diagonalized. Both matrices have only one null eigenvalue with a related eigenvector being proportional to W, and A respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0164" num="0217">The type and the number of calibration samples is not unique. A reasonable choice consists of using the minimum number of elements. In that way, it has been demonstrated that a pair of polarizers combined with a retarder, or alternatively, two retarders together with a polarizer, can be conveniently used as calibration samples sets. The characteristics of the first set are:
<ul id="ul0017" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0017-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0018" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0018-0001" num="0218">A linear polarizer oriented at −20° with respect to the incidence plane.</li>
        <li id="ul0018-0002" num="0219">A linear polarizer oriented at +40° with respect to the incidence plane.</li>
        <li id="ul0018-0003" num="0220">A linear retarder providing retardation between 30 and 170°, oriented parallel to the incidence plane.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0165" num="0221">The characteristics of the second set of calibration samples are:
<ul id="ul0019" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0019-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0020" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0020-0001" num="0222">A linear polarizer oriented at −20° with respect to the incidence plane.</li>
        <li id="ul0020-0002" num="0223">A linear retarder providing retardation between 30° and 170° oriented at +40° with respect to the incidence plane.</li>
        <li id="ul0020-0003" num="0224">A linear retarder providing retardation between 30° and 170°, oriented parallel with respect to the incidence plane.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07298480-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="15.16mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298480-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00002" nb-file="US07298480-20071120-M00002.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00002" he="20.83mm" wi="96.69mm" file="US07298480-20071120-M00002.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00003" nb-file="US07298480-20071120-M00003.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00003" he="15.16mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298480-20071120-M00003.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00004" nb-file="US07298480-20071120-M00004.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00004" he="20.49mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298480-20071120-M00004.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00005" nb-file="US07298480-20071120-M00005.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00005" he="8.13mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298480-20071120-M00005.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00006" nb-file="US07298480-20071120-M00006.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00006" he="7.45mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298480-20071120-M00006.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00007" nb-file="US07298480-20071120-M00007.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00007" he="28.19mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298480-20071120-M00007.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system for analysing a sample (<b>8</b>) comprising:
<claim-text>an illumination source (<b>5</b>) emitting a polychromatic light beam (<b>12</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>a polarisation state generator (PSG) (<b>6</b>) including a fixed linear polarizer (<b>13</b>) and a substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) mounted on a rotating holder (<b>14</b>), said light beam (<b>12</b>) passing through said PSG (<b>6</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sample holder (<b>3</b>), on which the sample (<b>8</b>) can be mounted, the light beam (<b>12</b>) being focused on the sample (<b>8</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>a polarisation state analyser (PSA) (<b>10</b>) including a fixed linear polarizer (<b>20</b>) and a substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) mounted on a rotating holder (<b>19</b>), the beam going through said PSA (<b>10</b>), after being transmitted, reflected or scattered by the sample (<b>8</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>a primary detection system (<b>11</b>) measuring the intensity of the light beam transmitted through said PSA (<b>10</b>) at each wavelength,</claim-text>
<claim-text>optics to collimate the beam into the PSG (<b>6</b>) and into the PSA (<b>10</b>) and to focus the beam into the sample surface,</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein,
<claim-text>said linear polarizer (<b>20</b>) and said substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) in the PSA (<b>10</b>) are identical to the linear polarizer (<b>13</b>) and the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) of the PSG (<b>6</b>) and inverted according to the sense of propagation of the light,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said rotating holders (<b>14</b>, <b>19</b>) run in a stepper mode allowing a set of only four selected orientation angles for the retarders (<b>21</b>, <b>22</b>), said set of four selected orientation angles being optimized in order to maintain the condition numbers of the modulation and analysis matrices associated respectively with the PSG (<b>6</b>) and the PSA (<b>10</b>) over 0.2.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) of the PSG (<b>6</b>) are total internal reflection based retarder providing a phase-shift of either {132°±30°+n360°} or {227°±30°+n360°} for all the wavelengths of the light beam (<b>12</b>), with “n” being any integer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) of the PSA (<b>10</b>) are total internal reflection based retarder providing a phase-shift of either {132°±30°+n360°} or {227°±30°+n360°} for all the wavelengths of the light beam (<b>12</b>), with “n” being any integer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) of the PSG (<b>6</b>) is placed at a set of four selected orientation angles θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3 </sub>and θ<sub>4</sub>, said θ<sub>1 </sub>being either {38±20°+n360°} or {218±20°+n360°}, said θ<sub>2</sub>, being either {75±20°+n360°} or {255±20°+n360°}, said θ<sub>3 </sub>being either {104±20°+n360°} or {284±20°+n360°}, and said θ<sub>4 </sub>being {142±20°+n360°} or {322±20°+n360°}, with “n” being any integer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) of the PSA (<b>10</b>) is placed at four selected orientation angles θ<sub>1</sub>, θ<sub>2</sub>, θ<sub>3 </sub>and θ<sub>4</sub>, said θ<sub>1 </sub>being either {38±20°+n360°} or {218±20°+n360°}, said θ<sub>2</sub>, being either {75±20°+n360°} or {255±20°+n360°}, said θ<sub>3 </sub>being either {104±20°+n360°} or {284±20°+n360°}, and said θ<sub>4 </sub>being {142±20° +n360°} or {322±20°+n360°}, with “n” being any integer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) of the PSG (<b>6</b>) comprises at least two prisms, said substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) causing at least four internal reflections to the light beam (<b>12</b>) entering on it and said beam (<b>12</b>) is not deviated.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) of the PSA (<b>10</b>) comprises at least two prisms, said substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) causing at least four internal reflections to the light beam (<b>12</b>) entering on it and said beam (<b>12</b>) is not deviated.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) of the PSG (<b>6</b>) is a bi-prism (<b>51</b>) in “V” shape, each bi-prism (<b>51</b>) consists of two rhombs (<b>50</b>, <b>50</b>′) having an identical shape, optically assembled by one of their sides.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) of the PSA (<b>10</b>) is a bi-prism (<b>51</b>) in “V” shape, each bi-prism (<b>51</b>) consists of two rhombs (<b>50</b>, <b>50</b>′) having an identical shape, optically assembled by one of their sides.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) of the PSG (<b>6</b>) comprises three triangular prisms (<b>24</b>, <b>25</b>, <b>26</b>) from which, at least two have an identical shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) of the PSA (<b>10</b>) comprises three triangular prisms (<b>24</b>, <b>25</b>, <b>26</b>) from which, at least two have an identical shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) of the PSG (<b>6</b>) comprises three prisms (<b>27</b>, <b>28</b>, <b>29</b>), two prisms (<b>27</b>, <b>29</b>) of said three prisms (<b>27</b>, <b>28</b>, <b>29</b>) are triangular and one prism (<b>28</b>) is trapezoidal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, characterised in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) of the PSA (<b>10</b>) comprises three prisms (<b>27</b>, <b>28</b>, <b>29</b>), two prisms (<b>27</b>, <b>29</b>) of said three prisms (<b>27</b>, <b>28</b>, <b>29</b>) are triangular and one prism (<b>28</b>) is trapezoidal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterized in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>21</b>) of the PSG (<b>6</b>) comprises four trapezoidal prisms (<b>31</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>33</b>, <b>34</b>) having an identical shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, characterized in that the substantially achromatic retarder (<b>22</b>) of the PSA (<b>10</b>) comprises four trapezoidal prisms (<b>31</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>33</b>, <b>34</b>) having an identical shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterised in that each prism is made of a material with an index of refraction greater than that of the surrounding media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterised in that the entrance and exit faces of the prisms comprise an antireflection treatment (coating) to minimise light insertion losses.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterised in that the faces of the prisms wherein total internal refection takes place, are uncoated.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, characterised in that the prisms of the substantially achromatic retarders (<b>21</b>, <b>22</b>) are made of a material presenting a low index of refraction like the BaF<sub>2</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that the primary detection system (<b>11</b>) measures simultaneously the intensity of all the wavelengths of the light beam transmitted through said PSA (<b>10</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that the primary detection system (<b>11</b>) measures simultaneously and separately the intensity of each wavelength of the light beam transmitted through said PSA (<b>10</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that it includes a secondary detection system (<b>32</b>) to monitor the power given by the illumination source (<b>5</b>) including a beam-splitter (<b>23</b>) located between the illumination source (<b>5</b>) and the PSG (<b>6</b>) and a secondary detector (<b>24</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that it includes a holder for reference samples (<b>7</b>), said holder is placed between the PSG (<b>6</b>) and the sample holder (<b>3</b>), said holder introduce a set reference samples (<b>15</b>), (<b>16</b>) in the beam path (<b>12</b>) during calibration, and remove them during measurement process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that it includes a holder for reference samples (<b>9</b>), said holder is placed between the sample holder (<b>3</b>) and the PSA (<b>10</b>), said holder introduce a set reference samples (<b>17</b>), (<b>18</b>) in the beam path (<b>12</b>) during calibration, and remove them during measurement process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that said system operates in a spectral range from 4 to 20 microns.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. A broadband ellipsometer/polarimeter system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterised in that said system operates in a FUV-NIR spectral range from 140 nm to 2000 nm.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
