<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298765-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298765</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10366983</doc-number>
<date>20030214</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>1045</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>38</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370537</main-classification>
<further-classification>710 63</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">System and method for multiplexing digital and analog signals using a single electrical connector</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6862636</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Young</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710 69</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7103381</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wright et al.</name>
<date>20060900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>455557</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7184794</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hess et al.</name>
<date>20070200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>455559</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0228369</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Simmons, III</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370537</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>32</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370537</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710 63</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710 64</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040160993</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040819</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ganton</last-name>
<first-name>Robert B.</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Diego</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Pieronek</last-name>
<first-name>James V.</first-name>
<address>
<city>San Diego</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Kyocera Wireless Corp.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>San Diego</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Marcelo</last-name>
<first-name>Melvin</first-name>
<department>2616</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A system and a method are provided for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector. The system includes a connector with at least four lines and analog and digital interfaces attached to the connector. The interfaces share: first and second analog-to-digital converters (ADCs); and first, second, and third switches. The analog interface includes an audio sub-system with a third ADC and first, second, and third digital-to-analog converters (DACs). The digital interface includes a digital sub-system. The switches have first terminals attached to the connector, second terminals connected to the third ADC and the DACs. The switches open in response to a digital mode signal, enabling a digital signal path from the digital interface terminals to the connector. The switches close in response to an analog mode signal, enabling an analog signal path from the connector to the audio sub-system.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="223.35mm" wi="154.60mm" file="US07298765-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="229.87mm" wi="164.76mm" file="US07298765-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="224.11mm" wi="144.10mm" file="US07298765-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="232.16mm" wi="163.58mm" file="US07298765-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="223.77mm" wi="155.53mm" file="US07298765-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="230.12mm" wi="167.81mm" file="US07298765-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="211.58mm" wi="115.57mm" file="US07298765-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="162.39mm" wi="121.24mm" file="US07298765-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention generally relates to electrical signal connector interfaces and, more particularly, to a system and method for using a single electrical connector to multiplex digital and analog signals to and from a device.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Connectors are used to interface devices for the purpose of communicating signals or power. These signals can include digital data signals and analog signals. The following discussion is directed to audio analog signals. However, the discussion applies to other types of analog signals as well. Typically, connectors are configured to accept one particular type of connector interface, for example, a jack. As is well known, there are a large variety of cable types and associated connector interfaces. Typically, each particular type of connector interface is configured to handle only one specific type of signal. For example, wireless communications devices may use a connector accepting a four-line jack for a headset. The lines from the jack supply an audio input signal from a microphone in the headset, accept an audio output signal for a mono speaker in the headset or audio output signals for stereo speakers in the headset, and ground the headset to the device. The connector for the headset jack does not accept other types of cable connectors. For example, a separate connector, incompatible with the headset jack, is used to send and receive digital signals through an alternate port. In addition, separate sub-systems are typically used in a wireless communications device to supply and accept different types of signals to and from a connector in the device. The sub-systems may have different operating parameters and sensitivities and are typically not designed to handle other types of signals. For example, voltages associated with an audio signal could damage digital data signal circuits. Therefore, using separate, incompatible connectors in a wireless device serves the purpose of protecting circuitry in the device from the inadvertent application of potentially damaging signals to the circuitry. For example, as noted above, a user cannot inadvertently insert the headset jack into a digital data connector.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Therefore, it is known to use separate connectors to accept and supply digital and analog signals. However, there are disadvantages associated with the use of separate connectors for different signal types. A wireless communications device is used as an example to illustrate these disadvantages. However, it should be appreciated that these disadvantages apply to other portable devices and non-portable devices as well. Advances in technology and manufacturing techniques permit wireless communications devices to be made increasingly smaller, which in turn, creates a need to reduce the space required for components in the devices by reducing the number and/or size of the components.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Unfortunately, providing separate connectors increases the component parts count in a wireless device. The subsequent increase in space usage can limit the size to which a wireless device can be reduced, or can limit space available in the wireless device for other components. Increasing the parts count for a wireless device also adds to the cost of producing the wireless device. Since general reliability decreases as parts count in a wireless device increases, increasing the parts count by using separate connectors also decreases the reliability of the wireless device.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It would be advantageous if the number of connectors used in a device to accept and supply digital and analog communication signals could be reduced.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention addresses connectors in a device used to accept and supply communication signals. The invention recognizes that space and costs for components are concerns in the manufacture of most devices, particularly portable devices, such as wireless communications devices. The invention also recognizes that reduced reliability associated with increased component parts count in a device is a concern. The invention addresses these problems by using a single connector to supply and accept digital and analog signals, thereby reducing component parts count and associated space, cost, and reliability concerns.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Accordingly, a system is presented for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector. The system includes a connector with at least four lines and analog and digital interfaces attached to the connector. The interfaces supply communication signals to, and accept communication signals from the connector. The interfaces share: first and second analog-to-digital converters (ADCs); first, second, and third switches; and a controller to supply mode signals. The analog interface includes an audio sub-system with a third ADC and first, second, and third digital-to-analog converters (DACs). The digital interface includes a digital sub-system. The switches have first terminals attached to the connector, second terminals connected to the third ADC and the DACs, and inputs to accept the mode signals. The switches open in response to a digital mode signal, enabling a digital signal path from the digital interface terminals to the connector. The switches close in response to an analog mode signal, enabling an audio signal path from the connector to the third ADC and the DACs.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Additional details of the above-described system, and a method for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector are provided below.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic block diagram depicting a Universal Serial Bus (USB) embodiment of the system for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, and <b>1</b>C are schematic block diagrams depicting a biasing circuit element for the detection circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic block diagram showing an RS-232 embodiment of the system for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic block diagram showing a baseband processor in an RS-232 embodiment of the system for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow chart illustrating the method for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flow chart showing in further detail the method illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a flow chart showing in further detail the method illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic block diagram depicting a Universal Serial Bus (USB) embodiment of the system <b>100</b> for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector. The system <b>100</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is configured for a USB digital mode. However, it should be appreciated that the present invention is applicable to other digital communication modes, particularly Recommended Standard−232 (RS-232), as described below. The system <b>100</b> is applicable to a device <b>102</b> and includes a connector with at least four lines. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a four-line connector <b>104</b> is used as an example. Connector <b>104</b> accepts a four-wire jack (not shown). Although a male connector is used to describe aspects of the system, it should be appreciated that the system can be enabled with other connector styles.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The jack and the connector <b>104</b> are used to receive communication signals for the device <b>102</b> from equipment (not shown) attached to the jack and to supply communication signals from the device <b>102</b> to equipment attached to the jack. As noted in the above Background Section, device connectors typically accept and supply one particular type of communication signal. In the system <b>100</b>, however, the connector <b>104</b> accepts both digital and analog communication signals. That is, the system <b>100</b> can operate in a digital mode or an analog mode. A wireless communications device is used as an example to discuss the operation of the system <b>100</b>. However, it should be appreciated that the discussion of system <b>100</b> also is applicable to other portable devices and non-portable devices as well.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">At least two factors contribute to the system <b>100</b> capability of operating in both digital and analog modes in a wireless communications device. First, it is relatively uncommon for a wireless device to simultaneously operate in both digital and analog modes. Therefore, it is possible, in most cases, for a single connector to accommodate both digital and analog signals. Second, with care, the states required for USB and RS-232 digital signals to provide the information needed by devices receiving the digital signals can be chosen to match the requirements of the analog portion of a wireless device, allowing the same lines to be used for digital and analog signals. To accomplish both analog and digital communication, the system <b>100</b> includes an analog interface <b>106</b> and a digital interface <b>108</b>. The analog interface <b>106</b> and the digital interface <b>108</b> share lines <b>110</b>, <b>112</b>, <b>114</b>, and <b>116</b> to the connector <b>104</b> and these lines are used for supplying and accepting analog and digital communication signals to and from the connector <b>104</b>, as further described below. In both a digital and an audio analog mode of operation, the line <b>114</b> is connected to a device ground <b>117</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The analog interface <b>106</b> and the digital interface <b>108</b> share a first detection sub-system <b>118</b> with an input to accept communication signals on line <b>110</b>. Detection sub-system <b>118</b> has an output to supply identification signals on line <b>120</b> in response to the communication signals on line <b>110</b>. The interfaces <b>106</b> and <b>108</b> also share a second detection sub-system <b>121</b> with an input to accept communication signals on line <b>116</b>. Detection sub-system <b>121</b> has an output to supply identification signals on line <b>122</b> in response to the communication signals on line <b>116</b>. The detection sub-systems <b>118</b> and <b>121</b> are used to detect and identify communication signals (analog or digital) on lines <b>110</b> and <b>116</b>, respectively “on the fly”. That is, the detection sub-systems <b>118</b> and <b>121</b> detect and identify the communication signals without input or instructions from the device <b>102</b> user or reconfiguration of the system <b>100</b>. The detection sub-system information is used by the system <b>100</b> to automatically switch operations between digital and analog modes as described below. The detection sub-system <b>118</b> includes a first analog-to-digital converter (ADC) <b>123</b> connected to the detection sub-system <b>118</b> input on line <b>110</b>. The detection sub-system <b>121</b> includes a second ADC <b>124</b> connected to the detection sub-system <b>121</b> input on line <b>116</b>. The ADC <b>123</b> and the ADC <b>124</b> supply digital identification signals on lines <b>120</b> and <b>122</b>, respectively, in response to digital communication signals on lines <b>110</b> and <b>116</b>, respectively. The ADC <b>123</b> and the ADC <b>124</b> supply analog identification signals on lines <b>120</b> and <b>122</b>, respectively, in response to analog communication signals on lines <b>110</b> and <b>116</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The analog interface <b>106</b> and the digital interface <b>108</b> also share a controller <b>126</b>, a first switch <b>128</b>, a second switch <b>130</b>, and a third switch <b>131</b>. The controller <b>126</b> has inputs to accept the identification signals on lines <b>120</b> and <b>122</b> and an output to supply a mode signal on line <b>132</b> in response to the identification signals. The switch <b>128</b> has a first terminal connected to line <b>110</b>, a second terminal connected to line <b>133</b>, and an input to accept the mode signal on line <b>132</b>. The switch <b>130</b> has a first terminal connected to line <b>112</b>, a second terminal connected to line <b>134</b>, and an input to accept the mode signal on line <b>132</b>. The switch <b>131</b> has a first terminal connected to line <b>116</b>, a second terminal connected to line <b>135</b>, and an input to accept the mode signal on line <b>132</b>. The identification signals from ADC <b>123</b> and ADC <b>124</b> identify the type of communication to be performed in the system <b>100</b> and the controller <b>126</b> supplies mode signals on line <b>132</b> containing instructions for the appropriate multiplexing mode, accordingly. Therefore, the controller <b>126</b> supplies a digital mode signal on line <b>132</b> in response to a digital identification signal on line <b>120</b> or <b>122</b>. It will be understood that line <b>132</b>, as with other lines, such as line <b>120</b>, could be multiple lines. The controller <b>126</b> supplies an analog mode signal on line <b>132</b> in response to an analog identification signal on line <b>120</b> or <b>122</b>. The operation of the switches <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>131</b>, in response to the mode control signal on line <b>132</b>, is discussed below.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The analog interface <b>106</b> includes an audio sub-system <b>138</b> with a first terminal connected to line <b>133</b>, a second terminal connected to line <b>134</b>, and a third terminal connected to line <b>135</b>. The system <b>100</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (and in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> below) is configured for audio analog communication. However, it should be appreciated that other analog communication configurations are applicable to the system. The digital interface <b>108</b> includes a digital sub-system <b>140</b> with a first terminal connected to line <b>110</b>, a second terminal connected to line <b>112</b>, and an input to accept the mode signal on line <b>132</b>. The audio sub-system <b>138</b>, the digital sub-system <b>140</b>, and the connector <b>104</b> exchange communication signals via communication signal paths controlled by switches <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>131</b> in response to mode signals on line <b>132</b>. Switches <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>131</b> open in response to a digital mode signal on line <b>132</b>. Opening the switches <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>131</b> isolates the audio sub-system <b>138</b> and creates digital signal paths on lines <b>110</b> and <b>112</b> from the connector <b>104</b> to the digital sub-system <b>140</b>. Switches <b>128</b> and <b>130</b> close in response to an analog mode signal on line <b>132</b>. Closing the switches <b>128</b> and <b>130</b> creates audio signal paths from the connector <b>104</b> to the audio sub-system <b>138</b> via lines <b>110</b> and <b>112</b>. The operation of the switch <b>131</b> in the analog mode, as well as the operation of sub-systems <b>138</b> and <b>140</b> is further described below.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The audio sub-system <b>138</b> includes a third ADC <b>142</b> connected to line <b>132</b> and first and second digital-to-analog converters (DACs) <b>144</b> and <b>144</b>L connected to line <b>134</b>. Audio sub-system <b>138</b> also includes a third DAC <b>144</b>R connected to line <b>135</b>. When configured for audio analog operation, the system <b>100</b> can operate in a mono audio mode or a stereo audio mode. The determination of a mono or stereo mode in the device <b>102</b> is described below. Supplying input signals to the DACs <b>144</b>, <b>144</b>L, and <b>144</b>R, and accepting audio output signals from the ADC <b>142</b> is performed by systems (not shown) outside the system <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">When the system <b>100</b> is operating in either the mono or the stereo audio mode, the ADC <b>142</b> accepts an audio input signal from the connector <b>104</b> via line <b>133</b>, the switch <b>128</b> and line <b>110</b>. In the mono audio mode, the DAC <b>144</b> supplies a mono audio output signal to the connector <b>104</b> via lines <b>134</b> and <b>112</b> and switch <b>130</b>. In addition, the switch <b>131</b> is opened and line <b>116</b> is grounded by systems (not shown) outside the system <b>100</b>. Some mono headsets connect the third and fourth rings of a jack (not shown), causing the fourth ring (corresponding to line <b>116</b>) to be grounded when the third ring on the jack contacts the third connector line (line <b>114</b>), which is grounded as noted above. When the system <b>100</b> is operating in the stereo audio mode, the switches <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>131</b> close, the DAC <b>144</b>L supplies a stereo audio output signal on line <b>134</b>, and DAC <b>144</b>R supplies a stereo audio output signal on line <b>135</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">On line <b>110</b>, audio communication signals are associated with an audio input signal on line <b>110</b> or signals supplied to line <b>110</b> by equipment attached to the jack in response to an audio output signal supplied by device <b>102</b> on lines <b>112</b> or <b>116</b>. Audio communication signals on line <b>116</b> are typically associated with a ground path (as described above) or voltage or impedance on line <b>116</b>, as described below.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In the USB digital mode configuration shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the digital sub-system <b>140</b> includes a USB transceiver <b>148</b>. The USB transceiver <b>148</b> has a D+terminal connected to the first digital sub-system <b>140</b> terminal on line <b>110</b>, a D− terminal connected the second digital sub-system <b>140</b> terminal on line <b>112</b>, and an input to accept mode signals on line <b>132</b>. The ADC <b>123</b> and the ADC <b>124</b> supply USB digital identification signals in response to detecting USB digital communication signals on lines <b>110</b> and <b>116</b>, respectively. Then, the controller <b>126</b> supplies a USB digital mode signal on line <b>132</b>, opening switches <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>131</b>, as described above. USB data is transmitted on lines <b>110</b> and <b>112</b>, using the digital signal path.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">USB communication requires the use of at least a four-wire cable. Two of the wires (lines <b>110</b> and <b>112</b>) are for data transmission as noted above, and two of the wires can be used to transfer power. In one case, line <b>116</b> can accept power from a power supply (not shown) connected to a jack inserted in connector <b>104</b>. Examples of devices (not shown) that can supply power to the device <b>104</b> include, but are not limited to, a computer with a USB bus, a charging accessory, and a power adapter in an automobile. Line <b>116</b> also can be used to supply power from the device <b>102</b>. Power supplied on line <b>116</b> by the device <b>102</b> can be used by an accessory device (not shown) connected to a jack inserted in connector <b>104</b>. Line <b>114</b> is used to complete the USB power circuit. USB digital communication signals on line <b>110</b> are associated with data transmissions on line <b>110</b>. USB digital communication signals on line <b>116</b> are discussed below.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, and <b>1</b>C are schematic block diagrams depicting a biasing circuit element for the detection circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>, the biasing circuit element <b>150</b> includes a power supply <b>151</b> and resistors <b>152</b> and <b>153</b>. Power supply <b>151</b> is connected to a resistor <b>152</b> first port on line <b>154</b>. A resistor <b>152</b> second port is connected to line <b>116</b>. A resistor <b>153</b> first port is connected to line <b>116</b> and a second port connected to a ground <b>155</b> on line <b>156</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>, the biasing circuit element <b>150</b> includes a power supply <b>157</b>, diodes <b>158</b> and <b>159</b>, and resistors <b>160</b> and <b>161</b>. Power supply <b>157</b> is connected to a diode <b>158</b> first port on line <b>162</b>. A diode <b>158</b> second port is connected to a resistor <b>160</b> first port on line <b>163</b>. A resistor <b>160</b> second port is connected to line <b>116</b>. A resistor <b>161</b> first port is connected to line <b>116</b> and a second port is connected to a diode <b>159</b> first port on line <b>164</b>. A diode <b>159</b> second port is connected to ground <b>155</b> on line <b>165</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref>, the biasing circuit element <b>150</b> includes a power supply <b>166</b>, a resistor <b>167</b>, and a capacitor <b>168</b>. Power supply <b>166</b> is connected to a resistor <b>167</b> first port on line <b>169</b>. A resistor <b>167</b> second port is connected to line <b>116</b>. Capacitor <b>168</b> has a first port connected to line <b>116</b> and a second port connected to line <b>116</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In some aspects of the system <b>100</b>, pull-up and pull-down resistors (not shown) are used on lines <b>110</b> and <b>112</b>. However, the pull-up resistor on line <b>112</b> may not be desirable for high-speed data transfer operations. These resistors can add functionality in some specific circumstances. The use of, and parameters of the resistors can depend on the supplied voltages in the system <b>100</b>, the impedance of circuitry included in or interfacing with the system <b>100</b>, and the desired impedance in the system <b>100</b>. A biasing circuit element <b>150</b> in the detection circuit <b>121</b> can be used to create a voltage level in ADC <b>124</b> usable for identifying the type of device or accessory attached to a jack (not shown) inserted in the connector <b>104</b>. The biasing circuit element <b>150</b> is not limited to the components and configuration shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, and <b>1</b>C. Other components and/or configurations also are applicable to the biasing circuit <b>150</b>. The following examples illustrate the use of the biasing circuit element <b>150</b>. The analog examples are based on the audio analog configuration of system <b>100</b> described above. However, it is understood that the examples apply equally to other analog communication configurations. The following are examples of detecting analog voltage. In the stereo audio mode, a speaker attached to line <b>116</b> via the connector <b>104</b> typically has low resistance, which the ADC <b>124</b> detects as a near ground voltage. In response, the ADC <b>124</b> supplies a stereo audio identification signal on line <b>122</b>. When line <b>116</b> is grounded, as described above for the mono audio mode, the ADC <b>124</b> detects ground voltage. In response, the ADC <b>124</b> supplies a mono audio identification signal on line <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Following is an example of detecting digital voltage. If power is applied to the line <b>116</b>, the ADC <b>124</b> detects a higher voltage and supplies a USB digital identification signal on line <b>122</b>. Other devices attached to line <b>116</b> could result in the ADC <b>124</b> detecting voltages between the near ground and the applied power voltage levels. In these cases, the ADC <b>124</b> could be calibrated to supply identification signals corresponding to the other devices. If the bias circuit <b>150</b> is not included in the detection circuit <b>121</b>, the varying resistances to ground with respect to line <b>116</b>, associated with devices attached to line <b>116</b>, could be used to identify these devices. Alternately, a mono or stereo mode could be selected by the device <b>102</b> user via a device user interface (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In some aspects of the system <b>100</b>, operational amplifiers or transistors, including bi-polar transistors, are used for the switches <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>131</b>. In one aspect, field-effect transistors (FETs) are used. The gates of the FETs accept the mode signals on line <b>132</b> and the sources and drains of the FETs are used for the switch terminals described.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic block diagram showing an RS-232 embodiment of the system <b>100</b> for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector. In the RS-232 digital mode, the digital sub-system <b>140</b> includes a Central Processing Unit (CPU) <b>202</b>, a fourth switch <b>204</b>, and a fifth switch <b>206</b>. Switch <b>204</b> has a first terminal connected to line <b>110</b>, a second terminal connected to a CPU Receive Data (RxD) terminal on line <b>208</b>, and an input to accept the mode signal on line <b>132</b>. Switch <b>206</b> has a first terminal connected to line <b>112</b>, a second terminal connected to a CPU Transmit Data (TxD) terminal on line <b>210</b>, and an input to accept the mode signal on line <b>132</b>. The CPU <b>202</b> also has an input to accept mode signals on line <b>132</b>. The switches <b>204</b> and <b>206</b> are used to isolate the RxD and TxD terminals from higher voltages present on lines <b>110</b> and <b>112</b> when the system <b>100</b> is operating in the audio analog mode. The ADC <b>123</b> supplies an RS-232 digital identification signal in response to an RS-232 digital communication signal on line <b>110</b>. Then, the controller <b>126</b> supplies an RS-232 digital mode signal on line <b>132</b> opening switches <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>131</b> and closing switches <b>204</b> and <b>206</b>. RS-232 data signals are transmitted on line <b>110</b> and <b>112</b>. Line <b>116</b> is not used in RS-232 digital mode. The switches <b>204</b> and <b>206</b> open in response to an analog mode signal. RS-232 digital communication signals on line <b>110</b> are associated with the transmission of RS-232 data on line <b>110</b>. The use of pull-up and pull-down resistors on lines <b>110</b> and <b>112</b> is discussed above.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic block diagram showing a baseband processor in an RS-232 embodiment of the system <b>100</b> for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, baseband processor <b>302</b> includes the analog interface <b>106</b> and the digital interface <b>108</b>. However, the digital interface <b>108</b> is modified in this embodiment so that the switches <b>204</b> and <b>206</b> are external to the digital interface <b>108</b>, and hence the baseband processor <b>302</b>. The operation of this embodiment is as described above for <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The baseband processor <b>302</b> can include functionality similar to that provided by the pull-up and pull-down resistors and the bias circuit element <b>150</b> described above, eliminating the need for these resistors and bias circuit element <b>150</b>. A Mobile Station Modem (MSM) is one example of a baseband processor. It is understood that the system <b>100</b> also is applicable to other types of baseband processors.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In some aspects of the system <b>100</b>, operational amplifiers or transistors, including bi-polar transistors, are used for the switches <b>204</b> and <b>206</b>. In one aspect, field-effect transistors (FETs) are used. The gates of the FETs accept the mode signals on line <b>132</b> and the sources and drains of the FETs are used for the switch terminals described.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow chart illustrating the method for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector. Although the method in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> (and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref> below) is depicted as a sequence of numbered steps for clarity, no order should be inferred from the numbering unless explicitly stated. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref>, <b>5</b>, and <b>6</b>, a method multiplexes audio analog signals. However, it should be appreciated that other analog communication signals can be multiplexed using the method. The method starts at Step <b>400</b>. Step <b>402</b> detects digital communication signals. Step <b>402</b><i>a </i>enables digital communication through a digital interface in response to detecting digital communication signals. Step <b>402</b><i>b </i>enables digital signal paths in the connector lines. Step <b>402</b><i>c </i>enables digital communication in a format selected from the group including USB and RS-232. Step <b>404</b> detects analog communication signals. Step <b>404</b><i>a </i>enables audio communication through an analog interface in response to detecting analog communication signals. Step <b>404</b><i>b </i>enables audio signal paths in the connector. Step <b>404</b><i>c </i>enables audio signal paths in first and second connector lines. Step <b>404</b><i>d </i>accepts an audio input signal on the first connector line. Step <b>404</b><i>e </i>supplies a mono audio output signal to the second connector line. Step <b>404</b><i>f </i>grounds the third connector line. Step <b>404</b><i>g </i>grounds the fourth connector line. Step <b>406</b> detects communication signals to and from a connector with at least four lines.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In one aspect of the method, Step <b>408</b> measures a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector. Then, enabling digital communication through a digital interface in Step <b>402</b><i>a </i>includes enabling digital communications responsive to measuring a digital voltage at the line. Then, enabling analog communication through an analog interface in Step <b>404</b><i>a </i>includes enabling analog communications responsive to measuring an analog voltage at the line. In another aspect of the method, measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector in Step <b>408</b> includes coupling, through a resistor, a supply voltage to the line; grounding the line through a resistor; and, measuring, at the line, the voltage produced as a result of coupling the voltage supply and grounding the line. In one aspect of the method, measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector in Step <b>408</b> includes coupling, through a resistor and a diode, a supply voltage to the line; grounding, through a resistor and a diode, the line; and, measuring, at the line, the voltage produced as a result of coupling the voltage supply and grounding the line. In another aspect of the method, measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector in Step <b>408</b> includes coupling, through a resistor, a supply voltage to the line; supplying, through a capacitor, a communication signal on the line; and, measuring, at the line, the voltage produced as a result of coupling the voltage supply and supplying the signal through the capacitor.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In one aspect of the method, detecting analog communication signals in Step <b>404</b> includes accepting an analog voltage, converting the analog voltage to a digital signal, and interpreting the digital signal. In one aspect of the method, enabling audio signal paths in the connector lines in Step <b>404</b><i>b </i>includes supplying a first stereo audio output signal to the second connector line and supplying a second stereo audio output signal to the fourth connector line.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flow chart showing in further detail the method illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The method starts at Step <b>500</b>. Step <b>502</b> enables USB digital communication in response to USB digital communication signals. Step <b>504</b> enables digital signal paths in first and second connector lines. Step <b>506</b> supplies a USB data output signal to the first connector line. Step <b>508</b> accepts a USB data input signal on the second connector line. Step <b>510</b> grounds a third connector line. Step <b>512</b> accepts power on a fourth connector line. Step <b>514</b> supplies power on the fourth connector line.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a flow chart showing in further detail the method illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The method starts at Step <b>600</b>. Step <b>602</b> enables RS-232 digital communication in response to RS-232 communication signals. Step <b>604</b> enables digital signal paths in first and second connector lines. Step <b>606</b> accepts an RS-232 data input signal on the first connector line. Step <b>608</b> supplies an RS-232 data output signal to the second connector line. Step <b>610</b> grounds a third connector line.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">A system and a method are provided for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector. Examples of the present invention have been enabled with a wireless communications device. However, it should be understood that the present invention is not limited to wireless communications devices or even to portable devices in general. The present invention system and method are applicable to any device that sends or receives digital and analog signals. Portable devices to which the present invention system is applicable also include lap top computers, personal digital assistants, and music players. Other variations and embodiments of the present invention will occur to those skilled in the art.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector, the method comprising:
<claim-text>detecting digital communication signals on the electrical connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to detecting digital communication signals, enabling digital communication through a digital interface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>detecting analog communications signals on the electrical connector; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to detecting analog communication signals, enabling analog communication through an analog interface,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein detecting communication signals includes detecting communication signals to and from a connector with at least four lines,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein enabling digital communication through a digital interface includes enabling digital signal paths in the connector lines in response to detecting digital communication signals,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein enabling analog communication through an analog interface includes enabling audio signal paths in the connector lines in response to detecting analog communication signals, and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein detecting an analog communication signal includes:</claim-text>
<claim-text>accepting an analog voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>converting the analog voltage to a digital signal; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>interpreting the digital signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A method for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector, the method comprising:
<claim-text>detecting digital communication signals on the electrical connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to detecting digital communication signals, enabling digital communication through a digital interface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>detecting analog communications signals on the electrical connector; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to detecting analog communication signals, enabling analog communication through an analog interface,</claim-text>
<claim-text>further comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector, and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein enabling digital communication through a digital interface includes enabling digital communications responsive to measuring a digital voltage, and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein enabling analog communication through an analog interface includes enabling analog communications responsive to measuring an analog voltage and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector includes:</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling, through a resistor, a supply voltage to the line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>grounding the line through a resistor; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>measuring, at the line, the voltage produced as a result of coupling the voltage supply and grounding the line.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A method for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector, the method comprising:
<claim-text>detecting digital communication signals on the electrical connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to detecting digital communication signals, enabling digital communication through a digital interface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>detecting analog communications signals on the electrical connector; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to detecting analog communication signals, enabling analog communication through an analog interface,</claim-text>
<claim-text>further comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector, and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein enabling digital communication through a digital interface includes enabling digital communications responsive to measuring a digital voltage, and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein enabling analog communication through an analog interface includes enabling analog communications responsive to measuring an analog voltage, and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector includes:</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling, through a resistor and a diode, a supply voltage to the line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>grounding, through a resistor and a diode, the line; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>measuring, at the line, the voltage produced as a result of coupling the voltage supply and grounding the line.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A method for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector, the method comprising:
<claim-text>detecting digital communication signals on the electrical connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to detecting digital communication signals, enabling digital communication through a digital interface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>detecting analog communications signals on the electrical connector; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to detecting analog communication signals, enabling analog communication through an analog interface,</claim-text>
<claim-text>further comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector, and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein enabling digital communication through a digital interface includes enabling digital communications responsive to measuring a digital voltage, and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein enabling analog communication through an analog interface includes enabling analog communications responsive to measuring an analog voltage and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein measuring a voltage at a line coupled to the electrical connector includes:</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling, through a resistor, a supply voltage to the line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>supplying, through a capacitor, a communication signal on the line; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>measuring, at the line, the voltage produced as a result of coupling the voltage supply and supplying the signal through the capacitor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A system for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a device using a single electrical connector, the system comprising:
<claim-text>the connector with at least four lines;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an analog interface with at least four terminals, each terminal attached to a connector line to communicate analog signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a digital interface with at least four terminals, each terminal attached to a connector line to communicate digital signals,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the analog and digital interfaces share:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first detection sub-system with an input to accept communication signals on a first connector line and an output to supply identification signals in response to the communication signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second detection sub-system with an input to accept communication signals on a fourth connector line and an output to supply identification signals in response to the communication signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the first detection sub-system includes a first analog-to-digital converter (ADC);
<claim-text>wherein the first ADC has an input to accept the communication signals from the first connector line; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first ADC supplies digital identification signals in response to accepting digital communication signals and supplies analog identification signals in response to accepting analog communication signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the second detection sub-system includes a second ADC;
<claim-text>wherein the second ADC has an input to accept the communication signals from the fourth connector line; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second ADC supplies digital identification signals in response to accepting digital communication signals and supplies analog identification signals in response to accepting analog communication signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the second detection sub-system includes a bias circuit element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the analog and digital interfaces share a controller with inputs to accept the identification signals from the detection sub-systems and an output to supply a mode signal in response to the identification signals; and,
<claim-text>wherein the controller supplies a digital mode signal in response to digital identification signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the controller supplies an analog mode signal in response to analog identification signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the analog and digital interfaces share:
<claim-text>a first switch with a first terminal connected to the first connector line, a second terminal, and an input to accept the mode signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second switch with a first terminal connected to a second connector line, a second terminal, and an input to accept the mode signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third switch with a first terminal connected to the fourth connector line, a second terminal, and an input to accept the mode signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first, second, and third switches open in response to a digital mode signal, enabling a digital signal path; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first, second, and third switches close in response to an analog mode signal, enabling an analog signal path.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the analog interface includes an audio sub-system with a first terminal connected to the second terminal of the first switch, a second terminal connected to the second terminal of the second switch, and a third terminal connected to the second terminal of the third switch; and,
<claim-text>wherein the analog interface terminals accept and supply audio communication signals when the analog signal path is enabled.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein the audio sub-system includes: a third ADO connected to the first audio sub-system terminal and a first digital-to-analog converter (DAC) connected to the second audio sub-system terminal; and,
<claim-text>wherein the third ADC accepts and processes an audio input signal from the first audio sub-system terminal and the first DAC supplies a mono audio output signal to the second audio sub-system terminal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the fourth connector line is grounded.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the audio sub-system includes a second DAC connected to the second audio sub-system terminal and a third DAC connected to the third audio sub-system terminal; and,
<claim-text>wherein the second DAC supplies a stereo audio output signal to the second audio sub-system terminal; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the third DAC supplies a stereo audio output signal to the third audio sub-system terminal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the digital interface includes a digital sub-system with a first terminal connected to the first connector line and a second terminal connected to the second connector line; and,
<claim-text>wherein the digital interface terminals accept and supply digital communication signals when the digital signal path is enabled.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the digital sub-system includes a Universal Serial Bus (USB) transceiver;
<claim-text>wherein a USB transceiver D+ terminal is connected to the first digital interface terminal, a USB transceiver D− terminal is connected to the second digital interface terminal, and the USB transceiver has an input to accept mode signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first and second ADCs supply USB digital identification signals in response to USB digital communication signals on the first and fourth connector lines, respectively;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the controller supplies a USB digital mode signal opening the first, second, and third switches in response to USB digital identification signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein power is applied to the fourth connector line.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the digital sub-system includes a Central Processing Unit (CPU) and fourth and fifth switches;
<claim-text>wherein the CPU has an input to accept mode signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the fourth switch has a first terminal connected to the first digital interface terminal, a second terminal connected to a CPU Receive Data (RxD) terminal, and an input to accept mode signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the fifth switch has a first terminal connected to the second digital interface terminal, a second terminal connected to a CPU Transmit Data (TxD) terminal, and an input to accept mode signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein the first and second ADCs supply Recommended System-232 (RS-232) digital identification signals in response to RS-232 digital communication signals on the first and fourth connector lines, respectively;
<claim-text>wherein the controller supplies an RS-232 digital mode signal opening the first, second, and third switches and closing the fourth and fifth switches in response to RS-232 digital identification signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the fourth and fifth switches open in response to an analog mode signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein the first through fifth switches are operational amplifiers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein the first through fifth switches are transistors.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref> wherein the transistors are field-effect transistors (FETs).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a baseband processor; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>sixth and seventh switches; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the baseband processor includes the analog and digital interfaces; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the digital interface includes a CPU.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> wherein the CPU includes an input to accept mode signals, a Receive Data (RxD) terminal connected to the first digital sub-system terminal, and a Transmit Data (TxD) terminal connected to the second digital sub-system terminal;
<claim-text>wherein the sixth switch has a first terminal connected to the first connector line, a second terminal connected to the first digital interface terminal, and an input to accept mode signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the seventh switch has a first terminal connected to the second connector line, a second terminal connected to the second digital interface terminal, and an input to accept mode signals.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein the first and second ADOs supply Recommended System-232 (RS-232) digital identification signals in response to RS-232 digital communication signals on the first and fourth connector lines, respectively;
<claim-text>wherein the controller supplies an RS-232 digital mode signal opening the first, second, and third switches and closing the sixth and seventh switches in response to RS-232 digital identification signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the sixth and seventh switches open in response to an analog mode signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the baseband processor is a Mobile Station Modem (MSM).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the sixth and seventh switches are operational amplifiers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the sixth and seventh switches are transistors.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref> wherein the transistors are FETs.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the bias circuit element includes:
<claim-text>a first power supply with an output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first resistor with a first port connected to the power supply output and a second port connected to the fourth connector line; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second resistor with a first port connected to the fourth connector line and a second port connected to ground.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the bias circuit element includes:
<claim-text>a second power supply with an output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first diode with a first port connected to the power supply output and a second port;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third resistor with a first port connected to the first diode second port and a second port connected to the fourth connector line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth resistor with a first port connected to the fourth connector line and a second port; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second diode with a first port connected to the fourth resistor second port and a second port connected to ground.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the bias circuit element includes:
<claim-text>a third power supply with an output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fifth resistor with a first port connected to the power supply output and a second port connected to the fourth connector line; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a capacitor with a first port connected to the connector on the fourth connector line and a second port connected to the second ADO on the fourth connector line.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. A system for multiplexing digital and analog signals to and from a wireless communications device using a single electrical connector, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a connector with at least four lines;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first and second analog-to-digital converters (ADCs) accepting digital and analog communication signals from first and fourth connector lines, respectively, and supplying digital and analog identification signals, respectively, in response to the communication signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller accepting the digital and analog identification signals and in response, supplying digital and analog mode signals, respectively;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first, second, and third switches with first terminals attached to the first connector line, a second connector line, and the fourth connector line, respectively, second terminals, and inputs to receive the mode signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third ADO connected to the second terminal of the first switch, first and second digital-to-analog converters (DACs) connected to the second terminal of the second switch, and a third DAC connected to the second terminal of the third switch; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Universal Serial Bus (USB) transceiver with D+ and D− terminals connected to the first and second connecter lines, respectively, and an input to accept mode signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein in response to analog mode signals:
<claim-text>the first, second, and third switches close;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the third ADC accepts an audio input signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first DAC supplies mono audio output signals; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second and third DACs supply stereo audio output signals; and,</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first, second, and third switches open in response to a USB digital mode signal and wherein power is applied to the fourth connector line.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
