<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299396-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299396</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11326822</doc-number>
<date>20060106</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>20</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>18</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714749</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Methods and apparatus for error detection and correction of an electronic shelf label system communication error</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5537414</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Takiyasu et al.</name>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370347</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5880449</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Teicher et al.</name>
<date>19990300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>235383</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5968197</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Doiron</name>
<date>19991000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>714748</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6425105</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Piirainen et al.</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>714748</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6829670</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Nakamura</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710310</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6938195</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Shi et al.</name>
<date>20050800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>714748</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6977888</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Frenger et al.</name>
<date>20051200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370218</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>15</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714748</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714749</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10044535</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20020111</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7007219</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11326822</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060156160</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060713</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Haulk</last-name>
<first-name>Kevin Winton</first-name>
<address>
<city>Griffin</city>
<state>GA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Harkins</last-name>
<first-name>Cheryl Kay</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lawrenceville</city>
<state>GA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Priest &amp; Goldstein, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>NCR Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Dayton</city>
<state>OH</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Kerveros</last-name>
<first-name>James C.</first-name>
<department>2117</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">In one aspect, the ESL system automatically detects ESL communication errors which result in incorrect data in the ESL's registers, and then automatically takes corrective action to update the ESL's memory with the correct data. In one aspect, the host computer transmits a register update message to an ESL. If a negative acknowledgment message or no response is received, then the host computer resends the register update message, or takes other appropriate corrective action. If the host computer receives a positive acknowledgement message, the host computer then automatically transmits one or more messages to the ESL to verify the contents of the ESL's registers to ensure that a positive acknowledgement was actually transmitted.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="230.12mm" wi="171.11mm" file="US07299396-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="230.63mm" wi="172.64mm" file="US07299396-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="157.56mm" wi="148.42mm" file="US07299396-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="251.12mm" wi="139.70mm" file="US07299396-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of U.S. Ser. No. 10/455,535, filed Jan. 11, 2002, now U.S. Pat. No. 7,007,219.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to improvements in electronic shelf label (ESL) systems used in transaction establishments. More specifically, the present invention relates to improvements in methods and apparatus for detecting and correcting communication errors which result in data errors in an ESL's registers or memory.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">ESL systems typically include a plurality of ESLs for each merchandise item in a store. ESLs display the price of corresponding merchandise items on store shelves and are typically attached to a rail along the leading edge of the shelves. A store may contain thousands of ESLs to display the prices of the merchandise items. The ESLs are coupled to a central server where information about the ESLs is typically maintained in an ESL data file which contains ESL identification information and ESL merchandise item information. The central server sends messages, including price change messages, to the ESLs.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">While prior ESL systems provide many of the capabilities required by retailers, these systems may suffer from various disadvantages. For example, while communication between the central server and the ESLs is quite reliable, occasionally noise or other interference cause the central server to detect a particular response when another response, or no response at all, was transmitted by the ESL. Such an error may cause the central server to believe an ESL is correctly displaying information, when in actuality the ESL is not displaying the correct information. Therefore, it would be desirable to provide an ESL system and method that automatically detects ESL communication errors which result in the ESL containing incorrect data in the ESL's registers, and then automatically takes corrective action to update the ESL's memory with the correct data.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The present invention advantageously provides methods and apparatus for an improved electronic shelf label (ESL) system. The present invention provides an ESL system and method that automatically detects ESL communication errors which may result in the ESL containing incorrect data in the ESL's registers, and then automatically takes corrective action to update the ESL's memory with the correct data. In one aspect, a host computer transmits a register update message to an ESL. If a negative acknowledgement message or no response is received, then the host computer may resend the register update message, or take other such action. If the host computer receives a positive acknowledgment message, or what appears to be a positive acknowledgement message, the host computer then automatically transmits one or more messages to the ESL to verify the contents of the ESL's registers to ensure that a positive acknowledgement was actually transmitted.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A more complete understanding of the present invention, as well as further features and advantages of the invention, will be apparent from the following detailed description and the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a block diagram of a transaction management system in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of an ESL in accordance with the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a method of detecting and correcting communication errors in accordance with the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention now will be described more fully with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which several presently preferred embodiments of the invention are shown. This invention may, however, be embodied in various forms and should not be construed as limited to the embodiments set forth herein. Rather, these embodiments are provided so that this disclosure will be thorough and complete, and will fully convey the scope of the invention to those skilled in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Further details of an ESL system suitable for use in conjunction with the present invention are found in U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/044,021 filed Jan. 11, 2002 entitled “Methods and Apparatus for Performing Delta Updates of an Electronic Shelf Label”, U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/044,610 filed Jan. 11, 2002 entitled “Methods and Apparatus for Intelligent Data Bedcheck of an Electronic Shelf Label”, U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/044,020 filed Jan. 11, 2002 entitled “Methods and Apparatus for Reduced Electronic Shelf Label Power Consumption”, U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/044,439 filed Jan. 11, 2002 entitled “Methods and Apparatus for Automatically Locating an Electronic Shelf Label”, U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/044,440 filed Jan. 11, 2002 entitled “Methods and Apparatus for Conserving Battery Power in an Electronic Shelf Label System”, U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/044,688 filed Jan. 11, 2002 entitled “Methods and Apparatus for Automatic Assignment of a Communication Base Station and Timeslot for an Electronic Shelf Label”, U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/044,535 filed Jan. 11, 2002 entitled “Methods and Apparatus for Error Detection and Correction in an Electronic Shelf Label System”, all of which are assigned to the assignee of the present invention and incorporated by reference herein in their entirety.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a transaction management system <b>100</b> in accordance with the present invention. The system <b>100</b> includes an ESL computer system <b>102</b> and a point-of-service (POS) system <b>114</b>. Here, components <b>102</b> and <b>114</b> are shown as separate components that are networked together, but they and their subcomponents may also be combined or divided in various ways.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The host computer system <b>102</b> includes an ESL table <b>109</b>, spool tables <b>104</b>, data reader <b>108</b>, ESL manager <b>110</b>, a client application <b>106</b> and a communication base station (CBS) manager <b>112</b>. POS system <b>114</b> includes a price look-up (PLU) file <b>118</b> and POS terminals <b>116</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The system <b>100</b> also includes CBSs <b>120</b> and ESLs <b>122</b>. The CBSs <b>120</b> may be suitably mounted in or near the ceiling of the retail establishment. ESLs <b>122</b> are typically attached to store shelving adjacent to items.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The ESL manager <b>110</b> records and schedules messages to the ESLs <b>122</b>. The ESL manager <b>110</b> monitors and maintains an action list for the ESLs <b>122</b> utilizing spool tables <b>104</b>, and provides a scheduling function for time related events which need to occur at a future point at time. Items on the action list may be provided from client components as requests for work, may be automatically generated by the ESL manager <b>110</b>, or could be due to requests that required additional processing at a later date, such as, for example, a series of sale prices to be represented at the tags at given times. Based on the events the ESL manager <b>110</b> has scheduled for an ESL <b>122</b>, the ESL manager <b>110</b> creates the appropriate request and sends the request to the CBS manager <b>112</b>. The requests may include register or memory updates of an ESL <b>122</b>, diagnostic requests such as bedchecks, location requests such as finds, assignments to a particular timeslot, and the like. Based on the response returned from the ESL <b>122</b> via the CBS manager <b>120</b>, the ESL manager <b>112</b> then updates the ESL table <b>109</b> and spool tables <b>104</b> as appropriate. Such updates may include marking a particular task as completed, updating the data image of the ESL <b>122</b>, and the like. A client application, such as client application <b>106</b>, may interface with the ESL manager <b>110</b>. The data reader <b>108</b> provides an interface from the ESL manager <b>110</b> to the POS system <b>114</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The CBS manager <b>112</b> is responsible for all communications, processing, and monitoring of the CBSs. The CBS manager <b>112</b> receives information intended to be transmitted to the ESLs <b>122</b> and processes it into a form appropriate for use by the CBSs <b>120</b> and ESLs <b>122</b>. The CBS manager <b>112</b> processes the response of a particular ESL <b>122</b> after a CBS <b>120</b> has received that response and then passed that response to the CBS manager <b>112</b>. Additionally, the CBS manager <b>112</b> monitors the CBSs <b>120</b> for problems, performs diagnostics on the CBSs <b>120</b> and logs errors.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The messages are sent to the CBSs <b>120</b> through communication link <b>124</b>. Communication link <b>124</b> may suitably utilize radio frequency (RF) communication, infrared (IR) communication, a wired link, or some combination of communication techniques. After receiving a message from the host system <b>102</b>, the CBSs <b>120</b> then transmit the message to the ESLs <b>122</b> utilizing communication link <b>126</b>, which may suitably utilize RF communication, IR communication, a wired link or some combination of communication techniques. In an alternate embodiment, host system <b>102</b> may communicate directly with ESLs <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">After receiving a message, the ESLs <b>122</b> transmit a response to CBSs <b>120</b> over communication link <b>126</b>. The CBSs <b>120</b> would then process and retransmit the response message to the CBS manager <b>112</b> over communication link <b>124</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The ESL data file <b>109</b> consists of multiple records, with each record corresponding to a particular ESL <b>122</b> in a retail establishment. The record for each ESL <b>122</b> includes a number of fields, with each field containing the data which is supposed or assumed to be in one of the registers of the ESL <b>122</b>. Thus, the record contains a picture, or full data image, of what data is intended to be stored in the ESL <b>122</b>, and consequently, what the ESL <b>122</b> should be displaying on the ESL's display. Additionally, each record may include a variety of additional non-display information related to the ESL <b>122</b>, such as the timeslot the ESL <b>122</b> listens on, the CBS <b>120</b> assigned to the ESL <b>122</b>, and the PLU number of the item associated with the ESL <b>122</b>. The record may also contain diagnostic and tally information related to that ESL <b>122</b>, such as when the last time a message was sent to the ESL <b>122</b>, the last time the ESL <b>122</b> had a data bedcheck, a count of how many times the ESL <b>122</b> has failed its data bedcheck, and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a block diagram of an exemplary ESL <b>122</b> in accordance with the present invention. A display <b>202</b> displays information, such as item price and related data. ESL <b>122</b> includes a transmitter <b>206</b> for transmitting messages and a receiver <b>207</b> for receiving messages. The transmitter <b>206</b> and receiver <b>207</b> may utilize RF communication, IR communication, a wired link or some combination of communication techniques. A battery <b>208</b> provides power for the operation of ESL <b>122</b>. The operation of ESL <b>122</b> is controlled by ESL circuitry <b>204</b>. ESL circuitry <b>204</b> decodes incoming messages received, and performs any actions indicated by the messages. For example, if a price change message is received, the ESL circuitry <b>204</b> would cause the display <b>202</b> to be updated with the new price information. ESL memory <b>210</b> includes a plurality of registers, such as registers <b>210</b><i>a</i>, <b>210</b><i>b</i>, . . . , <b>210</b><i>c</i>. The ESL memory <b>210</b> may contain many types of information. For example, the memory <b>210</b> may include display registers which contain the actual text to be displayed by the ESL <b>122</b>. This text may include item price, informative or promotional text, text directed to store employees, and the like. Other registers may contain data which controls various parameters related to the display of the text, such as display register selection and timing sequences, for example. The ESL <b>122</b> may also include a button <b>212</b> which may be depressed to initiate a particular function, such as, for example, the display of an alternate message.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">When the host computer <b>102</b> sends a message, such as a register update message, to an ESL <b>122</b>, the ESL <b>122</b> responds with a positive acknowledgement (ACK) message if the register update message was successfully received. While communication between the host computer <b>102</b>, or CBSs <b>120</b>, and the ESLs is quite reliable, occasionally noise or other interference may cause the host computer <b>102</b> to detect an ACK message when a negative acknowledgement (NACK) message, or no response at all, was transmitted by the ESL <b>122</b>. Such an error, or false positive, may cause the host computer <b>102</b> to believe an ESL is correctly displaying information, when in actuality the ESL <b>122</b> is not displaying the correct information due to the register update message not being correctly received by the ESL <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The present invention provides an ESL system and method that automatically detects ESL communication errors which result in the ESL containing incorrect data in the ESL's registers, and then automatically takes corrective action to update the ESL's memory with the correct data. In one aspect, the host computer <b>102</b> transmits a register update message to an ESL <b>122</b>. If a NACK message or no response is received, then the host computer may resend the register update message, log an error message to a human operator, or take other such action in accordance with the retail establishment's operating procedure. If the host computer <b>102</b> receives an ACK message, or what appears to be an ACK message, the host computer <b>102</b> then automatically transmits one or more messages to the ESL <b>122</b> to verify the contents of the ESL's registers.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In a preferred embodiment, one or more bedcheck messages may be transmitted by the host computer <b>102</b> to the ESL <b>122</b> which verifies that the data contained in the ESLs registers matches the data for that ESL contained in a host computer file, such as the ESL data file <b>109</b>. Each data bedcheck message contains a sumcheck or error checking code, such as a cyclical redundancy check (CRC), of register data in the ESL data file <b>109</b>. In other words, the sumcheck is a number calculated using the register data in the host computer file which corresponds to the data which should be stored in the registers of ESL <b>122</b>. The data bedcheck message requests that the ESL compare the received sumcheck with a sumcheck calculated using the data actually contained in the ESL. If the received sumcheck matches the calculated sumcheck, the ESL <b>122</b> responds to the data bedcheck message with an ACK. If the received sumcheck does not match the calculated sumcheck, the ESL <b>122</b> responds to the data bedcheck message with a NACK.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">If a NACK message or no response is received in response to the bedcheck message, then the host computer <b>102</b> assumes that the first ACK was an error or a “false positive.” The host computer <b>102</b> may then retransmit the register update message, log an error message to a human operator, or take other such action in accordance with the retail establishment's operating procedure. If a NACK message or no response is received in response to the retransmitted message, the host computer may then provide an error indication to a human operator indicating an ESL communication problem.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">If an ACK message is received in response to the bedcheck message, then the host computer <b>102</b> assumes that the first ACK was a valid acknowledgment and no further action is taken.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In a typical retail environment, the host computer <b>102</b> transmits messages to and receives responses from a plurality of ESLs <b>122</b>. The host computer may log the number of “false positives” received from each of the plurality of ESLs <b>122</b> over a period of time in order to provide a statistical record of which ESLs <b>122</b> may be more prone to communication failure. For example, if a store averages one “false positive” per ESL <b>122</b> per month and communication with a particular ESL <b>122</b> in that store results in 15 false positives per month, the host computer may provide an error indication to the system operator. The system operator may then take action to determine the source of the communication problem.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a method <b>300</b> of automatically detecting and correcting communication errors in an ESL system in accordance with the present invention. In step <b>302</b>, a computer system, such as host computer system <b>102</b>, transmits a message, such as a register update message, to an ESL. In step <b>304</b>, the host computer waits for a response to be transmitted from the ESL. If a NACK message or no response is received by the host computer system, then the method continues to step <b>306</b>. In step <b>306</b>, the host computer takes some form of corrective action, such as resending the register update message, logging an error message to a human operator, or other such action in accordance with the retail establishment's operating procedure. If an ACK message, or what appears to be an ACK message, is received by the host computer system in step <b>304</b>, the method continues to step <b>308</b>. In step <b>308</b>, the host computer automatically transmits one or more messages to the ESL to verify the contents of the ESL's registers. In a preferred embodiment, a bedcheck message may be transmitted to the ESL to verify that the contents of the ESL's registers match the data for that ESL contained in the host computer system. In step <b>310</b>, the host computer waits for a response. If a NACK message or no response is received by the host computer system, then the method continues to step <b>306</b>. If an ACK message is received by the host computer system in step <b>310</b>, the method continues to step <b>312</b>. In step <b>312</b>, the host computer logs the original message as successfully sent.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">At optional sten <b>314</b>, steps <b>302</b> through <b>312</b> are repeated a plurality of times. At optional step <b>316</b>, statistical data is tabulated of the number of times a negative acknowledgement or no response was received. At optional step <b>318</b>, if the number exceeds a threshold, an error indication is provided.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">It will be apparent to those skilled in the art that various modifications and variations can be made in the present invention without departing from the spirit and scope of the present invention. Thus, it is intended that the present invention cover the modifications and variations of this invention provided they come within the scope of the appended claims and their equivalents. For example, while a presently preferred embodiment utilizes an ESL to display informational text or price of an associated item, an ESL system may utilize ESLs in a variety of applications and environments without departing from the spirit and scope of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of automatically validating the contents of an electronic shelf label's (ESL's) registers in order to detect and correct communication errors, the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>wirelessly transmitting a verification message to verify that the contents of the electronic shelf label's registers match an expected content after transmission of an initial message and receipt of a response interpreted as a positive acknowledgement;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wirelessly receiving a response to the verification message verifying the contents of the registers match the expected content; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>logging an indication that the initial message was successfully received in response to the received response.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the expected contents are maintained by a host computer communicating with an electronic shelf label.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>retransmitting the initial message in response to the received response indicating that the contents of the ESL's registers do not match the expected contents.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>providing an indication of a communication problem in response to a negative acknowledgement or receiving no response to the retransmitted initial message.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the initial message is a command to update at least one of the ESL's registers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the verification message is a data bedcheck message.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the step of transmitting a verification message immediately follows the receipt of a positive acknowledgement acknowledging the transmitted initial message.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An electronic shelf label (ESL) system comprising:
<claim-text>an ESL for displaying information relating to an item associated with the ESL, the ESL including a plurality of registers for storing data, the data including information to be displayed by the ESL and parameters used by the ESL to control presentation and formatting of the information displayed; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a host computer system wirelessly transmitting a verification message to verify the contents of the ESL's registers in response to a transmitted initial message and receipt of a response interpreted as a positive acknowledgement of the initial message, the host computer wirelessly receiving a response to the verification message, the host computer determining whether the response to the verification message indicates that the contents of the ESL's registers match the expected contents as maintained by the host computer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the received response to the verification message is a positive acknowledgement, the host computer logging the transmitted initial message as successfully received.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the transmitted initial message is a command to update at least one of the ESL's registers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the verification message is a data bedcheck message.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method of determining when there is a communication failure with an electronic shelf label (ESL), the ESL having registers storing data maintained by a host system, the method comprising:
<claim-text>wirelessly transmitting a verification message to verify that the contents of an electronic shelf label's registers match an expected content after transmission of an initial message and receipt of a response interpreted as a positive acknowledgement;</claim-text>
<claim-text>waiting for an acknowledgement of the verification message; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wirelessly transmitting a register update message to the ESL to update its registers in response to a negative acknowledgement or after a timer expires and no response has been received by the host computer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>logging the transmitted initial message as successfully received in response to the acknowledgement indicating that the contents of the ESL's registers match the expected contents as maintained by the host computer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>tabulating statistical data of the number of times negative acknowledgements were received or no response was received.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>providing an error indication if the number exceeds a threshold.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
