<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298969-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298969</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11000779</doc-number>
<date>20041201</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>220</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>17</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>225</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396 28</main-classification>
<further-classification>396427</further-classification>
<further-classification>396428</further-classification>
<further-classification>348373</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Housing with camera and illuminator for fence and security observation</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0093805</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Gin</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>725105</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0119881</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Matko et al.</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348375</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>22</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396 12</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396 25</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396 28</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396175</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396419</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396427</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396428</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362152</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348143</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348159</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348373-375</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>352242</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>352243</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>10</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>33</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060115265</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060601</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Elberbaum</last-name>
<first-name>David</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Katten Muchin Rosenman LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Elbex Video Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Perkey</last-name>
<first-name>W. B.</first-name>
<department>2862</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Suthar</last-name>
<first-name>Rishi S.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An upright camera housing having an adjustable pan position and an upright front pane for at least one camera with adjustable lens and tilt includes a mount for installing the housing onto a vertical structure and for attaching the mount to the housing by fasteners at the horizontal axis of the housing. An adjustable tilt is provided for the camera within the interior of said housing through a screw guided movable slider driven by first adjustment tool and linked to said at least one camera and wherein said adjustment tool is accessed through first sealed access of said housing. An adjustable lens is provided for each camera for manual adjustment and remote control adjustment. A manual adjustment is accessed by second adjustment tool through a second sealed access of the housing and the remote control adjustment being provided by one geared motor.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="155.19mm" wi="99.48mm" file="US07298969-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="247.73mm" wi="184.49mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="266.11mm" wi="199.73mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="250.95mm" wi="190.08mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="237.74mm" wi="140.29mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="240.62mm" wi="187.11mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="244.69mm" wi="171.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="221.49mm" wi="139.62mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="250.44mm" wi="164.25mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="221.32mm" wi="109.73mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="249.77mm" wi="179.15mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298969-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention is related to closed circuit television and other observation cameras and their casing and to IR or other illuminators and their casings used for day-night observation of fences and other security installation.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Priort Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Cameras for closed circuit television, network cameras and other digital cameras used for fence observation are mounted inside an outdoor housings on top of the fence's pole or post for observing the fence from top, whereby, the angle of view of the observed fence is determined by the lens, the height of the pole or post and the housing's vertical tilt and horizontal coordinates. Long fences, such as border fences between countries, are extended over mountains and valleys and are not structured in straight lines and the observation of the fences therefore, requires many compromises relating to the angle of view.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">For example, the viewing of fence details calls for narrow-angle lens, which depicts the fence as a larger object onto the monitor screen, but which cuts portions of a fence section from the optical path of the camera and the viewed scene. On the other hand, the observation of a complete section of a fence such as between two poles calls for wider-angle lens, which depicts the fence on a monitor as a smaller object of a wider viewed area.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">These two conflicting limitations, the observation of the fence details versus the observation of the entire section of a fence is a major compromise issue, whereby it calls for a consideration of giving up on fence details or allowing portion of the fence to be left unobserved.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Moreover, the lens' angle of view limitations are coupled with landscape limitations due to the terrain and the elevation of the poles or posts of the fence, as well as the bend sections or corners of a stretched fence, all of which greatly compels the positioning of the housing's tilt and pan coordinates in line with the landscape. This landscape limitation further inhibits or prevents altogether the viewing of a complete individual section between two poles of a given fence.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The unavoidable lens compromise and the positioning limitation of the housing pan-tilt coordinates, because of the landscape, regularly leaves portions of the fence uncovered by the surveillance cameras. These uncovered sections are known as blind stretches, blind sections or blind spots.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Further, camera and illuminator housings mounted on poles above the fence are prone to vandalism or destruction by intruders at distances far from the fence itself, thereby, increasing the risks of intruder defeating the fence observation system, particularly at night.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">It is an object of the present invention to provide a camera system and illuminator system that are embedded inside or attached to the pole or post of a fence for observing the whole section of a fence without leaving blind spots between the two poles of the section.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A “fence section” in the following descriptions is a stretch of a fence between two adjacent fence poles.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">“Poles” in the following description are poles, posts, columns, or pillars made of steel or any other metal, or wood, or concrete, or other solid material and are fabricated, or assembled, or cemented, or molded, or injected structure.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">“Camera” in the following description is a color or black/white closed circuit television camera, or color or black/white Digital camera or color or black/white Web camera, mounted inside the one or more outdoor housing.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">“IR” in the following description relates to InfraRed illumination spectrum or band longer than 700 nm and which is not visible to human eyes.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">“IR camera” in the following description is a camera having no IR cut filter in its optical path, thereby enabling the camera to observe dark scenes exposed to IR illumination.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">“Day-night camera” in the following description is a camera with built mechanism for removing and reinserting an IR cut filter from its optical path for enabling the camera to observe at night time dark scenes exposed to IR illumination and for observing day light scenes undisturbed by IR.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">“B/W” in the following description refers to Black and White.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">This and other objects of the present invention are attained by one or more outdoor housing for one or more camera and one or more illuminator with an adjustable tilting facilities for the camera and/or the illuminator within the housing interior and adjustable panning facilities for the housing within the confine of the pole interior. The one or more camera may be provided with a fixed focal length lens or with an adjustable zoom or varifocal lens that can be adjusted manually while the housing is mounted inside a pole or attached to the pole or remotely by using a remotely controlled motorized zoom or varifocal lens.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The housing may include day-night camera for switching over automatically or upon command from day light observation to dark scene observation, such as during night time, using IR illuminator.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Alternatively, two or more cameras can be included in the housing, such as color camera, B/W camera and IR camera with the cameras being connected to a switchover circuit, which is activated by a light sensor for operating any of the cameras on the basis of the amount of light and/or the light spectrum, thereby enabling color or B/W observation in day time and IR observation during night time.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The switchover circuit further switches on the IR illuminator for darkness observation or it switches on a visual spectrum illuminators for color or B/W observation during nighttime.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The tilting adjusting mechanism is linked to all the cameras, such that all the cameras are directed to the same tilting coordinate, thereby, a switchover of observation from one camera to another will not change the observed scene.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">When the housing interior combines an IR or other illuminators, the tilting link can be extended between the cameras and the illuminator as well, so as to ensure that the illuminator is directed to the same scene corresponding to the camera pan-tilt coordinates.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Alternatively, the one or more illuminators may be installed into same or a separate housing and be adjusted individually in accordance with the landscape and/or for preventing direct light reflections by the fence from reaching the lens and/or the optical path of the camera.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">By this arrangement, with the one or more housings containing the one or more cameras and the one or more illuminators, all embedded and installed inside the poles or attached to the poles and positioned toward the adjacent pole, for observing the fence stretch between the two adjacent poles, can provide for observation of the entire section of the fence. Moreover, since the housing are embedded into or attached to the poles, the housing including the cameras and the illuminators are protected by the pole structure and therefore, cannot be vandalized or defeated from far, which improves greatly the camera reability to observe and detect intruders.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The foregoing and other objects and features of the present invention will become apparent from the following description of preferred embodiments of the invention with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a fence structure including the cameras and illuminators of the present invention and of the prior art;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A</figref>, <b>2</b>B and <b>2</b>C are perspective views of the cameras with an illuminator and the housing and with adjustment facilities for the pan-tilt and focus of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A</figref>, <b>3</b>B and <b>3</b>C are side views of the cameras tilt and focus adjustment;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A</figref>, <b>4</b>B and <b>4</b>C are perspective views of manual adjustment and remote control adjustment of motorized zoom or varifocal lens;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A</figref>, <b>5</b>B, <b>5</b>C, <b>5</b>D, <b>5</b>E, <b>5</b>F, <b>5</b>G and <b>5</b>H are perspective views of different cameras and illuminators combinations of the preferred embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A</figref>, <b>6</b>B and <b>6</b>C are perspective views of the illuminators of the present invention with housing and with the pan-tilt adjustment and locking facilities for each individual illuminator;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A and 7B</figref> are perspective views of the locking and unlocking mechanism and of the adjustment of another preferred embodiment of the illuminator of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8A</figref>, <b>8</b>B, <b>8</b>C and <b>8</b>D are side views of the tilting adjustment range for the illuminators of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A</figref>, <b>9</b>B and <b>9</b>C are top views of the panning adjustment range for the illuminators of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10A</figref>, <b>10</b>B and <b>10</b>C are perspective views of the housing assemblies with different design for providing improved architectural appearance.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a fence <b>1</b> constructed of poles <b>10</b> and wire <b>11</b> or barbed wire <b>1</b>A, stretched over a terrain. Adjacent to the fence are light poles <b>15</b> for supporting illuminators <b>13</b> and close circuit television camera <b>12</b> mounted on a well known camera mount <b>12</b>A for adjusting the housing's pan-tilt coordinates, for directing the cameras to observe the fence. The cameras <b>12</b> are typical example of the prior art for observing fences. However the terrain and the angle of view of the camera's lenses and/or the height of the light poles <b>15</b> forces many limitations with the pan-tilt-lens coordinate positioning of the cameras <b>12</b> and its ability to view the entire section of a fence.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The camera <b>2</b> of the present invention shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, mounted inside the pole <b>10</b>-<b>1</b>, the camera <b>5</b>B attached to the pole <b>10</b>-<b>2</b> along with the illuminator <b>5</b>G, the camera <b>5</b>C mounted into the pole <b>10</b>-<b>3</b> along with the illuminator <b>6</b>C, the camera <b>2</b> mounted into the pole <b>10</b>-<b>4</b>, the camera <b>5</b>A mounted into the pole <b>10</b>-<b>5</b> along with the illuminator <b>6</b>C, the camera <b>5</b>D mounted into the pole <b>10</b>-<b>6</b> and the camera <b>5</b>E mounted into the pole <b>10</b>-<b>7</b> are all positioned to observe an entire section of the fence regardless of the terrain and the angle of view of the lens. It will become obvious, including from the shown fence <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> that regardless of the lens' angle of view the cameras of the present invention, which are mounted into the pole or attached to the pole, and aimed toward the adjacent pole can view the entire section of the fence, unlike the cameras and housings of the prior art that could not be mounted into or attached to the pole.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The prior art housing has a longer horizontal structure such as the shown housing <b>12</b>, which cannot be installed inside the poles, moreover, an important adjustments for the camera in the field is the adjustment of the focus and/or the varifocal or zoom ring and which cannot be carried out if the housing is installed inside the pole. In the prior art the adjustment of the focus ring is carried by removing the cover of the housing <b>12</b> for accessing the camera or the lens itself. This will be impossible if the housing of the prior art would have been installed inside a pole of the fence.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Further, the pan/tilt mount <b>12</b>A attaching the camera housing <b>12</b> to the light pole <b>15</b> of the prior art is attached to the housing bottom, thereby the only way to attach the prior art camera <b>12</b> to the pole <b>10</b> will be by attaching it through a pan/tilt mount <b>12</b>A to the top of the pole <b>10</b>, this introduces the angle of view limitation and terrain limitation, leaving blind spots within the section view.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In order to install an outdoor camera housing inside poles, the housing system must be vertically structured, it must be sealed to prevent water from leaking into the housing, moreover the housing must be so constructed as to permit field adjustments of the focus or zoom ring and the adjustment of pan and tilt without dismantling the housing assembly. Moreover, if multiple cameras are installed inside the housing all should be adjusted simultaneously to the same direction for observing the same scene, thereby, providing identical viewing scene whenever a camera is switched over, such as from color to B/W or to IR, so that the scene displayed on a monitor or recorded by video or digital recorder remains the same.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is the camera assembly <b>2</b>H<b>1</b> including color camera <b>21</b>, B/W camera <b>22</b>, IR camera <b>23</b> and illuminator <b>29</b>. Each of the cameras includes geared focus ring <b>2</b>F for enabling the adjustment of the focus ring using a driver <b>2</b>F<b>4</b> with a soft rounded gear <b>2</b>F<b>5</b>, the driver's front end is supported by the guide hole <b>2</b>F<b>3</b> during the focus adjustment. It is however possible to use for example a rubber roller instead of the rounded soft gear <b>2</b>F<b>5</b> of the focus adjustment driver <b>2</b>F<b>4</b>. Moreover, it is also possible to adjust the focus ring without the use of the guide hole <b>2</b>F<b>3</b>. The person adjusting the focus ring using the driver <b>2</b>F<b>4</b> with rubber roller (not shown) replacing the gear <b>2</b>F<b>5</b> can adjust the focus ring by applying slight force and pressure the roller or the gear <b>2</b>F<b>5</b> to engage the focus ring <b>2</b>F while rotating the driver <b>2</b>F<b>4</b> for adjusting the focus.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">It is also possible to support the driver through the focus adjustment opening <b>2</b>F<b>1</b> of the camera housing <b>2</b>H as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>. Since the focus and the zoom rings rarely needs to be re-adjusted after installation, the geared portion of the focus or zoom rings and of the gear <b>2</b>F<b>5</b> of the adjustment driver, or a rubber roller (not shown) replacing the gear <b>2</b>F<b>5</b>, need not to be precise and accurate. It is only necessary to engage the geared edge focus ring <b>2</b>F or the zoom ring <b>2</b>Z with the gear <b>2</b>F<b>5</b> or with the rubber roller instead, such that while a serviceman is rotating the driver <b>2</b>F<b>4</b> or <b>2</b>Z<b>4</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> or the driver <b>2</b>F<b>4</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> will rotate with it the focus or zoom ring, which commonly require very slight force.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The camera assembly further includes an illuminator <b>29</b>, light sensing and switchover circuit <b>2</b>S<b>3</b> including two sensors <b>2</b>S<b>1</b> and <b>2</b>S<b>2</b>. Also incorporated in the camera assembly <b>2</b>H<b>1</b> is a tilting adjustment facilities including tilting adjustment screw <b>2</b>T<b>2</b>, tilting base <b>2</b>T<b>8</b>, tilting slider <b>2</b>T<b>7</b> and tilting links <b>2</b>L, <b>2</b>L<b>1</b> and <b>2</b>L<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The cameras <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> and <b>23</b> and the illuminator <b>29</b> are supported by a camera support <b>2</b>C having its center rotation <b>2</b>C<b>1</b>, through which the cameras and the illuminator are attached to the assembly <b>2</b>H<b>1</b> chassis via holes <b>2</b>C<b>4</b> in its right side <b>2</b>H<b>4</b>, and in its left side <b>2</b>H<b>3</b> using the screws <b>2</b>C<b>2</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> the screws <b>2</b>C<b>2</b> are collard screws having a collar <b>2</b>C<b>3</b> that is thicker than the thickness of the left side chassis <b>2</b>H<b>3</b> or the right side chassis <b>2</b>H<b>4</b> for enabling free tilting movement for the camera support <b>2</b>C even when the screws <b>2</b>C<b>2</b> are tightly fastened.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The tilting base <b>2</b>T<b>8</b> is attached to the bottom cover <b>2</b>B of the camera assembly <b>2</b>H<b>1</b>, which also support the two sides <b>2</b>H<b>3</b> and <b>2</b>H<b>4</b> of the chassis assembly. The tilting adjusting screw <b>2</b>T<b>2</b> passes through the two holes <b>2</b>T<b>9</b> and through threaded holes <b>2</b>T<b>10</b> of the tilting slider <b>2</b>T<b>7</b>. The tilting screw is secured to the tilting base by a locking ring <b>2</b>T<b>6</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A˜3C</figref>. By this arrangement the rotating of the tilting adjusting screw <b>2</b>T<b>2</b> clockwise will move the slider <b>2</b>T<b>7</b> all the way to the front of tilt base <b>2</b>T<b>8</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, while counter clockwise rotation will move the slider <b>2</b>T<b>7</b> all the way to the back of the tilt base <b>2</b>T<b>8</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref>, and any random rotating of the tilting adjusting screw <b>2</b>T<b>2</b> will move the slider <b>2</b>T<b>7</b> to a position along the screw <b>2</b>T<b>2</b> within the tilting base <b>2</b>T<b>8</b> movement range as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The tilting slider <b>2</b>T<b>7</b> is attached to a link <b>2</b>L using screw <b>2</b>L<b>3</b>, the link <b>2</b>L is attached to the camera support <b>2</b>C of camera <b>23</b> and to a link <b>2</b>L<b>1</b> using another screw <b>2</b>L<b>3</b>. The screw <b>2</b>L<b>3</b> shown is a collard screw, similar to the screws <b>2</b>C<b>2</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, for providing spacing between the links <b>2</b>L<b>1</b> and <b>2</b>L and between the link <b>2</b>L and the tilting movements slider <b>2</b>T<b>7</b> in order to enable free tilting even when the screws <b>2</b>L<b>3</b> are tightly fastened. The link <b>2</b>L<b>1</b> is further linked to the camera support <b>2</b>C of camera <b>22</b> and to another link <b>2</b>L<b>1</b>-<b>1</b>, which is further linked to camera support <b>2</b>C of camera <b>22</b>. The link <b>2</b>L<b>1</b>-<b>1</b> is attached to camera support <b>2</b>C of camera <b>21</b> and to a link <b>2</b>L<b>2</b> for linking to camera holder <b>2</b>C of the illuminator <b>29</b>. All the links <b>2</b>L<b>1</b>, <b>2</b>L<b>1</b>-<b>1</b> and <b>2</b>L<b>2</b> are attached to their respective camera support <b>2</b>C using collard screw <b>2</b>L<b>3</b>, which can be tightly fastened and provide free movements between the links and the camera supports <b>2</b>C.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The camera support <b>2</b>C is attached by two collard screws <b>2</b>C<b>2</b> to the two sides of the chassis, <b>2</b>H<b>3</b> left and <b>2</b>H<b>4</b> right through the holes <b>2</b>C<b>4</b> and <b>2</b>C<b>5</b> shown in the camera assembly chassis of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>. The threaded hole <b>2</b>C<b>1</b> of the camera support is the camera's or the illuminator's tilting movement center. By linking all the camera's and the illuminator supports <b>2</b>C to the tilting slider <b>2</b>T<b>7</b> through the links <b>2</b>L, <b>2</b>L<b>1</b>, <b>2</b>L<b>1</b>-<b>1</b> and <b>2</b>L<b>2</b> enables the adjustment of all the camera's and the illuminator tilting around the tilting movement centers <b>2</b>C<b>1</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A</figref>, <b>3</b>B and <b>3</b>C through the tilting adjustment screw <b>2</b>T<b>2</b> using the tilting screwdriver <b>2</b>T<b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The housing <b>2</b>H shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> includes a front pane <b>2</b>G, which has wider opening at its upper portion for providing the illuminator <b>29</b> with wider angle emission, commensurating with the angle of light emission that is preferable to be wider than the lens's angle of view, for illuminating the entire viewed scene observed by the cameras <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> and <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The housing <b>2</b>H shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> further includes six focus and/or zoom adjustment access holes with thread <b>2</b>F<b>1</b>, five focus access holes are shown sealed with sealing screws <b>2</b>F<b>2</b>. Similarly the tilting adjustment access hole with thread <b>2</b>T<b>1</b> is shown with its sealing screw <b>2</b>T removed. As the housing for fences must be sealed to prevent water from leaking into the housing, each of the sealing screws <b>2</b>F<b>2</b> and <b>2</b>T includes seal, alternatively the seal is attached to the surface of the adjustment opening access <b>2</b>F<b>1</b> and <b>2</b>T. Similarly the front pane <b>2</b>G is sealed throughout, along with the bottom cover <b>2</b>B shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The entire camera/housing assembly <b>2</b> is supported by two, top and bottom, panning brackets <b>2</b>H<b>2</b>, via two panning locking screws <b>2</b>P. Different shaped panning brackets <b>2</b>H<b>2</b> can be used, such as for attaching the brackets to the side of the pole, or specially constructed brackets to fit the brackets with the inner structure of a given pole. Alternatively, the two partly shown brackets <b>2</b>H<b>2</b> can be part of a single pole or wall mount for attaching the housing to a vertical structure such as the mount <b>2</b>H<b>2</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>. But regardless of the exact shape of the bracket <b>2</b>H<b>2</b>, it is obvious that the entire vertically structured camera/housing assembly <b>2</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> can be rotated to the left and the right about the panning axis of the assembly, represented by the panning locking screws <b>2</b>P.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">By this it become obvious that the pan and tilt of the camera/housing assembly <b>2</b> can be adjusted within the interior of a pole, or when the assembly <b>2</b> is attached to a pole and that the focus and/or the zoom rings of the lens can be accessed and adjusted without dismantling the housing. Further, to protect the camera assemblies inside the pole it is preferable to cut the smallest possible window for the camera and/or the illuminator. This is also because larger cut window reduces the structural strength of the pole and exposes the camera to acts of vandalism. On the other hand a smaller cut window may prevent free access to the focus adjustment screws <b>2</b>F<b>2</b>, because the access to the screws <b>2</b>F<b>2</b> is dependent upon the panning coordinate position setting, wherein a smaller window may cover, for example, the left side focus access screws <b>2</b>F<b>2</b> of a camera that is positioned to the left. For this reason two set of focus access screws <b>2</b>F<b>2</b> are provided for each camera <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> or <b>23</b> of the camera/housing assembly <b>2</b>. By such arrangement the right side access screws <b>2</b>F<b>2</b> are used for camera assembly <b>2</b> positioned to the left, and the left side access screws <b>2</b>F<b>2</b> are used for camera assembly positioned to the right, and this enables a smaller window size to be cut in the poles.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The light sensing circuit <b>2</b>S<b>3</b> uses well known light sensors, such as photo diodes or photo transistors having broad or limited sensitivities for a specific visual light spectrum, or UV, or to IR. The sensors may include a well known optical pass or cut filters to match the sensors spectrum with the surrounding illuminators, or for example to match the sensor with an IR illuminator of the camera assembly <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The light sensing circuit <b>2</b>S<b>3</b> further includes well known switching circuits or relays for switching over the camera's video or digital signals from one selected camera to another, on the basis of the sensing signals and/or may further include well known CPU or timer circuit for setting specific operation schedule, on the basis of time and date, all of which are based on well known technique for selecting the correct camera <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> or <b>23</b> for the correct application. The connecting wires and cables for the camera assembly <b>2</b> are not shown, as they are very well known as well.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">By this it becomes clear and obvious that the camera/housing assembly <b>2</b> can be attached to a pole, or installed inside a pole for observing the whole length of a section of a fence, this is further enhanced by adjusting the camera panning and tilting coordinates toward the adjacent fence pole. It is further obvious that the focus and/or zoom or varifocal rings can be accessed and adjusted while the housing is mounted, without disassembling the housing and that the access holes can be sealed and that the camera remains protected from rain or snow and better secured from vandalism and destruction.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> the cameras <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> or <b>23</b> may include one or two geared motors for remotely adjusting the focus ring and/or the varifocal or zoom lens. The focus motor <b>25</b> with its geared shaft is attached to the camera <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> or <b>23</b> body having its gear <b>25</b>A engaged with the focus ring <b>2</b>F. The varifocal or zoom motor <b>26</b> with its geared shaft is attached to the camera <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> or <b>25</b> body, having its gear <b>26</b>A engaged with the varifocal or zoom ring <b>2</b>Z. The one or two motors <b>25</b> and <b>26</b> used with the camera <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> or <b>23</b> are operated by variety of well known remote control devices that drive the motors either clockwise or counter clockwise to obtain the best focus under any of the illuminators environment and the correct angle of view through the varifocal or zoom adjustment.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The camera assembly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> therefore requires no focus access hole <b>2</b>F<b>1</b>, nor the focus access screw <b>2</b>F<b>2</b>, and the housing shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> does not include the focus access arrangement.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">In a further embodiment, an upright camera housing with at adjustable pan position and with upright front pane for at least one camera with adjustable lens and tilt comprising a mount for installing said housing onto a vertical structure selected from a group consisting of a pole, column, post, pillar and a wall and for attaching said mount to said housing by fasteners at said housing horizontal axis for enabling the adjustment and the locking of said adjustable pan position around said horizontal axis; an adjustment tilt for said at least one camera within the interior of said housing through a screw guided movable slider driven by first adjustment tool and linked to said at least one camera and wherein said adjustment tool is accessed through first sealed access of said housing; an adjustable lens for each said camera selected from a group comprising a fixed focal lens, varifocal lens and zoom lens including at least one adjustable ring selected from a group consisting of focus ring, varifocal ring, zoom ring and a combination thereof, for providing adjustment of said adjustable ring selected from a group consisting of manual adjustment and remote control adjustment; wherein said manual adjustment is accessed by second adjustment tool through at least one second sealed access of said housing for engaging and adjusting said adjustable ring and wherein said remote control adjustment is provided by at least one geared motor engaged to said at least one adjustable ring; and wherein said first sealed access and said second sealed access can be opened for adjustment and re-sealed after adjustment.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">In yet a further embodiment, an upright illuminator housing with at least one illuminator with adjustable pan and tilt within the interior of said housing comprising; a mount for installing said housing onto a vertical structure selected from a group consisting of a pole, column, post, pillar and a wail, wherein said mount can be attached by fasteners to said housing at its horizontal axis for enabling the adjustment and the locking of said housing pan position around said horizontal axis; each said illuminator is attached by dual fasteners at its tilting axis to a panning frame and said panning frame is attached by a fastener at its panning axis of one side and by dual semi circle blocks at its panning axis of the opposite side to a support assembly; said support assembly is mourned inside said housing and includes dual jaws each having cutout for accommodating said dual semi circle blocks and a vise screw for vising said dual send circle blocks between said jaws; said panning frame is cut open at its panning axis of said opposite side with each of the open cut is attached to one of said semi circle blocks, such that a whole circle block is introduced into said cutouts of said dual jaws, wherein said frame become loose around said illuminator and about its panning axis when said vise screw is released, thereby enabling to manually adjust the pan and tilt of said illuminator, and tightly locked onto said illuminator and about its panning axis when said vise screw is tightly vising said dual semi circle blocks between said jaws; and an open window of said housing provides open accesses for said at least one illuminator and for manually adjusting the pan and tilt direction of said illuminator and for a driver to lock and unlock said vise screw.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">As explained the camera and housing assembly <b>2</b> includes color, B/W and IR cameras <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> and <b>23</b> and a single illuminator <b>29</b>. However, depending on the application and the specific needs for a given observation of a fence it may be necessary to separate the illuminator <b>29</b> from the camera assembly <b>2</b> and moreover, it may be unnecessary to include three cameras inside the housing <b>2</b>H. For example it may be sufficient to have a single camera for the fence observation with a larger power illuminator, such as with triple illuminators <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a fence camera assembly including a single camera housing <b>5</b>A and day-night or IR camera <b>23</b>. The housing <b>5</b>B of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is for dual camera, such as the shown color camera <b>21</b> and B/W camera <b>22</b>, while the housing <b>5</b>C shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref> is for three cameras. Similarly, the housing <b>5</b>D of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5D</figref> includes a single camera <b>23</b> and a single illuminator <b>29</b>, while the housing <b>5</b>E of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5E</figref> includes two cameras <b>21</b> and <b>22</b> and a single illuminator <b>29</b>. The housing <b>5</b>H of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5H</figref> on the other hand incorporates no camera, but instead it incorporates three illuminators <b>29</b>, while the housing <b>5</b>G incorporates two illuminator <b>29</b> and no camera. The housing <b>5</b>F of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5F</figref> incorporates only a single illuminator <b>29</b>. It is obvious however that by extending the vertical length of the housing it is possible to install any practical number of cameras and/or illuminators in the housing assembly of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The common to all the housing <b>5</b>A, <b>5</b>B, <b>5</b>C, <b>5</b>D, <b>5</b>E, <b>5</b>F, <b>5</b>G and <b>5</b>H is that they all incorporate tilting adjustment mechanism for adjusting one or two, three or more cameras or adjusting the tilting of one, two or more cameras combined with one, two or more illuminator, or for adjusting the tiling of one, two, three or more illuminators. Any type of camera can be employed in the housing assembly of the present inventions, be it color, B/W, IR or day-night, similarly any type of illuminator can be employed such as visual spectrum illuminator, IR illuminator, UV illuminator for illuminating the scene with specific or wide spectrum.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Different sensors <b>2</b>S<b>1</b> and <b>2</b>S<b>2</b> of the sensing circuit <b>2</b>S<b>3</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> such as IR, UV or visual spectrum can be used and employed along with any type of cut or pass through optical filters to match with the selected cameras and illuminator. Further the sensors and filters can be selected on the basis of the specific fence being observed and the surrounding illumination environment.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Moreover, the housing assembly with its adjustment facilities for pan, tilt, focus and varifocal or zoom can be conveniently installed on walls of buildings, both indoors and outdoor and used for variety of security applications other than for fence observation. Long vertical structure that can be attached to a surface of a wall, pole and other vertical structures offer many advantages, such as improved housing stability and architectural harmony with the building's exterior and interior.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The housing <b>2</b>H shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> and the housings <b>5</b>A˜<b>5</b>H of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A˜5H</figref> are box type casing, however any other shape such as round housing <b>60</b>, oval housing <b>70</b> or truncated oval housing <b>80</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10A</figref>, <b>10</b>B and <b>10</b>C, or other designs, can be employed. The housing can be molded or extruded using a plastic material such as clear polycarbonate material or aluminum having a pane made of glass or made of acrylic material and/or other combinations of selected metals and plastic materials.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The two illuminators <b>29</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5G</figref> can only be adjusted and directed to a common pan-tilt coordinate, same applies to the three illuminators <b>29</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5H</figref>. Directing all the individual illuminators <b>29</b> toward the same scene increases the illumination intensity, but does not necessarily provide good illumination condition for a given observation needs. For example high intensity IR illuminator for a fence observation may cause serious IR reflection by the fence wires <b>11</b> or barbed wires <b>11</b>A shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The reflected IR may reach directly the CCD devices of the cameras and introduce bright vertical gleams into the pictures depicted on the surveillance system monitors and recorders.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">For such and other illumination need reasons it may become necessary to provide for multiple illuminators <b>29</b> with simple adjustments of the pan and tilt for each individual illuminator.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> are two illuminators <b>29</b> comprising raws of LEDs for emitting visual spectrum light, or IR, or UV light or any other specific light spectrum. The LEDs <b>29</b>B are surrounded by a case <b>29</b><i>c </i>and are attached to heat sink <b>29</b>A for dispersing the accumulated heat generated by the LEDs <b>29</b>B. The entire illuminator assembly <b>29</b> including the LEDs <b>29</b>B, the surrounding case <b>29</b>C, the rear heat sink <b>29</b>A and the connecting wires (not shown) are all sealed by a sealing compound, such as epoxy resin or silicon seal or similar, so as to make the illuminator <b>29</b> all weather resistant.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">By this arrangement the housing <b>40</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> does not need to be sealed for outdoor installation and moreover it does not require front pane, such as the front pane <b>2</b>G of the housing <b>2</b>H or the housing <b>5</b>F, <b>5</b>G and <b>5</b>H. The open window <b>41</b> in the housing <b>40</b>, incontrast to the sealed pane <b>2</b>G, provide free air circulation, which cools the heat sink <b>29</b>A and improve upon the LEDs <b>29</b>B illumination efficiency. Moreover the open window <b>41</b> provides access for manually adjusting the pan-tilt direction coordinates of each individual illuminator <b>29</b>, this is achieved by unlocking the locking screw <b>36</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, using the screwdriver <b>2</b>T<b>4</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">The two illuminators <b>29</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> are shown locked into straight forward position around the tilting axis about the collard screws <b>39</b>, and around the panning axis about the collard screws <b>32</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8A˜8D</figref>. The illuminator assembly <b>50</b> including the two illuminators <b>29</b> inside the housing assembly <b>40</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref> can be mounted attached to a pole of a fence or to a wall or to any other vertical structure using the top and bottom mounts <b>2</b>H<b>2</b>, similar to the mounting of the camera and housing assembly <b>2</b>C.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">By this the entire illuminator assembly <b>50</b> can be rotated to the left or the right around the panning axis represented by the panning locking screw <b>2</b>P. The illuminator assembly <b>50</b> can be mounted also inside a fence pole, using mounting brackets <b>2</b>H<b>2</b>, similar to the brackets used for mounting the camera and housing assembly <b>2</b>C. The bottom cover <b>42</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> and the top surface of the housing <b>40</b> are provided with thread for the panning locking screw <b>2</b>P and the rear surface of the housing <b>40</b> includes mounting holes for attaching the individual illuminator <b>29</b> using screws <b>46</b> and may include ventilation holes for providing better air circulation for reducing the heat generated by the illuminators <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">The bottom cover <b>42</b> is secured to the housing <b>40</b> by means of screws, requiring no seals. As explained each of the illuminators <b>29</b> is individually sealed by sealing compound such as epoxy resin or silicon seal or similar, and therefore the illuminator assembly <b>50</b> can be installed indoors and outdoor exposed to rain or snow with its front window <b>43</b> fully exposed and fully open, which also provides for adjusting manually the pan-tilt direction of each illuminator <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">The access for the screw driver <b>2</b>T<b>4</b> are provided via the open holes <b>43</b> in the front surface of the housing <b>40</b>, however it is also possible to increase the window <b>41</b> length to expose the locking screw <b>36</b> through the window <b>41</b>. The shown housing <b>40</b> is for incorporating two only illuminators <b>29</b>, however it is clear and obvious that the housing vertical length can be extended to accommodate any practical number of illuminator <b>29</b>, such as three, four, five or more illuminators <b>29</b>, with each individual illuminator <b>29</b> can have its pan-tilt direction individually adjusted and locked.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A and 7B</figref> is the illuminator's <b>29</b> pan-tilt locking mechanism. The illuminator case <b>29</b>C is supported by two collard screws <b>39</b> to the frame <b>33</b>, such that the illuminator case <b>29</b>C can be tilted up or down about the tilting axis, represented by the screws <b>39</b>. The frame <b>33</b> is attached and supported by a collard screw <b>32</b> to the illuminator holder <b>30</b> and by two semi circle blocks <b>37</b> and <b>38</b> to the illuminator locking holder <b>31</b>, such that the frame <b>33</b> can be rotated to the left and right around the panning axis represented by the collard screw <b>32</b> and the center of the circle combining the two semi circle blocks <b>37</b> and <b>38</b>. The frame <b>33</b> is cut open along with the semi circle blocks <b>37</b> and <b>38</b>. Therefore if the semi circle blocks are apart the frame <b>33</b> become loose around the illuminator case <b>29</b>C as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref> and when the semi circle blocks <b>37</b> and <b>38</b> are tighten together the frame <b>33</b> is tightly pressured against the two vertical sides for the illuminator case <b>29</b>C as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">The illuminator locking holder <b>31</b> includes fixed jaw <b>34</b> and movable jaw <b>35</b> and the movable jaw <b>35</b> can be vised by the locking screw <b>36</b>. The two jaws <b>34</b> and <b>35</b> include a cutout portion <b>34</b>A and <b>35</b>A for accommodating the two semi circle blocks, such that when the locking screw <b>36</b> is tighten clockwise the movable jaw <b>35</b> moves to clamp and vise the two semi circle blocks <b>37</b> and <b>38</b> to its pan position and moreover the two semi circle block themselves vise the frame <b>33</b> onto the illuminator case <b>29</b>C, thereby locking also the illuminator case <b>29</b>C to its adjusted tilt position as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">The adjusting of the pan-tilt of the illuminator <b>29</b> can be carried whenever the locking screw <b>36</b> is unlocked and the illuminator case is freely moving in all direction. By slight pushing of the case <b>29</b>C with a finger up, down, left or right it becomes simple to set the illuminator into its intended direction. The locking of the screw <b>36</b> by a driver such as the driver <b>2</b>T<b>4</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref> completes the adjustment of the illuminator <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">As each illuminator <b>29</b> can be adjusted individually the range of adjustments of the illuminator assembly <b>50</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref> are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8A˜8D</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A˜9C</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8A</figref>, <b>8</b>B, <b>8</b>C and <b>8</b>D are side view of the illuminators tilt position, with the frame <b>33</b> set to its center, or straight forward position, such as the position shown in the top view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8A</figref> shows the two illuminators <b>29</b> tilted upward, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8B</figref> shows the two illuminators <b>29</b> set to straight forward position, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8C</figref> shows the two illuminators <b>29</b> tilted downwards and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8D</figref> shows the one illuminator <b>29</b> tilted upward and the other illuminator <b>29</b> tilted downwards.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A</figref>, <b>9</b>B and <b>9</b>C are top view of the illuminator <b>29</b> pan position with the illuminator's tilt set to straight forward, such as the position shown in the side view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8B</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref> shows the illuminator set to the left, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref> shows the illuminator set to straightforward position and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8C</figref> shows the illuminator set to the right.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">The housing with cameras and/or illuminators assemblies of the present invention can be modified by changing one or more of the well described adjustments of focus and/or zoom or varifocal lens as well as the tilting setting or the links connecting one or more cameras and/or illuminators. In fact, it becomes obvious that unlimited shapes and sized can be designed for camera housings that can incorporate the means to adjust the focus, zoom, varifocal, tilt and pan. It will of course, be understood by those skilled in the art that the particular embodiment of the invention here presented is by way of illustration only, and is meant to be in no way restrictive, therefore, numerous changes and modifications may be made, and the full used of equivalents resorted to, without departing from the spirit of scope of the invention as outlined in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An upright camera housing with adjustable pan position and with upright front pane for at least one camera with adjustable lens and tilt comprising;
<claim-text>a mount for installing said housing onto a vertical structure selected from a group consisting of a pole, column, post, pillar and a wall and for attaching said mount to said housing by fasteners at a housing horizontal axis for enabling the adjustment and the locking of said adjustable pan position around said horizontal axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjustable tilt for said at least one camera within the interior of said housing through a screw guided movable slider driven by a first adjustment tool and linked to said at least one camera and wherein said adjustment tool is accessed through a first sealed access of said housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjustable lens for each said camera selected from a group comprising a fixed focal lens, varifocal lens and zoom lens including at least one adjustable ring selected from a group consisting of focus ring, varifocal ring, zoom ring and a combination thereof, for providing adjustment of said adjustable ring selected from a group consisting of manual adjustment and remote control adjustment; wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said manual adjustment is accessed by a second adjustment tool through at least one second sealed access of said housing for engaging and adjusting said adjustable ring and wherein said remote control adjustment is provided by at least one geared motor engaged to said at least one adjustable ring; wherein said first sealed access can be opened for adjustment and re-sealed after adjustment; and wherein said second sealed access used for manual adjustment can also be opened for adjustment and re-sealed after adjustment.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said mount is constructed for installing said housing inside said vertical structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein two said second sealed access are included for each said camera, one on the left side and one on the right side of said adjustable ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said housing is sealed housing for outdoor application.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said housing is fabricated by material and process selected from a group consisting of molded plastic, extruded plastic, extruded aluminum, pressed metal sheet and a combination thereof and wherein said pane is fabricated from material selected from a group consisting of plastic, glass and acryl.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said housing further includes at least one light sensor and a switch circuit for switching over said camera operation, selected from color, B/W and IR and for switching on and off an illuminator associated with said camera operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An upright camera housing with adjustable pan position and with upright front pane for at least one illuminator and at least one camera with adjustable lens and tilt comprising;
<claim-text>a mount for installing said housing onto a vertical structure selected from a group consisting of a pole, column, post, pillar and a wall and for attaching said mount to said housing by fasteners at a housing horizontal axis for enabling the adjustment and the locking of said adjustable pan position around said horizontal axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjustable tilt for said at least one illuminator and at least one camera within the interior of said housing through a screw guided movable slider driven by a first adjustment tool and linked to said at least one illuminator and said at least one camera and wherein said adjustment tool is accessed through a first sealed access of said housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjustable lens for each said camera selected from a group comprising a fixed focal lens, varifocal lens and zoom lens including at least one adjustable ring selected from a group consisting of focus ring, varifocal ring, zoom ring and a combination thereof, for providing adjustment of said adjustable ring selected from a group consisting of manual adjustment and remote control adjustment; wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>said manual adjustment is accessed by a second adjustment tool through at least one second sealed access of said housing for engaging and adjusting said adjustable ring and wherein said remote control adjustment is provided by at least one geared motor directly engaging said at least one adjustable ring; wherein said first sealed access can be opened for adjustment and re-sealed after adjustment; and wherein said second sealed access used for manual adjustment can also be opened for adjustment and re-sealed after adjustment.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said mount is constructed for installing said housing inside said vertical structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein two said second sealed access are included for each said camera, one on the left side and one or the right side of said adjustable ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said housing is sealed housing for outdoor application.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said housing is fabricated by material and process selected from a group consisting of molded plastic, extruded plastic, extruded aluminum, pressed metal sheet and a combination thereof and wherein said pane is fabricated from material selected from a group consisting of plastic, glass and acryl.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said housing further includes at least one light sensor and a switch circuit for switching over said camera operation, selected from color, B/W and IR and for switching on and off an illuminator associated with said camera operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including a complementary upright illuminator housing with adjustable pan position and with upright front illuminator pane for at least one illuminator with adjustable tilt comprising;
<claim-text>an illuminator mount for installing said illuminator housing onto a vertical structure selected from a group consisting of a pole, column, post, pillar and a wall and for attaching said illuminator mount to said illuminator housing by fasteners at a illuminator housing horizontal axis for enabling the adjustment and the locking of said adjustable pan position around said horizontal axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjustable tilt for said at least one illuminator within the interior of said illuminator housing through a screw guided movable slider driven by an adjustment tool driver and linked to said at least one illuminator and wherein said adjustment tool is accessed through a sealed illuminator access of said illuminator housing; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said sealed illuminator access can be opened for adjustment and re-sealed after adjustment.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said illuminator mount is constructed for installing said illuminator housing inside said vertical structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said illuminator housing is scaled housing for outdoor application.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said illuminator housing is fabricated by a material and a process selected from a group consisting of molded plastic, extruded plastic, extruded aluminum, pressed metal sheet and a combination thereof and wherein said illuminator pane is fabricated from material selected from a group consisting of plastic, glass and acryl.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said illuminator housing further includes at least one light sensor and a switch for switching said illuminator on and off.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including a complementary upright illuminator housing with at least one illuminator with adjustable pan and tilt within the interior of said illuminator housing comprising;
<claim-text>an illuminator mount for installing said illuminator housing onto a vertical structure selected from a group consisting of a pole, column, post, pillar and a wall, wherein said illuminator mount can be attached by fasteners to said illuminator housing at its horizontal axis for enabling the adjustment and the locking of said housing pan position around said horizontal axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>each said illuminator is attached by dual fasteners at its tilting axis to a panning frame and said panning frame is attached by a fastener at its panning axis of one side and by dual semi circle blocks at its panning axis of the opposite side to a support assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said support assembly is mounted inside said illuminator housing and includes dual jaws cach having cutout for accommodating said dual semi circle blocks and a vise screw for vising said dual semi circle blocks between said jaws;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said panning frame is cut open at its panning axis of said opposite side with each of the open cut is attached to one of said semi circle blocks, such that a whole circle block is introduced into said cutouts of said dual jaws, wherein said frame become loose around said illuminator and about its panning axis when said vise screw is released, thereby enabling to manually adjust the pan and tilt of said illuminator, and tightly locked onto said illuminator and about its panning axis when said vise screw is tightly vising said dual semi circle blocks between said jaws; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an open window of said housing provides open accesses for said at least one illuminator and for manually adjusting the pan and tilt direction of said illuminator and for a driver to lock and unlock said vise screw.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein said illuminator mount is constructed for installing said illuminator housing inside said vertical structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein said illuminator is sealed for outdoor application.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein said illuminator housing is fabricated by a material and a process selected from a group consisting of molded plastic, extruded plastic, extruded aluminum pressed metal sheet and a combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The upright camera housing according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein said illuminator housing further, includes at least one light sensor and a switch for switching said illuminator on and off.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
