<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296527-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296527</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10514033</doc-number>
<date>20030417</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>AU</country>
<doc-number>PS2214</doc-number>
<date>20020509</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1142301</main-classification>
<further-classification>114199</further-classification>
<further-classification>114249</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Apparatus and method for securing a mooring line of a vessel</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4299183</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Prock</name>
<date>19811100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4387659</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Terauchi et al.</name>
<date>19830600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>114199</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5297499</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Grange</name>
<date>19940300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>114218</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5732647</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Benmno</name>
<date>19980300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5957075</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Byrne et al.</name>
<date>19990900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>11423025</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6009824</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ross</name>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>114218</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2 185 950</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19870800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Derwent Abstract Accession No. 84-193863/31, SU 1057366 A (Gorki River Fleet) Nov. 30, 1983.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>24</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>2</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114199</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114218</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1142301</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>11423025</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>11423026</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114249</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>114251</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>15</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050284355</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051229</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Toth</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas</first-name>
<address>
<city>Edithvale</city>
<country>AU</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>AU</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>AU</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Morris Manning Martin LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Xia, Esq.</last-name>
<first-name>Tim Tingkang</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Harbour &amp; Marine Engineering Pty Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>East Bentleigh, Victoria</city>
<country>AU</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Olson</last-name>
<first-name>Lars A.</first-name>
<department>3617</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/AU03/00486</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030417</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20050802</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO03/095300</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20031120</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">There is disclosed, apparatus for securing a mooring line (<b>5</b>) of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye (<b>6</b>), said apparatus comprising a hook (<b>10</b>) around which the eye (<b>6</b>) of the mooring line (<b>5</b>) can be secured, the hook (<b>10</b>) having a pair of hook members (<b>11</b><i>a, </i><b>11</b><i>b</i>) defining a gap therebetween, and guide means (<b>15, 17, 9</b>) configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="163.07mm" wi="269.24mm" file="US07296527-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="344.42mm" wi="237.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296527-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="314.03mm" wi="231.82mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296527-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="289.90mm" wi="227.16mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296527-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="252.22mm" wi="232.16mm" file="US07296527-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="320.29mm" wi="233.43mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296527-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="269.07mm" wi="174.58mm" file="US07296527-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to an apparatus and method for securing a mooring line of a vessel.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Modern jetties, particularly those handling petroleum, gas or bulk commodities, typically use quick-release mooring hooks to hold vessel lines and restrain the vessel against the jetty face. The mooring hooks are attached to a base which is bolted to the top of the jetty, and are generally associated with a motorised capstan or winch which is used to retrieve heavy mooring lines from an arriving vessel, allowing the eye of the mooring line to be placed over the hook by the mooring crew and subsequently tensioned using the vessel's winches.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The hooks pivot vertically and horizontally to accommodate variations in mooring patterns and the vessel height above the jetty. Typically, these will change as the load in the vessel changes.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The quick-release mooring hooks are designed so that after a locking mechanism is released, the hook rotates so that the bend in the hook faces towards the vessel, thus releasing the eye of the mooring line. The major advantage of the quick-release hook is that lines can be released under full tension, enabling the vessel to depart quickly while retaining maximum control despite counteracting forces from wind, waves, tide or current.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The combination of a quick-release hook and capstan unit (or a winch) provides significant advantages to the safety of jetty personnel, and also increases productivity because of improved vessel turn around times. As such, they have become the industry standard, particularly in petroleum and mineral ports with exposed weather conditions.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">While the release mechanism provides an improvement over the prior art, the vessel lines have, up until now, been connected manually to the quick-release hook by a mooring crew, exposing members of the crew to the risk of injury. Particularly, if too much tension comes onto the mooring line as the eye of the mooring lines is being placed over the hook. In such situations, operators are exposed to the serious risk of injury. Particularly, crush injuries involving their hands and fingers. Further, mooring lines are heavy and lifting them can result in back injury.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Accordingly, it would be advantageous to provide an improved technique for securing the mooring line to a mooring hook.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Accordingly, the invention provides apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Preferably, said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Preferably, said first guide member has a mouth aperture which narrows to a throat aperture so that when the eye of the mooring line enters the mouth aperture, it is guided towards the throat aperture.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Preferably, said second guide member is carried by a hooking unit which also carries said hook and defines an upper limit of said path.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Preferably, said first guide member is mounted so that it can pivot vertically relative to said hooking unit.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Preferably, said hooking unit includes a quick-release mechanism for releasing said hooking means.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Preferably, said hooking unit is pivotally mounted to a base member.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Preferably, said hooking unit is both horizontally and vertically pivotally mounted to said base member.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The invention also provides a method for securing a mooring line of a vessel to a hooking means, comprising the steps of:</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">providing a hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">securing a heaving line to an eye of a mooring line of a vessel; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">guiding said heaving line along a path which passes through said gap heaved, whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hooking means.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The invention also provides a method for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, the method comprising the steps of:</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">replacing an existing hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured with a new hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">providing guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the new hook, the eye locates over the new hook.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The invention also provides a kit for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said kit comprising:</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured in use, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">guide means configured to guide in use, a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Further features of the invention will become apparent from the following description of a preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side view showing the apparatus of a first preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a similar side view to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> showing the movement of the mooring line through a number of different positions;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> are further side views showing the apparatus of the first preferred embodiment securing a mooring line at a relatively steep angle;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a side view of the hook of the first preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a plan view of the hook of the first preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a front view of the hook of the first preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a rear view of the guide box of the first preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a side view of the guide box of the first preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a plan view of the guide box of the first preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a side view of the apparatus of the second preferred embodiment mounted to a jetty;</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a plan view of a hook of a second preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a side view of the hook of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a plan view of a guide box of the second preferred embodiment; and</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is a side view of the guide box of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The first preferred embodiment provides apparatus for securing a mooring line <b>5</b> of a vessel by locating the eye of the mooring line <b>5</b> around a quick-release hook <b>10</b>. The apparatus guides a heaving line <b>3</b> so that it heaves the eye <b>6</b> of the mooring line <b>5</b> along a path which is located relative to the quick-release hook such that the heaving line automatically heaves the eye <b>6</b> over the hook <b>10</b>. When tension is subsequently applied to the mooring line <b>3</b>, the eye nestles within the bend <b>16</b> of the hook <b>10</b>. Thus, the person <b>2</b> or persons operating the apparatus do not have to handle the heavy mooring line <b>5</b>, nor handle the heaving line <b>3</b> while it is under tension.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a heaving line <b>3</b> is secured to the eye <b>6</b> of the mooring line <b>5</b>. The operator <b>2</b> feeds the heaving line through the mouth <b>14</b> of guide box <b>13</b>, and then through the throat <b>15</b> of the guide box, which provides a first guide member on the vessel side of the hook <b>9</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 through 7</figref>, the hook <b>10</b> has a pair of hook members <b>11</b><i>a</i>, <b>11</b><i>b </i>defining a gap <b>9</b> therebetween. The operator <b>2</b> feeds the heaving line <b>3</b> through the gap <b>9</b> in the hook <b>10</b> and then under a second guide member in the form of guide bar <b>17</b> before feeding it through capstan guide bar <b>19</b> and wrapping it around capstan head <b>20</b>, which forms part of capstan <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Thus, the throat <b>15</b>, the guide bar <b>17</b> and the gap <b>9</b> collectively act as a guide means which define a path along which the heaving line travels. In this respect, it will be appreciated that the heaving line <b>3</b> has some freedom of movement within this path. The purpose of the guide means is twofold. Firstly, the throat <b>15</b> and the guide bar <b>17</b> are located below the tips <b>12</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b><i>b </i>of the hook members <b>11</b><i>a</i>, <b>11</b><i>b </i>to ensure that the heaving line passes within gap <b>9</b>, and further, to ensure that when the eye <b>6</b> is heaved past the tips <b>12</b> of the hook <b>10</b>, the eye <b>6</b> will drop below the tips <b>12</b> so that it subsequently will locate within bend <b>16</b> of hook <b>10</b> when the mooring line <b>5</b> is under tension. Secondly the gap <b>9</b> between the hook members <b>11</b><i>a</i>, <b>11</b><i>b </i>ensures that the eye <b>6</b> does not fall to either side of the hook <b>10</b> and is directed into the correct position.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows how the eye <b>6</b> is moved into position over the hook <b>10</b>. At position A, the eye <b>6</b> has passed through the throat <b>15</b> of the guide box as it is heaved by the heaving line <b>3</b>. The heaving line <b>3</b> then brings the eye <b>6</b> into contact with the hook <b>10</b>. At this point, the eye <b>6</b> rides up the hook <b>10</b> towards the tips <b>12</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b><i>b </i>(position B). It will be appreciated that the heaving line <b>3</b> is caused to temporarily deviate from its original path through the gap, however, the guide bar causes the heaving line <b>3</b> to return to its initial position as the eye <b>6</b> is heaved past the hook <b>10</b>, (position C). In position C, the eye <b>6</b> is now located over the hook <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Note that in position C, the heaving line <b>3</b> is still under tension between the mooring line eye <b>6</b> and the capstan head <b>20</b>. The operator <b>2</b> then stops the capstan head <b>20</b> and (typically), reverses the capstan head <b>20</b> to let the tension out of the heaving line so that the eye <b>6</b> will locate within the bend <b>16</b> of the hook <b>10</b> (position D). It will not be necessary to reverse the capstan head <b>20</b> in all instances—for example the tension on mooring line <b>5</b> may be sufficient to pull the eye into the bend <b>16</b> (position D).</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> illustrate show the various pivot mountings employed in the apparatus. The guide box <b>13</b> which is carried by a pair of guide box arms <b>32</b><i>a</i>, <b>32</b><i>b </i>is pivotally mounted to the hook unit <b>28</b> around guide box vertical pivot mounting point <b>33</b>. This means that, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, when the heaving line <b>3</b> abuts the inside of the throat <b>15</b>, the guide box <b>13</b> is able to pivot vertically around mounting point <b>33</b>. Thus, the heaving line <b>3</b> is only burdened by the weight of the guide box <b>13</b> and not by the additional weight of the hook unit <b>25</b> as the eye <b>6</b> is being heaved.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, once the eye is located around the hook, the hook assembly pivots around hook unit vertical pivot point <b>29</b>. Horizontal movement is permitted by horizontal pivot mounting point <b>28</b> where the hook unit is mounted to a base unit <b>26</b> which is firmly secured to the jetty.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">It will be apparent to persons skilled in the art that the extent to which pivoting is permitted around pivot points <b>33</b>, <b>28</b> and <b>29</b> will depend on the requirements of the jetty.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The guide box <b>13</b> is shown in further detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 through 10</figref>. The relative width of the mouth <b>14</b> to the throat <b>15</b> and the angles defined between the perimeter of the throat and perimeter of the mouth allow the heaving line to be brought into position from a wide variety of different angles relative to the apparatus <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The guide box <b>13</b> also includes a rear mouth <b>35</b> to ensure that the mooring line is guided through the guide box when it is released from the hook <b>35</b> and does not snag on the guide box.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As explained previously, the apparatus of the present invention is designed specifically for use with a known quick-release hook.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">As such quick-release mechanisms are well known, the release mechanism is not illustrated in detail in the present application. In general terms, the release mechanism is locked by moving locking spigot <b>23</b> into a locked position. As indicated by dotted lines <b>24</b>, a locking handle can be placed over the locking spigot in order to actuate the spigot. When the locking spigot is subsequently moved using the handle <b>24</b> to the release position, the tips <b>12</b><i>a,</i><b>12</b><i>b </i>of the hook <b>10</b> rotates toward the vessel so that the bend <b>16</b> in the hook <b>10</b> points towards the vessel and the eye <b>6</b> releases. The tension on the mooring line <b>5</b> causes the mooring line to be drawn through the reverse mouth <b>35</b> and out of the guide box <b>13</b>. A cut-out portion <b>36</b> is provided in the mouth <b>35</b> to accommodate movement of the hook <b>10</b> as it rotates towards the vessel.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">A second preferred embodiment will now be described in relation to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11 to 15</figref> to the extent that this embodiment differs from the first preferred embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows an apparatus <b>101</b> of the second preferred embodiment. The apparatus is mounted to a jetty <b>150</b>. The apparatus is mounted so that pivot point <b>129</b> is located sufficient above the jetty surface <b>148</b> to allow the hook unit to pivot downwards. In addition to the capstan unit <b>121</b> there is additionally provided a winch unit <b>149</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">In this embodiment, the second guide member <b>117</b> is mounted substantially at the pivot point <b>129</b> instead of to the hooking unit and has guide rollers instead of a simple guide bar.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Further differences are illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12 through 14</figref>. In particular, it will be noted that the hook members <b>111</b><i>a,</i><b>111</b><i>b </i>are longer than the hook members of the first preferred embodiment to increase the hooking capability of the hook. Further, the tips <b>112</b><i>a,</i><b>112</b><i>b </i>are smoother than the tips of the hook of the first preferred embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>, it will be noted that the guide box <b>113</b> is generally of a more squat configuration than the guide box of the first embodiment and does not narrow to the same extent.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The guide box has the additional feature of a pair of handles <b>151</b><i>a,</i><b>151</b><i>b </i>which can be used to manipulate the guide box <b>113</b> into position.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">It will also be noted that the guide plates flare increasingly outwardly nearer the mouth <b>114</b> of the guide box.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">While <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11 to 15</figref> illustrate some preferred variations on the first preferred embodiment, it will be apparent that various other modifications may be made. For example, in some embodiments where the heaving line is expected to always be below the guide box, it may not be necessary to have a guide member such as a guide bar on the side of the hook opposite to the vessel. Or indeed, it will not be necessary to use any guide member which is provided on that side.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Further, rather than a guide box per se there may be a series of guide plates which define an aperture or a guide roller fairlead which also defines a mouth and throat aperture.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Still further, rather than the single hook which is illustrated for the purposes of illustrating the present invention, an actual installation may include two, three or four hooks or may include a back to back mounted hook assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The apparatus may also be provided with sensor switch or limit switch which prevents the eye from being pulled too far beyond the hook. The limit switch would be tripped by the mooring rope's eye and the switch would cut the power to the capstan or winch automatically.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The guide box may also be provided with electric or hydraulic actuators to manipulate and position the box in order to assist in the guiding or aligning of the rope eye. This may also be provided if a fairlead is used.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Various other modifications will be apparent. For example, the guide bar <b>17</b> and capstan of guide <b>19</b> could be replaced with guide rollers. Further, the capstan head <b>20</b> may be mounted so that it rotates in a vertical plane rather than a horizontal plane.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Still further, the hook members of the split hook could be designed to fold down when contacted by the eye as the eye is being heaved into place. For example, the hook members could be pivotally mounted and spring loaded so that they return to their normal position once the eye has passed.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Further, it will be appreciated that the apparatus of the present invention may be provided in kit form for upgrading an existing apparatus. That is the kit could consist of a split hook having a pair of hook members which define a gap which can replace an existing hook as well as guide means which can be welded or bolted to an existing unit. For example, the kit could include a guide box with mounts for mounting the guide box to an existing unit as well as guide bars or guide rollers which could be mounted to the existing unit. The various guide members and other component parts of the kit would be adapted so that they can be attached to an existing apparatus. For example, bolt holes may be provided in various of the components to the apparatus to facilitate it being bolted to an existing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">It will also be appreciated that the apparatus of the present invention can be used to replace an existing hook unit while maintaining the support structure and capstan/winch.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">These and other modifications will be apparent to persons skilled in the art, and should be considered as falling within the scope of the invention described herein.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The claims defining the invention are as follows:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. Apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first guide member is mounted so that it can pivot vertically relative to said hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. Apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said hook is operably connected to a quick-release mechanism for releasing said hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. Apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said second guide member is carried by a hooking unit which also carries said hook and defines an upper limit of said path; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said hooking unit is pivotally mounted to a base member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. Apparatus as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said hooking unit is both horizontally and vertically pivotally mounted to said base member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. Apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first guide member comprises a plurality of guide plates.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. Apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first guide member is a guide roller fairlead.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. Apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said second guide member is carried by a hooking unit which also carries said hook and defines an upper limit of said path; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said second guide member is a guide roller.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. Apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means comprises a guide member on a vessel side of said apparatus, the guide member defining a mouth aperture which narrows to a throat aperture whereby, when the eye of the mooring line enters the mouth aperture, the eye is guided towards the throat aperture; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide member is mounted so that the guide member can pivot vertically relative to said hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. Apparatus as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said guide member is a guide roller fairlead.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. Apparatus as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said guide member is a guide box.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. Apparatus as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said guide member is a guide roller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A kit for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured in use, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide in use, a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook, wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being adapted to be installed on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being adapted to be installed on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, whereby the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eve past the hook, the eve is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>mounting means for mounting said first guide member so that it can pivot vertically relative to said hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A kit for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured in use, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide in use, a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being adapted to be installed on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being adapted to be installed on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, whereby the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first guide member comprises a plurality of guide plates.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A kit for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured in use, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide in use, a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being adapted to be installed on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being adapted to be installed on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, whereby the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first guide member is a guide roller fairlead.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A kit for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured in use, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide in use, a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide means includes first and second guide members, the first guide member being adapted to be installed on a vessel side of the hook, and the second guide member being adapted to be installed on the opposite side of the hook to the first guide member, whereby the first and second guide members being located relative to the hook, such that when said heaving line heaves said eye past the hook, the eye is brought to a position below the highest point of said hook to thereby locate the eye over the hook;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said second guide member is adapted to define an upper limit of said path; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said second guide member is a guide roller.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A kit for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured in use, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide in use, a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook, wherein said guide means comprises a guide member adapted to be installed on a vessel side of said apparatus, the guide member defining a mouth aperture which narrows to a throat aperture whereby, when the eye of the mooring line enters the mouth aperture, the eye is guided towards the throat aperture; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>mounting means for mounting said guide member so that the guide member can pivot vertically relative to said hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A kit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein said guide member is a guide roller fairlead.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A kit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein said guide member is a guide box.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A kit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein said guide member is a guide roller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. Apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the hook is shaped so that the eye of the mooring line rides up the hook towards tips of the hook members as the heaving line heaves the eye past the hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A method for securing a mooring line of a vessel to a hooking means, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>providing a hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>securing a heaving line to an eye of a mooring line of a vessel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>guiding said heaving line along a path which passes through said gap heaved, whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hooking means; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guiding said heaving line along a path such that the eye of the mooring line rides up the hook towards tips of the hook members as the heaving line heaves the eye past the hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A method for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>replacing an existing hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured with a new hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the new hook, the eye locates over the new hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the hook is shaped so that the eye of the mooring line rides up the hook towards tips of the hook members as the heaving line heaves the eye past the hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. A method for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>replacing an existing hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured with a new hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing guide means configured to guide a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the new hook, the eye locates over the new hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said hook is operably connected to a quick-release mechanism for releasing said hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A kit for upgrading an apparatus for securing a mooring line of a vessel, the mooring line having an eye, said kit comprising:
<claim-text>a hook around which the eye of the mooring line can be secured in use, the hook having a pair of hook members defining a gap therebetween; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>guide means configured to guide in use, a heaving line attached to said eye along a path which passes through said gap whereby when said heaving line heaves the eye past the hook, the eye locates over the hook,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said hook is operably connected to a quick-release mechanism for releasing swing hook.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
