<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299001-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299001</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10938911</doc-number>
<date>20040910</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-322143</doc-number>
<date>20030912</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>31</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>20</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399327</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Fuser cleaning method and system in image-forming device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5528346</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kim et al.</name>
<date>19960600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399 33</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5850588</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yoshikawa</name>
<date>19981200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399327</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5970298</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Seki et al.</name>
<date>19991000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399327</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6091925</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sugimoto et al.</name>
<date>20000700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399327</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6181890</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kataoka et al.</name>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>399 67</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>07-104602</doc-number>
<date>19950400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-075750</doc-number>
<date>20000300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399327</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050100371</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050512</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yamazaki</last-name>
<first-name>Hajime</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Knoble Yoshida &amp; Dunleavy, LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ricoh Company, Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Gray</last-name>
<first-name>David M.</first-name>
<department>2852</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>LaBombard</last-name>
<first-name>Ruth N.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A fuser roller surface is cleaned immediately before and or after the fusing operation. The separate cleaning sequence assures that the fuser roller surface is substantially free from residual toner that has accumulated from previous fusing operation. A number of image-transfer sheets is counted, and the cleaning sequence is also optionally activated after a number of detected image-transfer sheets has reached a predetermined number.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="63.42mm" wi="153.25mm" file="US07299001-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="181.44mm" wi="159.00mm" file="US07299001-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="202.86mm" wi="168.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299001-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="165.95mm" wi="146.05mm" file="US07299001-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="180.26mm" wi="111.84mm" file="US07299001-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="198.20mm" wi="116.76mm" file="US07299001-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="247.90mm" wi="113.03mm" file="US07299001-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="260.10mm" wi="109.64mm" file="US07299001-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="261.20mm" wi="166.71mm" file="US07299001-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The current invention is generally related to a fuser or image-fixing unit in an image-forming apparatus, and more particularly related to a method of cleaning a fuser to substantially eliminate undesirable effects of residual toner on the fused image.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In the prior art, a fuser or fixation unit usually fixes a toner image on an image-transfer sheet of paper by fusing rollers that have been heated. In the above fuser, since toner is not completely fixed on the transfer sheet, some toner remains on the fusing rollers. This remaining toner is also so called residual toner. The residual toner is collected from the fusing rollers by cleaning rollers via pressure rollers.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">An image-transfer sheet is soiled by the residual toner in a prior art fuser. As described above, a portion of toner on the image-transfer paper becomes unfixed, and the residual toner is attached to a fuser separation pawl that separates the transfer paper from the fuser rollers. As the residual toner increases beyond a certain amount on the fuser separation pawl, aggregated toner falls from the fuser separation pawl and smears the transfer paper. Thus, the fuser separation pawl needs to be maintained. While the fuser separation pawl is periodically cleaned or replaced, the image forming device is not available.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">For the above prior art problems, prior art techniques had attempted to minimize the undesirable effects. Japanese Patent Publication 2000-75750 discloses a cleaning blade for removing adherents such as toner from the cleaning rollers as well as a ceramic heater for heating the cleaning blade beyond a melting temperature of the residual toner. The ceramic heater adds structural complexities and requires additional costs. In relation to the prior art cleaning technologies of a fuser, Japanese Patent Publication Hei 7-104602 also discloses techniques for increasing the cleaning efficiency for the cleaning material in the fusing rollers in an image forming device and for uniformly applying oil. Although the cleaning rollers are located on the transfer paper outlet side of the fusing rollers, the residual toner that has been cleaned by the cleaning rollers falls off onto the transfer sheet for undesirable effects.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It remains desirable to maintain the fuser rollers substantially free from residual toner without significant structural modifications to the fuser or fixing unit.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In order to solve the above and other problems, according to a first aspect of the current invention, a method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device, including the steps of: anticipating a print operation in the image-forming device to generate a print preparation command; cleaning residual toner from the fuser in response to the print preparation command prior to forming an image on an image-transfer sheet in the image-forming device by intermittently activating and deactivating for a predetermined number of times to rotate a fuser roller in the fuser and collecting the residual toner; forming the image on the image-transfer sheet; and fusing the image on the image-transfer sheet at a first predetermined temperature.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to a second aspect of the current invention, a system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device, including: a fuser for fusing an image on an image-transfer sheet at a first predetermined temperature; a user information access unit for obtaining a predetermined set of information to anticipate a print operation in the image-forming device so as to generate a print preparation command; a control unit connected to th user information access unit and the fuser for controlling a cleaning sequence for cleaning residual toner from the fuser in response to the print preparation command prior to fusing an image on an image-transfer sheet in the fuser, the control unit generating a cleaning complete signal upon finishing the cleaning seguence; a writing unit connected to the control unit for forming the image on the image-transfer sheet in response to the cleaning complete signal, wherein the fuser fuses the image on the image-transfer sheet after the cleaning sequence, wherein the fuser further includes a fuser roller, the control unit activating and deactivating the fuser for a predetermined number of times for intermittently rotating the fuser roller in the fuser in order to collect the residual toner.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">These and various other advantages and features of novelty which characterize the invention are pointed out with particularity in the claims annexed hereto and forming a part hereof. However, for a better understanding of the invention, its advantages, and the objects obtained by its use, reference should be made to the drawings which form a further part hereof, and to the accompanying descriptive matter, in which there is illustrated and described a preferred embodiment of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram illustrating a digital copier <b>100</b> that includes one preferred embodiment of the fuser according to the current invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating a controller of the digital copier in one preferred embodiment according to the current invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a diagram illustrating the fuser or the fixing unit in the image-forming device.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow chart illustrating steps involved in a first preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flow chart illustrating steps involved in a second preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a flow chart illustrating steps involved in a third preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flow chart illustrating steps involved in a fourth preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a flow chart illustrating steps involved in a fifth preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a flow chart illustrating steps involved in a sixth preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a flow chart illustrating steps involved in a seventh preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a graph illustrating parameters for the fuser cleaning job to be performed in the above described preferred processes according to the current invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT(S)</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Based upon incorporation by external reference, the current application incorporates all disclosures in the corresponding foreign priority document (JP2003-322143) from which the current application claims priority.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring now to the drawings, wherein like reference numerals designate corresponding structures throughout the views, and referring in particular to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a diagram illustrates a digital copier <b>100</b> that includes one preferred embodiment of the fuser according to the current invention. The digital copier <b>100</b> includes a contact glass <b>6</b> on a top surface. An automatic document feeder (ADF) <b>1</b> is located above the contact glass <b>6</b> and hinged at one end to cover or uncover the contact glass <b>6</b>. The ADF <b>1</b> further includes a document feeding tray <b>2</b> for feeding a stack of documents as well as a separation/transfer means for separating one document at a time from the document stack and for transferring the separated single document towards a predetermined scanning position on the contact glass <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A paper supplying motor is activated by a central processing unit (CPU), which is not illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, but included in the digital copier. The CPU activates the paper supplying motor in response to a paper supply activation signal. When the paper supplying motor is activated in a forward operation, the transfer rollers <b>3</b> rotate in a clockwise direction to feed a top sheet in the stack towards the contact glass <b>6</b>. Upon detecting a leading edge of the fed top sheet at a document detection unit <b>7</b>, the CPU activates the motor in a reverse operation to rotate the transfer rollers <b>3</b> in a counter-clockwise direction so as to prevent the feeding of other sheets in the stack. Upon detecting a trailing edge of the fed sheet at a document detection unit <b>7</b>, the CPU counts a number of pulse signals for a transfer belt motor to a predetermined number. Then, the CPU deactivates the transfer belt <b>4</b> to place the fed sheet at the scanning position on the contact glass <b>6</b>. Upon detecting a trailing edge of the fed sheet at a document detection unit <b>7</b>, the CPU also reactivates the paper supplying motor to repeat the above described sequence to transfer a next sheet in the stack towards the predetermined scanning position. At the scanning position, the document is exposed by light and scanned by a scanner <b>50</b> in the copier <b>100</b>. The scanner <b>50</b> further includes an exposing lamp <b>51</b>, mirrors <b>52</b>, <b>55</b> and <b>56</b>, a lens <b>53</b> and a CCD <b>54</b>. After scanning by the scanner <b>50</b>, the separation/transfer means further transfers the document away from at the scanning position on the contact glass <b>6</b> via the transfer belt <b>4</b> to output rollers <b>5</b> and an output port A.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, transfer paper is stored in a first tray <b>8</b>, a second tray <b>9</b> and a third tray <b>10</b>. The paper in the trays <b>8</b>, <b>9</b> and <b>10</b> is respectively supplied to a first supplying unit <b>11</b>, a second supplying unit <b>12</b> and a third supplying unit <b>13</b>. The paper is subsequently transferred by a paper vertical transfer unit <b>14</b> to a predetermined position to physically contact a photoreceptor <b>15</b>. An image that has been scanned by the scanning unit <b>50</b> is written on the photoreceptor <b>15</b> by laser from a writing unit <b>57</b>. A developing unit <b>27</b> generates a toner image on the photoreceptor <b>15</b>. While the image-transfer paper is further transferred by a transfer belt <b>16</b> at the same speed as the rotation of the photoreceptor <b>15</b>, the toner image is transferred onto the image-transfer paper. The transferred toner image is fixed or fused on the image-transfer paper by a fuser <b>17</b>. The image-transfer paper is finally outputted onto an output tray <b>19</b> by a paper output unit <b>18</b> unless it is stapled.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a block diagram illustrates a controller <b>20</b> of the digital copier <b>100</b> in one preferred embodiment according to the current invention. The controller <b>20</b> further includes a central processing unit (CPU) <b>21</b>, a read only memory (ROM) <b>22</b> for storing system programs for controlling the CPU <b>21</b>, a random access memory (RAM) <b>23</b> to be used for a work area for application programs, a non-volatile random access memory (NV-RAM) <b>24</b> for safely storing adjusted numerical values for control, timing and copy mode in case of shut down or power outage, and an engine control <b>25</b> for controlling a load <b>38</b> based upon the input from the sensor <b>37</b>. The access information including the operation panel, the ADF position and a document set to the ADF is inputted via the sensor <b>37</b>. The CPU <b>21</b>, the ROM <b>22</b>, the RAM <b>23</b>, the NV-RAM <b>24</b> and the engine <b>25</b> are all connected by a data and address bus.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the digital copier <b>100</b> also includes other units that are connected to the controller <b>20</b>. The digital copier <b>100</b> further includes a network control unit (NCU) <b>39</b> for connecting to an external host and a facsimile control unit (FCU) <b>40</b> for realizing a facsimile function via a public circuit. An image processing unit <b>32</b> and a hard disk drive (HDD) controller <b>31</b> are also connected to the controller <b>20</b>, and the image processing unit <b>32</b> is in turn connected to a scanning unit or scanner <b>35</b>, a writing unit <b>36</b> and an image RAM <b>33</b>. The HDD controller <b>31</b> is in turn connected to a hard disk drive (HDD) <b>34</b>. Lastly, the CPU <b>21</b> is ultimately connected to a fuser or a fixing unit <b>200</b> of the image-forming device. The CPU <b>21</b> executes a selected one of various control software programs in the RAM <b>23</b> for controlling a fuser cleaning job sequence according to the current invention. The above fuser cleaning control software programs are optionally stored in the ROM <b>22</b> or a secondary storage that is accessed by the HDD <b>34</b>. The digital copier <b>100</b> also includes a user information access unit <b>41</b> that is connected to the CPU <b>21</b> for obtaining a certain set of predetermined information that includes the document set information at the ADF, the opening-closing information of the ADF and the access information on the operation panel. The existence of any of the information generally indicates that the user has likely initiated a copy operation.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a diagram illustrates the fuser or the fixing unit <b>200</b> of the image-forming device. The fixing unit <b>200</b> further includes a fuser heater <b>105</b> such as a halogen heater, a fuser roller <b>101</b> that is heated by the fuser heater <b>105</b>, a temperature sensor <b>106</b> for sensing the surface temperature of the fuser roller <b>101</b> and a temperature breaker or fuse <b>116</b> for shutting the power to the fuser heater <b>105</b> when the temperature sensor <b>106</b> registers a temperature beyond a predetermined temperature. The fixing unit <b>200</b> further includes a fuser separation pawl <b>102</b> for separating a transfer sheet from the fuser roller <b>101</b>, a pressure roller <b>114</b> for applying a predetermined amount of pressure over the transfer paper by pressing against the fuser roller <b>101</b>, a pressure separation pawl <b>115</b> for separating the transfer sheet from the pressure roller <b>114</b>, a cleaning roller <b>113</b> for collecting toner from the pressure roller <b>114</b>, a spring <b>112</b> for pressing the pressure roller <b>114</b>, a delivery pawl <b>110</b> for controlling a direction of the fused transfer sheet, a first transferring roller <b>111</b> for transferring the fused transfer sheet, an output roller <b>108</b> for transferring the fused transfer sheet to an output, a second transferring roller <b>107</b> that passively rotates with the output roller <b>108</b>, and an sheet output sensor <b>109</b> for detecting the transfer sheet delivery.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, an operation of the fuser <b>200</b> will be described in the following. Upon entering via an entry guide plate <b>117</b>, the transfer sheet faces its toner image on the fuser roller <b>101</b>. The fusing roller <b>101</b> and the pressure roller <b>114</b> rotate together as indicated by arrows. As a leading edge of the transfer paper arrives the fuser roller <b>101</b>, the toner image on the transfer sheet is fixed by melting the toner. The heat source for melting the toner is provided by the internal fuser heater <b>105</b> that is located inside the fuser roller <b>101</b>. The internal fuser heater <b>105</b> is controlled based upon the temperature that is measured by the temperature sensor <b>106</b> so as to maintain the surface on the fuser roller <b>101</b> at a uniform temperature. As the trailing edge of the transfer paper is detected by the output sensor <b>109</b>, the fusing or fixing process is completed.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In the prior art, the cleaning roller <b>113</b> has collected the residual toner on the fuser roller <b>101</b> via the pressure roller <b>114</b> during the above described fusing operations. This collection or cleaning technique is largely passive and not active for cleaning the residual toner on the fuser roller <b>101</b> during the fusing operation. During the fusing operation, residual toner is partially collected by the pressure roller <b>114</b> and the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>. The pressure roller <b>114</b> collects the residual toner since its surface has a stronger surface adhesiveness and a lower temperature than the surface of the fuser roller <b>101</b>. Due to these characteristics, the residual toner on the fuser roller <b>101</b> is transferred onto the pressure roller <b>114</b>. By the same token, the cleaning roller <b>113</b> has a stronger surface adhesiveness and a lower temperature than the surface of the pressure roller <b>114</b>. Thus, the residual toner on the pressure roller <b>114</b> is transferred onto the cleaning roller <b>113</b> and is ultimately collected into a predetermined location.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">However, since the above passive cleaning is performed during the fusing operation in prior art, the fuser roller <b>101</b> is partially covered by the image-transfer sheet and the residual toner is not sufficiently cleaned. At the end of each fusing operation, the uncollected residual toner remains on the fuser roller <b>101</b> and or the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b> in a gel state due to the heat from the fuser heater <b>105</b>. Before a next round of the fusing operation, if there is a sufficient amount of time for the fuser roller <b>101</b> to cool down, the residual toner on the fuser roller <b>101</b> and or the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b> is solidified. During the next round of the fusing operation, the solidified the residual toner falls off from the fuser roller <b>101</b> and or the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b> onto the image-transfer paper to cause the undesired effect as described before.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">According to the current invention, the residual toner cleaning or collection operation is performed before and or after a fusing operation. In other words, the fuser roller <b>101</b>, the pressure roller <b>114</b> and the cleaning roller <b>113</b> are rotated at a predetermined temperature for a predetermined amount of time prior and or subsequent to the fusing operation without the image-transfer sheet. The pre-/post-fusing rotation is preferably immediately before and after the fusing operation. The amount of time for the pre-/post-fusing rotation depends upon many factors including a number of fused sheets between cleaning processes and the size of image area on the fused sheets. In addition, the temperature during the pre-/post-fusing rotation is preferably lower than that during the fusing operation. The lower temperature facilitates the cleaning process since the residual toner becomes more adhesive. During the pre-/post-fusing rotation, the residual toner is substantially cleaned from the fuser roller <b>101</b> since the image-transfer paper is not obstructing the fuser roller surface. The cleaned residual toner is ultimately collected into a predetermined receptacle via the pressure roller <b>114</b> and the cleaning roller <b>113</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a flow chart illustrates steps involved in a first preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. In a step S<b>201</b>, it is continuously determined whether or not any of the predetermined user access information has been obtained in the user information access unit <b>41</b>. The predetermined accessed information includes the document set information at the ADF, the opening-closing information of the ADF and the access information on the operation panel. The existence of any of the information generally indicates that the user has likely initiated a copy operation. If none of the information is polled, the first preferred process waits in the step S<b>201</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>201</b> any of the information is obtained, since it is sufficiently expected that a copy operation will be initiated, the copy engine activates the rotation of the fuser roller <b>101</b> based upon the above access information as a trigger in a step S<b>202</b>. During the rotation, the residual toner on the fuser roller <b>101</b> is removed by the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>, and the removed toner stays on the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>. It is further determined in a step S<b>203</b> whether or not a predetermined amount of time has passed since the activation of the fuser roller <b>101</b> in the step S<b>203</b>. If it is determined in the step S<b>203</b> that the predetermined amount of time has not elapsed, the rotation is maintained for a pre-cleaning operation.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, if it is determined in the step S<b>203</b> that the predetermined amount of time has elapsed, the rotation is discontinued in a step S<b>204</b> for the pre-cleaning operation. During the rotation of the fuser roller <b>101</b>, the removed residual toner physically falls off the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>. Subsequently, since the cleaning roller <b>113</b> and the pressure roller <b>114</b> are simultaneously rotated for a predetermined amount of time between the steps S<b>202</b> and S<b>204</b> to collect the removed residual toner. The removed residual toner is transferred to a predetermined collection area by the cleaning roller <b>113</b> via the pressure roller <b>114</b>. Furthermore, it is determined if a user has activated a copy/print operation in a step S<b>206</b>. If no copy/print operation is found in the step S<b>206</b>, the first preferred process waits in the step S<b>206</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>206</b> that the user initiates a copy/print operation, the preferred process initiates the copy/print operation in the step S<b>207</b> after the fuser roller <b>101</b> has been cleaned. In the above steps S<b>202</b> and S<b>203</b>, the cleaning operation is performed for the predetermine amount of time in the preferred process. In an alternative process, the cleaning operation is repeated for a predetermined number of rotations of the fuser roller <b>101</b> and or the cleaning roller <b>113</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a flow chart illustrates steps involved in a second preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. In a step S<b>301</b>, it is continuously determined whether or not any of the predetermined user access information has been obtain in the system. The predetermined accessed information includes the document set information at the ADF, the opening-closing information of the ADF and the access information on the operation panel. The existence of any of the information generally indicates that the user has likely initiated a copy operation. If none of the information is polled, the second preferred process waits in the step <b>301</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>301</b> any of the information is obtained, since it is sufficiently expected that a copy operation will be initiated, the copy engine activates the rotation of the fuser roller <b>101</b> based upon the above access information as a trigger in a step S<b>302</b>. During the rotation in the step S<b>302</b>, the residual toner on the fuser roller <b>101</b> is removed by the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>, and the removed toner stays on the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>. After the above initiated rotation, it is determined in a step S<b>303</b> if a user has activated a copy/print operation. If no copy/print operation is found in the step S<b>303</b>, the second preferred process proceeds to a step S<b>305</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>303</b> that the user has initiated a copy/print operation, it is further determined in a step S<b>304</b> whether or not a predetermined amount of time has passed since the activation of the fuser roller <b>101</b> in the step S<b>302</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, if it is determined in the step S<b>304</b> that the predetermined amount of time has not elapsed, the rotation is maintained and the second preferred process returns to the step S<b>303</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>304</b> that the predetermined amount of time has elapsed, it is further determined in the step S<b>305</b> if a user has activated a copy/print operation. If no copy/print operation is found in the step S<b>305</b>, the second preferred process waits in the step S<b>305</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>305</b> that the user has already initiated a copy/print operation, the rotation of the fuser roller <b>101</b> is discontinued in a step S<b>306</b> for the pre-cleaning operation. While the fuser roller <b>101</b> is rotating, the removed residual toner physically falls off the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>. Subsequently, since the cleaning roller <b>113</b> and the pressure roller <b>114</b> are simultaneously rotated for at least a predetermined amount of time between the steps S<b>302</b> and S<b>306</b> to collect the removed residual toner, the removed residual toner is transferred to a predetermined collection area by the cleaning roller <b>113</b> via the pressure roller <b>114</b>. Furthermore, the second preferred process initiates the copy/print operation in the step S<b>308</b> after the fuser roller <b>101</b> has been cleaned. As described above, the second preferred process ascertains that the pre-cleaning operation is completed even if a user interrupts with the copy/print operation. In the above steps, the cleaning operation is performed for the predetermine amount of time in the second preferred process. In an alternative process, the cleaning operation is repeated for a predetermined number of rotations of the fuser roller <b>101</b> and or the cleaning roller <b>113</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a flow chart illustrates steps involved in a third preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. In a step S<b>401</b>, it is continuously determined whether or not a print preparation command has been issued. The print preparation command is initiated for printing or faxing a document. If it is determined in the step S<b>401</b> that the print preparation command has not been issued, the third preferred process waits at the step S<b>401</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>401</b> that the print preparation command has been issued, the third preferred process proceeds to a step S<b>402</b>. When the CPU receives a print request from an external host via the NCU <b>39</b> or a fax receiving request via the FCU <b>40</b>, the CPU issues a printer preparation command for activating a polygon motor to the print engine <b>25</b>. The issuance of the print preparation command generally indicates that the print operation is likely to occur. Since it is sufficiently expected that the print operation will be initiated, the copy engine activates the rotation of the fuser roller <b>101</b> based upon the above information as a trigger in a step S<b>402</b>. During the rotation in the step S<b>402</b>, the residual toner on the fuser roller <b>101</b> is removed by the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>, and the removed toner stays on the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>. It is further determined in a step S<b>403</b> whether or not a predetermined amount of time has passed since the activation of the fuser roller <b>101</b> in the step S<b>402</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, if it is determined in the step S<b>403</b> that the predetermined amount of time has not elapsed, the rotation is maintained for a pre-cleaning operation. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>403</b> that the predetermined amount of time has elapsed, the rotation is discontinued in a step S<b>404</b> for the pre-cleaning operation. During the rotation of the fuser roller <b>101</b>, the removed residual toner physically falls off the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>. Subsequently, since the cleaning roller <b>113</b> and the pressure roller <b>114</b> are simultaneously rotated for a predetermined amount of time between the steps S<b>402</b> and S<b>404</b> to collect the removed residual toner, the removed residual toner is transferred to a predetermined collection area by the cleaning roller <b>113</b> via the pressure roller <b>114</b>. Furthermore, it is determined if a print command is issued in a step S<b>406</b>. If no print command is found in the step S<b>406</b>, the preferred process waits in the step S<b>406</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>406</b> that the print command has been issued, the third preferred process initiates the print operation in a step S<b>407</b> after the fuser roller <b>101</b> has been cleaned. In the above steps, the cleaning operation is performed for the predetermine amount of time in the third preferred process. In an alternative process, the cleaning operation is repeated for a predetermined number of rotations of the fuser roller <b>101</b> and or the cleaning roller <b>113</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a flow chart illustrates steps involved in a fourth preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. In a step S<b>501</b>, it is continuously determined whether or not a print job has been completed. If it is determined in the step S<b>501</b> that the print job has not been completed, the fourth preferred process waits at the step S<b>501</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>501</b> that the print job has been completed, the fourth preferred process proceeds to a step S<b>502</b>, where the above described steps associated with cleaning of the fuser <b>200</b> are performed. The fourth preferred process cleans the fuser <b>200</b> after each of the print job rather than before the print job in order to reduce a print response time after a user issues a print command. Although as described above, the fuser cleaning steps are performed in response to a print-related command or a predetermined information access in the anticipation of a print job in some of the preferred process, the print response time may be still affected. The fourth preferred process substantially eliminates an undesirable effect of the fuser cleaning steps on the print response time.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, a flow chart illustrates steps involved in a fifth preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. In a step S<b>601</b>, it is continuously determined whether or not a trailing end of the image-transfer sheet has been detected at a predetermined location in a printing path. If it is determined in the step S<b>601</b> that the image-transfer sheet has not been detected, the fifth preferred process waits at the step S<b>601</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>601</b> that the image-transfer sheet has been detected, the fifth preferred process proceeds to a step S<b>602</b>, where a predetermined counter is incremented by one for recording an additional sheet that has been fused. After the increment, it is determined in a step S<b>603</b> whether or not the counter value has reached a predetermined number of sheets. If the counter value has not reached a predetermined number of sheets, the fifth preferred process returns to the step S<b>601</b>. On the other hand, if the counter value has reached a predetermined number of sheets, the current and future print jobs will be suspended in the future in a step S<b>604</b> until a fuser cleaning job initiated in a step S<b>605</b> is completed. The fuser cleaning job includes that the fuser roller <b>101</b>, the pressure roller <b>114</b> and the cleaning roller <b>113</b> are rotated at a predetermined temperature for a predetermined amount of time subsequent to the fusing operation without the image-transfer sheet as described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Upon completing the fuser cleaning job, the counter is reset in the step S<b>606</b>. Because of the print suspension, it is further determined in a step S<b>607</b> whether or not print jobs are completed. If it is not completed, the fifth preferred embodiment returns to the step S<b>601</b> to repeat the steps. Otherwise, the fifth preferred embodiment terminates. The fifth preferred process prolongs the life of the fuser <b>200</b> by minimizing the number of unnecessary cleanings. The pre-cleaning step <b>605</b> is performed only after a predetermined number of image-transfer sheets is fused at the fuser <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, a flow chart illustrates steps involved in a sixth preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. In a step S<b>701</b>, it is continuously determined whether or not a print job has been completed. If it is determined in the step S<b>701</b> that the print job has not been completed, the sixth preferred process waits at the step S<b>701</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>701</b> that the print job has been completed, the sixth preferred process proceeds to a step S<b>702</b>, it is further determined in a step S<b>702</b> whether or not the counter value has reached a predetermined number of sheets. If the counter value has not reached a predetermined number of sheets, the sixth preferred process terminates. On the other hand, if the counter value has reached a predetermined number of sheets in the step S<b>702</b>, the fuser <b>200</b> is cleaned in a step S<b>703</b>. The fuser cleaning in the step S<b>703</b> includes that the fuser roller <b>101</b>, the pressure roller <b>114</b> and the cleaning roller <b>113</b> are rotated at a predetermined temperature for a predetermined amount of time subsequent to the fusing operation without the image-transfer sheet as described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The sixth preferred process cleans the fuser <b>200</b> after each of the print job rather than before the print job in order to reduce a print response time after a user issues a print command. Although as described above, the fuser cleaning steps are performed in response to a print-related command or a predetermined information access in the anticipation of a print job in some of the preferred process, the print response time may be still affected. The sixth preferred process substantially eliminates an undesirable effect of the fuser cleaning steps on the print response time.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, a flow chart illustrates steps involved in a seventh preferred process of actively collecting the residual toner on a fuser roller according to the current invention. In a step S<b>801</b>, it is continuously determined whether or not a trailing end of the image-transfer sheet has been detected by the sheet output sensor <b>109</b> at a predetermined location in a printing path. If it is determined in the step S<b>801</b> that the image-transfer sheet has not been detected, the seventh preferred process waits at the step S<b>801</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>801</b> that the image-transfer sheet has been detected, the seventh preferred process proceeds to a step S<b>802</b>, where a predetermined counter in the NV-RAM <b>24</b> is incremented by one for recording an additional sheet that has been fused. After the increment, it is determined in a step S<b>803</b> whether or not the print job has finished. If it is determined in the step S<b>803</b> that the print job has not finished, the seventh preferred process returns to the step S<b>801</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>803</b> that the print job has finished, it is further determined in a step S<b>804</b> whether or not the counter value has reached a predetermined number of sheets. If the counter value has not reached a predetermined number of sheets, the seventh preferred process returns to the step S<b>801</b>. On the other hand, if the counter value has reached a predetermined number of sheets, a fuser cleaning job is initiated in a step S<b>805</b>. The fuser cleaning job includes that the fuser roller <b>101</b>, the pressure roller <b>114</b> and the cleaning roller <b>113</b> are rotated at a predetermined temperature for a predetermined amount of time subsequent to the fusing operation without the image-transfer sheet as described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Still referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, upon completing the fuser cleaning job, the seventh preferred process further determines in a step S<b>807</b> whether or not a print job has interrupted. In case of the print job interrupt as found in the step S<b>807</b>, the seventh preferred process also interrupts any on-going cleaning job in a step S<b>806</b> and returns to the step S<b>801</b>. On the other hand, if it is determined in the step S<b>807</b> that no print job interrupts, it is further determined in a step S<b>808</b> whether or not the current fuser cleaning job has finished. In case the fuser cleaning job has not yet finished, the seventh preferred process returns to the step S<b>807</b>. In case the fuser cleaning is complete, the seventh preferred process resets the counter in a step S<b>809</b> and terminates. The seventh preferred process prolongs the life of the fuser <b>200</b> by minimizing the number of unnecessary cleanings. The pre-cleaning step <b>805</b> is performed only after a predetermined number of image-transfer sheets is fused at the fuser <b>200</b>. The seventh preferred process also a print job to be executed during the fuser cleaning by interrupting the fuser cleaning job in order to increase the print productivity. If power is interrupted during the fuser cleaning job, since the fuser cleaning job does not terminate normally, the counter value is not cleared to avoid any erroneous cleaning job.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">For example, the above described first through seventh preferred processes are implemented as a control software program. The CPU <b>21</b> executes a selected one of the control software programs in the RAM <b>23</b> for controlling a fuser cleaning job sequence according to the current invention. The above fuser cleaning control software programs are optionally stored in the ROM <b>22</b> or a secondary storage that is accessed by the HDD <b>34</b>. In alternative implementation, the above described first through seventh preferred processes are implemented as a hardware unit.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, a graph illustrates parameters for the fuser cleaning job to be performed in the above described preferred processes according to the current invention. The y axis indicates whether or not the fuser cleaning job is on or off while the x axis indicates duration in time. In this exemplary sequence, immediately following an image-forming or print job, a first exemplary cleaning job is illustrated. During the first cleaning job, the fuser is turned on and off a predetermine number of times N. After the fuser is activated to rotate without any image-transfer sheet for a first predetermined period a, it is deactivated for a second predetermined period b for physically separating the collected residual toner from the fuser separation pawl <b>102</b>. In this example, the activation period a is shorter than the deactivation period b, and the surface temperature on the fuser is maintained at a certain temperature. Following a predetermined number n of the burst or intermittent activations, the fuser is continuously activated for a predetermined amount of time C. Any combination of the above two activation patterns is practiced as the fuser cleaning job in a preferred process according to the current invention. In other words, the parameters a, b, C and N are optionally varied. Furthermore, although in the above example, the fuser cleaning takes place immediately subsequent to a print job, the relative relation between the fuser cleaning job and the print job is optionally changed in alternative processes.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">It is to be understood, however, that even though numerous characteristics and advantages of the present invention have been set forth in the foregoing description, together with details of the structure and function of the invention, the disclosure is illustrative only, and that although changes may be made in detail, especially in matters of shape, size and arrangement of parts, as well as implementation in software, hardware, or a combination of both, the changes are within the principles of the invention to the full extent indicated by the broad general meaning of the terms in which the appended claims are expressed.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>anticipating a print operation in the image-forming device to generate a print preparation command;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cleaning residual toner from the fuser in response to the print preparation command prior to forming an image on an image-transfer sheet in the image-forming device by intermittently activating and deactivating for a predetermined number of times to rotate a fuser roller in the fuser and collecting the residual toner;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming the image on the image-transfer sheet; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>fusing the image on the image-transfer sheet at a first predetermined temperature.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said cleaning step further comprises additional steps of:
<claim-text>rotating a fuser roller in the fuser for a predetermined amount of time; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>collecting the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said cleaning step further comprises additional steps of:
<claim-text>intermittently rotating a fuser roller in the fuser for a predetermined number of times;</claim-text>
<claim-text>rotating a fuser roller in the fuser for a predetermined amount of time; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>collecting the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said cleaning step further comprises additional steps of:
<claim-text>rotating a fuser roller in the fuser for a predetermined amount of time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>intermittently rotating a fuser roller in the fuser for a predetermined number of times; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>collecting the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">3</claim-ref> or <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">4</claim-ref> wherein said collecting step further comprises additional step of activating a pressure roller and a cleaning roller for a predetermined amount of time for collecting the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the fuser roller, the pressure roller and the cleaning roller are simultaneously rotated.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein said cleaning step is performed at a second predetermined temperature that is lower than the first predetermined temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said cleaning step is interrupted by said forming step of forming the image.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said forming step of forming the image is suspended during said cleaning step.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the print preparation command is generated when one of a predetermined set of information on the image-forming device is accessed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device, comprising:
<claim-text>a fuser for fusing an image on an image-transfer sheet at a first predetermined temperature;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a user information access unit for obtaining a predetermined set of information to anticipate a print operation in the image-forming device so as to generate a print preparation command;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control unit connected to said user information access unit and said fuser for controlling a cleaning sequence for cleaning residual toner from said fuser in response to the print preparation command prior to fusing an image on an image-transfer sheet in said fuser, said control unit generating a cleaning complete signal upon finishing the cleaning sequence;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a writing unit connected to said control unit for forming the image on the image-transfer sheet in response to the cleaning complete signal, wherein said fuser fuses the image on the image-transfer sheet after the cleaning sequence, wherein said fuser further comprises a fuser roller, said control unit activating and deactivating said fuser for a predetermined number of times for intermittently rotating said fuser roller in said fuser in order to collect the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said fuser further comprises a fuser roller, said control unit activating said fuser for rotating said fuser roller for a predetermined amount of time in order to collect the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said fuser further comprises a fuser roller, said control unit activating said fuser for intermittently rotating said fuser roller for a predetermined number of times and for additionally rotating said fuser roller for a predetermined amount of time to collect the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said fuser further comprises a fuser roller, said control unit activating said fuser for rotating said fuser roller for a predetermined amount of time and for additionally and intermittently rotating said fuser roller for a predetermined number of times to collect the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">13</claim-ref> or <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">14</claim-ref> wherein said fuser further comprises a pressure roller and a cleaning roller, said control unit simultaneously activating to rotate said fuser roller, said pressure roller and said cleaning roller for a predetermined amount of time for collecting the residual toner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the cleaning sequence is performed at a second predetermined temperature that is lower than the first predetermined temperature.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said control unit interrupts the cleaning sequence when said printer engine forms the image on the image-transfer sheet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said control unit suspends said printer engine from forming the image during the cleaning sequence.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The system for cleaning a fuser in an image-forming device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said user information access unit generates the print preparation command when one of a predetermined set of information on the image-forming device is accessed.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
