<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297576-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297576</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11195791</doc-number>
<date>20050803</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>94118488 A</doc-number>
<date>20050603</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>316</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>84</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438149</main-classification>
<further-classification>257E21441</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Method for fabricating thin film transistor (TFT) display</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0178527</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Liao et al.</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-280041</doc-number>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>594339</doc-number>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00004">
<othercit>Jia-Chong Ho et al., “Pentacene Organic Thin-Film Transistor Integrated with Color Twisted Nematic Liquid Crystals Display (CTNLCD)”, 2004.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00005">
<othercit>Joost P. A. Vogels et al., “Robust Flexible LCDs with Paintable Technology”, 2004.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>17</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438149</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438455</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438458</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060275959</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061207</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Huang</last-name>
<first-name>Liang-Yin</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hsinchu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ho</last-name>
<first-name>Jia-Chong</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hsinchu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Cheng-Chung</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hsinchu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Liao</last-name>
<first-name>Chi-Chang</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hsinchu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Rabin &amp; Berdo, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Industrial Technology Research Institute</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Hsinchu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Geyer</last-name>
<first-name>Scott B.</first-name>
<department>2812</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Ullah</last-name>
<first-name>Elias</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method for fabricating a thin film transistor (TFT) display is provided, wherein the processes of a liquid crystal substrate and an organic thin film transistor (OTFT) substrate are separated. The fabrication of liquid crystal substrate employs the technology of polymer encapsulated liquid crystal molecule, and leaves the polymeric layer as a substrate using a sacrificial layer, so as to improve the flexibility. And the TFT substrate has a high adhesive polymeric protective layer provided on its surface, so as to combine the fabricated TFT substrate and the liquid crystal substrate by laminating. Thereby, the processes of the liquid crystal substrate and the TFT substrate will not affect each other, to improve the process yield and meet the demand for the variety of products.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="224.71mm" wi="164.93mm" file="US07297576-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="244.77mm" wi="171.20mm" file="US07297576-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="222.17mm" wi="167.22mm" file="US07297576-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="241.30mm" wi="166.12mm" file="US07297576-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="228.43mm" wi="141.56mm" file="US07297576-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="251.97mm" wi="166.20mm" file="US07297576-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a method for fabricating a thin film transistor (TFT) display, in particular, to a method for fabricating a TFT display wherein the display section and TFT section are recombined after being processed separately, thereby improving the process yield.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In recent years, flexible flat panel display has the advantages such as low power consumption and high image quality, therefore it soon becomes the focus product since it came into the market. At the same time, based on the market demands for accommodation, portability and convenience, efforts have been exerted to develop flexible liquid crystal display (Flexi LCD) by those skilled in the art around the world, and many big companies have joined in this “display revolution” one after another. Organic thin film transistor (OTFT) makes use of organic molecule materials to develop TFTs adapted for electronic products. The transistor element may maintain its property and achieve normal image quality effect when the panel is bended. Such application accelerates the accomplishment of the flexible electronic products (such as displays), and has a lower cost.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Due to the wide application range of flexible electronic products, for example, from various portable electronic products to large-scale advertising signboard, the diversity of the products and the variety of the display modes are among the important factors to be considered in the commercialization of this technology.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As in the prior art, Philips Electronics of Netherlands has proposed modes of fabricating polymer dispersed liquid crystal (PDLC) and electronic ink technology (E-ink) displays directly on the organic thin film transistor (OTFT). However, its disadvantage resides in that the display section cannot be fabricated until the fabrication of the OTFT is finished, and the OTFT section might be damaged while fabricating the display section, thereby resulting in a lowered yield.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In view of the above problems, an object of the invention is to provide a method for fabricating a TFT display, wherein using the property of polymeric material, the display substrate and TFT substrate can be combined together by laminating after separate process, thereby achieving the improved yield and varied TFT display modes, and substantially solving the problems in the prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Therefore, in order to achieve the above object, the method for fabricating the TFT display disclosed in the invention comprises the following steps: first, providing a sacrificial layer which includes a support substrate and a release layer, wherein the support substrate is used for supporting, and the release layer is convenient to release the elements described below from the support substrate; then, forming a polymer layer on the sacrificial layer; and then fabricating an alignment layer on the polymer layer; afterwards, forming an electrode layer on the alignment layer; next, forming a precursor mixed layer fabricated by mixing liquid crystal and polymer, and illuminating the entire or part of the precursor mixed layer, separating the liquid crystal and polymer so as to form polymer spacers and an upper plate to encapsulate the liquid crystal on the electrode layer to fabricate a liquid crystal substrate; subsequently, providing a TFT substrate having a adhesive polymeric protective layer on the surface, and combining the TFT substrate and the liquid crystal substrate by laminating; finally, removing the sacrificial layer of the liquid crystal substrate, and the TFT display is fabricated.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Wherein, since the protective layer of the TFT substrate is a polymeric material, which is selected from thermoset or photopolymerizable materials, the polymeric material is cured and polymerized through heating and illuminating, to combine with the liquid crystal substrate. In addition, the step of removing the sacrificial layer has made the bottom layer of the liquid crystal substrate into a polymer layer, and the bottom layer of the TFT substrate of the present invention may also be made of polymer, therefore the flexibility of the TFT display can be improved, and various TFT display modes can be increased.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">To further understand the object, structure, features and functions of the present invention, further details will be given with reference to the embodiments as follows.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Further scope of applicability of the present invention will become apparent from the detailed description given hereinafter. However, it should be understood that the detailed description and specific examples, while indicating preferred embodiments of the invention, are given by way of illustration only, since various changes and modifications within the spirit and scope of the invention will become apparent to those skilled in the art from this detailed description.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present invention will become more fully understood from the detailed description given herein below for illustration only, and thus are not limitative of the present invention, and wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a flowchart of the method for fabricating a TFT display according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A to 2I</figref> is the process of fabricating an OTFT display according to the embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic view of forming a polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer by using partial illumination according to the embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref> is respectively a schematic view of combining the liquid crystal substrate and the OTFT substrate through heating or illuminating according to the embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the method for fabricating the OTFT primarily comprises the steps as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">First, providing a sacrificial layer (step <b>100</b>); then, forming a polymer layer on the sacrificial layer (step <b>110</b>); and then forming an electrode layer on the polymer layer (step <b>120</b>); afterwards, forming an alignment layer on the electrode layer (step <b>130</b>); next, forming a polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer on the alignment layer so as to fabricate a liquid crystal substrate (step <b>140</b>); subsequently, providing an OTFT substrate having a adhesive polymeric protective layer, and combining the TFT substrate and the liquid crystal substrate by laminating (step <b>150</b>); finally, removing the sacrificial layer, and the TFT display is fabricated (step <b>160</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Wherein, the TFT substrate employed in the invention is made of TFT selected from the group consisting of organic, inorganic TFT materials or a mixture of both. Taking only the OTFT for example hereinafter, and referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A to 2I</figref> in order, the fabrication of the OTFT display of the embodiments of the present invention is described.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, first, a support substrate <b>11</b> is coated on a removable release layer <b>12</b> to constitute a sacrificial layer <b>10</b> (step <b>100</b>). The support substrate <b>11</b> is used for supporting the elements described below, and the removable release layer <b>12</b> can release the elements described below from the support substrate <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Then, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, a polymer layer <b>20</b> is formed on the release layer <b>12</b> of the sacrificial layer <b>10</b> (step <b>110</b>). The polymer layer <b>20</b> has a thickness between 3 and 25 micrometers (μm), and its material is polyimide (PI).</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Then, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>, an electrode layer <b>30</b> is fabricated on the polymer layer <b>20</b> (step <b>120</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>, further alignment is conducted on the electrode layer <b>30</b> (step <b>130</b>), wherein first coating an alignment layer <b>40</b> (e.g., polyimide) on the electrode layer <b>30</b>, and then creating periodical groove structures on the surface of the alignment layer through rub of an alignment fabric <b>41</b> by rubbing alignment technology, to induce the liquid crystal molecules formed subsequently to arrange along the groove regularly, or adding a material layer of illumination-induced alignment effect into the electrode layer <b>30</b> to carry out the alignment of liquid crystal molecules.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Afterwards, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2E</figref>, the precursor mixed layer <b>50</b> by mixing the liquid crystal and the polymer is coated on the alignment layer <b>40</b>, wherein the polymer of the precursor mixed layer <b>50</b> is a photopolymerizable material. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref>, the liquid crystal and the polymer are separated by ultraviolet light illumination, so as to form a polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer <b>51</b> on the alignment layer <b>40</b>, so as to fabricate the liquid crystal substrate <b>60</b> (step <b>140</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Again, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2G</figref>, an OTFT substrate <b>70</b> is provided. Here, an array of OTFTs <b>100</b> of the bottom gate pattern is directly formed on the polymer support substrate <b>90</b>, and the surface is covered with a protective layer <b>80</b> having adhesive polymer (e.g., polyvinyl alcohol (PVA)), to function as a protection and an enclosure. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2H</figref>, the fabricated liquid crystal substrate <b>60</b> and the OTFT substrate <b>70</b> can be affixed together by laminating, as long as they are aligned with each other (step <b>150</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Finally, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2I</figref>, the release layer <b>12</b> strips the entire sacrificial layer <b>10</b>, so that an OTFT display <b>200</b> is fabricated (step <b>160</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Since in this embodiment, the support substrate <b>11</b> used for supporting the liquid crystal substrate may be removed by release technology, the entire OTFT display <b>200</b> can be made very thin (less than 150 μm), and both the upper and lower surfaces of the OTFT display <b>200</b> of this embodiment are polymeric materials, making it highly flexible.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Additionally, this embodiment employs the illumination for the entire precursor mixed layer <b>50</b> of the liquid crystal and polymer to form a film-shaped polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer <b>51</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2F</figref>). In particular, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer <b>51</b> including multiple spacers <b>52</b> can also be formed through illuminating or molding part of the thermoset polymer of the precursor mixed layer <b>50</b> of the liquid crystal and polymer, then aligning it with the OTFT substrate <b>70</b>, and illuminating and heating the whole layer so that the two are affixed together by laminating (step <b>150</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Furthermore, the polymeric protective layer <b>80</b> of the OTFT substrate <b>70</b> is selected from thermoset or photopolymerized material. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref>, in the step of combining the OTFT substrate <b>70</b> and the liquid crystal substrate <b>60</b>, the polymeric protective layer is cured and polymerized through heating or illuminating simultaneously, thereby combining the liquid crystal substrate <b>60</b> and the OTFT substrate <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Still further, the OTFT substrate <b>70</b> of this embodiment is selected from the OTFT substrates comprising an OTFT <b>100</b> with a bottom contact, top contact, bottom gate or top gate pattern. However, support substrate <b>90</b> of the OTFT substrate <b>70</b> is either an organic material or an inorganic material, so that the fabricated OTFT display <b>200</b> has at least one polymer substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In view of the above, the TFT display according to this invention utilizes polymer to encapsulate liquid crystal molecule, so as to realize the flexible display technology, and combined with the release process, thereby the process rate can be improved greatly. In addition, by using the property of polymer and through laminating, the liquid crystal substrate and the TFT substrate is fabricated separately before combining them together. Therefore, if a TFT display is fabricated with modular process, the temperature and method of the process selected by the liquid crystal substrate and the TFT substrate will not affect each other. Thus, the property of each may be improved to meet the demand for various TFT display modes, and an increased process yield is obtained.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The invention being thus described, it will be obvious that the same may be varied in many ways. Such variations are not to be regarded as a departure from the spirit and scope of the invention, and all such modifications as would be obvious to one skilled in the art are intended to be included within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for fabricating a thin film transistor (TFT) display, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>providing a sacrificial layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a polymer layer on the sacrificial layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming an electrode layer on the polymer layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming an alignment layer on the electrode layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer on the alignment layer, to fabricate a liquid crystal substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a TFT substrate having a polymeric protective layer and combining the TFT substrate with the liquid crystal substrate by a laminating; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing the sacrificial layer, thereby fabricating the TFT display.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the TFT substrate is made of a TFT of which a material is selected from the group consisting of an organic TFT material, an inorganic TFT material and a mixture of the organic and the inorganic TFT materials.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the sacrificial layer includes a support substrate and a release layer on the support substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of forming a polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer on the alignment layer, to fabricate a liquid crystal substrate comprises the steps of:
<claim-text>forming a precursor mixed layer on the electrode layer, where the precursor mixed layer is made by mixing a liquid crystal and a polymer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>separating the liquid crystal and the polymer of the precursor mixed layer using an illumination, to form the polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the step of separating the liquid crystal and the polymer of the precursor mixed layer using an illumination is implemented by illuminating the entire precursor mixed layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the step of separating the liquid crystal and the polymer of the precursor mixed layer using an illumination is implemented by illuminating a partial of the precursor mixed layer, to form the polymer encapsulated liquid crystal layer having a plurality of spacers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the polymer of the precursor mixed layer is selected from the group consisting of a photopolymerizable material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of combining the TFT substrate with the liquid crystal substrate by a laminating comprises the step of heating the polymeric protective layer of the TFT substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of combining the TFT substrate with the liquid crystal substrate by a laminating comprises the step of illuminating the polymeric protective layer of the TFT substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the polymer layer is polyimide (PI).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the polymer layer has a thickness between 3 and 25 micrometer (μm).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a material of the polymeric protective layer is selected from the group consisting of a thermoset material and a photopolymerizable material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the material of the polymeric protective layer is a polyvinyl alcohol (PVA).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the polymeric protective layer comprises an inorganic material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the TFT substrate is made of a TFT selected from the group consisting of a bottom contact, a top contact, a bottom gate and a top gate thin film transistors.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the TFT substrate comprises a polymeric support substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method for fabricating the TFT display of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the TFT substrate comprises a support substrate of an inorganic material.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
