<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298214-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298214</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11154759</doc-number>
<date>20050615</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>93118811 A</doc-number>
<date>20040628</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>134</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330297</main-classification>
<further-classification>330136</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Amplifying circuit with variable supply voltage</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4873493</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fujiwara</name>
<date>19891000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330136</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6624702</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Dening</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330297</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6639471</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Matsuura et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330297</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330127</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330129</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330136</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330278</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330279</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330297</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050285682</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051229</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Chao-Cheng</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hsin-Chu</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Tzung-Ming</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Feng</last-name>
<first-name>Chieh-Min</first-name>
<address>
<city>Zhudong Town</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Realtek Semiconductor Corp.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Khanh Van</first-name>
<department>2817</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An amplifying circuit with a variable supply voltage and a method thereof are disclosed. The amplifying circuit employs a voltage converter to adjust the supply voltage, thereby upgrading the energy efficiency of the circuit. The circuit also includes a control device, which can generate a control signal for controlling the voltage converter according to an output signal or input signal of the circuit.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="128.52mm" wi="197.70mm" file="US07298214-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="200.74mm" wi="139.95mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298214-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="221.32mm" wi="141.99mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298214-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="173.06mm" wi="133.77mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298214-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="178.14mm" wi="140.04mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298214-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="213.95mm" wi="130.73mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298214-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="233.34mm" wi="139.62mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298214-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">(a). Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates in general to electronic circuits, and more particularly to amplifying circuits with a variable supply voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">(b). Description of the Prior Arts</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Amplifiers are very common circuit components. However, most amplifiers do not utilize power efficiently. In general, only a part of the energy provided to an amplifier will be used to drive the amplifier outputting an output signal according to an input signal. Most of the energy is wasted.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is therefore an object of the present invention to provide an amplifying circuit with a variable supply voltage for solving the above-mentioned problems.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Another object of the present invention is to provide a method for adjusting a supply voltage provided to an amplifier that generates an output signal according to an input signal, thereby solving the above-mentioned problems.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to an embodiment of the present invention, the amplifying circuit includes an amplifier and a supply voltage adjusting circuit. The supply voltage adjusting circuit, coupled to the amplifier, is for adjusting the voltage provided to the amplifier according to an input signal or an output signal of the amplifier.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">According to another embodiment of the present invention, the method for adjusting the supply voltage includes: generating a control signal according to at least one of the input signal and the output signal; and adjusting the supply voltage according to the control signal.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a preferred embodiment of the amplifying circuit according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a circuit diagram of an embodiment of the voltage converter.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A</figref>, <b>3</b>B and <b>3</b>C are respectively equivalent circuit diagrams of the voltage converter of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> under different conditions.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of another preferred embodiment of the amplifying circuit according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a preferred embodiment of the amplifying circuit according to the present invention. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the amplifying circuit <b>1</b> includes an amplifier <b>10</b>, a voltage converter <b>11</b>, and a control device <b>12</b>. The voltage converter <b>11</b> coupled to the amplifier <b>10</b> can transfer a received source voltage V<sub>dd </sub>into a supply voltage, and provide the supply voltage to the amplifier <b>10</b>. If the gain of the voltage converter <b>11</b> is G, the supply voltage should be G*V<sub>dd</sub>. The voltage converter <b>11</b> can further dynamically adjust the gain G according to a control signal outputted by the control device <b>12</b> as described in the following.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The control device <b>12</b> can generate the control signal according to an output signal of the amplifier <b>10</b>. In this embodiment, the control device <b>12</b> includes a peak detector <b>121</b>, a voltage level sensor <b>122</b> and a gain control unit <b>123</b>. The peak detector <b>121</b> coupled to an output of the amplifier <b>10</b> is for detecting a voltage peak of the output signal of the amplifier <b>10</b>. The voltage level sensor <b>122</b> coupled to the peak detector <b>121</b> has a plurality of voltage ranges, and outputs a signal to the gain control unit <b>123</b> according to the voltage range that the voltage peak detected by the peak detector <b>121</b> falls into. Consequently, the gain control unit <b>123</b> can output the control signal to the voltage converter <b>11</b> according to the voltage range corresponding to the voltage peak. The principle and implementation of the peak detector <b>121</b>, the voltage level sensor <b>122</b> and the gain control unit <b>123</b> is well-known to those skilled in the art and not described in detail in this specification.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">As described above, the voltage converter <b>11</b> can dynamically adjust its gain value G according to the control signal, and thereby provide an appropriate supply voltage to the amplifier <b>10</b>. In this embodiment, the voltage converter <b>11</b> employs various coupling configurations of capacitors and switches to generate a plurality of gain values G. Hence, by turning on/off the switches, the voltage converter <b>11</b> can adjust the gain values G.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a circuit diagram of an embodiment of the voltage converter <b>11</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the voltage converter <b>11</b><i>a </i>is a switched-capacitor voltage converter, and includes two capacitors (C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>) and ten switches (S<sub>1 </sub>to S<sub>10</sub>). The input voltage (i.e. the voltage at X) is V<sub>dd</sub>, and the output voltage (i.e. the voltage at Y) is G*V<sub>dd</sub>, wherein G is the gain value of the voltage converter <b>11</b><i>a</i>. In operation, the states of switches S<sub>1 </sub>and S<sub>2 </sub>become connected (ON) or disconnected (OFF) according to a first clock signal and the states of switches S<sub>3 </sub>and S<sub>4 </sub>become connected or disconnected according to a second clock signal, wherein the first and second clock signals correspond to the control signal generated by the gain control unit <b>123</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. It is notable that the switches S<b>1</b>, S<b>2</b> and the switches S<b>3</b>, S<b>4</b> would not become connected simultaneously.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The voltage converter <b>11</b><i>a </i>of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> corresponds to three gain values G, that is, 1, 0.5, and −1. These gain values G can be obtained by changing the on/off states of the switches S<sub>5 </sub>to S<sub>10</sub>. The relation between the gain value G and the on/off states of switches is described as below:</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">(1) If switches S<sub>5</sub>, S<sub>6 </sub>and S<sub>9 </sub>are ON and switches S<sub>7</sub>, S<sub>8 </sub>and S<sub>10 </sub>are OFF, then <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> can be equivalent to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>. Accordingly, when switches S<sub>1 </sub>and S<sub>2 </sub>are ON (meanwhile, switches S<sub>3 </sub>and S<sub>4 </sub>are OFF), the voltage at capacitor C<sub>1 </sub>becomes V<sub>dd</sub>. Afterward, when S<sub>3 </sub>and S<sub>4 </sub>are ON (meanwhile, S<sub>1 </sub>and S<sub>2 </sub>are OFF), the voltage V<sub>dd </sub>at capacitor C<sub>1 </sub>would be transferred to the capacitor C<sub>2 </sub>such that the voltage at Y also becomes V<sub>dd</sub>. Thus, the gain G under the present condition is 1.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">(2) If switches S<sub>6</sub>, S<sub>8 </sub>and S<sub>9 </sub>are ON and switches S<sub>5</sub>, S<sub>7 </sub>and S<sub>10 </sub>are OFF, then <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> can be equivalent to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>. Consequently, when switches S<sub>1 </sub>and S<sub>2 </sub>are ON (meanwhile, switches S<sub>3 </sub>and S<sub>4 </sub>are OFF), the voltage at capacitor C<sub>1 </sub>becomes V<sub>dd</sub>*(1−G) (i.e. the voltage difference between X and Y). As a result, when S<sub>3 </sub>and S<sub>4 </sub>are ON (meanwhile, S<sub>1 </sub>and S<sub>2 </sub>are OFF), the voltage V<sub>dd</sub>*(1−G) at capacitor C<sub>1 </sub>would be transferred to the capacitor C<sub>2 </sub>such that the voltage at Y becomes V<sub>dd</sub>*(1−G). Hence the following equation is obtained:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>V</i><sub>dd</sub><i>*G=V</i><sub>dd</sub>*(1−<i>G</i>)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Obviously, it can be derived that G equals 0.5.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">(3) If switches S<sub>5</sub>, S<sub>7 </sub>and S<sub>10 </sub>are ON and switches S<sub>6</sub>, S<sub>8 </sub>and S<sub>9 </sub>are OFF, then <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> can be equivalent to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref>. Therefore, when switches S<sub>1 </sub>and S<sub>2 </sub>are ON (meanwhile, switches S<sub>3 </sub>and S<sub>4 </sub>are OFF), the voltage at capacitor C, becomes V<sub>dd</sub>. Subsequently, when switches S<sub>3 </sub>and S<sub>4 </sub>are ON (meanwhile, S<sub>1 </sub>and S<sub>2 </sub>are OFF), the voltage V<sub>dd </sub>at capacitor C<sub>1 </sub>would be transferred to the capacitor C<sub>2 </sub>such that the voltage at Y becomes −V<sub>dd</sub>. Thus, G is −1.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Those skilled in the art can easily design a voltage converter having a plurality of gain values according to the present invention. Any embodiment for dynamically adjusting the supply voltage of an amplifier through a voltage converter would not lie outside the spirit and scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of another preferred embodiment of the amplifying circuit according to the present invention. Comparing the amplifying circuit <b>1</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with the amplifying circuit <b>4</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the difference between them is that the control devices <b>12</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> are respectively coupled to the output and input terminals of the amplifier <b>10</b>. That is, the control device <b>12</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> generates the control signal according to an input signal of the amplifier <b>10</b> rather than an output signal. More specifically, the peak detector <b>121</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> detects the voltage peak of the input signal of the amplifier <b>10</b> and provides it to the voltage level sensor <b>123</b>. The remaining portion of the amplifying circuit <b>4</b> operates in the same way as that of the amplifying circuit <b>1</b>, and would not be described again here.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">While the present invention has been shown and described with reference to the preferred embodiments thereof and in terms of the illustrative drawings, it should not be considered as limited thereby. Various possible modifications and alterations could be conceived of by one skilled in the art to the form and the content of any particular embodiment, without departing from the scope and the spirit of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An amplifying circuit with a variable supply voltage comprising:
<claim-text>an amplifier for receiving an input signal and outputting an output signal with the variable supply voltage; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a supply voltage adjusting circuit coupled to the amplifier for adjusting the variable supply voltage according to at least one of the input signal and the output signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the supply voltage adjusting circuit comprises a voltage converter having a plurality of gain values, the voltage converter selecting one of the gain values for providing the variable supply voltage according to at least one of the input signal and the output signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The amplifying circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the voltage converter selects one of the gain values according to a voltage peak of at least one of the input and the output signals.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The amplifying circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the supply voltage adjusting circuit adjusts the variable supply voltage according to a voltage peak of at least one of the input and the output signals.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The amplifying circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a control device coupled to the amplifier for generating a control signal according to at least one of the input signal and the output signal such that the supply voltage adjusting circuit adjusts the variable supply voltage according to the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The amplifying circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the supply voltage adjusting circuit comprises:
<claim-text>an input for receiving an original supply voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output for outputting the variable supply voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of capacitors coupled to the input and the output; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of switches respectively coupled to at least one of the input, the output, and the capacitors, each of the switches being switched on or off according to the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The amplifying circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the control device comprises:
<claim-text>a peak detector for detecting a voltage peak of at least one of the input signal and the output signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a voltage level sensor coupled to the peak detector for generating a sensing signal according to the voltage peak; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gain control unit for outputting the control signal according to the sensing signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The amplifying circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the voltage converter selects one of the gain values for providing the variable supply voltage according to the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The amplifying circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the supply voltage adjusting circuit adjusts the variable supply voltage dynamically.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A method for adjusting a supply voltage provided to an amplifier that generates an output signal according to an input signal, the method cormprising:
<claim-text>generating a control signal according to at least one of the input signal and the output signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>adjusting the supply voltage according to the control signal, the step of adjusting the supply voltage cormprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>selecting one of a plurality of pain values according to the control signal; and adjusting the supply voltage according to the selected gain value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the gain value is selected according to a voltage peak of at least one of the input signal and the output signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the control signal is generated according to a voltage peak of at least one of the input signal and the output signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the step of adjusting the supply voltage comprises:
<claim-text>changing on/off states of a plurality of switches coupled to a plurality of capacitors according to the control signal, so as to adjust the supply voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of switches and capacitors form a voltage converter such that the supply voltage is adjusted after passing through the voltage converter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the step of generating the control signal comprises:
<claim-text>detecting a voltage peak of at least one of the input signal and the output signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating a sensing signal according to the voltage peak; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating the control signal according to the sensing signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the supply voltage is adjusted dynamically.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. An amplifying circuit with a variable supply voltage comprising:
<claim-text>an amplifier for receiving an input signal and outputting an output signal with the variable supply voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control device coupled to the amplifier for generating a control signal, comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a peak detector for detecting a voltage peak of at least one of the input signal and the output signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a voltage level sensor coupled to the peak detector for generating a sensing signal according to the voltage peak; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gain control unit for outputting the control signal according to the sensing signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a supply voltage adjusting circuit coupled to the amplifier for adjusting the variable supply voltage according to the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The amplifying circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the supply voltage adjusting circuit comprises:
<claim-text>an input for receiving an original supply voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output for outputting the variable supply voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of capacitors coupled to the input and the output; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of switches respectively coupled to at least one of the input, the output, and the capacitors, each of the switches being switched on or off according to the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method for adjusting a supply voltage provided to an amplifier that generates an output signal according to an input signal, the method comprising:
<claim-text>generating a control signal, comprising:
<claim-text>detecting a voltage peak of at least one of the input signal and the output signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating a sensing signal according to the voltage peak; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating the control signal according to the sensing signal; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>adjusting the supply voltage according to the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the step of adjusting the supply voltage comprises:
<claim-text>changing on/off states of a plurality of switches coupled to a plurality of capacitors according to the control signal, so as to adjust the supply voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
