<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298950-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298950</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10572448</doc-number>
<date>20040904</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>103 43 270</doc-number>
<date>20030917</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>6</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385135</main-classification>
<further-classification>385134</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Distribution cabinet for optical fibers</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5093887</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Witte</name>
<date>19920300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385135</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5787219</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mueller et al.</name>
<date>19980700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385134</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6097872</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kusuda et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385134</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6311008</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Foss</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385135</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO02/05002</doc-number>
<date>20020100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385134</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385135</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385136</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385137</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070058917</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070315</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Frohlich</last-name>
<first-name>Franz-Friedrich</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hagen</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>DE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>DE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Roberson</last-name>
<first-name>Keith A.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Corning Cable Systems LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Hickory</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Healy</last-name>
<first-name>Brian</first-name>
<department>2883</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Lam</last-name>
<first-name>Hung</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/EP2004/009890</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040904</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20060317</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2005/036231</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20050421</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The invention relates to a distribution cabinet (<b>10</b>) for optical fibers, comprising a housing (<b>11</b>) and a frame (<b>18</b>) that is pivotally mounted inside the housing (<b>11</b>). Cables encompassing optical fibers that are guided therein can be routed into and/or directed out of the distribution cabinet, the cables being routed to the frame (<b>18</b>) from a rear side (<b>14</b>) of the housing (<b>11</b>) and being routed away from the frame in the direction of the rear side. Subassemblies are fastened to the frame (<b>18</b>) in order to connect the optical fibers that are guided within the cables. At least one holding device (<b>23</b>) for the cables is fastened to the pivotally mounted frame (<b>18</b>), the cables being fixable to the holding device (<b>23</b>). The holding device (<b>23</b>) is configured so as to be pivotable relative to the housing (<b>11</b>) along with the frame (<b>18</b>), while also being pivotable relative to the frame (<b>18</b>).</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="92.71mm" wi="113.96mm" file="US07298950-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="163.24mm" wi="115.06mm" file="US07298950-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="153.16mm" wi="111.93mm" file="US07298950-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="125.48mm" wi="109.30mm" file="US07298950-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This National stage application claims the benefit of International Application No. PCT/EP04/009890, filed on Sep. 4, 2004, which claims the benefit of German Patent Application No. 10343270.1, filed on Sep. 17, 2003, and which was not published in the English language under PCT Article 21(2).</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a distribution cabinet for optical fibers.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Distribution cabinets are required when designing optical fiber cable networks in order to ensure the cables are arranged in a structured fashion. One requirement made of distribution cabinets for optical fibers is that they be equipped to the maximum extent with a high packing density and at the same time little mechanical load on the optical fibers.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The prior art discloses distribution cabinets for optical fibers in which assemblies for connecting optical fibers which are routed by means of patch cables are arranged, such that they can pivot, in a frame which can pivot in relation to a housing of the distribution cabinet. In distribution cabinets for optical fibers of this type, the cables are routed into the distribution cabinet for from an upper face and/or a lower face of the housing in the region of a rear face of the housing and from the rear face of the housing to the pivotable frame. According to the prior art, the cables are in this case attached firstly in a region of the rear face of the housing and secondly to the pivotable frame. In the case of distribution cabinets for optical fibers of this type, the frame is pivoted in relation to the housing or out of the housing in order to gain access to the rear face of the assemblies which are accommodated in the frame. When the frame is pivoted, the cables are also moved and mechanically loaded since they are fixed to the frame. On account of the cables being rigidly fixed to the pivotable frame in the manner customary according to the prior art, the cables are bent, compressed or even twisted, and this often leads to the optical transmission properties of the optical fibers which run in the cables being impaired. In addition, a mechanical force is exerted on the frame on account of the cables being rigidly fixed to the pivotable frame, and in extreme cases this may lead to the frame no longer being able to move. If a plurality of cables in the form of a bundle are routed from the rear face of the housing in the direction of the frame and fixed to the frame, the above problems are intensified since the cables which are combined to form one bundle adhere to one another in a frictionally engaging manner on account of the properties of the cable casing and therefore can form a rigid connection. Consequently, it is problematical to route the cables from the rear face of the housing of the distribution cabinet in the direction of the pivotable frame in the case of distribution cabinets for optical fibers which are known from the prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Against this background, the present invention is based on the problem of providing a novel distribution cabinet for optical fibers.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">This problem is solved by a distribution cabinet for optical fibers including the features of the present invention shown and described herein. In the distribution cabinet for optical fibers according to the invention, at least one holding device for the cables is attached to the frame which is mounted such that it can pivot, it being possible to fix the cables to the each holding device, and the each holding device being formed such that it can pivot firstly together with the frame in relation to the housing and secondly in relation to the frame. The mechanical load on the cables when the frame is pivoted is minimized on account of the ability of the each holding device to pivot in relation to the likewise pivotable frame. The difficulties known from the prior art are [thus] overcome.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to one preferred embodiment of the invention, the each holding device can be pivoted in relation to the frame in such a way that in each position of the frame the holding device is oriented toward the rear face of the housing. In this case, the each holding device is oriented toward a region of the rear face or rear wall of the housing in which the cables which can be routed into and/or out of the distribution cabinet are routed and/or attached.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The holding device is preferably attached to the rear face of the housing by means of at least one traction device in each case, to be precise in the region or in the vicinity of the region in which the cables which can be routed into and/or out of the distribution cabinet are routed and/or attached. The traction device is relatively relaxed in the position in which the relative distance between the respective holding device and the region of the rear face of the housing is the shortest, with the each traction device being tensioned as the relative distance increases.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Preferred embodiments of the invention can be found in the following detailed description. One exemplary embodiment is explained in greater detail with reference to the drawing figures, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>: shows a highly schematic plan view of a distribution cabinet for optical fibers according to the invention, with a pivoting frame in the starting position,</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>: shows a highly schematic plan view of the distribution cabinet for optical fibers according to the invention from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, with a pivoting frame pivoted out of the distribution cabinet,</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>: shows a highly schematic side view of the distribution cabinet for optical fibers according to the invention from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, with the pivoting frame shown in the starting position and in the pivoted-out position, and</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>: shows a perspective side view of a detail of the distribution cabinet for optical fibers according to the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In the text which follows, the present invention is described in greater detail with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 4</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> show a plan view of the distribution cabinet for optical fibers according to the invention, while <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a front view of the same.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A distribution cabinet <b>10</b> for optical fibers has a housing <b>11</b> which is formed, inter alia, by two struts <b>12</b>, <b>13</b> in the region of a rear wall or rear face <b>14</b> of the distribution cabinet for optical fibers and by two struts <b>15</b>, <b>16</b> in the region of a front wall or front face <b>17</b> thereof. A pivotable frame <b>18</b> is arranged in the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> for optical fibers, it being possible to pivot the frame <b>18</b> in relation to the fixed housing <b>11</b> about a pivot axis <b>19</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows the distribution cabinet for optical fibers with a frame <b>18</b> pivoted into the housing <b>11</b>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the same with a frame <b>18</b> pivoted out of the housing <b>11</b>. It follows directly from this that the front face of assemblies which are positioned in the frame can be accessed in the position of the pivotable frame <b>18</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, whereas the rear face of these assemblies can be accessed in the position of the frame <b>18</b> which is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Adjacent to the rear face <b>14</b>, cables (not illustrated in detail) are routed into and optionally out of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> for optical fibers from an upper face and/or a lower face of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b>. In this case, the cables which can be routed into and/or out of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> for optical fibers are routed and optionally attached in a region <b>20</b> of the rear wall <b>14</b>. Starting from this region <b>20</b>, the cables are then fed to the pivotable frame <b>18</b> in order to ultimately feed the cables to assemblies, which are arranged in the frame <b>18</b>, for connecting the optical fibers which are routed in the cables.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In the exemplary embodiment shown, the cables are fed to one end <b>21</b> of the pivotable frame <b>18</b> from the region <b>20</b>, with a guide rail <b>22</b> being rigidly connected to the frame <b>18</b> in the region of this end <b>21</b>. The cables can be routed in the vertical direction on the pivotable frame <b>18</b> along the guide rail <b>22</b>. For the purposes of the present invention, the cables are not attached directly to the guide rail <b>22</b> but rather to a holding device <b>23</b>, with the holding device <b>23</b> being formed such that it can pivot firstly together with the frame <b>18</b> in relation to the housing <b>11</b> and secondly can likewise pivot in relation to the frame <b>18</b>. The holding device <b>23</b> is accordingly not rigidly fixed to the pivotable frame <b>18</b> but engages thereon by means of a rotary bearing or hinge <b>24</b>. In this case, the rotary axis of the hinge <b>24</b> runs just like the pivot axis <b>19</b> of the frame <b>18</b> in an approximately vertical direction and therefore approximately parallel to the latter. As can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the guide rail <b>22</b> which is rigidly connected to the frame <b>18</b> does not extend over the entire vertical height of the pivotable frame <b>18</b> but only in the region of the top two thirds of the vertical height of the frame <b>18</b>. The holding device <b>23</b> is positioned below the guide rail <b>22</b>. It should be noted that <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the frame <b>18</b> in two different positions. The position according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is shown by solid lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, and the position according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is shown by dashed lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">For the purposes of the invention, the holding device <b>23</b> is formed such that it can pivot in relation to the frame <b>18</b> in such a way that the holding device <b>23</b> is oriented toward the rear face <b>14</b> of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> in each position of the pivotable frame <b>18</b>—be it in the position pivoted into the housing <b>11</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> or in the position pivoted out of the housing <b>11</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. It can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> that the holding device <b>23</b> is always oriented toward the region <b>20</b> in which the cables which can be routed into and/or out of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> are routed and/or attached. It can furthermore be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> that the holding device <b>23</b> is oriented toward the region <b>20</b> in such a way that an angular position of the holding device <b>23</b> with respect to the rear wall <b>14</b> of the housing <b>11</b> remains approximately unchanged in each position of the frame <b>18</b>. Therefore, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, in which the frame <b>18</b> is fully pivoted into the housing <b>11</b>, the angular position between the holding device <b>23</b> and the rear face <b>14</b> of the housing <b>11</b> is approximately 15°. If, however, the frame <b>18</b> is pivoted about its pivot axis <b>19</b> completely out of the housing <b>11</b>—the frame <b>18</b> is typically pivoted about its pivot axis <b>19</b> through 135° for this purpose—the angular position between the holding device <b>23</b> and the rear face <b>14</b> of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> changes only slightly. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, this angular position is approximately 25°. Therefore, while the guide rail <b>22</b> which is firmly connected to the pivoting frame <b>18</b> is pivoted through <b>1350</b> when the pivoting frame <b>18</b> moves from the position illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> to the position illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the angular position between the holding device <b>23</b> and the rear face <b>14</b> of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> changes only by approximately 10°. It follows directly from this that the cables which are attached to the holding device <b>23</b> are only subject to a low mechanical load despite the large pivoting movement of the frame <b>18</b>, and are therefore handled particularly carefully in the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> for optical fibers according to the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In order to assist the movement of the holding device <b>23</b> when the frame <b>18</b> is pivoted, or to assist the orientation of the holding device <b>23</b> toward the rear face <b>14</b> of the housing <b>11</b> in a controlled manner, the holding device <b>23</b> is connected to the rear face <b>14</b>, specifically to the region <b>20</b> of the rear face <b>14</b>, by means of a traction device <b>25</b>. The traction device <b>25</b> is attached by a first end <b>26</b> to a fixed point <b>27</b> of the region <b>20</b> of the rear face <b>14</b> and by a second end <b>28</b> to the holding device <b>23</b>. The traction device <b>25</b> may be in the form of a traction cord or a tension spring. The traction force in the traction device <b>25</b> is set such that the traction device <b>25</b> is relatively relaxed when there is an extremely small distance between the holding device <b>23</b> and the stationary point <b>27</b> or the region <b>20</b>. When the distance between the fixed point <b>27</b> and the holding device <b>23</b> increases, the traction device <b>25</b> is increasingly tensioned. This can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> in particular. The traction device is tensioned by the weight of the cables when the traction device <b>25</b> is in the form of a traction cord.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Preference is given to a refinement of the traction device in which there are two traction cords, with an accommodation depression which is made of plastic film being formed between the two traction cords, and it being possible to insert the cables into this accommodation depression. In the position of the frame <b>18</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the two traction cords and the accommodation depression are tensioned in this case and the cables which are inserted in the accommodation depression are raised. The traction cords are tensioned by the weight of the cables which are inserted in the accommodation depression. When the frame is pivoted into the position from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the cables are lowered with the accommodation depression, with the weight of the cables being transmitted as traction force by means of the traction cords to the holding device which is mounted on the frame such that it can pivot.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In the above-described, preferred exemplary embodiment of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> according to the invention, the movement of the cables when the frame <b>18</b> is pivoted is divided into two main components or zones by the holding device <b>23</b> which is formed such that it can pivot in relation to the pivotable frame <b>18</b>. The first main movement which can be executed by the cables is determined by the extent to which the cables hang freely between the region <b>20</b> of the rear face <b>14</b> of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> and the holding device <b>23</b> to which the cables are attached. The cables are raised when the frame <b>18</b> is in the position pivoted into the distribution cabinet <b>10</b>, which position is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and in contrast are lowered when said frame is pivoted into the position which is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. This follows directly from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. In addition to this movement component, the cables execute a relative movement between the holding device <b>23</b> and the guide rail <b>22</b> which is arranged above the holding device <b>23</b>. Whereas the guide rail <b>22</b> is rigidly connected to the pivotable frame, the holding device <b>23</b> can be pivoted in relation to the frame <b>18</b>. In the region between the holding device <b>23</b> and the guide rail <b>22</b>, the cables accordingly execute a slight bending movement with a little torsion.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a preferred embodiment of the holding device <b>23</b>. The cross section of the holding device <b>23</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is designed in the approximate shape of the alphabet letter “E”. The holding device <b>23</b> thus has a plate-like base element <b>29</b>, with three holding elements <b>30</b> which are at an angle of approximately 90° in relation to the base element <b>29</b> being provided in the exemplary embodiment from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Together with the base element <b>29</b>, the holding elements <b>30</b> bound two accommodation spaces <b>31</b> and <b>32</b> which are formed to be open in the direction of the rear face <b>14</b> of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> for optical fibers. This can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> in particular. The formation of the two accommodation spaces <b>31</b> and <b>32</b> makes it possible to separate incoming and outgoing cables from one another. This facilitates possible jumpering work on the cables.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">As can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, openings <b>33</b> are made in the holding elements <b>30</b> and in the base element <b>29</b>. Cable ties or touch-and-close fastening strips, for example, can be drawn through the openings <b>33</b> in order to fix the cables, which are arranged in the accommodation spaces <b>31</b> and <b>32</b>, in the holding device <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> also shows the hinge <b>24</b> which makes possible the relative movement between the holding device <b>23</b> and the frame <b>18</b>. The hinge <b>24</b> engages on the base element <b>29</b>. The holding device <b>23</b> can be attached to the pivotable frame <b>18</b> by means of an attachment element <b>34</b> which likewise engages on the hinge <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In the exemplary embodiment shown, a holding device <b>23</b> is attached to the pivotable frame <b>18</b>. As already mentioned, this holding device <b>23</b> engages on the end <b>21</b> of the frame <b>18</b>. In contrast to the exemplary embodiment shown, it is also possible to attach the holding device <b>23</b> to the frame <b>18</b> at an end <b>35</b> of said frame which is opposite the end <b>21</b>. Furthermore, it is also possible to arrange a holding device <b>23</b> at each of the two ends <b>21</b> and <b>35</b>. It is also possible, within the scope of the invention, to arrange a holding device <b>23</b> both on the frame <b>18</b> and on the rear wall <b>14</b> of the distribution cabinet <b>10</b> in each case.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The distribution cabinet for optical fibers according to the invention allows the cables which contain the optical glass fibers or optical fibers to be handled particularly carefully, with the frame which is arranged in the distribution cabinet such that it can pivot having an unlimited freedom of movement.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>That which is claimed:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A distribution cabinet for optical fibers, having a housing and a frame mounted in the housing that it can pivot, the optical fibers being routed to the frame from a rear face of the housing and away from said frame in the direction of the rear face, and assemblies for connecting the optical fibers being attached to the frame, wherein at least one holding device for the optical fibers is attached to the frame with the holding device being formed such that it can pivot firstly together with the frame in relation to the housing and secondly in relation to the frame, wherein the holding device is attached to a region of the rear face by at least one traction device and in which region the optical fibers are routed into and out of the distribution cabinet, the traction device being relatively relaxed in a position in which a relative distance between the holding device and the region of the rear face is relatively shortest with the traction device being tensioned as the relative distance increases.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the holding device can be pivoted in relation to the frame in such a way that in each position of the frame the holding device is oriented toward the rear face of the housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the holding device can be pivoted in relation to the frame in such a way that in each position of the frame the holding device is oriented toward the rear face of the housing in approximately the same angular position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein in each position of the frame, the holding device is oriented toward a region of the rear face of the housing in which the optical fibers are routed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the holding device is attached to the frame, such that it can pivot.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the holding device has a base element and a plurality of holding elements which are at an angle in relation to the base element and run approximately parallel to one another, the holding elements forming two accommodation spaces, which are open in the direction of the rear face of the housing, for receiving optical fibers routed from the rear face of the housing to the respective holding device and away from said rear face.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the traction device is attached by a first end to the rear face of the housing and by a second end to the respective holding device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the traction device is attached by the first end to the region of the rear face of the housing, in which the optical fibers are routed into and out of the distribution cabinet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A distribution cabinet having assemblies for connecting optical fibers, the distribution cabinet comprising:
<claim-text>a housing having a rear face and an opposing front face;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a frame pivotally mounted in the housing, the optical fibers being routed from the rear face in a first direction of the frame;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a holding device defining an accommodation space therein for the optical fibers, the holding device being attached to the frame with the accommodation space oriented in a second direction of the rear face, the holding device being configured to pivot with the frame relative to the housing or to the frame, the accommodation space remaining oriented In the second direction of the rear face upon pivoting of the frame such that a load on the optical fibers is minimized; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a traction device for attaching the holding device to a region of the rear face, the optical fibers being routed into and out of the distribution cabinet proximate the region of the rear face, the traction device being relaxed in a first state and defining a first distance between the holding device and the region of the rear face, the traction device being tensioned in a second state and defining a second distance greater than the first distance.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein holding device includes a hinge disposed between the accommodation space and the frame, the hinge being configured to maintain the accommodation space oriented in the second direction of the rear face upon pivoting of the frame.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the holding device includes an E shaped member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The distribution cabinet for optical fibers as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the traction device is one of a spring or a cord, the traction device being configured to urge the holding device toward the region of the rear face in the second state.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
