<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296919-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296919</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11302673</doc-number>
<date>20051214</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>29</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>366  3</main-classification>
<further-classification>366192</further-classification>
<further-classification>366194</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Slurry mixer constrictor valve</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3329390</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hulsey</name>
<date>19670700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>251  4</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4836149</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Newbold</name>
<date>19890600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>123 44 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5769389</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jacobsen et al.</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>25112906</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6923421</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Raftis</name>
<date>20050800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>251  4</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>366192</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>366194</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>366193</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>366  2</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>366  3</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10846131</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040514</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7007914</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11302673</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060092759</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060504</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Petersen</last-name>
<first-name>Bruce Lynn</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lisle</city>
<state>IL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Haszel</last-name>
<first-name>Richard James</first-name>
<address>
<city>Mundelein</city>
<state>IL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wittbold</last-name>
<first-name>James R.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Des Plaines</city>
<state>IL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Geoffrey</last-name>
<first-name>Michael M.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Janci</last-name>
<first-name>David F.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wanek</last-name>
<first-name>Laura R.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>United States Gypsum Company</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Chicago</city>
<state>IL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Soohoo</last-name>
<first-name>Tony G.</first-name>
<department>1723</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method for providing a smoothly mixed slurry to a web is provided which includes inserting calcined gypsum and water into a mixer (<b>12</b>), agitating the contents of the mixer (<b>12</b>) to form an aqueous dispersion of the calcined gysum, and passing the agitated contents from an outlet (<b>20</b>) of the mixer (<b>12</b>) into a slurry dispensing apparatus (<b>22</b>) including a flexible, resilient conduit (<b>24</b>). Additionally, the method includes the step of creating a back-pressure on the mixture in the slurry dispensing apparatus by constricting the conduit (<b>24</b>). The constricting of the conduit (<b>24</b>) is effected by a constrictor valve (<b>28</b>) located on the conduit (<b>24</b>).</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="196.68mm" wi="345.27mm" file="US07296919-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="198.71mm" wi="166.45mm" file="US07296919-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="222.93mm" wi="175.60mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296919-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="219.71mm" wi="145.12mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296919-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="225.47mm" wi="180.42mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296919-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="229.87mm" wi="172.72mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296919-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="229.87mm" wi="169.08mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296919-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="215.82mm" wi="160.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296919-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="246.04mm" wi="180.51mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296919-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="194.82mm" wi="139.70mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296919-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This is a divisional of application Ser. No. 10/846,131 filed May 14, 2004, now U.S. Pat. No. 7,007,914.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a method and apparatus for preparing gypsum products (i.e., products comprising calcium sulfate dihydrate) from starting materials comprising calcined gypsum (i.e., calcium sulfate hemihydrate) and water. More particularly, the present invention relates to an improved valve on a conduit located downstream of the slurry mixer and typically used to supply agitated gypsum slurry to a wallboard production line. The basic technology of gypsum wallboard manufacture is disclosed in U.S. Pat. Nos. 1,500,452; 2,207,339 and 4,009,062 all of which are incorporated by reference herein. The present apparatus provides an improved flow of slurry from the dispensing system which enhances the uniform smoothness of the gypsum slurry at the wallboard production line.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">It is well known to produce gypsum products by uniformly dispersing calcined gypsum in water to form a slurry and then casting the slurry into a desired shaped mold or onto a surface and allowing the slurry to set to form hardened gypsum by reaction of the calcined gypsum (calcium sulfate hemihydrite or anhydrite) with the water to form hydrated gypsum (calcium sulfate dihydrate).</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A gypsum wallboard mixer typically includes a housing defining a mixing chamber with inlets for receiving calcined gypsum and water, among other additives well known in the art. The mixer includes an impeller or other type of agitator for agitating the contents to be mixed into a mixture or slurry. The discharge gate or extractor controls the flow of slurry from the mixer to the dispensing system.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Slurries exhibiting certain viscosities or other properties require differing amounts of materials, additives, entrained air, and the like, and may also require different processing times and equipment. In setting slurry requiring a low amount of entrained air, it is known to use a “pinch-type” valve that squeezes an elastomeric conduit carrying the slurry. Squeezing down on the conduit reduces the orifice of the conduit, which in turn, increases the pressure drop through the orifice, increases the back pressure, increases the volume of slurry in the mixer, and accelerates the flow through the conduit. This will result in a smoother, less air entrained, and more desirable slurry for certain applications.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Prior apparatuses for addressing some of the operational problems associated with dispensing a smooth, setting slurry include a “pinch-type” valve which can be mechanically operated or operated by compressed air or hydraulics to “pinch” down on the elastomeric conduit. However, the pinch valve deforms the conduit into a flattened or rectangular orifice which is susceptible to plugging from prematurely setting slurry in the flow, particularly in the corners of the orifice, where the flow velocity is lower. Further, the inlet and outlet orifices of the pinch valve are abrupt because pressure is exerted on the conduit in a substantially singular plane and does not allow for a gradual transition. Such abrupt entrances and exits can lead to further plugging of slurry producing equipment, which causes costly downtime for repairs.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Muscle valves, consisting of a hydraulic chamber around a thick elastomeric sleeve, provide a round orifice but an abrupt flow channel since the pressure is exerted in a substantially singular plane or at one point along the conduit. Further, the muscle valves frequently are massive in size which limits the operator's access to the orifice for clearing a plug or buildup, or for general observation of the flow of slurry through the channel itself.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Plunger-type valves, knife gate valves, and custom made restrictors having an action similar to a “garotte” are also known. Similar problems are seen in the use of these valves as are exhibited with the muscle valves and the pinch valves. In particular, solids easily build up, forming crystalline gypsum, which then prematurely sets and causes further clogging of the apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Further, the prior art valves cannot easily reproduce exact settings which correspond to a given amount of restriction of the conduit. Further still, the prior art valves do not have interchangeable parts, nor are they adapted to be used with different sized conduits.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Accordingly, there is a need for an improved valve for a slurry mixing apparatus dispensing system and a method which promotes smoother, less air entrained slurry.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Another need is for an improved valve for a slurry mixing apparatus dispensing system which prevents build up of prematurely set slurry in the dispensing conduit.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Still another need is for an improved valve and method of use which is capable of continuously varying the flow of gypsum slurry from the mixing apparatus through the dispensing system to the production line.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A further need is for an improved valve system for a gypsum slurry mixing apparatus dispensing system and method of use which has parts that are readily adaptable to different sized conduits.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A further need is for an improved valve for a gypsum slurry mixing apparatus and dispensing system and method of use which provides an easily accessible mechanism for changing the volume of slurry emitted from the dispensing system.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Accordingly, the above-listed needs are met or exceeded by the present apparatus and method for controlling the flow of a slurry including the feature of using a constrictor valve on a mixing and dispensing apparatus. The mixing apparatus is used to mix and agitate calcined gypsum and water to form an aqueous dispersion or slurry of the calcined gypsum. After the contents are agitated, the contents are passed through the outlet of the mixer to the dispensing apparatus. The dispensing apparatus preferably includes an elongate, preferably flexible conduit which provides additional space for the uniform mixing of slurry. By providing the constrictor valve on the flexible conduit, a back-pressure is created on the mixture causing an increase in the volume of the mixture in the mixer when the conduit is constricted. Unwanted premature setting of gypsum is prevented when the conduit is constricted so that occurrences of lumps are reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In the preferred embodiment, the constrictor valve includes a first guide plate and a second guide plate that are spaced a distance apart along the length of the conduit. Extending between the two guide plates, a plurality of elongate members have first and second ends engaged on the first and second guide plates. Upon rotation of at least one of the first and second guide plates with respect to each other, the elongate members are configured to impart pressure on, and constrict the conduit. The elongate guide members are preferably rigid rods that are arrayed around the conduit and are configured to impart pressure on and constrict the conduit.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">More specifically, upon actuation by an actuator, at least one of the first and second guide plates rotates relative to the other plate about the longitudinal axis of the conduit. The circumferential displacement of the first end of the elongate member with respect to the second end of the elongate member causes the shape of the conduit to approximate a hyperboloid of rotation. Pressure is imparted on and constricts the conduit radially along the length of the conduit in multiple planes. The resulting shape of the conduit is generally smooth and circular at a plurality of cross-sections taken along the length of the conduit, and is preferably generally smooth and circular at any cross-section taken along the length of the conduit.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Another feature of the present invention is the inclusion of an actuator to rotate the first guide plate relative to the second guide plate. It is preferred that the amount of relative rotation between the guide plates of the constrictor valve is continuously variable, and can be either manually or automatically controlled.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a fragmentary schematic overhead plan view of a mixing apparatus incorporating the constrictor valve of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a front end elevational view of the housing portion of the constrictor valve of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, with the valve in a relaxed position and partially cut away to reveal the captive ring and the rotating guide plate;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a front end elevational view of the actuator portion of the constrictor valve of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, with the valve in a relaxed position;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a front end elevational view of the housing portion of the constrictor valve of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, with the valve in an actuated position and partially cut away to reveal the captive ring and the rotating guide plate;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an overhead plan view of the constrictor valve of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shown in a relaxed position;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an overhead plan view of the constrictor valve of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shown in an actuated position;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-section taken along the longitudinal axis of the constrictor valve of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and shown in a relaxed position;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross-section taken along the longitudinal axis of the constrictor valve of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and shown in an actuated position;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a back end elevational view of the constrictor valve of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, with the valve in a relaxed position and partially cut away to reveal the fixed guide plate; and</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a plan view of the scallop plate of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BEST MODE OF CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a mixing apparatus for mixing and dispensing a slurry is generally designated <b>10</b> and includes a mixer <b>12</b> having a mixer motor <b>13</b> and a housing <b>14</b> configured for receiving and mixing the slurry. The housing <b>14</b> defines a chamber (not seen) for holding the slurry, and has a preferably generally cylindrical shape. The housing <b>14</b> has an upper wall <b>16</b>, a lower wall (not seen) and an annular peripheral wall <b>18</b>. Calcined gypsum and water, as well as other materials or additives often employed in slurries to prepare gypsum products, are mixed in the mixing apparatus <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">An outlet <b>20</b>, also referred to as a mixer outlet, a discharge gate or a slot, is provided in the peripheral wall <b>18</b> for the discharge of the major portion of the well-mixed slurry into what is generally referred to herein as a dispensing apparatus <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The dispensing apparatus <b>22</b> includes an elongate, preferably cylindrical flexible, resilient tube or conduit <b>24</b> having a main inlet <b>26</b> in slurry receiving communication with the mixer outlet <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The dispensing apparatus <b>22</b> is shown disposed above a conventional gypsum wallboard line including a conveyor table <b>23</b>A upon which a web of face paper <b>23</b>B is moved upon a conveyor belt or web <b>23</b>C in a direction designated by the arrow D. The mixer <b>12</b> is shown supported by a frame member, which can be any sort of frame or platform sufficient for supporting the mixer and other associated equipment as is known in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In some applications, slurry S is dispensed from an outlet or spout <b>27</b> upon the web of paper <b>23</b>B.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In operation, it will be seen that a method for providing a smooth slurry to a web is provided, including inserting calcined gypsum and water into the mixer <b>12</b>, agitating the contents of the mixer to form an aqueous dispersion of the calcined gypsum, emitting the agitated contents from the outlet <b>20</b> of the mixer <b>12</b>, passing the agitated contents into the main inlet <b>26</b> of the dispensing apparatus <b>22</b>, creating a backpressure on the mixture and reducing the amount of mixture in the mixer <b>12</b> by constricting the conduit with a constrictor valve of the present invention, generally designated <b>28</b>. The slurry pressure in the mixer is increased by the constrictor valve <b>28</b> which created a Venturi-shaped orifice <b>29</b> in the conduit <b>24</b> which may be variably reduced in diameter.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Generally, the longer the conduit <b>24</b>, and in particular, the longer the portion of the conduit confined within the constrictor valve <b>28</b>, the less air entrained and the smoother the slurry. Smooth slurry typically has less uncontrolled entrained air and less lumps of partially congealed slurry. The benefits of improved slurry smoothness achieved by the present invention include: reduction and/or elimination of blisters in the board; uniformity of the board, leading to improved strength; and potential water reduction from the board formulation, which in turn will lead to energy savings in the kiln or an increase in line speed.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The conduit <b>24</b> is preferably a flexible hose of elastomeric material, such as Tygon® tubing or the like, and is of sufficient strength and flexibility, that upon being subjected to radial pressure, is capable of being reduced in size to approximately one-half the original diameter. Alternatively, any tubing exhibiting elastic properties is contemplated, and further, any reduction in orifice surface area that does not detrimentally affect the integrity of the conduit <b>24</b> is contemplated. Preferably, conduits having a diameter ranging between one to three inches and having a wall thickness of approximately ¼-inch are employed, however other diameters and wall thicknesses are contemplated to suit the application.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Factors which influence the particular thickness and configuration of the conduit <b>24</b> employed include, among other things, the thickness of the wallboard being produced, the amount of slurry required, the distance between the mixer <b>12</b>, the mixer outlet <b>20</b> and the wallboard forming plate, and the particular characteristics of the slurry formulation, including the setting rate, the water/stucco ratio, glass fiber usage and the percentage of foam desired. One conduit size may be more successful than others, depending on the particular wallboard production line.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>, the continuously variable valve, or constrictor valve <b>28</b> is coupled to the dispensing apparatus <b>22</b>. The constrictor valve <b>28</b> variably reduces the flow through the orifice and increases the pressure drop as material flows through the orifice. Circumferentially disposed around the flexible conduit <b>24</b>, the constrictor valve <b>28</b> has elongate members, preferably rigid rods <b>30</b>, arrayed parallel to and circumscribing the flexible conduit in spaced relation to each other. The rigid rods <b>30</b> (best seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>) are preferably formed of titanium, or other sufficiently strong materials for the specific application, and are preferably approximately nine inches long and a half-inch in diameter. It will be appreciated that different materials, lengths and sizes of the rods <b>30</b> may be used to suit the application. Further, it will be appreciated that the longer the length of the rod <b>30</b>, the longer the length of the conduit <b>24</b> upon which forces can be exerted and thus, the smoother the flow through the orifice. However, excessively long rods <b>30</b> are prone to bending due to the relatively large forces involved.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-8</figref>, a housing <b>32</b> of the valve <b>28</b> is preferably generally cylindrical and preferably supports a fixed guide plate <b>34</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) and a rotating guide plate <b>36</b>, although an alternate embodiment is contemplated in which both plates rotate. The rotating guide plate <b>36</b> and the fixed guide plate <b>34</b> are disposed on proximal and distal ends <b>38</b>, <b>40</b> of the housing <b>32</b>, respectively, in a spaced relationship from each other along the length of the conduit <b>24</b>. Preferably formed of ⅜-inch aluminum sheet, the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> have a generally hollow-centered disk-like shape, with the inner radius preferably being approximately half the outer radius. The inner radius is sufficient to allow the conduit <b>24</b> to pass through the center of the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>, with an additional clearance sufficient to permit the rigid rods <b>30</b> to extend therebetween.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Holding the rigid rods <b>30</b> in the arrayed position, elongate member engagers, preferably arcuate recesses or scallops <b>42</b> (best seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>), are formed on each of the annular guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> at the inner periphery of the plates along the entire inner circumference. The rigid rods <b>30</b> are disposed in the concave recesses or scallops <b>42</b> (best seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>) and are held in place by the flexible conduit <b>24</b>. Other elongate member engagers are also contemplated, such as clips, ties, or any other configuration that couples the rods <b>30</b> to the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>. Preferably, the longitudinal distance along the conduit <b>24</b> between the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> and the fixed guide plate <b>34</b> is about 7-inches when used with 9-inch length rigid rods <b>30</b>. Having this spacing between the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> may vary with rod lengths.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In the preferred embodiment, each scallop <b>42</b> is slightly larger in diameter than the diameter of the rigid rods <b>30</b>, and the scallops are preferably spaced apart from each other about the periphery of the plate <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> a distance less than the diameter of the rods. Further, in the preferred embodiment, the distance between the scallops <b>42</b> is about ¼-inch. It should be appreciated, however, that the number of rods <b>30</b>, thus the number of scallops <b>42</b>, is dependent on the diameter of the conduit <b>24</b> used and the dimensions of the rigid rod used. It is preferred that the distance between the scallops <b>42</b> is less than the diameter of the rigid rods <b>30</b>, and further, that the distance between the scallops is uniform around the inner circumference of the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> such that when pressure is imparted on the conduit <b>24</b>, the conduit is uniformly deformed and maintains a generally circular shape. Since this generally circular shape of the conduit <b>24</b> is desirable in preventing clogging, it will be appreciated that any other shape of the rigid rod <b>30</b>, such as tapered bars or any other shape is contemplated, which constricts the conduit while retaining the generally smooth, circular orifice <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Comparing now <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A to 3</figref>, and <b>4</b> to <b>5</b>, when the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> undergo relative rotation, the rigid rods <b>30</b> are maintained in the scallops <b>42</b> resulting in the rods appearing to twist around the flexible conduit <b>24</b> in a “wringing” action. It will be appreciated, however, that the rods <b>30</b> are approximately perfectly rigid, and the rods do not deform or deform only negligibly. The relative rotation of the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> results in the rigid rods <b>30</b> pushing down on the flexible conduit <b>24</b> to reduce the diameter of the conduit at the orifice without folding or other detrimental failure of the conduit. It will further be appreciated that during the relative rotating action, the rigid rods <b>30</b> are maintained in the scallops <b>42</b>, but due to a small amount of play, the rods <b>30</b> change in orientation with respect to the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>. Starting at a generally normal alignment to the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 4</figref>), after relative rotation of the guide plates, each rod <b>30</b> becomes skewed from normal (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 5</figref>). At one guide plate <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>, the rods will become angled downward and to one side, while at the other guide plate <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>, the rod will have an equal and opposite orientation (seen generally in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The relative rotation of the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> causes the rigid rods <b>30</b> to impart a constriction on the flexible conduit <b>24</b>. The individual cross-sectional areas of the conduit <b>24</b>, taken at locations along the length of the conduit, change in diameter but remain smooth and approximately round. The generally circular shape of the constricted orifice <b>29</b> is a result of the rigid rods <b>30</b> imparting pressure radially in multiple planes along the length of the conduit <b>24</b>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>6</b> and <b>7</b>, at the entrance to the valve <b>28</b>, the cross-sectional area of the conduit <b>24</b> gradually decreases in diameter from an initial diameter of the conduit down to as much as approximately one-half the diameter (or any other desirable diameter) at the center of the valve. In situ testing has shown that an entrance angle, A (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>), with respect to the longitudinal axis of the conduit is optimal (with respect to smooth slurry flow and low clogging) at or less than about 12-degrees used in conjunction with a three inch conduit <b>24</b>. However, given the multitude of factors involved in the non-Newtonian flow of a given slurry, having a given viscosity, and flowing through a given conduit, other angles are also contemplated which will provide a smooth transition into the Venturi and, further, will minimize internal obstructions which might provide a site for the collection and premature setting of slurry.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the resulting shape of the conduit <b>24</b> when the valve <b>28</b> is in an actuated position approximates a hyperboloid of rotation. That is, the curve of a conduit wall <b>44</b> resulting from the pressure imparted by the rigid rods <b>30</b> approximates a hyperbolic curve approaching its directrix. Further, if you take this hyperbola and rotate it about an axis which is 45-degrees from the directrix (the longitudinal axis of the conduit), you will get a hyperboloid of rotation. In this shape, not only is an approximately round flow channel created along the length of the conduit <b>24</b>, but also a gradual tapering of diameter at the proximal and distal ends <b>38</b>, <b>40</b> (the entrance and exit to the Venturi-shaped orifice) is created.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>5</b> and <b>8</b>, on the static, distal end <b>40</b> of the housing <b>32</b>, the fixed guide plate <b>34</b> is fixed to a distal housing plate <b>46</b>, preferably by using at least one but preferably a plurality of housing fasteners such as tie rods <b>48</b> spaced a distance apart around the outer periphery of the guide plate. Having a hollow-centered disc-shape which allows the conduit <b>24</b> and the rigid rods <b>30</b> to pass through, the distal housing plate <b>46</b> is preferably made of 14 gauge stainless steel. The distal housing plate <b>46</b> is in a fixed, spaced relationship with an inner housing plate <b>50</b> and an outer housing plate <b>52</b>, which are both located at the proximal end <b>38</b> of the valve <b>28</b>. Together, the three disk-shaped housing plates <b>46</b>, <b>50</b> and <b>52</b> form the static housing <b>32</b> of the constrictor valve <b>28</b>. The tie rods <b>48</b> maintain the fixed spacing between distal housing plate <b>46</b> and the inner and outer housing plates <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>. Further, the tie rods <b>48</b> are preferably arrayed on the outside periphery of the plates <b>46</b>, <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>, in a number and location sufficient to maintain the static relationship of the plates. Additionally, although other fasteners and configurations are contemplated, it is preferable that the conduit <b>24</b> be readily observable through the constrictor valve <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A</figref>, <b>2</b>B and <b>3</b>, on the proximal end <b>38</b> of the housing <b>32</b>, an arm <b>54</b> extending from the housing preferably has a minor arm component <b>56</b> and a major arm component <b>58</b>, which are further preferably adjustably connected to each other such as with a bolt and hole configuration <b>59</b>. At the end of the arm <b>54</b> is a middle disk <b>60</b> which extends between the inner and outer housing plates <b>50</b>, <b>52</b> and is preferably generally flush with the housing plates. The middle disk <b>60</b> of the arm <b>54</b> is also static with respect to the housing plates <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>, and is preferably fastened to the housing plates by the tie rods <b>48</b>. It is also contemplated, among other configurations, that the middle disk <b>60</b> is a washer or other spacer used to keep the inner and outer housing plates <b>50</b>, <b>52</b> in a spaced relationship. The inner radius of the middle disk <b>60</b> not only circumscribes both the conduit <b>24</b> and the rods <b>30</b>, but also is larger than the inner radii of the inner and outer housing plates <b>50</b>, <b>52</b> to form a cavity <b>62</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 3</figref>) between the housing plates <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">In the preferred embodiment, the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> is fixed to a captive plate <b>64</b> by at least one, but preferably a plurality of rotating guide plate fasteners <b>65</b>. The captive plate <b>64</b> also circumscribes the conduit <b>24</b> and the rigid rods <b>30</b> such that the captive plate does not interfere with or impede the circumferential movement and angular skewing of the rigid rods. While the captive plate <b>64</b> is disposed in the cavity <b>62</b> between the inner and outer housing plates <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>, it is itself circumscribed by the middle disk <b>60</b>. An inside edge of the middle disk <b>60</b> provides a generally circular interface <b>66</b> upon which the generally circular captive plate <b>64</b> can rotate within the cavity <b>62</b>. It is contemplated that a lubricant may be added to the clearance between the captive plate <b>64</b> and the middle disk <b>60</b> to facilitate the sliding engagement of the captive plate with the interface <b>66</b>. Since the captive plate <b>64</b> and the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> are fixed together by the rotating guide plate fasteners <b>65</b>, they rotate together in a single motion.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In the preferred embodiment, disposed between the middle disk <b>60</b> and the inner housing plate <b>46</b> is a spacer structure such as a plurality of washers <b>67</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>), which gives the captive plate <b>64</b> additional space to rotate within the cavity <b>62</b>. Alternately, other configurations are contemplated which facilitate the rotation of the captive plate <b>64</b> and the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> in the cavity <b>62</b> without interference from the inner and outer housing plates <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The rotation of the captive plate <b>64</b> and the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> is effected by the use of an actuator <b>68</b>, such as a commercially available linear actuator by Duff-Norton®, or any other mechanical device, such as a lever, or fluid power cylinder, as is known in the art. The actuator <b>68</b> is pivotally connected to an attachment member <b>70</b> with a rotating joint, such as with a pin connected joint <b>71</b>, which preferably couples the actuator to both the captive plate <b>64</b> and the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> by the plurality of rotating guide plate fasteners <b>65</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">At the other end of the actuator <b>68</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>), the actuator <b>68</b> is preferably coupled to the arm <b>54</b> with a coupling link <b>72</b>. The coupling link <b>72</b> is preferably attached to the arm <b>54</b> in the bolt and hole configuration <b>59</b>. On the other end, the coupling link <b>72</b> is preferably pivotally attached with a pin connected joint <b>71</b> to a controller <b>73</b>, such as a computer or a potentiometer, which controls the drive of the actuator <b>68</b>. Automatic or manual adjustment of the actuator <b>68</b> is contemplated, as is known in the art. In addition, continuous adjustment is also contemplated and is preferably regulated by a feedback loop, or any other known method. Constriction of the valve <b>28</b> may be triggered by the controller <b>73</b> sensing one or a plurality of factors, such as the electromotive loading on the mixer motor <b>13</b>, the flow rate through the dispensing system <b>22</b>, the pressure in the mixing or dispensing system, the viscosity of the slurry, the electromotive loading on the actuator <b>68</b>, or any other factor. Further, controllable, reproducible precision in the amount of constriction of the conduit can be achieved with the actuator configuration since the amount of constriction of the conduit is directly related to the amount of rotation of the guide plate.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">When the actuator <b>66</b> is actuated to extend linearly, the attachment member <b>70</b> rotates the captive plate <b>64</b>, and thus the rotating guide plate <b>36</b>, within the cavity <b>62</b> and upon the circular interface <b>66</b> of the middle disk <b>60</b>. More specifically, the rotation is generally about the longitudinal axis of the conduit <b>24</b>. When the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> rotates, a first end <b>74</b> of the rigid rods <b>30</b> disposed within the scallops <b>42</b> follows the path of rotation of the rotating guide plate <b>36</b>, while a second opposite end <b>76</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>) of the rigid rods is not circumferentially displaced. This “wringing” action is what imparts pressure on the flexible conduit <b>24</b>. Also, it is the rotation of at least one of the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> which results in the conduit having a generally smooth and circular shape in a plurality of cross-sections taken along the length of the conduit <b>24</b>. Further, in the preferred embodiment, and as seen in planar view in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, each and every cross section of the conduit <b>24</b> taken along the length of the conduit and normal to the longitudinal axis is generally smooth and circular in shape.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">To maintain the rods <b>30</b> within the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>, a proximal keeper plate <b>78</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>) and a distal keeper plate <b>80</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) are preferably disposed at the proximal end <b>38</b> and the distal end <b>40</b> of the constrictor valve <b>28</b>, respectively. Having a hollow-centered disk-shape which preferably circumscribes the conduit <b>24</b> only, the keeper plates <b>78</b>, <b>80</b> prevent the rigid rods <b>30</b> from sliding out of the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>. The keeper plates <b>78</b>, <b>80</b> are preferably disposed in a spaced relationship with the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>, the distance between the two keeper plates <b>78</b>, <b>80</b> preferably being slightly longer than the length of the rods <b>30</b>. The keeper plates <b>78</b>, <b>80</b> are preferably fastened to the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> by the rotating guide plate fastener <b>65</b> and a fixed guide plate fastener <b>82</b>. However, it is also contemplated that the keeper plates are fastened to the housing <b>32</b>, or that the keeper plates are omitted, assuming some other way is employed to retain the rods <b>30</b> in operational relationship with the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In the preferred embodiment and referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the fasteners <b>65</b> attach the proximal keeper plate <b>78</b>, the attachment member <b>70</b>, the captive plate <b>64</b> and the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> in a static relationship with respect to one another. Upon actuation of the actuator <b>68</b>, the attachment member <b>70</b>, the proximal keeper plate <b>78</b>, the captive plate <b>64</b> and the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> rotate in a single motion about the longitudinal axis at the center of the conduit <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">To assemble the constrictor valve <b>28</b>, the conduit <b>24</b> must be fed through the housing <b>32</b>, the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>, the middle disk <b>60</b>, the captive plate <b>64</b>, and the keeper plates <b>78</b>, <b>80</b>, and the rods <b>30</b> must be positioned in the scallops <b>42</b> between the conduit <b>24</b> and the guide plates. Once the rods <b>30</b> are in place, the keeper plates <b>78</b>, <b>80</b> can be fastened at both ends <b>38</b>, <b>40</b>. Although the valve <b>28</b> preferably includes hollow-centered disk shaped plates, it is also contemplated that the valve can be any other shape or configuration that has a static housing and enables the “wringing” action.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In the preferred embodiment, the fixed guide plate <b>34</b> and the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> are preferably easily interchangeable with different sized guide plates to accommodate different sized conduits <b>24</b>. Since the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> are the only disk-shaped plates that require the inside diameter to be generally coextensive with the diameter of the conduit <b>24</b>, as long as the housing plates <b>46</b>, <b>50</b>, <b>52</b> and the captive plate <b>64</b> have an inside diameter sufficient to accommodate a range of conduit sizes, only the guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> and the keeper plates <b>78</b>, <b>80</b> may be required to be changed to accommodate different sized conduits. The fixed and rotating guide plates <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> are removably fastened to the distal housing plate <b>46</b> and the captive plate <b>64</b>, respectively, and are changed with minimal disassembly. By unfastening the fastener <b>82</b> coupling the fixed guide plate <b>34</b> to the distal housing plate <b>46</b>, and the fastener <b>65</b> coupling the rotating guide plate <b>36</b> to the captive plate <b>64</b>, the two guide plates and the two keeper plates <b>78</b>, <b>80</b> can be readily interchanged without modifying the remaining valve housing <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">A typical mixer <b>12</b> of the type used with the present invention generates a slurry velocity in the approximate range of 500-3000 ft/min, measured at the discharge gate or outlet <b>20</b> with a corresponding force or pressure. The amount of flow through the dispensing system <b>22</b> in relation to the amount of material being input into the mixer <b>12</b> and the retention time of the material in the mixer, dictates the level of material in the mixer. The level of the material dictates the pressure head in the dispensing system <b>22</b>. When the pressure is increased, entrained air is reduced in the slurry. To increase or decrease this pressure to a desired amount, the pressure drop through the valve orifice can be variably reduced or increased by constricting the conduit <b>24</b> through the actuator <b>68</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">While specific embodiments of the constrictor valve of the present invention have been shown and described, it will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that changes and modifications may be made thereto without departing from the invention in its broader aspects and as set forth in the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for providing a smoothly mixed slurry to a web, comprising:
<claim-text>inserting calcined gypsum and water into a mixer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>agitating the contents of the mixer to form an aqueous dispersion of the calcined gypsum;</claim-text>
<claim-text>passing the agitated contents from an outlet of the mixer into a slurry dispensing apparatus including a flexible, resilient conduit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>creating a back-pressure on the mixture in the slurry dispensing apparatus by constricting the conduit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the constricting of the conduit is effected by a constrictor valve located on said conduit and configured to constrict the conduit to approximate a hyperboloid of rotation about a longitudinal axis of the conduit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said constrictor valve includes a plurality of elongate members arrayed around the conduit and are configured to be circumferentially displaced, said elongate members causing the shape of the conduit to approximate the hyperboloid of rotation about the longitudinal axis of the conduit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising the step of triggering an actuator to constrict the conduit wherein the actuator is triggered one of manually and automatically.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A method for providing a smoothly mixed slurry to a web, comprising:
<claim-text>inserting calcined gypsum and water into a mixer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>agitating the contents of the mixer to form an aqueous dispersion of the calcined gypsum;</claim-text>
<claim-text>passing the agitated contents from an outlet of the mixer into a slurry dispensing apparatus including a flexible, resilient conduit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>sensing a factor for constricting the valve;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the constricting of the conduit is effected by a constrictor valve located on said conduit to constrict the conduit to approximate a hyperboloid of rotation about a longitudinal axis of the conduit when the factor is sensed.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the factor for constricting the conduit is an electromotive loading on the mixer motor.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
