<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297595-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297595</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11019304</doc-number>
<date>20041223</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2003-0098355</doc-number>
<date>20031227</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>336</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438259</main-classification>
<further-classification>438267</further-classification>
<further-classification>438596</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Non-volatile memory device and fabricating method thereof</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6403421</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ikeda et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438267</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6743675</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Ding</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438257</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6838342</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ding</name>
<date>20050100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438257</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6884679</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Park et al.</name>
<date>20050400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438257</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6911370</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Wang et al.</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438315</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0224860</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hendriks et al.</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257315</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>Edward S. Yang, “Microelectronic Devices”, McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1988, pp. 341-353.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>6</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438257</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438259</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438267</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438596</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050139900</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050630</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jung</last-name>
<first-name>Sung Mun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kyunggido</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kim</last-name>
<first-name>Jum Soo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kyunggido</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sherr &amp; Nourse, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Dongbu Hitek Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Dang</last-name>
<first-name>Trung</first-name>
<department>2823</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention provides a non-volatile memory device and fabricating method thereof, in which a height of a floating gate conductor layer pattern is sustained without lowering a degree of integration and by which a coupling ratio is raised. The present invention includes a trench type device isolation layer defining an active area within a semiconductor substrate, a recess in an upper part of the device isolation layer to have a prescribed depth, a tunnel oxide layer on the active area of the semiconductor substrate, a floating gate conductor layer pattern on the tunnel oxide layer, a conductive floating spacer layer provided to a sidewall of the floating gate conductor layer pattern and a sidewall of the recess, a gate-to-gate insulating layer on the floating fate conductor layer pattern and the conductive floating spacer layer, and a control gate conductor layer on the gate-to-gate insulating layer.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="93.39mm" wi="146.13mm" file="US07297595-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="256.62mm" wi="162.64mm" file="US07297595-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="235.03mm" wi="159.60mm" file="US07297595-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="224.79mm" wi="176.36mm" file="US07297595-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the benefit of the Korean Application No. P2003-0098355 filed on Dec. 27, 2003, which is hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a non-volatile memory device and fabricating method thereof, and more particularly, to a non-volatile memory device having a high coupling ratio and fabricating method thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Discussion of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Generally, semiconductor memory devices are categorized into a volatile memory device, which loses data in case of cutting off power supply, such as DRAM (dynamic random access memory) and SRAM (static random access memory) and a non-volatile memory device, which saves data in spite of cutting off power supply, such as a flash memory device.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional diagram of a non-volatile memory device according to a related art.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a tunnel oxide layer pattern <b>106</b> and a floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>108</b> are sequentially stacked on an active area <b>104</b> of a semiconductor substrate <b>100</b> defined by a device isolation layer <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">A gate-to-gate insulating layer <b>110</b> is formed on the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>108</b> and the device isolation layer <b>102</b>. The gate-to-gate insulating layer <b>110</b> consists of an oxide/nitride/oxide (ONO) layer.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">And, a control gate conductor layer <b>112</b> is arranged on the gate-to-gate insulating layer <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In operating the above-configured non-volatile memory device, a ratio of voltage coupled to the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>108</b> by a voltage applied to the control gate conductor layer <b>112</b> is called a coupling ratio. And, it is well known that the speed and performance of the device are enhanced by high coupling ratio. The coupling ratio can be expressed by Equation 1.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mi>γ</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mfrac>
          <msub>
            <mi>C</mi>
            <mi>ONO</mi>
          </msub>
          <mrow>
            <msub>
              <mi>C</mi>
              <mi>ONO</mi>
            </msub>
            <mo>+</mo>
            <msub>
              <mi>C</mi>
              <mi>tunnel</mi>
            </msub>
          </mrow>
        </mfrac>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>[</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>1</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>]</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In Equation 1, C<sub>ONO </sub>is capacitance between the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>108</b> and the control gate conductor layer patter <b>112</b> and C<sub>tunnel </sub>is capacitance between the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>108</b> and a bulk, i.e., channel.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">As can be known by Equation 1, C<sub>ONO </sub>should be increased to raise the coupling ratio. For this, a contact area between the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>108</b> and the gate-to-gate insulating layer <b>110</b> needs to be increased.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">However, if a width of the active area is increased to increase the contact area between the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>108</b> and the gate-to-gate insulating layer <b>110</b>, the degree of device integration is lowered.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In case a height of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>108</b> is raised, it is difficult to carryout an etch process thereof.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Accordingly, the present invention is directed to a non-volatile memory device and fabricating method thereof that substantially obviate one or more problems due to limitations and disadvantages of the related art.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">An object of the present invention is to provide a non-volatile memory device and fabricating method thereof, in which a height of a floating gate conductor layer pattern is sustained without lowering a degree of integration and by which a coupling ratio is raised.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Additional advantages, objects, and features of the invention will be set forth in part in the description which follows and in part will become apparent to those having ordinary skill in the art upon examination of the following or may be learned from practice of the invention. The objectives and other advantages of the invention may be realized and attained by the structure particularly pointed out in the written description and claims hereof as well as the appended drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">To achieve these objects and other advantages and in accordance with the purpose of the invention, as embodied and broadly described herein, a non-volatile memory device according to the present invention includes a semiconductor substrate, a trench type device isolation layer defining an active area within the semiconductor substrate, a recess in an upper part of the device isolation layer to have a prescribed depth, a tunnel oxide layer on the active area of the semiconductor substrate, a floating gate conductor layer pattern on the tunnel oxide layer, a conductive floating spacer layer provided to a sidewall of the floating gate conductor layer pattern and a sidewall of the recess of the device isolation layer, a gate-to-gate insulating layer on the floating fate conductor layer pattern and the conductive floating spacer layer, and a control gate conductor layer on the gate-to-gate insulating layer.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Preferably, the depth of the recess is 300˜2,000 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Preferably, the floating conductor layer pattern and the conductive floating spacer layer are formed of polysilicon.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Preferably, the gate-to-gate insulating layer is an oxide/nitride/oxide stacked layer.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In another aspect of the present invention, a method of fabricating a non-volatile memory device includes the steps of forming a trench type device isolation layer defining an active area within a semiconductor substrate, forming a tunnel oxide layer on the active area of the semiconductor substrate, forming a floating gate conductor layer on the tunnel oxide layer and the device isolation layer, forming a floating fate conductor layer pattern exposing a portion of the device isolation layer by pattering the floating gate conductor layer, forming a recess in an upper part of the device isolation layer by removing the exposed portion of the device isolation layer to a prescribed depth, forming a conductive floating spacer layer on a sidewall of the floating gate conductor layer pattern and a sidewall of the recess of the device isolation layer, forming a gate-to-gate insulating layer on the floating fate conductor layer pattern and the conductive floating spacer layer, and forming a control gate conductor layer on the gate-to-gate insulating layer.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Preferably, the floating gate conductor layer pattern and the recess of the device isolation layer are formed by one etch process using a same mask layer pattern as an etch mask.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Preferably, the depth of the recess is 300˜2,000 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Preferably, the conductive floating spacer layer forming step comprising the steps of forming a floating space conductor layer on the sidewalls of the floating gate conductor layer pattern and the recess of the device isolation layer and anisotropically etching the floating spacer conductor layer to expose an upper surface of the floating gate conductor layer pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">More preferably, the floating spacer conductor layer is anisotropically etched by etchback.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Preferably, the gate-to-gate insulating layer comprises an oxide/nitride/oxide stacked layer.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">It is to be understood that both the foregoing general description and the following detailed description of the present invention are exemplary and explanatory and are intended to provide further explanation of the invention as claimed.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The accompanying drawings, which are included to provide a further understanding of the invention and are incorporated in and constitute a part of this application, illustrate embodiment(s) of the invention and together with the description serve to explain the principle of the invention. In the drawings:</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional diagram of a non-volatile memory device according to a related art;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional diagram of a non-volatile memory device according to the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 to 6</figref> are cross-sectional diagrams for explaining a method of fabricating a non-volatile memory device according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Reference will now be made in detail to the preferred embodiments of the present invention, examples of which are illustrated in the accompanying drawings. Wherever possible, the same reference numbers will be used throughout the drawings to refer to the same or like parts.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional diagram of a non-volatile memory device according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a tunnel oxide layer pattern <b>208</b> is arranged on an active area <b>206</b> of a semiconductor substrate <b>202</b> defined by a device isolation layer <b>204</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The device isolation layer <b>104</b> has a trench shape and a recess <b>216</b> having a prescribed depth is formed on a top of the device isolation layer <b>204</b>. And, the depth of the recess <b>216</b> is about 300˜2,000 Å.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">A floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> is arranged on the tunnel oxide layer <b>208</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A conductive gate spacer layer <b>219</b> is provided to sidewalls of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> and the recess <b>216</b> of the device isolation layer <b>204</b>. Both of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> and the conductive gate spacer layer <b>219</b> play a role as a floating gate. Both of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> and the conductive gate spacer layer <b>219</b> may be formed of polysilicon.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">An ONO (oxide/nitride/oxide) layer <b>220</b> is arranged on the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> and the conductive gate spacer layer <b>219</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">A control gate conductor layer <b>22</b> is arranged on the ONO layer <b>220</b>. And, the control gate conductor layer <b>22</b> can be formed of polysilicon as well.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the above-configured non-volatile memory device, by providing the conductive gate spacer layer <b>219</b> to the sidewall of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> and the sidewall of the recess <b>219</b> of the device isolation layer <b>204</b> and by forming the ONO layer <b>220</b> as the gate-to-gate insulating layer on the conductive gate spacer layer <b>219</b>, the contact area between the ONO layer <b>220</b> operative as the gate-to-gate insulating layer and both of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> and the conductive gate spacer layer <b>219</b> operative as the floating gate can be increased, whereby the coupling ratio of the device is raised.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 to 6</figref> are cross-sectional diagrams for explaining a method of fabricating a non-volatile memory device according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a device isolation layer <b>204</b> is formed in a semiconductor substrate <b>202</b> to define an active area <b>206</b>. The device isolation layer <b>204</b> is formed to have a general trench shape.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">A thin tuner oxide layer <b>208</b> is formed on the active area <b>206</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">A floating gate conductor layer <b>210</b> is formed on the tunnel oxide layer <b>208</b>. The floating gate conductor layer <b>210</b> is formed using a polysilicon layer.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">A mask layer pattern <b>212</b> is formed on the floating gate conductor layer <b>210</b>. The mask layer pattern <b>212</b> is formed using a photoresist pattern. And, the mask layer pattern <b>212</b> has an opening <b>214</b> exposing a portion of the floating gate conductor layer <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> is formed by etching the exposed portion of the floating gate conductor layer <b>210</b> using the mask layer pattern <b>212</b> as an etch mask.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">An exposed portion of the device isolation layer <b>204</b> is etched after forming the floating conductive layer pattern <b>211</b>, whereby a recess <b>216</b> having a prescribed depth of 300˜2,000 Å is formed.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">After forming the recess <b>216</b>, the mask layer pattern is removed.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a floating spacer conductor layer <b>218</b> is formed on exposed surfaces of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>21</b> and the device isolation layer <b>204</b>. In doing so, the floating spacer conductor layer <b>218</b> can be formed of polysilicon.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, anisotropic etch is carried out on the floating spacer conductor layer <b>218</b> to form a conductive floating spacer layer <b>219</b> on a sidewall of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> and a sidewall of the recess <b>216</b> of the device isolation layer <b>204</b>. The anisotropic etch is carried out in a manner of performing etch-back until an upper surface of the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> is exposed.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Subsequently, an ONO layer <b>220</b> is formed as a gate-to-gate insulating layer on the floating gate conductor layer pattern <b>211</b> and the conductive floating spacer layer <b>219</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Thereafter, a control gate conductor layer <b>222</b> is formed on the ONO layer <b>220</b> using polysilicon.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Accordingly, by forming the recess having the prescribed depth in the device isolation layer and by forming the conductive floating spacer layer to the sidewall of the recess and the sidewall of the floating gate conductor layer pattern, the present invention enables both of the floating gate conductor layer pattern and the floating spacer layer to operate as the floating gate.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Therefore, the present invention extends the contact area between the floating gate and the gate-to-gage insulating layer to raise the coupling ratio, thereby enhancing the device performance.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Moreover, the present invention facilitates to fabricate the non-volatile memory device having the raised coupling ratio.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">It will be apparent to those skilled in the art that various modifications and variations can be made in the present invention. Thus, it is intended that the present invention covers the modifications and variations of this invention provided they come within the scope of the appended claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07297595-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="6.69mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07297595-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of fabricating a non-volatile memory device, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>forming a trench type device isolation layer defining an active area within a semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a tunnel oxide layer only on the active area of the semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a floating gate conductor layer on the tunnel oxide layer and the device isolation layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a floating gate conductor layer pattern exposing a portion of the device isolation layer by patterning the floating gate conductor layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a recess in an upper part of the device isolation layer by removing the exposed portion of the device isolation layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a conductive floating spacer layer on a sidewall of the floating gate conductor layer pattern and a sidewall of the recess of the device isolation layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>anisotropic etching the conductive floating spacer layer to expose an upper conductive surface of the floating gate conductor layer pattern;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a gate-to-gate insulating layer on the floating gate conductor layer pattern and the conductive floating spacer layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a control gate conductor layer on the gate-to-gate insulating layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the floating gate conductor layer pattern and the recess of the device isolation layer are formed by one etch process using a same mask layer pattern as an etch mask.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, the conductive floating spacer layer forming step comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>forming a floating space conductor layer on the sidewalls of the floating gate conductor layer pattern and the recess of the device isolation layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>anisotropically etching the floating spacer conductor layer to expose an upper surface of the floating gate conductor layer pattern.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the floating spacer conductor layer is anisotropically etched by etchback.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the gate-to-gate insulating layer comprises an oxide/nitride/oxide stacked layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the depth of the recess is between approximately 300 Å and approximately 2,000 Å.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
