<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296685-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296685</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11090142</doc-number>
<date>20050328</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>SE</country>
<doc-number>0400789</doc-number>
<date>20040326</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>152</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>07</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>49</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209405</main-classification>
<further-classification>399403</further-classification>
<further-classification>399408</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Vibrating screen for screening crushed stone and gravel</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5085324</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dehlen</name>
<date>19920200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>209399</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5104521</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Rutherford</name>
<date>19920400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5248043</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dorn</name>
<date>19930900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5277319</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Henry, Jr.</name>
<date>19940100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>209399</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5346053</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dorn</name>
<date>19940900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>198399</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5361911</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Waites et al.</name>
<date>19941100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>209399</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5816413</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Boccabella et al.</name>
<date>19981000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0167341</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Bacho et al.</name>
<date>20050800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>209405</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0189265</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Malmberg</name>
<date>20050900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>AU</country>
<doc-number>199896986</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19990600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>17</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209399</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209403</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209405</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209408</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>198399</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050224397</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051013</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Malmberg</last-name>
<first-name>Mats</first-name>
<address>
<city>Rydsgard</city>
<country>SE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>SE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>SE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Drinker Biddle &amp; Reath LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sandvik Intellectual Property AB</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Sandviken</city>
<country>SE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Mackey</last-name>
<first-name>Patrick</first-name>
<department>3654</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Matthews</last-name>
<first-name>Terrell</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A vibrating screen for conducting material in a longitudinal direction while screening the material comprises a screening deck, exchangeable modular screening media, and an adapter arrangement for mounting the screening media on the deck. The screening deck includes transverse carriers oriented transversely of the longitudinal direction. The adapter arrangement comprises longitudinal support carriers arranged substantially in the longitudinal direction, and connecting elements oriented transversely of the longitudinal direction for interconnecting the support carriers and connecting the interconnected support carriers on the transverse carriers.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="139.95mm" wi="215.22mm" file="US07296685-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="216.32mm" wi="133.18mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296685-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="169.76mm" wi="145.63mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296685-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="216.66mm" wi="142.92mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296685-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="226.23mm" wi="119.55mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296685-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="233.43mm" wi="159.00mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296685-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="219.37mm" wi="170.18mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296685-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="179.75mm" wi="147.66mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296685-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="154.94mm" wi="157.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296685-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application claims priority under 35 U.S.C. §119 to Patent application Ser. No. 0400789-4 filed in Sweden on Mar. 27, 2004.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an adapter arrangement for mounting cross-tensioned or pre-tensioned screening media on a screening deck, normally provided with a special sub-frame, and to exchangeable modular screening elements for screening of material, such as crushed stone, gravel or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In mining and stone industries, it is often important to fractionate crushed stone and gravel into fractions of stones with different sizes. Mostly, fractionating is done by supplying an unfractionated stream of crushed stone or gravel to a vibrating screen provided with screening elements having screening holes for allowing stones smaller than the screening holes to pass through the holes.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Today, there are vibrating screens that are manufactured to use only cross-tensioned or pre-tensioned screening media. The cross-tensioned screening media can be either wire mesh screening media or polyurethane/rubber screening media with reinforcement. The pre-tensioned screening media can either be made of a metal sheet or be made of polyurethane/rubber material in a frame with metal reinforcement. The wire mesh screening media has the advantage that it is easy to mount, cheap and has the highest percentage open area.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The cross-tensioned screening media is bought in the desired length and hooks or other fastening means are attached on the two opposite sides of the screen by simple actions. The cross-tensioned screening media is mounted in the vibrating screen with the hooks or the fastening means attached to fastenings means on the side walls of the vibrating screen.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Several support beams are arranged between the side walls of the vibrating screen having their longitudinal direction parallel to the side walls of the vibrating screen. The support beams are arranged at different heights in order to support the cross-tensioned screening media between the side walls of the vibrating screen, causing the cross-tensioned screening media to have a crowned or slightly upwardly curved shape and to support the cross-tensioned or pre-tensioned screening media when being mounted. These vibrating screens have the disadvantage that they are manufactured to only have cross-tensioned screening media, and the wire meshes are not suitable for running larger batches since they have shorter lifetime compared with vibrating screens having screening media made of polyurethane (PU) or rubber.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">There are also vibrating screens having screening decks with modular screening elements, e.g. as described in SE-A-0 460 340 (corresponding to U.S. Pat. No. 5,085,324). This document shows a system with modular screening elements in a vibrating screen for screening of crushed rocks or gravel. The vibrating screen according to this document includes a multitude of screening elements. The modular screening elements and cross-tensioned polyurethane/rubber screening media are more expensive than the wire mesh screening media, but they have a longer lifetime. The modular screening elements are, however, supplied from the specific manufacture of the system of modular screening elements and therefore not as easily accessible as the cross-tensioned screening media. There are also manufacturers that deliver specific manufactured modular elements with a pre-tensioned screening media, e.g. the WS 83 module for the WS S5 modular screening system from the company Isenmann. The latter has the disadvantage of being more expensive than cross-tensioned wire mesh.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another vibrating screen with exchangeable modular screening elements is shown in the Swedish patent application, SE0400337-2, “Screening deck”.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In many cases, especially in the set-up of the vibrating screen, there is a need for running-in the screening deck of the vibrating screen in respect of the size of the screening holes. It might also be the case that a small batch of crushed stones or gravel should be fractionated with a specific size of the holes. In both cases there is a need for a quick, temporary and cheap solution. The cross-tensioned screening media is the best solution in these cases, but the present vibrating screens require to be substantially re-built before can be used with the cross-tensioned screening media if they are of the modular type. If they already are of the cross-tensioned screening media type, they have the disadvantage of not being able to use modular screening elements after the running-in period due to the construction with support beams arranged at different heights.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A difference between wire mesh and the cross-tensioned or the pre-tensioned screening media of polyurethane (PU) or rubber is that the wire mesh provides a larger open area, i.e. an area used for screening. This is caused by the fact that cross-tensioned and pre-tensioned screening media are provided with larger closed areas between the holes to get enough rigidity in the screening media, whereas the wire mesh has enough rigidity in wires forming the wire mesh and need not additional material between holes. The cross-tensioned or the pre- tensioned screening media of polyurethane (PU) or rubber needs also reinforcement material, e.g. wires, incorporated in the polyurethane (PU) or rubber to get enough rigidity.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Faced with the above prior art screening systems and the disadvantages and problems therewith, the object with the present invention is to improve the screening systems in a way that combines the advantages of the system with modular screening elements and the system with cross-tensioned screening media.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Another object of the present invention is to provide a way of providing a vibrating screen with a sub-frame for modular screening elements at the time it is provided with cross-tensioned or pre-tensioned screening media.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The above-mentioned objects are achieved by an adapter arrangement, which comprises longitudinal support carriers for supporting the cross-tensioned or pre- tensioned screening media, and connecting elements for connecting the support carriers to transverse carriers of the screening deck.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In the following, the invention will be explained with reference to the accompanying drawings, wherein</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic perspective assembly view of a prior art screening deck with modular screening elements,</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic perspective assembly view of a prior art screening deck with a cross-tensioned screening media,</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic perspective assembly view of a screening deck with modular screening elements and the adapter arrangement according to the present invention,</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A</figref>, <b>4</b>B, <b>4</b>C are perspective views of first, second and third adapter parts, respectively, of the adapter arrangement according to the present invention,</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a perspective view of a support carrier in the adapter arrangement according to the present invention,</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A</figref>, <b>6</b>B, and <b>6</b>C are cross-sectional views taken at circles a, b, c, respectively in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref>, showing how first, second, and third connecting elements, respectively, are attached to transverse carriers,</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref> is a side elevational view showing a transition between screening elements according to the present invention,</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a schematic perspective assembly view of a vibrating screen having a screening deck with both modular screening elements and the cross-tensioned or pre-tensioned screening media, where the screening media has been mounted by means of an adapter arrangement according to the present invention, and</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a schematic perspective assembly view of a screening deck with longitudinal carriers for holding modular screening elements, where a cross-tensioned or pre-tensioned screening media have been mounted by means of an adapter arrangement according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> schematically shows a prior art screening deck <b>100</b> in a vibrating screen for screening of crushed stones, gravel or the like comprising exchangeable modular screening elements <b>110</b> and transverse carriers <b>120</b>. The modular screening elements <b>110</b> differ in height to improve the screening of crushed stones or gravel. The modular screening elements <b>110</b> are normally alternately placed so that the neighboring screen elements always will be at different heights. Each carrier <b>120</b> has two parallel, elongated stanchions <b>130</b><i>a</i>, <b>130</b><i>b</i>. The modular screening elements <b>110</b> have snap locks <b>140</b>, which interact with the elongated stanchions <b>130</b><i>a</i>, <b>130</b><i>b </i>for fastening the screening elements to the transverse carriers <b>120</b>. The transverse carriers <b>120</b> are fastened by bolting, welding or other suitable fastening means to cross members (not shown) arranged in a vibrating screen mechanism. In a surface <b>150</b> of the modular screening element <b>110</b>, through-holes H have been provided for fractionating crushed stone and gravel into fractions of stones with different sizes. A longitudinal direction of the screening deck is indicated with an arrow A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The longitudinal direction of the screening deck is also the travelling direction for the material, i.e. stones or gravel, on the vibrating screen.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> schematically shows a part of a prior art vibrating screen <b>250</b>, where a cross-tensioned screening media <b>200</b> has been mounted. The screen <b>250</b> comprises a hook arrangement <b>210</b> in each end of the screening media <b>200</b>. Fastening means <b>220</b> fasten the hook arrangements <b>210</b> to the walls <b>230</b> of the vibrating screen.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The means for fastening the screening media <b>200</b> to the vibrating screen <b>250</b> or the side walls <b>230</b> of the vibrating screen <b>250</b> can be designed in many ways, e.g. the hook arrangement shown or a screw/bolt joint etc., but is not part of the present invention. The hook arrangement is typically jammed over the edges of the screening media <b>200</b> and fixed by a bolt and nut arrangement. If pre-tensioned screening media is to be used in the vibrating screen, the fastening means <b>220</b> will only have a down- holding function, whereas the fastening means have an outwardly stretching function when using cross-tensioned screening media to form the crowned shape of the screening media.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The fastening means <b>220</b> are flexibly mounted by a bolt arrangement or similar. The fastening means <b>220</b> also have a second function in that they function as side covers in the vibrating screen protecting the vibrating screen from wear due to the material being screened. When the modular screening elements are mounted in a vibrating screen (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>), special cover plates <b>820</b> can instead be mounted on the side walls to protect the vibrating screen from wear caused by the material being screened.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Further, supporting carriers <b>240</b> are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> that are mounted rigidly in the vibrating screen <b>250</b> to support the screening media. The supporting carriers <b>240</b> are arranged substantially parallel to the longitudinal direction A of the vibrating screen <b>250</b>. The difference in height of the support carriers <b>240</b> can be seen from a virtual reference line B extending from the fastening points of the screening media <b>200</b> to the side walls of the vibrating screen <b>250</b>. Due to the difference in height of the support carriers <b>240</b> the screening media <b>200</b> will form a crowned or slightly curved shape as is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> schematically shows the screening deck after two rows of modular screening elements have been removed and an adapter arrangement <b>300</b> has been mounted, in accordance with the present invention. The adapter arrangement <b>300</b> comprises longitudinal support carriers <b>310</b>, first connecting elements <b>320</b>, second connecting elements <b>330</b>, third connecting elements <b>390</b> and cappings <b>340</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">As is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A-6D</figref> each of the longitudinal support carriers <b>310</b> extends between two transverse carriers <b>120</b> and is provided with snap locks <b>410</b>, <b>420</b> (also shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) at each end to interact with fastening means <b>321</b>, <b>322</b>, <b>331</b>, <b>391</b> on respective first, second and third connecting elements <b>320</b>, <b>330</b>, <b>390</b>. Each of the first, second and third connecting elements <b>320</b>, <b>330</b>, <b>390</b> is provided with snap locks <b>350</b>, <b>360</b>, <b>380</b> and <b>392</b>, respectively, at its underside (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). The snap locks interact with the elongated stanchions <b>130</b><i>a</i>, <b>130</b><i>b </i>for fastening the first, second and third connecting elements <b>320</b>, <b>330</b>, <b>390</b> to the transverse carriers <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The cappings <b>340</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, are arranged on the upper edge of the supporting carriers <b>310</b> facing the screening media and protect the support carriers <b>310</b> from wear from the screened material and also from the screening media. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> the cappings <b>340</b> are shown as extending over two adjacently arranged longitudinal support carriers <b>310</b> that are interconnected by a first connecting element <b>320</b>, but the length of the cappings <b>340</b> can instead be equal to the length of a single support carrier <b>310</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> it is shown that the cappings <b>340</b> extend over three adjacently arranged support carriers <b>310</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> an adapter arrangement is schematically shown, only covering a part of the length of the transverse carriers <b>120</b>, but in practice the adapter arrangement <b>300</b> will be mounted along the entire length of the transverse carriers <b>120</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>) to fully function as support for the mounting of screening media on the screening deck. The cross-tensioned screening media typically extends between the side walls of the vibrating screen, a length which substantially equals the length of the transverse carriers <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref>, <b>4</b>B, <b>4</b><i>c </i>show a first set of adapter parts, the adapter parts including a first connecting element <b>320</b>, a second connecting element <b>330</b>, a third connecting element <b>390</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> it is shown that the first connecting element <b>320</b> further is provided with a slot <b>370</b> having fastening means <b>321</b>, <b>322</b> for receiving the respective ends of two support carriers <b>310</b>. The fastening means <b>321</b> is partly shown, but the fastening means <b>322</b> is concealed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Both fastening means <b>321</b>, <b>322</b> are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The fastening means <b>321</b>, <b>322</b> are arranged to interact with snap locks <b>420</b>, <b>410</b>, respectively, of the support carriers <b>310</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is also shown that the snap locks <b>350</b>, <b>360</b> are arranged to adapt to the difference in height between the stanchions <b>130</b><i>a</i>, <b>130</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>, it is shown that also the second connecting element <b>330</b> is provided with a slot <b>385</b> having fastening means <b>331</b> (concealed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, but shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) for receiving the snap lock <b>410</b> arranged at the end of the support carriers <b>310</b>. The second connecting element <b>330</b> is also provided with a snap lock <b>380</b> at its underside. The snap lock <b>380</b> interacts with the shorter, elongated stanchion <b>130</b><i>a </i>on the transverse carrier <b>120</b> for fastening the second connecting elements <b>330</b> to the transverse carrier <b>120</b>. The second connecting element <b>330</b> is typically used as an end element of the adapter arrangement, adjacent to modular elements <b>110</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 6</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> the third connecting element <b>390</b> is shown as provided with a slot <b>393</b> having fastening means <b>391</b> (concealed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, but shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) for receiving the snap lock <b>420</b> arranged at the end of the support carriers <b>310</b>. The third connecting element <b>390</b> is also provided with a snap lock <b>392</b> at its underside. The snap lock <b>392</b> interacts with the longer, elongated stanchion <b>130</b><i>b </i>on the transverse carrier <b>120</b> for fastening the third connecting element <b>390</b> to the transverse carrier <b>120</b>. The third connecting element <b>390</b> is typically used as an end element of the adapter arrangement, adjacent to the end of the screen (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 6</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">As an alternative to the configuration to the first set of adapter parts shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a second set of adapter parts can be used, adapted to transverse carriers having stanchions of equal height. This alternative configuration of the first, second and third connecting element would otherwise have the same functional structure as the earlier described first, second and third connecting elements <b>320</b>, <b>330</b>, <b>390</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> a support carrier <b>310</b> is shown having two snap locks <b>410</b>, <b>420</b> provided at its two ends. The support carrier <b>310</b> has an upper edge or side <b>430</b>, where a capping <b>340</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) would be mounted to protect the support carrier <b>310</b> from the screened material and the screening media. The support carrier <b>310</b> is further configured: (i) so that the snap lock <b>410</b> interacts with the fastening means <b>331</b> of the second connecting element <b>330</b> or the second fastening means <b>322</b> on the first connecting element <b>320</b>, and (ii) so that the snap lock <b>420</b> interacts with the fastening means <b>391</b> of the third connecting element <b>390</b> or the first fastening means <b>321</b> on the first connecting element <b>320</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The longitudinal support carriers <b>310</b> preferably have different heights to support the screening media in a manner forming the crowned or slightly upwardly curved shape, when mounted. Typically the support carriers <b>310</b> arranged closest to the side walls of the vibrating screen will be lower in height than the support carriers arranged halfway between the side walls to create the slightly upwardly curved shape of the cross-section of the screening media. The support carriers <b>310</b> also serve to support the screening media, when it is mounted.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As an alternative to having longitudinal support carriers <b>310</b> of different heights to create the slightly upwardly curved shape of the cross-section of the screening media, all support carriers <b>310</b> could have the same height and the cappings <b>340</b> could be of different respective heights to create the same effect. Cappings of different heights will be further discussed in connection with a vibrating screen having longitudinal carriers to hold modular screening elements, where the longitudinal support carriers <b>310</b> and the adapter parts are not needed.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A-6C</figref> show respective cross sections of the adapter arrangement <b>300</b> mounted on transverse carriers <b>120</b>. The adapter arrangement <b>300</b> comprises: (i) two of the support carriers <b>310</b> joined together by a first connecting element <b>320</b>, (ii) a second connecting element <b>330</b> to which one end of the support carriers <b>310</b> has been fastened, (iii) a third connecting element to which an opposite end of the support carriers <b>310</b> has been fastened, and (iv) a capping <b>340</b> mounted on top of the two support carriers. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A</figref>, <b>6</b>B and <b>6</b>C it is shown how the respective first, second and third connecting elements <b>320</b>, <b>330</b>, <b>390</b> are attached to the transverse carriers <b>120</b> and how the support carriers <b>310</b> are attached to the first, second and third connecting elements <b>320</b>, <b>330</b>, <b>390</b>. Further <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref> shows the transition between screening elements <b>110</b> and the adapter arrangement <b>300</b> for the screening media.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> a screening deck <b>100</b> of a vibrating screen <b>800</b> according to the invention is shown schematically, after three rows of modular screening elements <b>110</b> have been removed and a cross-tensioned screening media <b>810</b> has been mounted on top of the adapter arrangement <b>300</b>. Even though only one screening media <b>810</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> covering three rows, it is possible to use several screening media with possibly different hole sizes or different configuration of the holes extending between the side walls that are mutually parallel to and successively arranged in the longitudinal direction of the vibrating screen <b>800</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> a screening deck <b>900</b> is shown after modular screening elements <b>110</b> have been replaced by a cross-tensioned screening media <b>920</b> (i.e., the vibrating screen combines different types of screens). On the top edge of longitudinal carriers <b>910</b>, cappings <b>940</b><i>a</i>, <b>940</b><i>b</i>, <b>940</b><i>c </i>are arranged facing a cross-tensioned screening media <b>920</b> and protecting the support carriers <b>900</b> from wear from the screened material and also from the cross-tensioned screening media <b>920</b>. Similar to the transversal carriers <b>120</b>, the longitudinal carriers <b>910</b> are provided with two parallel, elongated stanchions. The stanchions have the same height. The modular screening elements <b>110</b> have snap locks <b>140</b>, which interact with the elongated stanchions for fastening the modular screening elements <b>110</b> to the longitudinal carriers <b>910</b>. The cappings <b>940</b><i>a</i>, <b>940</b><i>b</i>, <b>940</b><i>c </i>are provided with similar snap locks, which interact with the elongated stanchions for fastening the cappings <b>940</b><i>a </i>to the longitudinal carriers. To form the crowned or the slightly curved shape of the screening media and support the cross-tensioned screening media <b>920</b>, the cappings <b>940</b><i>a </i>have different heights. The screening media <b>920</b>, which also can be a pre-tensioned screening media, is fastened by any previously disclosed fastening method.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">When the vibrating screens are very wide, there would be provided an additional holding-down or fixing point with down holding means for holding down the middle of the cross-tensioned screening media so that the crowned shape is not so high as to cause the material being screened to deviate to the sides and producing poor screening results. Thereby two crowned shapes are arranged with the cross-tensioned screening media over the width of the vibrating screen.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">It is an advantage if modular screening elements and one or several screening media can be provided in the same vibrating screen as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, since the two solutions complement each other. Modular screening elements are very good since they have a long lifetime, and wire meshes are very good for screening the gravel into the right fractions of gravel. It is therefore an advantage that both types can be combined in the same vibrating screen by simple actions.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The present invention is implemented in a vibrating screen of the type shown in the Swedish patent application, SE0400337-2, but could of course be modified to function with other vibrating systems having exchangeable modular screening elements without deviating from the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Although the present invention has been described in connection with preferred embodiments thereof, it will be appreciated by those skilled in the art that additions, modifications, substitutions and deletions not specifically described may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as defined in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A vibrating screen for conducting material in a longitudinal direction while screening the material, the vibrating screen comprising a screening deck, exchangeable modular screening media, and an adapter arrangement for mounting the screening media on the deck, the screening deck including transverse carriers oriented transversely of the longitudinal direction, the adapter arrangement comprising longitudinal support carriers arranged substantially in the longitudinal direction, and connecting elements oriented transversely of the longitudinal direction interconnecting the support carriers and connecting the interconnected support carriers on the transverse carriers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the support carriers extend to different respective heights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the screening media is crown-shaped such that portions of the screening media spaced apart transversely of the longitudinal direction extend to different respective heights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the support carriers include support carriers extending to different heights to form the crown shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein longitudinally adjacent screening media extend to different respective heights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein longitudinally adjacent ones of the longitudinal support carriers extend to different respective heights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including capping mounted on upper edges of the longitudinal support carriers and covering the entire longitudinal length of the longitudinal edges.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the capping extend to different respective heights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein longitudinally adjacent capping extend to different respective heights to support longitudinally adjacent screening media at different respective heights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein each of at least some of the transverse carriers includes fastening elements projecting upwardly to different respective heights, the connecting elements being mounted on the fastening elements.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein each of at least some of the transverse carriers includes fastening elements projecting upwardly to the same height, the connecting element being mounted on the fastening elements.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the transverse carriers include upwardly projecting stanchions, and the connecting elements include snap locks engageable with the stanchions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein each of the longitudinal support carriers includes snap locks at respective longitudinal ends thereof, ad the transverse carriers include upstanding stanchions to which the snap locks are connected.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> further including a capping mounted on upper edges of the longitudinal support carriers and covering the entire length thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the screening media comprises cross-tensioned screening media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The vibrating screen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the screening media comprises pre-tensioned screening media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A vibrating screen for conducting material in a longitudinal direction while screening the material, the vibrating screen comprising a screening deck, exchangeable modular screening media, and an adapter arrangement mounting the screening media on the deck, the adapter arrangement comprising longitudinal support carriers arranged substantially in the longitudinal direction, and capping mounted on upper edges of the longitudinal support carriers on which the screening media rests.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
