<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298189-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298189</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10965985</doc-number>
<date>20041015</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2004-0030572</doc-number>
<date>20040430</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327158</main-classification>
<further-classification>327149</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Delay locked loop circuit</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6066969</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kawasaki et al.</name>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327156</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6342796</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Jung</name>
<date>20020100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327141</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6437619</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Okuda et al.</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327158</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6492852</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Fiscus</name>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327158</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6509776</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kobayashi et al.</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327277</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050242854</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051103</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kang</last-name>
<first-name>Yong Gu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chungcheongbuk-do</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chun</last-name>
<first-name>Jun Hyun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chungcheongbuk-do</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ladas &amp; Parry LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hynix Semiconductor Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kyoungki-do</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lam</last-name>
<first-name>Tuan T.</first-name>
<department>2816</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Hernandez</last-name>
<first-name>William</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The DLL circuit detects a frequency of an external clock signal and adjusts a coarse delay during a DLL circuit operation, thereby quickly terminating a feedback operation of the DLL circuit and having a reduced circuit area of a delay line. Therefore, the DLL circuit can be used for next generation high-integration and high-frequency memory devices such as DDR2 SDRAMs.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="129.62mm" wi="255.19mm" file="US07298189-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="252.48mm" wi="152.74mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298189-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="261.87mm" wi="159.00mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298189-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="247.65mm" wi="169.33mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298189-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="235.37mm" wi="184.32mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298189-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="227.08mm" wi="111.51mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298189-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a delay locked loop circuit, and more particularly to a delay locked loop circuit having an improved processing speed and a reduced area for elements of the circuit, so that the delay locked loop circuit can operate in a wide range of a frequency through.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">As generally known in the art, a semiconductor memory device has a phase difference between an externally inputted clock (external clock) and an internal clock due to several causes. That is, a phase of the external clock is delayed due to line loading and a clock input buffer receiving the external clock inputted into the semiconductor memory device. Also, a phase of the external clock is delayed due to line loading, an output buffer which receives internal cell data in order to output the internal cell data to the outside of the semiconductor memory device, and other logic circuits. As described above, a phase delayed by circuits accommodated in the semiconductor memory device is called “skew”. A delayed locked loop circuit compensates for a delay of such a phase.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Such a delayed locked loop circuit prevents occurrence of a phase difference between a clock and data, which are outputted to the outside of the semiconductor memory device from the inside thereof. Accordingly, the delayed locked loop circuit synchronizes a clock used in the semiconductor memory device with a chip-set clock and sends cell data to an external chip-set without errors. That is, in a data read operation, the delayed locked loop circuit equalizes a timing of an externally inputted clock with the timing at which data read from a cell in a semiconductor memory device pass through a data output buffer on the basis of the external clock.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In particular, since the delayed locked circuit used for high-speed synchronization memory devices such as DDR SDRAMs determines an operation frequency band of the memory devices and exerts serious influence on an operation time characteristic, the high-speed synchronization memory devices include a high-performance delay locked loop circuit having a wide frequency band and a low jitter characteristic.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a block diagram of a typical delayed locked loop circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the delay locked loop circuit includes a clock buffer <b>101</b> for receiving external clock signals (CLK and CLKB), a delay line <b>102</b> for receiving an output signal (RCK (rising clock) or FCK (falling clock)) of the clock buffer <b>101</b>, a clock divider <b>105</b> for dividing an output signal of the clock buffer <b>101</b>, a clock divider <b>109</b> for dividing an output signal IRCK from among output signals IRCK and IFCK of the delay line <b>102</b>, a replica delay part <b>108</b> for delaying an output signal of the clock divider <b>109</b> by a predetermined time td<b>1</b>+td<b>2</b>, a phase comparator <b>106</b> for comparing a phase of an output signal FBCLK outputted from the replica delay part <b>108</b> with a phase of an output signal REFLK of the clock divider <b>105</b>, a delay control part <b>107</b> for controlling a delay time of the delay line <b>102</b> by receiving an output signal of the phase comparator <b>106</b>, and a clock driver <b>103</b> for receiving the output signal IRCK or IFCK of the delay line <b>102</b>. An output signal RCKDLL or FCKDLL of the clock driver <b>103</b> controls the operation of a data output driver <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the CLK refers to an external clock signal, and the CLKB refers to an inverted external clock signal having a phase inverse to the CLK.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The clock buffer <b>101</b> is a buffer circuit for receiving the external clock signals CLK and CLKB and converting a voltage level of the clock buffer into a voltage level (e.g., CMOS level) used in a semiconductor device.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The delay line <b>102</b> is a circuit for delaying the output signal RCK or FCK of the clock buffer <b>101</b> by a predetermined time. Generally, the delay line <b>102</b> includes a plurality of unit delay circuits, and a delay time of the delay line <b>102</b> is controlled by the delay control part <b>107</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The clock driver <b>103</b> having a powerful driving force is a clock driving circuit which receives the output signal IRCK or IFCK of the delay line <b>103</b> and generates a driving signal for driving the data output driver <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The data output driver <b>104</b> outputs data to the outside thereof in response to the output signal RCKDLL or FCKDLL of the clock driver <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The clock divider <b>105</b> generates a predetermined reference clock by dividing a clock signal RCK or FCK outputted from the clock buffer <b>101</b> at the ratio of 1/n (generally, n may be ‘4’, ‘8’, ‘16’, etc., as an integer).</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The clock divider <b>109</b> is a circuit for dividing an output signal IRCK frequency of the delay line <b>102</b>. Generally, the clock divider has the same circuit structure as the clock divider <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The replica delay part <b>108</b> is a delay circuit having a delay time tD<b>1</b> and tD<b>2</b> obtained by adding a delay time tD<b>1</b> of the clock buffer <b>101</b> to a delay time tD<b>2</b> of the data output driver <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The phase comparator <b>106</b> compares a phase of the output signal REFCLK of the clock divider <b>105</b> with a phase of a feedback signal, which is an output signal of the replica delay part <b>90</b>. That is, the phase comparator <b>106</b> controls the delay control part <b>107</b> by calculating a delay time difference between tow signals REFCLK and FBCLK.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The delay control part <b>107</b> controls a delay time of the delay line <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">For reference, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, tCK denotes a period of the external clock, the RCK (rising clock) signal, which is the output signal of the clock buffer <b>101</b>, corresponds to the external clock signal CLK, and the FCK (falling clock), which is the output signal of the clock buffer <b>101</b>, corresponds to the external clock signal CLKB. The IRCK (internal rising clock) signal, which is the output signal of the delay line <b>102</b>, is a delay signal of the signal RCK, and the IFCK (internal falling clock) signal, which is the output signal of the delay line <b>102</b>, is a delay signal of the FCK signal.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the clock divider <b>105</b> receives only the RCK signal from among the output signals of the clock buffer <b>101</b>. Also, the clock divider <b>109</b> receives only the IRCK signal from among output signals of the delay line <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Hereinafter, a basic operation of the delay locked loop circuit will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The phase comparator <b>106</b> compares a phase of the output signal REFCLK of the clock divider <b>105</b> with a phase of the output signal FBCK of the replica delay part <b>90</b>, and sends a predetermined signal to the delay control part <b>107</b>. The control part <b>107</b> controls the delay line <b>102</b> in such a manner that the delay line <b>102</b> adjusts a delay time in order to minimize a phase difference. The control procedure is repeated until the phase difference is removed.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">However, a conventional delay locked loop circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> has the following problems.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">1. It is necessary to increase the number of unit delay circuits included in the delay line <b>102</b> in order to operate the delay locked loop circuit in a wide frequency band.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">2. If the number of the unit delay circuits is increased, an area occupied by the delay line <b>102</b> is large.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">3. The more the number of the unit delay circuits is, the more the power consumption is.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Accordingly, the present invention has been made to solve the above-mentioned problems occurring in the prior art, and an object of the present invention is to provide a delay locked loop circuit having a fast locking function and a relatively reduced delay line area.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Another object of the present invention is to provide a delay locked loop circuit suitable for a wide frequency band.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Still another object of the present invention is to provide a delay locked loop circuit having a fast locking function by including a unit for detecting levels of frequencies (lengths of periods) of external clock signals (CLK and CLKB).</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In order to accomplish this object according to an aspect of the present invention, there is provided a delay locked loop circuit comprising: a clock buffer for receiving an external clock signal; a delay selection part for receiving an output signal of the clock buffer, delaying the output signal by a predetermined time, and outputting the output signal; a delay line for receiving an output signal of the delay selection part, delaying the output signal by a predetermined time, and outputting the output signal; a first clock divider for dividing a frequency of the output signal of the clock buffer at the ratio of 1/n (n=a natural number of at least two) a second clock divider for dividing a frequency of the output signal of the delay line at the ratio of 1/n; a replica delay part for delaying an output signal of the second divider by a predetermined time; a phase comparator for comparing a phase of an output signal of the first divider with a phase of an output signal of the replica delay part; a delay controller for adjusting a delay time of the delay line in response to an output signal of the phase comparator; and a clock period detector for receiving the output signal of the first clock divider and the output signal of the replica delay part and outputting a first control signal group and a second control signal group, wherein the first control signal group is applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider so as to delay signals applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider, and the second control signal group is applied to the delay selection part so as to adjust a delay time of the delay selection part.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">According to the present invention, when a frequency of the external clock signal is within a reference frequency range, the first clock divider and the second clock divider controlled by the first control signal group divide signals applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider after delaying the signals by a first delay time. Also, when the frequency of the external clock signal is higher than the reference frequency range, the first clock divider and the second clock divider divide signals applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider after delaying the signals by a second delay time shorter than the first delay time, and, when the frequency of the external clock signal is lower than the reference frequency range, the first clock divider and the second clock divider divide signals applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider after delaying the signals by a third delay time longer than the first delay time.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">According to the present invention, the higher the frequency of the external clock signal is as compared with the reference frequency range, the longer the delay time of the delay selection part determined by the second control signal group is, and the lower the frequency of the external clock signal is as compared with the reference frequency range, the shorter the delay time of the delay selection part determined by the second control signal group is.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The above and other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will be more apparent from the following detailed description taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a typical delay locked loop circuit;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of a delay locked loop circuit according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates an example of a clock period detector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates an RC delay selection part according to one embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates an example of a delay circuit used for delay parts shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Hereinafter, a preferred embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to the accompanying drawings. In the following description and drawings, the same reference numerals are used to designate the same or similar components, and so repetition of the description on the same or similar components will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates an example of a delay locked loop circuit according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the delay locked loop circuit according to the present invention includes a clock buffer <b>201</b> for receiving external clock signals CLK and CLKB, an RC delay selecting part <b>211</b> for receiving an output signal of the clock buffer <b>201</b> and delaying RC, a delay line <b>202</b> for receiving an output signal RCKD or FCKD of the RC delay selection part <b>211</b>, a clock divider <b>205</b> for dividing an output signal of the clock buffer <b>201</b>, a clock divider <b>209</b> for dividing an output signal (IRCK) from among output signals IRCK and IFCK of the delay line <b>202</b>, a replica delay part <b>208</b> for delaying an output signal of the clock divider <b>209</b> by a predetermined time tD<b>1</b>+tD<b>2</b>, a phase comparator <b>206</b> for comparing a phase of an output signal FBCLK outputted from the replica delay part <b>208</b> with a phase of an output signal REFLK of the clock divider <b>205</b>, a delay control part <b>207</b> for controlling a delay time of the delay line <b>202</b> by receiving an output signal of the phase comparator <b>206</b>, a clock driver <b>203</b> for receiving an output signal IRCK or IFCK of the delay line <b>202</b>, and a clock period detector <b>210</b> for receiving the output signal of the clock divider <b>205</b> and the output signal of the replica delay part <b>208</b> and outputting a first control signal group and a second control signal group.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Since functions and structures of the clock buffer <b>201</b>, the delay line <b>202</b>, the clock driver <b>203</b>, the data output driver <b>204</b>, the phase comparator <b>206</b>, the delay control part <b>207</b>, the replica delay part <b>208</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> are identical to those shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, overlapping description will be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the clock divider <b>205</b> receives only the RCK signal from among output signals of the clock buffer <b>201</b>. The RCK signal applied to the clock divider <b>205</b> is delayed by a predetermined time by a signal TCK&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>3</b>&gt; applied to the clock divider <b>205</b>. The signal TCK&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>3</b>&gt; is outputted from the clock period detector <b>210</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> to be described later.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The clock divider <b>209</b> receives only the IRCK signal from among output signals of the delay line <b>202</b>. The IRCK signal is delayed by a predetermined time using the signal TCK&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>3</b>&gt; applied to the clock divider <b>209</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The delay locked loop circuit shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> according to the present invention further includes the clock period detector <b>210</b> for detecting a period of the external clock signal CLK. Signals applied to the clock dividers <b>205</b> and <b>209</b> are divided by the control signal TCK&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>3</b>&gt; outputted from the clock period detector <b>210</b>, after delaying the signals by a predetermined time. A delay time of the RC delay selection part <b>211</b> is determined by a control signal DET &lt;<b>1</b>:<b>5</b>&gt; outputted from the clock period detector <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Hereinafter, description about the clock period detector <b>210</b> will be given.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates an embodiment of the clock period detector <b>210</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The clock period detector <b>210</b> according to the present invention operates only when the delay locked loop circuit initially operates. Also, the clock period detector <b>210</b> detects a clock period and outputs a plurality of detection signals DET&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>5</b>&gt;.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the clock period detector includes an enable part <b>301</b>, delay parts <b>302</b> to <b>305</b>, detection units <b>306</b> to <b>310</b>, and a control signal generating part <b>311</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The enable part <b>301</b> outputs a signal for enabling operations of the detection units <b>306</b> to <b>310</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the enable part <b>301</b> receives an output signal REFCLK of the clock divider <b>205</b> and an output signal FBCLK of the replica delay part <b>208</b>, so as to output a signal DE&lt;<b>1</b>&gt; by means of an output port REFCKIB.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The delay part <b>302</b> receives the output signal FBCLK of the replica delay part <b>208</b> and outputs a signal DE&lt;<b>2</b>&gt; by means of an output port (out) after delaying the signal by a predetermined time.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The delay part <b>303</b> receives the output signal DE&lt;<b>2</b>&gt; of the delay part <b>302</b> and outputs a signal DE&lt;<b>3</b>&gt; by means of an output port (out) after delaying the signal by a predetermined time.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The delay part <b>304</b> receives the output signal DE&lt;<b>3</b>&gt; of the delay part <b>303</b> and outputs a signal DE&lt;<b>4</b>&gt; by means of an output port (out) after delaying the signal by a predetermined time.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The delay part <b>305</b> receives the output signal DE&lt;<b>4</b>&gt; of the delay part <b>304</b> and outputs a signal DE&lt;<b>5</b>&gt; by means of an output port (out) after delaying the signal by a predetermined time.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The delay parts <b>302</b> to <b>305</b> have the same structure, and a detailed embodiment of each delay part is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The detection unit <b>306</b> compares the output signal DE&lt;<b>1</b>&gt; of the enable part <b>301</b> with the output signal REFCLK of the clock divider <b>205</b> and outputs a detection signal DET&lt;<b>1</b>&gt;.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The detection unit <b>307</b> compares the output signal DE&lt;<b>1</b>&gt; of the enable part <b>301</b> with the output signal DE&lt;<b>2</b>&gt; of the delay part <b>302</b> and outputs a detection signal DET&lt;<b>2</b>&gt;.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">The detection unit <b>308</b> compares the output signal DE&lt;<b>1</b>&gt; of the enable part <b>301</b> with the output signal DE&lt;<b>3</b>&gt; of the delay part <b>303</b> and outputs a detection signal DET&lt;<b>3</b>&gt;.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The detection unit <b>309</b> compares the output signal DE&lt;<b>1</b>&gt; of the enable part <b>301</b> with the output signal DE&lt;<b>4</b>&gt; of the delay part <b>304</b> and outputs a detection signal DET&lt;<b>4</b>&gt;.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The detection unit <b>310</b> compares the output signal DE&lt;<b>1</b>&gt; of the enable part <b>301</b> with the output signal DE&lt;<b>5</b>&gt; of the delay part <b>305</b> and outputs a detection signal DET&lt;<b>5</b>&gt;.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The control signal generating part <b>311</b> receives the output signals DET&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>5</b>&gt; of the detection units <b>306</b> to <b>310</b> and outputs the signal TCK&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>3</b>&gt; for controlling the clock divider <b>209</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a signal TCKSETB is a setting signal for controlling an operation of the control signal generating part <b>311</b>. That is, the external clock signal having a period of 10 to 20 ns enables the signal TCK <b>1</b>, the external clock signal having a period of 3.75 to 10 ns enables the signal TCK <b>2</b>, the external clock signal having a period of 2 to 3.75 ns enables the signal TCK<b>3</b>. An initial default signal outputted from the control signal generating part <b>311</b> is the signal TCK<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">As described above, the output signal TCK&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>3</b>&gt; of the control signal generating part <b>311</b> delays signals applied to the clock dividers <b>205</b> and <b>209</b> by a predetermined time.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">That is, when the signal TCK<b>1</b> is enabled, the clock dividers delay applied signals RCK and IRCK by 3tCLK (tCLK denotes a period of the CLK), and divide the applied signals. When the signal TCK<b>2</b> is enabled, the clock dividers delay applied signals RCK and IRCK by 2tCLK, and divide the applied signals. When the signal TCK<b>3</b> is enabled, the clock dividers delay applied signals RCK and IRCK by tCLK, and divide the applied signals. Although a procedure for generating the signals TCK&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>3</b>&gt; is described in the specification providing that the clock dividers <b>205</b> and <b>209</b> employ three delay periods, this can be changed.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates the RC selection part <b>211</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a delay part <b>411</b> receives a signal RCK and outputs the signal RCK after delaying the signal RCK by a predetermined time. Herein, the signal RCK is an output signal of the clock buffer <b>201</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The delay part <b>411</b> operates when a detection signal DET&lt;<b>2</b>&gt; is enabled. An output signal of the delay part <b>411</b> is marked as “RCKD&lt;<b>1</b>&gt;”.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">A delay part <b>412</b> receives the output signal of the delay part <b>411</b> and outputs the output signal after delaying the output signal by a predetermined time. The delay part <b>412</b> operates when a detection signal DET&lt;<b>3</b>&gt; is enabled. An output signal of the delay part <b>412</b> is marked as “RCKD&lt;<b>2</b>&gt;”.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">A delay part <b>413</b> receives the output signal of the delay part <b>412</b> and outputs the output signal after delaying the output signal by a predetermined time. The delay part <b>413</b> operates when a detection signal DET&lt;<b>4</b>&gt; is enabled. An output signal of the delay part <b>413</b> is marked as “RCKD&lt;<b>3</b>&gt;”.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">A delay part <b>414</b> receives the output signal of the delay part <b>413</b> and outputs the output signal after delaying the output signal by a predetermined time. The delay part <b>414</b> operates when a detection signal DET&lt;<b>5</b>&gt; is enabled. An output signal of the delay part <b>414</b> is marked as “RCKD&lt;<b>4</b>&gt;”.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Accordingly, a signal outputted to a node ‘a’ is a signal RCKD&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>4</b>&gt;obtained after the signal RCK is delayed by a predetermined time.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">A selection part <b>415</b> is a circuit which outputs a signal RCKD by combining the signal RCKD&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>4</b>&gt; applied through the node ‘a’, a detection signal DET&lt;<b>2</b>:<b>5</b>&gt;, and an output signal RCK of the clock buffer <b>201</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a delay part <b>421</b> receives a signal FCK and outputs the signal FCK after delaying the signal RCK by a predetermined time. Herein, the signal FCK is an output signal of the clock buffer <b>201</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The delay part <b>421</b> operates when a detection signal DET&lt;<b>2</b>&gt; is enabled. An output signal of the delay part <b>421</b> is marked as “FCKD&lt;<b>1</b>&gt;”.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">A delay part <b>422</b> receives the output signal of the delay part <b>421</b> and outputs the output signal after delaying the output signal by a predetermined time. The delay part <b>421</b> operates when a detection signal DET&lt;<b>3</b>&gt; is enabled. An output signal of the delay part <b>422</b> is marked as “FCKD&lt;<b>2</b>&gt;”.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">A delay part <b>423</b> receives the output signal of the delay part <b>422</b> and outputs the output signal after delaying the output signal by a predetermined time. The delay part <b>423</b> operates when a detection signal DET&lt;<b>4</b>&gt; is enabled. An output signal of the delay part <b>423</b> is marked as “FCKD&lt;<b>3</b>&gt;”.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">A delay part <b>424</b> receives the output signal of the delay part <b>423</b> and outputs the output signal after delaying the output signal by a predetermined time. The delay part <b>424</b> operates when a detection signal DET&lt;<b>5</b>&gt; is enabled. An output signal of the delay part <b>424</b> is marked as “FCKD&lt;<b>4</b>&gt;”.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">Accordingly, a signal outputted to a node ‘b’ is a signal FCKD&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>4</b>&gt; obtained after the signal FCK is delayed by a predetermined time.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">A selection part <b>425</b> is a circuit, which outputs a signal FCKD by combining the signal FCKD&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>4</b>&gt; applied through the node ‘b’, a detection signal DET&lt;<b>2</b>:<b>5</b>&gt;, and an output signal FCK of the clock buffer <b>201</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">Generally, the delay parts shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> include a plurality of RC circuits connected to each other in series. In particular, the delay parts may include circuits shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. In this case, a delay time of an RC delay circuit is adjusted according to a frequency of an external clock signal.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">As understood with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the RC delay selection part is a circuit for delaying the output signal of the clock buffer <b>201</b> by a predetermined time using an output signal DEG&lt;<b>2</b>:<b>5</b>&gt; of the clock period detector. As a result, the delay time of the RC delay section part is determined by a detection signal outputted from the clock period detector <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">That is, after detecting a period of the external clock signal, the clock period detector according to the present invention previously changes a phase of a clock signal applied to the delay line <b>202</b> using the detected period so that two signals compared with each other in the phase comparator <b>206</b> are quickly synchronized with each other within allowance. Herein, the delay locked loop circuit according to the present invention adjusts a coarse delay through the RC delay selection part <b>211</b>. Thereafter, the delay locked loop circuit adjusts a fine delay through the delay line <b>202</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates an example of a delay circuit used for the delay parts <b>302</b> to <b>305</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, it can be understood that a delay time is adjusted by using resistors and capacitors. As described above, an influence on the delay circuit according to PVT (processes, voltage, temperature) can be reduced through the usage of resistors and capacitors.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">As described above, according to the present invention, the clock period detector is provided so as to detect a period of a clock, the RC delay selection part uses the detection information so as to adjust a coarse delay according to the length of a clock signal period, and the delay line adjusts a fine delay. As a result, since the RC delay selection part adjusts a coarse delay, the number of unit delay circuits included in the delay line can be reduced and fast locking can be quickly performed. Also, since delay periods of the clock dividers <b>205</b> and <b>209</b> are determined by a control signal TCK&lt;<b>1</b>:<b>3</b>&gt; outputted from the clock period detector, a delay locked loop circuit operable through a wide range of frequencies can be realized.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">As described above, according to the present invention, the delay locked loop can quickly perform normal functions. Also, a high integrated circuit can be realized by reducing an area of the delay line. Also, since the delay locked loop circuit is realized suitably for a wide range of frequencies, the delay locked loop circuit can be practically employed for next generation memories such as DDR2 SDRAMs in a high-speed frequency operation.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">Although a preferred embodiment of the present invention has been described for illustrative purposes, those skilled in the art will appreciate that various modifications, additions and substitutions are possible, without departing from the scope and spirit of the invention as disclosed in the accompanying claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A delay locked loop circuit comprising:
<claim-text>a clock buffer for receiving an external clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a delay selection part for receiving an output signal of the clock buffer, delaying the output signal by a predetermined time, and outputting the output signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a delay line for receiving an output signal of the delay selection part, delaying the output signal by a predetermined time, and outputting the output signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first clock divider for dividing a frequency of the output signal of the clock buffer at the ratio of 1/n (n=a natural number of at least two);</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second clock divider for dividing a frequency of the output signal of the delay line at the ratio of 1/n;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a replica delay part for delaying an output signal of the second divider by a predetermined time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a phase comparator for comparing a phase of an output signal of the first divider with a phase of an output signal of the replica delay part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a delay controller for adjusting a delay time of the delay line in response to an output signal of the phase comparator; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a clock period detector for receiving the output signal of the first clock divider and the output signal of the replica delay part and outputting a first control signal group and a second control signal group,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first control signal group is applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider so as to delay signals applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider, and wherein the second control signal group is applied to the delay selection part so as to adjust a delay time of the delay selection part.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The delay locked loop circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein, when a frequency of the external clock signal is within a reference frequency range, the first clock divider and the second clock divider controlled by the first control signal group divide signals applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider after delaying the signals by a first delay time.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The delay locked loop circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein, when the frequency of the external clock signal is higher than the reference frequency range, the first clock divider and the second clock divider divide signals applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider after delaying the signals by a second delay time shorter than the first delay time, and, when the frequency of the external clock signal is lower than the reference frequency range, the first clock divider and the second clock divider divide signals applied to the first clock divider and the second clock divider after delaying the signals by a third delay time longer than the first delay time.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The delay locked loop circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the higher the frequency of the external clock signal is as compared with a reference frequency range, the longer the delay time of the delay selection part determined by the second control signal group is, and the lower the frequency of the external clock signal is as compared with the reference frequency range, the shorter the delay time of the delay selection part determined by the second control signal group is.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A delay locked loop circuit comprising:
<claim-text>a clock buffer for receiving an external clock signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a delay selection part for receiving an output signal of the clock buffer and delaying and outputting the output signal in response to input of a predetermined clock period detecting signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a delay line for receiving an output signal of the delay selection part and outputting the output signal after a fine delay;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first clock divider for dividing a frequency of the output signal of the clock buffer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second clock divider for dividing a frequency of the output signal of the delay line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a replica delay part for delaying an output signal of the second clock divider by a predetermined time;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a phase comparator for comparing a phase of an output signal of the first clock divider with a phase of an output signal of the replica delay part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a delay control part for adjusting a delay time of the delay line in response to an output signal of the phase comparator; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a clock period detector for receiving the output signal of the first clock divider and the output signal of the replica delay part and outputting the clock period detecting signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The delay locked loop circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the clock period detector includes a control signal generating part for receiving the clock period detecting signal and a predetermined setting signal and outputting a control signal for controlling delay periods of the first clock divider and the second clock divider.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The delay locked loop circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the first clock divider determines the delay period in response to input of the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The delay locked loop circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the second clock divider determines the delay period in response to input of the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The delay locked loop circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the clock period detector further includes:
<claim-text>an enable part for receiving the output signal of the first clock divider and the output signal of the replica delay part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of delay parts for outputting a plurality of delay signals; and
<claim-text>a detection unit for outputting the clock period detecting signal in response to input of output signals of the enable part and the delay parts.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The delay locked loop circuit as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the delay parts include an RC delay part.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
