<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299479-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299479</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10883843</doc-number>
<date>20040706</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>92120647 A</doc-number>
<date>20030729</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>393</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>33</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>17</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>17</main-group>
<subgroup>03</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>33</main-group>
<subgroup>14</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>720601</main-classification>
<further-classification>720648</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Optical recording and/or reproducing device with a buffer member</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4533966</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kume</name>
<date>19850800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360 965</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4607301</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Iizuka</name>
<date>19860800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360 93</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6094323</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tong</name>
<date>20000700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360 9702</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6246654</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Omori et al.</name>
<date>20010600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>720604</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6411583</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Yamamoto et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>720647</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6426932</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Omori et al.</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>720648</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6650609</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Omori et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>720649</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6971111</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chuang et al.</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>720601</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7069563</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Huang et al.</name>
<date>20060600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>720601</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-236775</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>720601</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>720648</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050028175</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050203</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lin</last-name>
<first-name>Chih-Cheng</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Birch, Stewart, Kolasch &amp; Birch, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>ASUSTeK Computer Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Castro</last-name>
<first-name>Angel</first-name>
<department>2627</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Magee</last-name>
<first-name>Christopher R.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An optical disk drive includes a disk-carrying tray, a shielding member and buffer member disposed at adjoining position of the disk-carrying tray and the shielding member to absorb impact of broken pieces in case of breakup of an optical disk during the reading and writing operations.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="40.39mm" wi="156.80mm" file="US07299479-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="185.42mm" wi="141.56mm" file="US07299479-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="130.98mm" wi="164.34mm" file="US07299479-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="240.11mm" wi="168.99mm" file="US07299479-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="67.56mm" wi="159.00mm" file="US07299479-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This Nonprovisional application claims priority under 35 U.S.C. ยง 119(a) on patent application Ser. No. 092120647 filed in TAIWAN, R.O.C. on Jul. 29, 2003, the entire contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention relates to an optical disk drive, more particularly to an optical disk drive which includes a disk-carrying tray, a shielding member and a buffer member disposed at adjoining position of the disk-carrying tray and the shielding member so as to absorb impact of broken pieces of an optical disk that fly out due to outbreak of the optical disk under high rotation speed.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Advance of personal computer consequently results in swift improvement in the peripheral accessories, such as a hard disk drive, a DVD player, a scanning machine, and a printing machine. The peripheral accessories are inevitable tools in an office. Since the cost of the peripheral accessories becomes cheaper day-by-day, they are widely used at homes not only in offices. An optical disk drive, such as a DVD player, is widely used since an optical disk is capable of storing a large amount of data permanently. The stored data may include music and movies that can be written in programs and are stored in the optical disk. The latest DVD disk (digital versatile disc) of 17 GB has a relatively large storage capacity and subsequently renders a wide use of the DVD player at home and offices.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In order to increase the reading efficiency of the device <b>10</b>, the optical disk is arranged in such manner to rotate under high speed. The motor for running the optical disk of 40ร rotates 8000 rotations per minute. Under such high speed, the centrifugal force resulting from rotation of the optical disk is relatively large. There is possibility of a breakup of the rotating disk under high rotation speed.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">To lower the price of DVD disk, the manufacturing cost thereof must also be reduced. Some of the DVD disk manufacturers use recycled plastic in order to cut down the price of the DVD disk such that the quality of some of the DVC is subsequently affected and the service life and durability are consequently shortened. In some cases, interrupted tracks can be found on the inner portion of the recording surface of the optical disk. Such a DVD disk is susceptible to break under high rotation speed.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Imperfect production may cause the DVD disk to have a plurality of bubbles. Uneven coating on the recording surface of the DVD disk and improper utility of the DVD disk may cause the DVD disk to bend in one direction, which in turn, offset the gravity center away from an axis of the DVD disk. The DVD disk may vibrate in upward-and-downward direction under the high rotation speed. In case the DVD disk is produced from poor quality, a crack up or rupture of the DVD disk is possible.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a conventional optical disk drive <b>10</b> (a DVD player) is installed in a personal computer <b>1</b> so as to perform reading of the optical disk, and includes a disk compartment, a disk-carrying tray <b>12</b> disposed within the disk compartment and extendible outwardly therefrom upon pressing of an on/off switch <b>10</b>S that is formed on an outer face of the disk compartment. The disk-carrying tray <b>12</b> is formed with a recess to receive the optical disk <b>11</b> therein, and is retractable into the disk compartment upon pressing of the on/off switch <b>10</b>S. A shielding member <b>14</b> is attached to a distal end of the disk-carrying tray <b>12</b> in such a manner that the shielding member <b>14</b> is flush with the outer face of the disk compartment so as to provide aesthetic effect and prevent dirt from getting thereinto when the disk-carrying tray retracts interior of the disk compartment.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Note that the disk-carrying tray <b>12</b> and the shielding member <b>14</b> are made from plastic material, and are not integrally formed together. The shielding member <b>14</b> is attached to the disk-carrying tray <b>12</b> via hook-and-loop engagement. In case there is cracking or breakup of the optical disk under high rotation speed, the disk-carrying tray <b>12</b> and the shielding member <b>14</b> are first to be collided by the broken pieces, which in turn, may result in disengagement of the shielding member <b>14</b> from the disk-carrying tray <b>12</b>. The fly out broken pieces of the optical disk may injure a person standing nearby the device <b>10</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a state of cracking of the optical disk <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, to solve the aforesaid drawback, an elongated metal bar <b>16</b> is mounted rearwardly of the shielding member <b>14</b> in order to prevent impact of the broken pieces against the shielding member <b>14</b>. Two fastener screws <b>18</b> extends through opposite ends of the metal bar <b>16</b>, are fastened to the lateral side walls <b>17</b> of the disk compartment. Under such arrangement, the metal bar <b>16</b> can prevent the dispersion of the broken pieces. However, damage to the reading or/and writing head may result since the head can be collided by the broken pieces, which rebound from the metal bar <b>16</b>. In addition, boring of two holes in the lateral sidewalls <b>17</b> of the disk compartment for mounting of the metal bar <b>16</b> causes a large manufacture expense of the device <b>10</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The object of the present invention is to provide an optical disk drive that has a buffer member disposed at adjoining position of a disk-carrying tray and a shielding member so as to prevent and absorb the impact of broken pieces resulting from cracking of the optical disk under the high rotation speed during the reading operation.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to the present invention, an optical disk drive is provided to include: a disk compartment having an entrance-and-exit opening; a disk-carrying tray mounted within an interior of the disk compartment, and defining a disk-receiving recess therein, the disk carrying tray being movable between an opening position, in which the disk-carrying tray is exposed from the disk compartment via the opening so as to permit placing of the optical disk on the disk-receiving recess in the disk-carrying tray, and a closing position, in which the disk-carrying tray is withdrawn into the disk compartment to permit reading and writing of the optical disk; a shielding member attached to the disk-carrying tray in such a manner that the shielding member covers the opening and flushes with an outer surface of the disk compartment when the disk-carrying tray is disposed at the closing position; and a buffer member mounted on the disk-carrying tray, disposed rearwardly of the shielding member in such a manner that the buffer member blocks the opening in the disk compartment so as to stop and absorb impact of broken pieces in case a breakup of the optical disk occurs when the disk-carrying tray is disposed at the closing position.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Further scope of the applicability of the present invention will become apparent from the detailed description given hereinafter. However, it should be understood that the detailed description and specific examples, while indicating preferred embodiments of the invention, are given by way of illustration only, since various changes and modifications within the spirit and scope of the invention will become apparent to those skilled in the art from this detailed description.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWING</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The present invention will become more fully understood from the following detailed description and the accompanying drawings, which are given by way or illustration only, and thus are not limitative of the present invention, and in which:</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a perspective view a conventional disk recording and/or reproducing device installed in a CPU of a personal computer;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an enlarged perspective view, illustrating an interior of the conventional disk recording and/or reproducing device;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective fragmentary view of the preferred embodiment of an optical disk recording and/or reproducing device according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a fragmentary view, illustrating a disk-carrying tray of the preferred embodiment at an opening position; and</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a lateral side view of the disk-carrying tray of the preferred embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCCRIPTIONS OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a fragmentary perspective view of the preferred embodiment of an optical disk drive <b>2</b> according to the present invention is shown and is generally installed in a personal computer (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the device <b>2</b> includes a disk compartment <b>20</b>, a disk-carrying tray <b>21</b>, a tray driving mechanism (not visible), a shielding member <b>22</b>, and a buffer member <b>23</b>. The disk compartment <b>20</b> has opposite front and rear sides, and an entrance-and-exit opening <b>201</b> at the front end thereof. The disk-carrying tray <b>21</b> is mounted within an interior of the disk compartment <b>20</b>, and defines a disk-receiving recess therein. The structure of the tray driving mechanism is not the relevant feature of the present invention, a detailed description thereof is omitted herein for the sake of brevity.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">An on/off switch <b>202</b> is mounted on the disk compartment <b>20</b> below the opening <b>201</b>. The disk compartment <b>20</b> is further formed with a plurality of switches, such as volume adjusting switch, power indicating light, socket holes to receive microphone cable and etc. The disk-carrying tray <b>21</b> is movable upon pressing of the on/off switch <b>202</b> between an opening position of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, in which the disk-carrying tray <b>21</b> is exposed from the disk compartment <b>20</b> via the opening <b>201</b> so as to permit placing of the optical disk (DVD) on the disk-receiving recess in the disk-carrying tray <b>21</b>, and a closing position, in which the disk-carrying tray <b>21</b> is withdrawn into the disk compartment <b>20</b> to permit reading and writing operation of the disk.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The shielding member <b>22</b> is attached to the disk-carrying tray <b>21</b> in such a manner that the shielding member <b>22</b> covers the opening <b>201</b> and flushes with an outer surface of the disk compartment <b>20</b> when the disk-carrying tray <b>21</b> is withdrawn into the disk compartment, thereby disposing the same at the closing position, where reading or writing operation of the disk can be conducted.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The buffer member <b>23</b> is mounted adhesively on an inner surface of the shielding member <b>22</b> in such a manner that the buffer member <b>23</b> blocks the opening <b>201</b> so as to stop and absorb impact of broken pieces in case there is a breakup of the disk <b>24</b> when the disk-carrying tray <b>21</b> is disposed at the closing position.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In this preferred embodiment, the buffer member <b>23</b> extends along the width of the opening <b>201</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) such that when there is a crack in the disk during the reading or writing operation, the impact force of broken pieces that fly out under high velocity is absorb by the buffer member <b>23</b>. Under this condition, in case the reading and/or writing head of the device <b>2</b> is collided by the broken pieces, the head is not damaged because the force of the broken pieces that rebound from the buffer member is greatly reduced. Preferably, the buffer member <b>23</b> is made from elastomeric material, such as silicon rubber, latex, foam, and MYLAR, and has a plate-like configuration with a thickness ranging from 0.5 mm to 5.0 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Since provision of the buffer member <b>23</b> blocks the opening <b>201</b> in the disk compartment <b>20</b>, the broken pieces of the disk are confined within the disk compartment <b>20</b> in case cracking of the disk occurs during the reading and writing operation. The object of the invention is accordingly achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">While the present invention has been described in connection with what is considered the most practical and preferred embodiments, it is understood that this invention is not limited to the disclosed embodiments but is intended to cover various arrangements included within the spirit and scope of the broadest interpretation so as to encompass all such modifications and equivalent arrangements.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An optical disk drive capable of preventing occurrence of breakup of an optical disk therewithin, the device comprising:
<claim-text>a disk compartment having an entrance-and-exit opening;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a disk-carrying tray mounted within an interior of said disk compartment, said disk carrying tray being movable between an opening position and a closing position, in which said disk-carrying tray is withdrawn into said disk compartment to permit reading and writing of the optical disk;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shielding member attached to said disk-carrying tray in such a manner that said shielding member covers said opening and flushes with an outer surface of said disk compartment when said disk-carrying tray is disposed at said closing position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a buffer member mounted on said disk-carrying tray, disposed rearwardly of said shielding member in such a manner that said buffer member blocks said opening so as to stop and absorb impact of broken pieces in case a breakup of the optical disk occurs when said disk-carrying tray is disposed at said closing position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The optical disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said buffer member is attached adhesively on an inner surface of said shielding member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The optical disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said buffer member is made from an elastomeric material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The optical disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said buffer member has a thickness ranging from 0.5 mm to 5.0 mm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An optical disk drive capable of preventing occurrence of breakup of an optical disk therewithin, the device comprising:
<claim-text>a disk-carrying tray for carrying the optical disk thereon;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an entrance-and-exit opening via which said disk-carrying tray is exposed and withdrawn;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shielding member attached to said disk-carrying tray in such a manner that said shielding member covers said opening when said disk-carrying tray is withdrawn into the device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a buffer member having a plate-like configuration and mounted at adjoining position between said disk-carrying tray and said shielding member, wherein said buffer member is adapted to absorb impact of the broken pieces which fly out due to breakup of the optical disk.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The optical disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said buffer member is adapted to absorb impact and abrasion of the broken pieces which fly out due to breakup of the optical disk during reading and/or writing operations.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The optical disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said buffer member is mounted adhesively on said shielding member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The optical disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein is made from an elastomeric material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The optical disk drive according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said buffer member has a thickness ranging from 0.5 mm to 5.0 mm.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
