<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297219-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297219</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>08844267</doc-number>
<date>19970418</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>08</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>29</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>53</main-group>
<subgroup>58</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156173</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Drum assembly for an internal drum imaging device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4312696</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bryant</name>
<date>19820100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>156415</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4977473</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Arai et al.</name>
<date>19901200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360130</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>43840761</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438490</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438 62</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156171</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156173</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156131</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156132</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156133</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156346</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156401</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156403</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156415-417</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156420</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156182</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156189</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156190</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>156195</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>420221</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Menard</last-name>
<first-name>Alan W.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Bolton</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Petersen</last-name>
<first-name>Kenneth R.</first-name>
<address>
<city>West Hartford</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>McCormick, Paulding, Huber LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Gerber Systems Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>South Windsor</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Dixon</last-name>
<first-name>Merrick</first-name>
<department>1774</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method for manufacturing a drum assembly for an internal drum-type imaging apparatus, and a drum assembly produced using the method. The drum assembly defines an imaging surface which is at least semi-cylindrical. A drum skin defines an imaging surface, and is releasably wrapped around a cylindrical mandrel, which has an axis. The mandrel and wrapped drum skin have a first radius. A drum includes more than one drum portion, and is attached to the drum skin over an at least semi-cylindrical interface. The drum has a radius slightly greater than the first radius, and the drum and attached drum skin cooperate to define a vacuum chamber. A fluid bearing is generated between the drum skin and the mandrel, preferably by pressurizing the vacuum chamber, in order to separate the drum skin from the mandrel. The drum and attached drum skin are then moved relative to the mandrel and in a direction parallel to the axis to remove the drum assembly from the mandrel. The drum and drum skin provide an imaging surface that is greater than semi-cylindrical.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="109.90mm" wi="84.41mm" file="US07297219-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="250.36mm" wi="198.20mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297219-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="189.15mm" wi="171.79mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297219-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="282.70mm" wi="164.76mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297219-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="267.21mm" wi="172.97mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297219-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="210.14mm" wi="208.96mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297219-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="263.74mm" wi="188.04mm" file="US07297219-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="264.16mm" wi="163.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297219-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="267.21mm" wi="145.88mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297219-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to internal drum-type imaging devices, and more particularly to a method for manufacturing a drum assembly for such devices, and a drum assembly made using the method.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">CROSS REFERENCES TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Some of the matter contained in this application is disclosed in the commonly-owned U.S. patent application Ser. Nos. 08/844,250, entitled “Multiple Beam Scanning System For An Imaging Device”, and Ser. No. 08/844,668 entitled “Media Feed Apparatus for An Imaging Device”, both filed on even date herewith. Each of the foregoing patent applications are expressly incorporated by reference herein.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Imaging devices including internal drum design, such as photoplotters and scanners, are known in the art. Photoplotters are used, for example, in the fields of printing plate production, graphic arts and the fabrication of printed circuit boards. Photoplotters expose a photo-sensitive media plate disposed on a drum imaging surface by sweeping a modulated optical beam over the media plate. The modulated optical beam is provided by a beam generator. Scanners function by illuminating a sample copy mounted on the drum with an unmodulated optical beam. The light which is reflected or transmitted from the copy is received by a detector and recorded.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Internal drum devices have a cylindrical drum surface portion to receive the media. A drum assembly of the device supports and defines the drum surface, as well as a vacuum chamber. The drum surface includes a number of apertures for rigidly but releasably receiving an imaging plate. When an imaging plate is positioned on the drum surface and a vacuum is applied, the plate is retained for imaging.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">An optical beam generator emits a modulated optical feed beam onto a spinning mirror of a scanning assembly, and the mirror reflects the beam onto the media. As the mirror spins, the imaging beam reflected by the mirror advances across the plate from one side edge of the surface the other side edge thereof. The beam exposes a sequence of pixels, which form a scan line generally perpendicular to the axis of the drum. The mirror is mounted on a carriage which moves along the axis of the drum, generally perpendicular to the scan line. Since the carriage moves continuously, the imaging process generates slightly helical lines along the imaging plate. The rotating beam images the plate in this manner until the entire plate is imaged.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Known imaging apparatus utilize internal drum imaging surfaces that are semi-cylindrical or less than semi-cylindrical, i.e., the imaging beam only records on the media plate during one half or less for each rotation of the mirror. These known drum assemblies, including the drum casting and the drum skin, are relatively easy to manufacture.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Known drum assemblies are typically fabricated, for example by casting the drums as a single part, and provide a wide opening, i.e., at least a semi-cylindrical opening, for receiving a drum skin. A portion of the drum includes a series of lands for supporting the drum skin. Channels are provided between the lands, and define a portion of the vacuum chamber. An associated drum skin, fabricated from aluminum for example, is then positioned on the lands. Prior to positioning the drum skin, an adhesive is applied to the lands or other mounting points, and the drum skin is then attached.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It would be advantageous to provide in internal drum imaging device with a drum surface that permits imaging over more than 180° of each mirror revolution, i.e., the beam records on the media for more than one-half of each revolution. Such a drum surface would therefore be more than semi-cylindrical but less than completely cylindrical. In contrast to known drums which define an imaging surface that is less than semi-cylindrical, and therefore the opening is greater than semi-cylindrical, the proposed drums would include imaging areas that are greater than semi-cylindrical, and therefore define axial openings which are significantly less than semi-cylindrical.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The new drums provide significant advantages over previous drums, as set forth in co-pending application entitled “Media Feed Apparatus for An Imaging Device”, filed on Apr. 18, 1997 as Ser. No. 08/844,668, by the assignee of the present invention, and which is expressly incorporated by reference herein. As an example, for a given drum radius, the maximum imaging width (W) is equal to the radius (R) multiplied by the overall imaging angle (w), thus W=R*w. The new drums provide an increased imaging angle (w), and are thus capable of generating a wider scan and thereby imaging a wider media. In the alternative, for a media of the same width, such drums can be made with a smaller radius, which enables an overall reduction in size for the corresponding imaging apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Conventional drums are typically fabricated by directly placing a drum skin onto a drum, and attaching the drum skin to the drum. In some cases, the drum skin is mounted onto a mandrel, by clamping the drum skin edges between a strip and the mandrel. The mounted drum skin and mandrel are positioned on the drum, and the skin is attached to the drum using an adhesive, or any other conventional means for attachment. The skin is released from the mandrel, and the mandrel is then simply moved radially out from the drum and drum skin assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In view of the narrow opening provided in newer drums, conventional assembly methods cannot be used manufacture the drum assembly. Since the newer drums are greater than semi-cylindrical, it is not possible merely to lift the mandrel from the drum and drum skin assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Accordingly, it is an object of the present invention to provide a method of manufacturing a drum assembly for internal drum imaging devices, and a drum assembly made in accordance with the method.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">It is another object to provide such a method and a drum assembly where the drum surface enables imaging over more than 180° of each scan rotation, i.e., the drum is more than semi-cylindrical.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The above and other objects and advantages of this invention will become readily apparent based upon the following description and accompanying drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to one aspect of the present invention, a method is disclosed for manufacturing a drum assembly for an internal drum-type imaging apparatus. The drum assembly provides an imaging surface which is at least semi-cylindrical, and preferably is significantly greater than semi-cylindrical.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The method includes the steps of: releasably wrapping a drum skin around a cylindrical mandrel which has an axis, the mandrel and wrapped drum skin have a first radius and the drum skin defines an imaging surface; attaching a drum to the drum skin while the drum skin is wrapped around the mandrel, the drum having a radius slightly greater than the first radius, the drum and drum skin define an at least semi-cylindrical interface and define a vacuum chamber; generating a fluid bearing between the drum skin and the mandrel to separate the drum skin from the mandrel; and moving the drum and attached drum skin relative to the mandrel and in a direction parallel to the axis to remove the drum assembly from the mandrel while maintaining the fluid bearing between the drum skin and the mandrel, whereby the drum and drum skin define an imaging surface that is greater than semi-cylindrical.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">According to another aspect of the present invention, a drum assembly is disclosed for use in an internal drum-type imaging apparatus. The drum assembly is manufactured according to the above method.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The method of the present invention, and the drum assembly manufactured according to the method, provide an imaging surface that is greater than semi-cylindrical. In contrast to known drum assemblies for which the imaging surface is less than or equal to semi-cylindrical, the newer drums provide significant advantages.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">As an example, for a given drum radius, the newer drums are capable of imaging a wider media, since the beam records over more than one half of each rotation, thereby generating a wider scan. Alternatively, imaging media of the same width can be accommodated by newer drums having a smaller radius, which enables an overall reduction in size for the corresponding imaging apparatus. The smaller radius also reduces the distance traveled by the imaging beam between the mirror and the imaging plate, and the corresponding potential distortion of the beam associated with prior drums. Moreover, the newer drums simply cannot be manufactured using known assembly processes.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic, perspective view of a drum type imaging apparatus which incorporates a drum assembly of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of a portion of the imaging apparatus of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, illustrating the drum assembly in more detail.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevational view of an apparatus for manufacturing the drum assembly in accordance with the method of the present invention, and illustrating a platform supporting a portion of the drum and a bonding mandrel for supporting a drum skin of the assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a right end, elevational view of the apparatus of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a left end, elevational view of the platform and a completed drum assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an end view of the mandrel similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, but illustrating only the drum skin mounted to the mandrel by a clamping assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, but illustrating the apparatus after completion of the drum assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a fragmentary view taken along the line <b>8</b>-<b>8</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, but illustrating only one side of the clamping assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b> and <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a fragmentary view, similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 9</figref>, but illustrating the cooperation between a clamp of the clamping assembly, the drum skin and the mandrel.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a fragmentary view, similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, but illustrating the cooperation between a clamp and a clamping strip of the clamping assembly.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an imaging device generally designated <b>10</b>, incorporating a drum assembly of the present invention, and adapted for reflecting or turning an optical beam between an imaging surface and an optical beam processor <b>21</b>. The beam processor may be an optical beam generator for a photoplotter or an optical beam generator for a scanner. Such internal drum imaging device is shown and described in more detail in U.S. Pat. No. 5,291,392 issued to Gerber et al. on Mar. 1, 1994 entitled “Method and Apparatus For Enhancing the Accuracy of Scanner Systems”, and also in co-pending application filed on Apr. 18, 1997 as Ser. No. 08/844,668, entitled “Media Feed Apparatus for An Imaging Device”, both of which are assigned to the assignee of the present invention and are expressly incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Photoplotters expose a photosensitive media plate disposed on an imaging surface by sweeping a modulated optical beam from a beam generator over the media plate. Scanners function by illuminating the test sample with an unmodulated optical beam and capturing the reflected light by the beam receivers. While the following description of the imaging apparatus shown in the Figures relates to a photoplotting apparatus, one skilled in the art would recognize that the present invention is equally applicable to a scanning apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The photoplotter <b>10</b> has a drum assembly <b>12</b>, which includes a drum <b>14</b> and a drum skin <b>16</b> defining a generally cylindrical-shaped exposure chamber <b>18</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and described further below, the drum assembly defines an imaging surface <b>20</b> which is greater than semi-cylindrical, to enable an imaging beam to record on a print media for greater than one half of each revolution of the plotting optics. The imaging surface <b>20</b> provides an internal support structure for supporting a media sheet or plate (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) in a given orientation to a point along the central or z-axis <b>22</b> of the internal drum. Those skilled in the art will recognize that the z-axis <b>22</b> of the internal drum is preferably coaxial with a longitudinal axis of the support surface defined by the drum assembly <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The drum skin <b>16</b> is fabricated from a resilient but fairly rigid material, such as aluminum. The side of the drum skin which supports the media sheets is preferably coated to prevent damage to the skin during manufacture of the drum assembly a during use, for example with a 0.002 inch layer of a hard coat polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE) marketed under the name “POLYLUBE”. The media sheets may be a sheet of aluminum or polymer, such as polyester, having a photosensitive emulsion coated on one surface thereof or a sheet of photosensitive film. A plurality of apertures <b>24</b> are defined by the support surface <b>16</b> of the drum assembly <b>12</b> are provided for the purpose of drawing the plate or sheet down onto the support surface under vacuum pressure applied by a vacuum generator <b>26</b> and associated manifold system (not shown) disposed below the drum in the lower portion of the structure.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The photoplotter <b>10</b> further includes one or more known optical beam generators and beam forming optics. One or more optical beams are received and reflected to the media by a corresponding scanning assembly, which includes a spinning mirror for scanning a light beam across the imaging plate and along a plotting axis <b>29</b> which is parallel, and preferably coaxial with the drum axis, as is generally known in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates the drum assembly <b>12</b> of the imaging apparatus <b>10</b> in more detail. The drum assembly <b>12</b> includes a unitary main portion <b>28</b> and four upper portions <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b> and <b>36</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>), which cooperate to define a drum axis <b>29</b> (see also <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 5</figref>). As is discussed further below, the upper portions are properly positioned on the base portion using locating pins and recesses, and are preferably also adhesively attached to the main drum portion <b>28</b>. The main portion defines a drum skin receiving surface that is preferably about semi-cylindrical or 180°, and the upper portions <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> define an additional drum skin receiving surface, for example an additional 80° or so. Thus, with the drum portions attached to the drum skin <b>16</b>, the media support surface <b>20</b> defined by the drum skin <b>16</b> provides an imaging surface which covers a total angle <b>38</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) of about 260° of each revolution of an imaging beam. The total angle <b>38</b> may be larger or smaller, and is essentially limited only by the support structure for the imaging optics of the completed imaging apparatus and the need to mount and unmount plates in the exposure chamber, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The use of separate drum portions, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, enables easier casting of the overall drum, and particularly of the upper portions. The drum may also include a different number of portions, so long as the drum includes at least two portions are employed and none of the portions alone is greater than semi-cylindrical. For example, where two portions are utilized, the portions include similar left and right portions. In the illustrated embodiment, the portions of the drum define a series of lands and channels (not shown), as is known in the art. The lands provide an attachment surface and support for the drum skin <b>16</b>. The channels provide the vacuum chamber for retaining an imaging plate, as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The drum portions are fabricated from cast aluminum, such as 356 T 71 or -T 51 aluminum, or other suitable material. Since imaging operations generate a significant amount of heat, the drum skin <b>16</b> and material used to attached the skin to the drum are preferably fabricated from an identical or similar material. The portion of the drum skin <b>16</b> which supports imaging plates may also be coated with a protective layer of material such as “Teflon”.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Turning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, an apparatus for manufacturing the drum assembly in accordance with the present invention is indicated generally by the reference numeral <b>40</b>, and provides precise movement of the drum skin <b>16</b> relative to the drum <b>14</b> (shown in phantom). A pressurized air source <b>41</b> is also provided for removing the drum skin, and thus the finished drum assembly, from the mandrel assembly, as is described further below. The apparatus <b>40</b> includes a linear track <b>42</b>, a platform <b>43</b> mounted for sliding movement along the track, and a bonding mandrel assembly <b>44</b> mounted at one end of the track.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The track <b>42</b> includes a pair of parallel races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>), each of which is rigidly mounted to a generally planar, level surface <b>48</b>, such as a reinforced concrete floor. As discussed below, since the drum skin <b>16</b> is mounted precisely on the mandrel assembly <b>44</b> and must be precisely aligned with a drum positioned on the platform <b>43</b>, it is critical to enable precise, consistent relative movement of the platform and the mandrel assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In the illustrated embodiment, the races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b> are each of substantial dimension, e.g., about 3 inches in diameter and about 15 feet in length, and are manufactured by Thomson, Inc. While the illustrated races have a round cross section, other cross sections and races may also be employed with equal effect.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The platform <b>43</b> is supported on the races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b> by a set of linear bearing <b>49</b>, <b>50</b>, which complement the cross section of the races. The bearings <b>49</b>, <b>50</b> enable precise sliding movement of the platform along the races. Movement of the platform <b>43</b> along the races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b> is provided by a manually actuated drive <b>52</b>. The drive <b>52</b> includes an endless chain <b>54</b>, which extends along the length of the races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b> and is coupled through a right angle drive <b>56</b> to a travel wheel <b>58</b> and chain <b>60</b>. The drive <b>52</b> also includes an associated clamp (not shown) for releasably locking the bearings <b>49</b>, <b>50</b> in position on the races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b>, thus fixing the axial positions of the platform <b>43</b> and associated drum <b>12</b> relative to the mandrel assembly <b>44</b> and associated drum skin <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The platform <b>43</b> is also movable vertically relative to the races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b>, and thus to the mandrel assembly <b>44</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 5</figref>, the bearings <b>49</b>, <b>50</b> carry a base <b>62</b> of the platform <b>43</b>. A drum support member <b>64</b> is in turn mounted for precise vertical movement relative to the platform base <b>62</b>. The precise vertical movement is provided by a screw jack assembly <b>66</b>, which is driven by a hand wheel <b>68</b>. Those skilled in the art will recognize that various other mechanisms, including non-manual mechanisms, may be employed with equal effect.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Returning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, the mandrel assembly <b>44</b> includes a bonding mandrel <b>70</b>, which has a cylindrical shape and a radius equal to the interior radius <b>71</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) of the finished drum assembly. The mandrel <b>70</b> is preferably although not necessarily fabricated from steel, and is rigidly supported at opposite ends <b>72</b>, <b>74</b> by vertical support members <b>76</b>, <b>78</b>. The vertical support members <b>76</b>, <b>78</b>, in turn, are supported by a mandrel support frame, indicated generally at <b>80</b>. As noted above, it is critical to enable precise relative movement of the mandrel <b>70</b> and platform <b>43</b> one hand, and the drum skin <b>16</b> and the drum <b>14</b> on the other hand. Thus, the vertical support members <b>76</b>, <b>78</b> and mandrel support frame <b>80</b> are of a rigid, substantial construction.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b> and <b>6</b>, the drum skin <b>16</b> is attached to the bonding mandrel <b>70</b> by a clamping assembly <b>82</b>. The assembly <b>82</b> includes a clamping strip <b>84</b>, which extends parallel to the mandrel axis <b>85</b> and along the top of the mandrel <b>70</b>. The clamping strip <b>84</b> is mounted to the mandrel by pins <b>86</b>. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>, the drum skin <b>16</b> is slightly wider than the circumference of the drum support surface <b>20</b>, so that the edges of the drum skin <b>16</b> extend beyond the assembled drum castings <b>28</b>, <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>. Corresponding holes <b>88</b> are provided along the edges of the drum skin <b>16</b>, and the clamping assembly <b>82</b> engages the holes to clamp the drum skin to the mandrel <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Turning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref>, <b>8</b>, <b>9</b> and <b>10</b>, the clamping assembly <b>82</b> also includes several clamps <b>90</b>, which are seated in recesses <b>92</b> positioned along the clamping strip <b>84</b>. Each clamp <b>90</b> includes a hand knob <b>94</b>, a sleeve <b>95</b> which is seated in the recess <b>92</b>, a threaded body <b>96</b> which passes thorough the sleeve and is coupled to a block <b>98</b>. Each block <b>98</b> includes two pins <b>100</b>, <b>100</b>, and is mounted for pivotal movement relative to the threaded stud <b>96</b>. The pins <b>100</b> cooperate with the corresponding holes <b>88</b> provided along the outer edges of the drum skin <b>16</b>. Each of the blocks <b>98</b> is coupled to adjacent blocks by couplings <b>99</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In accordance with the method of the present invention, the drum assembly <b>12</b> is manufactured as follows. The mandrel <b>70</b> is cleaned to remove loose particles, and then sprayed with an anti-adherent material, i.e., a mold release, to facilitate subsequent removal of the drum skin at the end of the assembly process. As best illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b> and <b>6</b>, the drum skin <b>16</b> is manually wrapped around the mandrel. The clamping strip <b>84</b> is positioned on top of the mandrel <b>70</b> using the pins <b>86</b>. The pins of clamps <b>90</b> are then installed in the holes <b>88</b> along the edge of the drum skin <b>16</b> which is wrapped on the mandrel. The clamp heads <b>94</b> are then turned as needed to tighten and retain the drum skin on the mandrel <b>70</b>. Preferably, the clamps <b>90</b> hold the drum skin <b>16</b> on the mandrel with a force that is uniformly distributed along the drum skin. To that end, the blocks <b>98</b> may pivot relative to their respective threaded bodies <b>96</b>, to evenly distribute the force. The individual clamps <b>90</b> of the clamping assembly <b>82</b> are then tightened as needed to secure the drum skin to the mandrel.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Conventional sensors are mounted to the mandrel and/or drum skin for later use to ensure proper alignment of the drum and drum skin. Such sensors include remote transducers sold by Federal Gage Co. as model EAS-2883. Proper care must be taken to ensure that the skin is properly aligned on the mandrel, e.g., with the drum skin edges oriented generally parallel to the drum axis <b>85</b>, to enable subsequent proper positioning of the skin on the drum.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The main portion of the drum casting <b>28</b> is positioned on the drum support member <b>64</b> of the platform <b>43</b>. Conventional sensors are mounted to the drum support member <b>64</b> or other portion of the platform <b>43</b> and to the main portion <b>28</b> of the drum, again for use in properly positioning the main portion relative to the drum skin <b>16</b> wrapped on the mandrel <b>70</b>. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 7</figref>, such sensors <b>102</b> include indicating units sold by Federal Gage Co. as model DEI-73110. The drum <b>28</b> is adjusted or shimmed as needed to ensure that the drum axis <b>29</b> is parallel to the races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b>, and thus to the mandrel axis <b>85</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The main portion of the drum <b>28</b> and wrapped drum skin <b>16</b> are then “dry fit”, together with the upper portions <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b>, to ensure proper positioning and fit prior to assembly. With reference first to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the platform <b>43</b> is lowered as needed so that the drum axis <b>29</b> is positioned lower than the mandrel axis <b>85</b>, and the platform <b>43</b> is then moved from the position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> to a position immediately below the mandrel <b>70</b> and drum skin <b>16</b>. Next, the platform <b>43</b> is raised towards the mandrel and drum skin. Again, care is taken to ensure that the main portion of the drum <b>28</b> is aligned with the mandrel <b>70</b> and wrapped drum skin <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The platform is raised until the main portion of the drum <b>28</b> contacts the drum skin <b>16</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the upper portions <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> are then mounted on the main portion and against the drum skin, and checked to ensure proper fit and alignment. Once assembled, clearances between the drum portions are checked, and are preferably uniform and on the order of about five-one thousandths of an inch (0.005″). The clearance between the drum portions <b>28</b>, <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> the drum skin <b>16</b>, and will be filled with a material used to join these parts. The upper portions <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> are then carefully removed, and the main portion <b>28</b> is lowered from its position against the drum skin <b>16</b>. Then, the platform is moved from its position below the mandrel <b>70</b> and drum skin <b>16</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Immediately prior to final assembly, the exposed (attaching) surface of the drum skin <b>16</b> is cleaned with an appropriate cleaning agent, e.g., in the illustrated case the aluminum drum skin and drum portions are cleaned with an aluminum prep solution.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The lands defined on the main drum portion <b>28</b> are then covered with an epoxy adhesive. Since significant heat is generated during use of the finished imaging apparatus, the epoxy has properties, particularly thermal expansion properties, similar to that of the drum material and drum skin. Once the epoxy adhesive is applied to the lands of the main portion <b>28</b>, the platform <b>43</b> is again moved along the races <b>45</b>, <b>46</b> to a position below the drum skin <b>16</b> mounted on the mandrel <b>70</b>. The platform <b>43</b> is carefully raised towards the drum skin <b>16</b>, again to ensure the proper joining of the main portion <b>28</b> and the drum skin <b>16</b>. Once the platform <b>43</b> is raised so that the epoxy covered lands of the main drum portion <b>28</b> abut the drum skin, and assuming that the drum axis <b>29</b> is coaxial with the mandrel axis <b>85</b>, the upper portions <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> of the drum are attached. The drum portions <b>28</b>, <b>30</b>, <b>32</b>, <b>34</b>, <b>36</b> cover a portion of the drum skin <b>16</b> that is at least semi-cylindrical, or greater if desired. The epoxy adhesive is next applied to the lands of each upper portion, and each upper portion is mounted on the main drum portion <b>28</b> to abut the drum skin <b>16</b>. The epoxy is then allowed to cure as needed.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">After the epoxy has cured, and prior to removal of the drum assembly from the mandrel <b>70</b>, the clamping assembly <b>82</b> is removed. The drum assembly <b>12</b> is connected to the pressurized air source <b>41</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>). The air source pressurizes the vacuum chamber defined by the drum assembly, and generates an air bearing, and thus a clearance, between the drum skin <b>16</b> and the mandrel <b>70</b>. The platform <b>43</b> and drum assembly are then moved parallel to the mandrel axis <b>85</b> and away from the mandrel <b>70</b>, while maintaining the coaxial relationship of the drum axis <b>29</b> and the mandrel axis <b>85</b>, until the finished drum assembly is completely removed from the mandrel. The drum skin <b>16</b> which extends beyond the drum portions, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, is trimmed as needed, and the drum assembly is subsequently incorporated into a completed imaging apparatus <b>10</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The method of the present invention, and the drum assembly manufactured according to the method, provide an imaging surface that is greater than semi-cylindrical. In contrast to known drum assemblies for which the imaging surface is less than or equal to semi-cylindrical, the newer drums provide significant advantages.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">As an example, for a given drum radius, the new drums provided by the present invention are capable of imaging a wider media, since the beam records over more than one half of each rotation, thereby generating a wider scan. Alternatively, imaging media of the same width can be accommodated by new drums having a smaller radius, which enables an overall reduction in size for the corresponding imaging apparatus. The smaller radius also reduces the distance spanned by the imaging beam between the mirror and the imaging plate, and the corresponding potential distortion of the beam associated with prior drums. Moreover, the new drums described above simply cannot be manufactured using known assembly processes.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">While preferred embodiments have been shown and described, various modifications and substitutions may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. Accordingly, it is to be understood that the present invention has been described by way of example and not by limitation.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A drum assembly for an internal drum-type imaging apparatus, the drum assembly defining a concave imaging surface which is more than semi-cylindrical, the assembly made in accordance with a method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>releasably wrapping a drum skin partially around a generally cylindrical mandrel having an axis, the drum skin having a front face facing toward said mandrel and defining an imaging surface and also having a rear face facing away from said mandrel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>fixedly attaching a drum to said rear face of the drum skin while the drum skin is wrapped around the mandrel, the drum and drum skin each extending for more than 180° and less than 360° about the mandrel axis so as to define an interface of greater than 180° and less than 360° extent about the mandrel axis and which drum and drum skin cooperate to define a vacuum chamber;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating a fluid bearing between said front face of the drum skin and the mandrel to separate the drum skin from the mandrel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>moving the drum and attached drum skin relative to the mandrel and in a direction parallel to the mandrel axis to remove the drum and attached drum skin from the mandrel while maintaining the fluid bearing between the drum skin and the mandrel, whereby the drum and attached drum skin after removal from said mandrel provide said drum assembly with said front face of said drum skin defining said concave imaging surface which is more than semi-cylindrical.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the method further comprises the step of:
<claim-text>applying an anti-adherent material to the mandrel prior to the step of releasably wrapping the drum skin to the mandrel.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of attaching the drum includes adhesively attaching the drum to the drum skin.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the drum comprises more than one drum portion, and the step of attaching the drum includes attaching the drum portions one at a time to the drum skin.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the drum skin has a plurality of apertures, and the step of generating a fluid bearing includes the step of providing fluid to the vacuum chamber at a pressure greater than atmospheric pressure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of releasably wrapping a drum skin includes releasably clamping the drum skin to the mandrel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, the mandrel and wrapped drum skin having a first radius, and the step of attaching the drum includes attaching a drum having a radius slightly greater than the first radius.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the drum radius is about 20 mils greater than the first radius.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the drum is made of a plurality of portions each of which portions is of no more than 180° extent about said mandrel axis, and which portions are individually placed onto the rear face of the drum skin after the wrapping of the drum skin onto the mandrel, and which portions are then attached to the drum skin and to one another.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
