<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297034-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297034</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11526791</doc-number>
<date>20060925</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>4</main-group>
<subgroup>38</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439801</main-classification>
<further-classification>439 83</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">High current sealed connection system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4219251</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Romine</name>
<date>19800800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439692</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4614387</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hartl</name>
<date>19860900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439 70</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4625260</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jordan et al.</name>
<date>19861100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361720</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4717989</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>De Barros et al.</name>
<date>19880100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361818</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5439398</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Testa et al.</name>
<date>19950800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439801</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5655931</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Perugini</name>
<date>19970800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439573</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6111760</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nixon</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361814</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6142836</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Deckmann et al.</name>
<date>20001100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439801</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0005658</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Matsuda et al.</name>
<date>20010600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439801</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>10215985</doc-number>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 78</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 83</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439801</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361714</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wieland</last-name>
<first-name>Andrew Dean</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fargo</city>
<state>ND</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hopman</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey Gerald</first-name>
<address>
<city>Horace</city>
<state>ND</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Deere &amp; Company</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Moline</city>
<state>IL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hammond</last-name>
<first-name>Briggitte</first-name>
<department>2833</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Tsukerman</last-name>
<first-name>Larisa</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A circuit board assembly including a circuit board having at least one conductive element attached thereto and at least one surface mount stud carrier mounted on the circuit board and electrically connected to the at least one conductive element.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="76.71mm" wi="109.30mm" file="US07297034-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="239.10mm" wi="157.82mm" file="US07297034-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="223.52mm" wi="120.23mm" file="US07297034-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a high current sealed connection system, and, more particularly, to a high current surface mount sealed connection system.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">For certain high power applications, typical through-hole type electronic components are attached to a printed circuit board. A typical application includes a threaded stud that is threaded through a circuit board. Such an assembly requires access to both sides of the board to pass the stud through the board and to make contact with the traces on the circuit board.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Another high power device known as a power tap includes a series of legs that extend through a printed circuit board and are soldered thereto. A surface portion of the power tap has a threaded hole through which a threaded connector, such as a screw, is threaded into the hole and a conductor is attached thereto. Such a device is not available in a surface mount version and cannot be used with a printed circuit board that is adhered directly to a heat sink.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">What is needed in the art is a reliable way of connecting a printed circuit board to a heat sink yet having high current connections.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The present invention relates to a surface mount stud carrier having an environmental sealing system thereabout.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The invention comprises, in one form thereof, a circuit board assembly including a circuit board having at least one conductive element attached thereto and at least one surface mount stud carrier mounted on the circuit board and electrically connected to the at least one conductive element.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an electrical assembly including an embodiment of a surface mount stud carrier of the present invention located thereon;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a cross-sectional view through one plane of the surface mount stud carrier of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is another cross-sectional view along another plane of the surface mount stud carrier of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective cross-sectional view of the stud carriers of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>, mounted on an electrical assembly.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Referring now to the drawings, and more particularly to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, there is shown an electronic assembly <b>10</b> including a heat sink <b>12</b>, a printed circuit board <b>14</b> and conductors <b>16</b> being connected thereto. Heat sink <b>12</b> has a substantially flat surface beneath printed circuit board <b>14</b> for the conduction of heat from printed circuit board <b>14</b> to thereby increase the power handling capacity of electrical assembly <b>10</b>. Conductors <b>16</b> are connected to electrical assembly <b>10</b> to convey power thereto and/or therefrom.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Printed circuit board <b>14</b> includes conductive elements <b>18</b> onto which surface mount components <b>20</b> are mounted. A surface mount stud assembly <b>22</b> is mounted to printed circuit board <b>14</b> and includes a surface mount stud carrier <b>24</b> and a stud <b>26</b> extending therethrough. Although surface mount stud carrier <b>24</b> and stud <b>26</b> have been illustrated as being separate devices, carrier <b>24</b> and stud <b>26</b> may be integrally formed. Surface mount stud carrier <b>24</b> has feet or pads which are soldered to conductive elements <b>18</b> on printed circuit board <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Now additionally referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-4</figref>, there is shown a housing <b>28</b> that substantially covers printed circuit board <b>14</b> with studs <b>26</b> extending through openings or holes in housing <b>28</b>. Housing <b>28</b> was omitted from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> for the purpose of illustrating the components that are placed on a surface of printed circuit board <b>14</b>. Housing <b>28</b> includes inserts <b>30</b>, bosses <b>32</b> and a snapping edge <b>34</b>. Housing <b>28</b> is made from a non-conductive material, such as plastic, having inserts <b>30</b> molded thereinto. Insert <b>30</b> has a hole therethrough thereby allowing stud <b>26</b> to extend through the opening and to at least partially extend beyond a surface of housing <b>28</b>. Bosses <b>32</b> extend from housing <b>28</b> and come into contact with a surface of printed circuit board <b>14</b> so as to reduce any compressive load placed on housing <b>28</b> from being transferred directly through surface mount stud carrier <b>24</b> to printed circuit board <b>14</b>. Although bosses <b>32</b> are illustrated as straddling each side of surface mount stud carrier <b>24</b>, other geometries and locations are contemplated. Bosses <b>32</b> come into contact with printed circuit board <b>14</b> so that forces that may be applied to a surface of housing <b>28</b> do not compromise the soldering of the feet of stud carrier <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A seal <b>36</b> extends around the perimeter of housing <b>28</b> and a compressive force is exerted thereonto when snap <b>34</b> engages a edge of heat sink <b>12</b> thereby holding housing <b>28</b> onto heat sink <b>12</b>. Seal <b>36</b> provides an environmental seal to protect components <b>20</b>, conductive elements <b>18</b> and any other contents of printed circuit board <b>14</b>. Seal <b>36</b> may be removably attached to housing <b>28</b>. Seal <b>36</b> is held under compression and deforms to provide sealing contact with printed circuit board <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Printed circuit board <b>14</b> may be adhered to heat sink <b>12</b> by way of an adhesive. Since no components are on the side of printed circuit board <b>14</b> that is in contact with heat sink <b>12</b> and no leads from a component extend through circuit board <b>14</b>, intimate contact of board <b>14</b> with heat sink <b>12</b> is possible, thereby improving heat conduction from board <b>14</b> to heat sink <b>12</b>. An adhesive may be used to hold printed circuit board <b>14</b> to heat sink <b>12</b>. Alternatively, mechanical fasteners, such as screws can be used to hold board <b>14</b> to heat sink <b>12</b>. Printed circuit board may also be held in place by way of a compressive force that occurs by the attachment of housing <b>28</b> to heat sink <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">A seal <b>38</b> such as an o-ring <b>38</b> is positioned between surface mount stud carrier <b>24</b> and insert <b>30</b> to thereby seal housing <b>28</b> around the hole in insert <b>30</b>. A nut <b>40</b> is threaded onto stud <b>26</b> thereby applying a compressive force through insert <b>30</b> to o-ring <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">A conductor <b>16</b> may then be placed on stud <b>26</b> and another nut, not shown, can be threaded thereon, to hold conductor <b>16</b> in position on electrical assembly <b>10</b>. Electrical assembly <b>10</b> advantageously allows for intimate contact of printed circuit board <b>14</b> with heat sink <b>12</b> thereby efficiently conducting heat therefrom. The present invention provides for a high power capacity of a printed circuit board without having to make provisions for through-hole components, which would extend beneath a circuit board.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Having described the preferred embodiment, it will become apparent that various modifications can be made without departing from the scope of the invention as defined in the accompanying claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A circuit board assembly, comprising:
<claim-text>a circuit board having at least one conductive element attached to a first side thereto;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one surface mount stud carrier having a stud including a threaded portion extending therefrom mounted on the first side of the circuit board and electrically connected to said at least one conductive element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat sink having that is in contact with a second side of the circuit board; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a non-conductive housing in at least partial contact with a surface of the circuit board, wherein said housing has an opening through which the stud at least partially extends and a snap feature that retainingly engages said heat sink.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. An electrical assembly, comprising:
<claim-text>a surface mount stud carrier;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a stud having a threaded portion extending from said stud carrier;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a circuit board having at least one conductive element that is electrically connected to the surface mount stud carrier;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat sink having a surface that is in intimate contact with a side of the circuit board; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a non-conductive housing having an opening through which the stud at least partially extends, the housing having an opening through which the stud at least partially extends, the housing in at least partial contact with a surface of the circuit board, wherein said housing has a snap feature that retainingly engages said heat sink.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A circuit board assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a circuit board metalized on only a first side;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat sink secured to a second side of the circuit board;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a surface-mount stud connector having feet for securing to metalized conductive elements on the first side of the printed circuit board;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a stud having a threaded portion extending from the stud carrier the stud carrier preventing the stud from physically contacting the metalized surface of the circuit board; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a housing made of non-conductive material covering the circuit board, the housing having at least one insert molded thereinto, the insert having at least one opening extending therethrough allowing the stud to at least partially extend therethrough and project above the housing.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The circuit board assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the housing has a snap feature that retainingly engages the heat sink.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The circuit board assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> further comprising a seal around the perimeter of the housing, the seal forming an environmental seal with the first side of the printed circuit board when the snap engages the heat sink.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The circuit board assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the heat sink is held in place by way of a compressive forces that occurs by the attachment of the housing to the heat sink.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The circuit board assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> further comprising a compressive seal positioned between the insert and the surface mount stud carrier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The circuit board assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further comprising a threaded nut that engages the threaded portion of the stud and compresses the seal between the insert and the surface mount stud carrier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The circuit board assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the heat sink is secured to the second side of the printed circuit board by way of an adhesive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The circuit board assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the heat sink is secured to the second side of the printed circuit board by means of mechanical fasteners.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
