<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296721-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296721</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11465610</doc-number>
<date>20060818</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>25</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>227130</main-classification>
<further-classification>227  8</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Pneumatic nail gun having nail pusher</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3099837</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Heilman et al.</name>
<date>19630800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227136</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3622062</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Goode et al.</name>
<date>19711100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227130</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3858780</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Perkins et al.</name>
<date>19750100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227  8</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4313552</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Maurer</name>
<date>19820200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227109</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4319705</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Geist et al.</name>
<date>19820300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227120</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4736879</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yamada et al.</name>
<date>19880400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227130</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4784308</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Novak et al.</name>
<date>19881100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227130</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4909419</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yamada et al.</name>
<date>19900300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227  1</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5135152</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Uno et al.</name>
<date>19920800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227116</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6006975</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ishizawa</name>
<date>19991200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227119</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7225962</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Porth et al.</name>
<date>20070600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>227136</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>227130</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>227  8</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wen</last-name>
<first-name>Wan-Fu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>De Poan Pneumatic Corp.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Rada</last-name>
<first-name>Rinaldi I.</first-name>
<department>3721</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Lopez</last-name>
<first-name>Michelle</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An exemplary pneumatic nail gun includes a gun body having a nail punching piston and a nail pushing passage. A nail pusher has a nail pushing cylinder connecting to the nail pushing passage. The nail pushing cylinder includes a nail pushing piston and a spring. An air distribution ring having an axial through hole and a radial through hole. The axial through hole guides the high pressure air to drive the nail punching piston to reposition after the nail punching piston downwardly moving to punch the nails. The radial through hole guides the high pressure air into the nail pushing cylinder via the nail pushing passage to drive the nail pushing piston to take the nails, and also exhaust the high pressure air in the nail pushing cylinder and the nail pushing passage to make the nail pushing piston reposition to push the nails when the nail punching piston reposition.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="204.47mm" wi="132.08mm" file="US07296721-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="208.28mm" wi="134.54mm" file="US07296721-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="192.96mm" wi="134.11mm" file="US07296721-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="207.01mm" wi="133.01mm" file="US07296721-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="226.40mm" wi="145.20mm" file="US07296721-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="216.92mm" wi="142.07mm" file="US07296721-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="201.42mm" wi="123.70mm" file="US07296721-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a nail gun with a nail pusher, and particularly to a pneumatic nail gun having an air distribution ring being used for guiding high pressure air to drive or release a nail pushing position of a nail pusher.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Pneumatic nail gun generally utilizes a compressed high pressure air to drive a piston to punch a nail, for joining two objects by shooting a nail through both objects. A typical pneumatic nail gun includes a gun body having a cylinder and a nail punching piston dividing the cylinder into a top air chamber and a bottom air chamber. When a trigger of the gun body is triggered, high pressure air is introduced into the top air chamber for driving the nail punching piston to move downward, to punch the nail. In a reverse case, when the trigger is released, the high pressure air in the top air chamber is exhausted, and other high pressure air is introduced into the bottom air chamber to reposition the nail punching piston.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A conventional pneumatic nail gun is generally classified into two types, one kind being coupled with a magazine and another kind being coupled with a canister. The typical structure and function of a nail gun with a canister is briefly described as follows. This kind of nail gun has a nail pusher arranged at a side of the gun body thereof. The nail pusher includes a cylinder, a nail pushing piston disposed in the cylinder, and a spring abutting the nail pushing piston. Moreover, the gun body includes a nail pushing passage and an air collection chamber, and the nail pushing passage is connected between the air collection chamber of the gun body and the cylinder of the nail pusher. The air collection chamber is used for collecting the high pressure air that is introduced in from the top air chamber when the nail punching piston moves downward, so as to guide the high pressure air into the cylinder of the nail pusher via the nail pushing passage for driving the nail pushing piston. When the nail punching piston is driven to the original position, the high pressure air in the air collection chamber, the nail pushing passage, and the cylinder of the nail pusher are exhausted, to make the nail pushing piston reposition via pushing by the abutting spring.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">However, the air collection chamber can just receive limited high pressure air when the nail punching piston moves downward. Therefore, the limited high pressure air in the air collection chamber is not sufficient to drive the nail pushing piston to take the next nail for being driven and drive the nail punching piston to the original position, particularly in the process of continuously punching and pushing the nails. That is, the stability of the movement of the nail pushing piston is low, and the instability upward movement of the nail punching piston lowers the speed and efficiency of punching the nail.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Accordingly, what is needed is a pneumatic nail gun that can overcome the above-described deficiencies.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A pneumatic nail gun includes a gun body which includes a nail punching piston and a nail pushing passage. The nail punching piston is induced by high pressure air to move downwardly to punch the nails and move upwardly to reposition. A nail pusher is disposed between an end of the nail pushing passage and a canister. The nail pusher includes a nail pushing cylinder connecting to the nail pushing passage. The nail pushing cylinder includes a nail pushing piston and a spring therein. An air distribution ring fixing to an inner surface of the gun body and adjacent to the other end of the nail pushing passage. The air distribution ring includes at least one axial through hole and at least one radial through hole. The axial through hole guides the high pressure air to drive the nail punching piston to reposition after the nail punching piston moving downwardly to punch the nails. The radial through hole guides and pushes the high pressure air into the nail pushing cylinder via the nail pushing passage to drive the nail pushing piston to take the nails after the nail punching piston move downwardly to punch the nails. The radial through hole also exhausts the high pressure air in the nail pushing cylinder and the nail pushing passage to make the nail pushing piston reposition to push the nails when the nail punching piston move upwardly to reposition.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In an alternative modification, the pneumatic nail gun further includes an exhausting hole connecting with environment that is disposed at an inner surface of the nail pushing cylinder or the nail pushing piston, which can enhance the speed of reposition of the nail pushing piston after the next nail was taken. Moreover, the exhausting hole has a cross section farther smaller than the cross section of the nail pushing passage, which can help to maintain the air pressure of the high pressure air in the nail pushing cylinder and prevent the high pressure air from exhausting from the nail pushing cylinder too fast.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">These and other features and advantages of the various embodiments disclosed herein will be better understood with respect to the following description and drawings, in which like numbers refer to like parts throughout, and in which:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a pneumatic nail gun according to an exemplary embodiment of the present invention, the pneumatic nail gun having a nail pusher and an air distribution ring arranged in a gun body of the pneumatic nail gun;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an enlarged, perspective view of the air distribution ring of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the air distribution ring having radial through holes and axial through holes thereof;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an enlarged, cross-sectional view of the air distribution ring of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, showing the air distribution ring nesting on an inner surface of a gun body of the pneumatic nail gun of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an enlarged, cross-sectional view of another air distribution ring integrally formed with an inner surface of a gun body of the pneumatic nail gun of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the pneumatic nail gun of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, showing a state of the passage of the high pressure air therein when a trigger is not triggered;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is another cross-sectional view of the pneumatic nail gun of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, showing a state of the passage of the high pressure air therein when the trigger is triggered;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is further another cross-sectional view of the pneumatic nail gun of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, showing a state of the passage of the high pressure air therein when a trigger is released;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is an enlarged, cross-sectional view of part of a cylinder of a nail pusher of a pneumatic nail gun according to another embodiment of the present invention, showing an exhausting hole connecting with environment, which is disposed at an inner surface of the cylinder;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is an enlarged, cross-sectional view of part of a cylinder of a nail pusher of a pneumatic nail gun according to further another embodiment of the present invention, showing an exhausting hole connecting with environment, which is disposed at a nail pushing piston of nail pusher.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an exemplary pneumatic nail gun according to the present invention is shown. The pneumatic nail gun includes a gun body <b>1</b>, a nail pusher <b>3</b>, and an air distribution ring <b>5</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The gun body <b>1</b> includes a nail punching piston <b>2</b> and a nail pushing passage <b>10</b>. The nail punching piston <b>2</b> is induced by high pressure air to move downwardly to punch the nails and move upwardly to reposition.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The nail pusher <b>3</b> is disposed between an end of the nail pushing passage <b>10</b> and a canister <b>4</b>. The nail pusher <b>3</b> includes a nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) connecting to the nail pushing passage <b>10</b>, and the nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b> includes a nail pushing piston <b>32</b> and a spring <b>31</b> therein.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The air distribution ring <b>5</b> includes at least one axial through hole <b>51</b> and at least one radial through hole <b>52</b>. The air distribution ring <b>5</b> is fixed to an inner surface of the gun body <b>1</b> via nesting (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) or integrally formed with (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) the inner surface thereof. When the air distribution ring <b>5</b> is nested at the inner surface of the gun body <b>1</b>, a plurality of air seals <b>53</b> and <b>54</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) are employed. The air seals <b>53</b> are used for forming air seal with the outer surface of other elements in the gun body, and the air seals <b>54</b> are used for forming air seal between the radial through hole <b>52</b> and the nail pushing passage <b>10</b>. On the other hand, the air seals <b>54</b> may be omitted when the air distribution ring <b>5</b> is integrally formed with the inner surface of the gun body <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The gun body <b>1</b> forms a main air chamber <b>11</b> therein for collecting high pressure air guiding from air supplier and maintaining air pressure thereof (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 5</figref>). The main air chamber <b>11</b> includes a trigger <b>12</b> for triggering by the user, a trigger valve <b>121</b> is inserted into the main air chamber <b>11</b>, and the gun body <b>1</b> includes a trigger passage <b>13</b>. The trigger valve <b>121</b> may control the main air chamber <b>11</b> connection with the trigger passage <b>13</b> or not.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The gun body <b>1</b> may employ a movable cylinder <b>6</b> and a slidable sleeve valve <b>7</b>. In which, the movable cylinder <b>6</b> includes the nail punching piston <b>2</b>, which may divide the cylinder <b>6</b> into a top air chamber <b>60</b> and a bottom air chamber <b>61</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>). The cylinder <b>6</b> further includes a head valve <b>62</b> adjacent to top of the normal valve <b>14</b> to divides the cylinder <b>6</b> into a first air chamber <b>63</b> and a second air chamber <b>64</b> connecting to the main air chamber <b>11</b>. The first air chamber <b>63</b> includes a spring <b>65</b> therein, and the first air chamber <b>63</b> is connected to the main air chamber <b>11</b> via the trigger passage <b>13</b> and the trigger valve <b>121</b>. The second air chamber <b>64</b> includes a second passage <b>641</b> formed around peripheral of the second air chamber <b>64</b>, and connects to the main air chamber <b>11</b>. The cylinder <b>6</b> includes a plurality of main vent holes <b>66</b>, top vent holes <b>67</b>, intermediate vent holes <b>68</b>, and bottom vent holes <b>69</b> connecting the top and bottom air chambers <b>60</b> and <b>61</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The slidable sleeve valve <b>7</b> is disposed at peripheral position of the cylinder <b>6</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), and a ring groove <b>70</b> is formed therebetween. The slidable sleeve valve <b>7</b> includes a plurality of top groove <b>73</b>, a check valve <b>74</b>, an intermediate valve <b>75</b>, and a bottom valve <b>76</b> disposed an inner surface thereof. The slidable sleeve valve <b>7</b> divides the gun body <b>1</b> into a third air chamber <b>71</b> and a fourth air chamber <b>72</b> for containing high pressure air. The third air chamber <b>71</b> includes a third passage <b>711</b> connecting to the main air chamber <b>11</b>, and the third air chamber <b>71</b> is connected to the top vent holes <b>67</b> of the cylinder <b>6</b> via the top groove <b>73</b>. The third air chamber <b>71</b> includes a bottom spring <b>77</b>. The check valve <b>74</b> is cooperatively formed by the plurality of through holes <b>741</b> of the side surface of the slidable sleeve valve <b>7</b> and an O-ring (or elastomer band) <b>742</b>. The check valve <b>74</b> is used for single directly guiding the high pressure air in the ring groove <b>70</b> into the third air chamber (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>). The vent holes <b>751</b> of intermediate valve <b>75</b> may make the top air chamber <b>60</b> and the nail pushing passage <b>10</b> to be connected via the intermediate vent holes <b>68</b> when the cylinder <b>6</b> upwardly moves and the nail punching piston <b>2</b> moves downwardly (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>). The bottom valve <b>76</b> is closed when the slide sleeve valve <b>7</b> moves downwardly and is opened when the slide sleeve valve <b>7</b> upwardly moves (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>). When the bottom valve <b>76</b> is opened, the bottom vent holes <b>69</b> may make the fourth air chamber <b>72</b> connect with the bottom air chamber <b>61</b>. The fourth air chamber <b>72</b> includes fourth passage <b>721</b> disposed at peripheral portion thereof, which is connected to the main air chamber <b>11</b>. All the elements mentioned above are employed with air seals for maintaining the function of air seal.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The air distribution ring <b>5</b> may be disposed at an inner surface of the gun body <b>1</b> in the fourth air chamber <b>72</b>, to divides the fourth air chamber <b>72</b> into two regions that connecting via the axial through hole <b>51</b> so as to avoid impacting the air collection of the fourth air chamber <b>72</b>. The radial through hole <b>52</b> may make the intermediate valve <b>75</b>, the ring groove <b>70</b>, the nail pushing passage <b>10</b>, and the nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b> connect together.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In operation, before the trigger <b>12</b> is manipulated as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, high pressure air in the main air chamber <b>11</b> is applied to the first air chamber <b>63</b> through the trigger passage <b>13</b> and trigger valve <b>121</b>, and to the second, third, and fourth air chambers <b>64</b>, <b>71</b>, <b>72</b> through the second passage <b>641</b>, the third passage <b>711</b>, and the fourth passage <b>721</b>, respectively. The axial through hole <b>51</b> may make the top region and the bottom region of the fourth air chamber <b>72</b> connect with each other. The high pressure air in the third air chamber <b>71</b> and the bottom spring <b>77</b> cooperatively drive the slidable sleeve valve <b>7</b> move downwardly to certain position. Meanwhile, the main vent holes <b>66</b>, the top vent holes <b>67</b>, the intermediate vent holes <b>68</b>, and the bottom vent holes <b>69</b> is closed by the normal valve <b>14</b>, the nail punching piston <b>2</b>, the intermediated valve <b>75</b>, and the bottom valve <b>76</b>, respectively, so as to prevent the high pressure air in the first, second, third and fourth air chamber <b>63</b>, <b>64</b>, <b>71</b> and <b>72</b> entering into the cylinder <b>6</b>. The check valve <b>74</b> prevents the high pressure air in the third air chamber <b>71</b> from entering into the nail pushing passage <b>10</b> and the nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b> via the ring groove <b>70</b>, the vent holes <b>751</b> of the intermediate valve <b>75</b> and the radial through holes <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">When the trigger <b>12</b> is pulled as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the trigger valve <b>121</b> closes the fluid communication between the main air chamber <b>11</b> and the trigger passage <b>13</b>. High pressure air in the first air chamber <b>63</b> is discharged to the atmosphere, so that high pressure air in the second air chamber <b>64</b> drives the cylinder <b>6</b> to upwardly move to its upper dead center. The normal valve <b>14</b> opens the fluid communication from the second air chambers <b>64</b> to the main vent holes <b>66</b>, and introduces high pressure air into the cylinder <b>6</b>, applied to the nail punching piston <b>2</b>. Thus, the piston <b>2</b> rapidly moves toward the nails. In addition, the bottom exhausting hole <b>15</b> is opened for discharging compressed high pressure air under the piston <b>2</b> to an atmosphere.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">When the nail punching piston <b>2</b> move downwardly a certain distance to make the top air chamber <b>60</b> connect with the intermediate vent holes <b>68</b>, the high pressure air in the top air chamber <b>60</b> may continuously being guided into the nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b> via intermediate vent holes <b>68</b>, the vent holes <b>751</b> of the intermediate valve <b>75</b>, the radial through holes <b>52</b>, and the nail pushing passage <b>10</b>, to drive the nail pushing piston to take the nails.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Then, when the user releases the trigger <b>12</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the trigger valve <b>121</b> returns to the original open state so that the first air chamber <b>63</b> re-accumulates high-pressure air. Before the piston <b>2</b> move upwardly to close the top vent holes <b>67</b>, the high pressure air in the third air chamber <b>71</b> may exhaust to the top air chamber <b>60</b> via the top vent holes <b>67</b>, to make the slidable sleeve valve <b>7</b> upwardly move induced by the high pressure air in the fourth air chamber <b>72</b> for opening the bottom valve <b>76</b>. Then the high pressure air in the fourth air chamber <b>72</b> are guided into the bottom air chamber <b>61</b> via the bottom vent holes <b>69</b> to enhance the speed of upwardly moving of the piston <b>2</b>. Meanwhile, the residual high pressure air in the top air chamber <b>60</b> may be exhausted via top exhausting holes <b>16</b> in a top portion of the gun body <b>1</b> to make the top air chamber <b>60</b> in a state of lower pressure. The high pressure air in the nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b> may discharge to atmosphere via the passage <b>10</b>, the radial through hole <b>52</b>, the intermediate valve <b>75</b>, the ring groove <b>70</b>, the through holes <b>741</b>, the O-ring (or elastomer band) <b>742</b>, the top groove <b>73</b>, and the top air chamber <b>60</b>, to drive the nail pushing piston <b>32</b> to push nails.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">When the nail punching piston <b>2</b> is repositioned as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the main vent holes <b>66</b>, the top vent holes <b>67</b>, the intermediate vent holes <b>68</b>, and the bottom vent holes <b>69</b> is re-closed to make the air compressed in the first, second, third and fourth air chamber <b>63</b>, <b>64</b>, <b>71</b> and <b>72</b>, and to make the slidable sleeve valve <b>7</b> move downwardly for making the trigger <b>12</b> in an original state.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Therefore, from above description, it is known that in the above embodiment of the present invention, the axial and radial through holes <b>51</b> and <b>52</b> of the air distribution ring <b>5</b> may help to maintain the air pressure and enhance the speed of pushing the nails. The radial through holes <b>52</b> may help to exhaust the compressed air in the cylinder <b>30</b> rapidly, so as to improve the speed, stability, and efficiency of punching the nail.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In an alternative modification, the pneumatic nail gun further includes an exhausting hole <b>33</b> or <b>34</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 9</figref>) connecting with environment that is disposed at an inner surface of the nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b> or the nail pushing piston <b>32</b>, which can enhance the speed of taking and pushing the nails of the nail pushing piston. Moreover, the exhausting hole <b>33</b> or <b>34</b> has a cross section farther smaller than the cross section of the nail pushing passage <b>10</b>, which can help to maintain the air pressure of the high pressure air in the nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b> and prevent the high pressure air from fast exhausting from the nail pushing cylinder <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The above description is given by way of example, and not limitation. Given the above disclosure, one skilled in the art could devise variations that are within the scope and spirit of the invention disclosed herein, including configurations ways of the recessed portions and materials and/or designs of the attaching structures. Further, the various features of the embodiments disclosed herein can be used alone, or in varying combinations with each other and are not intended to be limited to the specific combination described herein. Thus, the scope of the claims is not to be limited by the illustrated embodiments.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A pneumatic nail gun, comprising:
<claim-text>a gun body including a nail punching piston and a nail pushing passage, the nail punching piston being induced by high pressure air to move downwardly to punch the nails and move upwardly to reposition;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a nail pusher disposed between an end of the nail pushing passage and a canister, the nail pusher comprising a nail pushing cylinder connecting to the nail pushing passage, the nail pushing cylinder comprising a nail pushing piston and a spring therein; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an air distribution ring fixing to an inner surface of the gun body and adjacent to the other end of the nail pushing passage, the air distribution ring comprising at least one axial through hole and at least one radial through hole, the at least one axial through hole guiding the high pressure air to drive the nail punching piston to reposition after the nail punching piston moves downwardly to punch the nails, the at least one radial through hole guiding and pushing the high pressure air into the nail pushing cylinder via the nail pushing passage to drive the nail pushing piston to take the nails after the nail punching piston move downwardly to punch the nails, and the at least one radial through hole also exhausting the high pressure air in the nail pushing cylinder and the nail pushing passage to make the nail pushing piston reposition to push the nails when the nail punching piston moves upwardly to reposition.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The pneumatic nail gun as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the gun body comprises a main air chamber for containing the high pressure air, a moveable cylinder for containing the nail punching piston, and a slidable sleeve valve disposed at a peripheral of the moveable cylinder, the moveable cylinder being divided into a first air chamber and a second air chamber in the gun body, the slidable sleeve valve being divided into a third air chamber and a fourth air chamber in the gun body, the first, the second, the third, and the fourth air chambers being connected to the main air chamber, and the air distribution ring being fixed to an inner surface of the fourth air chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The pneumatic nail gun as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the nail punching piston divides the moveable cylinder into a top air chamber and a bottom air chamber to contain the high pressure air, the moveable cylinder comprises a plurality of intermediate vent holes, the slidable sleeve valve comprises at least one intermediate valve, and the radial through hole guides and pushes the high pressure air in the top air chamber into the nail pushing cylinder via the intermediate vent holes of the moveable cylinder and the slidable sleeve valve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The pneumatic nail gun as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the slidable sleeve valve comprises at least one check valve and at least one intermediate valve, a ring groove is formed between the slidable sleeve valve and the moveable cylinder, the ring groove is connected with the at least one check valve and the at least one intermediate valve, and the radial through hole guides and pushes the high pressure air in the top air chamber into the nail pushing cylinder via the vent holes of the at least one intermediate valve, the ring groove, and the check valve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The pneumatic nail gun as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the air distribution ring further comprises a plurality of air seals disposed at an inner and outer surfaces thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The pneumatic nail gun as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the nail pushing cylinder comprises an exhausting hole connecting with environment, the exhausting hole is disposed at an inner surface of the nail pushing cylinder, which has a cross section farther smaller than the cross section of the nail pushing passage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The pneumatic nail gun as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the nail pushing piston comprises an exhausting hole connecting with environment, the exhausting hole has a cross section farther smaller than the cross section of the nail pushing passage.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
