<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299116-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299116</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10501951</doc-number>
<date>20030122</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>SE</country>
<doc-number>0200200</doc-number>
<date>20020122</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>359</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>22</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701 24</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Control system for a powered vehicle</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5416477</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Shibata</name>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340988</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5456332</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Borenstein</name>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5823884</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ager</name>
<date>19981000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6289270</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Baumgarten</name>
<date>20010900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>701 26</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>7-13622</doc-number>
<date>19950100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>International Search Report Apr. 17, 2003.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>International Preliminary Examination Report Dec. 9, 2003.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>701 24</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050065676</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050324</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Philipson</last-name>
<first-name>Niklas</first-name>
<address>
<city>Stockholm</city>
<country>SE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>SE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>SE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fainberg</last-name>
<first-name>Jim</first-name>
<address>
<city>Oslo</city>
<country>NO</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>NO</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>NO</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nixon &amp; Vanderhye P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Visual Act Scandinavia AB</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Saltsjo-Boo</city>
<country>SE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Thu V.</first-name>
<department>3661</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/SE03/00108</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030122</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20041109</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO03/062935</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20030731</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A control system for a powered vehicle describes a desired movement of the vehicle and communicates the movement to the vehicles drive system. The powered vehicle comprises a chassis and at least three rolling means mounted on the chassis for engaging a surface over which the vehicle moves. The drive system comprises at least two drive units, each comprising first and second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of the drive units. The control system comprises a computing means for calculating a desired movement of the vehicle, wherein translation of the vehicle is calculated in the form of a continuous cubic function and rotation of the vehicle is calculated in the form of a linear function. The control system also comprises a communicating means for transmitting the desired movement to the at least two drive units to move the vehicle in accordance with the desired movement.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="104.31mm" wi="73.24mm" file="US07299116-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="227.58mm" wi="158.50mm" file="US07299116-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="241.38mm" wi="168.74mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299116-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="223.60mm" wi="151.05mm" file="US07299116-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is the US national phase of international application PCT/SE03/00108 filed 22 Jan. 2003, which designated the US and claims priority to SE Application No. 0200200-4, filed 22 Jan. 2002. The entire contents of these applications are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates in a first aspect to a control system for a powered vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In a second aspect the present invention relates to a method of controlling a movement of a powered vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In a third aspect the present invention relates to at least one computer program product for controlling a movement of a powered vehicle.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF RELATED ART</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The theatre has automated much of the equipment used for movement of scenery and lighting. Most of stage activity involves simply moving scenery about the stage. Automated systems for doing this have been limited by poor radio communication, lack of accuracy and navigation, high noise and high costs.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The document U.S. Pat. No. 5,823,884 discloses a powered stage wagon comprising a chassis to which there is mounted a plurality of rolling support means, each of which is located at respective corner of the chassis. The powered stage wagon also comprises a first and a second drive means, both mounted on the chassis in engagement with the surface over which the stage wagon is to move and are mutually spaced. The document describes a method of calculating a travel path along which the stage wagon may be moved from a current position to a desired position. The method comprising the steps of calculating for each of said drive means the bisector of a line joining the current location of said drive means and the location of said drive means when the stage wagon has moved to its desired position; determining the point of intersection of the two bisectors; calculating for each of said drive means the length of an arc centred on said point of intersection and passing through both the current location of said drive means and the location of said drive means when the stage wagon has moved to its desired position; controlling the ratio of the rotational speeds of the first and second drive means in accordance with the ratio of said arc lengths; and controlling the relative orientation of said first and second drive means so that each of said drive means continuously defines a tangent to the respective arc associated with the drive means concerned.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">One main disadvantage with the method of calculating a travel path according to the document U.S. Pat. No. 5,823,884 is that it limits paths to certain predefined combinations of translation and rotation. Another disadvantage is that the method does not correct for any physical errors in movement that might occur.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is an object of the present invention to solve the above mentioned problems.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">According to the present invention there is provided in a first aspect a control system for a powered vehicle for describing a desired movement of said vehicle, and communicating said movement to a drive system of said vehicle. The powered vehicle comprising a chassis, at least three rolling means mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move. The drive system comprises at least two drive units, each comprising a first driving means and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit and consequently said vehicle. The control system also comprises a computing means for calculating a desired movement of said vehicle, wherein translation of said vehicle is calculated in said form of a continuous cubic function, and rotation of said vehicle is calculated in the form of a linear function. The control system also comprises a communicating means for transmitting said desired movement to said desired movement to said at least two drive units to move said vehicle in accordance with the desired movement. One advantage with the control system according to the present invention is that it can move a vehicle along any predefined path, with a predefined change in rotation in accordance with a time scale. Another advantage with this control system is that it is scalable, i.e. it can move any number of vehicles simultaneously along different paths. Another advantage with this control system is that it allows vehicles to move in any direction. It makes no assumptions as to one direction being more natural than another. Yet another advantage with this control system is that it uses the same method of describing any type of movement or path.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A further advantage in his context if said control system also comprises a navigation system for determining an actual position of said vehicle, which actual position is transmitted to said computing means for correcting errors between the actual position and a desired position according to said desired movement of said vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said continuous cubic function is a Beziér function of a third power.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A further advantage in his context if Beziér function is expressed in accordance with:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>x=ap</i><sup>3</sup><i>+bp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+cp+d</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>y=ep</i><sup>3</sup><i>+fp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+gp+h,</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
wherein a-h are constants and p is a variable satisfying 0≦p≦1. Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said computing means calculates said constants a-h according to the following expressions:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=x</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub><i>−x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>e=y</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub><i>−y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>b=</i>3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>f=</i>3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>c=</i>3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>g=</i>3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>d=x<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>h=y<sub>0</sub>,<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
wherein (X<sub>0</sub>, y<sub>0</sub>) is a start position and (x<sub>3</sub>, y<sub>3</sub>) is an end position of said movement, and (x<sub>1</sub>, y<sub>1</sub>) and (x<sub>2</sub>, y<sub>2</sub>) are control positions of said movement.
</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A further advantage in his context if said movement is made up of at least one segment.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if if said movement is made up of at least two segments, said control system has to apply to the following rules if said vehicle is to move smoothly from one segment to the next:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0015">a start position of the following segment must be the same as an end position of the preceding segment;</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0002" num="0016">a start rotation of the following segment must be the same as an end rotation of the preceding segment;</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0003" num="0017">a starting path of the following segment must be tangent to an end path of the preceding segment; and</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0004" num="0018">a starting speed and direction of rotation of the following segment must be the same as an end speed and direction of rotation of the preceding segment.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0019">A further advantage in his context if said computing means also calculates an instantaneous center of said vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0020">Another object of the invention is to provide a method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle. The vehicle comprises a chassis, a drive system, at least three rolling means mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move. The drive system comprises at least two drive units, each comprising a first driving means and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit. The method comprises the following steps:
<ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0003" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0003-0001" num="0021">with a computing means comprised in said control system, to calculate a desired movement of aid vehicle;</li>
        <li id="ul0003-0002" num="0022">by calculating a translation of said vehicle in the form of a continues cubic function; and</li>
        <li id="ul0003-0003" num="0023">by calculating a rotation of said vehicle in the form of a linear function; and</li>
        <li id="ul0003-0004" num="0024">with a communication means comprised in said control system, to transmit said desired movement to said at least two drive units to move said vehicle in accordance with said desired movement. One advantage with the method according to the present invention is that it can move a vehicle along any predefined path, with a predefined change in rotation in accordance with a time scale. Another advantage with this method is that it is scalable, i.e. it can move any number of vehicles simultaneously along different paths. Another advantage with this method is that it allows vehicles to move in any direction. It makes no assumptions as to one direction being more natural than another. Yet another advantage with this method is that is uses the same method of describing any type of movement or path.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0025">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said method also comprises the steps of:
<ul id="ul0004" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0004-0001" num="0026">with a navigation system comprised in said control system, to determine an actual position of said vehicle;</li>
    <li id="ul0004-0002" num="0027">to transmit said actual position to said computing means; and</li>
    <li id="ul0004-0003" num="0028">to correct errors between said actual position and a desired position according to said desired movement of said vehicle.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0029">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said continuous cubic function is a Beziér function of a third power.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0030">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said Beziér function is expressed in accordance with:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>x=ap</i><sup>3</sup><i>+bp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+cp+d</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>y=ep</i><sup>3</sup><i>+fp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+gp+h,</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
wherein a-h are constants, and p is a variable satisfying 0≦p≦1.
</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0031">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said method also comprises the steps of
<ul id="ul0005" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0005-0001" num="0032">to calculate said constants a-h according to the following expressions:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=x</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub><i>−x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>e=y</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub><i>−y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>b=</i>3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>f=</i>3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>c=</i>3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>g=</i>3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>d=x<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>h=y<sub>0</sub>,<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
wherein (x<sub>0</sub>, y<sub>0</sub>) is a start position and (x<sub>3</sub>, y<sub>3</sub>) is an end position of said movement, and wherein (x<sub>1</sub>, y<sub>1</sub>) and (x<sub>2</sub>, y<sub>2</sub>) are control positions of said movement.
</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0033">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said method also comprises the steps of:
<ul id="ul0006" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0006-0001" num="0034">to calculate an instantaneous center and angular velocity of said vehicle; and</li>
    <li id="ul0006-0002" num="0035">to calculate speeds and angles of said drive unit.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0036">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said method also comprises the steps of:
<ul id="ul0007" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0007-0001" num="0037">if said error will result in abrupt movement of said vehicle, to integrate succeeding corrections; and</li>
    <li id="ul0007-0002" num="0038">to add a suitable proportion of said corrections for each time slice.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0039">Another object of the invention is to provide at least one computer program product directly loadable into the internal memory of at least one digital computer. The at least one computer program product comprises software code portions for performing the steps of the method according to the present invention, when said at least one product is/are run on at least one computer. One advantage with the computer program product(s) according to the present invention is that it/they can move a vehicle along any predefined path, with a predefined change in rotation in accordance with a time scale. Another advantage with this product is that it is scalable, i.e. it can move any number of vehicles simultaneously along different paths. Another advantage with this product is that it allows vehicles to move in any direction. It makes no assumptions as to one direction being more natural than another. Yet another advantage with this product is that is uses the same method of describing any type of movement or path.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0040">It should be emphasised that the term “comprises/comprising” when used in this specification is taken to specify the presence of stated features, steps or components but does not preclude the presence of one or more other features, integers, steps, components or groups thereof.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0026" num="0041">Embodiments of the invention will now be described with a reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a block diagram of a first embodiment of a control system for a powered vehicle according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a side view from above of a drive unit that can be used in connection with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a schematic diagram of a powered vehicle that can be used in connection with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flowchart of a first embodiment of the method of controlling a movement of a powered vehicle according to the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0046"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a schematic diagram of some computer program products according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0032" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a block diagram of a control system <b>70</b> for a powered vehide <b>72</b> according to the present invention. The powered vehicle <b>72</b> comprises a drive system (not disclosed, see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>), a chassis (not disclosed), at least three rolling means (not disclosed) mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move. The drive system comprises at least two drive units (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), each comprising a first driving means and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive units. The control system <b>70</b> comprises a computing means <b>74</b> for calculating a desired movement of said vehicle <b>72</b>, wherein translation of said vehicle <b>72</b> is calculated in the form of a continuous cubic function, and rotation of said vehicle <b>72</b> is calculated in the form of a linear function. The control system <b>70</b> also comprises a communication means <b>76</b> for transmitting said desired movement to said at least two drive units to move said vehicle <b>72</b> in accordance with the desired movement. The control system <b>70</b> also comprises a navigation system <b>78</b> comprised in said vehicle <b>72</b> for determining an actual position of said vehicle, which actual position is transmitted to the computing means <b>74</b> via said communication means <b>76</b> for correcting errors between the actual position and a desired position according to said desired movement of said vehicle <b>72</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0048">In a preferred embodiment of the control system <b>70</b> according to the present invention the continuos cubic function is a Beziér function of a third power.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0049">In a preferred embodiment of the controlsystem <b>70</b> according the present invention the Beziér function is expressed in accordance with:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>x=ap</i><sup>3</sup><i>+bp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+cp+d</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>y=ep</i><sup>3</sup><i>+fp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+gp+h,</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0050">wherein a-h are constants and p is a variable satisfying 0≦p≦1.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0051">In a preferred embodiment of the control system <b>70</b> according to the present invention the constants a-h are calculated in accordance with the following expressions:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=x</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub><i>−X</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>e=y</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub><i>−y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>b=</i>3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>f=</i>3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>c=</i>3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>g=</i>3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>d=x<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>h=y<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0052">wherein (x<sub>0</sub>, y<sub>0</sub>) is a start position and (y<sub>3</sub>, y<sub>3</sub>) is an end position of said movement, and (x<sub>1</sub>, y<sub>1</sub>) and ((x<sub>2</sub>, y<sub>2</sub>) are control positions of said movement.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0053">In a preferred embodiment of the control system <b>70</b> according to the present invention the movement is made up of at least one segment.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0054">In a preferred embodiment of the control system <b>70</b> according to the present invention, if said movement is made up of at least two segments, the control system <b>70</b> has to apply the following rules if said vehicle <b>72</b> is to move smoothly from one segment to the next:
<ul id="ul0008" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0008-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0009" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0009-0001" num="0055">a start position of the following segment must be the same as an end position of the preceding segment;</li>
        <li id="ul0009-0002" num="0056">a start rotation of the following segment must be the same as an end rotation of the preceding segment;</li>
        <li id="ul0009-0003" num="0057">a starting path of the following segment must be tangent to an end path of the preceding segment; and</li>
        <li id="ul0009-0004" num="0058">a starting speed and direction of rotation of the following segment must be the same as an end sped and direction of rotation of the preceding segment.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0059">In a preferred embodiment of the control system <b>70</b> according to the present invention, the computing means <b>74</b> also calculates an instant aneous center of said vehicle <b>72</b>. The movement of any point on the vehicle <b>72</b> can always be described as a rotation about the instantaneous center is calculated errors in the vehicles position along the curve and its rotation as reported by the navigation system <b>78</b> may be accounted for.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0060"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a side view from above of a drive unit <b>10</b> which can be used in connection with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0061">The drive unit <b>10</b> comprises a rolling means <b>12</b> intended to be in frictional engagement with a surface over which said drive unit <b>10</b> is intended to move. Preferably, said rolling means <b>12</b> is a wheel <b>12</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises a first driving means <b>14</b>, and a second driving means <b>16</b>, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit <b>10</b>. The first driving means <b>14</b> is arranged on a rotatable support means <b>18</b> rotatable about a center axis, c.a.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0062">The first driving means <b>14</b> is operable to rotate said rolling means <b>12</b> about a rolling axis. The rolling axis is perpendicular to said center axis, c.a. As is apparent from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the rolling means <b>12</b> is displaced a predetermined distance from the center axis, c.a. The second driving means <b>16</b> is operable to rotate the support means <b>18</b> about said center axis, c.a. In one preferred embodiment of the drive unit <b>10</b>, which is disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the first and second driving means <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, each is a servomotor <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises a sprocket means <b>20</b> provided on the circumference of the support means <b>18</b>. The sprocket means <b>20</b> is driven by the second driving means <b>16</b> by way of a transmission means. In the embodiment disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the transmission means is a chain <b>22</b> which is engaged with said sprocket means <b>20</b> and a toothed wheel <b>24</b> driven by said second driving means <b>16</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> also comprises a tension wheel <b>26</b> which can be in engagement with the chain <b>22</b>. The tension wheel <b>26</b> can be moved along a groove <b>28</b> so as to alter the tension on the chain <b>22</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises an inductive sensor <b>30</b> arranged in a sensor holder <b>32</b> to detect the position of the sprocket means <b>20</b>, i.e. the orientation of the wheel <b>12</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises a rotation limiter <b>34</b> arranged in the vicinity of the sprocket means <b>20</b>. Preferably, the drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises a planetary gear-box (not disclosed) mounted on the first driving means <b>14</b>, and in connection with the wheel <b>12</b>. The rotatable support means <b>18</b> is supported by a ball bearing means (not disclosed). The support means <b>18</b> is preferably a plate <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0063"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a schematic diagram of a powered vehicle <b>50</b>;<b>72</b> which can be used in connection with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0064">This vehicle <b>50</b> comprises two drive units <b>10</b>, of the same kind disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, and two passive rolling means <b>52</b>. The two drive units <b>10</b> are arranged in two diagonally arranged corners of the vehicle and the two passive rolling means <b>52</b> are arrange in the two other corners of the vehicle. The vehicle <b>50</b> is e.g. powered by a battery pack <b>54</b>. The vehicle <b>50</b> also comprises a wireless communication means <b>56</b> for communicating with a remote computer system <b>58</b> to control said drive unit <b>10</b>, i.e. the movement and steering of the vehicle <b>50</b>. The vehicle <b>50</b> also comprises a laser navigation unit <b>60</b>, e.g. a laser scanner which makes use of several reflectors mounted along the perimeter of e.g. the stage area. The vehicle <b>50</b> also comprises a central processing unit <b>62</b> which is connected to the laser navigation unit <b>60</b>, the wireless communication means <b>56</b>, the battery pack <b>54</b> and a number of servo amplifiers <b>64</b> which in turn are connected to the drive units <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0065">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> there is a flowchart of a first embodiment of the method of controlling a movement of a powered vehicle according to the present invention. The method begins at block <b>80</b>. The vehicle comprises a chassis, a drive system, at least three rolling means mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move. The drive system comprises at least two drive units, each comprising a first driving means and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive units. At block <b>82</b> the method continues with the step:
<ul id="ul0010" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0010-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0011" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0011-0001" num="0066">with a computing means comprised in said control system, to calculate a desired movement of said vehicle. The method continues at block <b>84</b>, to calculate a translation of said vehicle in the form of a continues cubic function The next step, at block <b>86</b>, consists of calculating a rotation of said vehicle in the form of a linear function.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0067">The method continues at block <b>88</b> with the step: with a communication means comprised in the control system, to transmit said desired movement to said at last two drive units to move said vehicle in accordance with said desired movement. The method is completed at block <b>90</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0068">In a preferred embodiment of the method according to the present invention, the method also comprises the steps of:
<ul id="ul0012" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0012-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0013" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0013-0001" num="0069">with a navigation system comprised in said control system, to determine an actual position of said vehicle;</li>
        <li id="ul0013-0002" num="0070">to transmit said actual position to said computing means; and</li>
        <li id="ul0013-0003" num="0071">to correct errors between said actual position and a desired position according to the desired movement of said vehicle.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0072">In a preferred embodiment of the method according to the present invention, the continuos cubic function is a Beziér function of a third power.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0073">In a preferred embodiment of the method according to the present invention, the Beziér function is expressed in accordance with:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>x=ap</i><sup>3</sup><i>+bp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+cp+d</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>y=ep</i><sup>3</sup><i>+fp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+gp+h,</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0074">wherein a-h are constants, and p is a variable satisfying 0≦p≦1.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0075">In a preferred embodiment of the method according to the present invention, the method also comprises the steps of:</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0076">to calculate said constants a-h according to the following expressions:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=x</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub><i>−x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>e=y</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub><i>−y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>b=</i>3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>f=</i>3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>c=</i>3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>g=</i>3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>d=x<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>h=y<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0077">wherein (x<sub>0</sub>, y<sub>0</sub>) is a start position and (x<sub>3</sub>, y<sub>3</sub>) is an end position of said movement, and wherein (x<sub>1</sub>, y<sub>1</sub>) and (x<sub>2</sub>, y<sub>2</sub>) are control positions of said movement.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0078">In a preferred embodiment of the method according to the method according to the present invention, the method also comprises the steps of:
<ul id="ul0014" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0014-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0015" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0015-0001" num="0079">to calculate an instantaneous center and angular velocity of said vehicle; and</li>
        <li id="ul0015-0002" num="0080">to calculate speeds and angles of said drive units.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0081">In a preferred embodiment of the method according to the present invention, the method also comprises the steps of:
<ul id="ul0016" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0016-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0017" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0017-0001" num="0082">if said error will result in abrupt movement of said vehicle, to integrate succeeding corrections; and</li>
        <li id="ul0017-0002" num="0083">to add a suitable proportion of said correction for each time slice.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0084">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> there is disclosed a schematic diagram of some computer program products according to the present invention. There is disclosed n different digital computers <b>100</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>100</b><sub>n</sub>, wherein n is an integer. There is also disclosed n different computer program products <b>102</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>102</b><sub>n</sub>, here showed in the form of compact discs. The different computer program products <b>102</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>102</b><sub>n </sub>are directly loadable into the internal memory of the n different digital computers <b>100</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . <b>100</b><sub>n</sub>. Each computer program product <b>102</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>102</b><sub>n </sub>comprises software code portions for performing some or all the steps of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> when the product(s) <b>102</b><sub>1 </sub>. . . , <b>102</b><sub>n </sub>is/are run on said computer(s) <b>100</b><sub>1 </sub>. . . , <b>100</b><sub>n</sub>. Said computer program products <b>102</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>102</b><sub>n </sub>can e.g. be in the form of floppy disks, RAM disks, magnetic tapes, opto magnetical disks or any other suitable products.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0085">One advantage with the present invention is that it can move a vehicle or robot along any predefined path, with a predefined change in rotation in accordance with a time scale.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0086">Another advantage is that it can move any number of vehicles synchronously, that is move several vehicles as though they were one, transparently to the user and without any mechanical connection or any cables between the vehicles.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0087">Another advantage is that it allows vehicle to be of any size while using the same set of components.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0088">Another advantage with the present invention is that it allows the operator to control the speed of the movements dynamically, while the relation positions of all vehicles under his/her control remain the same.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0089">The invention is not limited to the embodiments described in the foregoing. It will be obvious that many different modifications are possible within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A control system for a powered vehicle for describing a desired movement of said vehicle, and communicating said movement to a drive system of said vehicle, wherein said powered vehicle comprising a chassis, at least three rolling means mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move, wherein said drive system comprising at least two drive units each comprising a first driving means and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit, wherein said control system comprises a computing means for calculating a desired movement of said vehicle, wherein translation of said vehicle is calculated in the form of a continuous cubic function and rotation of said vehicle is calculated in the form of a linear function, wherein said control system also comprises a communicating means for transmitting said desired movement to said at least two drive units to move said vehicle in accordance with the desired movement.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A control system for a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said control system also comprises a navigation system for determining an actual position of said vehicle, which actual position is transmitted to said computing means for correcting errors between the actual position and a desired position according to said desired movement of said vehicle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A control system for a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said continuous cubic function is a Beziér function of a third power.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A control system for a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said Beziér function is expressed in accordance with:
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>x=ap</i><sup>3</sup><i>+bp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+cp+d</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>y=ep</i><sup>3</sup><i>+fp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+gp+h,</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a-h are constants and p is a variable satisfying 0≦p≦1.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A control system for a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said computing means calculates said constants a-h according to the following expressions:
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=x</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub><i>−x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>e=y</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub><i>−y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>b</i>=3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>f</i>=3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>c</i>=3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>g</i>=3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>d=x<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>h=y<sub>0</sub>,<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein (x<sub>0</sub>, y<sub>0</sub>) is a start position and (x<sub>3</sub>, y<sub>3</sub>) is an end position of said movement, and (x<sub>1</sub>, y<sub>1</sub>) and (x<sub>2</sub>, y<sub>2</sub>) are control positions of said movement.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A control system for a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said movement is made up of at least one segment.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A control system for a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein, if said movement is made up of at least two segments, said control system has to apply to the following rules if said vehicle is to move smoothly from one segment to the next:
<claim-text>a start position of the following segment must be the same as an end position of the preceding segment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a start rotation of the following segment must be the same as an end rotation of the preceding segment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a starting path of the following segment must be tangent to an end path of the preceding segment; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a starting speed and direction of rotation of the following segment must be the same as an end speed and direction of rotation of the preceding segment.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A control system for a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said computing means also calculates an instantaneous center of said vehicle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle comprising a chassis, a drive system, at least three rolling means mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move, wherein said drive system comprises at least two drive units, each comprising a first driving means, and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit, wherein said method comprises the steps of:
<claim-text>with a computing means comprised in said control system, calculating a desired movement of said vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>calculating a translation of said vehicle in the form of a continuous cubic function; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>calculating a rotation of said vehicle in the form of a linear function; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>with a communicating means comprised in said control system, transmitting said desired movement to said at least one drive unit to move said vehicle in accordance with said desired movement.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said method also comprises the steps of:
<claim-text>with a navigation system comprised in said control system, determining an actual position of said vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting said actual position to said computing means; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>correcting errors between said actual position and a desired position according to said desired movement of said vehicle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said continuous cubic function is a Beziér function of a third power.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein said Beziér function is expressed in accordance with:
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>x=ap</i><sup>3</sup><i>+bp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+cp+d</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>y=ep</i><sup>3</sup><i>+fp</i><sup>2</sup><i>+gp+h,</i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a-h are constants, and p is a variable satisfying 0≦p≦1.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein said method also comprises the steps of:
<claim-text>to calculate said constants a-h according to the following expressions:
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>a=x</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub><i>−x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>e=y</i><sub>3</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub><i>−y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>b</i>=3<i>x</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>f</i>=3<i>y</i><sub>2</sub>−6<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>+3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>c</i>=3<i>x</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>x</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>g</i>=3<i>y</i><sub>1</sub>−3<i>y</i><sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>d=x<sub>0</sub><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>h=y<sub>0</sub>,<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein (x<sub>0</sub>, y<sub>0</sub>) is a start position and (x<sub>3</sub>, y<sub>3</sub>) is an end position of said movement, and wherein (x<sub>1</sub>, y<sub>1</sub>) and (x<sub>2</sub>, y<sub>2</sub>) are control positions of said movement.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said method also comprises the steps of:
<claim-text>to calculate an instantaneous center and angular velocity of said vehicle; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>to calculate speeds and angles of said drive unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said method also comprises the steps of:
<claim-text>if said error will result in abrupt movement of said vehicle, to integrate succeeding corrections; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>to add a suitable proportion of said corrections for each time slice.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. At least one computer program product (<b>102</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>102</b><sub>n</sub>) directly loadable into the internal memory of at least one digital computer (<b>100</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>100</b><sub>n</sub>), comprising software code portions for performing, when said at least one product (<b>102</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>102</b><sub>n</sub>) is/are run on said at least one computer (<b>100</b><sub>1</sub>, . . . , <b>100</b><sub>n</sub>), a method of controlling, with the aid of a control system, a movement of a powered vehicle comprising a chassis, a drive system, at least three rolling means mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move, wherein said drive system comprises at least two drive units, each comprising a first driving means, and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit, wherein said method comprises the steps of:
<claim-text>with a computing means comprised in said control system, calculating a desired movement of said vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>calculating a translation of said vehicle in the form of a continuous cubic function; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>calculating a rotation of said vehicle in the form of a linear function; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>with a communicating means comprised in said control system, transmitting said desired movement to said at least one drive unit to move said vehicle in accordance with said desired movement.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
