<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296861-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296861</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11255621</doc-number>
<date>20051021</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>103 18 850</doc-number>
<date>20030425</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>60</class>
<subclass>T</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>303 15</main-classification>
<further-classification>3031141</further-classification>
<further-classification>303155</further-classification>
<further-classification>303DIG 11</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Brake system for a motor vehicle</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4950038</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ocvirk et al.</name>
<date>19900800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6065815</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Terazawa et al.</name>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6290307</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Poertzgen et al.</name>
<date>20010900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>30 11 493</doc-number>
<date>19811000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>35 23 776</doc-number>
<date>19870100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>195 42 656</doc-number>
<date>19970500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2075607</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19811100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2 132 295</doc-number>
<date>19840700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2177468</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19870100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>61165004</doc-number>
<date>19860700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>303 15</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>303  3</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>303 10</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>303  962</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3031141</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3031133</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3031134</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3031135</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3031155</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>303155</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3031161</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3031162</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>303DIG 11</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>PCT/EP2004/003652</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040406</date>
</document-id>
<parent-status>PENDING</parent-status>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11255621</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060033383</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060216</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ohlig</last-name>
<first-name>Benedikt</first-name>
<address>
<city>Vallendar</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>DE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>DE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Giering</last-name>
<first-name>Wilfried</first-name>
<address>
<city>Mendig</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>DE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>DE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Michels</last-name>
<first-name>Erwin</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kail</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>DE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>DE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>MacMillan, Sobanski &amp; Todd, LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Lucas Automotive GmbH</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Rodriguez</last-name>
<first-name>Pam</first-name>
<department>3683</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The invention relates to a brake system for a motor vehicle comprising a master brake cylinder in which a primary piston for generating a brake pressure in a hydraulic brake circuit can be displaced according to actuation of a brake pedal, it being possible to displace the primary piston under the effect of a hydraulic servo pressure circuit in the master brake cylinder and the hydraulic servo pressure circuit comprising a pressure source for generating the servo pressure and a pressure accumulator for maintaining a minimum servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit. It is provided in this brake system that the pressure accumulator of the servo pressure circuit can be supplied with hydraulic fluid as a function of the servo pressure prevailing in the servo pressure circuit.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="169.25mm" wi="214.97mm" file="US07296861-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="203.45mm" wi="173.57mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296861-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="216.24mm" wi="170.69mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296861-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="211.75mm" wi="178.82mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296861-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="211.07mm" wi="169.33mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296861-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="200.66mm" wi="158.07mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296861-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of International Application No. PCT/EP2004/003652 filed Apr. 6, 2004, the disclosures of which are incorporated herein by reference, and which claimed priority to German Patent Application No. 103 18 850.9 filed Apr. 25, 2003, the disclosures of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention relates to a brake system for a motor vehicle comprising a master brake cylinder in which a primary piston for generating a brake pressure in a hydraulic brake circuit can be displaced according to actuation of a brake pedal, it being possible to displace the primary piston under the effect of a hydraulic servo pressure circuit in the master brake cylinder and the hydraulic servo pressure circuit comprising a pressure source for generating the servo pressure and a pressure accumulator for maintaining a minimum servo pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Brake systems of this type are known from the prior art. Thus DE 195 42 656 A1, and corresponding U.S. Pat. No. 6,290,307 B1, both of which are incorporated by reference herein, for example discloses a brake system for a motor vehicle in which actuation of a brake pedal is detected by sensors. A servo pressure circuit is controlled by a control unit with the aid of the detected pedal actuation. A pressure source is provided in this servo pressure circuit and generates a servo pressure in the hydraulic servo pressure circuit. The pressurised hydraulic fluid is supplied by means of a manifold valve to the master brake cylinder. More precisely, the primary piston that can be displaced inside the master brake cylinder by means of the servo pressure for generating a brake pressure is also pressurised with a servo force, resulting from the servo pressure, in addition to the pedal actuation force. As a result, the primary piston can be effectively displaced inside the master brake cylinder without the entire force required for generating the brake force having to be applied by the brake pedal.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In order to be able to provide a sufficiently high servo pressure at any instant during operation, the servo pressure circuit of DE 195 42 656 A1 provides a pressure accumulator connected downstream of the pressure source. This pressure accumulator is directly coupled to the servo pressure circuit. Whenever the pressure source of the servo pressure circuit is active hydraulic fluid is conveyed from the servo pressure circuit into the pressure accumulator and stored therein. However, this has the effect that in a state in which there is a relatively low hydraulic pressure in the servo pressure circuit and in which the full power of the pressure source would be inherently required for generating a brake pressure inside the master brake cylinder for displacing the primary piston, a certain portion of the hydraulic fluid conveyed by the pressure source will also always be conveyed into the pressure accumulator owing to the fluidic connection of the pressure accumulator and pressure source. The efficiency and the response characteristic of the brake system suffers as a consequence, in particular as not all of the hydraulic fluid required for actuating the primary piston is conveyed from the servo pressure circuit into the master brake cylinder.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is an object of the present invention to provide a brake system of the type designated at the outset in which the servo pressure circuit operates in a manner suitable to the situation and with increased effectiveness.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">This object is achieved by a brake system for a motor vehicle comprising a master brake cylinder in which a primary piston for generating a brake pressure in a hydraulic brake circuit can be displaced according to actuation of a brake pedal, it being possible to displace the primary piston under the effect of a hydraulic servo pressure circuit in the master brake cylinder and the hydraulic servo pressure circuit comprising a pressure source for generating the servo pressure and a pressure accumulator for maintaining a minimum servo pressure. To achieve said object the invention also provides that the pressure accumulator of the servo pressure circuit can be supplied with hydraulic fluid as a function of the servo pressure prevailing in the servo pressure circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to the invention, the pressure accumulator is supplied with hydraulic fluid contained in the servo pressure circuit or conveyed by the pressure source only if current operation of the entire brake system also allows it. Such a mode of supply takes place, for example, if no braking is currently being carried out which requires loading of the primary piston inside the master brake cylinder with hydraulic fluid flowing in from the servo pressure circuit. In such a situation the pressure source can be used to “load” the pressure accumulator, in other words to produce a pressure level therein which can subsequently be used in a later operating state to equalise pressure fluctuations. If, however, braking is initiated by actuation of the brake pedal, the possibility of supplying the pressure accumulator with hydraulic fluid originating from the pressure source is limited or even prevented, so hydraulic fluid conveyed by the pressure source can be supplied substantially completely to the master brake cylinder. As a result the primary piston inside the master brake cylinder can be quickly and effectively displaced for generating a brake pressure. The invention thus defies the drawbacks of the brake system according to DE 195 42 656 A1 discussed at the outset and allows operation of the various components of the servo pressure circuit in a manner suitable to the situation.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">To allow selective supplying of the pressure accumulator as a function of the current operating state of the brake system and still allow reliable discharge of hydraulic fluid from the pressure accumulator to equalise pressure fluctuations it is provided in a development of the invention that the pressure accumulator is fluidically connected by a supply line and/or a discharge line to the servo pressure circuit. As a result of the construction of the brake system with two at least partially separate lines for supplying the pressure accumulator with hydraulic fluid and for discharging hydraulic fluid from the pressure accumulator it is possible to reliably achieve situation-dependent control of the pressure accumulator. However, it is also possible to provide only one line which can be used both for supplying the pressure accumulator with hydraulic fluid and for discharging hydraulic fluid from the pressure accumulator.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A development of the invention provides that the supply line comprises a fluid supply controller for controlling the supply of hydraulic fluid to the pressure accumulator as a function of the servo pressure prevailing in the servo pressure circuit. A fluid supply controller of this type can be constructed so as to be passively or actively controllable. Thus in a development of the invention it is possible that the fluid supply controller comprises a pressure-limiting valve. The pressure-limiting valve can, for example, only open if a specific minimum pressure is achieved or exceeded. This means that the pressure source in the servo pressure circuit has adjusted a sufficiently high hydraulic pressure by means of which reliable operation of the brake system, in particular reliable displacement of the primary piston inside the master brake cylinder, is possible in the event of actuation of the brake pedal. If this state is attained, the pressure-limiting valve opens and the pressure accumulator can be filled, in other words “loaded”, with the hydraulic fluid conveyed by the pressure source. A corresponding pressure level is adjusted in the pressure accumulator in the process.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A further embodiment of the invention provides that the fluid supply controller comprises a throttle element. The use of a throttle element for the fluid supply controller in the supply line also allows function-dependent control of the pressure accumulator. The throttle element thus allows supplying of the pressure accumulator with hydraulic fluid conveyed by the pressure source only in the event of high hydraulic pressures. In other words, the throttle element, as a flow divider, to a certain extent also means that the hydraulic fluid conveyed by the pressure source is supplied to the master brake cylinder with higher priority and only on attaining a specific minimum pressure is a certain portion of the hydraulic fluid conveyed by the pressure source also conveyed to the pressure accumulator.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A development of the invention provides that the pressure-limiting valve and the throttle element are connected in series. A combination of this type of pressure-limiting valve and throttle valve in the supply line allows the quantity of hydraulic fluid supplied to the pressure accumulator and the pressure level that has built up therein to be limited as a result of the throttling effect of the throttle element, even in the event of the minimum pressure, preset by the pressure-limiting valve, for opening the pressure-limiting valve and for supplying the pressure accumulator being exceeded.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A pressure sensor or a plurality of pressure sensors may be provided at various points for monitoring the servo pressure prevailing in the servo pressure circuit. In this connection a development of the invention provides that the fluid supply controller comprises an actively controllable manifold valve, in particular a two-way solenoid valve. The actively controllable manifold valve can be controlled with the aid of the data captured by the pressure sensor. For example this actively controllable manifold valve can, on reaching a specific minimum pressure, be transferred from its closed state into its open state and be closed again after exceeding a specific minimum pressure in the servo pressure circuit. It is also possible to construct the pressure-limiting valve or the throttle element, both discussed above, so as to be actively controllable. Thus for example the pressure-limiting valve can also be controllable in such a way that the minimum pressure thereof that determines the operating state is changed as a function of the operating situation of the brake system. When using an actively controllable throttle element the throttling setting thereof can be changed as a function of the servo pressure currently prevailing in the servo pressure circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A development of the invention provides that the discharge line is constructed with a non-return valve. To avoid undesirable hydraulic fluid flows via the discharge line the non-return valve can be used between the pressure accumulator and the hydraulic line of the servo pressure circuit connecting the pressure source to the master brake cylinder in such a way that it only allows discharge of hydraulic fluid from the pressure accumulator into the servo pressure circuit. The non-return valve can, for example, also be replaced by an actively controllable component.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">With respect to the configuration of the pressure source, a development of the invention provides that the pressure source comprises a motor-driven pump. It may also be provided that the servo pressure circuit comprises a non-return valve connected downstream of the pressure source. The non-return valve is oriented such that it allows conveying of hydraulic fluid from the pressure wave source into the servo pressure circuit, in particular in the direction of the master brake cylinder, whereas it prevents flowing back of hydraulic fluid to the pressure source. Consequently it can be ensured that the servo pressure that has built up in the servo pressure circuit does not reduce in the direction of the pressure source in the event of power fluctuations in the pressure source. In particular, the non-return valve can prevent the servo pressure emanating from the pressure accumulator and exerted on the servo pressure circuit from discharging in the direction of the pressure source but in the direction of the master brake cylinder.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">As described above, the servo pressure circuit is used to displace the primary piston inside the master brake cylinder to generate a brake pressure in the brake circuit. For the event that the servo pressure circuit fails, for example because the pressure source fails, it should, however, be ensured that the primary piston can also be displaced in some other way, for example by a direct mechanical coupling to the brake pedal. In such a case the situations where the actuating force acting on the primary piston simultaneously also leads to recirculation of hydraulic fluid inside the servo pressure circuit or actuation of the primary piston is obstructed owing to the occurrence of above-atmospheric pressure or a vacuum in the servo pressure circuit should be avoided. For this reason, and for general shielding of the master brake cylinder and servo pressure circuit, a development of the invention provides that the servo pressure circuit comprises an actively controllable manifold valve, in particular a two-way solenoid valve, interconnected between the master brake cylinder and the pressure source and the pressure accumulator. The servo pressure circuit can be decoupled from the master brake cylinder by means of the actively controllable manifold valve and undesirable interactions can be ruled out. This actively controllable manifold valve can also be generally used for controlling the servo pressure acting on the primary piston. It may also be used to actively fill the pressure accumulator. Thus it is possible, for example, to close the actively controllable manifold valve after a braking operation has ended and to continue to operate the pump over a predetermined period. As a result, above-atmospheric pressure is generated in the portion of the servo pressure circuit that is close to the pump and shut by the actively controllable manifold valve, it being possible to use the pressure to supply the pressure accumulator with hydraulic fluid. If at the end of braking the servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit was already sufficiently high to supply the pressure accumulator, the pump can also be switched off as early as at the end of braking and the servo pressure prevailing in the servo pressure circuit can initially be used for supplying the pressure accumulator before this is reduced in some other way, for example in the direction of a hydraulic fluid reservoir.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">It may also be provided according to the invention that the servo pressure circuit comprises a further actively controllable manifold valve, in particular a two-way solenoid valve, interconnected between the master brake cylinder and the hydraulic fluid reservoir. As a result it is possible to connect the master brake cylinder to the hydraulic fluid reservoir and thus to reduce servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit after a braking operation has ended. A further manifold valve of this type may also ensure that no above-atmospheric pressure or vacuum builds up in the servo pressure circuit and obstructs or even blocks the primary piston displacement in the event of a mechanical actuation of the primary piston caused by an emergency.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The case was discussed above where pressure is no longer properly generated in the servo pressure circuit, for example owing to a failure of the pressure source. It is equally possible for the servo pressure circuit to supply excessive servo pressure which could possibly lead to an overreaction of the brake system. To prevent a scenario of this type a development of the invention provides that the servo pressure circuit comprises a bypass channel that can be activated as a function of pressure and is connected downstream of the pressure source. The bypass channel can be opened or closed as a function of the prevailing servo pressure and thus hydraulic fluid can be removed from the servo pressure circuit in the event of excessive servo pressure. During normal operation, i.e. if the servo pressure inside the servo pressure circuit is below a predetermined maximum value, the bypass channel is blocked.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">A development of the invention provides that a pressure sensor for detecting the hydraulic pressure prevailing in the pressure accumulator is associated with the pressure accumulator. As already generally stated above with respect to the servo pressure circuit, a separate pressure sensor can, in particular, also be associated with the pressure accumulator. The instantaneous “loading state” of the pressure accumulator can therefore be ascertained and evaluated with the aid of the pressure prevailing in the accumulator, for example to the extent that in the event of a specific minimum pressure not being attained inside the pressure accumulator and with the pressure source power simultaneously being available an active fluid supply control element is opened and hydraulic fluid is supplied to the pressure accumulator for increasing the accumulator pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Reference should be made to the fact that a low-pressure accumulator is preferably used as the pressure accumulator, the maximum accumulator pressure of which is limited. While a low-pressure accumulator of this type is suitable only for temporarily bridging a pressure drop, for example owing to starting delays in the motor drive of the pressure source, it does have the advantages that it is inexpensively available, requires only a small installation space and is usually sufficient during operation. The main load of the pressure generation generally falls to the pressure source anyway. With respect to the use of a low-pressure accumulator, a pressure sensor associated therewith satisfies the further task of also detecting attainment of a maximum pressure, whereupon an additional hydraulic fluid is to be supplied to the pressure accumulator in order to prevent damage or destruction to the low-pressure accumulator. Obviously the maximum pressure value to be detected by the pressure sensor should be selected with sufficient security with respect to a pressure value at which damage can actually occur to the pressure accumulator.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As already illustrated above, the brake system according to the invention can be constructed with a large number of active components and pressure sensors. In this connection a development of the invention provides a controller for evaluating detected hydraulic pressures and for evaluating actively controllable components. The controller can, for example, be formed by an electronic data processing system present in a motor vehicle anyway. It can, however, also be formed by a separate data processing system with a separate processor.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In the above description, it was generally illustrated that the brake system operates according to actuation of the brake pedal. This can mean that, on the one hand, the actuating force exerted on a brake pedal is mechanically transmitted to the primary piston and that actuation of the primary piston is assisted by the servo pressure circuit. In other words the pedal actuating force can be detected and accordingly intensified by the servo pressure circuit. As an alterative to this it is also possible, during normal operation, to completely mechanically decouple the primary piston and its movement from brake pedal actuation. This means that pedal actuation is accordingly no longer transmitted directly to the primary piston, rather the energy causing it dissipates. The primary piston is displaced in such a configuration of the brake system according to the invention exclusively during normal operation, under the effect of the servo pressure circuit. As a result, during normal operation the servo pressure circuit alone is responsible for displacement of the primary piston. For emergency operation, in which, for example, a component of the servo pressure circuit fails, a mechanical coupling of brake pedal and primary piston may be provided and be produced, for example, after bridging a movement pedal.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The invention also relates to a brake system for a motor vehicle comprising a master brake cylinder, in particular of the above-described type, in which, according to actuation of a brake pedal, but mechanically decoupled therefrom, a primary piston can be displaced for generating a brake pressure in a hydraulic brake circuit, it being possible to displace the primary piston under the effect of a hydraulic servo pressure circuit in the master brake cylinder and the hydraulic servo pressure circuit comprising a pressure source for generating the servo pressure. For the development of the invention it is provided that the servo pressure circuit comprises a bypass channel that can be activated as a function of pressure and is connected upstream of the master brake cylinder.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Other advantages of this invention will become apparent to those skilled in the art from the following detailed description of the preferred embodiment, when read in light of the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a schematic general diagram of a first embodiment of a brake system according to the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a general diagram according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> of a second embodiment of a brake system according to the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a general diagram according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> of a third embodiment of a brake system according to the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a general diagram according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1 to 3</figref> of a fourth embodiment of a brake system according to the invention and</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a general diagram according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1 to 4</figref> of a fifth embodiment of a brake system according to the invention;</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a first embodiment of a brake system according to the invention which is designated in general by <b>10</b>. It comprises a servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> and a brake cylinder subassembly <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The brake cylinder subassembly <b>14</b> comprises a master brake cylinder <b>16</b> in which a primary piston <b>18</b> is displaceably guided. A secondary piston <b>20</b> is also displaceably guided in the master brake cylinder <b>16</b> and mechanically coupled to the primary piston <b>18</b> by a spring arrangement. The primary piston <b>18</b>, with the master brake cylinder <b>16</b> and the secondary piston <b>20</b>, encloses a primary pressure chamber <b>22</b>. The secondary piston <b>20</b>, with the master brake cylinder <b>16</b>, encloses a secondary pressure chamber <b>24</b>. The primary pressure chamber <b>22</b> and the secondary pressure chamber <b>24</b> are fluidically coupled by respective supply channels to a hydraulic fluid accumulator <b>26</b> for supplying hydraulic fluid in the rest state shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The primary pressure chamber <b>22</b> and the secondary pressure chamber <b>24</b> are also fluidically coupled to a brake system <b>28</b> which, in a manner known per se, can bring about deceleration of the wheels of a motor vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The brake cylinder subassembly <b>14</b> also comprises a pedal simulation device <b>30</b>. In detail, the pedal simulation device <b>30</b> comprises a force input member <b>32</b> mechanically coupled to a brake pedal and which is workingly connected to a working piston <b>34</b>. The working piston <b>34</b> can be displaced in a piston chamber <b>36</b>, it limiting working chambers on either side inside the piston chamber <b>36</b>. A gas contained in the working chambers on either side of the working piston <b>34</b> is displaced from one working chamber through a throttle <b>38</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) into the respective other working chamber by a displacement of the working piston <b>34</b> inside the piston chamber <b>36</b> and, as a result, due to the effect of the throttle <b>38</b> a resistance to a movement of the force input member <b>32</b> is generated. A resistance which results from a simulation spring arrangement <b>40</b> acts on the force input member <b>32</b> in addition to the pneumatically generated resistance. This simulation spring arrangement <b>40</b> is constructed in multiple stages, i.e. it comprises a spring with low spring hardness and a spring with increased spring hardness which can be reduced by steps, i.e. compressed with a progressive spring characteristic.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Any pedal actuation, i.e. any displacement of the force input member <b>32</b>, is detected by a position sensor <b>42</b>, the position sensor <b>42</b> emitting a position signal to an electronic control unit <b>44</b>, with the aid of which the existence of a pedal actuation can be ascertained.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The brake system <b>10</b> according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is designed in such a way that a pedal actuation, and a displacement of the force input member <b>32</b> resulting therefrom, is not mechanically transmitted to the primary piston <b>18</b>, rather the energy applied during the pedal actuation is dissipated in the brake system <b>10</b>. To carry out braking, hydraulic pressure is generated in an actuating pressure chamber <b>46</b> by means of the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b>, which pressure displaces the primary piston <b>18</b>, and consequently the secondary piston <b>20</b>, and as a result provides for a pressure build up in the primary pressure chamber <b>22</b> and in the secondary pressure chamber <b>24</b>. The primary piston <b>18</b> is thus completely mechanically decoupled from the force input member <b>32</b> during normal operation of the brake system <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The construction of the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> is to be described hereinafter. The servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> is supplied with hydraulic fluid from the hydraulic fluid reservoir <b>26</b>. This is conveyed from the hydraulic fluid reservoir <b>26</b> via a supply line <b>48</b> by a pump <b>50</b> which is driven by a motor <b>52</b>. The pump <b>50</b> is fluidically coupled by a hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b> to the actuating pressure chamber <b>46</b>. A branch <b>56</b>, which is connected in parallel with the pump <b>50</b> and which comprises a pressure-limiting valve <b>58</b>, is provided in the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b> so as to issue from the pump <b>50</b>. A non-return valve <b>60</b> is accordingly integrated into the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b> and allows fluid to flow from the pump <b>50</b> into the actuating pressure chamber <b>46</b>, but blocks a flow of fluid in the opposite direction. A discharge line <b>62</b> comprising a non-return valve <b>64</b> subsequently opens into the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b>. The non-return valve <b>64</b> is oriented in such a way that it blocks a flow of fluid from the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b> into the discharge line <b>62</b> but allows fluid to flow in the opposite direction. A pressure accumulator <b>66</b> is coupled to the discharge line <b>62</b>. The pressure accumulator <b>66</b> is constructed as a low-pressure accumulator and is configured in such a way that hydraulic fluid can be stored therein up to a specific maximum pressure. The pressure accumulator is constructed in an inherently conventional manner and is coupled at its side remote from the non-return valve <b>64</b> to a backflow line <b>68</b>. The pressure accumulator <b>66</b> also comprises a spring element <b>70</b> which is used for pressure accumulation.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">A supply line <b>72</b> subsequently branches from the hydraulic fluid supply line and is likewise provided with a pressure-limiting valve <b>74</b>. The supply line <b>72</b> is hydraulically coupled to the pressure accumulator <b>66</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Starting from the branching of the supply line <b>72</b>, a two-way valve <b>76</b> that can be actively controlled by the electronic control unit <b>44</b> is arranged in the further course of the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b>. This, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, can be switched into a closed state and into an open state. Finally, a further bypass channel <b>78</b>, which likewise comprises a two-way valve <b>80</b> that can be controlled by the electronic control unit <b>44</b>, adjoins the further course of the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b>. A further pressure sensor <b>82</b>, which detects the servo pressure currently prevailing in the hydraulic fluid line <b>54</b> and forwards it to the electronic control unit <b>44</b> in the form of a corresponding signal, is arranged in the further course of and on the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> functions as follows. The motor <b>52</b>, which motively drives the pump <b>50</b>, is controlled according to the control of the electronic control unit <b>44</b>. The pump conveys hydraulic fluid from the hydraulic fluid reservoir <b>26</b> into the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b>. The actuating pressure chamber <b>46</b> is supplied with hydraulic fluid by the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b>, so a pressure builds up in this chamber, if required, which pressure, in the event of actuation of the brake pedal and displacement of the force input member <b>32</b>, leads, without mechanical coupling of force input member <b>32</b> and primary piston <b>18</b>, to the primary piston <b>18</b> being displaced to the left in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> under the effect of the hydraulic pressure that has built up in the actuating chamber <b>46</b>. As a result, a hydraulic pressure builds up in the primary pressure chamber <b>22</b> and, with displacement of the secondary piston <b>20</b>, in the secondary pressure chamber <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">With sufficiently high servo pressure in the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b>, the pressure-limiting valve <b>74</b> opens in the supply line <b>72</b>, so hydraulic fluid can flow into the pressure accumulator <b>66</b> via the supply line <b>72</b>. If, however, the servo pressure prevailing in the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b> exceeds a maximum value, the pressure-limiting valve <b>58</b> opens and short-circuits the entire portion of the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> adjoining the branch <b>56</b>. As a result, overburdening of the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> may be prevented. If, on the other hand, the servo pressure prevailing in the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b> sinks below a specific minimum value, and if the pressure accumulator <b>66</b> is sufficiently “loaded”, the pressure accumulator <b>66</b> can, if required, temporarily equalise a drop in pressure. Such a drop in pressure can, for example, come about because an actuation of the brake pedal (not shown) switches the two-way valve <b>46</b> over from its closed position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> into an open state and servo pressure is thus supplied from the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> to the actuating pressure chamber <b>56</b>. However, owing to a starting delay of the motor <b>52</b> the pump <b>50</b> cannot build up servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> quickly enough, so a pressure drop briefly occurs. This is equalised by the pressure accumulator <b>66</b>. The two-way valve <b>76</b>, controlled by the electronic control unit <b>44</b> according to the signal obtained by the position sensor <b>42</b> and further signals, for example from the pressure sensor <b>82</b>, thus acts as an activating element for activation of the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b>. The two-way valve <b>80</b> also acts as a pressure relief valve for the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b>. It is switched into its open position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, for example, if there is no brake actuation and thus a build up of pressure is not necessary in the actuating pressure chamber <b>46</b> either. As a result, it may also allow pressure equalisation between the master brake cylinder and the reservoir <b>26</b>. This is significant in particular with respect to a possible defect in the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> during which the primary piston <b>32</b> can be mechanically moved. Opening the two-way valve <b>80</b> prevents such a mechanical movement of the primary piston <b>32</b> from being obstructed by above-atmospheric pressure or a vacuum occurring in the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> as a result. As soon as, during normal operation with a completely functional servo pressure circuit <b>12</b>, a brake actuation is detected by the position sensor <b>42</b> the two-way valve <b>80</b> is switched into its closed position so hydraulic fluid can be supplied by the hydraulic fluid line <b>54</b> to the actuating pressure chamber <b>46</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A fundamental aspect of the invention lies in the fluidic connection of the pressure accumulator <b>66</b> in the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b>. In the solution shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, it is possible for the pressure accumulator <b>66</b> to be supplied with hydraulic fluid if there is a sufficiently high servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b>, i.e. if the pump <b>50</b> conveys enough hydraulic fluid from the hydraulic fluid accumulator <b>26</b>. The pressure accumulator <b>66</b>, if it is appropriately loaded, can equalise pressure fluctuations inside the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b>. This is necessary for example if pressure cannot be built up sufficiently quickly in the servo pressure circuit <b>12</b> owing to abrupt braking and owing to a starting delay in the unit comprising pump <b>50</b> and motor drive <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">For supplying the pressure accumulator there is also the possibility that the two-way valve <b>76</b> is closed after a braking operation has ended and the pump <b>50</b> continues to be operated over a predetermined period. As a result hydraulic pressure, which can be used to load the pressure accumulator <b>66</b>, builds up in the portion of the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>54</b> between the pump <b>50</b> and the two-way valve <b>76</b>. In the event that the servo pressure is already sufficiently high once the braking operation has ended, in order to load the pressure accumulator <b>66</b> the pump <b>50</b> can also be directly switched off once the braking operation has ended and when the two-way valve <b>80</b> is closed and the two-way valve <b>76</b> is open the pressure accumulator <b>66</b> can be loaded.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a second embodiment of the brake system according to the invention. To provide a simpler description and to avoid repetitions only the differences from the first embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shall be described. The same reference numerals as in the description of the first embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> will be used for identical or identically-acting components, but will be preceded by the number “1”.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The only difference between the embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and the second embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> lies in the fact that, in the supply line <b>172</b>, the pressure-limiting valve <b>74</b> provided in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> was been replaced in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> by a throttle element <b>186</b>. The throttle element <b>186</b> fulfils the function of limiting a supply of hydraulic fluid via the supply line <b>172</b> to the pressure accumulator <b>166</b> as a function of pressure. The throttle element <b>186</b> is used as a volume flow divider, the larger portion of the volume flow conveyed by the pump <b>150</b> flowing through the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>154</b> from the pump <b>150</b> into the actuating pressure chamber <b>146</b> and only a small portion is supplied via the throttle element <b>186</b> and the supply line <b>172</b> to the pressure accumulator <b>166</b>. However, in the event of high servo pressure inside the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>154</b> a sufficiently high quantity of hydraulic fluid is supplied via the throttle element <b>186</b> and the supply line <b>172</b> to the pressure accumulator <b>166</b> and the latter loaded thereby. A gas contained in the working chambers on either side of the working piston <b>134</b> is displaced from one working chamber through a throttle <b>138</b> (as shown in Fin. <b>2</b>) into the respective other working chamber by a displacement of the working piston <b>134</b> inside the piston chamber <b>136</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The remaining mode of operation of the brake system <b>110</b> corresponds to the mode of operation of the brake system <b>10</b> from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and illustrated in detail.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a third embodiment of a brake system according to the invention. Again only the differences from the embodiments according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> will be described to avoid repetitions. For this purpose, use will again be made of the reference numerals from the preceding description of the embodiments according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> for identically-acting and identical components, the reference numerals being preceded by the number “2”.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a combination of the two embodiments according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1 and 2</figref>. Firstly the pressure-limiting valve <b>274</b> and following it the throttle element <b>286</b> are connected in series into the supply line <b>272</b>. As a result it is possible to throttle the hydraulic flow via the throttle element <b>286</b> even in the event of sufficiently high servo pressure inside the servo pressure circuit <b>212</b> at which the pressure-limiting valve <b>274</b> opens for supplying the pressure accumulator <b>266</b>. As a result the quantity of hydraulic fluid supplied to the pressure accumulator <b>266</b> and the hydraulic pressure that has built up therein can be reduced, even in the event of sufficiently high hydraulic pressure, as the throttle element <b>286</b> again acts as a volume flow divider. With this solution it is possible, in any pressure region, as long as it lies below the maximum pressure value determining the function of the pressure-limiting valve <b>258</b>, to moderately supply the pressure accumulator <b>266</b>. A construction of this type is recommended in particular when using a low-pressure accumulator <b>266</b> which is to be protected from being supplied with excessive hydraulic pressure. A gas contained in the working chambers on either side of the working piston <b>234</b> is displaced from one working chamber through a throttle <b>238</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) into the respective other working chamber by a displacement of the working piston <b>234</b> inside the piston chamber <b>236</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Apart from that the brake system <b>210</b> according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> functions as described above with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with respect to the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a fourth embodiment of the brake system according to the invention. Again only the differences from the preceding embodiments according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1 to 3</figref> are to be described. The same reference numerals, as were used in the description of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1 to 3</figref>, will again be used for this description for identical or identically-acting components but will be preceded by the number “3”.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In the fourth embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a two-way valve <b>388</b>, which can be controlled by the electronic control unit <b>344</b>, is fitted into the supply line <b>372</b> leading from the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>354</b> to the pressure accumulator <b>366</b>. The supply line <b>372</b> also comprises a pressure sensor <b>390</b> between the pressure accumulator <b>366</b> and the two-way valve <b>388</b>. The hydraulic pressure prevailing in the pressure accumulator <b>366</b> can be detected by means of the pressure sensor <b>390</b>. If this hydraulic pressure falls below a predetermined minimum value and the pump <b>350</b> supplies a sufficiently high servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit <b>312</b> the two-way valve <b>388</b> is switched from its closed position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> into the open position. The hydraulic fluid can thus flow unhindered from the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>354</b> into the pressure accumulator <b>366</b> and thus load the pressure accumulator <b>366</b>. The change in the pressure level in the pressure accumulator <b>366</b> during this loading process is monitored by the pressure sensor <b>390</b> and the electronic control unit <b>344</b>. As soon as a desired level or a maximum permitted pressure level is attained in the pressure accumulator <b>366</b> the pressure sensor <b>390</b> detects this and emits a corresponding signal to the electronic control unit <b>344</b>. The unit then controls the two-way valve <b>388</b> so the latter returns to its closed position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and thus the fluidic connection via the supply line <b>372</b> to the hydraulic fluid supply line <b>354</b> is broken. The pressure accumulator <b>366</b> may thus be purposefully loaded as a function of pressure by active switching of the two-way valve <b>388</b> with the embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. A gas contained in the working chambers on either side of the working piston <b>334</b> is displaced from one working chamber through a throttle <b>338</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) into the respective other working chamber by a displacement of the working piston <b>334</b> inside the piston chamber <b>336</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Apart from that the brake system according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> functions as described above with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1 to 3</figref> with regard to embodiments 1 to 3.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">It should also be noted that, owing to the effect of the two-way valve <b>388</b>, the discharge line <b>362</b> can be omitted in a development (not shown) of the embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The pressure accumulator <b>366</b> is supplied and emptied via the line <b>372</b> in this case.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a fifth embodiment of the brake system according to the invention. Again only the differences from the above-described embodiments according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1 to 4</figref> are to be described. The same reference numerals as above for the description of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1 to 4</figref> will be used for identically-acting and identical components, but they will be preceded by the number “4”.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In the fifth embodiment according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the servo pressure circuit <b>412</b> is illustrated in a highly simplified manner compared with the above-described embodiments. The circuit includes only a pressure source comprising pump <b>450</b> and motor <b>452</b> and which can be short-circuited by the branch <b>456</b> and the pressure-limiting valve <b>458</b> located therein. The non-return valve <b>460</b> is also provided as is the bypass channel <b>478</b> with the two-way valve <b>480</b> integrated therein and controllable by the electronic control unit <b>444</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In this embodiment of the brake system according to the invention the pump <b>450</b> and the motor <b>452</b> are constructed in such a way that on activation by a brake pedal actuation, they can react sufficiently quickly without starting delay and thus a servo pressure can build up sufficiently quickly inside the servo pressure circuit <b>412</b>, which pressure then provides for a displacement of the primary piston <b>418</b> in the actuating pressure chamber <b>446</b>. Such a fast-reacting construction of the pressure source, comprising pump <b>450</b> and motor drive <b>452</b> allows a much simplified construction of the servo pressure circuit. A gas contained in the working chambers on either side of the working piston <b>434</b> is displaced from one working chamber through a throttle <b>438</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) into the respective other working chamber by a displacement of the working piston <b>434</b> inside the piston chamber <b>436</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The invention shows a simple and reliable possibility for providing a master brake cylinder with a servo pressure according to a brake pedal actuation.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Reference should be made to the fact that the invention was described in connection with a brake system in which, during normal operation, complete mechanical decoupling is provided between primary piston and force input member. It is, however, equally possible to use the invention in brake systems in which there is no such mechanical decoupling between force input member (and thus the brake pedal) and primary piston and the servo pressure only acts in a supportive manner to displace the primary piston directly moved by actuation of the brake pedal.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In accordance with the provisions of the patent statutes, the principle and mode of operation of this invention have been explained and illustrated in its preferred embodiments. However, it must be understood that this invention may be practiced otherwise than as specifically explained and illustrated without departing from its spirit or scope.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. Brake system for a motor vehicle comprising a master brake cylinder in which a primary piston for generating a brake pressure in a hydraulic brake circuit can be displaced according to actuation of a brake pedal, it being possible to displace the primary piston under the effect of a hydraulic servo pressure circuit in the master brake cylinder and the hydraulic servo pressure circuit comprising a pressure source for generating the servo pressure and a pressure accumulator for maintaining a minimum servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit, wherein a fluid supply controller comprises a throttle element and in that a discharge line is constructed with a non-return valve which only allows discharge of hydraulic fluid from the pressure accumulator into the servo pressure circuit, and wherein the throttle element limits a supply of hydraulic fluid through a supply line to the pressure accumulator, wherein the servo pressure circuit comprises a manifold two-way solenoid valve, that is actively controllably interconnected between the master brake cylinder and the pressure source and the pressure accumulator, wherein the servo pressure circuit comprises a further manifold two-way solenoid valve, that is actively controllably interconnected between the master brake cylinder and a hydraulic fluid reservoir.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. Brake system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a pressure sensor is arranged in the servo pressure circuit for detecting the servo pressure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. Brake system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the pressure source comprises a motor-driven pump.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. Brake system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the servo pressure circuit comprises a non-return valve connected downstream of the pressure source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. Brake system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the servo pressure circuit comprises a bypass channel that can be activated as a function of pressure and is connected downstream of the pressure source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. Brake system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a controller for evaluating detected hydraulic pressures and for controlling actively controllable components.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. Brake system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the primary piston is mechanically decoupled from the brake pedal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. Brake system for a motor vehicle comprising a master brake cylinder in which a primary piston for generating a brake pressure in a hydraulic brake circuit can be displaced according to actuation of a brake pedal, it being possible to displace the primary piston under the effect of a hydraulic servo pressure circuit in the master brake cylinder and the hydraulic servo pressure circuit comprising a pressure source for generating the servo pressure and a pressure accumulator for maintaining a minimum servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit, wherein a fluid supply controller comprises a throttle element and in that a discharge line is constructed with a non-return valve which only allows discharge of hydraulic fluid from the pressure accumulator into the servo pressure circuit, wherein the servo pressure circuit comprises a first manifold two-way solenoid valve, that is actively controllably interconnected between the master brake cylinder and the pressure source and the pressure accumulator, and wherein the servo pressure circuit comprises a second manifold two-way solenoid valve, that is actively controllably interconnected between the master brake cylinder and a hydraulic fluid reservoir.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. Brake system for a motor vehicle comprising a master brake cylinder in which a primary piston for generating a brake pressure in a hydraulic brake circuit can be displaced according to actuation of a brake pedal, it being possible to displace the primary piston under the effect of a hydraulic servo pressure circuit in the master brake cylinder and the hydraulic servo pressure circuit comprising a pressure source for generating the servo pressure and a pressure accumulator for maintaining a minimum servo pressure in the servo pressure circuit, wherein a discharge line is constructed with a non-return valve which only allows discharge of hydraulic fluid from the pressure accumulator into the servo pressure circuit, wherein the servo pressure circuit comprises a first manifold valve, in particular a two-way solenoid valve, that is actively controllably interconnected between the master brake cylinder and the pressure source and the pressure accumulator, wherein the servo pressure circuit comprises a second manifold valve, in particular a two-way solenoid valve, that is actively controllably interconnected between the master brake cylinder and a hydraulic fluid reservoir, wherein the pressure source is fluidly coupled by a fluid supply line to an actuating pressure chamber of the master cylinder, and wherein a pressure limiting valve is provided in the fluid supply line.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
