<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296949-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296949</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11175972</doc-number>
<date>20050706</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>E</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>E</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>18</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>E</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>405232</main-classification>
<further-classification>173  1</further-classification>
<further-classification>173 49</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Removal of obsolete drill platforms from inland seas and ocean floors</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3056267</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>McRee</name>
<date>19621000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>405191</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3466878</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Esquillan et al.</name>
<date>19690900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>405203</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4603748</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Rossfelder et al.</name>
<date>19860800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4693325</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bodine</name>
<date>19870900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5549168</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sadler et al.</name>
<date>19960800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5562169</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Barrow</name>
<date>19961000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5725329</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chelminski</name>
<date>19980300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>405232</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5771985</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jaworski</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5794716</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>White</name>
<date>19980800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6129487</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bermingham et al.</name>
<date>20001000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6345546</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Houze</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0053311</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Jones</name>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>405203</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00013">
<othercit>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three-phase<sub>—</sub>electric<sub>—</sub>power.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>405228</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1661776</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>173  1</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>173 49</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60586111</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040707</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060127186</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060615</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Raether</last-name>
<first-name>Roger</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sioux Falls</city>
<state>SD</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>The Webb Law Firm</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Under Pressure Systems, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>New Philadelphia</city>
<state>OH</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Mayo</last-name>
<first-name>Tara L.</first-name>
<department>3671</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention is a method for removing an obsolete drill platform that includes a body having a plurality of caissons embedded in a ground of an ocean or inland sea. The method includes the steps of vibrating at least one of the caissons, and lifting the at least one caisson from the ground while it is still being vibrated. The present invention is further directed to a method for installing a caisson on a floor of an ocean or inland. The method includes the steps of placing an end of the caisson on the floor, vibrating the caisson and forcing a portion of the caisson into the floor.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="152.65mm" wi="135.04mm" file="US07296949-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="262.30mm" wi="161.80mm" file="US07296949-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="219.79mm" wi="166.12mm" file="US07296949-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="264.24mm" wi="136.91mm" file="US07296949-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the benefit of U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 60/586,111, filed Jul. 7, 2004, entitled “Removal of Obsolete Drill Platforms from Inland Seas and Ocean Floors”, the disclosure of which is hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to the removal of obsolete drill platforms from inland seas and ocean floors.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Presently, drill platforms are used in oil and gas exploration in inland seas and ocean floors. After a period of time, the platforms become obsolete because gas and oil can no longer be extracted from the sea floor and ocean floor.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Several options currently exist for the removal of drill platforms after they have become obsolete. However, these options suffer from various drawbacks. First, a crane or other lifting device may be used to remove the caissons of a drill platform that were hammered into the soft mud or sand of the ocean floor. This method has achieved only very limited success and will not work with larger caissons.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Another method is to use explosives either above or below the mud line surrounding the caisson. While this method is both quick and inexpensive, it has a drastic, negative effect on marine life. The shock waves of such explosives tend to kill sensitive marine organisms and other living creatures. Furthermore, the byproduct residue from the explosions is detrimental to marine organisms and animals in the immediate area of the explosion as well as more distant areas.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">A third method of removal is for divers to use various cutting tools, such as cutting torches, high-pressure water with an abrasive assist and diamond chain saws, to remove the caissons. This method also has a variety of drawbacks. First, this type of removal is dangerous for the divers. Further, some of the abrasive assists used with a high-pressure water cutting device are not environmentally friendly. Finally, since the caissons cannot be cut below the mud line, jagged edges are left above or near the mud line which could endanger future recreational divers and any future undersea cables, pipelines or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A final method is to merely leave the platforms in place or modify them so a portion of the platform remains under water for the formation of a coral reef. This method is generally unacceptable or impossible. Furthermore, the United States Federal Government has recently instituted regulations for the removal of obsolete drill platforms. These new regulations have been implemented primarily because of environmental concerns. These regulations require the owner to take responsibility for all platforms in federal waters, the owner of a platform to remove the structure 15 feet below the mud line once it has become obsolete and obtain a permit to create an artificial reef.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Accordingly, a need exists for a method for removal of obsolete drill platforms that overcomes the drawbacks of the prior art methods for removal and conforms to the new United States Federal Government regulations.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The present invention is a method for removing an obsolete drill platform that includes a body having a plurality of caissons embedded in a ground of an ocean or inland sea. Specifically, the method includes the steps of vibrating at least one of the caissons, and lifting the at least one caisson from the ground while it is still being vibrated. The drill platforms include a drill deck attached to a plurality of caissons. The embedded portion of the caissons is surrounded by mud and/or sand. The step of vibrating causes liquefaction of the at least one of sand and mud. The at least one caisson can be vibrated at approximately 150 hertz or greater and, most desirably, at approximately 180 hertz.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The method may also include the step of attaching at least one vibrator to the at least one caisson prior to vibrating the at least one caisson. Three vibrators may be attached to the caisson and powered by a three-phase motor. The method may further include the step of lifting the at least one caisson with a crane and transporting it by boat.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The present invention is further directed to a method for installing a caisson on a floor of an ocean or inland. The method includes the steps of placing an end of the caisson on the floor, vibrating the caisson and forcing a portion of the caisson into the floor.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The present invention is also directed to an apparatus for removing an obsolete drill platform that includes a body having a plurality of caissons embedded in a ground of an ocean or inland sea. The apparatus includes at least one vibrator configured to be attached to one of the plurality of caissons, and a three-phase motor attached to the at least one vibrator for supplying power to the at least one vibrator. Desirably, three vibrators are attached to at least one of the plurality of caissons.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Further details and advantages of the present invention will become apparent upon reading the following detailed description in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side elevational view of a conventional drill platform attached to an inland sea or ocean floor;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a side elevational view of the conventional drill platform shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with the deck removed;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevational view of a plurality of caissons from a drill platform with vibrators attached thereto in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a side elevational view of a removed caisson being transported by a boat in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a top plan view of a support structure for attaching to caisson and holding a vibrator; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an exploded elevational view of the support structure shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The present invention will be described with reference to the accompanying figures where like reference numbers correspond to like elements.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an oil drill platform <b>10</b> includes a body <b>11</b> with a deck <b>12</b> having a plurality of caissons <b>14</b> attached thereto. Typically, caissons <b>14</b> are partially submerged in less than 200 ft. of water <b>16</b>. Caissons <b>14</b> are then embedded in the mud and/or sand that makes up a floor or ground <b>18</b> of an inland sea or ocean. Specifically, caissons <b>14</b> include three sections, a submerged portion <b>20</b>, an unsubmerged portion <b>22</b> and an embedded portion <b>24</b>. Each of the caissons <b>14</b> typically weighs approximately 600,000-800,000 lbs. However, this is not to be construed as limiting the present invention since it is envisioned that either heavier or lighter caissons <b>14</b> may be used.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and with continuing reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, at the time it is decided that oil drill platform <b>10</b> has become obsolete and must be removed, deck <b>12</b> and a portion of caissons <b>14</b> at section <b>22</b> are removed, so that only approximately 20 ft. of the caissons extends above water <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, one, non-limiting method of removing an obsolete drill platform according to the present invention includes attaching a plurality of vibrators <b>26</b><i>a</i>, <b>26</b><i>b </i>and <b>26</b><i>c </i>to caissons <b>14</b> at portion <b>22</b> of the caissons <b>14</b>. Typically, vibrators <b>26</b><i>a</i>-<b>26</b><i>c </i>vibrate at least approximately 150 hertz. At this high frequency, the mud and/or sand surrounding caissons <b>14</b> vibrate, causing liquid entrapped between the sand and/or mud to collect around caissons <b>14</b>, thereby reducing the strength and stiffness of the sand and/or mud surrounding caissons <b>14</b>. This process is referred to as liquefaction. Once liquefaction has occurred, caissons <b>14</b> may be easily removed.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">A typical vibrator for use with the present invention is a V-500 vibrator manufactured by FMC Technologies, Inc. Typically, these vibrators are adapted to vibrate at approximately 60 hertz along a vertical axis x. Vibrators <b>26</b><i>a</i>-<b>26</b><i>c </i>are connected to a three-phase motor <b>27</b> through wire cables CA and are triggered via diodes (not shown). Vibrators <b>26</b><i>a</i>-<b>26</b><i>c </i>are each driven by one of the phases of the motor <b>27</b> and are offset by 120°. This arrangement will result in each vibrator <b>26</b><i>a</i>-<b>26</b><i>c </i>operating at 60 hertz. However, the combined effect of vibrators <b>26</b><i>a</i>-<b>26</b><i>c </i>will vibrate each of the caissons <b>14</b> at 180 hertz. Alternatively, the vibration can be 150 hertz from a three-phase sine wave generator. The use of such vibrating configurations is not to be construed as limiting the present invention since it is envisioned that any type of triggering mechanism may be used to cause vibration. As caissons <b>14</b> are vibrated, liquefaction of the sand and/or mud of floor <b>18</b> will take place, thus allowing caissons <b>14</b> to be easily removed by cranes <b>30</b> mounted on boats <b>28</b>. Once caissons <b>14</b> are removed, cranes <b>30</b> may then lift them via cables <b>32</b> from floor <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and with continuing reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, once caissons <b>14</b> are lifted out of water <b>16</b>, they are laid on their sides and towed away by boot <b>28</b> via cables <b>32</b> so that they may either be reused or sold as scrap.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>, vibrators <b>26</b><i>a</i>-<b>26</b><i>c</i>, in the proposed operating frequency combinations, have the distinct possibility of causing an under-designed single steel weldment to fail because of metal fatigue. In order to prevent such a failure from occurring, the present invention includes several steel gussets B and C for each vibrator <b>26</b><i>a</i>-<b>26</b><i>c </i>welded to caisson <b>14</b> in concert with two large mounting rings D and E.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The mounting rings D and E also serve as an arrangement for distributing the vibrational force uniformly onto and into caisson <b>14</b>. The steel gussets B and C must be of sufficient mass and length prevent failure due to high frequency vibration.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Mounting plate F is welded to caisson <b>14</b> for installation. Hole G in the gusset weldment assembly is also used for installation. A lifting device is attached to mounting plate F and hole G to lift the weldment assembly in place.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The above process may be reversed, whereby liquefaction can be used to install caissons <b>14</b> on ocean or sea floor <b>18</b>. Specifically, each of caissons <b>14</b> is arranged such that an end of caisson <b>14</b> abuts floor <b>18</b>. Vibrators <b>26</b><i>a</i>-<b>26</b><i>c </i>are attached to caissons <b>14</b>, which are then attached to three-phase motor <b>27</b>. Caissons <b>14</b> are vibrated about the X axis at approximately 180 hertz (each vibrator <b>26</b> vibrates at 60 hertz 120° out of phase) so that liquefaction takes place. Caisson <b>14</b> is then forced into floor <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">While the present invention was described with reference to preferred embodiments of the method for removing an obsolete drill platform, those skilled in the art may make modifications and alterations to the present invention without departing from the scope and spirit of the present invention. Accordingly, the above detailed description is intended to be illustrative rather than restrictive. The invention is defined by the appended claims, and all changes to the invention that fall within the meaning and range of equivalency of the claims are to be embraced by their scope.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for removing an obsolete drill platform that includes a body having a plurality of caissons embedded in a ground of an ocean or inland sea, the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>attaching at least three vibrators directly to each one of the caissons, the three vibrators are positioned offset by 120°;</claim-text>
<claim-text>driving a first vibrator with a first phase of a three-phase generator, driving a second vibrator with a second phase of the three-phase generator and driving a third vibrator with a third phase of the three-phase generator thereby vibrating each of the caissons; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>lifting each of the caissons from the ground while it is still being vibrated.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the ground of the ocean or inland sea is made up of at least one of sand and mud.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the vibrating causes liquefaction of at least one of sand or mud.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein each of the caissons are vibrated at approximately 150 hertz or greater.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein each of the caissons are vibrated at approximately 180 hertz.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of lifting each of the caissons with a crane.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of transporting at least one caisson that has been lifted by a boat.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A method for installing a caisson on a floor of an ocean or inland sea comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>placing an end of the caisson on the floor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>attaching at least three vibrators directly to the caisson, the three vibrators are positioned offset by 120°;</claim-text>
<claim-text>driving a first vibrator with a first phase of a three-phase generator, driving a second vibrator with a second phase of the three-phase generator and driving a third vibrator with a third phase of the three-phase generator thereby vibrating the caisson; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forcing a portion of the caisson into the floor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An apparatus for removing an obsolete drill platform that includes a body having a plurality of caissons embedded in a ground of an ocean or inland sea, the apparatus comprising;
<claim-text>at least three vibrators attached directly to one of the plurality of caissons, the three vibrators are positioned offset by 120°; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a three-phase generator attached to each of the three vibrators for driving a first vibrator with a first phase of the three-phase generator, driving a second vibrator with a second phase of the three-phase generator and driving a third vibrator with a third phase of the three-phase generator thereby.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
