<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297322-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297322</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11076948</doc-number>
<date>20050311</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-082629</doc-number>
<date>20040322</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>209</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4235931</main-classification>
<further-classification>4235948</further-classification>
<further-classification>42359415</further-classification>
<further-classification>423598</further-classification>
<further-classification>42359416</further-classification>
<further-classification>4235949</further-classification>
<further-classification>4235947</further-classification>
<further-classification>501134</further-classification>
<further-classification>501135</further-classification>
<further-classification>501136</further-classification>
<further-classification>501137</further-classification>
<further-classification>502525</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Process and apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen, and the powders produced by the process</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3362784</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Aykan</name>
<date>19680100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>423598</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4765920</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gattuso et al.</name>
<date>19880800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>252 6258</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4777031</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Senecal et al.</name>
<date>19881000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>423632</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6793842</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Akimoto et al.</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>252 6256</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0143153</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Boulos et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4235921</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0118094</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Zhang</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4235921</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>6</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4235921</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4235931</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4235948</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>42359415</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>423598</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>42359416</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4235949</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4235947</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>501134</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>501135</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>501136</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>501137</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>502525</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050204514</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050922</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Takamatsu</last-name>
<first-name>Yukichi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kiriyama</last-name>
<first-name>Koji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Asano</last-name>
<first-name>Akira</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ishii</last-name>
<first-name>Takafumi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Antonelli, Terry, Stout &amp; Kraus, LLP.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Japan Pionics Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Vanoy</last-name>
<first-name>Timothy C.</first-name>
<department>1754</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A process for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen including the steps of: feeding at least one material selected from a liquid material and a solution material obtained by dissolving solid ingredient in organic solvent via a liquid flow controller into a vaporizer; vaporizing the materials in the vaporizer; adding oxygen; heating; cooling; and crystallizing. Also disclosed is the product formed by this process, and apparatus used in performing the process. The process and the apparatus enable easily mass-producing fine powders of metal compound containing oxygen used as materials for optical crystals, nonlinear crystals or magneto-optical crystals with reasonable production cost.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="249.85mm" wi="163.41mm" file="US07297322-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="226.40mm" wi="155.02mm" file="US07297322-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="225.13mm" wi="157.82mm" file="US07297322-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="259.16mm" wi="154.01mm" file="US07297322-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to an apparatus and a process for efficiently producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen that are used as ingredient of optical crystal, nonlinear crystal or magneto-optical crystal. The present invention also relates to the fine powders of metal compound containing oxygen produced by the process at low cost.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In the field of semi-conductive crystal, powders of metal compound containing oxygen such as lithium niobate, niobic acid tantalum or barium titanate is employed as material of optical crystal; powders of metal compound containing oxygen such as bismuthic acid barium, bismuthic acid silicon or bismuthic acid germanium is employed as material of nonlinear crystal; and powders of metal compound containing oxygen such as lithium niobate or lithium tantalate is employed as material of magneto-optical crystal. For example, lithium niobate is known as a transparent crystal without rendering color or tinted with pale yellow, and as revealing ferroelectricity. Also, surface acoustic wave devices, Q-switches, optical modulators, optical switches and so on that took advantages of electro-optic effect, nonlinear optical effect, ultrasonic propagation, piezoelectric effect, etc. as the characteristics of lithium niobates are put into practical use.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Conventionally, the powders of metal compound containing oxygen are produced in general by sol gel method, sintering method or sputtering method. Japanese Unexamined Patent Application Laid-Open Nos. Hei 5-9023, Hei 7-21831, Hei 9-208227, 2000-113898 and 2002-356326 disclose the sol-gel method, in which, for example, the powders of metal compound containing oxygen are obtained by dissolving several kinds of metal alkoxide in amine, hydrolyzing and adding a precipitant, thereafter drying precipitation. Japanese Unexamined Patent Application Laid-Open No. Hei 10-338524, for example, discloses the sintering method, in which the powders of metal compound containing oxygen are obtained by mixing several kinds of metal oxide and sintering the resultant mixture. Further, Japanese Unexamined Patent Application Laid-Open No. Hei 8-277467 discloses the sputtering method, in which the powders of metal compound containing oxygen are obtained after repeating the sintering and crushing the sintered objects several times, hot pressing and sputtering the sintered objects with aiming them as a target.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">However, it was difficult for the sol gel method to produce fine powders of metal compound containing oxygen. Further, although the sintering method and the sputtering method enable to produce fine powders of metal compound containing oxygen, they had disadvantages that the production cost was expensive. Furthermore, all the foregoing conventional methods had impropriety that they are not suitable for mass production.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Therefore, an object of the present invention is to provide a process and an apparatus for easily mass-producing fine powders of metal compound containing oxygen used as materials for optical crystals, nonlinear crystals or magneto-optical crystals with reasonable production cost.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As a result of intensive extensive research and investigation made by the present inventors in order to achieve the object, it has been found that the generation of the powders of metal compound containing oxygen by a gas phase crystal growth enable to easily mass-produce fine powders of metal compound containing oxygen with reasonable cost; and the present invention was completed.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Accordingly, the present invention provides an apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen comprising a liquid flow controller, a vaporizer and a reactor, which consists essentially of: means for feeding a gas containing a material and oxygen; means for heating the gas from the side surface of the feeding means; means for cooling the gas positioned at the downstream side of the feeding means; and means for receiving the product generated by the reaction.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Also, the present invention provides a process for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen comprising the steps of: feeding at least one material selected from a liquid material and a solution material obtained by dissolving solid ingredient in organic solvent via a liquid flow controller into a vaporizer, vaporizing the materials in the vaporizer; adding oxygen; heating; cooling; and crystallizing</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram illustrating one embodiment of an apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block-diagram illustrating another embodiment of the apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a vertical cross-sectional view illustrating one embodiment of a vaporizer employed for the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a vertical cross-sectional view illustrating one embodiment of a horizontal reactor employed for the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a vertical cross-sectional view illustrating another embodiment of a horizontal reactor aside from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> employed for the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a vertical cross-sectional view illustrating another embodiment of a horizontal reactor aside from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> employed for the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a vertical cross-sectional view illustrating still another embodiment of a horizontal reactor aside from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref> to <b>6</b> employed for the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a vertical cross-sectional view illustrating one embodiment of vertical reactor employed for the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">PREFERRED EMBODIMENT OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The present invention is applied to the process and the apparatus for producing the powders of metal compound containing oxygen used as the materials for optical crystals, nonlinear crystals or magneto-optical crystals, however, it is preferably applied to produce, in particular, the powders of metal compound containing oxygen having ferroelectricity, and to produce powders of metal compound containing oxygen having perovskite structure. Namely, both the powders of metal compound containing oxygen having the ferroelectricity and the powders of metal compound containing oxygen having perovskite structure each produced in accordance with the present invention exhibit minuteness and excellent quality without requiring expensive production costs.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Examples of the powders of metal compound containing oxygen in the present invention include, but not limited to, lithium niobate, lithium tantalate, barium titanate, lead titanate, niobic acid tantalum, bismuthic acid barium, bismuthic acid silicon, bismuthic acid germanium, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">A liquid material or a solution material prepared by dissolving a solid ingredient in organic solvent are employed as the material for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen in the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">An example of the liquid material containing silicon is tetra ethoxy silicon (Si(OC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>4</sub>).</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Examples of the solid ingredient containing niobium include penta etoxyniobium (Nb(OC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>5</sub>) or so. Examples of the solid ingredient containing lithium include (2,2,6,6-tetramethyl-3,5-heptanedionite) lithium (Li (DPM)) or so. Typical examples of the solid ingredient containing tantalum include penta etoxytantalum (Ta(OC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>5</sub>), pentadimethylaminotantalum (Ta(N(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>), pentadiethylaminotantalum (Ta(N(C<sub>2</sub>H5)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>5</sub>), (di-isopropoxy) tris (2,2,6,6-tetramethyl-3,5-heptanedionite) tantalum (Ta(OiPr)<sub>2</sub>(DPM)<sub>3</sub>), etc.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Further, typical examples of the solid ingredient containing titanium include tetra iso-propoxytitanium (Ti(OCH(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>4</sub>), tetra n-propoxytitanium (Ti(OC<sub>3</sub>H<sub>7</sub>)<sub>4</sub>), tetra dimethylaminotitanium (Ti(N(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>4</sub>), tetra diethylaminotitanium (Ti(N(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>)<sub>4</sub>), tetra (2,2,6,6,-tetramethyl-3,5heptanedionite) titanium (Ti(DPM)<sub>4</sub>), (di-tertiarybuthoxy) bis(2,2,6,6-tetramethyl-3,5-heptanedionite) titanium (Ti(OtBu)<sub>2</sub>(DPM)<sub>2</sub>), (di-isopropoxy) bis(2,2,6,6,-tetramethyl-3,5,-heptanedionite) titanium (Ti(OiPr)<sub>2</sub>(DPM)<sub>2</sub>), etc.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Still further, examples of the solid ingredient containing barium include bis(2,2,6,6,-tetramethyl-3,5heptanedionite) barium (Ba(DPM)<sub>2</sub>) or so. Examples of the solid ingredient containing lead include bis(2,2,6,6,-tetramethyl-3,5heptanedionite) lead (Pb(DPM)<sub>2</sub>) or so. Furthermore, typical examples of the solid ingredient containing bismuth include bismuth (III) tertiarybthoxy (Bi(OtBu)<sub>3</sub>), bismuth (III) tertialeabentoxyd (Bi(OtAm)<sub>3</sub>), triphenyl bismuth (BiPh<sub>3</sub>), etc.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Moreover, examples of the solid ingredient containing germane include tetra ethoxy germanium (Ge(OC<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>4</sub>) or so.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">However, it is necessary that these solid ingredients are usually dissolved in organic solvent with concentration of about 0.1 to 1.0 mol/litter and then be employed as the solution material.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The above-mentioned organic solvent to be used as a solvent for a solid ingredient is that having a boiling point usually ranging from 40° C. to 140° C. at an ordinary pressure. Examples of the solvent include such ethers as propyl ether, methylbutyl ether, ethylpropyl ether, ethylbutyl ether, trimethylene oxide, tetrahydrofuran and tetrahydropyran; alcohols such as methyl alcohol, ethyl alcohol, propyl alcohol and butyl alcohol; ketones such as acetone, ethyl methyl ketone, isopropyl methyl ketone and isobutyl methyl ketone; amines such as propylamine, butylamine, diethylamine, dipropylamine and triethylamine; esters such as ethyl acetate, propyl acetate and butyl acetate; and hydrocarbons such as hexane, heptane and octane.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In the following, detailed description will be given of the apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen according to the present invention with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, which however shall never limit the present invention thereto.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> are blocks diagram illustrating embodiments of the apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen in accordance with the present invention; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a vertical cross-sectional view illustrating one embodiment of a vaporizer employed for the present invention; and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 to 8</figref> are vertical cross-sectional view illustrating embodiments of the reactor employed for the present invention, wherein <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 to 7</figref> illustrate horizontal reactors and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a vertical reactor.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> respectively, the apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen in accordance with the present invention comprises a liquid flow controller <b>5</b>, a vaporizer <b>6</b> and a reactor <b>12</b> that reacts the vaporized material and oxygen while heating, cooling, and crystallizing. However, it usually further comprises an inert gas supply line <b>1</b>, a degasser <b>4</b>, a heat insulating material <b>7</b>, a gas mass flow controller <b>8</b>, a gas preheater <b>9</b>, a carrier gas supply line <b>10</b>, an oxygen supply line <b>11</b>, a gas mixer <b>13</b> and so on; and in the case of producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen, a material container <b>3</b> filled with the liquid material <b>2</b> or the solution material <b>2</b> is connected.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">As the liquid flow controller <b>5</b> in the present invention, a liquid mass flow controller is usually employed.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Furthermore, although the vaporizer employed in the present invention is not particularly specified, for example, a vaporizer with the material feed portion <b>15</b> whose interior comprises a corrosion resistant synthetic resin <b>18</b> such as fluorocarbon polymers, polyimide-based resin or so, a vaporizer with an ejection tube of double structure consisting of an inner tube for a liquid material or a solution material and an outer tube for a carrier gas as the ejection tube <b>19</b> for ejecting and vaporizing the liquid material or the solution material to a vaporizing chamber <b>14</b>, or a vaporizer having means <b>20</b> for flowing cooling water around the outside surface of the material feed portion are exemplified each as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Still further, reference numeral <b>16</b> expresses an exhaust slot for the vaporized gas and reference numeral <b>17</b> expresses heaters in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Not only a vaporizer vaporizing one kind of material, but also a vaporizer simultaneously vaporizing two kinds or more materials is employable in the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The reactor used for the present invention consists essentially of means for feeding a gas containing a material and oxygen, means for heating the gas, means for cooling the gas and means for receiving the product. That is, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 to 8</figref>, the reactor consists of a gas feeding inlet <b>21</b>, passageway <b>22</b> as the feeding means for a vaporized gas containing materials and oxygen, a heater <b>23</b> for heating the gas from the side of the passageway <b>22</b> as the heating means, the cooling means (<b>27</b>-<b>30</b>) to cool the gas at downstream side of the passageway <b>22</b>, a reservoir <b>25</b> as the receiving means for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen as the product and exhaust outlet <b>26</b> of the gas. The passageway <b>22</b> is surrounded by a cylindrical wall or a rectangular wall, the surface of which is respectively formed preferably with a quartz plate or a quartz layer <b>24</b> in order to prevent adhesion of the product generated by the reaction between the material and oxygen.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Further, examples of the foregoing cooling means include a cooling plate <b>28</b> provided adjacent a cooling pipe <b>27</b> in which a coolant such as cooling water flows as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 8</figref>, a coolant supplying pipe <b>29</b> conveying cooling gas such as an inert gas or so as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> and a cooling pipe <b>27</b> in which a coolant such as cooling water flows as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. In the case where the cooling plate is employed as the cooling means, partitions <b>30</b> for extending the gas passageway may be provided together with the cooling pipe <b>27</b> in which the coolant flows as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, aiming for increasing the amount of the powders of metal compound containing oxygen as the product. Additionally, a coolant supply pipe or a cooling pipe may be employed as the cooling means other than the cooling plate shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> for the vertical reactor. Moreover, the reacting means under heating and the cooling means may be separated into different devices in the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The present invention provides a process for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen usually with the use of the foregoing apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen. In other words, the present invention provides a process for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen comprising the steps of: feeding at least one material selected from a liquid material and a solution material obtained by dissolving solid ingredient in organic solvent via a liquid flow controller into a vaporizer; vaporizing the materials in the vaporizer; adding oxygen; heating; cooling; and crystallizing.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In the present invention, after setting the material container <b>3</b> filled with the material as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> or <b>2</b>, for example, the solution material or the liquid material is introduced into the liquid mass flow controller <b>5</b> via the degasser <b>4</b> as the effect of pressuring with an inert gas onto the material container <b>3</b>, is further supplied to the vaporizer <b>6</b>, and resultantly is vaporized there.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Further in the present invention, before or soon after the gas containing vaporized material is supplied into the reactor, oxygen or a gas containing oxygen will be added. The gas containing material and oxygen is heated by a heater in the reactor to the temperature of about 300 to 1000° C. usually, and the metal compound containing oxygen generates. Regarding with the pressure of the gas, although the reaction may be carried out under the reduced pressure of 0.1 kPa (absolute pressure) or under the compressed pressure of 2 MPa (absolute pressure), without being specified, it is usually the same as the pressure in the vaporizer.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Then, the gas is cooled by the foregoing cooling means provided to the reactor, and metal compounds containing oxygen among the gas are crystallized to powders. In the present invention, the temperature of the gas after being cooled is usually within the range from the liquefaction temperature of the organic solvent to around 200° C. when the organic solvent is present, and usually within the range from 20° C. to around 200° C. when the organic solvent is absent. The powders of the metal compound containing oxygen that crystallized by cooling of the gas will fall over the reservoir as the receiving means for the powders as the product and will be collected after the completion of the production.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">This invention will be described in further detail with reference to EXAMPLES, which does not limit the scope of this invention.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">EXAMPLES</heading>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Example 1</heading>
<p id="h-0008" num="0000">(Fabrication of Vaporizer)</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">There was prepared a material feed portion <b>15</b> in which the inside thereof was constituted of a fluorocarbon polymers (PFA: a polymer of tetrafluoroethylene and perfluorovinylether) <b>18</b>, and the portion in contact with the outside of the vaporizer was constituted of stainless steel (SUS316). The PFA made portion was a column having an outside diameter of 16 mm and a height of 34.2 mm. The stainless steel outside the column had a thickness of 2.0 mm. Further, an ejection tube with double structure at front end having an internal tube corresponding to a passageway for the material, and an outer tube corresponding to a passageway for a carrier gas was provided separately in two sets. Additionally, a cooling pipe that provides cooling water along the side surface of the material feed portion was equipped as a cooling means for the material feed portion.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">There was also prepared, in addition to the foregoing material feed portion <b>15</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a vaporizer which was made of stainless steel (SUS316) and incorporated with a vaporized gas exhaust slot <b>16</b> and a heater <b>17</b>. The vaporizer had two ejection tubes connecting with a vaporizing chamber. The vaporization chamber <b>14</b> was in the form of a column having an inside diameter of 65 mm and a height of 92.5 mm and a protrusion height at the bottom of 27.5 mm. The vaporized gas exhaust port was placed at a height of 15 mm from the bottom of the vaporizer.</p>
<p id="h-0009" num="0000">(Fabrication of Reactor)</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">A reactor made of stainless steel (SUS316) was fabricated as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The reactor had the internal sizes of 600 mm in breadth, 300 mm in length and 250 mm in height; the passageway <b>22</b> for the gas containing material and oxygen had an inside diameter of 18 mm, and a length of 170 mm; and the reservoir for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen had the sizes of 200 mm in breadth, 200 mm in length and 50 mm in height. Further, a quartz plate having a thickness of 1.2 mm was attached to the side surface of the passageway for the gas. Furthermore, the cooling means for the gas were provided by placing the cooling plate <b>28</b> over the reservoir for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen in a manner entirely covering the upper face (angle of inclination: 15 degrees), and by placing the cooling pipe connecting to cooling line for flowing water and to a temperature controller further over the cooling plate.</p>
<p id="h-0010" num="0000">(Fabrication of Apparatus for Producing Powders of Metal Compound Containing Oxygen)</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Subsequently, an apparatus for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> was fabricated by connecting the foregoing vaporizer and reactor with a degasser, a liquid mass flow controller, a carrier gas supply line, an oxygen supply line and so on. Further, the oxygen supply line was settled so as to add oxygen just before the reactor.</p>
<p id="h-0011" num="0000">(Production of Powders of Metal Compound Containing Oxygen)</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">A material container filled with the solution material (concentration: 0.3 mol/L) prepared by dissolving Ti(OiPr)<sub>2</sub>(DPM)<sub>2 </sub>in THF solvent and a material container filled with the solution material (concentration: 0.3 mol/L) prepared by dissolving Ba(DPM)<sub>2 </sub>in THF solvent were settled to the above production apparatus, and the production of barium titanate powders was carried out.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The vaporization chamber was set on 1.3 kPa (10 torr) and at the temperature of 270° C., the solution material in which Ti(OiPr)<sub>2</sub>(DPM)<sub>2 </sub>as a solid material dissolved in THF as a solvent and the solution material in which Ba(DPM)<sub>2 </sub>as a solid material dissolved in THF as a solvent were fed at a flow rate of 0.5 g/min and 0.6 g/min respectively and further nitrogen gas was supplied at a flow rate of 600 milliliter/min, and then the solution material was vaporized in the chamber. During the foregoing process, cooling water was supplied to maintain the temperature of the stainless steel part on the side surface of the material feed portion at 30±2° C.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">On the other hand, the internal pressure of the reactor was set on 1.3 kPa, the side temperature of the passageway <b>22</b> of gas containing the material and oxygen was set at 600° C., and cooling water was supplied to maintain the temperature of the gas being discharged from the exhaust outlet <b>26</b> of the gas within 75±2° C. At the same time, oxygen heated at 270° C. was added to the gas containing the vaporized material with the flow rate of 2000 milliliter/min just before the reactor.</p>
<p id="h-0012" num="0000">(Evaluation of Powders of Metal Compound Containing Oxygen)</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">A crystallized particle size measurement with the use of a scanning electron microscope (SEM) and a composition analysis with the use of a X-ray Fluorescence Spectroscopy (XRF) about the resultant powders of barium titanate were carried out. As a result, the crystallized particle sizes were within the range of 0.01 to 0.1 μm, and the composition was recognized that Ti atom was 0.95 to 1.05 per Ba atom.</p>
<heading id="h-0013" level="1">Example 2</heading>
<p id="h-0014" num="0000">(Fabrication of Reactor)</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">A reactor made of stainless steel (SUS316) was fabricated as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The reactor had the internal sizes of 600 mm in breadth, 300 mm in length and 250 mm in height; the passageway <b>22</b> for the gas containing material and oxygen had an inside diameter of 18 mm, and a length of 170 mm; and the reservoir for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen had the sizes of 200 mm in breadth, 200 mm in length and 50 mm in height. Further, a quartz plate having a thickness of 1.2 mm was attached to the side surface of the passageway for the gas. Furthermore, the cooling means for the gas were provided by placing 20 units of the coolant (nitrogen) supplying pipe <b>29</b> with an inner diameter of 10 mm over the reservoir for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen in a manner entirely covering the upper face.</p>
<p id="h-0015" num="0000">(Production and Evaluation of Powders of Metal Compound Containing Oxygen)</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The production of barium titanate powders was carried out in a similar manner as Example 1 except that the above reactor was employed. As a result of the evaluation about the resultant powders of barium titanate in the same manner as Example 1, the crystallized particle sizes were within the range of 0.01 to 0.1 μm, and the composition was recognized that Ti atom was 0.96 to 1.05 per Ba atom.</p>
<heading id="h-0016" level="1">Example 3</heading>
<p id="h-0017" num="0000">(Fabrication of Reactor)</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">A reactor made of stainless steel (SUS316) was fabricated as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The reactor had the internal sizes of 600 mm in breadth, 300 mm in length and 250 mm in height; the passageway <b>22</b> for the gas containing material and oxygen had an inside diameter of 18 mm, and a length of 170 mm; and the reservoir for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen had the sizes of 200 mm in breadth, 200 mm in length and 50 mm in height. Further, a quartz plate having a thickness of 1.2 mm was attached to the side surface of the passageway for the gas. Furthermore, the cooling means for the gas were provided by placing the cooling pipe <b>27</b> with an inner diameter of 6.5 mm connected to the cooling line and the temperature controller and further flowing water as the coolant over the reservoir for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen in a manner entirely covering the upper face.</p>
<p id="h-0018" num="0000">(Production and Evaluation of Powders of Metal Compound Containing Oxygen)</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The production of barium titanate powders was carried out in a similar manner as Example 1 except that the above reactor was employed. As a result of the evaluation about the resultant powders of barium titanate in the same manner as Example 1, the crystallized particle sizes were within the range of 0.01 to 0.1 μm, and the composition was recognized that Ti atom was 0.95 to 1.04 per Ba atom.</p>
<heading id="h-0019" level="1">Example 4</heading>
<p id="h-0020" num="0000">(Fabrication of Reactor)</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">A reactor made of stainless steel (SUS316) was fabricated as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The reactor had the internal sizes of 600 mm in breadth, 300 mm in length and 350 mm in height; the passageway <b>22</b> for the gas containing material and oxygen had an inside diameter of 18 mm, and a length of 170 mm; and the reservoir for the powders of metal compound containing oxygen had the sizes of 200 mm in breadth, 200 mm in length and 50 mm in height. Further, a quartz plate having a thickness of 1.2 mm was attached to the side surface of the passageway for the gas. Furthermore, the cooling means for the gas were provided by placing 3 pieces of the cooling plate <b>30</b> inside of which cooling water flows and having the size of 10 mm in breadth, 290 mm in length and 250 mm in height; and placing 2 pieces of the partition having the size of 5 mm in breadth, 290 mm in length and 250 mm in height with the same spaces.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">(Production and Evaluation of Powders of Metal Compound Containing Oxygen) The production of barium titanate powders was carried out in a similar manner as Example 1 except that the above reactor was employed. As a result of the evaluation about the resultant powders of barium titanate in the same manner as Example 1, the crystallized particle sizes were within the range of 0.01 to 0.1 μm, and the composition was recognized that Ti atom was 0.95 to 1.05 per Ba atom.</p>
<heading id="h-0021" level="1">INDUSTRIAL APPLICABILITY</heading>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In the present invention, it is easy to control the size or so of the powders of metal compound containing oxygen by adjusting the condition such as the concentration or the feed amount of material or oxygen contained in the gas introduced to the reactor, heating temperature, cooling method, cooling temperature and so on. Further, the present invention enables to continuously produce the powders of metal compound containing oxygen with the use of the liquid material of high purity, the solution material prepared by dissolving solid ingredients of high purity in organic solvent. Accordingly, as described in Examples, it became possible to easily mass-produce the fine powders of metal compound containing oxygen as well as reducing the production cost.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">While there has been shown and described what are at present considered the preferred embodiments of the invention, it will be obvious to those skilled in the art that various changes and modification may be made therein without departing from the scope of the invention defined by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A process for producing powders of metal compound containing oxygen and having perovskite structure, comprising the sequential steps of:
<claim-text>feeding at least one material selected from a liquid material and a solution material obtained by dissolving solid ingredient in organic solvent via a liquid flow controller into a vaporizer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>vaporizing the materials in the vaporizer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>adding oxygen;</claim-text>
<claim-text>heating;</claim-text>
<claim-text>cooling; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>crystallizing, forming said perovskite structure.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The process according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein in the step of heating, said at least one material is reacted with oxygen, forming said metal compound containing oxygen.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The process according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said at least one material includes ingredients included in said metal compound containing oxygen.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The process according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said at least one material includes said liquid material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The process according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said at least one material includes said solution material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The process according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said solid ingredient is dissolved in said organic solvent in an amount of about 0.1 to 1.0 mol/liter.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
