<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296907-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296907</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10550370</doc-number>
<date>20040907</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>IT</country>
<doc-number>FI2003A0235</doc-number>
<date>20030910</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>161</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>21</class>
<subclass>V</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362147</main-classification>
<further-classification>362145</further-classification>
<further-classification>362364</further-classification>
<further-classification>362365</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Lighting fixture</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5045984</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Trowbridge et al.</name>
<date>19910900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362365</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6164802</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gromotka</name>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362375</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0012017</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Reggiani</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362148</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>0845633</doc-number>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>FR</country>
<doc-number>2638815</doc-number>
<date>19901100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362145</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362147</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362148</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362150</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362254</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362364</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362365</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362640</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060176705</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060810</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Targetti</last-name>
<first-name>Giampaolo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Florence</city>
<country>IT</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>IT</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>IT</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Pollack, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Targetti Sankey S.p.A.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Florence</city>
<country>IT</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Tso</last-name>
<first-name>Laura</first-name>
<department>2875</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/IT2004/000480</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040907</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20050919</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2005/024297</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20050317</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A recessed lighting fixture with a device for quickly mounting or dismounting the lamp is disclosed. The device comprises an annular body having a front edge defining an aperture with dimensions generally greater than the diameter of the lamp. Flexible retaining members extend radially from the front edge at the aperture, suitable for holding the body at the lamp laterally. At least a pair of radial projections extend internally from the edge and define a span having a width generally smaller than the diameter of the lamp, such that the edge rests against the radial projections and is biased against them by the flexible retaining members.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="67.23mm" wi="96.52mm" file="US07296907-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="202.69mm" wi="122.94mm" file="US07296907-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to lighting arrangements and, more particularly, to fixtures for lighting and the like.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">With conventional lighting fixtures intended to be recessed in support panels, such as those used to form a ceiling or partition wall, appropriate devices must often be provided to allow access to the lamp so as to facilitate its mounting to and detachment from the ceiling or wall. In some cases, rings are used for this purpose. Specifically, the rings are fastened by screws to a support structure on which the edge of the lamp rests. In other arrangements, elastic rings of the open type are inserted in a seat of the lamp to prevent the lamp from falling out. In this regard, two small adjacent arms are typically provided, which extend perpendicularly from the ring openings, and are adjusted in order to remove the lamp. Still other devices utilize elastic thread-like elements with internally projecting protuberances on which the edge of the lamp rests.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Although useful, these lighting arrangements are considered unattractive and, therefore, generally unacceptable for this purpose. Accordingly, a system is desired for rapid assembly and disassembly of a lamp in a recessed lighting fixture which not only meets traditional requirements of good service, but also has an aesthetically pleasing appearance.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">OBJECTS AND SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Accordingly, it is an object of the present invention to provide a lighting fixture of the recessed type, that includes a system for rapid assembly and/or disassembly of a lamp so as to facilitate maintenance of the fixture, without impairing the fixture's appearance.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Another object of the present invention is to provide a recessed lighting fixture in which the lamp can be readily disassembled by applying light, eccentric pressure to a selected glass surface of the lamp without the necessity of removing a locking element.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A further object of the present invention is to provide a lighting fixture of the recessed type that can be easily assembled without tools.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to one aspect of the present invention, a recessed lighting fixture is provided having a system for quick mounting and dismounting of a lamp. The fixture comprises: an annular body with a front edge defining an aperture having dimensions larger than the diameter of the lamp; a flexible retaining member extending radially from the edge at the aperture suitable for holding the body of the lamp laterally; and at least one pair of radial projections extending internally from the edge and defining a span having a width smaller than the diameter of the lamp.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In this manner, the lamp may be firmly locked in a desired position in the lighting fixture between the radial projections on which the fixture and its edge rests, with the flexible retaining member forcing it against the projections. Moreover, a relatively light amount of pressure applied eccentrically to a selected glass surface of the lamp is all that is needed to remove the lamp from the fixture. Conversely, with equally simple operation, i.e., slight tilting and pressure against the flexible retaining member, the lamp may be readily positioned in the fixture.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A specific, illustrative lighting fixture, according to the present invention, is described below with reference to the following drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side view of a device for quickly mounting and/or dismounting a lamp of a lighting fixture, according to one aspect of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a plan view of the device shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The same numerals are used throughout the drawing figures to designate similar elements. Still other objects and advantages of the present invention will become apparent from the following description of the preferred embodiments.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Referring now to the drawings and, more particularly, to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-2</figref>, there is shown generally a specific, illustrative, recessed-type lighting fixture with a device for mounting and/or dismounting a lamp, in accordance with various aspects of the present invention. According to one embodiment, shown generally in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the lighting fixture has an annular body <b>1</b> shaped so as to be housed in a seat of appropriate shape (not shown) that can be attached to the panel in which the fixture is to be recessed. Preferably, the annular body has a curved perimeter profile and the seat in which it is engaged is shaped correspondingly, so as to be mobile inside the seat and, more specifically, tiltable relative to an axis perpendicular to the panel in which the fixture rests. As illustrated, annular body <b>1</b> is formed by an external wall <b>2</b>, substantially tapered and having a rounded profile, and an internal wall <b>3</b> extending coaxially from one end of the external wall and defining a circular groove <b>4</b> therewith. The internal wall has a front edge <b>5</b> that defines an aperture <b>7</b> in which a lamp <b>8</b> is placed, such being designated by a narrow line in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A plurality diametrically opposed uprights <b>6</b>, preferably at least one pair, are desirably provided which rise from front edge <b>5</b> with two projections <b>9</b> extending generally internally from the same edge, substantially at a 90° angle relative to the uprights. It is also desired that the diameter of aperture <b>7</b>, defined by the front edge, be slightly larger than the diameter of lamp <b>8</b>, while the span defined by projections <b>9</b> is slightly smaller than the lamp diameter.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">It is preferred that the two uprights support two relatively flexible and substantially fork-shaped plate members or elements <b>10</b>, <b>11</b>. In particular, each plate element desirably comprises a base <b>10</b><i>a</i>, <b>11</b><i>a </i>and a pair of wide apart arms <b>10</b><i>b</i>. The respective bases <b>10</b><i>a</i>, <b>11</b><i>a </i>(of the plate elements <b>10</b>, <b>11</b>) are then joined to the uprights in any known manner, for example by screws, adhesives or clamping, while arms <b>10</b><i>b</i>, <b>11</b><i>b </i>extend diametrically towards one another.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Under normal operating conditions, according to one aspect of the present invention, the lamp rests with its front edge on the two radial projections and is pressed against them by wide apart arms <b>10</b><i>b</i>, <b>11</b><i>b </i>acting generally sideways thereon, such that the lamp is locked relatively firmly inside the annular body. This is shown, for instance, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> which illustrates, by a dotted line, a plan profile of the lamp as it rests on the radial projections.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">When disassembly/dismounting of the lamp <b>8</b> is desired, it is sufficient to exert a relatively light amount of pressure eccentrically on and relative to a selected glass surface of the lamp, preferably in proximity to one of the radial projections, so as to disengage the lamp from the other radial projection and, thereby, cause its release from annular body. Notably in this regard, the diameter of the lamp is slightly smaller than the diameter of aperture <b>7</b> defined by edge <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Conversely, when the lamp is being mounted to the fixture, it is considered sufficient to perform the above-described operation in reverse, namely, by first inserting the lamp in the aperture, while making sure that the lamp is held at a slightly tilted orientation so that it can be readily engaged, first on one and then on the other of the two radial projections and, at the same time, exerting a slight amount of pressure to permit bending of arms <b>10</b><i>b</i>, <b>11</b><i>b </i>to a sufficient extent as to allow tilted insertion of the lamp.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In order to allow the lamp to be oriented in multiple directions, the uprights may also be formed with a pin engaged in a slotted guide. Arrangements of this general description are known by those skilled in the art and further description is considered unnecessary for purposes of illustrating the present invention. Alternatively or concurrently, the uprights may simply be formed integrally with the seat for housing the annular body such that the lamp is fixed.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Although the flexible laminar elements <b>10</b>, <b>11</b> have been shown and described as having a fork-shaped configuration, other arrangements may be utilized, giving consideration to the purpose for which the present invention is intended. Generally speaking, the flexible retaining member can take any shape suitable for ensuring that the elastic forces applied to the sides of the lamp which can be readily overcome upon applying a moderate yet sufficient force, pressing the lamp against radial projections <b>9</b>, and firmly holding the lamp in a selected position of use.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Various modifications and alterations may be appreciated based on a review of this disclosure. These changes and additions are intended to be within the scope and spirit of the invention as defined by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A recessed type lighting fixture having a device for removably mounting a lamp, which comprises:
<claim-text>an annular body with a front edge defining an aperture having a diameter generally larger than that of the lamp;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a flexible retaining member extending radially from the edge at the aperture, suitable for holding the body of the lamp laterally; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one pair of radial projections extending internally from the edge and defining a span having a width generally smaller than the diameter of the lamp, such that the edge rests against the projections, the flexible retaining members biasing the edge against the projections.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The lighting fixture set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein two diametrically opposed uprights extend from the edge to where the flexible retaining member is attached.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The lighting fixture set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the flexible retaining member comprises a pair of fork-shaped plate elements, each being formed by a base, integral to the edge, and a pair of widely spaced apart arms extending radially towards one another.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The lighting fixture set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the respective bases of the plate elements are attached to the uprights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The lighting fixture set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the radial projections are positioned approximately 90° relative to the uprights.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The lighting fixture set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the annular body is suitable for engaging a corresponding seat integral to the panel, the fixture being recessed, and mounted so as to be oriented in the seat.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The lighting fixture set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the annular body is formed by an external wall and an internal wall extending coaxially from one end of the body and ending at the edge.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
