<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298044-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298044</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11230830</doc-number>
<date>20050920</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>94113662 A</doc-number>
<date>20050428</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>143</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>23</main-group>
<subgroup>34</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257720</main-classification>
<further-classification>257713</further-classification>
<further-classification>257719</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E23088</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E23101</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Electronic device with heat dissipation module</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5136152</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lee</name>
<date>19920800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257699</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5857761</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Abe et al.</name>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362551</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6351610</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Numako et al.</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>396180</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6789921</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Deloy et al.</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362252</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0121097</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chiu et al.</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 62  37</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0136163</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Horng et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361719</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0066103</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Shinozaki</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710301</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0146850</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Meir</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361687</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257720</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E23088</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060244129</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061102</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Liu</last-name>
<first-name>Hsiang-Chao</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tao Yuan Shien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Thomas, Kayden, Horstemeyer &amp; Risley</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Quanta Computer Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tao Yuan Shien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ho</last-name>
<first-name>Tu-Tu</first-name>
<department>2818</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electronic device. The electronic device includes a circuit board, a heat dissipation module, and a light-emitting diode. The circuit board includes a heating element thereon. The heat dissipation module is disposed on the circuit board and the heating element. The light-emitting diode is disposed on the heat dissipation module. The heat dissipation module is connected to the heating element and the light-emitting diode.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="87.46mm" wi="150.11mm" file="US07298044-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="239.18mm" wi="176.61mm" file="US07298044-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="198.29mm" wi="154.18mm" file="US07298044-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="132.67mm" wi="160.70mm" file="US07298044-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention relates to an electronic device with a heat dissipation module, and in particular, to an electronic device with a heat dissipation module for light-emitting diodes.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The typical backlight source of a conventional liquid crystal display is a cold cathode fluorescent lamp (CCFL). Although the cold cathode fluorescent lamps are excellent for linear light-emitting and uniform light sources, they suffer from redundant power consumption and damage environment. Compared with cold cathode fluorescent lamps, a light-emitting diode uses a point light source, has low power-consumption, long life-span, miniaturization, and environmental protection. Light-emitting diodes are gradually replacing cold cathode fluorescent lamps. Thus, light-emitting diodes are often employed in the liquid crystal displays of mobile phones, camera, and notebook computers.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">High luminance of the light-emitting diodes, however, generates excessive heat. Thus, heat dissipation for light-emitting diodes is problematic in electronic devices. Heat dissipation modules are typically only designed for central processing units and chipsets, not light-emitting diodes.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY </heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Electronic devices with a heat dissipation module are provided. Accordingly, an exemplary embodiment of an electronic device comprises a circuit board, a heat dissipation module, and a light-emitting diode. The circuit board comprises a heating element thereon. The heat dissipation module is disposed on the circuit board and the heating element. The light-emitting diode is disposed on the heat dissipation module. The heat dissipation module is connected to the heating element and the light-emitting diode simultaneously.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The heating element comprises a chipset or a central processing unit. The heat dissipation module comprises a heat pipe and a heat exchanger, and the light-emitting diode is disposed on the heat pipe. The heat dissipation module comprises a fan, which blows toward the heat exchanger and exhausts the heat on the heat exchanger. The heat exchanger has a plurality of fins, and the fan blows toward the fins and exhausts the heat on the fins.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The electronic device further comprises a light guiding element, connected to the light-emitting diode, transmitting light from the light emitting diode.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Note that the light guiding element is an optical fiber tube, a glass tube, or a plastic tube. The electronic device is a notebook computer with a liquid crystal display. The light guiding element transmits the light from the light-emitting diode as a backlight source of the liquid crystal display.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The invention can be more fully understood by reading the subsequent detailed description and examples with references made to the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic view of an embodiment of an electronic device with a heat dissipation module;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a side view of the electronic device in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic view of a notebook computer employing the heat dissipation module in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic view of another embodiment of an electronic device with a heat dissipation module.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an electronic device <b>1</b> with a heat dissipation module comprises a circuit board <b>2</b>, a heat dissipation module <b>3</b>, a light-emitting diode <b>4</b>, and a light guiding element <b>5</b>. The circuit board <b>2</b> comprises a central processing unit <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The heat dissipation module <b>3</b>, disposed on the circuit board <b>2</b>, connected to the central processing unit <b>6</b> (heating element), comprises a heat pipe <b>31</b>, a heat exchanger <b>32</b>, and a fan <b>33</b>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the heat exchanger <b>32</b> comprises a plurality of fins <b>32</b><i>a </i>thereon, and the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> is disposed on the heat pipe <b>31</b> of the heat dissipation module <b>3</b>. When the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> emits light, heat is transmitted to the heat pipe <b>31</b> and the heat exchanger <b>32</b> sequentially. Further referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, when heat is transmitted to the fins <b>32</b><i>a </i>of the heat exchanger <b>32</b>, the fan <b>33</b> blows toward the fins <b>32</b><i>a </i>and exhausts heat from the fins <b>32</b><i>a</i>. Thus, heat on the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> is dissipated.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Additionally, referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> is connected to the light guiding element <b>5</b>. The light guiding element <b>5</b> can transmit light from the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> for providing the use of the electronic device <b>1</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the electronic device <b>1</b> can be a notebook computer <b>7</b> with a body <b>7</b><i>b </i>and a liquid crystal display <b>7</b><i>a </i>disposed on the body <b>7</b><i>b</i>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the circuit board <b>2</b> and the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> are disposed in the body <b>7</b><i>b</i>, and the light guiding element <b>5</b> is disposed in the liquid crystal display <b>7</b><i>a</i>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, light from the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> can be transmitted through the light guiding element <b>5</b> to the liquid crystal display <b>7</b><i>a</i>, providing liquid crystal display <b>7</b><i>a </i>as a backlight source. The light guiding element <b>5</b> can be an optical fiber tube, a glass tube, or a plastic tube.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">When the electronic device <b>1</b> is used, light is provided by the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> through the light guiding element <b>5</b>, to serve as a backlight source for the liquid crystal display <b>7</b><i>a</i>. Because a large amount of heat is produced by the light-emitting diode <b>4</b>, the light-emitting diode <b>4</b> is disposed on the heat pipe <b>31</b> of the heat dissipation module <b>3</b>, which can rapidly transmit heat to the heat pipe <b>31</b>. Furthermore, heat is transmitted to the heat exchanger <b>32</b> through the heat pipe <b>31</b>. The fins <b>32</b><i>a </i>of the heat exchanger <b>32</b> can increase heat dissipation area, and airflow generated by the fan <b>33</b> exhausts heat from the fins <b>32</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Note that the heat dissipation module <b>3</b> of the present invention is not limited to that depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, which comprise a fan <b>33</b>. The heat dissipation module <b>3</b> may not comprise a fan <b>33</b>, and may only comprise the heat pipe <b>31</b> and the heat exchanger <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Furthermore, the heat dissipation module <b>3</b> of the present invention is not limited to that depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, in which the module is disposed on the heat pipe <b>31</b>. The heat dissipation module <b>3</b> can also be disposed on the heat exchanger <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Additionally, the electronic device <b>1</b> of the present invention is not limited to the notebook computer <b>7</b> depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The electronic device <b>1</b> can be any electronic device requiring liquid crystal displays.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Note that the heat dissipation module <b>3</b> is not limited to being disposed on the central processing unit depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The heat dissipation module <b>3</b> can be disposed on any heating element on the circuit board <b>2</b>. For example, the heat dissipation module can be disposed on the chipset <b>8</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">While the invention has been described by way of example and in terms of the preferred embodiment, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited thereto. To the contrary, it is intended to cover various modifications and similar arrangements (as would be apparent to those skilled in the art). Therefore, the scope of the appended claims should be accorded the broadest interpretation so as to encompass all such modifications and similar arrangements.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electronic device, comprising:
<claim-text>a circuit board comprising a heating element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat dissipation module, comprising a heat pipe and a heat exchanger, disposed on the circuit board and the heating element; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light-emitting diode disposed on the heat pipe of the heat dissipation module, wherein the heat dissipation module directly contacts the heating element and the light-emitting diode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the heating element comprises a chipset.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the heat dissipation module further comprises a fan, blowing toward the heat exchanger and exhausting the heat from the heat exchanger.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the heat exchanger comprises a plurality of fins, and the fan blowing towards the fins and exhausts the heat from the fins.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a light guiding element, connected to the light-emitting diode and transmitting light from the light-emitting diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the light guiding element is an optical fiber tube.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the light guiding element is a glass tube.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the light guiding element is a plastic tube.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the electronic device is a notebook computer with a liquid crystal display.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the light guiding element transmits light from the light-emitting diode serving as a backlight source of the liquid crystal display.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The electronic device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the heating element comprises a central processing unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A notebook computer, comprising:
<claim-text>a body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a liquid crystal display disposed on the body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a circuit board, disposed in the body, comprising a heating element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat dissipation module disposed on the circuit board and the heating element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light-emitting diode disposed on the heat dissipation module, wherein the heat dissipation module connects the heating element and the light-emitting diode; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light guiding element, disposed in the liquid crystal display, connected to the light-emitting diode and transmitting light from the light-emitting diode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The notebook computer as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the light-emitting diode is disposed in the body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The notebook computer as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the heating element comprises a central processing unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The notebook computer as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the heating element comprises a chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The notebook computer as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the heat dissipation module comprises a heat pipe and a heat exchanger, and the light-emitting diode is disposed on the heat pipe.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The notebook computer as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the heat dissipation module further comprises a fan, blowing toward the heat exchanger and exhausting the heat from the heat exchanger.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The notebook computer as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the light guiding element transmits light from the light-emitting diode serving as a backlight source of the liquid crystal display.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A notebook computer with a liquid crystal display, comprising:
<claim-text>a circuit board comprising a heating element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat dissipation module disposed on the circuit board and the heating element;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light-emitting diode disposed on the heat dissipation module, wherein the heat dissipation module directly contacts the heating element and the light-emitting diode; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light guiding element, connected to the light-emitting diode and transmitting light from the light-emitting diode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
