<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297880-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297880</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10939554</doc-number>
<date>20040913</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>326</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>19</main-group>
<subgroup>52</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>23</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>60</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>32</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>177144</main-classification>
<further-classification> 7386262</further-classification>
<further-classification>177136</further-classification>
<further-classification>177154</further-classification>
<further-classification>280735</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Load limiter for strain gauge occupant classification sensor</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4361199</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ulicny</name>
<date>19821100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4420054</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Caris</name>
<date>19831200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6323443</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Aoki et al.</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>177144</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6331682</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hopkins et al.</name>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6729193</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Ishida</name>
<date>20040500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73862627</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6916997</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Thakur et al.</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>177136</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6969809</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Rainey</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>177136</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6981717</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Sakamoto et al.</name>
<date>20060100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>280735</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7044006</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kouyama et al.</name>
<date>20060500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73862381</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00010">
<othercit>Lebow Model 6214 Data Sheet (http://www.lebow.com/prodfolder/6214.pdf).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>Co-pending U.S. Appl. No. 10/754,859, filed Jan. 9, 2004, entitled “Shock Resistant Strain Gage-Seat Mounted”.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>177136</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>177144</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>177154-157</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>280735</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73862627</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73862381</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2972172</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060054766</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060316</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sulkowski</last-name>
<first-name>Michael</first-name>
<address>
<city>Commerce Township</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Al-Khairy</last-name>
<first-name>Issam</first-name>
<address>
<city>Windsor</city>
<country>CA</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CA</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CA</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Smith</last-name>
<first-name>Ralph E.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Chrysler LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Auburn Hills</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Friedman</last-name>
<first-name>Carl D.</first-name>
<department>3632</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Le</last-name>
<first-name>Tan</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An over-travel protection device for mounting an occupant classification sensor having a deflecting member, the sensor being mounted between first and second seat mounting portions, is described. The device has a sensor plate positioned adjacent the occupant classification sensor and a spacer having a land. The spacer is positioned adjacent to the occupant classification sensor. A compliant element is located between the sensor plate and the second seat mounting portion. The land is spaced from the first mounting portion until the deflecting member deflects a predetermined amount, causing the land to abut the first seat mounting portion and thereby preventing further displacement of the deflecting member.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="92.46mm" wi="155.11mm" file="US07297880-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="202.52mm" wi="152.65mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297880-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates generally to methods of attaching an occupant classification sensor to a vehicle, and more particularly to methods of preventing over-extension or over-compression of the sensor.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A common type of occupant classification sensor uses a load cell to determine the weight of a vehicle occupant. The sensor is located in a load path between an occupant's seat and the vehicle floor. While the occupant is seated his weight causes a load beam within the cell to deflect. A sense element is mounted to the load beam and is deflected therewith. The sense element converts this deflection into an electrical property indicative of the occupant's weight. If the load beam is subjected to a large enough force, however, it may be deflected beyond its range of elasticity and assume a permanent deflection or “offset”. This offset is undesirable and, depending on the magnitude of offset and the ability of other electronics in the occupant classification system to compensate for it, may result in a need to replace the sensor.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">It is therefore desirable to provide a method for mounting an occupant classification sensor which prevents over-deflection of the sensor's load beam or similar deflecting member.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Accordingly, an aspect of the present invention is to provide an apparatus for mounting an occupant classification sensor which limits movement of the sensor's load beam or other deflecting member.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In accordance with these aspects, an over-travel protection device for mounting an occupant classification sensor having a deflecting member, the sensor being mounted between first and second seat mounting portions, is described. The device has a sensor plate positioned adjacent the occupant classification sensor and a spacer having a land. The spacer is positioned adjacent to the occupant classification sensor. A compliant element is located between the sensor plate and the second seat mounting portion. The land is spaced from the first mounting portion until the deflecting member deflects a predetermined amount, causing the land to abut the first seat mounting portion and thereby preventing further displacement of the deflecting member.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Further areas of applicability of the present invention will become apparent from the detailed description provided hereinafter. It should be understood however that the detailed description and specific examples, while indicating preferred embodiments of the invention, are intended for purposes of illustration only, since various changes and modifications within the spirit and scope of the invention will become apparent to those skilled in the art from this detailed description.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a cross-section of an over-travel protection device in-situ, and</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a plan view of a sensor plate of the device shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Turning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an over-travel protection device is shown attached to an occupant classification sensor (OCS) <b>12</b> and first and second mounting portions of a vehicle seat assembly. In the depicted embodiment, the first mounting portion is a seat rail <b>10</b>, and the second mounting portion is a seat riser <b>26</b>. The OCS is of a type known in the art, and has deflecting members, such as beams <b>24</b>, which are positioned between outer bushings <b>30</b> and a center bushing <b>32</b>. The outer bushings <b>30</b> are indirectly mounted to the seat riser <b>26</b> via the over-travel protection device. The center bushing is indirectly connected to the seat rail <b>10</b> via the over-travel protection device. The beams <b>24</b> deflect when a force is applied to the OCS through center bushing <b>32</b>. The deflection of the beams cause an electrical signal to vary in accordance with the magnitude of the force, and the electrical signal is available for use through a connector <b>14</b>. While a single over-travel protection device is shown, it is understood that an occupant classification system may use more than one of the arrangements shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> for each vehicle seat. For example, a seat may have such an arrangement at each corner, for a total of four.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The over travel protection device has a sensor plate <b>16</b> that has a clearance hole <b>42</b> and a pair of threaded holes <b>44</b> disposed therein. Each threaded hole <b>44</b> receives the threaded end of a shoulder bolt <b>18</b>. The shoulder bolts <b>18</b> are preferably of a socket-head type. Each shoulder bolt <b>18</b> passes through a pliable element, such as grommet <b>28</b>. The grommets <b>28</b> are positioned in holes formed in the seat riser <b>26</b>, and each grommet has a peripheral radial groove for engaging the periphery of its mating hole in the seat riser <b>26</b>. Spacers <b>34</b> retain the grommets <b>28</b> in their position against the head of shoulder bolts <b>18</b>. The spacers <b>34</b> also facilitate in clamping the outer bushings <b>30</b> of the OCS <b>12</b>. The grommets <b>28</b> operate to absorb minor coplanarity differences between the faces of the outer bushings <b>30</b> and the seat riser <b>26</b>. Absorbing the coplanarity differences operates to reduce undesirable offset in the electrical signal available at connector <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The over travel protection device also has a center bolt <b>20</b>. The center bolt <b>20</b> passes through an opening in the seat rail <b>10</b>, an axial bore though spacer <b>36</b>, a washer <b>40</b>, the center bushing <b>32</b>, and a threaded nut <b>22</b>. The threaded nut <b>22</b> and center bushing <b>32</b> are spaced away from the sensor plate <b>16</b> by virtue of a clearance hole <b>42</b> formed in the sensor plate <b>16</b>. The spacer <b>36</b> has a body of a first diameter which necks down to a second diameter. The spacer portion which has necks down to a second diameter passes through an orifice <b>46</b> formed in the seat riser <b>26</b>. The boundary region between the first diameter and the second diameter forms an upper land <b>38</b>. Washer <b>40</b> forms a lower land in the plane interfacing with the spacer <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The diameter of orifice <b>46</b> is less than the first diameter of spacer <b>36</b>, and greater that the second diameter of spacer <b>26</b>. The axial length of the portion of spacer <b>26</b> which is necked down to the second diameter is greater than the thickness of the material used to form the seat riser <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In operation, the seat riser <b>26</b> is made fast to the vehicle floor as is known in the art (not shown). The seat rail <b>10</b> transfers a force, such as from the weight of a seat occupant, to the center bushing <b>32</b> of OCS <b>20</b> via spacer <b>36</b>, washer <b>40</b>, and nut <b>22</b>. The force applied to the center bushing of the OCS causes the beams <b>24</b> to deflect since their opposite ends are motion restrained by outer bushings <b>30</b>. Also, a reactive force distributed through shoulder bolts <b>18</b> causes grommets <b>28</b> to deflect. In the event the applied force is sufficiently great, the beams <b>24</b> and grommets <b>28</b> will deflect until either the upper land <b>38</b> or washer <b>40</b> comes into contact with the seat riser <b>26</b>. Once contact occurs, the magnitude of the force applied to the OCS is clipped at a magnitude depending on the spring constant of the beams <b>24</b> and the magnitude of deflection. The remainder of the force in excess of the clipped magnitude is shunted around the OCS through the seat riser <b>26</b> and either upper land <b>36</b> or washer <b>40</b>, depending on the direction of the force. If the force is downward on the seat rail <b>10</b>, then upper land <b>38</b> will operate to shunt the excess force to the seat riser <b>26</b>. On the other hand, if the force is upward on the seat rail <b>10</b>, then the washer <b>40</b> will operate to shunt the excess force to the seat riser <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Turning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a plan view of the sensor plate <b>16</b> is shown. The sensor plate <b>16</b> has two threaded holes <b>44</b> for receiving the threaded ends of shoulder bolts <b>18</b>. A clearance hole <b>42</b> is formed therein of a sufficient diameter to prevent the sensor plate <b>16</b> from contacting wither the nut <b>22</b> or the center bushing <b>32</b>. In one aspect of the invention, the diameter of clearance hole <b>42</b> is sufficient to allow a tool to engage and apply torque to nut <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The invention being thus described, it will be obvious that the same may be varied in many ways. Such variations are not to be regarded as a departure from the spirit and scope of the invention, and all such modifications as would be obvious to one skilled in the art are intended to be included within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An over-travel protection device comprising:
<claim-text>a first seat mounting portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second seat mounting portion spaced apart from said first seat mounting portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an occupant classification sensor having a pair of deflecting members mounted to said second seat mounting portion, said occupant classification sensor having an upper surface and a lower surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sensor plate attached to said lower surface of said occupant classification sensor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a spacer having a land mounted to said first seat mounting portion, said spacer being positioned adjacent to said upper surface of said occupant classification sensor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a compliant element located between said occupant classification sensor and said second seat mounting portion, said land being spaced from said second mounting portion until said deflecting members and said compliant element deflect a predetermined amount, causing the land to abut said second seat mounting portion and thereby preventing further displacement of the deflecting members and compliant element.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said first seat mounting portion comprises a seat rail and said second seat mounting portion comprises a seat riser.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a washer forming a second land spaced from the second seat mounting portion until said deflecting member deflects a predetermined amount in a negative direction, causing said second land to abut said second seat mounting portion and thereby preventing further displacement of said deflecting members and compliant element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, further comprising a fastener for securing said spacer, washer, and the occupant classification sensor to said second seat mounting portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein said sensor plate has a clearance hole disposed therein, said clearance hole allowing said fastener to enter therein.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein said first and second lands abut an orifice periphery of said second seat mounting portion to prevent further displacement of said deflecting members and said compliant element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An over-travel protection device, comprising:
<claim-text>a seat rail;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a seat riser separated from said seat rail;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an occupant classification sensor including a pair of deflecting members mounted to a side of said seat riser opposite said seat rail, said occupant classification sensor mounted to said seat riser via a pair of fasteners attached to said seat riser via a pair of deflectable grommets;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sensor plate mounted to said occupant classification sensor on a side of said occupant classification sensor opposite said seat riser;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a spacer having a land mounted between said seat rail and said seat riser; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a washer disposed between said occupant classification sensor and said seat riser,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein upon deflection of said deflecting members and said deflectable grommets in a first direction, said land will abut said seat riser, and upon deflection of said deflecting members and said deflectable grommets in a second direction, said washer will abut said seat riser.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The over-travel protection device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said sensor plate includes a plurality of openings that correspond to said fasteners.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The over-travel protection device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said grommets are formed of a compliant material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The over-travel protection device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said grommets include a peripheral radial groove for engaging said seat riser.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The over-travel protection device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said grommets operate to absorb minor coplanarity differences in said occupant classification sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The over-travel protection device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said spacer has a body of a first diameter that necks down to a second diameter.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
