<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297134-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297134</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10132932</doc-number>
<date>20020426</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>930</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>61</class>
<subclass>M</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>60410304</main-classification>
<further-classification>606192</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Dual use catheter</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4610660</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Rosenberg</name>
<date>19860900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>604544</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5047045</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Arney et al.</name>
<date>19910900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5409459</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gambale</name>
<date>19950400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>60410202</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5451233</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yock</name>
<date>19950900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5534007</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>St. Germain et al.</name>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>623  111</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5807355</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ramzipoor et al.</name>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>604526</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5891110</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Larson et al.</name>
<date>19990400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6050972</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Zadno-Azizi et al.</name>
<date>20000400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>604 9701</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6540719</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Bigus et al.</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>604 9601</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>60410304</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>60410201</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>60410202</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>60410103</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>60410203</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>604910</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>604912</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>604921</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>606191</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>606192</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>606194</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20030204201</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20031030</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Krivoruchko</last-name>
<first-name>Mike</first-name>
<address>
<city>Forestville</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hodgson</last-name>
<first-name>Serge</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Medtronic Vascular, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Santa Rosa</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Anhtuan T.</first-name>
<department>3731</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Tuan Van</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A catheter assembly and method includes a multi-lumen portion having a guide wire lumen and an inflation/deployment lumen. The guide wire lumen includes a distal guide wire lumen portion having a rapid exchange guide wire port, and a proximal guide wire lumen portion rotatable to selectively expose the rapid exchange guide wire port. The inflation/deployment lumen includes a rotatable seal which facilitates rotation of the proximal guide wire lumen portion.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="131.74mm" wi="224.96mm" file="US07297134-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="226.23mm" wi="162.05mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297134-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="205.82mm" wi="167.13mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297134-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="228.43mm" wi="153.25mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297134-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an intra-vascular device and method. More particularly, the present invention relates to an intra-vascular catheter which can be utilized in a rapid exchange or over-the-wire (OTW) operating mode.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Human blood vessels often become occluded or completely blocked by plaque, thrombi, other deposits, embolic or other substances, which reduce the blood carrying capacity of the vessel. Should the blockage occur at a critical place in the circulatory system, serious and permanent injury, or even death, can occur. To prevent this, some form of medical intervention is usually performed when significant occlusion is detected.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Various types of intervention techniques have been developed which facilitate the reduction or removal of the blockage in the blood vessel, allowing increased blood flow through the vessel. One technique for treating occlusion of a blood vessel is the use a dilation catheter having a dilation balloon. However, in practice, is often necessary to exchange one dilation catheter for another.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In doing so, it is often necessary to utilize an over-the-wire (OTW) dilation catheter which uses long exchange wires, e.g., 300 cm exchange wires. However, use of long exchange wires often requires two operators to perform the procedure. During this procedure, it is necessary that the operators communicate with each other which makes the procedure time-consuming. In addition, since the exchange wire is so long, it often is awkward to handle and for that reason may come into contact with the floor or become contaminated which necessitates removing the entire apparatus being utilized for the procedure.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">To avoid these difficulties with OTW dilation catheters, rapid exchange dilation catheters have been developed which utilized a relatively short guide wire. The rapid exchange dilation catheter has been widely praised by the medical profession and has met with much commercial success in the marketplace.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, the OTW dilation catheter is still desirable for use in certain circumstances, for example, when the additional length of the guide wire facilitate positioning or is otherwise desirable. Thus, a dilation catheter that can operate in an over-the-wire mode or a rapid exchange mode would provide needed flexibility for the medical profession.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In accordance with an embodiment of the present invention, a catheter assembly includes a multi-lumen portion having a guide wire lumen and an inflation/deployment lumen. The guide wire lumen includes a distal guide wire lumen portion having a rapid exchange guide wire port, and a proximal guide wire lumen portion rotatable to selectively expose the rapid exchange guide wire port.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In accordance with one embodiment, the inflation/deployment lumen has a distal inflation/deployment lumen portion; a proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion; and a rotatable seal forming a fluid tight seal between the distal inflation/deployment lumen portion and the proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">To configure the catheter assembly for use in an over-the-wire mode, the distal guide wire lumen portion and the proximal guide wire lumen portion are aligned. A guide wire is then passed through the entire length of the guide wire lumen and out through a guide wire lumen port of a handle coupled to the guide wire lumen.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">To configure the catheter assembly for use in a rapid exchange mode, the proximal guide wire lumen portion is rotated around the inflation/deployment lumen to expose the rapid exchange guide wire port of the distal guide wire lumen portion. The rotatable seal of the inflation/deployment lumen facilitate this rotation. A guide wire is then passed through just the length of the distal guide wire lumen portion and out through the rapid exchange guide wire port of the distal guide wire lumen portion.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The present invention is best understood by reference to the following detailed description when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side plan view, in partial cross-section, of a dual use catheter in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an enlarged view of the region II of the catheter of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the catheter taken at III-III of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a side plan view, in partial cross-section, of a dual use catheter in accordance with another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an enlarged view of the region V of the catheter of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the catheter taken at VI-VI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a perspective view, in partial cross-section, of a dilation balloon assembly in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a side plan view, in partial cross-section, of a dual use catheter in accordance with another embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a perspective view, partially in cross-section, of the deployment of a stent of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Common reference numerals are used throughout the drawings and detailed description to indicate like elements.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side plan view, in partial cross-section, of a dual use catheter <b>100</b> in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, catheter <b>100</b>, sometimes called a catheter assembly, includes a handle <b>102</b>, a multi-lumen portion <b>104</b>, a dilation balloon <b>106</b> and a guide wire <b>108</b>. More particularly, handle <b>102</b> is mounted to a proximal end <b>110</b> of multi-lumen portion <b>104</b> and dilation balloon <b>106</b> is mounted at a distal end <b>112</b> of multi-lumen portion <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Multi-lumen portion <b>104</b> includes a guide wire lumen <b>114</b> and a deployment/inflation lumen <b>116</b> in a side-by-side arrangement. Dilation balloon <b>106</b> is mounted around guide wire lumen <b>114</b> adjacent a distal end <b>118</b> of guide wire lumen <b>114</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Deployment/inflation lumen <b>116</b>, sometimes called an inflation lumen <b>116</b>, terminates inside of dilation balloon <b>106</b> at a distal end <b>120</b> of inflation lumen <b>116</b>. Accordingly, inflation lumen <b>116</b> is in fluid communication with dilation balloon <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Proximal ends <b>122</b>, <b>124</b> of guide wire lumen <b>114</b> and inflation lumen <b>116</b>, respectively, are mounted to handle <b>102</b> using any one of a number of techniques well known to those of skill in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Handle <b>102</b> includes an over-the-wire (OTW) guide wire lumen port <b>126</b> and an inflation/deployment lumen port <b>128</b>, sometimes called an inflation lumen port <b>128</b>. Guide wire lumen port <b>126</b> is in communication with guide wire lumen <b>114</b>. Inflation lumen port <b>128</b> is in fluid communication with inflation lumen <b>116</b> and thus with dilation balloon <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In accordance with this embodiment, catheter <b>100</b> is configured for use in an over-the-wire mode. Accordingly, guide wire <b>108</b> enters guide wire lumen <b>114</b> at distal end <b>118</b>, extends through guide wire lumen <b>114</b> to handle <b>102</b>, extends through handle <b>102</b>, and exits at guide wire lumen port <b>126</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an enlarged view of the region II of catheter <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view of catheter <b>100</b> taken at III-III of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b> and <b>3</b> together, guide wire lumen <b>114</b> includes a distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> and a proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b>. Distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> extends between distal end <b>118</b> of guide wire lumen <b>114</b> and a rapid exchange guide wire port <b>134</b> of distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">When catheter <b>100</b> is used in the over-the-wire mode, distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> and proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b> are aligned. More particularly, distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> and proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b> share a common longitudinal axis L<b>1</b> such that distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> and proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b> operate as if guide wire lumen <b>114</b> is a single unitary lumen.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Inflation lumen <b>116</b> includes a distal inflation/deployment lumen portion <b>136</b>, sometimes called a distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b>, and a proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion <b>138</b>, sometimes called a proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>. Distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b> extends proximally from distal end <b>120</b> of inflation lumen <b>116</b> to a proximal end <b>140</b> of distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b>. Proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> extends distally from handle <b>102</b> to a distal end <b>142</b> of proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b> and proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> are mounted together by a rotatable seal <b>144</b> of inflation lumen <b>116</b>. More particularly, distal end <b>142</b> of proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> is mounted to proximal end <b>140</b> of distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b> by rotatable seal <b>144</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> and distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b> are aligned. More particularly, proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> and distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b> share a common longitudinal axis L<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Rotatable seal <b>144</b> forms a fluid tight seal between proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> and distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b>. Rotatable seal <b>144</b> allows proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> to be rotated around longitudinal axis L<b>2</b> relative to distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b> without compromising the fluid tight seal. Accordingly, proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> can be rotated relative to distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b> without leakage of fluid between proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> and distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, during use, guide wire <b>108</b> is introduced intra-vascularly and guided to the treatment side of a patient, e.g., a restriction such as an occlusion of a vessel. Guide wire <b>108</b> is then fed, sometimes called passed, through distal end <b>118</b> of guide wire lumen <b>114</b>, through distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>, through proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b>, through handle <b>102</b> and out through guide wire lumen port <b>126</b> of handle <b>102</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Dilation balloon <b>106</b> is advanced over guide wire <b>108</b> and thus guided to the treatment site. Dilation balloon <b>106</b> can include radiopaque markers to facilitate observation and positioning of dilation balloon <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Once located at the treatment site, dilation balloon <b>106</b> is inflated through inflation lumen port <b>128</b> of handle <b>102</b> to open the restriction in the vessel. Illustratively, a pressurized fluid is introducing through inflation lumen port <b>128</b> of handle <b>102</b> to inflate dilation balloon <b>106</b>. Dilation balloon <b>106</b> is then deflated and withdrawn from the patient.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a side plan view, in partial cross-section, of dual use catheter <b>100</b> in accordance with another embodiment of the present invention. Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, in accordance with this embodiment, catheter <b>100</b> is configured for use in a rapid exchange mode. Accordingly, a guide wire <b>108</b>A enters guide wire lumen <b>114</b> at distal end <b>118</b>, extends through distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> and exits at rapid exchange guide wire port <b>134</b>. This allows guide wire <b>108</b>A to be relatively short, e.g., 180 cm, and more particularly, to be shorter than guide wire <b>108</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, e.g., 300 cm.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an enlarged view of the region V of catheter <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view of catheter <b>100</b> taken at VI-VI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref>, <b>5</b>, and <b>6</b> together, when catheter <b>100</b> is used in the rapid exchange mode, distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> and proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b> are offset, sometimes called un-aligned. More particular, distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> has a longitudinal axis Li which is parallel to and offset from a longitudinal axis L<b>3</b> of proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">To use catheter <b>100</b> in the rapid exchange mode, proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b> is rotated around inflation lumen <b>116</b> with respect to distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b> and moved out of the way. Thus, proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b> is rotated to selectively expose rapid exchange guide wire port <b>134</b>. For example, handle <b>102</b> is rotated to rotate proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b>. This exposes rapid exchange guide wire port <b>134</b> of distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Rotation of proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b> also rotates proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> relative to distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b>. However, rotatable seal <b>144</b> facilitate this rotation without compromising the seal and the axial connection between proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b> and distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b> as discussed above.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, during use, guide wire <b>108</b>A is introduced intra-vascularly and guided to the treatment side of a patient, e.g., a restriction such as an occlusion of a vessel. Guide wire <b>108</b>A is then fed through distal end <b>118</b> of distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>, though distal guide wire portion <b>130</b>, and out through rapid exchange guide wire port <b>134</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Dilation balloon <b>106</b> is advanced over guide wire <b>108</b>A and thus guided to the treatment site. Dilation balloon <b>106</b> can include radiopaque markers to facilitate observation and positioning a dilation balloon <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Once located at the treatment site, dilation balloon <b>106</b> is inflated through inflation lumen port <b>128</b> of handle <b>102</b> to open the restriction in the vessel. Illustratively, a pressurized fluid is introducing through inflation lumen port <b>128</b> of handle <b>102</b> to inflate dilation balloon <b>106</b>. Dilation balloon <b>106</b> is then deflated and withdrawn from the patient.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As discussed above, inflation of dilation balloon <b>106</b> opens the restriction in the vessel. However, in certain applications such as when it is desirable to prevent subsequent collapse of the vessel, a stent is employed with dilation balloon <b>106</b> as discussed in greater detail below with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a perspective view, in partial cross-section, of a dilation balloon assembly <b>700</b> in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. Dilation balloon assembly <b>700</b> includes dilation balloon <b>106</b> and a stent <b>702</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Stent <b>702</b> is located on and around dilation balloon <b>106</b>. Inflation of dilation balloon <b>106</b> as discussed above likewise expands stent <b>702</b> and anchors stent <b>702</b> within the vessel at the treatment site. Dilation balloon <b>106</b> is then deflated and withdrawn from the patient. However, stent <b>702</b> remains at the treatment side and prevents or minimizes subsequent collapse or obstruction of the vessel.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a side plan view, in partial cross-section, of a dual use catheter <b>100</b>A in accordance with another embodiment of the present invention. Catheter <b>100</b>A of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is similar to catheter <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and only the significant differences are discussed below.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, in accordance with this embodiment, catheter <b>100</b>A is used in a rapid exchange mode. Accordingly, guide wire <b>108</b>A enters distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>A at distal end <b>118</b>A, extends through distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>A and exits at rapid exchange guide wire port <b>134</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">However, in accordance with this embodiment, a proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b>A of guide wire lumen <b>114</b> is rotated to expose rapid exchange guide wire port <b>134</b>A of distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>A without rotation of handle <b>102</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In accordance with this embodiment, proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b>A includes a proximal end <b>802</b>A, which is detached from handle <b>102</b>A. This allows proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b>A to be rotated around inflation/deployment lumen <b>116</b> without rotation of handle <b>102</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Rotation of proximal guide wire lumen portion <b>132</b>A also rotates proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>A relative to distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b>A and also relative to handle <b>102</b>A. However, rotatable seal <b>144</b>A, sometimes called a first rotatable seal, facilitate this rotation relative to distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b>A without compromising the seal between proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>A and distal inflation lumen portion <b>136</b>A similar to that discussed above. Other numbered items pictured having an “A” suffix are similar in structure to similarly numbered items discussed above without the “A” suffix.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">To facilitate rotation of proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>A relative to handle <b>102</b>A, a rotatable seal <b>804</b>, sometimes called a second rotatable seal, forms a fluid tight seal (although where no fluid tightness is required to facilitate balloon pressurization, a rotatable axially secure mechanical connection is also to be considered synonymous with a fluid tight seal) between proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>A and handle <b>102</b>A. Rotatable seal <b>804</b> allows proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>A to be rotated around its longitudinal axis relative to handle <b>102</b>A without compromising the fluid tight seal and/or the mechanical connection there between. Accordingly, proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>A can be rotated relative to handle <b>102</b>A without leakage of fluid between proximal inflation lumen portion <b>138</b>A and handle <b>102</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Also in accordance with this embodiment, catheter <b>100</b>A employs a self-expanding stent <b>806</b>. More particularly, distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>A performs as a pushrod. Stent <b>806</b>A is placed around distal guide wire lumen portion <b>130</b>A adjacent distal end <b>118</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">A sheath <b>808</b> radially compresses and restrains from extending stent <b>806</b>. Sheath <b>808</b> is connected to a sheath retraction wire <b>810</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Sheath retraction wire <b>810</b> enters distal end <b>120</b>A of lumen <b>116</b>A, passes through lumen <b>116</b>A, through handle <b>102</b>A, and exits through inflation lumen port <b>128</b>A of handle <b>102</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a perspective view, partially in cross-section, of the deployment of stent <b>806</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 9</figref> together, sheath retraction wire <b>810</b> is retracted (pulled) out of inflation lumen port <b>128</b> to retract sheath <b>808</b> and to deploy stent <b>806</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Upon deployment, stent <b>806</b> self-expands and anchors within the vessel at the treatment site. Catheter <b>100</b>A is then withdrawn from the patient. However, stent <b>806</b> remains at the treatment side and prevents or minimizes subsequent collapse or obstruction of the vessel.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">An embodiment according to the invention includes a method of configuring a catheter assembly for use in an over-the-wire mode including the steps of aligning a distal guide wire lumen portion of a guide wire lumen with a proximal guide wire lumen portion of the guide wire lumen and passing a guide wire through a distal end of the guide wire lumen, through the distal guide wire lumen portion and through the proximal guide wire lumen portion. Where the step of passing a guide wire through a distal end of the guide wire lumen includes passing the guide wire through a handle and out through a guide wire lumen port of the handle. A method of configuring a catheter assembly for use in a rapid exchange mode includes rotating a proximal guide wire lumen portion around an inflation/deployment lumen to expose a rapid exchange guide wire port of a distal guide wire lumen portion of a guide wire lumen and passing a guide wire through a distal end of the distal guide wire lumen portion, through the distal guide wire lumen portion and out through the rapid exchange guide wire port, where the inflation/deployment lumen includes a distal inflation/deployment lumen portion, a proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion, and a rotatable seal forming a fluid tight seal between the distal inflation/deployment lumen portion and the proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion. The step of rotating includes rotating the proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion relative to the distal inflation/deployment lumen portion relative to a longitudinal axis of the catheter.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">This disclosure provides exemplary embodiments of the present invention. The scope of the present invention is not limited by these exemplary embodiments. Numerous variations, whether explicitly provided for by the specification or implied by the specification or not, such as variations in structure, dimension, type of material and manufacturing process may be implemented by one of skill in the art in view of this disclosure.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A catheter assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a multi-lumen portion comprising a guide wire lumen and an inflation/deployment lumen,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide wire lumen comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a distal guide wire lumen portion comprising a rapid exchange guide wire port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a proximal guide wire lumen portion rotatable around said inflation/deployment lumen to offset said proximal guide wire lumen portion from said distal guide wire lumen portion to selectively expose said rapid exchange guide wire port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said inflation/deployment lumen comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a distal inflation/deployment lumen portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotatable seal rotatably mounting said distal inflation/deployment lumen portion to said proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a longitudinal axis of said distal guide wire lumen portion is parallel to and offset from a longitudinal axis of said proximal guide wire lumen portion when said proximal guide wire lumen portion is offset from said distal guide wire lumen portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a dilation balloon mounted around said guide wire lumen adjacent a distal end of said guide wire lumen.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein said inflation/deployment lumen is in fluid communication with said dilation balloon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein said inflation/deployment lumen comprises a distal end inside of said dilation balloon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. That catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> further comprising a stent located on and around said dilation balloon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a handle comprising:
<claim-text>an over-the-wire guide wire lumen port in communication with said guide wire lumen; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inflation/deployment lumen port in fluid communication with said inflation/deployment lumen.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> further comprising a guide wire entering said guide wire lumen at a distal end of said guide wire lumen, extending through said guide wire lumen to said handle, extending through said handle and exiting at said over-the-wire guide wire lumen port.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said catheter assembly is configured in an over-the-wire mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said distal guide wire lumen portion and said proximal guide wire lumen portion are aligned.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a guide wire entering said distal guide wire lumen portion at a distal end of said guide wire lumen, extending through said distal guide wire lumen portion and exiting at said rapid exchange guide wire lumen port.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein said catheter assembly is configured in a rapid exchange mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>
<claim-text>wherein said distal guide wire lumen portion and said proximal guide wire lumen portion are offset, said catheter assembly further comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a guide wire entering said distal guide wire lumen portion at a distal end of said guide wire lumen, extending through said distal guide wire lumen portion and exiting at said rapid exchange guide wire lumen port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> farther comprising:
<claim-text>a stent around said distal guide wire lumen portion adjacent a distal end of said guide wire lumen;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sheath radially compressing and restraining said stent; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sheath retraction wire connected to said sheath.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said sheath retraction wire extends through said inflation/deployment lumen.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a dilation balloon in fluid communication with said inflation/deployment lumen.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a handle comprising an inflation/deployment lumen port in fluid communication with said inflation/deployment lumen.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> further comprising a second rotatable seal forming a fluid tight seal between said proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion and said handle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The catheter assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said distal guide wire lumen portion and said proximal guide wire lumen portion share a common longitudinal axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A catheter assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a multi-lumen portion comprising a guide wire lumen and an inflation/deployment lumen,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said guide wire lumen comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a distal guide wire lumen portion comprising a rapid exchange guide wire port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a proximal guide wire lumen portion rotatable to selectively expose said rapid exchange guide wire port; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said inflation/deployment lumen comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a distal inflation/deployment lumen portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotatable seal forming a fluid tight seal between said distal inflation/deployment lumen portion and said proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion, wherein said proximal guide wire lumen portion is rotated around said proximal inflation/deployment lumen portion to offset said proximal guide wire lumen portion form said distal guide wire lumen portion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a longitudinal axis of said distal guide wire lumen portion is parallel to and offset from a longitudinal axis of said proximal guide wire lumen portion when said proximal guide wire lumen portion is offset from said distal guide wire lumen portion, and wherein said distal guide wire lumen portion and said proximal guide wire lumen portion share a common longitudinal axis when said proximal guide wire lumen portion is aligned with said distal guide wire lumen portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
