<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298105-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298105</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11614239</doc-number>
<date>20061221</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>P</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318432</main-classification>
<further-classification>318800</further-classification>
<further-classification>388906</further-classification>
<further-classification>388917</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Motor speed estimation system and method using hybrid model reference adaptive system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3889167</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tanaka et al.</name>
<date>19750600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4295084</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nagase et al.</name>
<date>19811000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4760321</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tanaka et al.</name>
<date>19880700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4777581</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Smith</name>
<date>19881000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5548197</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Unsworth et al.</name>
<date>19960800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5859514</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chouffier et al.</name>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6014006</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Stuntz et al.</name>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>318804</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6281659</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Giuseppe</name>
<date>20010800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6414463</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Griepentrog et al.</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6509711</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Zaremba</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>318800</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6577096</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Cho</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6646409</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Won et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>318701</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6683428</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Pavlov et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>318432</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6984959</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Satake et al.</name>
<date>20060100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>318720</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0192520</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Yin et al.</name>
<date>20060800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0192522</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kerkman et al.</name>
<date>20060800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>16</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-exemplary-claim>19</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318430-434</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318727</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>318798-802</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>388904</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>388906</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3889072</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3889075</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>388917</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11375800</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20060314</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7193387</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11614239</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lu</last-name>
<first-name>Haihui</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Qian</last-name>
<first-name>Wei</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Haas</last-name>
<first-name>Steven M.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Walbrun</last-name>
<first-name>William R.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Rockwell Automation Technologies, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Mayfield Heights</city>
<state>OH</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ro</last-name>
<first-name>Bentsu</first-name>
<department>2837</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Motor drives, motor speed controllers, motor speed estimation systems, and methods are presented for controlling motor speed and for estimating motor speed, in which a speed estimate controller provides a rotor speed estimate based on a first error term from a torque-based MRAS component for a first range of motor speeds and based on a second error term from a rotor flux-based MRAS component for a second range of speeds.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="171.28mm" wi="237.83mm" file="US07298105-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="238.59mm" wi="178.73mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298105-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="227.58mm" wi="180.17mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298105-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="233.68mm" wi="153.42mm" file="US07298105-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="245.36mm" wi="178.90mm" file="US07298105-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="241.64mm" wi="178.90mm" file="US07298105-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of, and claims priority to and the benefit of, U.S. patent application Ser. No. 11/375,800, field Mar. 14, 2006, entitled SYSTEM AND METHOD FOR MOTOR SPEED ESTIMATION USING HYBRID MODEL REFERENCE ADAPTIVE SYSTEM, now U.S. Pat. No. 7,193,387 B1, the entirety of which is hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to electric induction motors and more particularly to estimating motor speed using hybrid model reference adaptive systems.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Motor control systems are widely used to control various aspects of motor performance in a broad spectrum of applications in which electric motors drive loads. Induction motors are asynchronous AC motors having a stator with stator windings providing a rotating AC stator field, with a rotor attached to the motor shaft to rotate within the stator field. Induction motors generally include a so-called squirrel cage rotor with the rotor rotating at a speed less than the rotational speed of the rotating stator field. The rotation of the stator magnetic field induces a current in the rotor conductors, in turn creating a rotor magnetic field that causes the rotor to turn in the direction the stator field is rotating. For many electric motor applications, control of the motor speed is important, particularly where the shaft load varies. In this regard, speed control during startup is particularly important in many motor control applications.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">To regulate the motor performance according to a desired speed, it is necessary to measure or estimate the actual rotational speed of the rotor at any given time. In certain induction motor control architectures, moreover, soft-starters are used to energize the stator windings during startup, with the soft startup controls being bypassed once the motor reaches the normal operating speed, in order to minimize steady state heat generation. Many conventional motor control systems employ some form of tachometer or other sensor device mechanically coupled to the motor shaft to produce a feedback signal representing the motor speed, to facilitate closed loop startup speed control. However, such external sensors add cost to the motor drive system, and require maintenance.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Sensorless systems have been proposed and introduced, often employing model-based estimation or speed estimation based on measuring stator current harmonic content. However, actual motor startup times using these systems often varies with line voltage and motor load, which makes it difficult to coordinate motor startup with other equipment in various automated systems. Model-based approaches in particular suffer from variance in motor parameters and weak signals during motor startup. Stator-current-harmonics-based approaches require complex signal processing and the measured harmonics are related to the rotor structure, whereby the speed estimate cannot be updated quickly. Thus, there is a continuing need for improved motor controls and sensorless speed estimation techniques and systems for motor control applications, particularly for controlling motor speeds during startup.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">One or more aspects of the invention are now summarized to facilitate a basic understanding of the invention, wherein this summary is not an extensive overview of the invention, and is intended neither to identify certain elements of the invention, nor to delineate the scope thereof. The primary purpose of the summary, rather, is to present some concepts of the invention in a simplified form prior to the more detailed description that is presented hereinafter. The present invention involves hybrid Model Reference Adaptive System (MRAS)-based speed estimation and motor control techniques that are particularly useful in controlling AC induction motor speed during startup without the need for tachometers or other speed sensors. The invention employs a torque-based MRAS error term over a first speed range, such as from zero to about 80% of full speed, and then a rotor-flux-based MRAS error term for a second speed range, wherein the hybrid MRAS components and closed loop controller are used in providing an estimated speed that is compared with a threshold to determine when the speed estimation switches from torque to flux-based MRAS. In certain embodiments, one of the MRAS error terms is provided to a regulating speed estimate controller, such as a proportional-integral (PI) controller, where the speed estimate controller generates the speed estimate with at least one speed estimate controller gain factor (e.g., K<sub>I </sub>and/or K<sub>P</sub>) being adjusted inversely with respect to the stator or rotor flux modulus, wherein the hybrid MRAS technique is less sensitive to motor parameter inaccuracy or variations compared with previous sensorless motor startup approaches, while retaining the cost and maintenance advantages of sensorless control.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In accordance with one or more aspects of the invention, a motor drive system is provided for operating an induction motor. The drive system includes a switching system for selectively coupling the motor leads to an AC power source, as well as a motor startup control system for controlling and estimating the motor speed during startup. The motor startup control system includes a hybrid MRAS component, a motor controller with an output driving a switch control circuit and speed estimate controller providing a rotor speed estimate, with an error selector to provide a speed estimate controller error input from a torque-based MRAS component when the rotor speed estimate is less than or equal to a first threshold or from a rotor flux-based MRAS component when the estimated speed is above the threshold. The torque-based MRAS component provides a first error term representing a difference between a calculated torque value and an estimated torque value, while the flux-based MRAS component provides a second error term based on a difference between a calculated rotor flux and an estimated rotor flux, which can be computed as a vector product. The speed estimate controller provides the speed estimate during startup according to the selected controller error input, with one or more speed estimate controller gain factors being adapted or adjusted based on the stator or rotor flux modulus.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In one embodiment, the control system evaluates stator equations to derive a calculated rotor flux according to current and voltage feedback values, and evaluates rotor equations to derive an estimated rotor flux according to current feedback values and according to the most recent rotor speed estimate. The torque-based MRAS component computes a calculated torque value according to the calculated rotor flux and computes an estimated torque value according to the estimated rotor flux, and then provides the first error term as the difference between the calculated and estimated torque values. In this example, the rotor flux-based MRAS component provides the second error term as a vector product of the calculated rotor flux and the estimated rotor flux from the stator and rotor equations. The motor drive system may also include bypass switches to selectively to connect the motor leads to the AC power source bypassing the switching system, with a bypass controller to activate the bypass switches when the rotor speed exceeds a second threshold value.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Further aspects of the invention provide a system for controlling the speed of an electric motor during startup. The system is comprised of a speed estimate controller providing a rotor speed estimate according to a controller error input and a motor controller providing a controller output for controlling the motor speed during startup according to a desired startup speed profile and according to the estimated motor speed. The system further includes a hybrid model reference adaptive system (MRAS) component, with a torque-based MRAS component providing a first error term representing a difference between a calculated torque value and an estimated torque value, and a rotor flux-based MRAS component providing a second error term representing a difference between a calculated rotor flux and an estimated rotor flux. An error selector is operatively coupled with the hybrid MRAS component and with the speed estimate controller to provide the error input to the speed estimate controller, where the first error term is provided as the controller error input when the rotor speed estimate is less than or equal to a first threshold and the second error term is provided as the controller error input when the rotor speed estimate is greater than the first threshold.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Other aspects of the invention relate to a hybrid model reference adaptive system (MRAS) motor speed estimation system for estimating the speed of an electric motor. The hybrid MRAS system includes a speed estimate regulator or controller, torque and flux based MRAS components, and an error selector, where the speed estimate controller provides a rotor speed estimate according to a controller error input, and the controller includes one or more gain factors that are adjusted at least partially based on a stator or rotor flux modulus. The torque-based MRAS component provides a first error term representing a difference between a calculated torque value and an estimated torque value, and the rotor flux-based MRAS component provides a second error term representing a difference between a calculated rotor flux and an estimated rotor flux. The error selector provides the error input to the speed estimate controller according to the first error term when the rotor speed estimate is in a first speed range and provides the error input according to the second error term when the rotor speed estimate is in a second speed range.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Further aspects of the invention relate to a method for controlling the speed of an electric motor. The method includes providing a rotor speed estimate according to a controller error input, computing a first error term as the difference between a calculated torque value and an estimated torque value, computing a second error term as a vector product of a calculated rotorflux and an estimated rotor flux, and providing the error input to the controller according to the first error term when the rotor speed estimate is in a first speed range and providing the error input according to the second error term when the rotor speed estimate is in a second speed range. In certain embodiments, the method also includes adjusting at least one gain factor of the controller at least in part according to a stator or rotor flux modulus.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The following description and drawings set forth certain illustrative implementations of the invention in detail, which are indicative of several exemplary ways in which the principles of the invention may be carried out. The illustrated examples, however, are not exhaustive of the many possible embodiments of the invention. Other objects, advantages and novel features of the invention will be set forth in the following detailed description of the invention when considered in conjunction with the drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a detailed schematic diagram illustrating an exemplary motor drive system for driving an induction motor, including a hybrid MRAS-based startup control system for controlling and estimating motor speed during startup and a bypass system for operating the motor at full speed;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating further details of the speed estimation system of the MRAS-based startup control system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a graph of motor speed vs. time during startup, showing control of the motor speed in first and second ranges in the system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> according to a threshold;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow diagram illustrating an exemplary method for motor startup control and speed estimation using a first error term from a torque-based MRAS system in a first speed range and using a second error term from a rotor-flux-based MRAS in a second speed range; and</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref> are detailed flow diagrams illustrating exemplary speed estimate update operation using a hybrid torque and rotor flux-based MRAS system.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Referring now to the figures, several embodiments or implementations of the present invention are hereinafter described in conjunction with the drawings, wherein like reference numerals are used to refer to like elements throughout, the invention is hereinafter illustrated and described in the context of startup control for a three-phase induction motor, although the invention is not limited to the illustrated examples and can be employed in controlling AC motors of any number of phases. The embodiments illustrated below employ closed-loop control of motor speed during startup, in which an error value used by a regulating controller is obtained using a torque-based MRAS component for a first range of speeds, and then the error is obtained for a second speed rage using a rotor flux-based MRAS component, thereby providing hybrid MRAS speed estimation and control. The inventors have found that the hybrid MRAS approach can be easily implemented in existing motor control apparatus, including soft starters and other motor control devices, and may facilitate uniform speed tracking performance throughout a motor startup process wherein certain motor control drives can be upgraded to implement various features of the invention by software updates in order to implement the hybrid MRAS concepts illustrated and described herein. For instance, where the stator resistance is known or can be measured, the hybrid MRAS systems can be implemented to yield good speed estimation and control performance to facilitate linear ramp control or any other form of desired speed control profile desired by a user.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">While not wishing to be tied to any particular theory, the inventors take advantage of the fact that the flux linkages of a motor can be calculated from a set of stator equations and a set of rotor equations, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5B and 5C</figref> below, wherein the stator equations do not involve motor speed and can thus be regarded as a reference model. The rotor equations, however, include speed and are thus used as an adjustable model, where the motor speed (e.g., rotor speed) is a parameter in the adjustable model. Moreover, the inventors have appreciated that the estimated torque changes proportionally with the speed estimation error throughout a significant major portion of the startup process, i.e., over a first speed range, wherein a torque-based MRAS component can be successfully used to provide a closed loop control/estimation error term in this first range of speeds. However, the inventors have further found that this relationship does not hold for higher speeds (e.g., in a second speed range), wherein the speed estimation error has almost no impact on rotor flux estimation until the motor speed is in this second (higher) range. The invention uses these discoveries in providing control based on the torque MRAS for low speeds and then using flux-based MRAS components to generate the error term in a second higher speed range, which can be used in motor startup control for implementing any desired speed control profile or operating mode, including but not limited to current limiting mode, soft start mode, current limit with kickstart mode, soft start with kickstart mode, etc., for both no load and loaded operation. The exemplary hybrid MRAS techniques illustrated and described below employ a threshold speed value defining the boundary between the first and second speed ranges, where any suitable threshold value may be used. In one example, the threshold may be set at about 80% of the motor's full speed, with torque-based MRAS being used for 0 to about 80% of rated speed, and rotor-flux-based MRAS being employed for the second 80%˜100% speed range, where the estimated speed is used for switching between the two control ranges.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In these examples, moreover, the adaptive regulator or controller gain is auto-adjusted to be inversely proportional to the square of the stator or rotor flux modulus. In the illustrated examples below, leakage inductance is removed from the reference model in the torque-based stage, where the calculated torque is essentially accurate since stator resistance R<sub>S </sub>is the only motor parameter in the reference model, and Rs has been found to be fairly constant during the startup process. The stator equations yield the stator flux term ψ<sub>S </sub>and the proportional and integral gains K<sub>P </sub>and K<sub>I </sub>of a PI type controller are adjusted based on the reciprocal of the square of the stator flux 1/|ψ<sub>S</sub>|<sup>2 </sup>(or based on the reciprocal of the square of the rotor flux 1/|ψ<sub>r</sub>|<sup>2</sup>) such that the adjustment of the controller gains is essentially free of motor parameter variations since its calculation involves only stator resistance Rs, which can be considered constant during startup, where R<sub>S </sub>can be measured or estimated using any suitable techniques in constructing the stator equations. In the rotor-flux-based control range, the motor is approaching full speed, wherein the remaining motor parameters approach normal values, by which the speed estimation provides an accurate speed value until well after the motor transitions into steady-state operation.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> show an exemplary motor drive system <b>2</b> for driving a polyphase induction motor <b>4</b> using power from a three phase AC power source <b>6</b>. The system <b>2</b> includes a switching system <b>10</b> with three pairs of SCR switching devices <b>10</b><i>a</i>, <b>10</b><i>b</i>, <b>10</b><i>c </i>coupled between power supply lines A, B, and C of the AC power source <b>6</b> and leads R, S, and T of the motor <b>4</b>, respectively, with the individual switching devices operating to selectively couple a corresponding motor lead to the AC power source according to a corresponding switch control signal <b>22</b>. In this manner portions of the power supply voltages can be applied to the motor windings to generate/create motor phase currents I<sub>R</sub>, I<sub>S</sub>, and I<sub>T</sub>. Each phase coupling also includes a bypass switch <b>12</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b><i>b</i>, and <b>12</b><i>c</i>, respectively, to selectively bypass the switching system <b>10</b> and the switch pairs <b>10</b><i>a</i>, <b>10</b><i>b</i>, and <b>10</b><i>c </i>thereof by connecting the motor leads R, S, and T to the AC power source lines A, B, and C according to a bypass control signal <b>16</b> from a bypass control component <b>14</b>. The switching system <b>10</b> is operated by a hybrid MRAS-based startup control system <b>20</b> for controlling motor speed during startup, which includes a hybrid MRAS-based speed estimation system <b>20</b><i>a </i>for providing a speed estimate ω′r using torque and rotor flux-based MRAS components <b>34</b> and <b>36</b>. While illustrated with SCR type switches <b>10</b><i>a</i>-<b>10</b><i>c</i>, any type of electrical switching devices may be used in the system <b>10</b> and for the bypass switches <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The startup control system <b>2</b> and the speed estimation system <b>20</b><i>a </i>thereof can be implemented as any suitable hardware, software, and/or combinations thereof, where the control system <b>20</b> includes a switch control circuit <b>24</b> with circuitry for providing a plurality of switch control signals <b>22</b> to control operation of the switching devices <b>10</b><i>a</i>, <b>10</b><i>b</i>, and <b>10</b><i>c </i>of the switching system <b>10</b> during startup of the motor <b>4</b> according a control output signal <b>25</b><i>a </i>from a motor controller <b>25</b>, which can be any suitable controller or regulator <b>25</b> by which the motor is controlled according to drive process feedback <b>18</b> and an estimated motor speed signal ω′r from the speed estimation system <b>20</b><i>a</i>. In addition, the motor controller <b>25</b> can be operated in a number of different modes or control schemes, including controlling torque, speed, etc., wherein the exemplary motor controller <b>25</b> operates to control the speed of the induction motor <b>4</b> during startup according to a user defined startup speed profile <b>28</b>. The switch control circuit <b>24</b> provides appropriate switching signals <b>22</b> to operate the motor <b>4</b> in accordance with the motor control output <b>25</b><i>a</i>, which may include pulse width modulation or other switch timing control.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The hybrid MRAS speed estimation system <b>20</b><i>a </i>includes a PI controller <b>26</b> providing the speed estimate ω′r in radians per second, revolutions per minute, or other suitable units, which is indicative of the speed of the motor <b>4</b> at any given time. In this regard, the speed estimation may be performed at a rather high sampling rate such as every 100 us in one example, whereas the speed control of motor controller <b>25</b> may in certain embodiments be carried out at a slower rate, such as every 50 ms. The PI controller <b>26</b> in the speed estimation system <b>20</b><i>a </i>provides the speed estimate ω′r during startup and thereafter according to a controller error input e. The speed estimation system <b>20</b><i>a </i>also includes a hybrid model reference adaptive system (MRAS) component <b>38</b> with a torque-based MRAS component <b>34</b> providing a first error term ε<sub>1 </sub>representing the difference or error between a calculated torque value <b>34</b><i>b </i>(torque T in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), and an estimated torque value <b>34</b><i>a </i>(T′ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). The hybrid MRAS component <b>38</b> also includes a rotor flux-based MRAS component <b>36</b> providing a second error term ε<sub>2 </sub>representing the difference or error between a calculated rotor flux <b>36</b><i>b </i>(ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq </sub>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) and an estimated rotor flux <b>36</b><i>a </i>(ψ′<sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq </sub>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), which may be computed as a vector product with the calculated and estimated polyphase flux terms ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq </sub>and ψ′<sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq </sub>being represented in the arbitrary dual axis reference frame (d-q frame). These two MRAS components <b>34</b> and <b>36</b> provide the respective error terms ε<sub>1 </sub>and ε<sub>2 </sub>to an error selector <b>40</b> providing a comparison function <b>44</b> and a switching function <b>46</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) to provide the error input e to the speed estimate PI controller <b>26</b> as the first error term ε<sub>1 </sub>when the rotor speed estimate ω′r is less than or equal to a first threshold TH<b>1</b> <b>42</b> (a first speed range) or as the second error term ε<sub>2 </sub>when the rotor speed estimate is greater than the threshold <b>42</b> (a second speed range). Any threshold TH<b>1</b> <b>42</b> can be used, for example, about 80% of the rated full speed of the motor <b>4</b> in one embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The speed estimate controller <b>26</b> operates in generally continuous fashion to provide the motor speed estimate ω′r, with the switching system <b>10</b> providing feedback current and voltage values <b>18</b> from the motor drive process to the control system <b>20</b>, such as phase or line voltages, stator current values, etc. The speed estimation system <b>20</b><i>a </i>includes stator equations <b>32</b> and rotor equations <b>30</b>, as well as known or estimated values (e.g., resistances, inductances, number of poles P, etc.) for computing calculated and estimated flux and torque values using the current and voltage feedback <b>18</b> as inputs, where the calculated and estimated flux values ψ may also be represented in the d-q frame format. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the rotor speed estimate ω′r is provided by the PI speed estimate controller <b>26</b> to the rotor equations <b>30</b>, and also to the motor controller <b>25</b> and the bypass control component <b>14</b>, which selectively provides the bypass control signal <b>16</b> to bypass the switching system <b>10</b> when the rotor speed estimate ω′r is greater than a second threshold TH<b>2</b> <b>14</b><i>a</i>. As best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, moreover, the solutions X to the stator equations <b>30</b> (e.g., calculated rotor flux values ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq</sub>) are provided as inputs to the torque-based MRAS component <b>34</b> and to the rotor-flux based MRAS component <b>36</b>. In addition, the reciprocal of the square of the stator flux modulus 1/|ψ<sub>S</sub>|<sup>2 </sup>(e.g., or the reciprocal of the square of the rotor flux modulus 1/|ψ<sub>r</sub>|<sup>2</sup>) is provided from the stator equations <b>32</b> to the speed estimate controller <b>26</b> for adjustment of the PI controller gains K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In operation, the speed estimation system <b>20</b><i>a </i>in the motor startup control system <b>20</b> evaluates the stator equations <b>32</b> to derive a calculated rotor flux <b>36</b><i>b </i>(ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq </sub>in the d-q reference frame, as shown best in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) according to the current and voltage feedback values <b>18</b>, and evaluates the rotor equations <b>30</b> to derive an estimated rotor flux <b>36</b><i>a </i>(ψ′<sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq</sub>) according to the feedback values <b>18</b> and according to the rotor speed estimate ω′r. The system <b>20</b><i>a </i>also computes either the stator flux modulus |ψ<sub>S</sub>|<sup>2 </sup>or the rotor flux modulus |ψ<sub>r</sub>|<sup>2</sup>. The torque-based MRAS component <b>34</b>, in turn computes a calculated torque value T according to the calculated rotor flux <b>36</b><i>b </i>(ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq</sub>) and computes an estimated torque value T′ according to the estimated rotor flux <b>36</b><i>a </i>(ψ′<sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq</sub>). The torque-based MRAS component <b>34</b> then provides the first error term ε<sub>1 </sub>as the difference between the calculated and estimated torque values <b>36</b><i>b </i>and <b>36</b><i>a</i>, respectively (ε<sub>1</sub>=T−T′). The rotor flux-based MRAS component <b>36</b> provides the second error term ε<sub>2 </sub>as a vector product of the calculated rotor flux <b>36</b><i>b </i>(ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq</sub>) and the estimated rotor flux <b>36</b><i>a </i>(ψ′<sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq</sub>).</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Referring also to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a plot <b>52</b> is provided in a graph <b>50</b> showing motor speed ω′r vs. time t, wherein the system <b>2</b> provides for torque MRAS based speed estimation and speed control using the first error term ε<sub>1 </sub>in a first speed range <b>54</b> from zero to a first threshold speed value TH<b>1</b> (threshold <b>42</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>). When the estimated speed ω′r exceeds the threshold TH<b>1</b> in a second speed range <b>56</b>, the speed estimate controller <b>26</b> uses the second error term ε<sub>2 </sub>(rotor flux-based MRAS control) until the speed ω′r exceeds the second (bypass) threshold TH<b>2</b> (TH<b>2</b> <b>14</b><i>a </i>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), at which time the bypass control <b>14</b> provides the bypass control signal <b>16</b> to activate bypass switches <b>12</b><i>a</i>-<b>12</b><i>c</i>, wherein the bypass threshold TH<b>2</b> is typically above the first threshold TH<b>1</b>, and preferably near the full speed FS rating for the motor <b>4</b>. The control system <b>20</b> can be employed for dual range control and/or speed estimation techniques using a hybrid MRAS approach to achieve a substantially uniform speed tracking performance throughout the startup speed range without the need for external tachometers or other sensors, and without suffering from noise associated with conventional harmonic measurement estimation techniques. Thus, the system <b>20</b> facilitates advanced sensorless control of startup speed profile in soft starters and other motor control applications.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-5C</figref>, the motor control and speed estimation aspects of the hybrid MRAS approach are further illustrated in a flow diagram <b>70</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> showing an exemplary method for motor startup control and speed estimation using a first error term ε<sub>1 </sub>from a torque-based MRAS system (e.g., <b>34</b> above) in a first speed range (range <b>54</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) and using a second error term ε<sub>2 </sub>from a rotor-flux-based MRAS (<b>36</b>) in a second speed range (<b>56</b>). Although illustrated as a single flow, it will be appreciated that the speed estimation and motor control loops can be processed separately at different update rates, for instance, wherein the speed control loop will typically be processed at a lower rate than the speed estimation loop. Moreover, the hybrid MRAS-based speed estimation process can continue operating even after the startup process is complete (e.g., during bypass operation), in order to provide sensorless speed value feedback for steady state motor control or data acquisition. The process <b>70</b> begins at <b>72</b>, in which the rotor speed is estimated using a first error term ε<sub>1 </sub>from a torque-based MRAS system (MRAS <b>34</b>), and the motor phase switches (e.g., switches <b>10</b><i>a</i>, <b>10</b><i>b</i>, and <b>10</b><i>c </i>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) are controlled at <b>74</b> according to the desired motor startup speed profile (speed profile <b>28</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) and the speed estimate ω′r. A determination is made at <b>76</b> as to whether the estimated rotor speed ω′r is greater than the threshold TH<b>1</b> (e.g., greater than about 80% of rated speed in one example). If not (NO at <b>76</b>), the method <b>70</b> returns to <b>74</b> to continue motor control and torque-based MRAS speed estimation according to error term ε<sub>1</sub>. Once the speed ω′r exceeds TH<b>1</b> (YES at <b>76</b>), the second speed range (e.g., range <b>56</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) is entered, and the startup process continues to <b>78</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, where the rotor speed ω′r is estimated using a second error term ε<sub>2 </sub>from a rotor flux-based MRAS system (MRAS <b>36</b>) and the motor switching is controlled according to the desired speed profile and the speed estimate ω′r. The speed estimate ω′r is compared to a second (e.g., bypass) threshold TH<b>2</b> at <b>80</b> (e.g., bypass threshold <b>14</b><i>a </i>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), and if the speed is still in the second range (NO at <b>80</b>), the method <b>70</b> returns to <b>78</b> to continue rotor flux-based MRAS speed estimation according to error term ε<sub>2 </sub>and corresponding motor speed control. When the speed estimate ω′r exceeds TH<b>2</b> (YES at <b>80</b>), the startup control switches are bypassed at <b>82</b> and the motor leads are connected to the power leads (e.g., bypassed) to complete the motor startup process <b>70</b> at <b>84</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref> illustrate an example of the speed estimate update operation <b>100</b> using a hybrid torque and flux-based MRAS system <b>20</b><i>a</i>. The speed estimate update process <b>100</b> begins at <b>102</b>, wherein the most recent current and voltage feedback values are obtained at <b>104</b> for use at <b>106</b> and <b>108</b> in evaluating or solving stator and rotor equations (e.g., equations <b>32</b> and <b>30</b> in the controller <b>20</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> above). At <b>106</b>, the stator equations are evaluated using the feedback values to obtain calculated rotor flux and torque values ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq </sub><b>36</b><i>b </i>and T <b>34</b><i>b</i>, respectively. As best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>, the stator equations <b>32</b> are evaluated at <b>106</b><i>a </i>using the feedback values <b>18</b> for the motor terminal voltages V<sub>D</sub>, V<sub>Q </sub>and stator currents I<sub>D</sub>, I<sub>Q </sub>as well as the mutual inductance L<sub>m</sub>, the rotor and stator inductances L<sub>r </sub>and L<sub>s</sub>, and the stator resistance R<sub>s</sub>, to obtain the calculated rotor flux value ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq</sub>, where the values for L<sub>m</sub>, L<sub>r</sub>, L<sub>s</sub>, and R<sub>s </sub>can be measured values or may be estimated or otherwise specified based on the particular motor <b>4</b> being controlled. The torque-based MRAS component <b>34</b> then computes the calculated torque value T <b>34</b><i>b </i>at <b>106</b><i>b </i>based on the calculated rotor flux values ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq </sub><b>36</b><i>b</i>, the feedback values <b>18</b>, and the stator resistance R<sub>S</sub>. Referring back to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, the rotor equations <b>30</b> are evaluated at <b>108</b> using the current feedback values <b>18</b> and the most recent rotor speed estimate ω′r to obtain estimated rotor flux and torque values <b>36</b><i>a </i>and <b>34</b><i>a </i>(ψ′<sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq</sub>, and T′ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). As best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>, the rotor equations <b>30</b> employ the feedback values <b>18</b> (I<sub>D</sub>, and I<sub>Q</sub>) along with the speed estimate ω′r and the motor parameters L<sub>m</sub>, L<sub>r</sub>, and R<sub>r </sub>at <b>108</b><i>a </i>from which the flux values <b>36</b><i>a ψ′</i><sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq </sub>can be computed. At <b>108</b><i>b</i>, the torque-based MRAS component <b>34</b> then computes the estimated torque value T′ using the motor parameters L<sub>m</sub>, L<sub>r</sub>, and the estimated rotor flux values <b>36</b><i>a ψ′</i><sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, once the calculated and estimated flux and torque values have been obtained from evaluation of the stator and rotor equations <b>32</b> and <b>30</b> at <b>106</b> and <b>108</b>, respectively, the speed estimate update process <b>100</b> continues at <b>110</b>, where the first error term ε<sub>1 </sub>is computed (e.g., by the torque-based MRAS component <b>34</b>) from the calculated and estimated torque values T <b>34</b><i>b </i>and T′ <b>34</b><i>a</i>, respectively, wherein ε<sub>1 </sub>is computed as T−T′ in the illustrated embodiment. At <b>112</b>, the second error term ε<sub>2 </sub>is computed (e.g., by the flux-based MRAS component <b>36</b>) from the calculated and estimated rotor flux values ψ<sub>rd</sub>, ψ<sub>rq </sub><b>36</b><i>b </i>and ψ′<sub>rd</sub>, ψ′<sub>rq </sub><b>36</b><i>a</i>, respectively. In this example, the second error term ε<sub>2 </sub>is computed as a vector product ψ<sub>rq</sub>*ψ′<sub>rd</sub>−ψ<sub>rd</sub>*ψ′<sub>rq</sub>. At <b>113</b>, a flux modulus is calculated for use by the estimation controller, which can be either the stator flux modulus |ψ<sub>S</sub>| or the rotor flux modulus |ψ<sub>r</sub>|, The current speed is then estimated at <b>114</b> using one of the error terms ε<sub>1 </sub>and ε<sub>2</sub>, where the controller <b>26</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) generates a new estimate of the speed ω′r based on the controller gain parameters K<sub>P </sub><b>26</b><i>a </i>and K<sub>I </sub><b>26</b><i>b </i>(<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), the reciprocal of the square of either the stator flux modulus 1/|ψ<sub>S</sub>|<sup>2 </sup>or the rotor flux modulus 1/|ψ<sub>r</sub>|<sup>2</sup>, and the controller error input e (selected as either ε<sub>1 </sub>or ε<sub>2 </sub>based on the current speed estimate ω′r from the last update cycle), and the estimate update is completed at <b>116</b>. In the illustrated example, the gain parameters K<sub>P </sub><b>26</b><i>a </i>and K<sub>I </sub><b>26</b><i>b </i>are modified according to the flux modulus by the modified PI control output equation ω′r=(K<sub>P</sub>+(K<sub>I</sub>/S))*e/(|ψ<sub>S</sub>|<sup>2</sup>), where e=ε<sub>1 </sub>for ω′r less than or equal to TH<b>1</b> and e=ε<sub>2 </sub>for ω′r greater than TH<b>1</b>. In this manner, the controller <b>26</b> provides the motor speed estimate ω′r using a dual range hybrid MRAS technique based on either torque or flux-based MRAS components with K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P </sub>being modified or adapted according to the reciprocal of the square of the flux modulus.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The above examples are merely illustrative of several possible embodiments of various aspects of the present invention, wherein equivalent alterations and/or modifications will occur to others skilled in the art upon reading and understanding this specification and the annexed drawings. In particular regard to the various functions performed by the above described components (assemblies, devices, systems, circuits, and the like), the terms (including a reference to a “means”) used to describe such components are intended to correspond, unless otherwise indicated, to any component, such as hardware, software, or combinations thereof, which performs the specified function of the described component (i.e., that is functionally equivalent), even though not structurally equivalent to the disclosed structure which performs the function in the illustrated implementations of the invention. In addition, although a particular feature of the invention may have been disclosed with respect to only one of several implementations, such feature may be combined with one or more other features of the other implementations as may be desired and advantageous for any given or particular application. Also, to the extent that the terms “including”, “includes”, “having”, “has”, “with”, or variants thereof are used in the detailed description and/or in the claims, such terms are intended to be inclusive in a manner similar to the term “comprising”.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A motor drive system, comprising:
<claim-text>a switching system including a plurality of switching devices coupled between a power source and a motor and operative according to a corresponding plurality of switch control signals; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a motor startup control system for controlling the motor speed during startup, the motor startup control system comprising:
<claim-text>a hybrid model reference adaptive system (MRAS) component including:
<claim-text>a torque-based MRAS component providing a first error term at least partially according to a calculated torque value and an estimated torque value; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotor flux-based MRAS component providing a second error term at least partially according to a calculated rotor flux and an estimated rotor flux;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a speed estimate controller providing a rotor speed estimate according to a controller error input;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a motor controller providing a motor controller output for controlling the motor speed during startup according to a desired startup speed profile and according to the rotor speed estimate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch control circuit providing the switch control signals to the switching system during startup of the motor according to the controller output; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an error selector operatively coupled with the hybrid MRAS component and with the speed estimate controller to provide the error input to the speed estimate controller, the error selector providing the first error term as the controller error input when the rotor speed estimate is in a first speed range and providing the second error term as the controller error input when the rotor speed estimate is in a second speed range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising bypass switches operative to selectively bypass the switching system by connecting the motor leads to the power source according to a bypass control signal; and a bypass control component receiving the rotor speed estimate from the speed estimate controller and providing the bypass control signal to bypass the switching system when the rotor speed estimate is in a third speed range.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first speed range is from zero to about 80% of the rated full speed of the motor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>:
<claim-text>wherein the motor startup control system evaluates stator equations to derive a calculated rotor flux according to current and voltage feedback values, and evaluates rotor equations to derive an estimated rotor flux according to current and voltage feedback values and according to the rotor speed estimate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the torque-based MRAS component computes a calculated torque value according to the calculated rotor flux, computes an estimated torque value according to the estimated rotor flux, and provides the first error term as the difference between the calculated and estimated torque values; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the rotor flux-based MRAS component provides the second error term as a vector product of the calculated rotor flux and the estimated rotor flux.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>:
<claim-text>wherein the motor startup control system computes one of a stator flux modulus and a rotor flux modulus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the speed estimate controller is a proportional integral (PI) controller with proportional and integral gains K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P</sub>, respectively;</claim-text>
<claim-text>and wherein the speed estimate controller adjusts K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P </sub>according to a reciprocal of the square of the stator or rotor flux modulus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising bypass switches operative to selectively bypass the switching system by connecting the motor leads to the power source according to a bypass control signal; and a bypass control component receiving the rotor speed estimate from the speed estimate controller and providing the bypass control signal to bypass the switching system when the rotor speed estimate is greater than a second threshold.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising bypass switches operative to selectively bypass the switching system by connecting the motor leads to the power source according to a bypass control signal; and a bypass control component receiving the rotor speed estimate from the speed estimate controller and providing the bypass control signal to bypass the switching system when the rotor speed estimate is greater than a second threshold.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>:
<claim-text>wherein the motor startup control system computes one of a stator flux modulus and a rotor flux modulus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the speed estimate controller is a proportional integral (PI) controller with proportional and integral gains K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P</sub>, respectively;</claim-text>
<claim-text>and wherein the speed estimate controller adjusts K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P </sub>according to a reciprocal of the square of the stator or rotor flux modulus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising bypass switches operative to selectively bypass the switching system by connecting the motor leads to the power source according to a bypass control signal; and a bypass control component receiving the rotor speed estimate from the speed estimate controller and providing the bypass control signal to bypass the switching system when the rotor speed estimate is in a third speed range.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The motor drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein at least one gain value in the speed estimate controller is adjusted at least in part according to one of a stator flux modulus and a rotor flux modulus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A control system for controlling the speed of an electric motor, comprising:
<claim-text>a speed estimate controller providing a rotor speed estimate according to a controller error input;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a hybrid model reference adaptive system (MRAS) component, including a torque-based MRAS component providing a first error term based on a calculated torque value and an estimated torque value, and a rotor flux-based MRAS component providing a second error term based on a calculated rotor flux and an estimated rotor flux;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an error selector operatively coupled with the hybrid MRAS component and with the speed estimate controller to provide the error input to the speed estimate controller, the error selector providing the first error term as the controller error input when the rotor speed estimate is in a first speed range and providing the second error term as the controller error input when the rotor speed estimate is in a second speed range; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a motor controller providing a controller output for controlling the motor speed according to a desired speed profile and according to the rotor speed estimate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The control system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the first speed range is from zero to about 80% of the rated full speed of the motor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The control system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the control system evaluates stator equations to derive a calculated rotor flux according to current and voltage feedback values, and evaluates rotor equations to derive an estimated rotor flux according to current and voltage feedback values and according to the rotor speed estimate, wherein the torque-based MRAS component computes a calculated torque value according to the calculated rotor flux, computes an estimated torque value according to the estimated rotor flux, and provides the first error term as the difference between the calculated and estimated torque values, and wherein the rotor flux-based MRAS component provides the second error term as a vector product of the calculated rotor flux and the estimated rotor flux.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The control system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the control system computes one of a stator flux modulus and a rotor flux modulus, wherein the speed estimate controller is a proportional integral (PI) controller with proportional and integral gains K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P</sub>, respectively, and wherein the speed estimate controller adjusts K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P </sub>according to a reciprocal of the square of either the stator flux modulus or the rotor flux modulus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The control system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein at least one gain value in the controller is adjusted according to a stator flux modulus or a rotor flux modulus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A hybrid model reference adaptive system (MRAS) motor speed estimation system for estimating the speed of an electric motor, comprising:
<claim-text>a speed estimate controller providing a rotor speed estimate according to a controller error input;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a torque-based MRAS component providing a first error term based at least partially on a calculated torque value and an estimated torque value;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotor flux-based MRAS component providing a second error term based at least partially on a calculated rotor flux and an estimated rotor flux; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an error selector providing the error input to the speed estimate controller according to the first error term when the rotor speed estimate is in a first speed range and providing the error input according to the second error term when the rotor speed estimate is in a second speed range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The motor speed estimation system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the torque-based MRAS component computes the calculated torque value and the estimated torque value, and provides the first error term as the difference between the calculated and estimated torque values, and wherein the rotor flux-based MRAS component provides the second error term as a vector product of the calculated rotor flux and the estimated rotor flux.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The motor speed estimation system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the speed estimate controller is a proportional integral (PI) controller with proportional and integral gains K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P</sub>, respectively, and wherein the speed estimate controller adjusts K<sub>I </sub>and K<sub>P </sub>according to either the stator flux modulus or the rotor flux modulus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method of controlling the speed of an electric motor, the method comprising:
<claim-text>providing a rotor speed estimate according to a controller error input;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a controller output according to the rotor speed estimate and according to a desired speed profile;</claim-text>
<claim-text>controlling the motor speed according to the controller output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>computing a first error term at least partially according to a calculated torque value and an estimated torque value;</claim-text>
<claim-text>computing a second error term at least partially according to a calculated rotor flux and an estimated rotor flux; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing the controller error input according to the first error term when the rotor speed estimate is in a first speed range and providing the error input according to the second error term when the rotor speed estimate is in a second speed range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, further comprising adjusting at least one gain factor of the controller at least in part according to a stator flux modulus or a rotor flux modulus.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
