<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298398-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298398</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10696281</doc-number>
<date>20031029</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>P2003-182778</doc-number>
<date>20030626</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>796</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>228</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34820899</main-classification>
<further-classification>348143</further-classification>
<further-classification>396 52</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Image capturing apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5389997</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ohishi</name>
<date>19950200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>396 53</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5708266</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Soshi et al.</name>
<date>19980100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>25023114</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6816288</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hashizume</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>358474</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6965400</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Haba et al.</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3482221</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6982746</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kawahara</name>
<date>20060100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>34820899</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-009367</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19980100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-033053</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34820899</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3482081</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3482083</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348143</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348154</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348155</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3482082</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3482084</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396 54</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396 52</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396155</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>396 53</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>12</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>16</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040263681</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20041230</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Teramoto</last-name>
<first-name>Tougo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wakayama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sato</last-name>
<first-name>Junji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sakai</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sidley Austin LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Konica Minolta Holdings, Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ye</last-name>
<first-name>Lin</first-name>
<department>2622</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Hernandez</last-name>
<first-name>Nelson D.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention provides a technique capable of changing the image capturing direction of a camera at high speed while suppressing noise generated by resonance. At the time of changing the angle of the image capturing direction of a surveillance camera from a base angle to a first angle, if driving of both of a motor for panning and a motor for tilting is simply started simultaneously and completed simultaneously, there is a case such that the motor for panning generates resonance with the body of the surveillance camera or the like and noise becomes too loud. In such a case, the drive speed of the motor for panning, that is, the pulse rate is shifted to a high speed side on which resonance does not generate and the panning is finished first. Specifically, the angle of the image capturing direction is changed from the base angle to a second angle and, after that, changed from the second angle to the first angle.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="143.09mm" wi="245.70mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="128.78mm" wi="152.23mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="188.81mm" wi="134.37mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="215.39mm" wi="141.31mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="221.06mm" wi="133.10mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="221.91mm" wi="132.67mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="131.23mm" wi="125.65mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="189.48mm" wi="112.52mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="163.91mm" wi="153.92mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="122.77mm" wi="114.22mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="171.87mm" wi="125.05mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="191.69mm" wi="144.44mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="94.83mm" wi="134.79mm" file="US07298398-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is based on application No. 2003-182778 filed in Japan, the contents of which are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to an image capturing apparatus capable of changing its image capturing direction in a state where a body of the image capturing apparatus is fixed.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Background Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Since a surveillance camera used by being mounted on the wall, the ceiling or the like of a room has to monitor a wide range, usually, the image capturing direction of the camera can be freely changed by the driving of various motors or the like by a remote control or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Conventionally, such a surveillance camera is turnable around two axes of the horizontal axis and the vertical axis. For example, in the case of using a pulse motor as a drive source for turning the camera around each of the horizontal and vertical axes, by controlling the turn amount in the turn direction around the horizontal axis as a center (hereinafter, referred to as “tilting direction”) and the turn amount in the turn direction around the vertical axis as a center (hereinafter, referred to as “panning direction”) in accordance with the number of pulses given to the pulse motors, a change in the image capturing direction can be easily controlled.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">However, generally, depending on the drive frequency, that is, the pulse rate (the number of pulses given per second, hereinafter, the unit will be abbreviated as “pps”) given to a pulse motor, the drive source such as a pulse motor generates resonance with a body of the surveillance camera or the like and noise generates. Consequently, since it is desirable to reduce noise sound as much as possible in a quiet room or the like, the drive source is driven generally on the basis of a pulse rate lower than the drive frequency at which resonance is caused (hereinafter, referred to as “resonance frequency”).</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">There are mainly two types of operating the surveillance camera. One of the types is a type of instructing only the driving direction and the other type is a type of directly instructing a target direction.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In the operation method of the former type, for example, by tilting an operation lever to a desired direction, the image capturing direction can be changed to the instructed direction. In order to stop the changing of the image capturing direction, it is sufficient to move the operation lever to the original position. In the operation method, the user has to operate the lever while watching a captured image and, when the image capturing direction reaches a desired direction, move the lever to the original position to stop the changing of the image capturing direction. When the changing speed of the image capturing direction is too fast, it is difficult to perform an accurate operation. Therefore, it is desirable to change the image capturing direction slowly.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">On the other hand, in the operation method of the latter type, for example, a chart indicating a changeable range of the image capturing direction and the present image capturing direction are displayed on the screen of a personal computer or the like. By moving a cursor to a desired image capturing direction (target direction) and clicking the mouse, the image capturing direction can be automatically changed to the instructed target direction. In the operation method, when the target direction is directly designated, a turn in the panning direction and a turn in the tilting direction are simultaneously started and simultaneously completed, thereby enabling the image capturing direction to be changed to the designated target direction as fast as possible. Consequently, a time lag in changing of the image capturing direction is short and the operability is good.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In the operation method of the latter type, however, in order to change the image capturing direction to the target direction as fast as possible, when a pulse rate is simply changed, depending on the changing direction of the image capturing direction, the pulse rate given to one of the two pulse motors may enter the resonance frequency range and it causes large noise sound at the time of changing of the image capturing direction.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">As a technique of suppressing the noise which will be generated during changing of the image capturing direction, a noise preventing technique has been proposed, which suppresses noise caused by resonance resulting from vibration of an intermediate gear during changing of the image capturing direction by inserting a friction member into the intermediate gear for transmitting a driving force of a stepping motor to prevent vibration of the gear (for example, Japanese Patent Application Laid-Open No. 10-9367 (1998)).</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">However, since the resonance which generates during changing of the image capturing direction due to the motor itself is larger than the resonance which generates due to the gear, only by the countermeasure of suppressing the resonance which generates due to the gear like the above-described noise preventing technique, generation of the resonance during changing of the image capturing direction, that is, generation of noise cannot be sufficiently suppressed.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The present invention is directed to an image capturing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to an aspect of the present invention, an image capturing apparatus includes: an image capturing part for capturing an image of a subject; a plurality of drivers for driving the image capturing part in a plurality of directions on the basis of a plurality of drive speed control values, respectively; an instructor for instructing a designated amount of operation of the image capturing part; a detector for detecting whether or not each drive speed control value for the designated operation is within a structural resonance range of the image capturing part, to determine an objective drive speed control value which is within the structural resonance range among the plurality of drive speed control values; a changing part for changing the objective drive speed control value to an alternative drive speed control value to reduce a driving time period of the objective driver required for the designated amount of operation; and a controller for controlling the plurality of drivers with the plurality of drive speed control values in which the objective drive speed control value is changed to the alternative speed control value.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Since the first drive speed control value set as a value which lies within the structural resonance changed of the image capturing apparatus among the plurality of drive speed control values is changed so that drive time of the first driver based on the first drive speed control value becomes shorter and the first driver is driven, while suppressing noise caused by resonance, the image capturing direction of the apparatus can be changed at high speed.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">According to another aspect of the present invention, an image capturing apparatus includes: a first driver for changing a relative angle of an image capturing part to an image capturing apparatus body in a first direction; a second driver for changing the relative angle in a second direction; a controller for controlling respective driving operations of the first and second drivers; an instructor for instructing a designated amount of change in the relative angle for attaining a designated change in an image capturing direction; and a setting part for setting a first drive amount and a first drive speed control value for the first driver and setting a second drive amount and a second drive speed control value for the second driver on the basis of the designated amount of change in the relative angle instructed by the instructor. When resonance conditions that: i) the first drive amount is smaller than the second drive amount, and ii) the first drive speed control value is within a structural resonance range of the image capturing apparatus, are satisfied, the setting part changes the first drive speed control value to an alternative speed control value out of the resonance range. When the resonance conditions are satisfied, the controller controls the second driver drive on the basis of the second drive speed control value and controls the first driver drive on the basis of the alternative speed control value such that the first drive amount is attained by the first driver within a time period in which the second drive amount is attained by the second driver.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">At the time of changing the image capturing direction only by a designated amount by changing the relative angle of the image capturing part to the image capturing apparatus body by the first and second drivers, in the case where the conditions are satisfied that the first drive amount of the first driver is smaller than the second drive amount of the second driver and the first drive speed control value for the first driver is a value within the structural resonance range of the image capturing apparatus, the first drive speed control value is changed to an alternative value out of the resonance range and the first driver is driven only by the first drive amount in the drive period of the second driver. Thus, while suppressing noise caused by resonance, the image capturing direction of the apparatus can be changed at high speed.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">According to still another aspect of the present invention, an image capturing apparatus includes: a first driver for changing a relative angle of an image capturing part to an image capturing apparatus body in a first direction; a second driver for changing the relative angle in a second direction; a controller for controlling the first and second drivers; and an instructor for instructing a designated amount of change in the relative angle for attaining a designated change in an image capturing direction. The controller is operable to attain the designated amount of change in the relative angle with a combination of: a) a first control time period in which the controller controls the first and second drivers on the basis of first and second drive speed control values, respectively, and b) a second control time period following the first time period in which the controller controls the first and second drivers while stopping one of the first and second drivers. The first and second drive speed control values are determined out of a structural resonance range of the image capturing apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">At the time of changing the image capturing direction only by a designated amount by changing the relative angle of the image capturing part to the image capturing apparatus body by the first and second drivers, from start of driving of the first and second drivers to a specific time point, the first and second drivers drive on the basis of drive speed control values for the first and second drivers set out of the structural resonance range of the image capturing apparatus. After the specific time point until a designated change in the image capturing direction is completed, one of the first and second drivers is stopped. Thus, while suppressing noise caused by resonance, the image capturing direction of the camera can be changed at high speed.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Therefore, an object of the present invention is to provide a technique capable of changing the image capturing direction of an image capturing apparatus at high speed while suppressing noise caused by resonance.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">These and other objects, features, aspects and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description of the present invention when taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram showing the outline of a surveillance camera system according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram illustrating a swing mechanism of a surveillance camera;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram showing the functional configuration of driving of the swing mechanism;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a diagram showing an operation screen for changing the image capturing direction;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a diagram showing changing a relative angle of the image capturing direction to a body of the image capturing apparatus;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a diagram showing the changing the relative angle of the image capturing direction which is converted in the number of pulses given to a motor;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a diagram showing the relationship between the pulse rate given to the motor and noise level;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a diagram showing the relationship between a combination of a pulse rate given to a pan motor and a pulse rate given to a tilt motor and resonance;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a diagram illustrating a motor control method in the case where the pulse rate of a motor which is driven at lower speed than another motor lies in a resonance range;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a flowchart showing the flow of operation of changing the image capturing direction;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a flowchart showing the flow of operation of changing the image capturing direction;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a flowchart showing the flow of operation of changing the image capturing direction;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a diagram illustrating the swing mechanism using a truss-structured actuator;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a diagram showing the configuration of the truss-structured actuator; and</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is a diagram showing the relationship between the duty ratio of a drive signal given to the truss-structured actuator and noise.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Hereinafter, embodiments of the present invention will be described with reference to the drawings.</p>
<p id="h-0005" num="0000">Outline of Surveillance Camera System</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram showing an outline of a surveillance camera system <b>1</b> as an example of an image capturing apparatus according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The surveillance camera system <b>1</b> has a surveillance camera <b>10</b> and a controller <b>20</b> for controlling the surveillance camera <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The surveillance camera <b>10</b> mainly has a housing <b>11</b>, a transparent cover <b>12</b> constructed by a combination of an almost semi-spherical portion and an almost semi-cylindrical portion, and a camera unit <b>50</b> covered with the transparent cover <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The camera unit <b>50</b> has an image capturing unit <b>60</b> for acquiring image data of a subject, and a driving mechanism (hereinafter, referred to as “swing mechanism”) <b>40</b> for changing the image capturing direction (the direction of the optical axis of the taking lens) of the image capturing unit <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The image capturing unit <b>60</b> faces the front in the state where a direction ST perpendicular to a face <b>11</b><i>a </i>on which the camera unit <b>50</b> is provided of the housing <b>11</b> is the image capturing direction. The image capturing direction of the image capturing unit <b>60</b> can be changed by the swing mechanism <b>40</b> by using the direction (front direction) ST as a reference. The concrete structure and the like of the swing mechanism <b>40</b> will be described later.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The housing <b>11</b> has various processing blocks for driving the image capturing unit <b>60</b>, performing communication, and capturing and processing image data acquired by the image capturing unit <b>60</b>. In the following, a part fixed to the wall, such as the housing <b>11</b> will be also referred to as the surveillance camera body.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The surveillance camera <b>10</b> and the controller <b>20</b> are connected to each other via a communication line <b>30</b> such as a LAN cable or another wireless line.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The controller <b>20</b> is constructed by a general personal computer or the like and has an operation unit <b>22</b> including a keyboard and a mouse, a monitor <b>21</b>, and a control unit (so-called personal computer body) <b>23</b>. The control unit <b>23</b> has therein a hard disk for storing image data captured by the surveillance camera <b>10</b> and a central processing unit for controlling various data communications with the surveillance camera <b>10</b> and the driving of the surveillance camera <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">An operation screen for changing the image capturing direction of the image capturing unit <b>60</b> is displayed on the monitor <b>21</b> and the user variously operates the operation unit <b>22</b>, thereby enabling an instruction of changing the image capturing direction only by an arbitrary amount to be given. That is, the operation unit <b>22</b> gives an instruction of changing the image capturing direction only by a designated amount in accordance with a change in the angle of the image capturing unit <b>60</b> relative to the surveillance camera body. The operation screen for changing the image capturing direction will be described later.</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">Swing Mechanism of Surveillance Camera</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram for explaining the swing mechanism <b>40</b> of the surveillance camera <b>10</b>. The image capturing unit <b>60</b> performs an operation (hereinafter, referred to as “panning operation”) of rotation around an axis P<sub>p </sub>perpendicular to the ground (hereinafter, referred to as “panning axis”) and an operation (hereinafter, referred to as “tilting operation”) of rotation around an axis T<sub>p </sub>(hereinafter, referred to as “tilting axis”) which is parallel to the ground. In other words, the swing mechanism <b>40</b> has a driving mechanism (hereinafter, referred to as “panning mechanism”) for making the camera unit <b>50</b> perform the panning operation and a driving mechanism (hereinafter, referred to as “tilting mechanism”) for making the camera unit <b>50</b> perform the tilting operation.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Specifically, the panning mechanism changes the relative angle of the image capturing unit <b>60</b> to the surveillance camera body including the housing <b>11</b> in a first direction around the panning axis (hereinafter, referred to as “panning direction). The tilting mechanism changes the relative angle of the image capturing unit <b>60</b> to the surveillance camera body in a second direction around the tilting axis (hereinafter, referred to as “tilting direction).</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The details of the swing mechanism <b>40</b> will be described below with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The camera unit <b>50</b> has a shape of a combination of a cylindrical part <b>54</b> having an almost cylindrical shape and a spherical part <b>52</b> having an almost spherical shape.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In the spherical part <b>52</b>, the image capturing unit <b>60</b> and a tilt large gear <b>74</b> integrally connected to the image capturing unit <b>60</b> are provided. Further, the spherical part <b>52</b> has a slit <b>53</b> in its front part. A light flux from the subject is incident on a taking lens <b>61</b> of the image capturing unit <b>60</b> without causing an eclipse.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In the cylindrical part <b>54</b>, a tilt motor <b>70</b> constructed by a pulse motor is provided. The driving force of the tilt motor <b>70</b> is transmitted from a pinion gear <b>71</b> to the tilt large gear <b>74</b> via gears <b>72</b> and <b>73</b>. By the rotation of the tilt large gear <b>74</b>, the image capturing unit <b>60</b> turns around the tilting axis Tp as a center to change the image capturing direction vertically.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">A pan motor <b>41</b> constructed by a pulse motor is mounted on a base plate <b>77</b> to be fixed to the housing <b>11</b>, and the driving force of the pan motor <b>41</b> is transmitted from a pinion gear <b>42</b> to a gear <b>51</b> provided on the top face of the cylindrical part <b>54</b> via gears <b>43</b> and <b>44</b>. The gear <b>51</b> is integrally connected to the camera unit <b>50</b>, and the camera unit <b>50</b> itself rotates around the panning axis Pp by the rotation of the gear <b>51</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">To change the image capturing direction, a change in the image capturing direction can be easily controlled by the total number of pulses given to the pulse motor by using the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> taking the form of pulse motors.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram showing the functional configuration regarding driving of the swing mechanism <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">In the housing <b>11</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a control microcomputer <b>13</b> for receiving a control signal from the controller <b>20</b> and controlling the driving of the swing mechanism <b>40</b> in a centralized manner is provided. In the housing <b>11</b>, a pan motor driver <b>14</b> for controlling the driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor driver <b>15</b> for controlling the driving of the tilt motor <b>70</b> are provided.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">By transmitting commands by serial communication from the control microcomputer <b>13</b> to the pan motor driver <b>14</b> and the tilt motor driver <b>15</b>, the panning operation and the tilting operation can be controlled independently. That is, the control microcomputer <b>13</b> controls the driving of the panning mechanism and the tilting mechanism of the swing mechanism <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">By freely setting and adjusting the pulse rates (also referred to as “first and second pulse rates”) given to the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> and the total number of pulses under control of the control microcomputer <b>13</b>, the driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> can be controlled. That is, a change in the image capturing direction can be controlled easily and reliably.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The control microcomputer <b>13</b> also sets a drive amount of the panning mechanism (hereinafter, “panning amount (first drive amount)”) and a pulse rate of the panning mechanism (hereinafter, “pan-pulse rate”), and a drive amount of the tilting mechanism (hereinafter, “tilting amount (second drive amount)) and a pulse rate of tilting mechanism (hereinafter, “tilt-pulse rate”) on the basis of the instruction given by the operation unit <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The pulse rate is a value of controlling the driving speed (hereinafter, “drive speed control value”) of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b>. In the following, the pan-pulse rate will be also referred to as a panning speed control value (first drive speed control value) and the tilt-pulse rate will be also referred to as a tilting speed control value (second drive speed control value).</p>
<p id="h-0007" num="0000">Operation for Changing Image Capturing Direction</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a diagram showing an operation screen DS for changing the image capturing direction of the image capturing unit <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">On the operation screen DS, a frame (camera changeable range frame) <b>25</b> showing the range in which the image capturing direction can be changed is displayed. The image capturing direction can be changed arbitrarily as long as it is shown in the camera changeable range frame <b>25</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The lateral direction of the camera changeable range frame <b>25</b> indicates the angle (hereinafter, “pan angle”) in the panning operation direction (pan direction) of the image capturing direction in the case where the front direction ST is a reference (origin O). The vertical direction of the camera changeable range frame <b>25</b> indicates the angle (hereinafter, “tilt angle”) in the tilting operation direction (tilt direction) of the image capturing direction in the case where the front direction ST is a reference (origin O). In the case where the image capturing direction is on a plane parallel to the ground, the tilt angle is 0°. In the case where the image capturing direction is on the plane vertical to both the wall face to which the housing <b>11</b> is attached and the ground face, the pan angle is 0°.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">For example, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, by using the front direction ST as a reference, the image capturing direction can be changed within the range from +70° to −70° in the panning direction and can be changed within the range from +20° to −70° in the tilting direction.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the present image capturing direction is a direction corresponding to the angle P<sub>0</sub>. By operating the keyboard, mouse, or the like of the operation unit <b>22</b> to designate a next angle of the image capturing direction (target angle) by a cursor CR and clicking an execution button (in this case, the return key in the keyboard or the click button of the mouse), the angle of the image capturing direction can be changed to the designated angle (target angle). That is, the angle of the image capturing direction is changed to the angle designated by the user.</p>
<p id="h-0008" num="0000">Control Method of Changing Image Capturing Direction</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a diagram illustrating the angle of changing the image capturing direction. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows the changing angle of the image capturing direction in the case where the angle of the image capturing direction is changed from an angle P<sub>0 </sub>to an angle P<sub>1</sub>. The angle P<sub>0 </sub>is set as the origin. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the lateral axis denotes the changing angle in the panning direction, and the vertical axis indicates the changing angle in the tilting direction. The changing angle in the panning direction in the case of changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1 </sub>is indicated as an angle θ<sub>p </sub>(in unit of “degrees”) and the changing angle in the tilting direction is indicated as an angle θ<sub>t </sub>(in unit of “degrees”).</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a diagram showing the numbers of pulses given to the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> obtained by converting the changing angle of the image capturing direction in the case where the angle of the image capturing direction is changed from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the lateral axis indicates the number of pulses given to the pan motor <b>41</b>, and the vertical axis indicates the number of pulses given to the tilt motor <b>70</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, in a manner similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the point corresponding to the angle P<sub>0 </sub>is set as the origin. The total number of pulses given to the pan motor <b>41</b> (hereinafter, “pan-pulse number”) for changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1 </sub>is indicated as a pulse number P<sub>t</sub>, and the total number of pulses given to the tilt motor <b>70</b> (hereinafter, “tilt-pulse number”) for changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1 </sub>is indicated as the pulse number T<sub>t</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">When the reduction ratio in the panning operation is set as η<sub>p </sub>(where η<sub>p</sub>&gt;1) and the step angle of the pan motor <b>41</b> (angle per pulse) is set as θ<sub>sp</sub>, the pan—pulse number P<sub>t </sub>necessary for the panning operation is expressed by the following equation (1).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>P</i><sub>t</sub>=θ<sub>p</sub>·η<sub>P</sub>/θ<sub>SP</sub>  (1)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">When the reduction ratio in the tilting operation is set as η<sub>T </sub>(where η<sub>T</sub>&gt;1) and the step angle of the tilt motor <b>70</b> (angle per pulse) is set as θ<sub>ST</sub>, the tilt—pulse number T<sub>t </sub>necessary for the tilting operation is expressed by the following equation (2).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>T</i><sub>t</sub>=θ<sub>T</sub>·η<sub>T</sub>/θ<sub>ST</sub>  (2)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">In the following, description will be given on assumption that the step angles of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> are the same (θ<sub>s</sub>=θ<sub>SP</sub>=θ<sub>ST</sub>) in the embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">In the case where a pulse rate P<sub>i </sub>(the number of pulses per second, hereinafter, abbreviated as “pps”) is given to the pan motor <b>41</b>, time required for the panning operation is P<sub>t</sub>/P<sub>i </sub>(seconds).</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">In the case of simultaneously starting the driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> at predetermined speeds and simultaneously stopping the driving, the pulse rate Ti to be given to the tilt motor <b>70</b> is equal to P<sub>i</sub>·(T<sub>t</sub>/P<sub>t</sub>) (pps).</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a diagram showing the relationship between the pulse rates to the pulse motors used as the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> and noise level. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the lateral axis indicates the pulse rate and the vertical axis indicates the noise level.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Generally, in the pulse motor, as the pulse rate becomes higher, the noise level tends to increase. Particularly, in a hatched range (hereinafter, “resonance range”) Bc of the pulse rate from P<sub>VL </sub>to P<sub>VU </sub>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, resonance generates in the pulse motor itself or between the pulse motor and the device itself of the surveillance camera <b>10</b>, and the noise level increases.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">Therefore, when the limit level at which the noise level is permitted (hereinafter, “noise permissible level”) is equal to or lower than noise level S<sub>c</sub>, a range in which the pulse rate can be used is constructed by a range of the pulse rates (0 to P<sub>VL</sub>) on the low than that in the resonance range Bc and a range of pulse rates (P<sub>VU </sub>to P<sub>H</sub>) on the high side. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, at the pulse rates P<sub>VL</sub>, P<sub>VU</sub>, and P<sub>H</sub>, the noise level is the noise permissible level S<sub>c</sub>, the pulse rate P<sub>H </sub>is the maximum pulse rate at which the noise level is permitted (hereinafter, referred to as “permissible maximum pulse rate”).</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a diagram illustrating the relationship between the combination of the pulse rate given to the pan motor <b>41</b> and the pulse rate given to the tilt motor <b>70</b> and resonance. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the lateral axis indicates pulse rate P<sub>i </sub>(pps) given to the pan motor <b>41</b>, and the vertical axis indicates pulse rate T<sub>i </sub>(pps) given to the tilt motor <b>70</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, a composite vector of the pulse rates given to the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b>, that is, vectors (hereinafter, “drive speed vectors”) V<sub>1 </sub>to V<sub>4 </sub>of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b> are also shown. Further, a hatched area a, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> indicates an area of the drive speed vectors in which the pan motor <b>41</b> generates resonance and noise exceeding the noise permissible level S<sub>C </sub>generates. An area a<b>2</b> indicates an area of the drive speed vectors in which the tilt motor <b>70</b> generates resonance and noise exceeding the noise permissible level S<sub>C </sub>generates.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the drive speed vector V<sub>1 </sub>is a drive speed vector in the case where both of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b> are simultaneously driven at the maximum permissible pulse rate P<sub>H</sub>. The drive speed vector V<sub>2 </sub>is a drive speed vector in the case where the tilt motor <b>70</b> is driven at the maximum permissible pulse rate P<sub>H </sub>and the pan motor <b>41</b> is driven at the pulse rate P<sub>VM </sub>in the resonance range B<sub>C</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">Since the drive speed vector V<sub>2 </sub>lies in the area a<sub>1 </sub>in which the pan motor <b>41</b> which is driven at lower speed than the tilt motor <b>70</b> generates resonance, if the pan motor <b>41</b> and tilt motor <b>70</b> are driven with the drive speed vector V<sub>2</sub>, noise exceeding the noise permissible level S<sub>C </sub>generates.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Therefore, in the surveillance camera system <b>1</b> according to the embodiment, in such a case, for example, until predetermined time elapses from start of driving, it is controlled so that the pulse rate given to the pan motor <b>41</b> lies out of the resonance range B<sub>C</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">Concretely, until predetermined time elapses since the start of driving, it is controlled so that the pulse rate given to the pan motor <b>41</b> becomes the minimum pulse rate P<sub>VU </sub>exceeding the resonance range B<sub>C </sub>and the driving in the panning direction is finished before the driving in the tilting direction. After the driving in the panning direction is completed, only the driving in the tilting direction is maintained, and a change in the image capturing direction is completed. In short, until the predetermined time elapses since the start of driving, it is controlled to change the drive speed vector V<sub>2 </sub>to the drive speed vector V<sub>3 </sub>so as to be out of the area a<sub>1</sub>, in which the pan motor <b>41</b> generates resonance, thereby avoiding generation of resonance, that is, generation of noise exceeding the noise permissible level S<sub>C</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">A method of controlling a process of avoiding generation of resonance (generation of noise exceeding the noise permissible level S<sub>C</sub>) (hereinafter, also referred to as “resonance avoiding process”) will be described below.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a diagram for explaining a motor control method in the case where the pulse rate given to the pan motor <b>41</b> which is driven at lower speed than the tilt motor <b>70</b> is at a resonance frequency.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, in a manner similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the changing angle of the image capturing direction in the case where the angle of the image capturing direction is changed from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1 </sub>is converted to the number of pulses given to each of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, in a manner similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a point corresponding to the angle P<sub>0 </sub>is shown as the origin, and points corresponding to angles P<sub>1 </sub>to P<sub>3 </sub>in the image capturing direction are also shown. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the lateral axis indicates the number of pulses given to the pan motor <b>41</b>, and the vertical axis indicates the number of pulses given to the tilt motor <b>70</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> further shows, in a manner similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the pan-pulse number P<sub>t </sub>given to the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt-pulse number T<sub>1</sub>. given to the tilt motor <b>70</b> necessary to change the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> also shows loci W<sub>2</sub>, W<sub>3</sub>, and W<sub>4 </sub>indicative of a state where the pan-pulse number and the tilt-pulse number are integrated (hereinafter, “pulse integration loci”).</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">At the time of changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, when the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b> are driven so that the drive speed vector becomes the drive speed vector V<sub>2 </sub>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> from the start of the change in the image capturing direction to the end of the change, the pulse integration locus becomes the locus W<sub>2 </sub>which is directed like the drive speed vector V<sub>2</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">As described above, when the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b> are driven by the drive speed vector V<sub>2</sub>, noise caused by resonance generates. In order to avoid generation of resonance, first, until application of the pan-pulse number necessary to change the image capturing direction is completed, the driving of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b> is controlled so that the drive speed vector becomes the drive speed vector V<sub>3 </sub>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. After completion of the application of the pan-pulse number necessary to change the image capturing direction, until the tilt-pulse number necessary to change the image capturing direction is completed, the pulses are given to the tilt motor <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">Specifically, first, by changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>2 </sub>and, after that, changing from the angle P<sub>2 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, the angle of the image capturing direction is changed from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>. At this time, the pulse integration locus becomes the locus W<sub>3 </sub>and the pulse integration locus at the time of changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>2 </sub>is directed like the drive speed vector V<sub>3</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">In other words, as compared with the drive speed vector V<sub>2</sub>, when the drive speed vector V<sub>3 </sub>is set, the pulse rate given to the pan motor <b>41</b> is higher (faster). At the time point when the angle of the image capturing direction reaches the angle P<sub>2</sub>, the angle of the image capturing direction in the panning direction has reached the target angle, so that the driving by the pan motor <b>41</b> is stopped. After that, only the tilt motor <b>70</b> rotates. At the time point when the angle of the image capturing direction reaches from the angle P<sub>2 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, the driving of the tilt motor <b>70</b> is stopped.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">That is, for example, when conditions are satisfied such that the panning amount is smaller than that tilting amount and the panning speed control value (in this case, the pan-pulse rate) of the pan motor <b>41</b> is a value in a structural resonance range of the surveillance camera <b>10</b> (hereinafter, also referred to as “resonance conditions”), the tilt motor <b>70</b> is driven by giving the pulse based on the tilting speed control value under control of the control microcomputer <b>13</b>, and the pan motor <b>41</b> is driven by giving the pulse based on the panning speed control value which is changed. In this case, it is controlled so that, after completion of driving of a panning amount by the pan motor <b>41</b>, the driving of a tilting amount by the tilt motor <b>70</b> is completed.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">Further, in other words, to a specific time point when the driving of a designated amount (in this case, the panning amount) by one of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> (in this case, the pan motor <b>41</b>) is completed since the start of driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b>, under control of the control microcomputer <b>13</b>, by giving pulses based on the panning speed control value and the tilt drive speed control value as values out of the structural resonance region of the surveillance camera <b>10</b> to the pan motor <b>41</b> and tilt motor <b>70</b>, thereby driving the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b>. Until the changing of the image capturing direction only by the designated amount is completed after the specific time point, it is controlled so that one of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> (in this case, the pan motor <b>41</b>) is stopped.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">As described above, the angle of the image capturing direction is once changed from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>2 </sub>and, after that, changed from the angle P<sub>2 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>. Therefore, as compared with the case of changing the angle from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>directly to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, the locus of changing of the image capturing direction becomes longer. However, both in the case of changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1 </sub>through the angle P<sub>2 </sub>and in the case of changing the angle directly from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, the same number of tilt-pulses is given to the tilt motor <b>70</b> at the maximum permissible pulse rate P<sub>H</sub>, so that time required to reach the target angle becomes the same. That is, in this example, the drive time of the tilt motor <b>70</b> controls the rate of the whole direction change. Consequently, even if the drive conditions of the pan motor <b>41</b> are changed, the whole required time does not change if it is within the drive time of the tilt motor <b>70</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">In the above, in the case where the pulse rate of the pulse motor which is driven at lower speed than another motor is in the resonance range, to suppress noise caused by resonance, the pulse rate of the pulse motor driven at lower speed than another is shifted to the high speed side exceeding the resonance range. Alternately, the pulse rate may be shifted to the low speed side below the resonance range.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">Concretely, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, for example, until predetermined time elapses since start of the driving, to make the pulse rate given to the pan motor <b>41</b> out of the resonance range B<sub>C</sub>, in place of changing the drive speed vector V<sub>2 </sub>to the drive speed vector V<sub>3</sub>, the drive speed vector V<sub>2 </sub>can be changed to the drive speed vector V<sub>4</sub>. In this case, the pulse rate P<sub>VL </sub>is given to the pan motor <b>41</b>, so that the pan motor <b>41</b> does not generate resonance.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows a pulse integration locus W<sub>4 </sub>of the case where the drive speed vector is set to V<sub>4</sub>. In the case where the drive speed vector V<sub>4 </sub>is set, the pulse rate of the pan motor <b>41</b> is lower (slower) than that in the case where the drive speed vector V<sub>2 </sub>is set. Consequently, at the time point when the angle of the image capturing direction reaches the angle P<sub>3</sub>, driving to the tilting direction reaches to the target angle first, and the driving of the tilt motor <b>70</b> is stopped. After that, only the pan motor <b>41</b> rotates. At the time point when the angle of the image capturing direction reaches from the angle P<sub>3 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, the driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> is stopped.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">As described above, in the case where the angle of the image capturing direction is changed once from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>3 </sub>and, after that, changed from the angle P<sub>3 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, as compared with the case of directly changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, the locus of changing of the angle of the image capturing direction is longer. In the case of changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1 </sub>through the angle P<sub>3</sub>, as compared with the case of directly changing the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>0 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>, time is required longer only by time required to change the angle of the image capturing direction from the angle P<sub>3 </sub>to the angle P<sub>1</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">In other words, when the pulse rate to be given to the pulse motor which is driven at lower speed than another is in the resonance range at the time of changing the image capturing direction, if the pulse rate given to the pulse motor driven at lower speed than another is shifted to the low speed side so as to avoid the resonance range, as compared with the case of shifting the pulse rate to the high speed side, time required to change the image capturing direction becomes longer. As a result, time since the user instructs a change in the image capturing direction until the change in the image capturing direction is completed, that is, a time lag becomes longer, and a low operability state in which the user feels something strange is resulted.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">Therefore, in the surveillance camera system <b>1</b> according to the embodiment, as described above, the control method is employed in which when the pulse rate given to the pulse motor which is driven at lower speed than another motor is in the resonance range, the pulse rate to be given to the pulse motor driven at lower speed than another is shifted to the high speed side so as to avoid the resonance range.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">On the other hand, in the case where the pulse rate given to the pulse motor driven at lower speed than another is not in the resonance range, the pulse rate to be given to the pulse motor driven at lower speed than another is not changed. Specifically, for example, in the case where resonance conditions are not satisfied such that the pan drive amount is smaller than the tilt drive amount and the pan drive speed control value is a value out of the structural resonance range of the surveillance camera <b>10</b>, under control of the control microcomputer <b>13</b>, by giving the pulse based on the pan drive speed control value which is not changed to the pan motor <b>41</b>, the pan motor <b>41</b> is driven and, by giving the pulse based on the tilt drive speed control value to the tilt motor <b>70</b>, the tilt motor <b>70</b> is driven. At this time, it is controlled so that start of the driving of the pan drive amount of the pan motor <b>41</b> and start of the driving of the tilt drive amount of the tilt motor <b>70</b> become almost the same, and end of the driving of the pan drive amount of the pan motor <b>41</b> and end of the driving of the tilt drive amount of the tilt motor <b>70</b> become almost the same, thereby enabling the image capturing direction of the camera to be changed at higher speed in a state where resonance is not generated.</p>
<p id="h-0009" num="0000">Flow of Operation of Changing Image Capturing Direction</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0100"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10 to 12</figref> show flowcharts of the flow of an operation of changing the image capturing direction. The operation flow is executed by a joint control performed by the controller <b>20</b> and the control microcomputer <b>13</b> in the surveillance camera <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0101">When the user designates the next image capturing direction (target angle of the image capturing direction) on the operation screen DS shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the control microcomputer <b>13</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> can obtain the information of the target angle via the control unit <b>23</b>, and calculate the rotation angle, specifically, a rotation direction, a rotation amount, and the total number of pulses of the panning operation and the tilting operation. The control microcomputer <b>13</b> executes the flow of the operation of changing the image capturing direction shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10 to 12</figref>, thereby changing the image capturing direction by controlling the rotation of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b> via the motor drivers <b>14</b> and <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0102">For example, a high-speed mode for changing the image capturing direction at high speed, a low-speed mode of changing the image capturing direction at low speed, or the like is set by operating the operation unit <b>22</b> by the user, thereby enabling the pulse rate or the drive speed to be given to the motor <b>41</b> or <b>70</b> which rotates at higher speed to be designated. The drive speed of the pulse motor which can be set in the low-speed or high-speed mode, that is, the pulse rate can be set so as to be out of the resonance range.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0103">The flow of the operation of changing the image capturing direction shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10 to 12</figref> will be described below.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0104">In step S<b>1</b>, whether the target angle of the image capturing direction instructed by the user lies within a changeable range or not is determined. For example, when the user sets the cursor CR in the camera changeable range frame <b>25</b> on the operation screen DS shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and designates the desired angle of the image capturing direction (target angle), it is regarded that the target angle is within the changeable range, the program advances to step S<b>2</b>. On the other hand, when the target angle is out of the changeable range, the operation flow is finished and the system waits for the next designation of the target angle by the user.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0105">In step S<b>2</b>, the setting routine for setting the speeds of the panning operation and the tilting operation is invoked and the pan and tilt speeds setting operation flow shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is executed.</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0106">In step S<b>21</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, whether the pan drive amount is larger than the tilt drive amount or not is determined. In the case where the pan drive amount is larger than the tilt drive amount, the program advances to step S<b>22</b>. In the case where the pan drive amount is equal to or smaller than the tilt drive amount, the program advances to step S<b>25</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0107">First, the case where the program advances from step S<b>21</b> to step S<b>22</b> will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0108">In step S<b>22</b>, the rotation speed of the panning operation (pan drive speed) for the larger drive amount is set, and the program advances to step S<b>23</b>. In this case, as the pulse rate given to the pan motor <b>41</b>, the pulse rate corresponding to the drive speed designated by the user is set.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0109">In step S<b>23</b>, the rotation speed in the tilt direction (tilt drive speed), that is, the pulse rate given to the tilt motor <b>70</b> is set in accordance with the following expression (3), and the program advances to step S<b>24</b>.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Tilt drive speed=Pan drive speed×(Tilt drive amount/Pan drive amount)  (3)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0110">In step S<b>24</b>, by executing the resonance avoiding process flow shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, when the pulse rate set in step S<b>23</b> lies within the resonance range, the resonance avoiding process is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0111">In step S<b>31</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, whether the pulse rate (drive speed) set in step S<b>23</b> lies within the resonance range or not is determined. In the case where the pulse rate (drive speed) is within the resonance range, the program advances to step S<b>32</b>. In the case where the pulse rate is out of the resonance range, the resonance avoiding process flow and the pan and tilt speeds setting operation flow are finished and the program advances to step S<b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0113" num="0112">In step S<b>32</b>, the pulse rate (drive speed) set in step S<b>23</b> is changed to the high speed side so as to be out of the resonance range, the resonance avoiding process flow and the pan and tilt speeds setting operation flow are finished, and the program advances to step S<b>3</b>. In this case, for example, the pulse rate is replaced to P<sub>VU </sub>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0113">Specifically, when the tilt drive amount is smaller than the pan drive amount and, further, the pulse rate of the tilting operation is a value within the resonance range, the control microcomputer <b>13</b> changes the tilt drive speed control value to a value out of the resonance range. Concretely, the tilt-pulse rate is changed to the value P<sub>VU </sub>exceeding the maximum value of the resonance range.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0114">The case where the program advances from step S<b>21</b> to step S<b>25</b> will now be described.</p>
<p id="p-0116" num="0115">In step S<b>25</b>, the rotation speed in the tilting operation (tilt drive speed) for the larger drive amount is set, and the program advances to step S<b>26</b>. The pulse rate to be given to the tilt motor <b>70</b> is set to the pulse rate corresponding to the drive speed designated by the user.</p>
<p id="p-0117" num="0116">In step S<b>26</b>, the rotation speed in the pan direction (pan drive speed), that is, the pulse rate to be given to the pan motor <b>41</b> is set in accordance with the following equation (4), and the program advances to step S<b>27</b>.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Pan drive speed=Tilt drive speed×(Pan drive amount/Tilt drive amount)  (4)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0118" num="0117">In step S<b>27</b>, by executing the resonance avoiding process flow shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> in a manner similar to step S<b>24</b>, in the case where the pulse rate set in step S<b>26</b> is in the resonance range, the above-described resonance avoiding process is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0119" num="0118">In step S<b>31</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, whether the pulse rate (drive speed) set in step S<b>26</b> lies within the resonance range or not is determined. If the pulse rate (drive speed) is within the resonance range, the program advances to step S<b>32</b>. If the pulse rate is out of the resonance range, the resonance avoiding process flow and the pan and tilt speeds setting operation flow are finished, and the program advances to step S<b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0120" num="0119">In step S<b>32</b>, the pulse rate (drive speed) set in step S<b>26</b> is changed to the pulse rate (drive speed) on the high speed side so as to be out of the resonance range, the resonance avoiding process flow and the pan and tilt speeds setting operation flow are finished, and the program advances to step S<b>3</b>. For example, the pulse rate is replaced to P<sub>VU </sub>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0121" num="0120">Specifically, when the resonance conditions are satisfied such that the pan drive amount is smaller than the tilt drive amount and, further, the pan-pulse rate is a value in the structural resonance range of the surveillance camera <b>10</b>, the control microcomputer <b>13</b> changes the drive speed control value (pan-pulse rate) of the panning operation to a value out of the resonance range (alternative speed control value). Concretely, the pan-pulse rate is changed to the value P<sub>VU </sub>exceeding the maximum value of the structural resonance range of the surveillance camera <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0122" num="0121">In step S<b>3</b>, a timer (error timer) for detecting an operation error of the panning operation and the tilting operation is set and started. In this case, time required to change the angle of the image capturing direction to the target angle (changing required time) is calculated from each drive amount and each pulse rate, for example, time twice as long as the changing required time is set as error time, and counting is started from start of changing the angle until error time elapses.</p>
<p id="p-0123" num="0122">In step S<b>4</b>, the pulse rate and the total number of pulses of each of the panning operation and the tilting operation are designated, commands for starting the driving of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b> are transmitted to the motor drivers <b>14</b> and <b>15</b> to start the driving of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b>, and the program advances to step S<b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0124" num="0123">In step S<b>5</b>, whether the driving of the motors <b>41</b> and <b>70</b> has been completed or not is determined. The control microcomputer <b>13</b> waits for a signal (drive complete signal) indicative of completion of the driving on the basis of the designated number of pulses returned from each of the motor drivers <b>14</b> and <b>15</b>. If the control microcomputer <b>13</b> does not receive the drive complete signal, the program advances to step S<b>6</b>. If the control microcomputer <b>13</b> receives the drive complete signal, the flow of the operation of changing the image capturing direction is finished.</p>
<p id="p-0125" num="0124">In step S<b>6</b>, whether the error timer expires or not is determined. In this case, whether the error time has elapsed since start of the error timer or not is determined. If the error time has not elapsed yet, it is regarded that the error time does not expire and the program returns to step S<b>5</b>. On the other hand, if the error time has elapsed, it is regarded that the error time expires and the program advances to step S<b>7</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0126" num="0125">In step S<b>7</b>, an error process is performed and the flow of the operation of changing the image capturing direction is finished. The error process is a so-called initializing process of resetting the image capturing direction to the front direction irrespective of an instruction of the image capturing direction by the user and waiting for the next instruction of the image capturing direction. Specifically, the control microcomputer <b>13</b> waits for the drive complete signal to be sent. If the error timer expires before the drive complete signal is received, it is determined that an error generates in the operation of changing the image capturing direction and the error process is performed.</p>
<p id="p-0127" num="0126">As described above, in the surveillance camera system <b>1</b> according to the embodiment, for example, if the pan drive amount is smaller than the tilt drive amount and the pan-pulse rate lies within the structural resonance range of the surveillance camera <b>10</b> at the time of changing the image capturing direction only by a designated amount, the pan-pulse rate is changed to an alternative value out of the resonance range (in this case, the value P<sub>VU </sub>exceeding the maximum value of the resonance range). By giving the pulse based on the tilt-pulse rate, the tilt motor <b>70</b> is driven. By giving the pulse based on the changed pan-pulse rate, the pan motor <b>41</b> is driven. After completion of driving of the pan drive amount by the pan motor <b>41</b>, driving of the tilt drive amount by the tilt motor <b>70</b> is completed. As a result, while suppressing noise caused by resonance, the image capturing direction of the camera can be changed at high speed.</p>
<p id="p-0128" num="0127">In other words, at the time of changing the image capturing direction, in a period from the start of driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> until a specific time point at which the driving of one of the motors (in this case, the pan motor <b>41</b>) is completed, the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> are driven so that the pulse rate given to the pan motor <b>41</b> and that given to the tilt motor <b>70</b> are out of the resonance range. After the specific time point at which the driving of one of the motors is completed and until the change in the image capturing direction of the designated amount is completed, it is controlled so as to stop one of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> (in this case, the pan motor <b>41</b>). As a result, while suppressing noise caused by resonance, the image capturing direction of the camera can be changed at high speed.</p>
<p id="h-0010" num="0000">Modifications</p>
<p id="p-0129" num="0128">Although the embodiment of the present invention has been described above, the present invention is not limited to the above description.</p>
<p id="p-0130" num="0129">For example, although the pulse motor is used as the swing mechanism <b>40</b> for changing the image capturing direction, the present invention is not limited to the pulse motor. Another driving means such as a trussed actuator may be used. For example, a technique using a truss-structured actuator as another driving means is disclosed in Japanese Patent Application Laid-Open No. 2001-54289. In the following, a swing mechanism <b>40</b>A including the truss-structured actuator, the resonance range, and the like will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0131" num="0130"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a diagram for explaining the swing mechanism <b>40</b>A using the truss-structured actuator.</p>
<p id="p-0132" num="0131">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, in the swing mechanism <b>40</b>A, two truss-structured actuators <b>100</b> and <b>101</b> are used. One of the trussed actuators <b>100</b> and <b>101</b> is used for the panning operation and the other is used for the tilting operation. The truss-structured actuator <b>100</b> for the tilting operation has a tilt rotor <b>126</b> and a tilt stator <b>122</b> for rotatably supporting the tilt rotor <b>126</b>. The truss-structured actuator <b>101</b> for the panning operation has a pan rotor <b>136</b> and a pan stator <b>132</b> for rotatably supporting the pan rotor <b>136</b>. The configuration of the truss-structured actuators <b>100</b> and <b>101</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>. The same configuration is used for the tilting operation and the panning operation.</p>
<p id="p-0133" num="0132">The image capturing unit <b>60</b> is the same as the image capturing unit <b>60</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Since the image capturing unit <b>60</b> and the tilt rotor <b>126</b> are coupled to each other via a support <b>62</b>, the image capturing unit <b>60</b> rotates around a T axis (tilting axis) by the rotation of the tilt rotor <b>126</b>. The other end of the tilt stator <b>122</b>, to which the tilt rotor <b>126</b> is fixed, is fixed to the pan rotor <b>136</b>. Therefore, in association with the rotation of the pan rotor <b>136</b>, the image capturing unit <b>60</b> and the truss-structured actuator <b>100</b> for the tilting operation integrally rotate around a P axis (panning axis). The pan stator <b>132</b> is fixed to the housing <b>11</b> or the like of the surveillance camera <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0134" num="0133"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 14A and 14B</figref> are diagrams showing the configuration and the operation principle of the truss-structured actuator <b>100</b>. Since the truss-structured actuators <b>100</b> and <b>101</b> have similar configurations and operation principles, the truss-structured actuator <b>100</b> for the tilting operation will be described as an example. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14A</figref> is a cross section of the truss-structured actuator <b>100</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14B</figref> is a cross section taken along line C-C of the truss-structured actuator <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0135" num="0134">The truss-structured actuator <b>100</b> has first and second piezoelectric devices (displacement devices) <b>82</b> and <b>83</b>, a chip member (member to be displaced) <b>84</b>, a base member <b>85</b>, a rotor (member to be driven) <b>86</b>, a pressure spring (first pressure member) <b>87</b>, a rigid ball <b>94</b>, and a pressing spring (second pressure member) <b>89</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0136" num="0135">A drive unit <b>120</b> is constructed by the first and second piezoelectric devices <b>82</b> and <b>83</b>, chip member <b>84</b>, and base member <b>85</b>. A pressing member <b>130</b> is constructed by the rigid ball <b>94</b> and the pressing spring <b>89</b>′. In a position axially symmetrical with a rotor rotation axis <b>86</b><i>a </i>of a portion in which the chip member <b>84</b> and the rotor <b>86</b> (in this case, the tilt rotor <b>126</b>) are in contact with each other, there is a portion in which the rigid ball <b>94</b> and the rotor <b>86</b> are in contact with each other. The rigid ball <b>94</b> is held by a base <b>92</b> movably in the radial direction of the rotor <b>86</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0137" num="0136">The rigid ball <b>94</b> is pressed by the pressing spring <b>89</b>′ to the rotor <b>86</b>. The pressing spring <b>89</b>′ is, for example, a helical compression spring. One end of the pressing spring <b>89</b>′ is in contact with the base <b>92</b>, and the other end is in contact with the rigid ball <b>94</b>. In order to regulate the direction of pressing the rotor <b>86</b>, the rigid ball <b>94</b> and the pressing spring <b>89</b>′ are surrounded by a regulating member <b>95</b> and it is set so that a load for pressing the rotor <b>86</b> is applied in one direction.</p>
<p id="p-0138" num="0137">A force of pressing the rotor <b>86</b> by the chip member <b>84</b> and a force of pressing the rotor <b>86</b> by the rigid ball <b>94</b> are almost balanced. A pressing force of the pressing spring <b>89</b>′ is set so that a load in one direction does not work on the rotation axis <b>86</b><i>a </i>of the rotor <b>86</b> and a bearing portion. Since a frictional force acting between the rigid ball <b>94</b> and the rotor <b>86</b> becomes resistance of the driving force of the actuator, it is preferable to make the frictional force as low as possible.</p>
<p id="p-0139" num="0138">A preferable material of the rigid ball <b>94</b> is a material resistive to friction such as stainless steel or SUJ<b>2</b> (high carbon chromium bearing steel) used for a ball bearing. Since the rigid ball <b>94</b> is a sphere, it comes into rolling contact with the rotor <b>86</b>, and a coefficient of friction is set to be low. Since the rotatable rigid ball <b>94</b> is pressed to be in contact with the rotor <b>86</b> by the pressing spring <b>89</b>′, the rigid ball <b>94</b> can be pressed to be in contact with the rotor <b>86</b> without disturbing the rotation of the rotor <b>86</b>, and a load on the rotor axis <b>86</b><i>a </i>can be lessened.</p>
<p id="p-0140" num="0139">The principle of rotation of the rotor <b>86</b> by the actuator will now be described. By applying drive signals having a predetermined phase difference to the first and second piezoelectric devices <b>82</b> and <b>83</b>, the piezoelectric devices <b>82</b> and <b>83</b> are driven with different phases, and the chip member <b>84</b> provided at the intersection of the piezoelectric devices <b>82</b> and <b>83</b> is driven so as to draw a predetermined elliptical orbit (including a circular orbit).</p>
<p id="p-0141" num="0140">During the period in which the chip member <b>84</b> is driven so as to draw a predetermined elliptical orbit, the chip member <b>84</b> is in contact with the inner face (inner circumferential face) of the rotor <b>86</b> for a predetermined interval. By a frictional force acting between the chip member <b>84</b> and the inner circumferential face of the rotor <b>86</b>, the rotor <b>86</b> is rotated in a predetermined direction. By inverting the deviation direction of the phase of the drive signal, the direction of the elliptical orbit indicative of the driving of the chip member <b>84</b> is inverted so that the rotation of the rotor <b>86</b> can be inverted.</p>
<p id="p-0142" num="0141">Although there are various methods of changing the rotation speed of the rotor <b>86</b>, in this example, it is assumed that an intermittent driving method of changing the ratio (hereinafter, referred to as “duty ratio”) between time of giving the drive signal and time of intermission is employed. The duty ratio is a value of controlling the drive speed (drive speed control value) in the pan and tilt directions of the image capturing direction.</p>
<p id="p-0143" num="0142"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is a schematic diagram showing the relationship between the duty ratio of a drive signal given to the trussed actuator and sound. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>, the lateral axis indicates the duty ratio and percentage (%) is used as a unit. A state in which the duty ratio is 100% denotes a state where the drive signal is outputted without intermission. In this state, the rotation speed (drive speed) of the rotor <b>86</b> is the highest speed. A state in which the duty ratio is 50% is a state where time in which the drive signal is outputted, that is, the driving force is transmitted to the rotor <b>86</b> is 50%. Therefore, the smaller the numerical value of the duty ratio is, the time in which the drive signal is outputted becomes shorter, and the rotation speed of the rotor <b>86</b> becomes lower.</p>
<p id="p-0144" num="0143">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>, the vertical axis indicates noise level and the lateral axis expresses the ratio of intermittence driving (duty ratio). That is, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> shows the relationship between the ratio of intermittence driving and the noise level.</p>
<p id="p-0145" num="0144">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>, the peak of a curve indicative of noise level around the duty ratio=a (%) coincides with the peak of the audible range of the human ear. With the distance from the duty ratio=a (%), the noise level tends to decrease. The peak of the curve indicative of the noise level shown around the duty ratio=b (%) appears by resonance with a peripheral member (each of the members provided for the surveillance camera <b>10</b>) due to the oscillation frequency peculiar to the rotation mechanism including the rotor <b>86</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0146" num="0145">When the noise permissible level is set to S<sub>C </sub>in a manner similar to the foregoing embodiment, in the range of the duty ratio higher than L (%) and lower than U (%) shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> (hereinafter, “noise generation range”), the noise level exceeds the noise permissible level S<sub>C</sub>. Consequently, designing has to be made so as to set the duty ratio on the outside of the noise generation range.</p>
<p id="p-0147" num="0146">The present invention is not limited to the case of using the pulse motor. Also in the case of using another actuator, a range in which resonance is generated by the actuator itself or between the actuator and a device and noise becomes large exists. There is a case of using the actuator while setting the duty ratio in ranges sandwiching the resonance range. In such a case, in a manner similar to the foregoing embodiment, when the duty ratio of the actuator which is driven at lower speed than another actuator lies within the resonance range, by performing a resonance avoiding process of changing the duty ratio of the actuator driven at lower speed than another to an alternative value exceeding the upper limit value of the resonance range, effects similar to those of the foregoing embodiment can be obtained.</p>
<p id="p-0148" num="0147">Although the panning operation and the tilting operation are simultaneously started at the time of changing the image capturing direction in the foregoing embodiment, the present invention is not limited thereto. In the case of shifting the drive speed of the pulse motor which is driven at lower speed than the other one to the high speed side so as not to cause resonance, the drive time of the pulse motor driven at lower speed than the other one becomes shorter than the drive time of the other one. Consequently, for example, after the driving of the pulse motor on the high speed side is started, the driving of the pulse motor on the low speed side may be started so that the driving of the pulse motor on the low speed side is finished within the drive time of the pulse motor on the high speed side.</p>
<p id="p-0149" num="0148">Specifically, for example, in the case where the resonance conditions that the pan drive amount is smaller than the tilt drive amount and the pan-pulse rate (pan drive speed control value) is a value in the structural resonance range of the surveillance camera <b>10</b> are satisfied, it is sufficient to change the pan-pulse rate to an alternative value (alternative speed control value) out of the resonance range and perform driving of the pan drive amount by the pan motor <b>41</b> within the drive period of the tilt drive amount by the tilt motor <b>70</b>. Even when such a configuration is employed, time required to change the image capturing direction does not become longer. Thus, while suppressing noise caused by resonance, the image capturing direction of the camera can be changed at high speed.</p>
<p id="p-0150" num="0149">However, for example, in the case of changing the pan-pulse rate to an alternative value out of the resonance range, if the driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> is started and finished during driving of the tilt motor <b>70</b> without simultaneously starting the driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> unlike the foregoing embodiment, calculation which is complicated to a certain extent is necessary for a process of determining the drive start and finish time of the pan motor <b>41</b>. Therefore, by simply almost simultaneously starting the driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> and the tilt motor <b>70</b> and completing the driving of the pan motor <b>41</b> during the driving of the tilt motor <b>70</b>, the image capturing direction of the camera can be changed at high speed more easily while suppressing noise caused by resonance.</p>
<p id="p-0151" num="0150">Although the image capturing direction can be changed in two directions of the pan and tilt in the foregoing embodiment, the present invention is not limited thereto. For example, the image capturing direction may be variously changed by two or more driving means.</p>
<p id="p-0152" num="0151">While the invention has been shown and described in detail, the foregoing description is in all aspects illustrative and not restrictive. It is therefore understood that numerous modifications and variations can be devised without departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An image capturing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>an image capturing part for capturing an image of a subject;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of drivers for driving said image capturing part in a plurality of directions on the basis of a plurality of drive speed control values, respectively;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an instructor for instructing a designated amount of operation of said image capturing part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detector for detecting whether or not each drive speed control value for said designated amount of operation is within a structural resonance range of said image capturing part and, if a drive speed control value for said designated amount operation is within the structural resonance range of the image capturing part, determine an alternative drive speed control value for that drive speed control value that is not within said structural resonance range from among said plurality of drive speed control values;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a changing part for changing said drive speed control value for said designated amount of operation that is within the structural resonance range of the image capturing part to said alternative drive speed control value to reduce a driving time period for said designated amount of operation; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller for controlling said plurality of drivers with said plurality of drive speed control values in which said drive speed control value for said designated amount of operation that is within the structural resonance range of the image capturing part is changed to said alternative speed control value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said plurality of drivers are pulse motors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said plurality of drive speed control values are a plurality of pulse rates given to said plurality of drivers, respectively.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>when no drive speed control values are detected within said resonance range by said detector, said controller controls said image capturing part such that respective actions of said plurality of drivers for said designated amount of operation are almost simultaneously finished.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An image capturing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a first driver for changing a relative angle of an image capturing part to an image capturing apparatus body in a first direction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second driver for changing said relative angle in a second direction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller for controlling respective driving operations of said first and second drivers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an instructor for instructing a designated amount of change in said relative angle for attaining a designated change in an image capturing direction; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a setting part for setting a first drive amount and a first drive speed control value for said first driver and setting a second drive amount and a second drive speed control value for said second driver on the basis of said designated amount of change in said relative angle instructed by said instructor,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein, when resonance conditions that:</claim-text>
<claim-text>i) said first drive amount is smaller than said second drive amount, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>ii) said first drive speed control value is within a structural resonance range of said image capturing apparatus, are satisfied, said setting part changes said first drive speed control value to an alternative speed control value out of said resonance range, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>when said resonance conditions are satisfied, said controller controls said second driver drive on the basis of said second drive speed control value and controls said first driver drive on the basis of said alternative speed control value such that said first drive amount is attained by said first driver within a time period in which said second drive amount is attained by said second driver.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>when said resonance conditions are satisfied, said controller controls said second driver on the basis of said second drive speed control value, controls said first driver on the basis of said alternative speed control value and, controls such that the driving operation of said second drive amount by said second driver is completed after completion of the driving operation of said first drive amount by said first driver.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>when said resonance conditions are not satisfied, said controller controls said first driver on the basis of said first drive speed control value, controls said second driver on the basis of said second drive speed control value, and controls such that driving operation of said first drive amount by said first driver and the driving operation of said second drive amount by said second driver are almost simultaneously started and thereafter almost simultaneously finished.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>when said resonance conditions are satisfied, said setting part changes said first drive speed control value to a value larger than a maximum value of said resonance range, as said alternative speed control value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said first and second drivers are first and second pulse motors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said first and second drive speed control values are first and second pulse rates given to said first and second pulse motors, respectively.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An image capturing apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a first driver for changing a relative angle of an image capturing part to an image capturing apparatus body in a first direction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second driver for changing said relative angle in a second direction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller for controlling said first and second drivers; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an instructor for instructing a designated amount of change in said relative angle for attaining a designated change in an image capturing direction,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said controller is operable to attain said designated amount of change in said relative angle with a combination of:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a) a first control time period in which said controller controls said first and second drivers on the basis of first and second drive speed control values, respectively, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>b) a second control time period following said first time period in which said controller controls said first and second drivers while stopping one of said first and second drivers,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first and second drive speed control values are determined out of a structural resonance range of said image capturing apparatus.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said first and second drivers are first and second pulse motors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The image capturing apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>said first and second drive speed control values are first and second pulse rates given to said first and second pulse motors, respectively.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
