<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296587-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296587</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11165370</doc-number>
<date>20050624</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>321</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>17</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>43</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>13731501</main-classification>
<further-classification>13731541</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Self-extracting service module for piping infrastructures</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4822213</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Grace et al.</name>
<date>19890400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>405303</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5038817</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Henry et al.</name>
<date>19910800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>137315</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5437480</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Weil</name>
<date>19950800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>285167</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5529087</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Berry et al.</name>
<date>19960600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>13731541</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5820166</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Webb</name>
<date>19981000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>285 23</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5868442</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lin</name>
<date>19990200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>285367</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5873611</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Munley et al.</name>
<date>19990200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>285367</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6109662</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>van Zuthem et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2851462</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6186164</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Pfeifer et al.</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>13731541</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6209443</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Perez</name>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 92 39</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6467814</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wivagg</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>285205</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>U.S. Appl. No. 10/926,328, filed Aug. 26, 2004, Tadros.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>44</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>13731501</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>13731541</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060289063</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061228</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gill</last-name>
<first-name>Richard Taylor</first-name>
<address>
<street>2020 Saddle Drive</street>
<city>Nanoose Bay, British Columbia</city>
<postcode>V9P 9C2</postcode>
<country>CA</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CA</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CA</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fasken Martineau Dumoulin LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Kevin</first-name>
<department>3753</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A self-extracting service module for piping infrastructures comprises a platform on which is mounted equipment for controlling and or monitoring the flow of liquid or gaseous media throughout the piping infrastructures. A first remote-controllable pipe coupling system is interconnected with the equipment inlet and a second pipe coupling system is interconnected to the equipment outlet. The pipe coupling systems are remotely manipulable for engaging and disengaging the equipment with piping infrastructure inlets and outlets. The platform is attached to actuators positioned near each corner of the platform. The service module is extracted from the piping infrastructure by first isolating the equipment from the flow of liquid media after which, the pipe coupling systems are remotely disengaged from the piping infrastructure inlet and outlet. The actuators are then operated to move the platform from within the piping infrastructure to a position where service work is easily performed on the equipment.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="173.74mm" wi="219.63mm" file="US07296587-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="222.59mm" wi="156.63mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296587-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="138.60mm" wi="135.30mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296587-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="214.97mm" wi="144.53mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296587-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="220.81mm" wi="151.13mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296587-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="220.81mm" wi="174.92mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296587-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="143.85mm" wi="147.49mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296587-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="210.82mm" wi="139.02mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296587-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates to self-extracting service modules for piping infrastructures. More particularly, this invention relates to service modules containing equipment for regulating and/or monitoring the flow of liquid or gaseous media through piping infrastructures.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Complex and extensive piping infrastructure systems are commonly used for high-volume transport of liquid media and gases over extended distances and multiple changes of elevation in various municipal and industrial applications. Examples of such piping infrastructures include public works for distribution of water to and within residential and industrial communities, collection, treatment and disposal of residential and industrial waste streams, movement of raw materials, reagents, products and waste streams within pulp and paper mills, transfer of crude oil and resulting petroleum products within refineries, and transport of natural gas. Reliable and efficient transport of liquid media and gases in such systems requires a plurality of strategically located pressure-regulating and monitoring service stations throughout the piping infrastructures to constantly maintain and control pressures applied to ensure target flow rates are maintained. Depending on the type of liquid material or gases being transported and on location within the piping infrastructure, a service module provided at a service station may contain one or more pieces of pressure-regulating and/or monitoring equipment such as single- or double-port main valves, pressure-reducing valves, pressure-relief and check valves, pumps, pump control valves, flow meters, and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In most municipal water supply and waste disposal systems, the attendant piping infrastructure is buried underground and therefore the pressure-regulating and monitoring service stations are typically situated below ground within buried or subterranean concrete vaults. The walls of the vaults are provided with integrally installed inlets and outlets for engaging the piping infrastructure. The inlets and outlets are coupled to the requisite equipment installed within the vaults. Each service station is provided with bypass lines to enable shutdown and routine servicing of the equipment or, alternatively, replacement of failed or obsolete equipment. Such stations i.e., underground concrete vaults, are made just large enough to house the requisite equipment, one or two bypass lines and to provide the necessary minimal space for one or two workers to enter the station and perform the necessary service work. Access is typically provided through vertical openings provided in the tops of such vaults. The openings are commonly referred to as manholes, and are just large enough for a service worker to fit through. Such concrete vault service stations can be constructed on-site, that is by first constructing the vault by pouring the concrete walls and floor, the piping infrastructure inlet and outlet are integrally cast into the vault walls when the concrete is being poured, then installing the requisite equipment and bypass lines(s), and finally, connecting the service station into the flow of liquid media contained within the piping infrastructure. Alternatively, subterranean concrete vaults can be pre-cast and partially configured with equipment off-site, then trucked to their installation location within the piping infrastructure wherein they are installed and their construction and configuration is completed. Because of the interior space required for access and service work, such vaults are typically very heavy, e.g., 20,000-55,000 lbs (9,000-25,000 kg), they are commonly cast in two pieces and require heavy-duty specialized cranes, excavators and personnel for their handling and installation.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Federal and regional government agencies have designated such service stations, e.g., buried concrete vaults, as “confined spaces” wherein workers may encounter atmospheric hazards such as lack of oxygen or the presence of toxic vapours, and/or physical hazards such as electrical shock, mechanical malfunctions, or entrapment/engulfment by liquids or solids. “Confined spaces” are defined as spaces that are large enough for a person to enter through manhole or hatch covers, have limited means of entry or egress, and are not designed for extended human occupancy. Examples of such service stations include pumping stations, meter stations and valve stations. Entry into and service work inside “confined space” stations are strictly regulated under occupational safety legislation to ensure worker safety and rapid exit in case of emergencies.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is an object of the present invention, at least in preferred forms, to provide a self-extracting service module containing thereon equipment for regulating and/or monitoring the flow of liquid or gaseous media being transported throughout piping infrastructures. The service module is provided with actuators for moving the module into and out of confined spaces in piping infrastructures, and also is provided with remote-controllable pipe coupling systems for engaging and disengaging the equipment configuration with the piping infrastructure. The self-extracting service module of the present invention enables controllable removal of pressure-regulating and/or monitoring equipment from a confined space within a piping infrastructure to a location where service work can be easily performed without the attendant hazards and constrictions associated with confined spaces.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">According to one aspect of the present invention, there is provided a self-extracting service module having a platform for mounting thereon equipment for regulating and/or monitoring the flow of liquid or gaseous media within a piping infrastructure. The equipment may comprise one piece of equipment or alternatively, two more pieces of interconnected equipment such as single- or double-port main valves, pressure-reducing valves, pressure-relief and check valves, strainers, pumps, pump control valves, and flow meters. The equipment is interconnected at its inlet and outlet ends to remote-controllable pipe coupling systems provided for engaging and disengaging the equipment to and from piping infrastructure inlets and outlets. The platform is attached to actuators which are controllable to move the platform into and from within piping infrastructure. The actuators may be controlled by hydraulic, pneumatic or mechanical systems. The actuators are mountable into or onto substructure supports for the piping infrastructure.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a self-extracting service module having remote-controllable pipe coupling systems interconnected with the inlet and outlet of equipment mounted thereon, wherein each pipe coupling system comprises a collar portion having an outside diameter matching the outside diameter of the piping infrastructure inlet or outlet, and a slidable compressible sleeve portion superposed over the collar portion when in the disengaged position. The collar portion may be provided with an integral guide for sliding the compressible sleeve therealong. The sleeve portion is remotely manipulable to slidingly superpose a portion of a piping infrastructure inlet and the collar portion, and after which it is sealingly compressed onto the inlet and the collar portion.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In a preferred form, the invention provides a self-extracting service module for piping infrastructures, wherein the platform is attached to a plurality of actuators (preferably hydraulically operated), each actuator positioned near a corner of the platform whereby the weight of the platform and the pressure-regulating/monitoring system is distributed preferably equally among the plurality of actuators. Each actuator preferably comprises a flexible expandable bladder contained within a rigid frame having a movable member extending therein, whereby supplying a hydraulic pressure to the bladder will cause the bladder to expand axially against the movable member thereby extending the member from a resting position within the rigid frame along a linear axis, while releasing hydraulic pressure within the bladder will cause it to progressively collapse thereby allowing the movable member to retract within the rigid frame back to the resting position.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In another preferred form, the invention provides a service module platform attached to a plurality of actuators mounted at the bottom of a concrete vault wherein the platform is in a raised position when the actuators are pressurised, and in lowered position when the actuators are depressurised.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In an alternative preferred form, the invention provides a service module platform attached to a plurality of double-acting actuators mounted horizontally onto or into a supporting substructure of a piping infrastructure wherein the platform moves along a horizontal axis when a first side of the actuators is pressurised while the opposite side is depressurized, and retracts along the horizontal axis when the opposite side of actuators is pressurised and the first side is depressurised.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In another preferred form, the invention provides a service module attached to two sets of matched actuators mounted horizontally onto or into a supporting substructure of a piping infrastructure wherein the platform moves along a horizontal axis when a first set of actuators is pressurised while the second set is depressurized, and retracts along the horizontal axis when the second set of actuators is pressurised and the first set is depressurised.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a self-contained service station unit for sub-surface installation within subterranean piping infrastructures. The service station unit may be a concrete vault. The service station unit is provided with a piping infrastructure inlet and an outlet integrally fixed into and therethrough its walls for interconnecting with the subterranean piping infrastructure. The service station unit is provided with a self-extracting service module having a supporting structure such as a platform for mounting thereon equipment for regulating and/or monitoring the flow of liquid or gaseous media within the piping infrastructure. The equipment may be one piece or alternatively, two or more pieces of interconnected pressure-regulating or monitoring equipment such as single- or double-port main valves, pressure-reducing valves, pressure-relief and check valves, strainers, pumps, pump control valves, and flow meters. The equipment is interconnected at its inlet and outlet ends to remote-controllable pipe coupling systems provided for engaging and disengaging the equipment configuration to and from piping infrastructure inlets and outlets. Each pipe coupling system comprises a collar portion having an outside diameter matching the outside diameter of the piping infrastructure inlet or outlet, and a slidable compressible sleeve portion superposed over the collar portion when in the disengaged position. The collar portion may be provided with an integral guide for sliding the compressible sleeve therealong. The sleeve portion is remotely manipulable to slidingly superpose a portion of a piping infrastructure inlet and the collar portion, and after which it is sealingly compressed onto the inlet and the collar portion. The service module platform is attached to a plurality of interconnected actuators mounted at the bottom of the service station unit wherein the platform is in a raised position when the actuators are pressurised, and in lowered position with the actuators are depressurised. An actuator is preferably positioned near each corner of the platform whereby the weight of the platform and the equipment configuration mounted thereon is distributed among the plurality of actuators. Each actuator comprises a flexible expandable bladder contained within a rigid frame having a movable member extending therein, whereby supplying a hydraulic pressure to the bladder will cause the bladder to expand axially against the movable member thereby extending the member from a resting position within the rigid frame along a linear axis, while releasing hydraulic pressure within the bladder will cause it to progressively collapse thereby allowing the movable member to retract within the rigid frame back to the resting position. The hydraulic pressure to the actuators may be supplied by a feed line tapped into the piping infrastructure or alternatively, by a self-contained hydraulic pump and reservoir system.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The present invention will be described in conjunction with reference to the following drawing, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side view of one embodiment of the present invention shown engaged with a piping infrastructure;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a sectional end view of the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a sectional plan view of the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a side view of the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shown disengaged from a piping infrastructure;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a side view of the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shown in an elevated position above the piping infrastructure;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an end view of the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a plan view of the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The present invention provides a self-extracting service module which is mountable within a piping infrastructure service station wherein various types of pressure-regulating and/or monitoring equipment are required for controlling the flow of liquid or gaseous media through the piping infrastructure, e.g., within buried underground concrete vaults interconnected with underground municipal water lines, sewer lines, and natural gas lines. The service module comprises a supporting structure providing a platform for mounting thereon equipment for regulating and/or monitoring the flow of media therethrough, the platform being securely attachable to a plurality of actuators mountable into the piping infrastructure service station for raising and lowering the platform within the service station, and a remote pipe coupling system for detachably engaging the equipment with the piping infrastructure inlet and outlet coming into the piping infrastructure service station. When used with a buried concrete vault, the type, size and configuration of the actuators should enable sufficient displacement to raise the platform from within the vault to an easily accessible surface ground level. Suitable actuators include those operated by hydraulic pressure or pneumatic pressure or mechanical pressure. However, hydraulic actuators are preferable. The hydraulic actuators may be operable by upstream line pressure from the piping infrastructure or alternatively by a stand-alone hydraulic pump/reservoir system, to increase and decrease hydraulic pressure within the actuators thereby affecting the raising and lowering of the service module platform. Engagement and disengagement of the piping infrastructure outlet and inlet are accomplished by controllably operating the remote pipe coupling systems interconnected with the inlet and the outlet of the equipment mounted on the service module platform. After the self-extracting service module is installed in the service station and engaged with the piping infrastructure, then the open top vault is sealed in accordance with regulatory requirements with a hinged hatch or alternatively, a removable cover plate overlying the service module platform along with tread plates covering the open top on either side of the cover plate.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">When routine service or replacement work on the pressure regulating/monitoring equipment is required, the cover plate for the service station is removed or opened, after which the equipment on the service module is isolated from the media flow, and then disengaged from the piping infrastructure by remotely manipulating the remote pipe coupling systems to separate the equipment from the piping infrastructure inlet and outlet, and then pressuring the actuators to raise the service module platform to ground level thereby extracting the service module platform from within the concrete vault. The equipment mounted on the service module can then be easily accessed and serviced. After service has been completed, the pressure within the activators is controllably reduced thereby allowing the combined weight of the service module platform and the equipment mounted thereon to lower the module back down into the vault, after which the pressure-regulating/monitoring system is reconnected to the piping infrastructure by remotely manipulating the remote pipe coupling systems to sealably engage the equipment configuration with the piping infrastructure. If so required by the design and configuration of the piping infrastructure, the self-extracting service module of the present invention may be used in an above- or below-ground service station wherein the activators are mounted to the service station in a horizontal plane thereby providing lateral access and egress into piping infrastructure.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The present invention also provides a self-contained service station unit for sub-surface installation within subterranean piping infrastructures, comprising a concrete vault wherein is mounted a self-extracting service module provided with equipment mounted thereon for regulating and/or monitoring the flow of liquid or gaseous media therethrough the piping infrastructure.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">An example of a preferred embodiment of the present invention is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b>, and <b>3</b> comprising a self-extracting service module <b>20</b> installed within concrete vault <b>10</b> and engaged with a piping infrastructure inlet <b>11</b> and a piping infrastructure outlet <b>12</b>. The self-extracting service module <b>20</b> comprises:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0025">(a) a platform <b>32</b> mounted on a plurality of supporting crossmembers <b>31</b> integrally supported by opposing frame rails <b>30</b>, for installing thereon platform <b>32</b>, equipment <b>35</b> which in this case comprises a pressure-relief valve <b>38</b> connected to a main strainer <b>37</b>,</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0002" num="0026">(b) a first and a second remote pipe coupling system <b>21</b> for remotely engaging and disengaging equipment <b>35</b> with piping infrastructure inlet <b>11</b> and outlet <b>12</b> respectively, and</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0003" num="0027">(c) hydraulic lift system comprising four interconnected hydraulic lift units <b>40</b>, each unit <b>40</b> mounted on the floor of vault <b>10</b> under each corner of service module <b>20</b>.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0028">When engaged with a piping infrastructure as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b>, and <b>3</b>, frame rails <b>30</b> of self-extracting service module <b>20</b> rest on support stands <b>39</b>. The first remote pipe coupling system <b>21</b> is detachably engaged at one end to connector pipe portion <b>36</b> of piping infrastructure inlet <b>11</b> and at the other end, is interconnected to main strainer <b>37</b>. The second remote pipe coupling system <b>21</b> is detachably engaged at one end to connector pipe portion <b>36</b> of piping infrastructure outlet <b>12</b>, and at the other end, interconnected to pressure-reducing valve <b>38</b>. Piping infrastructure inlet <b>11</b> and outlet <b>12</b> are also connected by by-pass piping <b>13</b>. Those skilled in the art will understand that isolation valves <b>15</b> must be installed between by-pass piping <b>13</b> and remote pipe coupling systems <b>21</b>, and that by-pass piping <b>13</b> will be equipped with requisite pressure-regulating devices (not shown) for maintaining the flow of media while equipment <b>35</b> is disengaged from the piping infrastructure.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0029">In this embodiment, each hydraulic lift unit <b>40</b> is secured to concrete vault <b>10</b> by floor mount <b>41</b> and top mount <b>42</b>. Travelling plate <b>45</b> secures frame rail <b>30</b> of service module <b>20</b> to hydraulic lift unit <b>40</b>. Each hydraulic lift unit <b>40</b> contains an extendible member <b>43</b>. Increasing hydraulic pressure in lift units <b>40</b> cause extendible members <b>43</b> to move upward along guide/support members <b>44</b> thereby raising service module <b>20</b>, while reducing hydraulic pressure in lift units <b>40</b> causes the weight of service module <b>20</b> and equipment <b>35</b> mounted thereon to compress extendible members <b>43</b> thereby lowering service module <b>20</b> until it rests on support stands <b>39</b>. The hydraulic pressure for pressuring actuators <b>40</b> in this example is supplied by feed lines <b>16</b><i>a</i>-<b>16</b><i>b </i>tapped into by-pass piping <b>13</b>. Those skilled in this art will understand that a piping infrastructure (not shown) interconnected with a control panel (not shown) is required to regulate the flow of media through feed lines <b>16</b><i>a </i>to and <b>16</b><i>b </i>to and from hydraulic actuators <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0030">When service work is required on equipment <b>35</b>, self-extracting service module <b>20</b> is disengaged from the piping infrastructure by remotely manipulating pipe coupling systems <b>21</b> whereby they are first loosened from an engaged position shown by coupling system <b>21</b> engaged with inlet <b>11</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, then slidably retracted from piping infrastructure outlet <b>11</b> to a disengaged position as shown by coupling system <b>21</b><i>a </i>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. This can be achieved by means of elongated tools (not shown) that can be manipulated from outside the vault <b>10</b> through the open manhole. When both pipe coupling systems <b>21</b> are disengaged as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, then service module <b>20</b> may be raised by concurrently applying hydraulic line pressure to interconnected lift units <b>40</b> thereby causing the extendible members <b>43</b> to move upwards in unison along guide/support members <b>44</b> thereby raising metal platform <b>32</b> from within concrete vault <b>10</b> to a position where metal platform <b>32</b> is approximately level with the top of concrete vault <b>10</b> thereby making equipment <b>35</b> readily accessible at ground level as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5</figref>, <b>6</b> and <b>7</b> without the worker space constraints and hazards attendant within the confines of concrete vault <b>10</b>. Personnel can easily access equipment configuration <b>35</b> from all sides by standing on treadplates <b>14</b>. Treadplates <b>14</b> can be removable or alternatively, attached by hinges (not shown) to the top of vault <b>10</b>. While those skilled in the art will understand that a variety of actuators may be selected for use with the self-extracting service model of the present invention, it is preferred to use a low-pressure actuator of the type described in U.S. Pat. No. 6,299,443, the disclosure of which is incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0031">In this example, first remote pipe coupling system <b>21</b> comprises a coupling engagement plate <b>22</b> sealably interconnected with strainer valve <b>37</b>. Coupling control plate <b>22</b> is provided with coupling collar <b>23</b> having an outside diameter selected to match the outside diameter of connector piping portion <b>36</b> on piping infrastructure inlet <b>11</b>. Coupling collar <b>23</b> is fitted with a controllably slidable and compressible coupling sleeve <b>24</b>. The inner diameter of coupling sleeve <b>24</b> is selected to slidingly engage the outside diameters of coupling collar <b>23</b> and connector piping portion <b>36</b>. Coupling engagement plate <b>22</b> is provided with means for affecting engagement and disengagement of pipe coupling system <b>21</b> with connector piping portion <b>36</b> whereby coupling engagement plate <b>22</b> may be remotely manipulated to first, slide coupling sleeve <b>24</b> over coupling collar <b>23</b> and connector piping <b>36</b> until it abuts spool <b>19</b>, and then compressed to provide a leak-proof seal. The means for affecting engagement and disengagement of pipe coupling system <b>21</b> may be an elongate mechanical tool (not shown) having one end adapted for engaging plate <b>22</b> and the other end having a handle portion. The compression/release of the slide coupling sleeve <b>24</b> may likewise be operated by an elongated tool having a wrench socket at one end and a handle at the other. The wrench socket may be used to tighten or loosen bolts that compress the sleeve <b>24</b> to grip or release the coupling collar <b>23</b> and the piping portion <b>36</b>. An example of such a system is disclosed in pending U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/926,328 filed Aug. 26, 2004 by Fred M. Tadros, the disclosure of which is specifically incorporated herein by reference. Alternatively, the engagement/disengagement means and the compression/release means may incorporate electric motors that loosen the bolts and slide the coupling sleeve as required. The motors may be electrically or electronically controlled from a remote location outside the vault, and may be battery-powered, wired to an electrical supply, or powered by a removable wand carrying an electrical cable. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, coupling engagement plate <b>22</b><i>a </i>may be remotely manipulated to first decompress coupling sleeve <b>24</b><i>a </i>from coupling collar <b>23</b><i>a </i>and connector piping <b>36</b><i>a</i>, then controllably sliding coupling sleeve <b>24</b><i>a </i>toward pressure-reducing valve <b>38</b> thereby completely releasing/freeing equipment configuration <b>35</b> to enable vertical movement of service module <b>20</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>, thereby extracting service module <b>20</b> from within vault <b>10</b> and raising it to ground level for service work. Those skilled in this art will understand that isolation valves <b>15</b> are required between pipe coupling systems <b>21</b> and by-pass piping <b>13</b>, and that isolation valves <b>15</b> must be closed before remote pipe coupling systems <b>21</b> are disengaged from connector piping portions <b>36</b>. When isolation valves <b>15</b> are in closed positions, media moving through the piping infrastructure will be routed through by-pass piping <b>13</b> around equipment <b>35</b> mounted on service module <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0032">The self contained service station unit containing herein the self-extracting service module provided by the present invention may be constructed and assembled off-site, and then delivered to the service station location for subsurface installation within subterranean piping infrastructures. Such service station units can be considerably smaller than conventional units containing therein similar requisite equipment configurations for regulating and/or monitoring the flow of liquid or gaseous media therethrough.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0033">If so desired, the self-extracting service module of the present invention can be retrofitted into existing service stations to enable the raising of equipment configurations to surface ground level for service work there by avoiding the hazards and constraints of performing such work in confined spaces.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0034">While this invention has been described with respect to the preferred embodiments, it is to be understood that various alterations and modifications can be made to components of the self-extracting service module for piping infrastructures within the scope of this invention, which are limited only by the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A self-extracting service module apparatus for piping infrastructures used for transporting media, the apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>equipment for controlling a flow of media therethrough, the equipment having an inlet and an outlet;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a movable platform supporting said equipment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first remote-controllable pipe coupling/de-coupling device interconnected with the equipment inlet and a second remote-controllable pipe coupling/de-coupling device interconnected with the equipment outlet; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of actuators acting on said platform, said actuators being operable to move said platform back and forth along an axis when said first and second remote-controllable devices are de-coupled from said inlet and said outlet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the equipment is adapted for controlling liquid media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the equipment is adapted for controlling said media selected from a group consisting of water, reagent, product, waste stream, and sewage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the equipment is adapted for controlling gaseous media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the movable platform is provided with a supporting substructure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the substructure comprises frame rails integrally engaged with the platform.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the substructure comprises framerails integrally engaged with a plurality of crossmembers, the crossmember integrally engaged with the platform.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the actuators are pressure-operated devices wherein each device is provided with a moveable member that extends along a linear axis when pressure is increased and is retractable when pressure is decreased.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the pressure-operated device is a hollow flexible axially expandable bladder mounted within a rigid frame whereby increasing pressure within the bladder causes the moveable member to extend along a liner axis within the rigid frame.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the pressure is selected from a group consisting of hydraulic pressure, pneumatic pressure and mechanical pressure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the pressure is provided by media drawn from the piping infrastructure, said drawn media controllably circulated to the actuators.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the actuators are mounted within a supporting substructure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the actuators move the platform mounted thereto within the substructure, back and forth along a vertical axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the substructure is a concrete vault provided with a piping infrastructure inlet and an outlet, the vault provided with a removable top.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the actuators move the platform mounted thereto within the substructure, back and forth along a horizontal axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the platform is mounted onto a plurality of wheels for rolling along a track integrally connected to the substructure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the remote-controllable pipe coupling device comprises a coupling control plate provided with a collar portion having an outside diameter matching the outside diameter of the piping infrastructure inlet, a slidable compressible sleeve portion superposed over the collar portion, a first device for remotely manipulating said sleeve portion to slidingly superpose a portion of the piping infrastructure inlet and a portion of the collar portion, and a second device for sealably compressing said sleeve portion onto the inlet and the collar portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein the collar portion has an outside diameter matching the outside diameter of the piping infrastructure outlet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein the collar portion is provided with an integral guide for moving said sleeve portion therealong.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein the piping infrastructure inlet and outlet are each provided with a spool for abutting the sleeve portion thereagainst for coupling therewith.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein the first device is a hand-operated tool selected from a group consisting of mechanical tools, hydraulic tools and pneumatic tools.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein the second device is a hand operated tool selected from a group consisting of mechanical tools, hydraulic tools and pneumatic tools.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the equipment is adapted for controlling gaseous media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the movable platform is provided with a supporting substructure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the substructure comprises frame rails integrally engaged with the platform.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein the substructure comprises framerails integrally engaged with a plurality of crossmembers, the crossmember integrally engaged with the platform.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. A service station assembly for regulating the flow of liquid media within a piping infrastructure; the assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a vault;</claim-text>
<claim-text>equipment for controlling the flow of media therethrough, the equipment having an inlet and an outlet;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a movable platform supporting said equipment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first remote-controllable pipe coupling/de-coupling device interconnected with the equipment inlet and a second remote-controllable pipe coupling/de-coupling device interconnected with the equipment outlet; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of actuators acting on said platform, said actuators being operable to move said platform back and forth along an axis when said first and second remote-controllable devices are de-coupled from said inlet and said outlet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref> wherein the equipment is adapted for controlling liquid media.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00028">claim 28</claim-ref> wherein the equipment is adapted for controlling said media selected from a group consisting of water, reagent, product, waste stream, and sewage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00027">claim 27</claim-ref> wherein the actuators are pressure-operated devices wherein each device is provided with a moveable member that extends along a linear axis when pressure is increased and is retractable when pressure is decreased.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref> wherein the pressure-operated device is a hollow flexible axially expandable bladder mounted within a rigid frame whereby increasing pressure within the bladder causes the moveable member to extend along a liner axis within the rigid frame.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00032" num="00032">
<claim-text>32. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref> wherein the pressure is selected from a group consisting of hydraulic pressure, pneumatic pressure and mechanical pressure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00033" num="00033">
<claim-text>33. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref> wherein the pressure is provided by media drawn from the piping infrastructure, said drawn media controllably circulated to the actuators.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00034" num="00034">
<claim-text>34. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein the actuators are mounted within a supporting substructure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00035" num="00035">
<claim-text>35. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein the actuators move the platform mounted thereto within the substructure, back and forth along a vertical axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00036" num="00036">
<claim-text>36. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00034">claim 34</claim-ref> wherein the substructure is a concrete vault provided with a piping infrastructure inlet and an outlet, the vault provided with a removable top.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00037" num="00037">
<claim-text>37. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein the actuators move the platform mounted thereto within the substructure, back and forth along a horizontal axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00038" num="00038">
<claim-text>38. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00037">claim 37</claim-ref> wherein the platform is mounted onto a plurality of wheels for rolling along a track integrally connected to the substructure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00039" num="00039">
<claim-text>39. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein the remote-controllable pipe coupling device comprises a coupling control plate provided with a collar portion having an outside diameter matching the outside diameter of the piping infrastructure inlet, a slidable compressible sleeve portion superposed over the collar portion, a first device for remotely manipulating said sleeve portion to slidingly superpose a portion of the piping infrastructure inlet and a portion of the collar portion, and a second device for sealably compressing said sleeve portion onto the inlet and the collar portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00040" num="00040">
<claim-text>40. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00039">claim 39</claim-ref> wherein the collar portion has an outside diameter matching the outside diameter of the piping infrastructure outlet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00041" num="00041">
<claim-text>41. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00039">claim 39</claim-ref> wherein the collar portion is provided with an integral guide for moving said sleeve portion therealong.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00042" num="00042">
<claim-text>42. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00039">claim 39</claim-ref> wherein the piping infrastructure inlet and outlet are each provided with a spool for abutting the sleeve portion thereagainst for coupling therewith.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00043" num="00043">
<claim-text>43. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00039">claim 39</claim-ref> wherein the first device is a hand-operated tool selected from a group consisting of mechanical tools, hydraulic tools and pneumatic tools.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00044" num="00044">
<claim-text>44. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00039">claim 39</claim-ref> wherein the second device is a hand operated tool selected from a group consisting of mechanical tools, hydraulic tools and pneumatic tools.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
