<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298121-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298121</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11111139</doc-number>
<date>20050421</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>234</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>40</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>323282</main-classification>
<further-classification>323285</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Circuit and method for increasing the stability of switch-mode power supplies</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5717318</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Matsuda et al.</name>
<date>19980200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>323273</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5945820</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Namgoong et al.</name>
<date>19990800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>323282</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6597159</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Yang</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>323283</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>323283</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>323284</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>323285</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>323351</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>323282</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>323288</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>1</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060238180</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061026</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Carter</last-name>
<first-name>Michael</first-name>
<address>
<city>Clayton</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Powers</last-name>
<first-name>Randall L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Raleigh</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fogg &amp; Powers LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fogg</last-name>
<first-name>David N.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Moura</last-name>
<first-name>Richard J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>ADC DSL Systems, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Eden Prairie</city>
<state>MN</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Han</last-name>
<first-name>Jessica</first-name>
<department>2838</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An improved circuit and method for increasing the stability of switch-mode power supplies via frequency fold-back is disclosed. For example, a circuit for increasing the stability of a switch-mode power supply using the compensation signal to control the frequency of the oscillator is disclosed, which includes an operational amplifier that functions to scale the compensation signal. Thus, the switching frequency of the power supply involved is decreased as the load is reduced. This novel use of the compensation signal to control the switching frequency of a switch-mode power supply significantly increases the stability of the power supply as compared to prior switch-mode power supplies. Therefore, the switch-mode power supply may be used for those applications where relatively high stability is desired.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="134.79mm" wi="188.64mm" file="US07298121-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="202.10mm" wi="155.19mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298121-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application is related to commonly assigned and co-pending U.S. patent application Ser. No. 11/111,138 entitled “CIRCUIT AND METHOD FOR REDUCING THE SIZE AND COST OF SWITCH-MODE POWER SUPPLIES,” filed on the same date as the present application, which is incorporated herein by reference in its entirety.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to the power supply field, and more specifically, but not exclusively, to an improved circuit and method for increasing the stability of switch-mode power supplies.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Switch-mode power supplies are used in a broad range of electronic applications, such as, for example, telecommunication systems, computers, television equipment, video equipment, etc., where it is important to accurately regulate a power supply output over a wide range of loads. Some advantages of switch-mode power supplies over other types of regulated power supplies (e.g., linear power supplies) are that they are smaller, weigh less, consume less power, and are highly efficient compared to many other types of regulated power supplies.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In numerous applications, switch-mode power supplies must operate with stability over a very wide range of loads. One technique used for operating such switch-mode power supplies over very wide ranges of loads is to fold back the switching frequency in response to decreases in the loads. However, in certain applications, the switch-mode power supply may be operated as a current source instead of as voltage source. Stability in this mode of operation is much more difficult to achieve.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Valid loads for voltage source switch-mode power supplies typically range from some non-zero minimum to some predetermined maximum. Short circuits are typically handled by turning off the power supply and retrying to start periodically. Valid loads for power supplies operating in current source mode range from open circuit to short circuit. The power supply is not permitted to power cycle and must provide a stable current/voltage at all loads. Typically, current source mode power supplies have a maximum output voltage they will put out at open circuit. This protects the power supply components from excessive voltages. The conditions of open circuit and short circuit represent opposite ends of the load spectrum, but both conditions are very light loads on a current source power supply. Maximum load occurs halfway in between where the output voltage and current are at their maximum.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">One technique used to increase stability over a very wide load range is to lower the power supply switching frequency at light loads. An existing technique used to perform this frequency fold-back in switch-mode power supplies is to add a winding to the power transformer that is ratioed to the output voltage of the supply involved. This voltage is then used as an input to a voltage controlled oscillator. This technique can be used readily with a voltage source, where the output voltage varies linearly from minimum load to maximum load. However, this added winding frequency fold-back technique cannot be used with a current source, because the minimum load condition for a current source occurs at both ends of the load spectrum: full output voltage and no output voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">As such, another technique was derived to perform frequency fold-back with a current source mode switch-mode power supply. Every switch-mode power supply has at least one error amplifier to sense the value of the output and compare it to a reference value. The result of this comparison is commonly referred to as the compensation signal. The compensation signal is proportional to the output load in both current source mode and voltage source mode power supplies. This technique takes this compensation signal, scales it, and uses it to control the power supply's oscillator. The lower frequency at lighter loads improves the stability of the control loop under these conditions.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Notwithstanding the distinct advantages of the above-described technique, it would be advantageous to have a switch-mode power supply that is even more stable than prior switch-mode power supplies. As described in detail below, the present invention provides an improved switch-mode power supply that is more stable than prior switch-mode power supplies.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The present invention provides an improved circuit and method for implementing frequency fold-back in switch-mode power supplies. In accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention, a circuit and method for controlling the switching frequency of the oscillator for a switch-mode power supply is provided. This novel use by the present invention of using the compensation signal to control the switching frequency of a switch-mode power supply significantly increases the stability of the power supply as compared to prior switch-mode power supplies. As such, in accordance with the present invention, a switch-mode power supply may be used for those applications where relatively high stability is desired.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The novel features believed characteristic of the invention are set forth in the appended claims. The invention itself, however, as well as a preferred mode of use, further objectives and advantages thereof, will best be understood by reference to the following detailed description of an illustrative embodiment when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> depicts a schematic diagram of an example electronic circuit that can be used to control the frequency of the oscillator for a switch-mode power supply, in accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">With reference now to the figures, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> depicts a schematic diagram of an example electronic circuit <b>100</b> that can be used to control the frequency of the oscillator for a switch-mode power supply, in accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention. For this example embodiment, circuit <b>100</b> includes a resistor <b>102</b> coupled to an input connection <b>101</b> of circuit <b>100</b>. Input connection <b>101</b> is connected to feedback circuitry (not shown) that produces a compensation signal that indicates the loading of the power supply involved. The other side of resistor <b>102</b> is connected to an input of an operational amplifier <b>104</b>. Thus, a voltage at input connection <b>101</b> is coupled to the positive input of operational amplifier <b>104</b>. For this example, resistor <b>102</b> may be implemented with a 30.1 KΩ (1% tolerance) resistor, and operational amplifier <b>104</b> may be implemented with an LM 2904 operational amplifier.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The negative input of operational amplifier <b>104</b> is connected to one side of a resistor <b>114</b>, a resistor <b>118</b>, and a capacitor <b>116</b>. The other side of resistor <b>118</b> is connected to circuit ground. The other sides of resistor <b>114</b> and capacitor <b>116</b> are connected together, to a source of a Field-Effect Transistor (FET) <b>108</b>, and to the anode of a diode <b>120</b>. The output of operational amplifier <b>104</b> is connected to a resistor <b>106</b>, and the second side of resistor <b>106</b> is connected to the gate of transistor <b>108</b>. As such, for this example embodiment, resistors <b>106</b>, <b>114</b> and <b>118</b> may be implemented with, respectively, 68.1Ω, 100 KΩ, and 49.9 KΩ resistors (e.g., all with 1% tolerance), and capacitor <b>116</b> may be implemented with a 0.1 μF capacitor (e.g., rated for 50V). Also, for this example, transistor <b>108</b> may be implemented with a 2N7002 transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The cathode of diode <b>120</b> is connected to a resistor <b>122</b>. The second side of resistor <b>122</b> feeds into a resistor <b>124</b> and a capacitor <b>126</b>, which sets the switching frequency of the control chip <b>110</b>. The other side of capacitor <b>126</b> is connected to circuit ground. The other side of resistor <b>124</b> is connected to a capacitor <b>128</b>, a capacitor <b>130</b>, the collector of transistor <b>108</b>, a resistor <b>112</b>, and a voltage reference (VREF) input of control chip <b>110</b>. The other sides of capacitors <b>128</b> and <b>130</b> are connected to circuit ground. The other side of resistor <b>112</b> is connected to input connection <b>101</b> and resistor <b>102</b>, and to a compensation (COMP) input of control chip <b>110</b>. Resistor <b>112</b> functions as a pull-up resistor for the compensation circuitry output. An output connection of control chip <b>110</b> is coupled to power circuitry (not shown) for a power supply. As such, for this example embodiment, resistors <b>112</b>, <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> may be implemented, respectively, with a 2.21 KΩ resistor, a 16.9 KΩ resistor, and an 86.6 KΩ resistor (e.g., all having a tolerance of 1%). Also, for this example, capacitors <b>126</b>, <b>128</b> and <b>130</b> may be implemented, respectively, with a 390 pF capacitor (e.g., rated at 100V), a 0.1 μF capacitor (e.g., rated at 50V), and another 0.1 μF capacitor (e.g., also rated at 50V). The control chip (e.g., oscillator device) <b>110</b> may be implemented, for example, as part of a UCC3813 Pulse Width Modulation (PWM) control chip. Note that capacitors <b>128</b> and <b>130</b> may be provided for noise suppression in a practical application as shown, but these components are not required to practice the invention and do not limit the scope of the invention in any way.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In operation, circuit <b>100</b> can receive a compensation signal at input <b>101</b>, which is a voltage that indicates the loading of the power supply involved. A compensation signal received at input <b>101</b> is developed across resistor <b>102</b> and applied as a voltage to the positive input of operational amplifier <b>104</b>. The output signal from operational amplifier <b>104</b> is applied to the gate of transistor <b>108</b> through resistor <b>106</b>. As the compensation signal voltage at input connection <b>101</b> is increased, the voltage applied to the gate of transistor <b>108</b> is increased. As transistor <b>108</b> is turned on, it develops a voltage across resistor <b>122</b> through diode <b>120</b>. This voltage across resistor <b>120</b> produces a current that sums with current coming from the voltage across resistor <b>124</b>. These currents charge capacitor <b>126</b>. The (PWM) control chip <b>110</b> provides the thresholds at which capacitor <b>126</b> discharges through control chip <b>110</b>. This output signal from operational amplifier <b>104</b> is also developed across resistor <b>124</b> and capacitor <b>126</b> and applied to the Rt/Ct input connection of control chip <b>110</b>. Transistor <b>108</b> and diode device <b>120</b> function to limit the current summed into the oscillator capacitor <b>126</b>. This limits the range over which the frequency fold-back circuit can vary the switching frequency. Therefore, in accordance with the principles of the present invention, operational amplifier <b>104</b> functions to suitably scale the compensation signal to control the frequency of the oscillator implemented in control chip <b>110</b>. Importantly, this novel use by the present invention of the compensation signal to control the switching frequency of a switch-mode power supply significantly increases the stability of the power supply as compared to prior switch-mode power supplies. As such, in accordance with the present invention, a switch-mode power supply may be used for those applications where relatively high stability is desired, such as, for example, to provide a highly stable 60 mA current source for a T1 communication line.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The description of the present invention has been presented for purposes of illustration and description, and is not intended to be exhaustive or limited to the invention in the form disclosed. Many modifications and variations will be apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art. These embodiments were chosen and described in order to best explain the principles of the invention, the practical application, and to enable others of ordinary skill in the art to understand the invention for various embodiments with various modifications as are suited to the particular use contemplated.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A frequency control circuit for a switch-mode power supply, comprising:
<claim-text>an oscillator device, an output of said oscillator device operable to set a frequency of said switch-mode power supply;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a storage device coupled to a switching rate input of said oscillator device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transistor device, an output of said transistor device coupled to said storage device, said transistor device operable to increase or decrease a level of a signal stored in said storage device, and responsive to said increase or decrease of said level of said signal, increase or decrease a switching rate of said oscillator device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an amplifier device, an input of said amplifier device operable to receive a signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply, and an output of said amplifier device coupled to an input of said transistor device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a diode device coupled to an emitter of said transistor device, said diode device operable to limit voltage at said output of said transistor device to a predetermined level.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said amplifier device is operable to scale said signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply and control said frequency of said oscillator device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply comprises a compensation signal from a feedback circuit associated with said switch-mode power supply.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said oscillator device comprises an oscillator device in a switch-mode power supply semiconductor chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said transistor device comprises a Field-Effect Transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said storage device comprises a capacitor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A frequency control circuit for a switch-mode power supply, comprising:
<claim-text>a voltage or current controlled oscillator for said switch-mode power supply;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for receiving a first signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means, coupled to said means for receiving, for generating a second signal indicating an increase or decrease in said load condition for said switch-mode power supply;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means, coupled to said means for generating, for storing said second signal indicating said increase or decrease in said load condition for said switch-mode power supply; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means, coupled to said means for storing, for increasing or decreasing a switching rate of said voltage or current controlled oscillator responsive to said second signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>means for limiting a voltage to a predetermined level, said voltage being output from said means for generating and associated with said first signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said means for generating comprises an amplifier device operable to scale said first signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply and control said frequency of said oscillator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said first signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply comprises a compensation signal from a feedback circuit associated with said switch-mode power supply.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said voltage or current controlled oscillator comprises an oscillator device arranged in a switch-mode power supply semiconductor chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, further comprising a transistor device and a diode device operable to limit a voltage to a predetermined level, said voltage being output from said means for generating and associated with said first signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The frequency control circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said means for generating comprises an operational amplifier.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A method for frequency control in a switch-mode power supply, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>receiving a first signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating a second signal indicating an increase or decrease in said load condition for said switch-mode power supply;</claim-text>
<claim-text>storing said second signal indicating said increase or decrease in said load condition for said switch-mode power supply;</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling said stored second signal to an input of a voltage or current controlled oscillator device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>increasing or decreasing a switching rate of said voltage or current controlled oscillator device responsive to said second signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>coupling a diode device to an output an amplifier device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>coupling said amplifier device to a frequency control input of said voltage or current controlled oscillator device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>limiting a voltage at said output of said amplifier device to a predetermined level.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>scaling said first signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>controlling a frequency of said voltage or current controlled oscillator device responsive to the scaling step.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein said first signal indicating a load condition for said switch-mode power supply comprises a compensation signal from a feedback circuit associated with said switch-mode power supply.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein said voltage or current controlled oscillator device comprises an oscillator device arranged in a switch-mode power supply semiconductor chip.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the generating step is performed by an operational amplifier.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
