<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298590-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298590</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10952283</doc-number>
<date>20040927</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>350</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>58</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3602457</main-classification>
<further-classification>360245</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Suspension limiter with proximally cantilevered limiter members</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6172853</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Davis et al.</name>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6195237</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Perez</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6233121</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Pan</name>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6417996</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Budde</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6424498</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Patterson et al.</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6426851</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Perez</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6587311</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Niijima et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>360255</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6791798</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Mei</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6801400</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Fu et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7130157</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Sassine et al.</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0075602</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Mangold et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0070883</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Mahoney et al.</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0180052</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Suzuki et al.</name>
<date>20050800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3602457</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>28</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3602457</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>360245</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mei</last-name>
<first-name>Shijin</first-name>
<address>
<city>Temecula</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Intellectual Property Law Office of Joel D. Voelzke</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Magnecomp Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Temecula</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Evans</last-name>
<first-name>Jefferson</first-name>
<department>2627</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A disk drive suspension and method uses two proximally cantilevered members to limit tongue movement in a suspension of a load beam having a beam portion and a flexure having a tongue. The suspension has a limiter structure comprising the two proximally cantilevered members arranged on the beam portion and the tongue respectively and intersecting for increasing engagement responsive to undue tongue travel against dislodgment.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="81.96mm" wi="124.21mm" file="US07298590-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="239.01mm" wi="140.04mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298590-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="214.46mm" wi="155.96mm" file="US07298590-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="195.58mm" wi="134.87mm" file="US07298590-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="212.09mm" wi="153.16mm" file="US07298590-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="162.48mm" wi="137.08mm" file="US07298590-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Not applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR DEVELOPMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Not Applicable</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">REFERENCE TO A MICROFICHE APPENDIX</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Not Applicable</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">This invention relates to disk drive suspensions, and more particularly to improvements in limiter structures for disk drive suspensions providing increased security of engagement through intersection of two proximally directed members that respond to tongue undue travel by increasing the impalement of the tongue provided member on the load beam provided member of the limiter structure.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Many limiters are known and used for the purpose of preventing damaging excursions of the flexure tongue and slider toward the disk when the suspension undergoes shock. In general, known limiters are located some distance from the dimple contact point and thus do not transmit reaction force directly from the slider, but only through bridging structures. Limiter structures using beam portion members and tongue members do not arrange these members proximally for increased security upon a tongue excursion. See U.S. Pat. No. 6,172,853 to Davis, U.S. Pat. No. 6,195,237 to Perez, U.S. Pat. No. 6,233,121 to Pan, U.S. Pat. No. 6,417,996 to Budde and U.S. Pat. No. 6,424,498 to Patterson, for example.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is an object therefore to provide an improved disk drive suspension. It is another object to provide a suspension having an improved limiter structure against undue travel of the suspension tongue and slider under shock and under load-unload conditions. A further object is the provision of a limiter structure that includes a member vertically spaced from the slider and formed from the free proximate end of the cantilevered flexure tongue. Another object is the formation of a limiter structure cooperating part on the suspension beam portion cantilevered proximally like the tongue limiter member to interengage vertically with the tongue free end defined limiter structure to limit tongue free end travel.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">These and other objects of the invention to become apparent hereinafter are realized in a disk drive suspension comprising a disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion and in a second plane generally parallel to the first plane a flexure, the flexure having a proximally cantilevered tongue being adapted to carry a slider and having a proximate end, a limiter structure limiting travel of the tongue away from the beam portion, the limiter structure comprising intersected first and second proximally cantilevered members defined by the beam portion and the tongue proximate end respectively and arranged for engagement in response to undue tongue travel in a manner such that tongue travel away from the beam portion increasingly secures the engagement of the members.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In this and like embodiments, typically, the beam portion member has a flat extent within the first plane, the tongue member engaging the beam portion member flat extent, the beam portion comprises a wall extending opposite the tongue proximate end, the wall being configured to define the beam portion member in tongue member engaging relation, the beam portion being otherwise free of tongue travel limiting members, the tongue member extends from the second plane at an angle of about 45 to about 80 degrees, the beam portion member extending at an angle of about 0 degrees to the beam portion, the tongue member is U-shaped and free of bends along its longitudinal axis other than at the tongue, the tongue has a given lateral extent, and the tongue member has a lesser lateral extent, there is also included a slider having a leading edge end at the tongue proximate end, whereby the limiter structure is adjacent the slider leading edge end, the tongue member comprises left and right legs closely bracketing the beam portion member, and a cross-piece overlying the beam portion member, the cross piece having less vertical height from the tongue than the beam portion member has lateral width, and/or the tongue member has a cross piece and left and right legs bracketing the beam portion member, the legs being free of bends other than at the tongue, the cross member and legs having substantially equal widths.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In a further embodiment, there is provided a disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion and in a second plane generally parallel to the first plane a flexure, the flexure having a proximally cantilevered tongue having a proximate end, a slider carried by the tongue, a limiter structure limiting travel of the tongue away from the beam portion, the limiter structure comprising intersected first and second proximally cantilevered members defined by the beam portion and the tongue proximate end respectively and arranged for engagement in response to undue tongue travel in a manner such that tongue travel away from the beam portion increasingly secures the engagement of the members.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In this and like embodiments, typically, the beam portion member is flat, the tongue member bracketing the beam portion member in engaging relation upon undue travel of the tongue, the beam portion comprises a wall extending opposite the tongue proximate end, the wall being apertured and configured within the aperture to define the beam portion member in tongue member engaging relation, the beam portion being otherwise free of tongue travel limiting members, the tongue member extends from the second plane at an angle of about 45 to about 90 degrees, the beam portion member extending at an angle of about 0 degrees to the beam portion, the tongue member is U-shaped and free of bends along its longitudinal axis other than at the tongue, the tongue has a given lateral extent, and the tongue member has a lesser lateral extent, the slider has a leading edge end at the tongue proximate end and a trailing edge end, the limiter structure being more closely adjacent the slider leading edge end, the tongue member comprises left and right legs bracketing the beam portion member, and a cross-piece overlying the beam portion member, the cross piece having less vertical height from the tongue than the beam portion member has lateral width, and the tongue member legs are free of bends other than at the tongue, the cross piece and legs having substantially equal widths.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In a further embodiment, the invention provides a disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion adapted to be supported by a spring portion and a base portion, the beam portion having a proximally cantilevered limiter member, a flexure carried by the beam portion, the flexure comprising a frame and a tongue portion generally in a second plane and having a tongue proximate end cantilevered from the frame for supporting a slider, and a limiter structure limiting the tongue from undue travel, the limiter structure comprising a tongue limiter member extending from the tongue proximate end into the first plane and arranged to bracket the beam portion limiter member, the tongue member shifting distally on the beam portion member responsive to increased tongue travel against tongue limiter member dislodgement from the beam portion limiter member in tongue undue travel limiting relation.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">As in previous embodiments, generally the beam portion limiter member is flat for engagement with the tongue limiter member, the beam portion comprises a wall extending opposite the tongue proximate end, the wall being configured to define the beam portion limiter member in tongue limiter member engaging relation, the tongue limiter member extends at an angle to the beam portion limiter member of about 45 to about 80 degrees, the tongue limiter member is straight beyond the tongue, the tongue has a given lateral extent, the tongue limiter member having a lesser lateral extent, there is also included a slider having a leading edge end at the tongue proximate end, whereby the limiter structure is adjacent the slider leading edge end, and the tongue limiter member comprises left and right legs bracketing the beam portion limiter member, and a cross-piece overlying the beam portion limiter member, the cross piece having less vertical height than the beam portion limiter member has lateral width.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In its method aspects the invention provides a method of limiting undue relative movement between a beam portion and flexure tongue in a disk drive suspension, the flexure tongue having a cantilevered proximate end, including cantilevering a beam portion limiter member proximally, and cantilevering a tongue limiter member proximally and vertically in beam portion member intersecting relation such that tongue travel away from the beam portion increasingly secures engagement of the members.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Typically, the method includes defining the beam portion limiter member as a flat extent coplanar with the beam portion, angling the tongue limiter member at about 45 to about 80 degrees to the beam portion limiter member, bracketing the beam portion limiter member with the tongue limiter member, supporting a slider on the tongue, and maintaining the tongue limiter free of bends other than at the tongue.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Other embodiments will appear hereinafter.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The invention will be further described in conjunction with the attached drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a top plan view of an improved suspension according to the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is an oblique, fragmentary view thereof, showing the distal end of the suspension;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a side elevation view thereof;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is bottom plan view thereof;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a top plan view thereof;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an oblique view of the formed suspension flexure;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a top plan view of the suspension flexure before forming; and,</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an oblique view of the formed beam portion.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The invented suspension is suitable for both pico and femto form factor suspensions. It is readily formed from suitably etched parts by conventional forming techniques such as bending. Advantages of the invention suspension include a single large radius bend between the tongue free end and no further bends to complicate manufacture and increase scrap, a proximally oriented beam portion limiter member, the member being flat and unformed for ease of manufacture and limit suspension height, the tongue limiter member is at the slider leading edge for enhanced protection, reaction forces transfer directly from the slider since the limiter structure is formed from the flexure tongue and generally opposite the slider and closely adjacent the dimple contact locus for engagement opposite the slider. Other advantages include a U-shape limiter that has spaced legs fixed to the edges of the flexure tongue portion free end for stiffness and strength despite thinness, lowest vertical profile, and a cantilever flexure, proximally toward the suspension base portion such that it further engages the beam portion limiter member upon a tongue excursion and does not slip off, and the possibility of effecting the forming steps before or after other manufacturing operations.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">With reference now to the drawings in detail, In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref> and <b>6</b>, disk drive arm <b>8</b> carries suspension <b>10</b> for angular or translational motion. Suspension <b>10</b> comprises in a generally horizontal plane a base portion <b>9</b>, a spring portion <b>11</b>, and a beam portion <b>12</b> and in the same or a generally parallel plane a flexure <b>14</b> separate or integral with and carried by the beam portion. Flexure <b>14</b> comprises an open frame <b>16</b> and a tongue portion <b>18</b> having a free end <b>22</b> cantilevered into the frame from the frame and extending proximally, that is toward the base portion <b>9</b>. Slider <b>24</b> is supported by the tongue portion <b>18</b>. A limiter structure <b>26</b> limits the tongue portion <b>18</b> from undue travel. Limiter structure <b>26</b> comprises tongue limiter member <b>28</b> which is part of the tongue free end <b>22</b> and extends angularly, e.g. at about 45 to about 80 of about 90 degrees to the second or tongue plane P-P. Tongue limiter member <b>28</b> is bent out of the tongue free end <b>22</b> and is suitably but not necessarily vertically spaced from and opposite the slider <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Limiter structure <b>26</b> includes a beam portion limiter member <b>56</b> and a tongue limiter member <b>28</b>. Beam portion <b>12</b> of suspension <b>10</b> defines the beam portion limiter member <b>56</b> that is formed in beam portion <b>12</b> such as to be able to engage the tongue limiter member <b>28</b> against undue travel of the tongue portion <b>18</b>. For this purpose, the beam portion limiter member <b>56</b> is also proximally disposed (cantilevered toward the base portion <b>9</b>) as shown providing the limiter structure <b>26</b> with a pair of proximally disposed members <b>28</b>, <b>56</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">As shown, tongue limiter member <b>28</b> is interiorly open, being generally U-shaped with left and right legs <b>32</b>, <b>34</b> and cross piece <b>36</b> extending therebetween parallel to the opposing area <b>44</b> of the tongue free end <b>22</b> and is arranged to be open to the opposing area <b>25</b> that surmounts slider <b>24</b>. Tongue area <b>44</b> extends opposite limiter structure cross piece <b>36</b> into the flexure opening <b>38</b> in a manner to provide a locus of attachment <b>46</b> on the tongue portion <b>18</b> for attachment of the slider <b>24</b>. Beam portion <b>12</b> provides a gram load onto the slider <b>24</b> through tongue portion <b>18</b> via a dimple <b>48</b>. Dimple <b>48</b> can also be formed on the tongue portion <b>18</b>. In either case the apex <b>50</b> of the dimple defines the locus <b>52</b> of dimple <b>48</b> contact.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 5A</figref>, the tongue limiter member <b>28</b> of limiter structure <b>26</b> is formed from a flat, etched flexure blank <b>54</b> by bending the flexure free end <b>22</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> to be already etched to define the limiter structure <b>26</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> the limiter structure <b>26</b> is shown bent upward from the general plane of the tongue P-P to an angle of from about 45 to about 80 or 90 degrees. This bend <b>29</b> is the only bend in the tongue limiter member <b>28</b> so that the member continues straight out from the bend. Others have put multiple bends in their limiters but this entails increased manufacturing expense that is unnecessary when security of engagement can be obtained by the present two proximal members arrangement.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Flexure <b>14</b> is shown as a separate element from the beam portion <b>12</b>, but could be integrated therewith and both made from a single piece of metal foil.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Returning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref>, the tongue limiter member cross piece <b>36</b> is located above the tongue portion free end <b>22</b> and suitably opposite the slider <b>24</b>. Slider <b>24</b> is shown to have in one embodiment of the invention a first portion <b>24</b><i>a </i>that is covered by the tongue free end <b>22</b>, and a second portion <b>24</b><i>b </i>that is not covered by the free end, but which is exposed to the cross piece <b>36</b>. In this manner, the limiter structure <b>26</b> is far closer to the dimple contact locus <b>52</b> than previously known limiters extending from a flexure. A typical suspension according to the invention will have a slider (containing the read/write heads) that is 0.049 inch long and 0.039 inch wide. The limiter structure <b>26</b> in a thusly dimensioned slider application can be located as close as 0.012 inch from the dimple, less than one-half the previously closest limiter of which the applicant is aware. Other proximity measures are provided below.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In certain other limiters (not shown) the free end of the flexure defines at its outermost part a limiter that interengages with the load beam or the flexure but which transmits the force along the length of the tongue, from the dimple, for example, to the free end outermost part and lacks the direct force transmission provided by this invention.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Tongue limiter member <b>28</b> engages suspension-defined cooperating part beam portion limiter member <b>56</b>. Thus, the tongue limiter member cross piece <b>36</b>, spaced above the slider <b>24</b>—exposed second portion <b>24</b><i>b</i>, has a relatively thin cross-section dimension, low height, and is sized to interengage with the flat, proximally cantilevered member <b>56</b>. In one embodiment, see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, beam portion limiter member cooperating part <b>56</b> is defined by the beam portion <b>12</b> by forming an area <b>58</b> of the beam portion into a proximally extended and cantilevered shape that will receive and retain the tongue limiter member <b>28</b>, as shown, with the tendency of the tongue limiter member to move farther down the beam portion limiter member as the tongue portion <b>18</b> moves away from the beam portion <b>12</b>, for lessened chance of dislodgement as the extent of the tongue portion excursion increases. Typically the gap <b>62</b> between the cross piece <b>36</b> and the beam portion member <b>56</b> is about 0.004 inch but it can be more or less in particular applications, as the desired permissible travel and other factors require.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In a further embodiment, and with reference particularly to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 2</figref>, suspension <b>10</b> comprises beam portion <b>12</b> and a separate flexure <b>14</b> carried by the beam portion. Flexure <b>14</b> comprises the open frame <b>16</b> having a given longitudinal extent F and a tongue portion <b>18</b> cantilevered within the frame extent under dimple <b>48</b> load from the beam portion <b>12</b>. Slider <b>24</b> has first and second contiguous areas <b>24</b><i>a</i>, <b>24</b><i>b</i>. Slider <b>24</b> also has a given longitudinal extent S. First area <b>24</b><i>a </i>has a longitudinal extent A less than the slider longitudinal extent S and defines the locus <b>46</b> of slider attachment. Second area <b>24</b><i>b </i>has a longitudinal extent B less than one-half the slider given longitudinal extent S. Limiter structure <b>26</b> is defined opposite the second area <b>24</b><i>b </i>to limit the tongue portion <b>18</b> from undue travel, the limiter structure extending out of the plane P-P of the tongue free end <b>22</b>. Beam portion <b>12</b> defines the beam portion member <b>56</b> as in the previous embodiment to engage the limiter structure against undue travel of the tongue portion <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In general, the dimple <b>48</b> extends in a cylindrical plane C-C that has the diameter D of the dimple. Limiter structure <b>26</b> is preferably substantially entirely within four cylindrical plane diameters (4×D) of the dimple perimeter <b>48</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In general, slider <b>24</b> has a given footprint FP defined by its longitudinal and transverse sides, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The interiorly open tongue limiter member <b>28</b> has first interengaging part, cross piece <b>36</b>, centered on the slider <b>24</b> longitudinal axis SLA and defined by the locally apertured free end <b>22</b>, the end being deflected upward to be above the general plane of the tongue portion <b>18</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>. In this embodiment, the limiter structure <b>26</b> further includes cooperating beam portion limiter member <b>56</b>. The interengaging parts <b>28</b>, <b>56</b> are opposed vertically above the slider footprint FP against undue travel of the tongue portion <b>18</b> and its slider <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In the invention method, undue relative movement is limited between beam portion <b>12</b> and flexure tongue portion <b>18</b> of disk drive suspension <b>10</b> where the flexure tongue has a cantilevered proximate end by cantilevering a beam portion limiter member <b>56</b> proximally, and cantilevering a tongue limiter member <b>28</b> proximally and vertically in beam portion member intersecting relation such that tongue portion travel away from the beam portion increasingly secures engagement of the limiter members. The method further includes defining the beam portion limiter member <b>56</b> as a flat extent coplanar with the beam portion <b>12</b>, angling the tongue limiter member at about 45 to about 80 degrees to the beam portion limiter member, bracketing the beam portion limiter member with the tongue limiter member, supporting a slider <b>24</b> on the tongue portion, and maintaining the tongue limiter free of bends along its longitudinal axis other than bend <b>29</b> at said tongue.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The invention thus provides an improved disk drive suspension having an improved limiter structure against undue travel of the suspension tongue and slider under shock and under load-unload conditions through the provision of a limiter structure that includes a member vertically spaced from the slider and formed from the free proximate end of the cantilevered flexure tongue and a limiter structure cooperating part on the suspension beam portion cantilevered proximally like the tongue limiter member to interengage vertically with the tongue free end defined limiter structure to limit tongue free end travel.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The foregoing objects are thus met.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion and in a second plane generally parallel to said first plane a flexure, said flexure having a proximally cantilevered tongue being adapted to carry a slider and having a proximate end, a limiter structure limiting travel of said tongue away from said beam portion, said limiter structure comprising intersected first and second proximally cantilevered members defined by said beam portion and said tongue proximate end respectively and arranged for engagement response to undue tongue travel, said tongue having a given lateral extent, and said tongue member having a lesser lateral extent.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, in which said beam portion member has a flat extent within said first plane, said tongue member engaging said beam portion member flat extent.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, in which said beam portion comprises a wall extending opposite said tongue proximate end, said wall being configured to define said beam portion member in tongue member engaging relation, said beam portion being otherwise free of tongue travel limiting members.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, including also a slider having a leading edge end at said tongue proximate end, and wherein said limiter structure is adjacent said slider leading edge end.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, in which said tongue member comprises left and right legs closely bracketing said beam portion member, and a cross-piece overlying said beam portion member, said cross piece having less vertical height from said tongue than said beam portion member has lateral width.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion and in a second plane generally parallel to said first plane a flexure, said flexure having a proximally cantilevered tongue being adapted to carry a slider and having a proximate end, a limiter structure limiting travel of said tongue away from said beam portion, said limiter structure comprising intersected first and second proximally cantilevered members defined by said beam portion and said tongue approximate end respectively and arranged for engagement response to undue tongue travel, wherein said tongue member extends from said second plane at an angle of about 45 to about 80 degrees, said beam portion member extending at an angle of about 0 degrees to said beam portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion and in a second plane generally parallel to said first plane a flexure, said flexure having a proximally cantilevered tongue being adapted to carry a slider and having a proximate end, a limiter structure limiting travel of said tongue away from said beam portion, said limiter structure comprising intersected first and second proximally cantilevered members defined by said beam portion and said tongue proximate end respectively and arranged for engagement response to undue tongue travel, wherein said tongue member is U-shaped and free of bends along its longitudinal axis other than at said tongue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion and in a second plane generally parallel to said first plane a flexure, said flexure having a proximally cantilevered tongue being adapted to carry a slider and having a proximate end, a limiter structure limiting travel of said tongue away from said beam portion, said limiter structure comprising intersected first and second proximally cantilevered members defined by said beam portion and said tongue proximate end respectively and arranged for engagement response to undue tongue travel, wherein said tongue member has a cross piece and left and right legs bracketing said beam portion member, said legs being free of bends other than at said tongue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion adapted to be supported by a spring portion and a base portion, said beam portion having a proximally cantilevered limiter member, a flexure carried by said beam portion, said flexure comprising a frame and a tongue portion generally in a second plane and having a tongue proximate end cantilevered from said frame for supporting a slider, and a limiter structure limiting said tongue from undue travel, said limiter structure comprising a tongue limiter member extending from said tongue proximate end into said first plane and arranged to bracket said beam portion limiter member, said tongue member shifting distally on said beam portion member responsive to increased tongue travel against tongue limiter member dislodgement from said beam portion limiter member in tongue undue travel limiting relation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, in which said beam portion limiter member is flat for engagement with said tongue limiter member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, in which said beam portion comprises a wall extending opposite said tongue proximate end, said wall being configured to define said beam portion limiter member in tongue limiter member engaging relation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, in which tongue limiter member extends at an angle to said beam portion limiter member of about 45 to about 80 degrees.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, in which said tongue limiter member is straight beyond said tongue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, in which said tongue has a given lateral extent, said tongue limiter member having a lesser lateral extent.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, including also a slider having a leading edge end at said tongue proximate end, whereby said limiter structure is adjacent said slider leading edge end.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, in which said tongue limiter member comprises left and right legs bracketing said beam portion limiter member, and a cross-piece overlying said beam portion limiter member, said cross piece having less vertical height than said beam portion limiter member has lateral width.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method of limiting undue relative movement between a beam portion and flexure tongue in a disk drive suspension, said flexure tongue having a cantilevered proximate end, including cantilevering a beam portion limiter member proximally, an cantilevering a tongue limiter member proximally and vertically in beam portion member intersecting relation, and angling said tongue limiter member at about 45 to about 80 degrees to said beam portion limiter member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, including also defining said beam portion limiter member as a flat extent coplanar with said beam portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, including also bracketing said beam portion limiter member with said tongue limiter member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, including also supporting a slider on said tongue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, including also maintaining said tongue limiter free of bends other than at said tongue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A disk drive suspension comprising generally in a first plane a beam portion and in a second plane generally parallel to said first plane a flexure, said flexure having a proximally cantilevered tongue being adapted to carry a slider, a limiter structure limiting travel of said tongue away from said beam portion, said limiter structure comprising a beam portion member engaging a tongue member in response to undue tongue travel, said tongue member being U-shaped and otherwise free of bends along its longitudinal axis other than at said tongue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The disk drive suspension of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein said tongue member is disposed at a proximate end of said tongue, and said beam portion member engages said tongue member such that tongue travel away from said beam portion increasingly secures the engagement of said members.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein said tongue member extends from said second plane at an angle of about 45 to about 90 degrees, said beam portion member extending at an angle of about 0 degrees to said beam portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, in which said tongue has a given lateral extent, and said tongue member has a lesser lateral extent.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, in which said slider has a leading edge end at said tongue proximate end and a trailing edge end, said limiter structure being more closely adjacent said slider leading edge end.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, in which said tongue member comprises left and right legs bracketing said beam portion member, and a cross-piece overlying said beam portion member, said cross piece having less vertical height from said tongue than said beam portion member has lateral width.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. The disk drive suspension according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref>, wherein said tongue member has legs and a crosspiece that bracket said beam portion member, said legs being free of bends other than at said tongue.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
