<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296471-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296471</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11227202</doc-number>
<date>20050916</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-364927</doc-number>
<date>20041216</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>P</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7351436</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Acceleration sensor</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5081867</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yamada</name>
<date>19920100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7351433</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5239870</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kaneko</name>
<date>19930800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7351433</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5520051</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fujii et al.</name>
<date>19960500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 7351436</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>03-202778</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>19910900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>4-81630</doc-number>
<date>19920300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>06-242139</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19940900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>08-105913</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19960400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>08105913</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19960400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-51967</doc-number>
<date>19990200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-304762</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20001100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-242191</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20010900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001242191</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20010900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003215154</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-184081</doc-number>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-233072</doc-number>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>1020040047684</doc-number>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 7351436</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>21</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060130584</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060622</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ono, legal representative</last-name>
<first-name>Nobuko</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ishikawa</last-name>
<first-name>Hiroshi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kawasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tanaka</last-name>
<first-name>Hiroshi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yamada</last-name>
<first-name>Sumio</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<inventors>
<deceased-inventor sequence="001">
<last-name>Ono, deceased</last-name>
<first-name>Masaaki</first-name>
</deceased-inventor>
</inventors>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Arent Fox LLP.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<us-deceased-inventor sequence="001">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ono, deceased</last-name>
<first-name>Masaaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</us-deceased-inventor>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fujitsu Media Devices Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fujitsu Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kawasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Williams</last-name>
<first-name>Hezron</first-name>
<department>2856</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Shah</last-name>
<first-name>Samir M.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A structure with superior shock resistance is proposed for a parasol-type acceleration sensor. The acceleration sensor comprises a support portion the lower end of which is fixed to a substrate; a beam portion on which a detection element for applying changes to an output signal in correspondence with strain caused by acceleration acting on the detection element is formed, one end of the beam portion being connected to the top part of the support portion; a suspended weight connected to the other end of the beam portion; and a stopper substrate with a window portion through which, in order to guide an output signal of the detection element via a pad that is formed on the upper end face of the support portion, a conductor lead that is connected to the pad passes. Overswing of the weight is limited by means of the stopper substrate.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="80.86mm" wi="136.82mm" file="US07296471-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="205.74mm" wi="106.17mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296471-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="260.69mm" wi="176.36mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296471-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="208.87mm" wi="165.69mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296471-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="226.74mm" wi="173.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296471-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="223.18mm" wi="175.85mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296471-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="150.71mm" wi="121.50mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296471-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="123.61mm" wi="164.85mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296471-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is based upon and claims the benefit of priority from the prior Japanese Patent Application No. 2004-364927, filed on Dec. 16, 2004, the entire contents of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to an acceleration sensor and, more particularly, to a semiconductor acceleration sensor with improved shock resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In order to implement various types of control in moving bodies such as automobiles and ships and in robots, mechanical fabrication devices, or mobile devices that are grasped and used by a user, such as notebook PCs, portable telephones, PDA (Personal Digital Assistant), DVC (Digital Video Camera), DSC (Digital Still Camera), for example, it is essential to detect the stress acting on all or part of the target body in correspondence with the objective of the control. By sensing the stress on the basis of the acceleration acting on all or part of the target, it is possible to sense the acceleration.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A variety of devices for detecting this stress or acceleration have been conventionally developed, of which one device is known in which a gauge resistor is formed on the semiconductor substrate as a detection element and which converts the mechanical strain produced on the basis of a force acting on the that is supplied from outside into an electrical signal as a result of the piezoresistive effect (“Development of three-weight sensor” ‘Invention’ Journal pages 52 to 63, published by the Invention Society on September 2003).</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In addition, the fact that it is also possible to use a change in the electrostatic capacity corresponding with strain instead of using the piezoresistive effect of the gauge resistor is explained in “Development of three-weight sensor” ‘Invention’ Journal pages 52 to 63, published by the Invention Society on September 2003.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In particular, the characteristic of the invention that is described in “Development of three-weight sensor” ‘Invention’ Journal pages 52 to 63, published by the Invention Society on September 2003 is the fact that it is possible, by means of force sensors for a plurality of axial directions formed on a semiconductor substrate, to constitute sensors of a plurality of types, that is, sensors of four types, namely, a three-axis force sensor, a three-axis acceleration sensor, a three-axis angular speed sensor, and a six-axis motion sensor by means of one device.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Proposals have been made for each of a variety of problems relating to a semiconductor acceleration sensor that employs the principles mentioned in “Development of three-weight sensor” ‘Invention’ Journal pages 52 to 63, published by the Invention Society on September 2003. One of these various problems is that a large unforeseen shock can sometimes be applied as a result of the environment in which the acceleration sensor is applied (depending on what kind of device the acceleration sensor is used in). In such a case, there is a risk that the weight will be displaced greatly and the gauge resistor will be accordingly damaged.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In order to eliminate this inconvenience, a constitution in which a stopper that limits the displacement of the weight is provided has been proposed (Japanese Patent Application Laid Open No. 2000-304762).</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Here, as indicated in “Development of three-weight sensor” ‘Invention’ Journal pages 52 to 63, published by the Invention Society on September 2003 and in Japanese Patent publication H8-7228, an acceleration sensor with a structure in which the relationship between the weight and support portion is reversed, that is, in which the support portion is placed in the center of the acceleration sensor and the weight is suspended by means of a beam portion at the periphery of the support portion, is known. In the following description, an acceleration sensor with this structure is expediently referred to as a parasol-type acceleration sensor.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An acceleration sensor with a parasol-type acceleration sensor structure in which this support portion is placed in the center is illustrated in “Development of three-weight sensor” ‘Invention’ Journal pages 52 to 63, published by the Invention Society on September 2003, Japanese Patent Application Laid Open No. 2000-304762, and Japanese Patent publication H8-7228. However, the application of a structure that limits shocks of the acceleration sensor shown in Japanese Patent Application Laid Open No. 2000-304762 to a parasol-type acceleration sensor is not suggested.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Therefore, an object of the present invention is to propose a structure with superior shock resistance for an acceleration sensor having a structure in which the support portion is placed in the center, that is, a parasol-type acceleration sensor, such that there is no damage to the acceleration sensor even when the product on which the acceleration sensor is mounted is dropped or a strong shock is applied.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The first aspect of the acceleration sensor according to the object of the present invention comprises a support portion the lower end of which is fixed to a substrate; a beam portion on which a detection element for applying changes to an output signal in correspondence with strain caused by acceleration acting on the detection element is formed, one end of the beam portion being connected to the top part of the support portion; a suspended weight connected to the other end of the beam portion; and a stopper substrate with a window portion through which, in order to guide an output signal of the detection element via a pad that is formed on the upper end face of the support portion, a conductor lead that is connected to the pad passes, wherein the stopper substrate is fixed by means of adhesive to a region surrounding the pad of the upper end face of the support portion and upward overswing of the weight is limited by means of the stopper substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The second aspect of the acceleration sensor according to the object of the present invention comprises a support portion the lower end of which is fixed to a substrate and the upper end face of which comprises a pad; four beam portions the respective one end of which is connected to the upper end portion of the support portion in an orthogonal direction with the support portion at the center and on which a detection element that applies changes to the output signal in correspondence with strain caused by acceleration acting on the detection element is formed; a suspended weight connected to the other end of the four beam portions; a support-portion extension part disposed between two adjacent beam portions of the four beam portions; and a stopper substrate with a window portion through which, in order to guide an output signal of the detection element via a pad that is formed on the upper end face of the support portion, a conductor lead that is connected to the pad passes, wherein the stopper substrate is fixed by means of adhesive to the extension of the support portion and limits upward overswing of the weight.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The third aspect of the acceleration sensor according to the object of the present invention comprises a support portion the lower end of which is fixed to a substrate and the upper end face of which comprises a pad; four beam portions the respective one end of which is connected to the upper end portion of the support portion in an orthogonal direction with the support portion at the center and on which a detection element that applies changes to the output signal in correspondence with strain caused by acceleration acting on the detection element is formed; a suspended weight connected to the other end of the four beam portions; a support-portion extension that is disposed between two adjacent beam portions of the four beam portions; and a stopper substrate with a window portion through which, in order to guide an output signal of the detection element via a pad that is formed on the extension of the support portion, a conductor lead that is connected to the pad passes, wherein the stopper substrate is fixed by means of adhesive to the upper end face of the support portion and limits upward overswing of the weight.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The fourth aspect of the acceleration sensor according to the object of the present invention comprises a support portion the lower end of which is fixed to a substrate; a beam portion on which a detection element for applying changes to an output signal in correspondence with strain caused by acceleration acting on the detection element is formed, one end of the beam portion being connected to the top part of the support portion; a suspended weight connected to the other end of the beam portion; a stopper substrate with a window portion through which, in order to guide an output signal of the detection element via a pad that is formed on the upper end face of the support portion, a conductor lead that is connected to the pad passes; and a frame portion that surrounds the weight, wherein the stopper substrate is fixed by means of adhesive to the upper end face of the frame portion and limits upward overswing of the weight.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The fifth aspect of the acceleration sensor according to the object of the present invention is an acceleration sensor according to any of the first to third aspects, wherein the support portion, beam portion and weight are integrally formed by means of a semiconductor substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The sixth aspect of the acceleration sensor according to the object of the present invention is an acceleration sensor according to the fourth aspect, wherein the support portion, beam portion, weight and frame portion are integrally formed by means of a semiconductor substrate and the weight and frame portion are connected by means of a join portion and the frame portion is separated from the weight by cutting the join portion after mounting in the package.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The seventh aspect of the acceleration sensor according to the object of the present invention is an acceleration sensor according to the second aspect, further comprising a groove between the extension of the support portion and the pad formed on the upper end face of the support portion.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The eighth aspect of the acceleration sensor according to the object of the present invention is an acceleration sensor according to the first to seventh aspects, wherein the interval between the weight and the stopper substrate is 2 to 12 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The characteristics of the present invention will become clearer from the embodiments of the invention that are described hereinbelow with reference to the drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">According to the characteristics of the present invention, it is possible to provide an acceleration sensor in which the shock resistance is improved at low cost and which exhibits high connection reliability.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a parasol-type acceleration sensor chip;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a first embodiment structure of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a second embodiment structure of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a third embodiment structure of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a fourth embodiment structure of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates the constitution of the fabrication process for an acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> and a frame <b>19</b> of the embodiment in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a modified example of the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a gap G between an weight <b>11</b> and upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> of an acceleration sensor common to each embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Embodiments of the present invention will be described hereinbelow with reference to the drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a parasol-type acceleration sensor chip.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a cross-sectional view and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> is an upper view. Further, the cross-sectional view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a cross-sectional view along the line A-B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the acceleration sensor chip comprises a support portion <b>10</b> that is fixed to the center of a substrate <b>16</b>, and a weight <b>11</b> that is disposed at the periphery of the support portion <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The weight <b>11</b> is suspended linked to the other end of a beam portion (detection beam) <b>12</b> one end of which is connected to the top part of the support portion <b>10</b>. The beam portion <b>12</b> is flexible so that when the stress or acceleration is applied, the beam portion <b>12</b> may strain. The support portion <b>10</b>, weight <b>11</b>, and beam portion <b>12</b> are integrally formed by means of a semiconductor substrate by means of micromachine technology.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">A detection element <b>13</b> that applies changes to the output signal in correspondence with the strain caused by the acceleration acting on the weight <b>11</b> is formed on the top part of the beam portion <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Here, the substrate <b>16</b> fulfills the role of a stopper for the downward movement of the weight <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A plurality of bonding pads <b>14</b> are provided on the upper end face of the support portion <b>10</b> in the upper view shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>. The bonding pads <b>14</b> are electrically connected by means of leads (not shown) to the detection element <b>13</b>. The bonding pads <b>14</b> are connected by means of a metal wire <b>5</b> or similar to an external lead-out terminal that is formed on the side of the package (not illustrated).</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In the case of the acceleration sensor chip shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the downward movement of the weight <b>11</b> is limited by means of the substrate <b>16</b> but the upward movement of the weight <b>11</b> is unrestricted. Therefore, when a large shock is applied to the acceleration sensor, there is the risk of damage to the beam portion <b>12</b> as described earlier.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Therefore, the present invention proposes a structure to resolve this problem.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the first embodiment structure of the acceleration sensor of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the first embodiment; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is an upper view in which the acceleration sensor chip (the part circled by a broken line part <b>2</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>) housed within the package is observed with the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>) removed; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref> is an upper view of a state where the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is covered. Further, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a cross-sectional view along the broken line A-B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, the package is formed in multiple layers (three layers in this embodiment) by means of ceramic material.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> is housed in a package and the acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> comprises a support portion <b>10</b> that is centrally fixed to the substrate <b>16</b>, and a weight <b>11</b> that is disposed at the periphery of the support portion <b>10</b>. The weight <b>11</b> is suspended linked to the other end of the beam portion (detection beam) <b>12</b> one end of which is connected to the top part of the support portion <b>10</b>. The support portion <b>10</b>, weight <b>11</b> and beam portion <b>12</b> are integrally formed by means of a semiconductor substrate by means of micromachine technology.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">A detection element <b>13</b> that applies changes to the output signal in correspondence with the strain caused by the acceleration acting on the weight <b>11</b> is formed on the top part of the beam portion <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Here, the substrate <b>16</b> fulfills the role of a stopper for the downward movement of the weight <b>11</b>. The substrate <b>16</b> is also fixed to the inside bottom face of the package by means of adhesive <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">A plurality of bonding pads <b>14</b> are provided on the upper end face of the support portion <b>10</b> in the upper view shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>. The bonding pads <b>14</b> are electrically connected by means of leads (not shown) to the detection element <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In addition, the bonding pads <b>14</b> are connected by means of a metal wire <b>5</b> or similar to the external lead-out terminal <b>4</b> that is formed on the side of the package (not illustrated).</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The external lead-out terminal <b>4</b> is also connected to an electrode terminal <b>18</b> that is formed on the package bottom face by means of an electrically conductive film that is formed along the package wall. The electrode terminal <b>18</b> is soldered to the required circuit parts of the substrate when the acceleration sensor is mounted on the circuit substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Here, the present invention is characterized by further comprising the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> that fulfils the role of a stopper for the upward movement of the weight <b>11</b>. The upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is bonded by means of adhesive <b>15</b><i>b </i>formed to surround the plurality of bonding pads <b>14</b> to the upper end face of the support portion <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> is a planar view of the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> that fulfils the role of a stopper to limit the overswing of the upward movement of the weight <b>11</b>. The upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> comprises a window portion <b>15</b><i>a </i>at the center thereof. Therefore, the connecting wires <b>5</b> are able to connect the bonding pads <b>14</b> and external lead-out terminals <b>4</b> via the window portion <b>15</b><i>a </i>of the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the second embodiment structure of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the second embodiment; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is an upper view in which the acceleration sensor chip (part circled by the broken line portion <b>2</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>) housed in the package is observed with the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref>) removed; and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3D</figref> is an upper view of a state where the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is covered. Further, the cross-sectional view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a view along the broken line A-B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, the package is formed in three layers by means of ceramic material similarly to the example in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> is housed in a package and the acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> comprises a support portion <b>10</b> that is centrally fixed to the substrate <b>16</b>, and an weight <b>11</b> that is disposed at the periphery of the support portion <b>10</b>. The weight <b>11</b> is suspended linked to the other end of the beam portion (detection beam) <b>12</b> one end of which is connected to the top part of the support portion <b>10</b>. The support portion <b>10</b>, weight <b>11</b> and beam portion <b>12</b> are integrally formed by means of a semiconductor substrate by means of micromachine technology.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">A detection element <b>13</b> that applies changes to the output signal in correspondence with the strain caused by the acceleration acting on the weight <b>11</b> is formed on the top part of the beam portion <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The substrate <b>16</b> fulfils the role of a stopper for the downward movement of the weight <b>11</b>. The substrate <b>16</b> is also fixed to the inside bottom face of the package by means of adhesive <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">A plurality of bonding pads <b>14</b> are provided on the upper end face of the support portion <b>10</b> in the upper view shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>. The bonding pads <b>14</b> are electrically connected by means of leads (not shown) to the detection element <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The bonding pads <b>14</b> are also connected by means of a metal wire <b>5</b> or similar to an external lead-out terminal that is formed on the side of the package.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The external lead-out terminal <b>4</b> is connected to an electrode terminal <b>18</b> that is formed on the package bottom face by means of an electrically conductive film that is formed along the package wall. The electrode terminal <b>18</b> is soldered to the required circuit parts of the substrate when the acceleration sensor is mounted on the circuit substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Here, so too with the third embodiment, the present invention is characterized by further comprising the stopper substrate <b>15</b> that fulfils the role of a stopper for the upward movement of the weight <b>11</b>. In the second embodiment, the weight <b>11</b> forms a substantially square frame shape with four sides, the center of each of the four sides being connected to the other end of the beam portion (detection beam) <b>12</b> and linked to the middle support portion <b>10</b>. In addition, in comparison with the first embodiment in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, in the case of the third embodiment, the middle support portion <b>10</b> comprises extension parts <b>11</b><i>a </i>to <b>11</b><i>d </i>of the support portion that extend in an oblique direction at an angle to the beam portion (detection beam) <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Furthermore, a characteristic of this embodiment is that the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is bonded by means of adhesive <b>15</b><i>b </i>to extension parts <b>10</b><i>a </i>to <b>10</b><i>d </i>of the support portion <b>10</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref> is a planar view of the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> that fulfils the role of a stopper to limit the overswing of the upward movement of the weight <b>11</b>. Similarly to the first embodiment, the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> comprises a window portion <b>15</b><i>a </i>at the center thereof. Therefore, the connecting wires <b>5</b> are able to connect the bonding pads <b>14</b> and external lead-out terminals <b>4</b> via the window portion <b>15</b><i>a </i>of the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">In comparison with the first embodiment, the second embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a constitution in which the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is bonded at four points spaced apart from the plurality of bonding pads <b>14</b>, whereby the bonding strength can be increased and the flow of adhesive <b>15</b><i>b </i>to the bonding pads <b>14</b> can be prevented. Deterioration of the electrical connection can therefore be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the third embodiment structure of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the third embodiment; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> is an upper view in which the acceleration sensor chip (part circled by the broken line portion <b>2</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>) housed in the package is observed with the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>) removed; and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4D</figref> is an upper view of a state where the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is covered. Further, the cross-sectional view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> is a view along the broken line A-B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>, the package is formed in three layers by means of ceramic material similarly to the earlier embodiments in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">The acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> is housed in a package and the acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> comprises a support portion <b>10</b> that is centrally fixed to the substrate <b>16</b>, and an weight <b>11</b> that is disposed at the periphery of the support portion <b>10</b>. The weight <b>11</b> is suspended linked to the other end of the beam portion (detection beam) <b>12</b> one end of which is connected to the top part of the support portion <b>10</b>. The support portion <b>10</b>, weight <b>11</b> and beam portion <b>12</b> are integrally formed by means of a semiconductor substrate by means of micromachine technology.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">A detection element <b>13</b> that applies changes to the output signal in correspondence with the strain caused by the acceleration acting on the weight <b>11</b> is formed on the top part of the beam portion <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The substrate <b>16</b> fulfils the role of a stopper for overswing of the downward movement of the weight <b>11</b>. The substrate <b>16</b> is also fixed to the inside bottom face of the package by means of adhesive <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Here, so too with the fourth embodiment, similarly to the earlier embodiments, the present invention is characterized by comprising the stopper substrate <b>15</b> that fulfils the role of a stopper for the upward movement of the weight <b>11</b>. Similarly to the second embodiment in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the weight <b>11</b> forms a substantially square frame shape with four sides, the center of each of the four sides being connected to the other end of the beam portion (detection beam) <b>12</b> and linked to the middle support portion <b>10</b>. In addition, the middle support portion <b>10</b> comprises extension parts <b>11</b><i>a </i>to <b>11</b><i>d </i>of the support portion that extend in an oblique direction at an angle to the beam portion (detection beam) <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">The difference of the fourth embodiment from the second embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is the position of the plurality of bonding pads <b>14</b>. That is, in the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the plurality of bonding pads <b>14</b> are arranged on four extension parts <b>11</b><i>a </i>to <b>11</b><i>d </i>of the extended support portion. Therefore, the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> comprises four window portions <b>15</b><i>a </i>for connecting a lead-out wire such as the metal wire <b>5</b> to the bonding pads <b>14</b> in correspondence with the four extension parts <b>11</b><i>a </i>to <b>11</b><i>d </i>respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Furthermore, the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is connected to the support portion <b>10</b> by means of adhesive <b>15</b><i>b </i>that is formed on the upper end of the support portion <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">In the fourth embodiment, the bonding pads <b>14</b> are in positions spaced apart from the center and, therefore, the length of lead-out wires such as the metal wire <b>5</b> for a connection with the external lead-out terminal <b>4</b> may be made shorter than in the case of the first and second embodiments, whereby reliability can be increased.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> also illustrates the fourth embodiment of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the fourth embodiment; <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is an upper view in which the acceleration sensor chip (part circled by the broken line portion <b>2</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>) housed in the package is observed with the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>) removed; and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5D</figref> is an upper view of a state where the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is covered. Further, the cross-sectional view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a view along the broken line A-B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">This embodiment is a constitution in which a frame <b>19</b> for holding the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> is provided independently of the acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>, the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> comprises a window portion <b>15</b><i>a </i>through which lead-out wire such as the metal wire <b>5</b> for connecting the bonding pads <b>14</b> and external lead-out terminals <b>4</b> is passed as per the other embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">The window portion <b>15</b><i>a </i>forms a square in this embodiment but may also form another shape such as a circle, for example. In addition, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the plurality of bonding pads <b>14</b> is formed on the end face of the support portion <b>10</b> similarly to the second and third embodiments. However, the bonding pads <b>14</b> may also be formed on each of the four extension parts <b>11</b><i>a </i>to <b>11</b><i>d </i>as per the fourth embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> illustrates the constitution of the fabrication process for the acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> and frame <b>19</b> of the embodiment in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b> and frame <b>19</b> can be fabricated by cutting same from a semiconductor substrate by means of micromachine technology. Thus, machining is performed by leaving parts <b>20</b><i>a </i>to <b>20</b><i>d </i>that link the parts of the frame <b>19</b> and acceleration sensor chip <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">Thereafter, the frame <b>19</b> is afforded a structure that is produced by fixing the frame <b>19</b> to the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> or substrate <b>16</b> through bonding and then cutting the frame <b>19</b> from the body of the acceleration sensor chip by means of a laser. As a result, collective die-bonding of the external lead-out terminals <b>4</b> of package <b>1</b> and bonding pads <b>14</b> of the sensor chip is possible and an easily-fabricated sensor with superior shock resistance that can be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a modified example of the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. This modified example is characterized in that grooves <b>21</b> are formed between the adhesive <b>15</b><i>b </i>for fixing the upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> formed on the four extension parts <b>11</b><i>a </i>to <b>11</b><i>d </i>and the bonding pads <b>14</b>. As a result of forming these grooves <b>21</b>, the risk of adhesive <b>15</b><i>b </i>flowing to the part of the bonding pads <b>14</b> can be avoided. Accordingly, an acceleration sensor with superior shock resistance with which electrical connection reliability is high can be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates a gap G between the weight <b>11</b> and upper stopper substrate <b>15</b> of an acceleration sensor common to each embodiment. It is possible to limit the upward movement of the weight <b>11</b> by making the gap G approximately 2 to 12 μm by means of the adhesive <b>15</b><i>b </i>or by inserting a spacer. As a result, the reliability of the shock resistance can be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The present invention makes it possible to provide an acceleration sensor with superior shock resistance by means of a simple constitution. It is thus possible to provide highly reliable electronic devices by installing the acceleration sensor according to the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An acceleration sensor, comprising:
<claim-text>a support portion a lower end of which is fixed to a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a beam portion on which a detection element for applying changes to an output signal in correspondence with strain caused by acceleration acting on the detection element is formed, one end of the beam portion being connected to an upper end of the support portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a suspended weight connected to another end of the beam portion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a stopper substrate with a window portion through which, in order to guide an output signal of the detection element via a pad that is formed on the upper end face of the support portion, a conductor lead that connects the pad connects to a terminal outside the stopper substrate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the stopper substrate is fixed by means of adhesive to a region on the upper end face of the support portion, surrounding the pad formed on the upper end face of the support portion and upward overswing of the weight is limited by means of the stopper substrate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The acceleration sensor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the support portion, beam portion and weight are integrally formed by means of a semiconductor substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The acceleration sensor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the interval between the weight and the stopper substrate is 2 to 12 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
