<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296346-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296346</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11492650</doc-number>
<date>20060725</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<disclaimer>
<text>This patent is subject to a terminal disclaimer.</text>
</disclaimer>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29846</main-classification>
<further-classification> 29825</further-classification>
<further-classification> 29830</further-classification>
<further-classification> 29852</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e51">Plating buss and a method of use thereof</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5132878</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Carey</name>
<date>19920700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5976341</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schumacher et al.</name>
<date>19991100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6040702</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hembree et al.</name>
<date>20000300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6313651</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hembree et al.</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6319418</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Verdeflor et al.</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6348142</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Vivares et al.</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6426290</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Vivares et al.</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6432291</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Vivares et al.</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6479894</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Huang et al.</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6632343</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Farnworth et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6691696</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Akram et al.</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6908784</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Farnworth et al.</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6957963</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Rathburn</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7181837</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Johnson</name>
<date>20070200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 29846</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>1 381 260</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00016">
<othercit>Stacked Orthogonal Serpentine Delay Lines with Vias for Two-dimensional Microchannel Plate Readout, by M. Lampton et al in Rev Scientific Instruments vol. 71, No. 12, Dec. 2000.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29825</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29830</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29846</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29852</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10861847</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040604</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7181837</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11492650</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060254813</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061116</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Johnson</last-name>
<first-name>Mark S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Dinsmore &amp; Shohl LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Micron Technology, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Arbes</last-name>
<first-name>Carl J.</first-name>
<department>3729</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention relates generally to a plating buss design and method for minimizing short circuit problems in PCB panel singulation. More particularly, the invention encompasses a serpentine plating buss which increases the PCB singulation process window thereby minimizing short circuit problems due to indexing errors caused by occasional manufacturing and equipment alignment problems. The serpentine plating buss design therefore increases board yield.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="142.92mm" wi="153.50mm" file="US07296346-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="188.21mm" wi="179.07mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296346-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="187.03mm" wi="173.82mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296346-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="216.66mm" wi="172.89mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296346-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="170.94mm" wi="171.28mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296346-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="174.16mm" wi="170.26mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296346-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="225.47mm" wi="105.07mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296346-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/861,847, filed Jun. 4, 2004 now U.S. Pat. No. 7,181,837.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to the field of printed circuit fabrication, and more particularly to an improved plating buss on a substrate such as for example a printed circuit board (PCB), which addresses manufacturing variations and alignment problems associated with PCB singulation for improved board yield.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Basically, a printed circuit board consists of a sheet of rigid insulating substrate such as phenolic, glass impregnated epoxy or the like, having a pre-defined pattern of thin metallic—usually copper—foil conductive paths (so-called “traces”) appearing on one or both sides of the substrate. These traces collectively define all the electrical interconnections among all the components and are routed between appropriate locations on the board.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Electrolytic plating is one method used to improve electrical conductivity and/or wire bondability in the trace termination areas provided on a multi-layered printed circuit board (PCB). Generally, a panel populated with an array of PCBs is connected to one terminal of either a d.c. or a pulsed plating voltage source and placed in an electrolyte in order to be plated. A metal to be deposited is then connected to the other terminal and similarly immersed in the electrolyte. The transfer of the metal is accomplished via the ions contained in the current flowing between the metal and the panel.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Since electroplating of metals requires that all sites on the panel to be plated must be electrically connected to the plating bath, one prior art method electrically connects the traces to a common straight-line plating buss (also known as a “tie” or “commoning” bar) for convenience. The straight-line plating buss is then used to provide the current during the plating process. However, a plating buss serves no useful function after the electroplating process. Thus, for improved process efficiency, prior art methods have provided the straight-line plating buss centered between adjacent PCBs defined on the panel, such that during a PCB singulation stage, the straight-line plating buss gets cut away.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">PCB singulation is the process of taking a finished panel, and separating or depaneling the plurality of PCBs formed thereon into individual PCBs for a subsequent packaging process. One method of PCB singulation is to use a dicing saw. The panel is mounted on a saw carrier, mechanically, adhesively or otherwise, as known in the art. The saw carrier is then mounted on a stage of the dicing saw. Typically, the PCBs are arranged in rows and columns on the panel with the periphery of each PCB being rectangular. During the dicing process, the panel is sawn or diced with a rotating blade along a street lying between each of the rows and columns thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Once all cuts associated with mutually parallel streets having one orientation are complete, either the blade is rotated 90° relative to the panel or the panel is rotated 90°, and cuts are made through streets in a direction perpendicular to the initial direction of cut. Since each PCB on a conventional panel has the same size and rectangular configuration, each pass of the saw blade is incrementally indexed one unit (a unit being equal to the distance from one street to the next) in a particular orientation of the panel. As such, the saw and the software controlling it are designed to provide uniform and precise indexing in fixed increments across the surface of the panel.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">As mentioned previously above, PCB singulation is also used to remove process remnants, such as straight-line plating busses used in the (post formation) plating process of the PCBs. An illustration of one prior art plating buss is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, wherein a PCB panel <b>100</b> has a plurality of traces <b>102</b> formed thereon by electrodeposition, which are connected by an associated straight-line plating buss <b>104</b>. At the PCB singulation stage, a saw blade dices the panel <b>100</b> along a cut, which removes panel material between parallel lines <b>106</b> and <b>108</b> in order to separate adjacent PCB segments <b>110</b>. If the cut is properly aligned, parallel lines <b>106</b> and <b>108</b> will flank a street <b>112</b> defined between the adjacent PCB segments <b>112</b> in order to also remove the straight-line plating buss <b>104</b> which was formed there along. As can be imaged, dicing the panel along the street <b>112</b> will thereby disconnect the associated traces <b>102</b>. According the width on the straight-line plating buss <b>104</b> can be considered as the “process window” for the PCB singulation stage.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">However, over time, the blade and/or stage of the dicing saw may experience drift due to indexing errors of its drive motor and associated gearing. Additionally, variations in the PCB manufacturing process effecting PCB sizes and street locations, and variations in blade width due to uneven heating and wear can also result in indexing errors. Such indexing errors result potentially in the location of cut, illustrated by parallel lines <b>106</b> and <b>108</b>, moving off the street <b>112</b> and out of the process window. As illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, moving off the street <b>112</b> creates the potential for shorted circuits due to the cut failing to remove the straight-line plating buss <b>104</b> connecting the traces <b>102</b> in one of the adjacent PCB segments <b>110</b>. This circumstance decreasing board yield by rejecting PCBs with shorted traces even though all other features on each PCB may be good.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In view of the foregoing considerations, the present invention is directed to an improved plating buss, wherein the plating buss connecting traces of adjacent printed circuit board (PCB) in a substrate panel are provided in a serpentine design. The serpentine plating buss widens the PCB singulation process window, thereby minimizing short circuit problems often seen in PCB singulation due to indexing errors resulting from occasional manufacturing variations and alignment problems. Accordingly, the serpentine plating buss of the present invention increases board yield. Another benefit of the serpentine plating buss is that the sawn edge of each finished PCB may be improved due to the fact that no longer must PCB singulation be directly on top of the entire plating buss in order to disconnect joined conductive traces.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In one embodiment, a substrate panel containing a plurality of printed circuit boards is disclosed. The substrate panel comprises a plurality of conductive traces provided on the substrate, and a serpentine plating buss interconnecting the plurality of conductive traces and provided between adjacent ones of the plurality of printed circuit boards.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In another embodiment, a method for manufacturing a printed circuit is disclosed. The method comprises providing a substrate panel, providing a plurality of printed circuit boards on the substrate, the printed circuit boards having a plurality of conductive traces provided on the substrate, and interconnecting the plurality of conductive traces with a serpentine plating buss provided on the substrate between adjacent ones of the plurality of printed circuit boards.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In another embodiment, a method for manufacturing a printed circuit is disclosed. The method comprises providing a substrate having at least a pair of adjacent segments, the substrate having a conductive serpentine plating buss interconnecting conductive traces of the pair of adjacent segments, and singulating the substrate, the singulation removing a portion of the serpentine plating buss which disconnects the conductive traces.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In still another embodiment, a method for manufacturing a printed circuit board is disclosed comprising providing an unclad laminated substrate panel used for forming a plurality of printed circuit boards, associating an image of a desired circuitry pattern with the panel, the image comprises various circuitry traces interconnected by a serpentine plate buss, and developing the panel, wherein the desired circuitry pattern is defined on the panel.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">These and other features and objects of the present invention will be apparent in light of the description of the invention embodied herein.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a top elevation of a portion of a substrate panel bearing conductive traces connected by a prior art straight-line plating buss, and illustrating the alignment of a singulation cut having no indexing error which will result in no shorted traces;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top elevation of a portion of a substrate panel bearing conductive traces connected by a prior art straight-line plating buss, and illustrating the alignment of a singulation cut having an indexing error which will result in shorted traces;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a</i>-<b>3</b><i>d </i>are side section views of a substrate panel showing a step-by-step explanation of a printed circuit manufacturing technique used to form the plating buss of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a top elevation of a portion of a substrate panel bearing conductive traces connected by a plating buss according to the present invention, illustrating the alignment of a singulation cut having no indexing error which will result in no shorted traces;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a top elevation of a portion of a substrate panel bearing conductive traces connected by a plating buss according to the present invention, illustrating the alignment of a singulation cut having an indexing error which will result still in no shorted traces;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref><i>a</i>-<b>6</b><i>c </i>are illustrations of various serpentine plating buss embodiments according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In the drawings, dimensions of materials have been modified for clarity of illustration and are not necessarily true to scale.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a</i>-<b>3</b><i>d </i>provides a step-by-step explanation of a printed circuit manufacturing technique used to form a plating buss according to the present invention. In conjunction with this explanation, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> each present a top elevation of a substrate panel having a plurality of adjacent printed circuit boards (PCBs) thereon and bearing conductive traces connected by a plating buss according to the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref><i>a</i>-<b>6</b><i>c </i>are illustrations of various serpentine plating buss embodiments according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>a</i>, manufacturing of a plurality of PCBs <b>10</b> begins similar to most other commonly used additive techniques. Namely, an unclad laminated substrate panel <b>12</b> used for forming the plurality of PCBs <b>10</b> is first provided. The panel <b>12</b> is normally made of a nonconductive material, such as phenolic, glass-impregnated epoxy, polymide, FR4, FR5 or the like. The panel <b>12</b> is then drilled in accordance with a predetermined pattern, such as by a C-N-C drilling machine. In particular, variously sized holes <b>14</b> are imparted through the panel <b>12</b> at a variety of locations, in the exact configuration of a desired hole pattern for each printed circuit. For ease of illustration, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> do not show any of the holes <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The panel <b>12</b> is then coated with an activating layer <b>16</b> which promotes the adhesion of a conductive material, such as copper, to the unclad laminant panel <b>12</b>. Following coating, an outer surface of the activating layer <b>16</b> is coated with a resist material <b>18</b> as illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>b</i>. The resist material <b>18</b> is preferably a photopolymer plating resist solution well-known in the art, and is normally light sensitive.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">A photographic film image or artwork <b>20</b> of a desired circuitry pattern <b>22</b> is then associated with the panel <b>12</b>. In particular, the artwork <b>20</b> provides a picture or image of various circuitry traces and is properly designed to selectively prevent light from passing through portions of the film. For example, with one well-known technique, the circuitry pattern is presented on the film in the form of an emulsion material which prevents the passage of light. The remainder of the film, where no circuitry is desired, is clear. A maskless, fully digital process, such as for example, a Digital Micromirror Device (DMD) or Gradient Light Valve (GLV) imaging system, may also be used to project a negative of the desired circuitry pattern <b>22</b>, onto the panel <b>12</b> as is known in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The desired circuitry pattern <b>22</b> includes a serpentine plating buss design according to the present invention, which connects together a plurality of traces. One embodiment of the serpentine plating buss <b>24</b> is illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, which connects a plurality of traces <b>26</b> in an “accordion” fashion. It is to be appreciated that the plating buss design of the present invention need not be continuous, equally sized, accordion shaped, or rectangular in dimension. For example, as illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref><i>a</i>-<i>c</i>, the serpentine plating buss of the present invention may be a saw toothed pattern <b>40</b>, a triangular pattern <b>42</b>, a curvilinear pattern <b>44</b>, or combinations thereof. A discussion of the advantages of having such a serpentine plating buss according to the present invention is provided in a later section.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Referring back to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>b</i>, with the artwork <b>20</b> in place, the panel <b>12</b> is then “exposed” to ultraviolet light <b>28</b>. As previously described, the artwork <b>20</b> is designed to selectively allow and/or prevent passage of the ultraviolet light <b>28</b> at desired locations. The resist material <b>18</b> is normally configured to “cure,” harden or otherwise react in response to exposure to ultraviolet light such that it is impervious to developer chemistry. At locations on the panel <b>12</b> where ultraviolet light is prevented from reaching the resist material <b>18</b> (i.e., the desired circuitry pattern), the resist material <b>18</b> will not cure, such that it will be attacked by developer chemistry.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The panel <b>12</b> is then “developed”. With this commonly-used technique, any resist material <b>18</b> not cured during exposure is removed from the panel <b>12</b>. As illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>c</i>, only cured portions of the resist material <b>18</b> remain on the panel <b>12</b>. Following developing, the desired circuitry pattern <b>22</b> having the design of the serpentine plating buss <b>24</b> is defined on the panel <b>12</b>. In particular and at this stage, the circuitry pattern <b>22</b> is defined by the activating layer <b>16</b> not otherwise covered by the resist material <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The panel <b>12</b> is then processed through an energized plating bath <b>30</b> to deposit an electrolytic material layer, such as metals or precious metals like copper, silver, gold, platinum, nickel, tin, and the likes, onto the desired circuitry pattern <b>22</b>. During the electroplating process, the resist material <b>18</b> resists or shields the electrolytic material from plating to certain areas of the panel <b>12</b>, wherein the electroplated material is deposited only on exposed portions of the activating layer <b>16</b>. In this manner, only the desired circuitry pattern <b>22</b> receives the electroplated material. The panel <b>12</b> is then passed to additional (post plating buss formation) electroplating processes, wherein the formed plating busses <b>24</b> are then used to make electrical contact for improved electrical conductivity and/or wire bondability in termination (e.g. “trace”) areas of each of the printed circuit board <b>10</b> provided on panel <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">After plating, panel <b>12</b> is then subjected to a “stripping” process. During the stripping process, the resist material <b>18</b> is removed, leaving the plated material layer <b>32</b> and other optional electroplated material layers (not shown) as illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>d</i>. The plated material layer <b>32</b> is provided on the panel <b>12</b> in the desired circuitry pattern <b>22</b> which includes the serpentine plating buss, such as for example, the accordion plating buss <b>24</b> illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, or one of the plating busses illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref><i>a</i>-<b>6</b><i>c</i>. After stripping, the panel <b>12</b> is then singulated into individual PCBs <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">With refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a conventional saw blade is employed at the PCB singulation stage. If there is no indexing errors, the saw blade will remove the material of the panel located between parallel lines <b>34</b> and <b>36</b> as a cut is made along a street <b>38</b>. As can be imaged, making such a cut will separate the adjacent boards <b>10</b> and remove a portion of the serpentine plating buss <b>24</b>, which disconnects the associated traces <b>26</b>. Since the design of the serpentine plating buss <b>24</b> zigzags over the street <b>38</b>, the entire plating buss need not be removed in order to disconnect the traces, unlike the straight-line plating buss shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">It is also to be appreciated that the “process window” defined by the serpentine plating buss <b>24</b> is larger than the prior art straight-line plating buss shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>. In this manner, even if over time, indexing errors result in the cut moving from the center of the street <b>38</b>, the saw blade will still remove a portion of the serpentine plating buss <b>24</b> and disconnect the traces <b>26</b> in both adjacent boards <b>10</b>, such as illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Accordingly, board yield is increased as fewer PCBs are rejected with shorted traces. In one embodiment, a panel <b>12</b> provided with the serpentine plating buss of the present invention enlarges the PCB singulation process window to greater or equal to about ±0.165 mm from centerline of the street, as compared to a prior art process windows of less than or equal to about ±0.085 mm from centerline of the street. It is to be appreciated that the process window of the present invention is solely dependent upon the width of the serpentine pattern, whereas the prior art process window is dependent on saw blade width, buss line width, positional accuracy of the saw blade, and positional accuracy of the buss to the fixing feature.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Although the additive method was described in the formation of the plating buss of the present invention, those skilled in the art recognize that the subtractive method of forming a PCB may also be used. For example, in the subtractive method, a plurality of boards defined by a substrate is provided having at least one surface coated with a conductive material, such as a metal like copper. The circuitry pattern including an embodiment of a plating buss design according to the present invention is then printed onto the conducive material-coated surface of the board by a resist material. The remaining exposed conductive material-coated surface is etched away, and the resist is then removed leaving conductive circuitry having the serpentine plating buss of the present invention interconnecting conductive traces and adjacent PCB segments.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Additionally, although dicing was described as a suitable method for PCB singulation, the plating buss according to the present is also beneficial to panel subjected to other PCB singulation methods, such as for example, punching or stamping.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Thus, while certain representative embodiments and details have been shown for purposes of illustrating the invention, it will be apparent to those skilled in the art that various changes in the invention disclosed herein may be made without departing from the scope of the invention, which is defined in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for manufacturing a printed circuit, the method comprising:
<claim-text>providing a substrate panel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a plurality of printed circuit boards on the substrate, said printed circuit boards having a plurality of conductive traces provided on a planar surface of said substrate panel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a serpentine plating buss on said planar surface between adjacent ones of said plurality of printed circuit boards, said serpentine plating buss interconnecting said plurality of conductive traces.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said substrate panel is non-conductive.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said substrate panel comprises phenolic, glass-impregnated epoxy, polymide, FR4, FR5, and combinations thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said serpentine plating buss is provided along a street defined between said adjacent ones of said plurality of printed circuit boards.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said serpentine plating buss defines an improved process window for PCB singulation which is wider than a process window defined by a straight-line plating buss.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said serpentine plating buss defines a PCB singulation process window greater or equal to about ±0.165 mm from centerline of a street defined between said adjacent ones of said plurality of printed circuit boards.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising providing said serpentine plating buss in a pattern comprising accordion, rectangular, saw toothed, triangular, curvilinear, and combinations thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising removing a portion of said serpentine plating buss to disconnect said plurality of conductive traces.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said plurality of conductive traces and said serpentine plating buss are provided via patterning of said substrate panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising electroplating said substrate panel and using said serpentine plating buss to make electrical contact in termination areas of said plurality of printed circuit boards during electroplating.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>electroplating said substrate panel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>singulating said substrate panel to separate said plurality of printed circuit boards.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>patterning of said substrate to provide said plurality of conductive traces and said serpentine plating buss;</claim-text>
<claim-text>electroplating said substrate panel and using said serpentine plating buss to make electrical contact in termination areas of said plurality of printed circuit boards during electroplating; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>singulating said substrate panel to separate said plurality of printed circuit boards.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
