<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296757-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296757</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11085892</doc-number>
<date>20050322</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>323</us-term-extension>
<disclaimer>
<text>This patent is subject to a terminal disclaimer.</text>
</disclaimer>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>24</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>62</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239 11</main-classification>
<further-classification>239  1</further-classification>
<further-classification>239589</further-classification>
<further-classification>239590</further-classification>
<further-classification>239591</further-classification>
<further-classification>239266</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e55">Method of and apparatus for mounting water cutting nozzles</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7159791</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lambden</name>
<date>20070100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>239  1</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>2</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239 11</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239  1</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239589</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239590</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239591</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239266</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239267</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239268</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239536</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10831842</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040426</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7159791</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11085892</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050252986</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051117</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lambden</last-name>
<first-name>Richard L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Colleyville</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>O'Neil</last-name>
<first-name>Michael A.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Perfect Score Technologies, L.L.C.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Red Oak</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hwu</last-name>
<first-name>Davis</first-name>
<department>3752</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A system for retaining and locating a jewel of the type comprising a nozzle for a water cutting system includes a first support structure component having a water discharge passageway extending therethrough and having an exterior locating surface formed at the water receiving end of the water directing passageway. A second support structure component has a water directing passageway formed therein and has a jewel receiving cavity formed therein at the discharge end of the water receiving passageway. The second support structure component further comprises a chamber for receiving and retaining the first support structure component with the locating surface thereof positioned in engagement with the locating surface of the jewel.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="77.13mm" wi="85.17mm" file="US07296757-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="211.33mm" wi="110.83mm" file="US07296757-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="209.21mm" wi="101.68mm" file="US07296757-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of application Ser. No. 10/831,842 filed Apr. 26, 2004, now U.S. Pat. No. 7,159,791.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates generally to water cutting systems, and more particularly to improvements in the mounting of the jewels which comprise the nozzles of water cutting systems.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND AND SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">As is well known to those skilled in the art, water cutting systems are utilized in a wide variety of industries to effect cutting of metals, plastics, and other materials. In the operation of a water cutting system, water at extremely high pressure, e.g., 50,000 psi, is directed through a nozzle which forms the water into a very small diameter, very high velocity stream. The nozzle typically comprises a jewel selected from the group consisting of diamonds, sapphires, and rubies. The jewel has a very small diameter orifice formed therethrough. For example, the diameter of the orifice formed through the jewel is typically between about 0.0004 inches and about 0.0016 inches.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Heretofore the jewels comprising the nozzles of water cutting systems have been mounted in nozzle support structures formed from stainless steel or other metals that are not subject to deterioration caused by exposure to water. A water discharge passageway extends through the support structure and a jewel receiving cavity is formed at the water receiving end of the water discharge passageway. The jewel comprising the nozzle of the water cutting system is mounted in the jewel receiving cavity and is retained either by a suitable adhesive or by positioning the jewel in a band of soft metal such as brass and then pressing the band of soft metal having the jewel retained therein into the jewel receiving cavity.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The jewel comprising the nozzle of the water cutting system has a locating surface comprising the inner end thereof. The jewel receiving cavity has a locating surface comprising the bottom thereof. Engagement between the locating surface of the jewel and the locating surface of the jewel receiving cavity is necessary to assure proper alignment of the orifice extending through the jewel.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As will be understood, the locating surfaces comprising the interior surface of the jewel and the bottom surface of the jewel receiving cavity must be entirely smooth, flat, and free of any radially extending grooves or ridges. Otherwise the water passing through the water discharge passageway of the support structure will enter the space between the bottom of the jewel receiving cavity and the interior surface of the jewel with the result being degradation of the locating surfaces and misalignment of the jewel within the jewel receiving cavity. However, because the locating surface of the jewel receiving cavity is located at the bottom thereof, consistency in providing the jewel engaging surface with the required surface finish has been difficult to achieve.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The present invention comprises a method of and apparatus for mounting the jewels which comprise the nozzles of water cutting systems which overcome the foregoing and other difficulties which have long since characterized the prior art. In accordance with the broader aspects of the invention a structure for receiving and positioning a jewel comprising the nozzle of a water cutting system includes two components. A first component has a water discharge passageway extending therethrough. The water discharge passageway extends from a jewel engaging exterior locating surface. Because it comprises an exterior surface of the first component, lapping the locating surface to achieve the required surface finish of less than 8 RMS is straightforward. Manufacturing techniques other than lapping which provide the necessary surface finish can also be used in the practice of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The second component of the jewel receiving and positioning structure comprises a chamber which receives the first component therein. The second component has a water directing passageway formed therein which extends to a jewel receiving cavity. A jewel comprising the nozzle of the water cutting system is received in the jewel receiving cavity of the second component with the locating surface thereof mounted in engagement with the exterior locating surface of the first component. Because the jewel is trapped between the first and second components of the support structure, the use of either an adhesive or a metal band to retain the jewel in the jewel receiving cavity is eliminated. Precise machining of the interior surfaces of the jewel receiving cavity is unnecessary since the positioning of the jewel is not dependent on the interior surfaces of the cavity, but instead depends upon the engagement of the locating surface of the jewel with the exterior locating surface of the first component of the support structure.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A more complete understanding of the present invention may be had by reference to the following Detailed Description when taken in connection with the accompanying Drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a sectional view illustrating a prior art system for mounting jewels comprising the nozzles of water cutting systems;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an enlargement of a portion of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a sectional view illustrating an improved system for mounting jewels comprising the nozzles of water cutting systems constructed in accordance with the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an enlargement of a portion of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Referring now to the Drawings, and particularly to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> thereof, there is shown a support structure <b>10</b> of the type heretofore utilized to receive and position a jewel <b>12</b> which comprises the nozzle of a water cutting system. The support structure <b>10</b> is typically formed from stainless steel, however, other materials that are not subject to degradation due to exposure to water can also be utilized in the manufacture of the support structure <b>10</b>. A water discharge passageway <b>14</b> extends through the support structure <b>10</b>. A jewel receiving cavity <b>16</b> is formed in the support structure <b>10</b> at the water receiving end of the water discharge passageway <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The jewel <b>12</b> has an orifice <b>18</b> extending therethrough which typically has a diameter of between about 0.0004 inches and about 0.0016 inches. The jewel <b>12</b> typically has a width of about 0.072 inches and a thickness of about 0.035 inches. Water at extremely high pressure, e.g., 50,000 psi, is directed through the orifice <b>18</b> extending through the jewel <b>12</b>. The function of the jewel <b>12</b> is to form the water into a very small diameter, very fast moving water stream.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The proper functioning of the jewel <b>12</b> depends upon accurate positioning thereof relative to the support structure <b>10</b>. To this end the jewel <b>12</b> is provided with a locating surface <b>22</b> which comprises the interior surface of the jewel <b>12</b>. The support structure <b>10</b> is provided with a cooperating locating surface <b>24</b> which comprises the bottom surface of the cavity <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Although the jewel <b>12</b> is characterized by very small dimensions, providing the necessary surface finish on the locating surface <b>22</b> thereof is relatively straightforward. This is because the surface <b>22</b> comprises an exterior surface of the jewel <b>12</b>. Conversely, providing the necessary surface finish on the locating surface <b>24</b> of the support structure <b>10</b> has proven to be problematic. This is because the locating surface <b>24</b> is situated at the bottom of the cavity <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Irregularities in the surface finish of the locating surface <b>24</b> of the support structure <b>10</b> inevitably leads to failure of the nozzle of the water cutting system in which the jewel <b>12</b> is employed. This is because irregularities in the surface finish of the locating surface <b>24</b> of the support structure <b>10</b>, and in particular radially extending grooves or ridges formed in the surface <b>24</b>, allows water to enter the space between the locating surface <b>24</b> of the support structure <b>10</b> and the locating surface <b>22</b> of the jewel <b>12</b>. The presence of water in the space between the locating surface <b>24</b> and the locating surface <b>22</b> causes degradation of the locating surfaces resulting in misalignment of the jewel <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, there is shown a method of and apparatus for positioning jewels comprising the nozzles of the water cutting systems which incorporates the present invention. A support structure <b>30</b> includes a first or interior component <b>32</b> and a second or exterior component <b>34</b>. The first component <b>32</b> has a water discharge passageway <b>36</b> extending therethrough. The first component <b>32</b> further comprises a locating surface <b>38</b>. As will be appreciated by those skilled in the art, the locating surface <b>38</b> of the first component <b>32</b> is an exterior surface. Because the locating surface <b>38</b> is formed on the exterior of the first component <b>32</b>, the lapping thereof to achieve the required surface finish of less than 8 RMS is relatively straightforward. Other manufacturing techniques adapted to provide a very smooth surface finish may also be used in the practice of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The second component <b>34</b> of the support structure <b>30</b> has a chamber <b>40</b> which receives the first component <b>32</b>. A water directing passageway <b>42</b> extends through the second component <b>34</b> and is axially aligned with the water discharge passageway <b>36</b> of the first component <b>32</b>. A jewel receiving cavity <b>44</b> is formed in the second component <b>34</b> and receives a jewel <b>46</b> therein. The jewel <b>46</b> has an orifice <b>48</b> extending therethrough which defines the discharge nozzle of the water cutting system comprising the support structure <b>30</b> and the jewel <b>46</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The jewel <b>46</b> is substantially identical to the jewel <b>12</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> and described hereinabove in conjunction therewith. The orifice <b>48</b> extending through the jewel <b>46</b> typically has a diameter of between about 0.0004 inches and about 0.0016 inches, it being understood that the diameter of the orifice <b>48</b> is dependent upon the requirements of particular applications of the invention. The jewel <b>46</b> typically has a width of about 0.072 inches and a thickness of about 0.035 inches, however, it will be further understood that the dimensions of the jewel <b>46</b> are dependent upon the requirements of particular applications of the invention. The jewel <b>46</b> is typically formed from a material selected from the group consisting of diamonds, sapphires, and rubies.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Referring particularly to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the jewel <b>46</b> has a locating surface <b>50</b> which engages the locating surface <b>38</b> of the first component <b>32</b> to effect proper positioning and alignment of the jewel <b>46</b>. Because of the extremely smooth surface finishes of the locating surface <b>38</b> and the locating surface <b>50</b> water cannot penetrate the junction therebetween. By this means degradation of the locating surfaces is avoided and continued proper alignment of the jewel <b>46</b> is assured. Additionally, the jewel receiving cavity <b>44</b> is dimensioned to provide a gap <b>52</b> between the surface of the jewel <b>46</b> opposite the locating surface <b>50</b> and the adjacent surface of the second component <b>34</b>. High pressure water within the water directing passageway <b>42</b> enters the gap <b>52</b> thereby further assuring a very tight engagement between the locating surface <b>38</b> of the first component <b>32</b> and the locating surface <b>50</b> of the jewel <b>46</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The embodiment of the invention shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> begins with the positioning of the jewel <b>46</b> in the jewel receiving cavity <b>44</b> with the locating surface <b>50</b> thereof facing outwardly from the passageway <b>42</b>. Thereafter the first component <b>32</b> of the support structure <b>30</b> is inserted into the chamber <b>40</b> of the second component <b>34</b> until the locating surface <b>38</b> of the first component engages the locating surface <b>50</b> of the jewel <b>46</b>. Thereafter the first component <b>32</b> of the support structure <b>30</b> is clamped in engagement with the second component <b>34</b> thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Although preferred embodiments of the invention have been illustrated in the accompanying Drawings and described in the foregoing Detailed Description, it will be understood that the invention is not limited to the embodiments disclosed, but is capable of numerous rearrangements, modifications, and substitutions of parts and elements without departing from the spirit of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An apparatus for locating a water cutting system nozzle jewel of the type having a water discharge orifice extending therethrough and having a locating surface comprising:
<claim-text>a first support structure component having a water discharge passageway extending therethrough and having an exterior locating surface at the water receiving end of the water discharge passageway;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second support structure component having a water directing passageway formed therethrough, having a jewel receiving cavity formed therein at the water discharge end of the directing passageway, and having a chamber for receiving the first support structure component therein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the water discharge passageway of the second support structure component being axially aligned with the water discharge passageway of the first support structure component;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the jewel received in the jewel receiving cavity of the second support structure component; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the locating surface of the first support structure component engaging the locating surface of the jewel thereby eliminating the need for means for retaining the jewel in the jewel receiving cavity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The apparatus for locating a water cutting system nozzle jewel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the exterior locating surface of the first support structure component and the locating surface of the jewel have extremely smooth surface finishes thereby preventing water from penetrating the junction therebetween, whereby degradation of both locating surfaces is avoided and continued proper alignment of the jewel is assured.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
