<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298640-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298640</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11121145</doc-number>
<date>20050503</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>79</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>365148</main-classification>
<further-classification>365100</further-classification>
<further-classification>365104</further-classification>
<further-classification>36518904</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">1T1R resistive memory array with chained structure</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5313418</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wada et al.</name>
<date>19940500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>365104</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6204139</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Liu et al.</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438385</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6473330</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ogiwara et al.</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>365145</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6583003</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hsu et al.</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438238</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6841833</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hsu et al.</name>
<date>20050100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257379</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>365100</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>365104</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>365148</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>36518904</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>15</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60567486</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040503</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050248978</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051110</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Zheng</first-name>
<address>
<city>Colorado Springs</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Paz de Araujo</last-name>
<first-name>Carlos A.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Colorado Springs</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>McMillan</last-name>
<first-name>Larry D.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Colorado Springs</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Patton Boggs LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Symetrix Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Colorado Springs</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Matsushita Electric Industrial Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Osaka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Elms</last-name>
<first-name>Richard T.</first-name>
<department>2824</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Luu</last-name>
<first-name>Pho M.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A 1T1R resistive memory array comprised of chains of memory cells, where each memory cell is composed of a resistive element in parallel with a switch. Such chains of memory cells are non-volatile and provide for each of the memory cells to be randomly accessed.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="113.20mm" wi="155.87mm" file="US07298640-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="239.95mm" wi="148.08mm" file="US07298640-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="268.65mm" wi="164.42mm" file="US07298640-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="244.94mm" wi="163.91mm" file="US07298640-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="233.26mm" wi="159.51mm" file="US07298640-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="228.09mm" wi="145.97mm" file="US07298640-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="246.80mm" wi="152.91mm" file="US07298640-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="153.67mm" wi="171.28mm" file="US07298640-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCES TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority from U.S. Provisional Patent Application Ser. No. 60/567,486 filed May 3, 2004, the entire teachings of which are herein incorporated by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The principles of the present invention are generally related to resistive memory arrays, and in particular, but not by way of limitation, to a device and method for configuring a resistive memory array, writing and reading from the resistive memory array, and producing the resistive memory array.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Resistive memory materials have recently been used to produce non-volatile memory cells. Data is stored in the memory cells by changing resistance of the resistive memory materials. Resistive memory materials may include colossal magnetoresistance (CMR) material, high temperature superconductivity (HTSC) materials, or other materials that have a perovskite structure capable of having electrical resistance characteristics altered by external influences. Such external influences may include applying positive and negative or reverse polarity voltages to the resistive memory materials to change the resistance characteristics thereof. The electric field strength or electric current density from one or more pulses is generally sufficient to switch the physical state of the resistive memory materials so as to modify the resistive properties. Alternatively, a pulse with the same polarity, but with different pulse widths, may be utilized to reverse the resistive property of the resistive memory materials previously set. Whichever technique is selected, in applying a pulse to the resistive memory materials, the pulse is to be low enough in energy so as not to destroy or damage the resistive material.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic of a resistive memory array <b>100</b> provided in U.S. Pat. No. 6,841,833 to Hsu et al. The memory array <b>100</b> utilizes a 1-transistor, 1-resistor (1T1R) memory cell configuration and includes sixteen memory cells <b>102</b> composed of a resistive memory element in series with a transistor. The memory array <b>100</b> includes columns of bit lines BL<b>1</b>-BL<b>4</b> and rows of word lines WL<b>1</b>-WL<b>4</b>. In addition, a common line CL extends between bit line pairs BL<b>1</b>-BL<b>2</b> and BL<b>3</b>-BL<b>4</b> is shared by every two bits (i.e., memory cells) connected between the bit line pairs BL<b>1</b>-BL<b>2</b> and BL<b>3</b>-BL<b>4</b>. While the memory array <b>100</b> is reduced in size by having two bits share a common line CL, the consequence is that the memory array <b>100</b> is not a random access memory. Instead, all of the memory cells <b>102</b> must be erased before a write operation. By having to erase all of the memory cells, the use of such a resistive memory array <b>100</b> is slow and is inefficient.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">To improve size, speed, and efficiency of resistive memory arrays, the principles of the present invention provide for a 1T1R resistive memory array configured as chains of memory cells, where each memory cell is composed of a resistive element in parallel with a switch. Such a configuration is non-volatile and provides for each of the memory cells to be randomly accessed. One embodiment of the principles of the present invention includes an electronic memory including a plurality of memory cells, each memory cell includes a switch and a resistive memory element connected in parallel. The resistive memory element is capable of existing in one of a plurality of resistive states, where each resistive state represents a different data state. The electronic memory further includes a memory write and read circuit selectably coupled to the resistive memory element and capable of writing a data state to the resistive memory element and reading the data state.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another embodiment includes a method of writing to an electronic memory including a plurality of memory cells, where each memory cell is composed of a resistive memory element. The method includes randomly accessing one of the resistive memory cells and writing data to the randomly accessed resistive memory cell without altering data in any other memory cell.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Yet another embodiment includes an electronic memory including a plurality of memory cells, where each memory cell is composed of a switch connected in parallel with a resistive memory element, a plurality of bit lines may form columns electrically coupling memory cells in series along the bit lines. The memory cells along at least two columns may have substantially the same spacing. A plurality of word lines may form forming rows and be coupled to the switches of the memory cells along the word lines. Circuitry may be coupled to the bit lines and word lines to write and read data to and from at least one memory cell.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Still yet, another embodiment may include an electronic memory cell, including a switch and a resistive memory element coupled in parallel.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Another embodiment may include a method for reading data from an electronic memory having memory cells arranged in rows of word lines and columns of bit lines, each bit line being connected to a column of memory cells having a switch in parallel with a resistive memory element and each word line being connected to switches in rows of the memory cells. The method may include applying a voltage level to all but one word line to turn on each of the switches of the corresponding memory cells, applying a voltage level to the one remaining word line to turn off the switch of the corresponding memory cell to access that memory cell, applying a voltage level to a first side of a bit line of the memory cell being accessed, and sensing the voltage level on the bit line on a second, opposite side of the memory cell being accessed.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An electronic system, including an electronic memory. The electronic memory may include a switch and a resistive memory element coupled in parallel. The system may further include a processor in communication with the memory to write data to and read data from the electronic memory. The electronic system may be a communication device, computing device, or other device that utilizes a memory for storing data.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Yet another embodiment may include a method of manufacturing an integrated circuit electronic memory. The method may include forming a plurality of transistors, forming an insulating layer above the transistors, depositing a resistive material on the insulating layer, etching the resistive material to form a resistive element associated with each of the transistors, etching the insulating layer between the resistive elements to form vias through to the active areas of the transistors, and depositing a conductor in the vias to connect said transistors to the resistive elements.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The principles of the present invention further provide for a substrate and transistor deposited on the substrate. An insulating layer may be disposed above the transistor. A resistive element may be disposed on the insulating layer above the transistor and at least two conductors may electrically connect the transistor in parallel with the resistive element.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A more complete understanding of the method and apparatus of the present invention may be obtained by reference to the following Detailed Description when taken in conjunction with the accompanying Drawings wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic of a prior art resistive memory array;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic of an exemplary resistive memory array according to the principles of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic of the resistive memory array of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrating an exemplary technique for writing a logic high value into a resistive memory cell;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a timing diagram showing an exemplary technique for writing a logic high value into the resistive memory cell in the resistive memory array of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic of the resistive memory array of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrating an exemplary technique for writing a logic low value into a resistive memory cell;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a timing diagram showing an exemplary technique for writing a logic low value into the resistive memory cell in the memory array of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a schematic of the resistive memory array of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrating an exemplary technique for reading from a resistive memory cell;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a timing diagram showing an exemplary technique for reading from a resistive memory cell of the resistive memory array of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a block diagram of an exemplary resistive memory array according to the principles of the present invention connected to write and read circuitry;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a block diagram of an exemplary system that includes a resistive memory array in accordance with the principles of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11A-11D</figref> are cross-section views as viewed through a bit line of an exemplary resistive memory array;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is the cross-section view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11D</figref> of a resistive memory array and a layout of a corresponding 4×4 chained 1T1R resistive memory array according to the principles of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic of an exemplary resistive memory array <b>200</b> according to the principles of the present invention. The memory array <b>200</b> is composed of memory cells <b>202</b> that include a resistive memory element R<b>11</b> connected in parallel with a switch M<b>11</b>. In one embodiment, the switch M<b>11</b> may be MOS transistor. Alternatively, other types of transistors may be utilized. The resistive memory element R<b>11</b> may be formed of CMR, HTSC, or other resistive materials capable of having resistive characteristics altered by an external influence.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The memory array <b>200</b> may be configured by forming series or chains of memory cells <b>202</b>. As shown, the chains of memory cells <b>202</b> may be connected along bit lines BL<b>1</b>-BL<b>4</b>. Word lines WL<b>1</b>-WL<b>4</b> may be connected to memory cells <b>202</b> via gate terminals of the switches along respective memory cells <b>202</b>. Each bit line may have a select switch MB<b>1</b>-MB<b>4</b> and sense switch MS<b>1</b>-MS<b>4</b> connected thereto used to control access to memory cells <b>202</b> along the corresponding bit lines BL<b>1</b>-BL<b>4</b>. For example, to access a memory cell <b>202</b> having switch M<b>11</b>, select switch MB<b>1</b> and control switch MS<b>1</b> are selectably turned on. Below control switch MS<b>1</b> may be a sense amplifier (see, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>) that is used for reading data stored in the memory cells along the bit lines as understood in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic of the resistive memory array <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrating an exemplary technique for writing a logic high level into a memory cell <b>302</b>. In one embodiment, if a positive pulse is applied to the resistive element R<b>22</b>, the resistance increases. If a negative pulse or reverse polarity pulse is applied to the resistive element R<b>22</b>, the resistance decreases. The low resistance (LR) may be as low as 100 ohm to 10 k-ohm, and the high resistance (HR) may range from 50 k-ohm to 10 mega-ohm. The amount of change depends on the resistive material, deposition condition, film thickness and area. Another technique for changing the resistance of the resistive element R<b>22</b> is to change the pulse amplitude and pulse width of a pulse being applied to the memory cell <b>302</b>. For example, a 5 volt (5V) and 10 nanosecond (10 ns) pulse may be applied to the resistive element R<b>22</b> to increase the resistance and a 3V and 4 microsecond (μs) pulse may be applied to the resistive element R<b>22</b> to decrease the resistance. However, utilizing positive and reverse polarity pulses are generally a faster techniques for changing the resistance of a resistive element between a high and low logic level.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As previously described, the switches at the top and bottom of the bit lines BL<b>1</b>-BL<b>4</b> are row/column select switches MB<b>1</b>-MB<b>4</b> and sense switches MS<b>1</b>-MS<b>4</b>. The select switches MB<b>1</b>-MB<b>4</b> and sense switches MS<b>1</b>-MS<b>4</b> are used to select a certain bit and to separate the memory array <b>200</b> from external circuitry. For example, if memory cell <b>302</b> is to be selected, select switch MB<b>2</b> and sense switch MS<b>2</b> are turned on and the other select and sense switches are turned off. In addition, word line WL<b>2</b> is grounded and each of the other word lines WL<b>1</b>, WL<b>3</b>-WL<b>4</b> are turned high. By applying a low voltage onto word line WL<b>2</b>, switch M<b>22</b> remains or is turned off so that current is forced through resistive element R<b>22</b> connected in parallel to the switch M<b>22</b>. Because word lines WL<b>1</b>, WL<b>3</b> and WL<b>4</b> are high, each of the corresponding switches M<b>12</b>, M<b>32</b>, and M<b>42</b>, respectively, are turned on such that current flows through the switches and bypasses each of the resistive elements R<b>12</b>, R<b>32</b>, and R<b>42</b>, respectively connected in parallel. The process of being able to select one memory cell along a bit line enables random access writing and reading. While not writing to or reading from the memory array <b>200</b>, select switches MB<b>1</b>-MB<b>4</b> and sense switches MS<b>1</b>-MS<b>4</b> may be turned off so that the memory array <b>200</b> is isolated from the external circuitry, thereby keeping electrical noise from the memory array <b>200</b>. It should be understood that the memory array <b>200</b> is shown as a 4×4 chain array, and may be sized and dimensioned as desired, such as 128×128 or larger.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a timing diagram showing an exemplary technique for writing a logic high into a memory cell <b>302</b> in the memory array <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. In writing a high value to memory cell <b>302</b>, select switch MB<b>2</b> and sense switch MS<b>2</b> are turned on at time t<sub>1 </sub>while other select switches MB<b>1</b>, MB<b>3</b> and MB<b>4</b> and sense switches MS<b>1</b>, MS<b>3</b>, and MS<b>4</b> are turned off. At time t<sub>2</sub>, word lines WL<b>1</b>, WL<b>3</b>, and WL<b>4</b> are switched high while word line WL<b>2</b> is maintained at a low voltage level so that memory switches M<b>12</b>, M<b>32</b>, and M<b>42</b> are turned on and memory switch M<b>22</b> is maintained off to cause current to flow through memory switches M<b>12</b>, M<b>32</b> and M<b>42</b>, rather than the parallel resistive elements R<b>12</b>, R<b>32</b>, and R<b>42</b>, respectively. Accordingly, the current flows through resistive element R<b>22</b> to enable data to be written into memory cell <b>302</b> via a pulse on bit line BL<b>2</b>. At time t<sub>3</sub>, a positive pulse on bit line BL<b>2</b> is applied to increase resistance of resistive element R<b>22</b>. In one embodiment, the positive pulse may be 5V in amplitude and 10 ns in duration. At time t<sub>4</sub>, the pulse on bit line BL<b>2</b> transitions low. At t<sub>5</sub>, word lines WL<b>1</b>, WL<b>3</b>, and WL<b>4</b> are transitioned low. Select switch MB<b>2</b> and sense switch MS<b>2</b> are transitioned low at t<sub>6</sub>. At this point, the write cycle is complete and a high logic level is stored in the memory cell <b>302</b> by causing the resistive element R<b>22</b> to have a high resistance value. It should be understood that the timing diagram in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is exemplary and that alternative timing may be utilized to write a high logic value to the memory cell <b>302</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic of the memory array of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrating an exemplary technique for writing a logic low value or “0” into a memory cell. To write a “0” into memory cell <b>302</b>, a similar operation is performed as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> with the exception that a pulse in the opposite polarity is applied to the memory cell <b>302</b>. This causes the opposite effect as that of writing a “1” into the memory cell <b>302</b> described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> and causes resistance of the resistive element R<b>22</b> to be lowered. It should be understood that the high and low resistance values of the resistive element R<b>22</b> are relative and are used to enable a sense amplifier to sense a difference in current flow to determine whether a high or low logic level is stored in the memory cell.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a timing diagram showing an exemplary technique for writing a logic low into the memory cell <b>302</b> in the memory array <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The timing shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is slightly different from that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> to show that there may be several embodiments for writing data into a resistive memory cell according to the principles of the present invention. As shown, the word lines WL<b>1</b>, WL<b>3</b>, and WL<b>4</b> are driven high at time t<sub>1 </sub>to cause the current to flow through switches M<b>12</b>, M<b>32</b> and M<b>42</b>, respectively. Word line WL<b>2</b> remains low to cause current to flow through resistive element R<b>22</b>, which is being altered in resistance to write a “0” therein. At time t<sub>2</sub>, select switch MB<b>2</b> and sense switch MS<b>2</b> are driven high. Between times t<sub>3</sub>-t<sub>4</sub>, bit line BL<b>2</b> is grounded and sense line SL<b>2</b> is pulsed, which causes resistive element R<b>22</b> to transition from a high to a low resistance level. In one embodiment, the pulse may be 5V in amplitude and 10 ns in duration. At time t<sub>5</sub>, the select and sense switches MB<b>2</b> and MS<b>2</b> are transitioned low and word lines WL<b>1</b>, WL<b>3</b>, and WL<b>4</b> are transitioned low at time t<sub>6</sub>, thereby ending the write cycle to store a low logic level in the memory cell <b>302</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a schematic of the memory array <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrating an exemplary technique for reading from a memory cell. In reading a memory cell <b>302</b>, the memory cell <b>302</b> is selected in the same manner as used in the write operation, but the voltage on bit line BL<b>2</b> is low enough not to change the resistance of the resistive element R<b>22</b>. In one embodiment, the voltage applied to bit line BL<b>2</b> is 0.5 volts. The sense line SL<b>2</b> is connected to a sense amplifier (not shown), as understood in the art. Depending on the resistance of the resistive element R<b>22</b> set by the write operation, the sense amplifier senses a different current and/or voltage to determine whether a high or low logic level (i.e., data value) was stored in the memory cell <b>302</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a timing diagram showing an exemplary technique for reading from a memory cell of the memory array of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. At time t<sub>1 </sub>word lines WL<b>1</b>, WL<b>3</b>, and WL<b>4</b> are switched high to turn on switches M<b>12</b>, M<b>32</b>, and M<b>42</b>, respectively. Word line WL<b>2</b> remains low to access the memory cell <b>302</b>. At time t<sub>2</sub>, selection switch MB<b>2</b> and sense switch MS<b>2</b> are turned on. During times t<sub>3 </sub>and t<sub>4</sub>, a low voltage pulse is applied to bit line BL<b>2</b> to cause a current to flow through the resistive element R<b>22</b>. The current flowing through the resistive element R<b>22</b> flows to the sense line SL<b>2</b>, which is connected to a sense amplifier. The sense amplifier is able to measure current and/or voltage, which is a function of a voltage drop across the resistive element R<b>22</b> set or stored during a writing operation. At time t<sub>5</sub>, the select and sense switches MB<b>2</b> and MS<b>2</b> are turned off. The word lines WL<sub>1</sub>, WL<sub>3</sub>, and WL<sub>4 </sub>are turned off at time t<sub>6</sub>, which ends the reading process. It should be understood that the timing shown in the timing diagram <b>800</b> may be different from that shown and still provide the same or equivalent functionality in accordance with the principles of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a block diagram of a memory circuit <b>900</b> including an exemplary resistive memory array <b>902</b> according to the principles of the present invention connected to write and read circuitry. The memory circuit <b>900</b> includes a resistive memory array <b>902</b>. In one embodiment, the resistive memory array <b>902</b> is formed of 128×128 memory cells. However, the resistive memory array <b>902</b> may have virtually any size as understood in the art. The resistive memory array <b>902</b> may be connected to a 7-bit decoder word line drive circuit <b>904</b> via word lines <b>906</b>. The resistive memory array <b>902</b> may be further coupled to a 3-to-1 bit multiplexer <b>908</b> and sense amplifiers/input-output transistors <b>910</b> via bit lines <b>912</b>. Control logic circuitry <b>914</b> may be in communication with (i) the decoder <b>904</b> via control lines <b>916</b>, (ii) multiplexer <b>908</b> via control lines <b>918</b>, and (iii) sense amplifier <b>910</b> via control lines <b>920</b>. External input lines may include an address input line <b>922</b> and control lines <b>924</b>. A data output line <b>926</b> may be used to output data from the memory circuit <b>900</b> via the sense amplifiers/transceivers <b>910</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In operation, an external processor (see, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>) may be used to drive the control logic <b>914</b>. The control logic circuitry <b>914</b> communicates with the decoder <b>904</b>, multiplexer <b>908</b>, and sense amplifiers <b>910</b>, which, in combination, are used to write data into the resistive memory array <b>902</b> and read data stored in the resistive memory array <b>902</b> as described in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-8</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a block diagram of an exemplary system <b>1000</b> that includes a resistive memory array in accordance with the principles of the present invention. The system <b>1000</b> may include a processor <b>1002</b> and resistive memory array <b>1004</b>. The processor <b>1002</b> may communicate with the resistive memory array <b>1004</b> to write and read data thereto. The system may be any system that utilizes memory for data storage. For example, the system may be a computing device, communication device, storage device, or any other electronic device that utilizes memory for storage of information.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11A-11D</figref> are cross-section views as viewed through a bit line during a CMOS manufacturing process of an exemplary resistive memory array. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11A</figref> shows a first stage structure <b>1100</b><i>a </i>of the resistive memory array that includes a silicon substrate <b>1102</b> having ion implementation regions <b>1104</b> applied thereto after forming and etching a gate oxide layer <b>1106</b> grown over the substrate <b>1102</b>. The combination of the ion implantation regions <b>1104</b> and gate oxide layer <b>1106</b> forms a transistor or switch, such as switch M<b>22</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Word lines <b>1108</b> may be deposited on the gate oxide layer <b>1106</b> (i.e., gate terminal of the transistor) for conducting current within the memory array <b>1100</b> and controlling switches that the word lines <b>108</b> are in contact. A silicon oxide (SiO<sub>2</sub>) layer <b>1110</b> may be deposited over the substrate and word lines <b>1108</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11B</figref> shows a second stage structure <b>1100</b><i>b </i>of the memory array during the manufacturing process. In one embodiment, a buffer layer <b>1112</b> may be deposited on the SiO<sub>2 </sub>layer <b>1110</b>. The buffer layer <b>1112</b> is a non-conductive material as understood in the art. Above the buffer layer, resistive material <b>1114</b> may be deposited to form a resistor. The resistive material <b>1114</b> may be composed of colossal magnetoresistive material, high temperature superconductivity (HTSC) material, PCMO (Pr<sub>0.7</sub>Ca<sub>0.3</sub>MnO<sub>3</sub>), or other resistive material. In one embodiment, the resistive material <b>1114</b> is deposited directly on the SiO<sub>2 </sub>layer <b>1110</b>. The resistive material may have physical dimensions of 45 nm to 1 μm length, 45 nm to 1 μm width, and 25 nm to 300 nm thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11C</figref> is a cross-section view showing a third stage structure <b>1100</b><i>c </i>of the memory array having vias <b>1116</b> to expose the ion implantation regions <b>1104</b> in the substrate <b>1102</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11D</figref> is a cross-section view of a fourth stage structure <b>1100</b><i>d </i>of the memory array that includes metal plugs <b>1118</b> to operate as drain and source terminals of the switch and to connect the switch in parallel to the resistive material <b>1114</b>. Another SiO<sub>2 </sub>layer <b>1120</b> may be deposited thereon to insulate the metal plugs <b>1118</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is cross-section view of the fourth stage structure <b>1100</b><i>d </i>and a layout of a complete resistive memory array <b>1200</b> according to the principles of the present invention. The cross-section view reflects the resistive memory array along a line defined by I-I′, which extends a long a bit line <b>1122</b>. Because of the resistive material <b>1114</b> being in parallel with the transistor composed of the ion implantation regions <b>1104</b> and CO<sub>2 </sub>oxide layer <b>1106</b>, a memory cell may be as small as 4F<sup>2</sup>, where F is defined as feature size as understood in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The particular systems, memory designs, and methods described herein are intended to illustrate the functionality and versatility of the invention, but the invention should not be construed to be limited to those particular embodiments. It is evident that those skilled in the art may make numerous uses and modifications of the specific embodiments described, or equivalent structures and processes may be substituted for the structures and processed described. For example, the memory is shown with the resistive elements and their associated transistors arranged in columns. The resistive elements may just as well have been arranged in rows. Thus, herein, the arrangement is referred to as a row/column arrangement. Since certain changes may be made in the above systems and methods without departing from the scope of the invention, it is intended that all subject matter contained in the above description or shown in the accompanying drawings may be interpreted as illustrative and not in a limiting sense, consequently, the invention is to be construed as embracing each and every novel feature and novel combination of features present or inherently possessed by the systems, devices, and methods described in the claims below and their equivalence.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electronic memory comprising a plurality of memory cells, each memory cell including:
<claim-text>a switch;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a resistive memory element connected in parallel with said switch, said resistive memory element capable of existing in one of a plurality of resistive states, each resistive state representing a different data state; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a memory write and read circuit selectably coupled to said resistive memory element and capable of writing a data state to said resistive memory element and reading the data state;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said plurality of memory cells are arranged in a row/column configuration, each row/column configuration including a plurality of said resistive memory elements connected in series and a plurality of said switches connected in series, each of said switches associated with one of said resistive memory elements; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said memory further comprising a source of a programming voltage and a row/column selection transistor connected between said source of the programming voltage and said row/column of memory cells.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The electronic memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a sense amplifier and a row/column sense transistor connected between said sense amplifier and said row/column of memory cells.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The electronic memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said resistive memory element includes a material selected from the group consisting of colossal magnetoresistance (CMR) materials and high temperature superconductivity (HTSC) materials.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The electronic memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said resistive memory element is composed of Pr<sub>0.7</sub>Ca<sub>0.3</sub>MnO<sub>3</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The electronic memory according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each of said memory cells has a maximum size of 4F<sub>2</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
