<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297126-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297126</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11081285</doc-number>
<date>20050315</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>462</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>61</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 57</main-classification>
<further-classification>601 30</further-classification>
<further-classification>601 49</further-classification>
<further-classification>601 56</further-classification>
<further-classification>  5915</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Portable foot and wrist massager</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4326506</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kawabata</name>
<date>19820400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4802463</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Rojas</name>
<date>19890200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4979502</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hunt</name>
<date>19901200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4989584</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Simon</name>
<date>19910200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>601 70</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5007410</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>DeLaney</name>
<date>19910400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>601 53</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5188095</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Healy</name>
<date>19930200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>601 61</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5334131</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Omandam et al.</name>
<date>19940800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5599280</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wolden</name>
<date>19970200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5807287</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cheng</name>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6537235</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Connor et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 15</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 27</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 30</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 31</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 46</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 49</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 53</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 56</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 57</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 58</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 59</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 61</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 66</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 69</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>601 70</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  5694</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  5915</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060211960</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060921</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kries</last-name>
<first-name>Gary W.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Isleton</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>West</last-name>
<first-name>R. Michael</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<last-name>Grose</last-name>
<first-name>Ronald L.</first-name>
<role>14</role>
<address>
<city>Lodi</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Thanh</last-name>
<first-name>Quang D.</first-name>
<department>3771</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A portable massager adaptable for foot and wrist applications. An elongated resonator plate is formed from a plurality of contiguous hollow flutes oriented in a longitudinal direction. One or more vibrator cutouts are provided in the resonator plate, passing from its upper side to its lower side. A vibrator, preferably capable of operating from low voltage DC, nests within each cutout. A lower sheet covers the lower side of the resonator plate and lower face of the vibrator. An upper sheet accommodates the upper face of the vibrator and covers at least a portion of the upper side of the resonator plate. Top and bottom vinyl covers encase the massager construction. A vibrator control switch may be included in the power line extending from an external electrical connector to the vibrator. The massager may be powered by a wall transformer or by alternative mobile power sources.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="179.58mm" wi="176.78mm" file="US07297126-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="262.72mm" wi="178.22mm" file="US07297126-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="255.10mm" wi="174.41mm" file="US07297126-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="256.62mm" wi="165.35mm" file="US07297126-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention relates generally to electrically powered massaging devices. More particularly, the invention pertains to a portable foot or wrist massager including an internal resonating plate provided with a plurality of contiguous hollow flutes to enhance the effectiveness of the massager's vibrators.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The prior art shows a variety of electrically powered massaging devices which are adapted both for therapeutic uses and for general relaxation. Some massagers are designed for more general use, such as a mattress to lie upon. For example, vibratory mats or pads are shown in U.S. Pat. No. 4,326,506, issued to Kawabata and in U.S. Pat. No. 5,807,287, granted to Cheng. Other massaging devices are adapted to cover or wrap around particular parts of the body. U.S. Pat. No. 4,979,502 to Hunt, shows combined massage and heating devices particularly adapted for the chest, waist, arm and legs. A strap-on massager for the leg is disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 5,334,131, issued to Omandam et al. A foot massager is shown in U.S. Pat. No. 4,802,463, granted to Rojas. And, a scarf with an electrically operated massager is taught in U.S. Pat. No. 6,537,235 issued to Connor et al. Lastly, in U.S. Pat. No. 5,599,280 granted to Wolden, a therapeutic wrist device having vibration and heat is illustrated.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, there is a need for a massager which may be adapted to massage both the feet and the wrists of the human body, using very similar construction techniques.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">There is also a need for a massager having high and substantially uniform vibratory output across its working surface.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">There is also a need for a portable massager which may be powered by different power sources readily available at home, in the office, in an automobile or in connection with other modes of transportation.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">These and other objects of the present invention will be described in the drawings and in the detailed description of the preferred embodiment set forth below.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The invention comprises a portable electrically powered massager, which may be constructed either for foot massaging or for wrist massaging applications. The massager includes an elongated resonator plate in its core. The resonator plate is formed from a plurality of contiguous hollow flutes, oriented in the longitudinal aspect of the resonator plate. The resonator plate is manufactured from substantially rigid plastic material, to enhance the transmissivity of vibratory waves. At least one vibrator cutout is provided in the resonator plate, passing from its upper side to its lower side.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A vibrator is snugly positioned within the vibrator cutout so that vibrations are directly coupled to the resonator plate. A cutout cover, slightly larger than the cutout itself, may be glued over the bottom of the vibrator and the adjacent portion of the resonator plate. A lower sheet, preferably manufactured from foam, covers the lower side of the resonator plate and the cutout cover. An upper sheet, also preferably manufactured from foam material, may also include a cutout to accommodate the upper face of the vibrator. The upper sheet covers at least a portion of the upper side of the resonator plate, generally surrounding the vibrators. Top and bottom vinyl or cloth covers are provided to encase the entirety of the massager components.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A control switch may be mounted inside the vibrator, and is series-connected within the power line extending from an external electrical connector to the vibrators. The external electrical connector, in turn, is detachably connected to a power line extension. The power line extension may lead to a small wall transformer, for home or office use, or to a cigarette lighter plug, for portable or field use, such as in an automobile or other vehicle.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of the massager of the present invention, a portion of the cover, the upper sheet, and the resonator plate being broken away to show inner details;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded perspective view of the foot massager of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, showing the top and bottom covers, the upper and lower sheets, the resonator plate and the two vibrators;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view showing the foot massager in a typical office or home use, being powered by a wall transformer;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective view showing the foot massager in an automobile, being powered by the power line extension connected to a cigarette lighter socket;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is fragmentary, perspective view taken to an enlarged scale, showing the contiguous hollow flutes in the resonator plate;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a fragmentary, end elevational view taken of the resonator plate and a vibrator, showing the waves transferring vibratory energy from the vibrator throughout the resonator plate;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a perspective view of the massager of the present invention, configured as a wrist massager, a portion of the cover, the upper sheet and the resonator plate being broken away to show inner details of construction; and,</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a perspective view of the wrist massager being employed at a computer workstation, using an external wall transformer as a power supply.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The portable massager <b>11</b> of the present invention, sized and configured for the application of massaging feet, is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Although not critical, a longitudinal dimension of 16″, or so, and a transverse dimension of 12″, or so, are suitable to accommodate the feet of most <b>20</b> people. Such dimension are also not so large as to make the massager <b>11</b> unwieldy to handle or transport. At the core of the massager <b>11</b> is an elongated resonator plate <b>12</b>. As is shown most clearly in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>, plate <b>12</b> includes plurality of contiguous, hollow flutes <b>13</b>. It is significant to note that flutes <b>13</b> are oriented in the longitudinal direction or aspect of plate <b>12</b>. The flutes have a uniform diameter, and may range in size from approximately 1/16″ to ½″. Relatively thin and planar, plate <b>12</b> is preferably manufactured from a substantially rigid but lightweight material, such as plastic. Other materials may also be suitable for plate <b>12</b>, providing they can be formed to include the plurality of flutes or equivalent structure, and are sufficiently rigid to transmit vibratory waves effectively.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">At least one vibrator cutout <b>14</b> is provided in the resonator plate <b>12</b>, passing from its upper side <b>16</b> to its lower side <b>17</b>. Preferably, two vibrator cutouts <b>14</b> are used in most applications, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. A conventional electric vibrator <b>18</b> nests within each of the vibrator cutouts <b>14</b>. The plan dimensions of the vibrators are such that they fit snugly within the cutouts <b>14</b>, providing effective coupling of the case vibrations to the structure of the resonance plate <b>12</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the height of the vibrator <b>18</b> is such that its upper face <b>19</b> extends beyond the plane of the upper side <b>16</b> of the resonator plate <b>12</b>. And, the lower face <b>20</b> of the vibrator <b>18</b> is co-planar with the lower side <b>17</b> of plate <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">A cutout cover <b>21</b> may be provided for additional support for the vibrator, and to enhance vibratory coupling between the vibrator <b>18</b> and the resonance plate <b>12</b>. Cutout cover <b>21</b> is slightly larger than the plan dimensions of the cutout <b>14</b>, and may be glued to the bottom of the vibrator and the lower side of the resonator plate immediately surrounding the cutout <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Vibrators <b>18</b> are preferably capable of operating from low voltage DC, in the range of approximately 3-24 volts. This capability will enable the massager <b>11</b> to be operated from a variety of readily available wall transformers <b>22</b> which typically convert 120 volts AC to low voltage DC. Such a capability will also enable the massager to operate from the nominal 12 volts DC which is available in automobiles, boats, and some trains and airplanes. Solar cells and low voltage power packs also provide 12 volts DC for operation of the massager. However, higher operating voltages or operation from alternating current is also possible by simply using vibrators of different operating specifications for the massager <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">A lower sheet <b>23</b> covers the lower side <b>17</b> of the resonator plate <b>12</b> and cutout covers <b>21</b>. Lower sheet <b>23</b> is preferably constructed from foam, or other resilient material. A power line <b>24</b> extends from each vibrator <b>18</b> to an external connector <b>26</b>, having a female end <b>27</b> and a male end <b>28</b>. A push-button switch <b>29</b> is series-connected within power line <b>24</b>, so that the user may selectively control the operation of the vibrators <b>18</b>. The base of switch <b>29</b> is adhesively attached to the upper side of lower sheet <b>23</b>. The control button of switch <b>29</b> passes through an aperture <b>31</b> in resonator plate <b>12</b>. A power line extension <b>32</b> connects male end <b>28</b> to wall transformer <b>22</b>. Alternatively, for portable operation, such as in a motor vehicle, a power line extension <b>33</b> may be provided, connecting male end <b>28</b> to a standard cigarette lighter plug <b>34</b>. (See, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">An upper sheet <b>36</b>, also made from foam or other resilient material, includes two vibrator cutouts <b>37</b>, sized, configured, and located to accommodate the upper faces <b>19</b> of vibrators <b>18</b>. Upper sheet <b>36</b> covers at least a portion of the upper side <b>16</b> of the resonator plate <b>12</b>, generally in the vicinity of the vibrators <b>18</b>. The portion of upper side <b>16</b> which is not covered by upper sheet <b>36</b>, allows the user of the massager to enjoy substantially direct contact with the vibrating resonator plate <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Massager <b>11</b> also includes a top cover <b>38</b> and a bottom cover <b>39</b>, encasing its operative components. Covers <b>38</b> and <b>39</b> may be manufactured from either vinyl, leather, or fabric, as required. Top cover <b>38</b> is co-extensive with the upper sheet <b>36</b> and the remaining uncovered upper side <b>16</b> of resonator plate <b>12</b>. Top cover <b>38</b> includes an aperture <b>41</b> to pass the control button of switch <b>29</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, bottom cover <b>39</b> is co-extensive with the lower sheet <b>23</b>. Top cover <b>38</b> and bottom cover including peripheral edges connected to form a peripheral seam <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">For the purpose of massaging a user's wrists, while working at a computer station or the like, a massager <b>43</b> is disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 and 8</figref>. Except for its overall plan dimensions, massager <b>43</b> is constructed virtually identically to the massager <b>11</b> described above. Massager <b>43</b> is sized and configured to accommodate the wrist and lower palms of a user, while working at a computer keyboard <b>44</b>. As such, massager <b>43</b> may be approximately 15″, or so, in its longitudinal dimension, and approximately 4″, or so, in its transverse dimension. Massager <b>43</b> also includes a pair of vibrators <b>18</b>, mounted within and coupled to a resonator plate <b>46</b> of the appropriate dimensions. As with massager <b>11</b>, the flutes <b>13</b> of resonator plate <b>46</b> in massager <b>43</b> are oriented in the longitudinal direction or aspect of plate <b>46</b>. Because in all other respects, massager <b>43</b> is identical to massager <b>11</b>, no further explanation regarding its structural features need be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In operation, both massagers enjoy the same enhanced performance, provided principally by their respective resonator plates <b>12</b> and <b>46</b> in combination with associated vibratory mechanisms. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> depicts the unique coupling and transmission of vibratory waves <b>47</b>, provided by the resonator plates of the present invention. The contiguous, hollow flutes, oriented in the longitudinal direction or aspect of the massager, are effective to distribute the vibratory waves <b>47</b> both transversely and longitudinally throughout the massager's operating surface. As a consequence, efficient and uniform distribution of the vibratory waves throughout the massager is effected, to the enjoyment of the user.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A portable massager comprising:
<claim-text>a. an elongated resonator plate, said plate including a plurality of contiguous hollow flutes oriented in a longitudinal direction, said plate further including at least one vibrator cutout passing from an upper side to a lower side thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b. an electric vibrator, said vibrator being sized and configured to fit within said cutout of said resonator plate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c. a lower sheet of resilient material, said lower sheet covering said lower side of said resonator plate and supporting a lower face of said vibrator; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>d. an upper sheet of resilient material, said upper sheet covering an upper face of said vibrator and at least a portion of said upper side of said resonator plate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further including a top cover co-extensive with and covering said upper sheet and said upper side of said resonator plate, and a bottom cover co-extensive with and covering said lower sheet, said top cover and said bottom cover including peripheral edges connected to form a peripheral seam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> in which said resonator plate is formed from a substantially rigid plastic material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> in which said flutes have a uniform diameter within the range of 1/16″ to ½″.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> in which a power line extends from said vibrator to a power supply external to the massager.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> in which said vibrator is powered by a DC voltage in the range of approximately 3 to 24 volts, and in which said power supply is a wall transformer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> in which a vibrator control switch is provided in said power line, and in which a detachable electrical connector is provided at an end of said power line external to said massager.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> in which one end of a power extension cord is connected to said electrical connector and the other end of said power extension cord includes an automobile cigarette lighter plug.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> having an elongated dimension and a transverse dimension so as to accommodate two feet resting thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> having an elongated dimension and a transverse dimension so as to accommodate two wrists resting thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A portable massager comprising:
<claim-text>a. an elongated resonator plate, said plate including a plurality of contiguous hollow flutes oriented in a longitudinal direction, said plate further including a pair of vibrator cutouts passing from an upper side to a lower side thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b. a pair of electric vibrators, said vibrators being sized and configured to fit within said cutouts of said resonator plate, each of said vibrators having a lower face and an upper face;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c. a lower sheet of resilient material, said lower sheet covering said lower side of said resonator plate and supporting said lower faces of said vibrators;</claim-text>
<claim-text>d. an upper sheet of resilient material, said upper sheet covering said upper faces of said vibrators and at least a portion of said upper side of said resonator plate; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>e. a top cover co-extensive with and covering said upper sheet and said upper side of said resonator plate, and a bottom cover co-extensive with and covering said lower sheet, said top cover and said bottom cover including peripheral edges connected to form a peripheral seam.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> in which said resonator plate is formed from a substantially rigid plastic material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> in which said flutes have a uniform diameter within the range of 1/16″ to ½″.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> in which a power line extends from said vibrators to a power supply external to the massager.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A portable massager comprising:
<claim-text>a. an elongated resonator plate, said plate being substantially rigid and including a plurality of contiguous hollow flutes oriented in a longitudinal direction, said plate further including a pair of vibrator cutouts passing from an upper side to a lower side thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>b. a pair of electric vibrators, said vibrators being sized and configured to fit within said cutouts of said resonator plate, each of said vibrators having a lower face and an upper face;</claim-text>
<claim-text>c. a lower sheet of foam, said lower sheet covering said lower side of said resonator plate and supporting said lower faces of said vibrators;</claim-text>
<claim-text>d. an upper sheet of foam, said upper sheet covering said upper faces of said vibrators and at least a portion of said upper side of said resonator plate; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>e. a top cover co-extensive with and covering said upper sheet and said upper side of said resonator plate, and a bottom cover co-extensive with and covering said lower sheet, said top cover and said bottom cover including peripheral edges connected to form a peripheral seam.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> in which said resonator plate is formed from a plastic material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> in which said flutes have a uniform diameter within the range of 1/16″ to ½″.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> in which a power line extends from said vibrators to a power supply external to the massager and in which a vibrator control switch is provided in said power line, said vibrator control switch being located on said lower sheet and having a switch control element extending through said top cover so as to be user accessible.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> having an elongated dimension and a transverse dimension so as to accommodate two feet resting thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A massager as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> having an elongated dimension and a transverse dimension so as to accommodate two wrists resting thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
