<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299312-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299312</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10939088</doc-number>
<date>20040910</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>245</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>24</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710260</main-classification>
<further-classification>710302</further-classification>
<further-classification>439 78</further-classification>
<further-classification>361760</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Telecommunication apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6392142</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Uzuka et al.</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>174541</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6425027</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Mills et al.</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710300</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6578103</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hill et al.</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710313</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6965959</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Linares et al.</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710300</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7000053</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Ho et al.</name>
<date>20060200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710302</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0085361</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wachel</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361803</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0086550</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hershkovits et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>37922103</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>CompactPCI Short Form Specification, PICMG, Nov. 1, 1995.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>IEEE Standard 1101.11, May 21, 1998.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00010">
<othercit>CompactPCI and Computer Telephony, Joe Pavlat, CompactPCI Systems, 1997.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>Adaptors for Network Technology, Teletekno Oy, 2000.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>Definition of Eurocard from Wikipedia , undated.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00013">
<othercit>Definition of BNC connector from Wikipedia , undated.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710300</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710301</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710302</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710305</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710313</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 78</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 79</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 82</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439445</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439572</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361752</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361760</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361788</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060059290</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060316</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>McKeown</last-name>
<first-name>Shane</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fife</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>GB</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>GB</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Agilent Technologies, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Santa Clara</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Dang</last-name>
<first-name>Khanh</first-name>
<department>2111</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A transition module using an input/output (I/O) bus interface can be connected to a backplane having a bus connector. The transition module is provided with an external connector for receiving an input signal, an interface circuit coupled to the external connector and a processing unit for carrying out initial filtering and processing of the input signal before coupling the signal to a processor card connected to the backplane via the I/O bus interface and the bus connector.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="103.04mm" wi="171.03mm" file="US07299312-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="247.23mm" wi="190.84mm" file="US07299312-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="227.67mm" wi="173.82mm" file="US07299312-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="243.84mm" wi="191.35mm" file="US07299312-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to apparatus used in telecommunications, in particular to modularised network cards which are coupled to backplanes; and more particularly to a card having increased functionality.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Worldwide today, substantial demands are being placed on modern telecommunication networks by the increase in the numbers of telephone lines, pages, fax machines and subscribers to other data systems, such as the Internet. This increased demand is placing ever increasing pressure on telecommunication service operators to achieve greater throughput whilst achieving the so-called “five nines” operational availability (i.e., 99.999% up time) as well as provide the capability to support future functionality or features whilst keeping costs to a minimum. In telecommunication networks, service operators employ exchange rooms which have high-densities of high-power networking and processing equipment, which are all housed in a mechanical chassis. Many challenging considerations arise from having such a tightly packed arrangement of high-power equipment, including the need for specialist cooling systems, cabling arrangements and ease of maintenance. The “five nines” operational availability and other service level agreements (SLA's) impose great demands on network maintenance and the so-called “hot-swap” technology employed in equipment housed in a chassis allows faulty cards to be easily replaced.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Typically the mechanical chassis houses the electronic equipment which carries out networking and processing of routed data signals. The data signals may be transmitted on either electrical cables or optical fibre cables, which are often arranged around and supported by the outside of the chassis. The cables are plugged into the electronic equipment contained in the chassis. Often a series of cables will be plugged into a single modularised network card and a series of cards may be layered within a chassis. The modularised network cards are connected by a backplane. Typically a backplane is a printed circuit board which contains slots or sockets into which modularised cards, other electronic circuit boards and/or cables can be plugged. Typically, backplanes have front and rear sides and provide a physical connection between an interface processor or modularised card, the data signals and power distribution buses, all housed within the chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The cabling issues associated with such densely laid out equipment can provide many challenges. The cables should be easy to replace and readily accessible whilst not being pulled across other pieces of equipment as this can limit accessibility. The cables should also be as short as possible to reduce cost and increase performance. Both electrical and optical fibre cables are restricted in how far they can be bent since this can cause stress, loss, and fatigue in the cable which may eventually,lead to down time of the network. It can often therefore be desirable to connect cables only to the rear of cards contained within a chassis in order to improve the maintainability.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Compact Peripheral Component Interconnect (cPCI) is an adaptation of the Peripheral Component Interconnect (PCI) which is an international standard specification for industrial computer applications. cPCI is often used for small, high-speed industrial computing applications where transfers occur between a number of high-speed cards. cPCI provides a way for rear cabling through the use of Rear Transition Modules (RTMs). Typically the RTM provides a connector to terminate an external cable and interface devices, recover the signal and convert it to digital format. In known modularised processing cards, an interface between an incoming signal and a hardware processor and filter is required, this is known as the interface circuit. The signal may then be converted into a digital format by the hardware processor before being transmitted to a host processor on a front card for further processing.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Typically an RTM connects to a Front processor card through a J3 or J5 connector. J3 and J5 connectors are standard connectors known in the art. However the use of these connectors is not mandated by Compact PCI and can be specific to the design of a processor card and RTM. Therefore, known RTMs can have limited functionality since they may only be compatible with one type of processor card. It is often however, desirable to have compatibility with any kind of commercially available front processor card. Since no pins are defined for power and ground in J3 and J5 connectors, known RTMs must derive power from the front processor card, but the pins used for power and ground are custom.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Another means for facilitating rear cabling can be provided by a PCI mezzanine card (PMC) which connects to a PMC site located on the front processor card. A PMC is a board that can be plugged into a standard interface on the front processor card. The hardware processing can be performed on the PMC but an RTM may still only be compatible with its mating PMC card. Both PMC and known RTMs do not necessarily support “hot-swap” technology.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">An alternative to the use of RTMs with a standard PMC card is the use of a PMC card which contains the interface circuit. The external interface to the PMC card is through the front of the card cage and whilst no RTM is required, other problems may arise with this connectivity from the use of PMC cards. For example the orientation of PMC cards, i.e. connected into a slot on the front processor card and being parallel with the card can be unfavourable to the thermal behaviour of the module since the PMC card dissipates heat and can block the air flow in the chassis which may lead to the processor overheating. Furthermore, the external connection is to the front of the card cage and often it is desirable to connect to the rear of the card cage.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Accordingly, in a first aspect, the invention provides a rear panel transition module having a compact Peripheral Component Interconnect (cPCI) input/output (I/O) bus interface for connection to a rear side of a backplane conforming to the cPCI bus standard and having a cPCI bus connector, the rear panel transition module further comprising an external connector having an input for receiving input signals, an interface circuit coupled to the external connector, and at least one processing unit coupled between the interface circuit and the cPCI I/O bus interface.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The rear panel transition module may further comprise a controller to support live insert functionality (hot-swap). The external connector may be any one of BNC, D-type or SC/FC. The at least one processing unit can perform initial filtering and/or processing of a signal input.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to a second aspect, the invention provides a transition module having an input/output (I/O) bus interface coupled to a connector for connection to a backplane having a bus connector, the transition module further comprising an external connector having an input for receiving input signals, an interface circuit coupled to the external connector, and at least one processing unit coupled between the interface circuit and the I/O bus interface.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to a another aspect, the invention provides a modularised card apparatus comprising a backplane having a rear side and a front side and conforming to the cPCI bus standard, the backplane having a cPCI bus connector, the modularised card apparatus further comprising a front processing card having a processing unit and a first cPCI input/output (I/O) bus interface for connecting to a slot on the front side of the backplane, a rear transition module comprising a second cPCI I/O bus interface for connecting to a rear slot on the rear side of the backplane, the rear transition module further comprising an external connector having an input for receiving input signals, an interface circuit coupled to the external connector, and at least one processing unit coupled between the interface circuit and the second cPCI I/O bus interface.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The front processing card conveniently has no external connection provided thereon. The cPCI bus connector on the backplane may be a feed-through connector.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The rear transition module can further comprise a resistive electrical connection between an IDSEL input on the second cPCI I/O bus interface and an appropriate address line. Assignment of interrupt signals may be carried out on the rear transition module. A resistive electrical connection may be provided on the rear transition module between an INTA# pin on the second cPCI I/O bus interface and an INTD# pin on the rear side of the backplane.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The backplane can comprise a plurality of slots on the rear side. An IDSEL input on the second cPCI I/O bus interface may be connected to an appropriate address line via a resistive electrical connection provided on the backplane The IDSEL pin on the first cPCI I/O bus interface is connected to a ground plane.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">According to a further aspect, the invention provides a modularised card apparatus comprising a backplane having a first side and a second side, the backplane having a bus connector, the modularised card apparatus further comprising a processing card having a processing unit and a first input/output (I/O) bus interface for connecting to a slot on the second side of the backplane, a transition module comprising a second I/O bus interface coupled to a connector for connecting to a slot on the first side of the backplane, the transition module further comprising an external connector having an input for receiving input signals, an interface circuit coupled to the external connector, and at least one processing unit coupled between the interface circuit and the second I/O bus interface.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Thus, the telecommunications apparatus according to at least some embodiments of the present invention, provides an external connecting means which can support “hot-swap” technology, be compatible with any commercial processor, have good thermal performance and allow cabling to the rear of the chassis.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Two embodiments of the invention will now be described, by way of example only, with reference to the accompanying drawings in which;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of an active rear transition module of a first embodiment of the invention connected to a backplane;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic diagram of the backplane of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> showing a feed-through connector;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic illustrating connections between the active rear transition module of the first embodiment of the invention and a front processor card via a backplane;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic diagram demonstrating interrupt signal assignment on the rear transition module of the first embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic diagram of an active rear transition module of a second embodiment of the invention connected to a backplane; and</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a schematic diagram illustrating connections between the active rear transition module of the second embodiment of the invention and a front processor card via a backplane.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, a first embodiment of the present invention provides a rear panel transition module <b>24</b> having a compact Peripheral Component Interconnect (CPCI) input/output (I/O) bus interface for connection with a rear side of a backplane <b>30</b>. A modularised apparatus <b>6</b> comprising the rear transition module <b>24</b>, a cPCI bus connector <b>18</b> and a front processor card <b>26</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The cPCI bus connector <b>18</b> is a standard J1 connector. The rear panel transition module <b>24</b> is a printed circuit board. (PCB) which comprises a user-defined connector <b>8</b> which is coupled to an interface circuit <b>12</b> provided on the rear panel transition module <b>24</b>. The interface circuit <b>12</b> is coupled to at least one processing unit <b>14</b> and the processing unit <b>14</b> is, in turn, coupled to a cPCI I/O bus interface <b>16</b>. The active rear transition module <b>24</b> is used for I/O connection between a telecommunications signal input <b>10</b> and a front processor card <b>26</b>. The active rear transition module <b>24</b> is provided with at least one user-defined external connector <b>8</b> for I/O connection with a telecommunications signal input <b>10</b>. The external connector <b>8</b> is therefore designed to be compatible with the carrier of the telecommunications signal. The input signal may be one of any standard telecommunications signals known in the art such as E1, T1, STM-1 or Ethernet. The input signal may therefore be transmitted over a copper twisted pair cable, coaxial cable or optical fibre. The external connector <b>8</b> may therefore be a BNC, D-type or an optical. SC/FC connector, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The external connector <b>8</b> is coupled to the interface circuit <b>12</b> on the rear panel transition module <b>24</b>. The interface circuit <b>12</b> is a standard circuit, known in the art. The interface circuit <b>12</b> is coupled to the processing unit <b>14</b>, which may perform a filtering function. The processing and filtering executed by the processing unit <b>14</b> may vary depending upon the application of the modularised apparatus <b>6</b>. However in the exemplary embodiment shown the active rear transition module <b>24</b> is used to monitor telecommunications signals within a Signalling System Seven (SS7) type network. The rear transition module <b>24</b> is provided with an input signal from a network interface, for example, E1, STM-1 or Ethernet interface, of an SS7 network. The input signal is converted from an optical to an electrical signal, if necessary, and coupled to the front processor card <b>26</b> which executes further processing of the collated message signals. The processing unit <b>14</b> is coupled to a first cPCI I/O bus interface <b>16</b>. The first cPCI interface <b>16</b> can be connected to the cPCI bus connector <b>18</b>, or J1 connector, which is provided on the backplane <b>30</b>. The cPCI front processor card <b>26</b> is provided with a second standard cPCI I/O bus interface <b>20</b> coupled between the cPCI connector <b>18</b> and a host processor unit <b>22</b> provided on the front processor card <b>26</b>, which executes the processing of the collated message signals to run network surveillance and trouble shooting applications. In this way the rear transition module <b>24</b> can be coupled to the front processor card <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The active rear transition module <b>24</b> may be configured to monitor any of E1, Ethernet, STM-1 or other standard type of telecommunications signals. The host processor unit <b>22</b> on the front card <b>26</b> may be used to process only a sample of the signalling links that may be carried by such a telecommunications signal. For example a standard E1 signal may be divided or multiplexed into <b>31</b> time slots each of which can transmit a message or portion of a data signal. A standard STM-1 signal comprises 63 E1 signals. The active rear transition module <b>24</b> can select signalling messages of interest from specific timeslots and only these specific signals will be coupled to the host processor unit <b>22</b> on the front processor card <b>26</b> for processing. The active rear transition module <b>24</b> therefore performs initial signal recovery of an STM-1 signal, converting the optical signal to an electrical signal. The processing unit <b>14</b> provided on the active rear transition module <b>24</b> also carries out deframing of the STM-1 signal to recover the tributary E1 channels. The E1 channels are also deframed or demultiplexed in order to recover and extract data from specific time slots of interest. The extracted data from individual time slots can then be reconstructed by the processing unit <b>14</b> to recover a message sequence. A message sequence of interest can then be coupled to the front processor card <b>26</b> via the cPCI I/O interface <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The cPCI bus connector <b>18</b> on the cPCI backplane <b>30</b> is used for the cPCI I/O bus interface <b>16</b> which is a 32-bit PCI bus. The cPCI bus connector <b>18</b> has pins defined for power and ground signals, allowing the rear transition module <b>24</b> to take power directly from the backplane <b>30</b>. A “hot-swap” controller on the rear transition module <b>24</b> also provides the rear transition module <b>24</b> with live insertion support or “hot-swap” capability.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The backplane <b>30</b> is designed so that the PCI bus connector <b>18</b> passes straight through from the front to the rear of the chassis. The backplane <b>30</b> connects the cPCI bus interface <b>20</b> on the front processor card <b>26</b> to the cPCI I/O interface <b>16</b> on the rear transition module <b>24</b>. The connection of the first and second cPCI I/O interface buses to the cPCI bus connector <b>18</b> on the backplane <b>30</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Some small deviations from the standard cPCI pin out allow for the PCI connection to be made by a straight through connection. This includes special routing of initialisation device select (IDSEL) and interrupt signals on the rear transition module <b>24</b>. The cPCI I/O interface <b>20</b> on the front processor card <b>26</b> is standard. The backplane <b>30</b> can contain several, for example eight, cPCI bus connectors <b>18</b>. Each cPCI bus connector <b>18</b> can connect a front processor card <b>26</b> to a single active rear transition module <b>24</b> in an adjacent rear slot via a “feed-through connector” on the backplane <b>30</b>. As there is a direct connection between front (system slot) and rear (peripheral slot), there are some rules that the rear cards must follow for certain PCI signals, which differ from the standard cPCI specification. For example, IDSEL is a PCI signal which is used to provide a unique access to each logical slot on the cPCI bus connector <b>18</b> for configuration purposes. Each slot is given a unique address by connecting one of the address lines (AD<b>31</b> through AD<b>24</b>) to each slot's IDSEL pin. The Compact PCI standard requires that the backplane <b>30</b> shall connect the IDSEL pin on each peripheral slot to the appropriate address line and that the IDSEL pin on the System (front) slot should be grounded. These are conflicting requirements when a feed-through connector is used.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic illustrating how the IDSEL signal can be connected between the active rear transition module <b>24</b> of the first embodiment of the invention and a standard front processor card <b>26</b> via the backplane <b>30</b>. On the active rear transition module <b>24</b>, the IDSEL input on the PCI interface <b>16</b> is connected to AD<b>31</b> address line through a 1 K ohm resistor R<b>1</b>. In this embodiment the resistor R<b>1</b> is provided on the active rear transition module <b>24</b>. In other embodiments it is envisaged that the IDSEL pin on the PCI interface <b>16</b> may be connected to the backplane <b>30</b> via an optional link provided on the active rear transition module <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The “feed-through” nature of the pins of the backplane <b>30</b> may make it necessary for interrupt signal assignment to be carried out on the active rear transition module <b>24</b>. The cPCI specification defines four interrupt signals, INTA# to INTD#. The backplane <b>30</b> is required to rotate the interrupt assignments through the logical board slots to provide a unique PCI interrupt to each board for the first four peripheral slots.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The active rear transition module <b>24</b> is always in the first peripheral slot (IDSEL=AD<b>31</b>). Therefore the INTA# pin on the RTM <b>24</b> should connect to the INTD# signal on the system (front) slot. However, this cannot be done on the backplane <b>30</b> of the illustrated embodiment, owing to the feed-through nature of the pins of the backplane <b>30</b>. Therefore the Interrupt assignment is done on the active rear transition module <b>24</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The INTA# signal on the active rear transition module <b>24</b> is coupled, by an optional link R<b>2</b>, to the INTD# pin on the backplane <b>30</b> as indicated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The use of an optional link R<b>2</b> offers the additional functionality that the rear transition module <b>24</b> of the present invention can be easily adapted for use with a backplane having multiple-peripheral slots. In other embodiments of the invention a number of additional optional links may be placed on the PCB rear transition module <b>24</b> to allow for adaptive connecting and increased functionality. For example an optional link between INTA# on the backplane <b>30</b> and INTA# on the PCI bus. I/O interface connector <b>16</b> can accommodate the use of a backplane with multiple peripheral slots.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">A second embodiment of the invention will now be described by way of example only. Similar reference numerals to those used to represent features of the first embodiment will be used to represent features of the second embodiment but will be raised by a factor of ‘100’. In this embodiment the backplane <b>130</b> is designed to support multiple active rear transition modules <b>124</b> on a single PCI bus connector <b>118</b>. In the second embodiment the front and rear cards are offset, so that the first and second cPCI I/O interfaces <b>120</b> and <b>116</b><i>a</i>, <b>116</b><i>b </i>are offset. This allows signals to be routed more flexibly on the PCB backplane <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows how IBSEL signals are connected in the second embodiment of the invention When a backplane <b>130</b> with multiple peripheral slots is used. The backplane <b>130</b> is connected to the IDSEL input on the rear card <b>124</b> via a 1 K ohm resistor R<b>4</b> provided on the PCB backplane <b>130</b>. An optional link R<b>3</b> may be provided on the PCB of the active rear transition module <b>124</b> between the IDSEL pin on the rear transition module <b>124</b> and the IDSEL input of the backplane <b>130</b>. The IDSEL pin on the front cPCI bus interface <b>120</b> is coupled to ground. Furthermore the optional link R<b>1</b> connected to INTD# in the first embodiment is removed and a link is provided between the INTA# pin on the backplane <b>130</b> and the INTA# pin on the rear transition module <b>124</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Although only two particular embodiments of the present invention have been described in detail, it will be apparent to one skilled in the art that various changes may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A rear panel transition module having a standard compact Peripheral Component interconnect (cPCI) input/output (I/O) bus interface coupled to a standard J1 connector for connection to a rear side of a backplane having a cPCI bus connector conforming to the cPCI bus standard, the rear panel transition module further comprising:
<claim-text>an external connector having an input for receiving input signals,</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface circuit coupled to the external connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one processing unit coupled between the interface circuit and the standard cPCI I/O bus interface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interrupt assignment link for optionally coupling one of four interrupt lines from the cPCI bus connector to an interrupt signal on the rear panel transition module.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A rear panel transition module according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a controller to support live insert functionality (hot-swap).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A rear panel transition module according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the external connector is any one of BNC, D-type or SC/FC.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A rear panel transition module according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one processing unit performs initial filtering and/or processing of a signal input.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A transition module having an input/output (I/O) bus interface coupled to a connector for connection to a backplane having a bus connector, the transition module further comprising:
<claim-text>an external connector having an input for receiving input signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface circuit coupled to the external connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one processing unit coupled between the interface circuit and the I/O bus interface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interrupt assignment link for optionally coupling one of four interrupt lines from the cPCI bus connector to an interrupt signal on the rear panel transition module.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A modularised card apparatus a backplane having a rear side and a front side and conforming to the cPCI bus standard, the backplane having a cPCI bus connector, the modularised card apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a front processing card having a processing unit and a first cPCI input/output (I/O) bus interface for connecting to a slot on the front side of the backplane; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rear transition module having:
<claim-text>a second cPCI I/O bus interface coupled to a standard J1 connector for connecting to a rear slot on the rear side of the backplane;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an external connector having an input for receiving input signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface circuit coupled to the external connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one processing unit coupled between the interface circuit and the second cPCI I/O bus interface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interrupt assignment link for optionally coupling one of four interrupt lines from the cPCI bus connector to an interrupt signal on the rear panel transition module.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A modularised card apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the front processing card has no external connection provided thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A modularised card apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the cPCI bus connector on the backplane is a feed-through connector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A modularised card apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the rear transition module further comprises a resistive electrical connection between an IDSEL input on the second cPCI I/O bus interface and an appropriate address line.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A modularised card apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein a resistive electrical connection is provided on the rear transition module between an INTA# pin on the second cPCI I/O bus interface and an INTD# pin on the rear side of the backplane.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A modularised card apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the backplane comprises a plurality of slots on the rear side.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A modularised card apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein an IDSEL input on the second cPCI I/O bus interface is connected to an appropriate address line via a resistive electrical connection provided on the backplane.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A modularised card apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the IDSEL pin on the first cPCI I/O bus interface is connected to a ground plane.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A modularised card apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a backplane having a first side and a second side, the backplane having a bus connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a processing card having a processing unit and a first input/output (I/O) bus interface for connecting to a slot on the second side of the backplane; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transition module having a second I/O bus interface coupled to a connector for connecting to a slot on the first side of the backplane, the transition module including:</claim-text>
<claim-text>an external connector having an input for receiving input signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interface circuit coupled to the external connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one processing unit coupled between the interface circuit and the second I/O bus interface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an interrupt assignment link for optionally coupling one of four interrupt lines from the cPCI connector to an interrupt signal on the rear panel transition module.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
