<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296596-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296596</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11085021</doc-number>
<date>20050321</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>229</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137801</main-classification>
<further-classification>  4676</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Water mixing single handle faucet fitted with a water inlet and outlet</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3965936</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lyon</name>
<date>19760600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>13762517</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5329958</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bosio</name>
<date>19940700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>137269</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5368071</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hsieh</name>
<date>19941100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>13762541</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5375624</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Knapp</name>
<date>19941200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>13762517</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5853023</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Orlandi et al.</name>
<date>19981200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>137271</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5857489</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chang</name>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>13762517</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6070611</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Becker</name>
<date>20000600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>1376254</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0094213</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Knapp</name>
<date>20040500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>13762517</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>1</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137801</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1376254</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  4675-678</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Mary</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taichung Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Egbert Law Offices</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Kuching International Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taichung Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Huson</last-name>
<first-name>Gregory</first-name>
<department>3753</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Schneider</last-name>
<first-name>Craig</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The water mixing single handle faucet fitted with a water inlet and outlet includes circular groove, located on the first baffle plate to accommodate the valve core, a valve core location hole, cold water inlet, hot water inlet and water outlet mounted onto the first baffle plate. The cold water inlet is connected to a cold water inlet pipe, hot water inlet connected to hot water inlet pipe, and water outlet connected to water outlet pipe on the main body. The water outlet is located nearby outflow side of the faucet while cold/hot water inlet is located at the remote side. The present invention can thus ensure an easier machining and moulding of bar copper in order to promote the rate of finished products and minimize the manufacturing cost.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="117.86mm" wi="146.81mm" file="US07296596-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="146.81mm" wi="118.11mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296596-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="184.49mm" wi="125.81mm" file="US07296596-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">RELATED U.S. APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Not applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR DEVELOPMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Not applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">REFERENCE TO MICROFICHE APPENDIX</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Not applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The present invention relates generally to a single handle water mixing faucet.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Currently, a single handle water mixing faucet is widely applied because of its ease-of-operation. However, since cold/hot water inlet is located at a frontal section and water outlet at rear section of baffle plate of the faucet (e.g. T-shaped faucet), it will likely make it difficult for moulding of baffle plate, where air pockets will be easily formed, thus leading to a higher degree of defects and manufacturing cost. Besides, considering that cold/hot water inlet is located at frontal section and bar copper is applied to machine-shaping of column faucet, pipe column of water inlet is vulnerable to puncture during machining of water outlet tube orifice, causing serious concern to a higher defective rate.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Thus, to overcome the aforementioned problems of the prior art single handle water mixing faucet, it would be an advancement in the art to provide an improved one of desirable performance.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">To this end, the present invention is directed to an improved structure of water mixing single handle faucet fitted with a water inlet and outlet, which can ensure an easier machining and moulding of bar copper in order to promote the rate of finished products and minimize the manufacturing cost.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The enhanced efficacy of the present invention is as follows: owing to the fact that water outlet <b>33</b> on the first baffle plate <b>11</b> is located nearby outflow side of the faucet while cold/hot water inlet <b>31</b>, <b>32</b> is located at the remote side, “T”-shaped faucet could be placed on “Y”-shaped second <b>12</b>, third <b>13</b> and fourth baffle plate <b>14</b> in a horizontal plane (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), and used to separate cold/hot water inlet pipe <b>41</b> <b>42</b> and outlet pipe <b>43</b> for a more convenient moulding. In the case of column faucet (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), cold/hot water inlet's pipe column will not be punctured during machining by bar copper, thereby promoting efficiently the rate of finished products and reducing considerably the manufacturing cost for a higher availability.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Although the invention has been explained in relation to its preferred embodiment, it is to be understood that many other possible modifications and variations can be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as hereinafter claimed.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a schematic view of the structure of the first embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows another schematic view of the structure of the second embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The features and the advantages of the present invention will be more readily understood upon a thoughtful deliberation of the following detailed description of a preferred embodiment of the present invention with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the present invention has offered a preferred embodiment of water mixing single handle faucet (e.g. a T-shaped faucet) fitted with an improved water inlet and outlet. A circular groove, located on the first baffle plate <b>11</b> to accommodate the valve core, comprises a valve core location hole <b>2</b>, cold water inlet <b>31</b>, hot water inlet <b>32</b> and water outlet <b>33</b> mounted onto the first baffle plate <b>11</b>. Among them, cold water inlet is connected to cold water inlet pipe <b>41</b>, hot water inlet connected to hot water inlet pipe <b>42</b>, and water outlet <b>33</b> connected to water outlet pipe <b>43</b> on the main body. Moreover, the water outlet <b>33</b> is located nearby outflow side of the faucet while cold/hot water inlet is located at the remote side.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the faucet is fitted with a second <b>12</b>, third <b>13</b> and fourth baffle plate <b>14</b> in a “Y”-shaped configuration, of which the second baffle plate <b>12</b> is placed between cold water inlet pipe <b>41</b> and hot water inlet pipe <b>42</b>, the third baffle plate <b>13</b> placed between cold water inlet pipe <b>41</b> and water outlet pipe <b>43</b>, and the fourth baffle plate <b>14</b> placed between hot water inlet pipe <b>42</b> and water outlet pipe <b>43</b>. The inner ends of second, third and fourth baffle plates are tightly bonded, while the outer ends are separately sealed into inner wall of faucet body, such that the first baffle plate <b>11</b> is tightly covered onto the second, third and fourth baffle plates.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the second preferred embodiment of the present invention is represented by a column faucet. A circular groove, located on the first baffle plate <b>11</b> to accommodate the valve core, comprises a valve core location hole <b>2</b>, cold water inlet <b>31</b>, hot water inlet <b>32</b> and water outlet <b>33</b> mounted onto the first baffle plate <b>11</b>. Among them, cold water inlet <b>31</b> is connected to cold water inlet pipe <b>41</b>, hot water inlet <b>32</b> connected to hot water inlet pipe <b>42</b>, and water outlet <b>33</b> connected to water outlet pipe <b>43</b> on the main body. And, the water outlet <b>33</b> is located nearby outflow side of the faucet while cold/hot water inlet is located at the remote side.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The cold water inlet pipe <b>41</b> is fixedly connected to cold water inlet <b>31</b> on the first baffle plate, while hot water inlet pipe <b>42</b> is fixedly connected to hot water inlet <b>32</b> on the first baffle plate.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A single-handle water mixing faucet comprising:
<claim-text>a faucet body having an inner wall, said faucet body having a water outlet pipe, said faucet body having a circular groove formed on an interior thereof, said faucet body having a cold water inlet and a hot water inlet formed therein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first baffle plate received in said circular groove, said first baffle plate being disk-shaped, said first baffle plate suitable for supporting a valve core thereon, said first baffle plate having a valve core location hole thereon, said first baffle plate having a cold water inlet hole and a hot water inlet hole and a water outlet hole formed therethrough, said cold water inlet hole being in fluid communication with said cold water inlet of said faucet body, said hot water inlet hole being in fluid communication with said hot water inlet of said faucet body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second baffle plate having an outer end sealed to said inner wall of said faucet body and extending transversely thereto, said second baffle plate extending between said hot water inlet hole and said cold water inlet hole;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third baffle plate having an outer end sealed to said inner wall of said faucet body and extending inwardly therefrom between said cold water inlet hole and said water outlet hole; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth baffle plate having an outer end sealed to said inner wall of said faucet body and extending inwardly therefrom between said hot water inlet hole and said outlet hole, an opposite end of said second baffle plate and said third baffle plate and said fourth baffle plate being tightly bonded together, said second baffle plate and said third baffle plate and said fourth baffle plate arranged in a Y-shaped configuration, said first baffle plate having a bottom surface affixed directly onto a top edge of said second baffle plate and onto a top edge of said third baffle plate and onto a top edge of said fourth baffle plate.                                                                         </claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
