<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296738-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296738</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10893313</doc-number>
<date>20040719</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-070004</doc-number>
<date>20040312</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>449</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235383</main-classification>
<further-classification>235379</further-classification>
<further-classification>235380</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">POS terminal, method of correcting a quantity, and computer-readable storage medium recording therein a program for causing a computer to correct a quantity</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6101485</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fortenberry et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>705 27</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0083944</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Duvall et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>705 21</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>SHO 57-97165</doc-number>
<date>19820600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>HEI 3-276390</doc-number>
<date>19911200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>HEI 8-83382</doc-number>
<date>19960300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>6</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235379</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235380</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235383</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235375</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>705 16</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>705 24</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>13</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>16</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050203803</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050915</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hada</last-name>
<first-name>Tomohiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Maebashi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Staas &amp; Halsey LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Fujitsu Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kawasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hess</last-name>
<first-name>Daniel</first-name>
<department>2876</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A point-of-sale (POS) terminal includes a commodity information input part for inputting commodity information on commodities; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; and a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information. The POS terminal further includes a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction in dependence on the item information stored in the storage part; a quantity correction indication part for indicating correction of the quantity; and a quantity correction part for correcting the quantity. When the correction is indicated, the quantity correction part corrects the quantity by replacing the quantity in the item information last stored in the storage part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part. The calculation part recalculates the amount of money based on the new quantity.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="143.17mm" wi="238.08mm" file="US07296738-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="239.01mm" wi="156.97mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296738-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="260.94mm" wi="166.54mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296738-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="249.34mm" wi="181.10mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296738-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="165.02mm" wi="77.30mm" file="US07296738-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="241.30mm" wi="176.28mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296738-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="255.78mm" wi="186.35mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296738-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="195.58mm" wi="67.56mm" file="US07296738-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="258.15mm" wi="185.17mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296738-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="253.75mm" wi="177.04mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296738-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="255.78mm" wi="178.73mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296738-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="126.92mm" wi="108.46mm" file="US07296738-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="95.17mm" wi="97.20mm" file="US07296738-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00013" num="00013">
<img id="EMI-D00013" he="262.21mm" wi="170.26mm" file="US07296738-20071120-D00013.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">(1) Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a point-of-sale terminal (POS terminal) for inputting a quantity for commodities involved in a transaction and inputting commodity information on the commodities, a method of correcting the quantity, and a computer-readable storage medium with a program for causing a computer to correct the quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">(2) Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In the POS terminal of a POS system for registration of transaction information on commodities, when selling a plurality of identical commodities in a transaction, the quantity of commodities is typically registered by two registration methods, a pre-declaration method and an after-declaration method.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the pre-declaration method, commodity registration is performed after the declaration of a quantity. More specifically, the quantity of commodities is first declared by inputting the quantity with a numeric key, etc., provided in the POS terminal. Then, commodity registration is performed by inputting information on the commodities (an identification number, etc.) with a bar-code reader, etc. For example, when registering (or selling) two identical commodities, a numeric key “2” is depressed and then a Multiplication (×) key is depressed. This means that the depressed numeric key is a multiplier. Next, the commodity is scanned with a bar-code reader.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In the after-declaration method, the declaration of a quantity is performed after commodity registration. For instance, when registering two identical commodities, scanning is performed with a bar-code reader, and then the numeric key “2” and Multiplication (×) key are depressed.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In the above-described POS system, there is a possibility that an operator will register an incorrect quantity. Because of this, in conventional POS systems, an incorrect quantity registered can be corrected by methods disclosed in Japanese Patent Laid-Open Nos. HEI 3-276390, HEI 8-83382, and SHO 57-97165.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">For instance, in the after-declaration method, when an operator inputs an incorrect quantity, the quantity can be corrected by inputting only a correct quantity with a numeric key and a Multiplication (×) key immediately after the incorrect input. Until the time the next commodity is scanned with a bar-code reader, an incorrect quantity can be easily corrected by inputting a correct quantity with a numeric key and a Multiplication (×) key immediately after the input of the incorrect quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">However, in the pre-declaration method, the input of a quantity through a numeric key, which is performed after scanning is performed by a bar-code reader, is handled as the declaration of a quantity for the next item. Therefore, after an item registered by an incorrect quantity is deleted, it is necessary to perform quantity declaration and commodity registration again.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">That is, when correcting an incorrect quantity registered by the pre-declaration method, the operator has to perform four steps, (1) selection of an item to be corrected, (2) deletion of the item, (3) quantity declaration (e.g., depression of a numeric key “2” and a Multiplication (×) key), and (4) commodity registration (re-registration). These four steps is a troublesome and time-consuming operation. In addition, there is a possibility that when performing commodity registration, other commodities will be registered by mistake.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In the pre-declaration method and after-declaration method, when correcting a quantity for an item registered two or more before, that item is deleted and then it is necessary to perform quantity declaration and commodity registration again. As described above, it is necessary to perform four steps, (1) selection of an item to be corrected, (2) deletion of the item, (3) quantity declaration (e.g., depression of a numeric key “2” and a Multiplication (×) key), and (4) commodity registration.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present invention has been made in view of the circumstances described above. Accordingly, it is the primary object of the present invention to provide a POS terminal, a quantity correction method, and a computer-readable medium with a quantity correction program, which are capable of correcting a quantity easily and preventing commodity misregistration from taking place during the correction.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">To achieve this end, there is provided a first point-of-sale terminal including a commodity information input part for inputting commodity information on commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction in dependence on the item information stored in the storage part; the point-of-sale terminal comprising a quantity correction indication part for indicating correction of the quantity; and a quantity correction part for correcting the quantity, when the correction is indicated by the correction indication part, by replacing the quantity in the item information last stored in the storage part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part; the calculation part recalculating the amount of money based on the new quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In accordance with the present invention, there is provided a second point-of-sale terminal including a commodity information input part for inputting commodity information on commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; and a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction in dependence on the item information stored in the storage part; the point-of-sale terminal comprising a quantity correction indication part for indicating correction of the quantity; an item selection part for selecting item information containing the quantity to be corrected, from the item information stored in the storage part; and a quantity correction part for correcting the quantity, when the correction is indicated by the correction indication part, by replacing the quantity in the item information selected by the item selection part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part; the calculation part recalculating the amount of money based on the new quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In accordance with the present invention, there is provided a first quantity correction method for use in a point-of-sale terminal which includes a commodity information input part for inputting commodity information on commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction in dependence on the item information stored in the storage part; the method comprising a quantity correction indication step of indicating correction of the quantity; and a quantity correction step of correcting the quantity, when the correction is indicated in the indication step, by replacing the quantity in the item information last stored in the storage part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part; a recalculating step of recalculating the amount of money recalculated in the calculation part based on the new quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In accordance with the present invention, there is provided a second quantity correction method for use in a point-of-sale terminal which includes a commodity information input part for inputting commodity information on commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction in dependence on the item information stored in the storage part; the method comprising a quantity correction indication step of indicating correction of the quantity; an item selection step of selecting item information containing the quantity to be corrected, from the item information stored in the storage step; and a quantity correction step of correcting the quantity, when the correction is indicated in the indication step, by replacing the quantity in the item information selected in the item selection step with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part; a recalculating step of recalculating the amount of money recalculated in the calculation part based on the new quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In accordance with the present invention, there is provided a first computer-readable storage medium recording therein a quantity correction program for causing a computer to function for use in a point-of-sale terminal which includes: a commodity information input part for inputting commodity information on commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction in dependence on the item information stored in the storage part; the program instruct the computer to function as the following: a quantity correction indication part for indicating correction of the quantity; and a quantity correction part for correcting the quantity, when the correction is indicated by the correction indication part, by replacing the quantity in the item information last stored in the storage part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part; the calculation part recalculating the amount of money based on the new quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In accordance with the present invention, there is provided a second computer-readable storage medium recording therein a quantity correction program for causing a computer to function for use in a point-of-sale terminal which includes: a commodity information input part for inputting commodity information on commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction in dependence on the item information stored in the storage part; the program instruct the computer to function as the following: a quantity correction indication part for indicating correction of the quantity; an item selection part for selecting item information containing the quantity to be corrected, from the item information stored in the storage part; and a quantity correction part for correcting the quantity, when the correction is indicated by the correction indication part, by replacing the quantity in the item information selected by the item selection part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part; function as the calculation part recalculating the amount of money based on the new quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">According to the present invention, a quantity for an item can be easily corrected and commodity misregistration can be prevented during the correction.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The present invention will be described in further detail with reference to the accompanying drawings wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram showing a POS system with a POS terminal constructed in accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic diagram showing the keyboard of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic diagram showing an example displayed on the screen of the touch panel of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flowchart showing how a quantity for an item last input is to be corrected by the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic diagram showing a second example displayed on the screen of the touch panel of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a schematic diagram showing a third example displayed on the screen of the touch panel of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flowchart showing how a quantity for an item input two or more before is to be corrected by the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a schematic diagram showing a fourth example displayed on the screen of the touch panel of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a schematic diagram showing a fifth example displayed on the screen of the touch panel of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a schematic diagram showing a sixth example displayed on the screen of the touch panel of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11A</figref>, <b>11</b>B, and <b>11</b>C are diagrams showing examples displayed on the screen of the display of the multi-item keyboard of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12A and 12B</figref> are diagrams showing examples displayed on the screen of the customer display panel of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a flowchart used to explain operation of the POS terminal shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Referring now in greater detail to the drawings and initially to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 through 3</figref>, there is shown a POS system <b>1</b> with a POS terminal constructed in accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The POS system <b>1</b> is used in a store for collecting, calculating, and analyzing various kinds of information (the quantity of commodities sold, etc.) at the point where commodities are sold. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the POS system <b>1</b> is made up of a POS terminal <b>10</b> and a POS server <b>30</b>. In an example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the POS system <b>1</b> includes one POS terminal <b>10</b> and one POS sever <b>30</b>, but the present invention is not limited to this example. For instance, the POS system <b>1</b> may include two or more POS terminal <b>10</b>, or may include a plurality of POS servers <b>30</b> according to purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The POS server <b>30</b> is connected so it can communicate with the POS terminal <b>10</b> through a communication line <b>31</b>. This POS server <b>30</b> acquires, calculates, and analyzes various kinds of information transmitted from the POS terminal <b>10</b>. The POS server <b>30</b> also manages an item master <b>32</b> that registers information, such as a unit price, an item name, etc., for commodities handled in stores, and further transmits that information to the POS terminal <b>10</b> through the communication line <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The POS terminal <b>10</b> is installed in a store, for customer checkout and acquiring and registering various kinds of information on the transaction. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the POS terminal <b>10</b> is equipped with a bar-code reader (a commodity information input part and a quantity input part) <b>11</b>, a keyboard (a quantity input part, a quantity correction indication part, and an item selection part) <b>12</b>, an item information list memory part (storage part) <b>13</b>, a quantity correction part <b>14</b>, a calculation part <b>15</b>, and a customer display panel <b>16</b>, a touch panel (an item selection part and a quantity correction indication part) <b>17</b>, an input control part <b>18</b>, an output control part <b>19</b>, a receipt printer <b>20</b>, a journal printer <b>21</b>, and a registration part <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The bar-code reader <b>11</b> inputs or registers commodity information on commodities involved in a transaction. More specifically, the bar-code reader <b>11</b> acquires commodity information by scanning a bar code printed on a commodity and sends the acquired commodity information to the registration part <b>22</b> (described later). Note that the means to input commodity information is not limited to the bar-code reader <b>11</b>. The input means may be modified within the scope of the present invention. For example, an operator may input a commodity code with the keyboard <b>12</b> (described in detail later).</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The keyboard <b>12</b> inputs a quantity for commodities involved in a transaction. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the keyboard <b>12</b> is equipped with numeric keys, a Correction key, a Clear key <b>123</b>, a Deposit/Total key, a Quantity Correction key (which corresponds to a quantity correction indication part) <b>121</b>, a Multiplication (×) key <b>122</b>, etc. An operator causes the POS terminal <b>10</b> to perform various kinds of processing by selectively depressing these keys when necessary.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In the POS terminal <b>10</b>, the input of the quantity of sold commodities (a quantity for an item) by the keyboard <b>12</b> is performed by selecting a numeric key “n” (where n is a natural number) indicative of a quantity and then depressing the Multiplication (×) key <b>122</b> indicating that a plurality of commodities were sold.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> of the keyboard <b>12</b> is employed when an operator corrects a quantity (total-number). If the operator depresses the Quantity Correction key, the quantity correction part <b>14</b> corrects a quantity, as described in detail later. Note that the Quantity Correction key of the keyboard <b>12</b> will hereinafter be represented as the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> (which corresponds to a quantity correction indication part).</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the POS terminal <b>10</b>, when registering or selling commodities, the input of the quantity by the keyboard <b>12</b> is performed only when a plurality of identical commodities are registered at a time. In the case where a quantity is 1, it is not necessary to depress the numeric key “1” and Multiplication (×) key of the keyboard <b>2</b>. When one commodity is registered through the bar-code reader <b>11</b> without using the keyboard <b>12</b>, a quantity “1” is automatically set as the initial value. In addition, information on a quantity input through the keyboard <b>12</b> is delivered to the registration part <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In the POS system <b>10</b>, when selling a plurality of identical commodities, they may be registered by either the pre-declaration method (which performs commodity registration after the declaration of a quantity) or the after-declaration method (which performs the declaration of a quantity after commodity registration). By previously selecting one of the two methods, the input manipulation can be performed with the selected method.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">In the preferred embodiment, a description will hereinafter be given in the case where a quantity and commodities are registered by the pre-declaration method. That is, in the POS system <b>10</b>, by inputting a quantity through the keyboard <b>12</b> and then performing commodity registration with the bar-code reader <b>11</b>, information on an item (item information) is registered.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">More specifically, when registering a plurality of identical commodities in one transaction, a numeric key “n” indicative of a quantity is first selected in the keyboard <b>12</b>. Then, the Multiplication (×) key <b>122</b> is depressed. Thereafter, commodity registration is performed by the bar-code reader <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Note that the keyboard <b>12</b> may be replaced with a multi-item keyboard with a display for presenting an item name, a quantity, a total price, and a message to an operator (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11A to 11C</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">In dependence on the commodity information scanned by the bar-code reader <b>11</b>, the registration part <b>22</b> acquires item information on that commodity and registers it as item list information in the item information list memory part <b>13</b>. More specifically, the registration part <b>22</b> acquires item information (an item name, a unit price, etc.) by referring to the item master <b>32</b> of the POS server <b>30</b> in dependence on the commodity code (commodity information) scanned by the bar-code reader <b>11</b>. In addition, when a quantity is input through the keyboard <b>12</b> before a commodity code is scanned by the bar-code reader <b>11</b>, the registration part <b>22</b> registers the input number in the item information list memory part <b>13</b>. On the other hand, when no quantity is input through the keyboard <b>12</b>, the registration part <b>22</b> registers <b>1</b> in the item information list memory part <b>13</b>. At this time, the input number or 1 is registered as item list information so that it is correlated with the above-described item name and unit price.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The registration part <b>22</b> further sets different item numbers to item information registered in one transaction. With these different item numbers, specific item information can be selected in one transaction. That is, for example, if an item number is input through the keyboard <b>12</b>, the item information specified by the item number can be selected from the item information stored in the item information list memory part <b>13</b>. Thus, the keyboard <b>12</b> also functions as an item selection part.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The item information list memory part <b>13</b> stores commodity information and a quantity, input through the bar-code reader <b>11</b> and keyboard <b>12</b>, as item information. This item information list memory part <b>13</b> is constructed of a memory device such as a random access memory, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The item information list memory part <b>13</b> generates and stores an item information list, in which a quantity is correlated with commodity information (a commodity code, an item name, a unit price, etc.) for all commodities registered in one transaction. In the item information list memory part <b>13</b>, many pieces of item information on all commodities registered in at least one transaction are stored in a time-series as an item information list. Note that there are cases where item information registered in that item information list will hereinafter be referred to as item list information.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">And the registration of item information into the item information list memory part <b>13</b> is controlled by the registration part <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The touch panel <b>17</b>, in addition to commodity information and a quantity input through the bar-code reader <b>11</b> and keyboard <b>12</b>, presents the content of the item information list registered in the item information list memory part <b>13</b> to an operator, and allows the operator to send signals to the POS terminal <b>10</b> by touching an area on the screen with a finger, pencil, or other object.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">For instance, in an example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, commodity “A” of unit price 500 yen is registered as item list information, and “Item Name,” “Unit Price,” “Quantity,” “Discount Total,” “Total Price,” “Total Amount,” etc., are displayed as a list on the touch panel <b>17</b>. Thus, in the touch panel <b>17</b>, item information stored in the item information list memory part <b>13</b> is displayed as an item information list. And the operator is able to confirm commodity registration by viewing the information displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">By touching item information where a quantity is to be corrected, the operator is also able to select the specific item information from the item information list displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>. Thus, the touch panel <b>17</b> also functions as an item information selection part that allows an operator to select item information where a quantity is to be corrected, from the item information list displayed on the screen. Note that the item information selected in this way is delivered to the quantity correction part <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Also, in the touch panel <b>17</b>, keys for executing various functions are displayed on the screen. In the example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, there are disposed keys for executing “Journal Inquiry,” “Stop,” “Customer,” “Discount,” “% Discount,” “Price Confirmation,” “Quantity Correction,” “Correction/Deletion,” and “Page Switching” on the bottom of the screen. And by touching these keys displayed on the screen when necessary, the operator is able to execute each function.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Note that the “Quantity Correction” key displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b> will hereinafter be represented as a Quantity Correction key <b>171</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">In the POS terminal <b>10</b>, if the operator selects the Quantity Correction key <b>171</b>, the quantity correction part <b>14</b> corrects a quantity, as described in detail later. Note that in the POS terminal <b>10</b>, when commodity information is registered by the bar-code reader <b>11</b>, the item information on the commodity, last registered, has been selected. Therefore, if the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> or Quantity Correction key <b>171</b> is selected in this state, the quantity correction part <b>14</b> corrects a quantity for the item information on the commodity last registered. Also, when the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> or Quantity Correction key <b>171</b> is selected in the state where a specific item is selected on the touch panel <b>17</b>, the quantity correction part <b>14</b> corrects a quantity for the item information selected on the touch panel <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">If the Correction/Deletion key is selected in the state where specific item information is selected on the touch panel <b>17</b>, the selected item information can be deleted. This makes it possible to register item information from the beginning in the same manner as the quantity correction method used in conventional POS terminals.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The quantity correction part <b>14</b> is used for correcting a quantity on the item information list stored in the item information list memory part <b>13</b>. Therefore, when the correction of a quantity is selected by the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> or Quantity Correction key <b>171</b>, a quantity on the item information list selected through the touch panel <b>17</b> is replaced with another quantity newly input through the keyboard <b>12</b>. In this way, the selected quantity through the touch panel <b>17</b> is corrected. That new quantity is correlated with the commodity information of the selected item information and is stored in the item information list memory part <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">In dependence on item information stored in the item information list memory part <b>13</b>, the calculation part <b>15</b> calculates an account of money involved in the transaction. For instance, the calculation part <b>15</b> calculates a total price for each commodity by multiplying a unit price by a quantity, or calculates a total amount by summing up the total prices. In the POS terminal <b>10</b>, when a quantity is corrected by the quantity correction part <b>14</b>, the calculation part <b>15</b> recalculates the total price and total amount in dependence on the corrected quantity. Note that the calculation (or recalculation) of the total price and total account by the calculation part <b>15</b> is performed, for example, when the Multiplication (×) key <b>122</b> is depressed after the input of a numeric key indicative of a quantity.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">In the POS terminal <b>10</b>, the functions of the above-described registration part <b>22</b>, quantity correction part <b>14</b>, and calculation part <b>15</b> are realized by executing a program (a business application program, a quantity correction program, etc.) with a central processing unit (CPU) installed in the POS terminal <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Note that the program (a quantity correction program, etc.) for realizing the functions of the registration part <b>22</b>, quantity correction part <b>14</b>, and calculation part <b>15</b> is provided in a form recorded on a computer-readable medium such as flexible disks, CD-ROM, CD-R, CD-R/W, DVD, DVD-R, DVD-R/W, magnetic disks, optical disks, magneto-optic disks, etc. And the computer reads out the program from the computer-readable medium and transfers it to an internal storage device or external storage device. Also, by previously storing the program in a storage device such as magnetic disks, optical disks, magneto-optic disks, etc., it may be sent from the storage device to the computer through a communication path.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">When realizing the functions of the registration part <b>22</b>, quantity correction part <b>14</b>, and calculation part <b>15</b>, the program stored in an internal storage device (e.g., the RAM or ROM installed in the POS terminal <b>10</b> of the preferred embodiment) is carried out by the microprocessor of the computer (e.g., the CPU of the printer of the preferred embodiment). At this time, the computer may carry out the program stored in the storage device by reading out the program from the device.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">In the preferred embodiment, the aforementioned computer includes hardware and an operating system (OS) and refers to hardware that operates under control of the OS. Also, in the case where hardware can be operated by an application program alone without the OS, the hardware itself corresponds to the computer. The hardware has at least a microprocessor such as a CPU, and means for reading out computer programs from a storage medium. In the preferred embodiment, the POS terminal <b>10</b> has the function of the computer.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">The above-described storage medium in the preferred embodiment, in addition to the aforementioned flexible disks, CD-ROM, CD-R, CD-R/W, DVD, DVD-R, DVD-R/W, magnetic disks, optical disks, and magneto-optical disks, may also include IC cards, ROM cartridges, magnetic tape, punch cards, internal storage media for computers (memory such as RAM and ROM), external storage media, and computer-readable media such as a print with a bar code.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The customer display panel <b>16</b> displays to a customer the commodity information read through the bar-code reader <b>11</b> or transaction information such as a quantity input through the keyboard <b>12</b>, and is constructed of a liquid crystal display, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The receipt printer <b>20</b> prints various kinds of transaction information on receipt paper that is given to a customer. The journal printer <b>21</b> prints various kinds of transaction information on journal paper. The output control part <b>19</b> controls data that is output to the customer display panel <b>16</b>, touch panel <b>17</b>, receipt printer <b>20</b>, and journal printer <b>21</b>. The input control part <b>18</b> controls the data input from the bar-code reader <b>11</b>, keyboard <b>12</b>, and touch panel <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">In the POS terminal <b>10</b> constructed as described above, a method of correcting a quantity for an item last input will be described according to a flowchart (steps A<b>10</b> to A<b>80</b>) shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>5</b>, and <b>6</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref> show examples displayed on the screen of the touch panel <b>17</b> of the POS terminal <b>10</b>, respectively. In an example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a quantity “1” is registered for commodity “A” by mistake and is corrected to a correct quantity “5.”</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">When registering the transaction of commodity A in the POS terminal <b>10</b>, the operator inputs a numeric key “1” by mistake (step A<b>10</b>). Next, the Multiplication “×” key is depressed and input (step A<b>20</b>). Thereafter, commodity A is scanned by the bar-code reader <b>11</b> (step A<b>30</b>), and the registration part <b>22</b> registers the commodity information and quantity for commodity A in the item information list memory part <b>13</b> as the item information. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the item information is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">In the state after the registration of the commodity information through the bar-code reader <b>11</b>, the item information on commodity A last registered has been selected (step A<b>40</b>). In this state, if the operator selects the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> or Quantity Correction key <b>171</b> (step A<b>50</b>), a quantity is corrected for the information on the item last registered. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a quantity input guidance, such as “Please correct the quantity”, is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>. In this way, the quantity for the item information on commodity A can be corrected.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">If the operator inputs a correct quantity “5” with the numeric key “5” of the keyboard <b>12</b> in accordance with the quantity input guidance (step A<b>60</b>) and then depresses the “×” key (step A<b>70</b>), the quantity for commodity A is corrected by the quantity correction part <b>14</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, item list information with the corrected quantity is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>. That is, the calculation part <b>15</b> recalculates the total price and total amount, using the corrected quantity. The result of recalculation is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>. Thereafter, the operator scans the next commodity “B” with the bar-code reader <b>11</b> (step A<b>80</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">For an item input two or more before, the quantity correction method will be described according to a flowchart (steps B<b>10</b> to B<b>90</b>) shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 to 12</figref>. In the following description, the keyboard <b>12</b> is assumed to be a multi-item keyboard with a display. Also, the information displayed on the screen of the multi-item keyboard will be described together.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">In an example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a quantity “5” is registered for commodity A by mistake and is corrected to a correct quantity “10” after commodity B is registered.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">That is, when registering the transaction of commodity A in the POS terminal <b>10</b>, the operator depresses and inputs a numeric key “5” by mistake (step B<b>10</b>). Next, the “×” key is depressed and input (step B<b>20</b>). Thereafter, commodity A is scanned by the bar-code reader <b>11</b> (step B<b>30</b>), and the registration part <b>22</b> registers the commodity information and quantity for commodity A in the item information list memory part <b>13</b> as the item information.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Next, if the operator registers commodity information on commodity B with the bar-code reader <b>11</b> (step B<b>40</b>), the registration part <b>22</b> registers a quantity “1” in the item information list memory part <b>13</b> as the item information on commodity B.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">If the operator selects the item information on commodity A from the list displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b> (step B<b>50</b>), item list information is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b> with the item information on the commodity “A” being selected, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. At this time, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11A</figref>, the item information on the selected commodity A (an item name and a quantity), the total price, and a guidance for the operator are displayed on the screen of the multi-item keyboard. Also, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12A</figref>, the item name and total price for commodity B registered last are displayed on the customer display panel <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">In this state, if the operator selects the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> or Quantity Correction key <b>171</b> (step B<b>60</b>), a quantity can be corrected for the item information being selected. Therefore, as shown in FIG. <b>9</b>, a quantity input guidance, such as “Please correct the quantity”, will be displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>. Also, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11B</figref>, a quantity input guidance, such as “Please correct the quantity”, will be displayed on the screen of the multi-item keyboard. That is, for the item information on commodity A selected in step B<b>50</b>, the quantity can be corrected.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">If the operator inputs a correct quantity “10” with the numeric keys “1” and “0” of the keyboard <b>12</b> in accordance with the quantity input guidance (step B<b>70</b>) and then depresses the “×” key (step B<b>80</b>), the quantity for commodity A is corrected by the quantity correction part <b>14</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, item list information with the corrected quantity is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>. That is, the calculation part <b>15</b> recalculates the total price and total amount, using the corrected quantity. The result of recalculation is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>, screen of the multi-item keyboard, and each screen of the customer display panel. Thereafter, the operator is able to return to the operation of registering other commodities. When all commodities are registered, the transaction is completed through customer checkout.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">Also, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11C</figref>, the item information after correction is displayed on the screen of the multi-item keyboard. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12B</figref>, the item information on commodity A after correction is also displayed on the customer display panel <b>16</b>. Thereafter, the operator scans the next C commodity with the bar-code reader <b>11</b> (step B<b>90</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Next, operation of the POS terminal <b>10</b> will be described according to a flowchart (steps C<b>10</b> to C<b>150</b>) shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">When performing a new transaction in the POS terminal <b>10</b>, the registration part <b>22</b> performs initialization by setting <b>1</b> to the item number (step C<b>10</b>) and shifts to an input waiting state (step C<b>20</b>). When a numeric value is input with a numeric key of the keyboard <b>11</b> (see the route labeled “Numeric Key” in step C<b>20</b>), the registration part <b>22</b> judges that a quantity has been declared, and acquires the input value represented by the numeric key as the quantity (step C<b>100</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">Thereafter, if a commodity is scanned with the bar-code reader <b>11</b> (step C<b>30</b>), the registration part <b>22</b> performs the retrieval of commodity information (item information) such as an item name and a unit price, by referring to the item master <b>32</b> of the POS server <b>30</b> in dependence on the commodity code read with the bar-code reader <b>11</b> (step C<b>40</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">The registration part <b>22</b> registers the acquired item information in the item information list memory part <b>13</b> so that it is correlated with the item number (step C<b>50</b>). The value of the item number is incremented by 1 (step C<b>60</b>), and the item list information is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b> (step C<b>70</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">The calculation part <b>15</b> calculates the total prices and total amount for commodities involved in a transaction (step C<b>80</b>). The price information is displayed on the touch panel <b>17</b>, the customer display panel <b>16</b>, and the display of the multi-item keyboard (step C<b>90</b>), and the operation of the POS terminal <b>10</b> returns to step C<b>20</b>. Note that the total amount calculated by the calculation part <b>15</b> in step C<b>80</b> is the sum of the total prices calculated by multiplying a unit price by a quantity for each item.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">On the other hand, when a commodity is scanned with the bar-code reader <b>11</b> (see the route labeled “Scanning” in step C<b>20</b>), the registration part <b>22</b> sets a quantity “1”. Next, step C<b>30</b> is carried out.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">When specific item information is selected by inputting an item number through the touch panel <b>17</b> or keyboard <b>12</b> (see the route labeled “Item Selection” in step C<b>20</b>), the selected item information is acquired (step C<b>110</b>). Thereafter, if the correction of a quantity is declared through the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> or <b>171</b>, a numeric value (input value) input through a numeric key of the keyboard <b>12</b> is acquired as a corrected quantity by the quantity correction part <b>14</b> (step C<b>120</b>). For the item information selected in step C<b>110</b>, a correction is made by replacing the quantity with the corrected quantity. In this way, a change in item list information is made (step C<b>130</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">Note that the above-described steps C<b>110</b> to C<b>130</b> correspond to the aforementioned steps A<b>40</b> to A<b>70</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> or steps B<b>50</b> to B<b>90</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">Thereafter, the last item number is set to the item number (step C<b>140</b>), and step C<b>70</b> is carried out.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">When a key indicative of the completion of a transaction is input (see the route labeled “Transaction Completion” in step C<b>20</b>), the POS terminal <b>10</b> performs various processes involved in the transaction completion such as the printing of a receipt by the receipt printer <b>20</b>, printing of journal paper by the journal printer <b>21</b>, and customer checkout (step C<b>150</b>). The operation of the POS terminal <b>10</b> returns to step C<b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">Thus, according to the POS terminal <b>10</b> of the preferred embodiment of the present invention, when a quantity is corrected for item list information registered last, the quantity can be corrected by inputting only a corrected quantity through the keyboard <b>12</b>, etc., without rescanning the commodity with the bar-code reader <b>11</b>. This renders it possible for operator to handle the POS terminal <b>10</b> easily and can enhance the operation efficiency of the POS terminal <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">In addition, in a transaction performed by the POS terminal <b>10</b>, even when a quantity is corrected for an item registered two or more before, it is corrected by selecting an item to be corrected with the touch panel <b>17</b> or keyboard <b>12</b> and depressing the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> or <b>171</b>. That is, a quantity can be corrected by inputting only a corrected quantity through the keyboard <b>12</b>, etc., without rescanning the commodity with the bar-code reader <b>11</b>. Therefore, the operator is able to handle the POS terminal <b>10</b> easily and the operation efficiency of the POS terminal <b>10</b> can be enhanced.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">Furthermore, since it is not necessary to rescan a commodity with the bar-code reader <b>11</b> when correcting a quantity for the commodity, commodity misregistration is difficult to occur. Thus, reliability can also be enhanced.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">Although the preferred embodiment has been described with reference to the case where a quantity and commodities are registered by the pre-declaration method, the quantity correction method of the present invention may be applied when a quantity and commodities are registered by the after-declaration method. That is, in a transaction performed by the POS terminal <b>10</b>, when correcting a quantity for an item input two or more before, item information to be corrected is first selected with the touch panel <b>17</b>. Then, a signal indicative of quantity correction is input through the Quantity Correction key <b>121</b> or <b>171</b>. Next, a corrected quantity is input through the keyboard <b>12</b>. In this way, a quantity can be corrected by inputting only a corrected quantity through the keyboard <b>12</b> without rescanning a commodity with the bar-code reader <b>11</b>. Thus, as with the preferred embodiment, the operator is able to handle the POS terminal <b>10</b> easily and the operation efficiency of the POS terminal <b>10</b> can be enhanced.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">While the present invention has been described with reference to the preferred embodiment thereof, the invention is not to be limited to the details given herein, but may be modified within the scope of the invention hereinafter claimed.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">For example, in the preferred embodiment, for various kinds of input operations through the keyboard <b>12</b> or touch panel <b>17</b>, the input operation last performed may be cancelled by depressing the CLEAR key <b>123</b> immediately after the input operation.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">Note that if the preferred embodiment of the present invention is disclosed, it is possible for those skilled in this art to carry out and manufacture the POS terminal, the quantity correction method, the computer-readable medium with a quantity correction program, made in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">And the POS terminal, the quantity correction method, and the computer-readable medium can be summarized as follows.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A point-of-sale terminal of pre-declaration type, which performs commodity registration after a declaration of a quantity when selling a plurality of identical commodities, including: a scanner for inputting commodity information for commodities involved in a transaction as a commodity information input part; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction depending on the item information stored in said storage part,
<claim-text>said point-of-sale terminal comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a quantity correction indication part for indicating correction of the quantity; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a quantity correction part for correcting the quantity, when the correction is indicated by said correction indication part, by replacing the quantity in the item information last stored in the storage part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said calculation part recalculating the amount of money based on the new quantity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A point-of-sale terminal including: a scanner for inputting commodity information for commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction depending on the item information stored in said storage part,
<claim-text>said point-of-sale terminal comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a quantity correction indication part for indicating correction of the quantity;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an item selection part for selecting item information containing the quantity to be corrected, from the item information stored in said storage part; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a quantity correction part for correcting the quantity, when the correction is indicated by said correction indication part, by replacing the quantity in the item information selected by said item selection part with another quantity newly input by said quantity input part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said calculation part recalculating the amount of money based on the new quantity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A quantity correction method for use in a point-of-sale terminal of pre-declaration type, which performs commodity registration after a declaration of quantity when selling a plurality of identical commodities, which includes: a scanner for inputting commodity information for commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction depending on the item information stored in the storage part;
<claim-text>said method comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>indicating correction of the quantity; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>correcting the indicated quantity by replacing the quantity in the item information last stored in the storage part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>recalculating the amount of money calculated in the calculation part based on the newly input quantity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A quantity correction method for use in a point-of-sale terminal which includes: a scanner for inputting commodity information for commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction depending on the item information stored in the storage part;
<claim-text>said method comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>indicating correction of the quantity;</claim-text>
<claim-text>selecting item information containing the indicated quantity to be corrected, from the item information stored in said storage part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>correcting the quantity by replacing the quantity in the selected item information with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>recalculating the amount of money calculated in the calculation part based on the newly input quantity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A computer-readable storage medium recording therein a quantity correction program for causing a computer to function for use in a point-of-sale terminal of pre-declaration type, which performs commodity registration after a declaration of a quantity when selling a plurality of identical commodities, which includes: a scanner for inputting commodity information for commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for the commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; and a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction depending on the item information stored in the storage part,
<claim-text>said program instructing the computer to perform a method comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>indicating correction of the quantity; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>correcting the indicated quantity by replacing the quantity in the item information last stored in the storage part with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said calculation part recalculating the amount of money based on the newly input quantity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A computer-readable storage medium recording therein a quantity correction program for causing a computer to function for use in a point-of-sale terminal which includes: a scanner for inputting commodity information on commodities involved in a transaction; a quantity input part for inputting a quantity for said commodities; a storage part for storing the quantity and the commodity information, as item information; a calculation part for calculating an amount of money involved in the transaction depending on the item information stored in the storage part,
<claim-text>said program instructing the computer to perform a method comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>indicating correction of the quantity;</claim-text>
<claim-text>selecting item information containing the indicated quantity to be corrected, from the item information stored in the storage part; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>correcting said quantity by replacing the quantity in the selected item information with another quantity newly input by the quantity input part;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said calculation part recalculating the amount of money based on the newly input quantity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
