<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296887-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296887</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11519609</doc-number>
<date>20060912</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351 44</main-classification>
<further-classification>  2449</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Windproof glasses</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5394567</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Vatterott</name>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>  2449</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6062688</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Vinas</name>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351 47</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>8</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351 44</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351 41</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351111</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351158</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351 62</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  2426</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  2431</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  2 13</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  2449</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hsiung</last-name>
<first-name>Seu-Yao</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Pelton, Esq.</last-name>
<first-name>William E.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Cooper &amp; Dunham LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>A Plus La Mode International, Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Dang</last-name>
<first-name>Hung Xuan</first-name>
<department>2873</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A pair of windproof glasses has a frame assembly and a windproof shield assembly. The frame assembly has a frame, two lenses, two legs and at least two first engaging elements embedded in the frame. The windproof shield assembly mounted detachably on the frame assembly and has two windproof shields mounted detachably on sides of the frame. Each windproof shield has at least one engaging element detachably engaging respectively with at least one of the at least two first engaging elements with a magnetic force. A wearer may quickly attach the windproof shields to the frame without sequentially align the first and second engaging elements.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="121.67mm" wi="308.69mm" file="US07296887-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="165.27mm" wi="156.80mm" file="US07296887-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="247.57mm" wi="171.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296887-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="169.67mm" wi="155.79mm" file="US07296887-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="251.63mm" wi="165.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296887-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="173.40mm" wi="152.06mm" file="US07296887-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to glasses, and more particularly to a pair of windproof glasses that can be assembled and disassembled quickly.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Glasses such as nearsighted glasses, reading glasses and sunglasses are used widely in the world to improve people's vision or shield their eyes from the sunlight.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Furthermore, windproof glasses have been developed to prevent people's eyes from wind and dust.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a pair of conventional windproof glasses has two eye frames (<b>90</b>), two lenses, two legs (<b>91</b>) and a two windproof shields (<b>93</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The eye frames (<b>90</b>) are connected with each other and each eye frame (<b>90</b>) has an opening, an upper mounting tab (<b>901</b>) and a lower mounting tab. The opening is defined through the eye frame (<b>90</b>). The upper mounting tab (<b>901</b>) is formed and extends from the eye frame (<b>90</b>) and has a pin hole defined through the upper mounting tab (<b>901</b>). The lower mounting tab is formed and extends from the eye frame (<b>90</b>) below the upper mounting tab (<b>901</b>) and has a pin hole defined through the lower mounting tab.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The lenses are mounted respectively in the openings in the eye frames (<b>90</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The legs (<b>91</b>) are pivotally mounted respectively on the eye frames (<b>90</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The windproof shields (<b>93</b>) are made of soft material, are detachably mounted respectively on the eye frames (<b>90</b>) and each windproof shield (<b>93</b>) has two mounting pins (<b>931</b>). The mounting pins (<b>931</b>) are mounted on the windproof shield (<b>93</b>) and are detachably mounted respectively in the pin holes in the upper mounting tab (<b>901</b>) and the lower mounting tab on a corresponding eye frame (<b>90</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">However, the upper mounting tabs (<b>901</b>) and the lower mounting tabs extending toward and pressing against a wearer's face causes the wearer uncomfortable and event hurts the wearer's face.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Furthermore, the mounting pins (<b>931</b>) and pin holes in the mounting tabs are too little so the wearer have to pay much attention to mount each mounting pin (<b>931</b>) in a corresponding pin hole when assembling the windproof shields (<b>93</b>) to the eye frames (<b>90</b>). Therefore, assembling the windproof shields (<b>93</b>) to the eye frames (<b>90</b>) wastes time.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">To overcome the shortcomings, the present invention provides a pair of windproof glasses to mitigate or obviate the aforementioned problems.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The main objective of the invention is to provide a pair of windproof glasses that can be assembled and disassembled quickly.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A pair of windproof glasses has a frame assembly and a windproof shield assembly. The frame assembly has a frame, two lenses, two legs and at least two first engaging elements embedded in the frame. The windproof shield assembly mounted detachably on the frame assembly and has two windproof shields mounted detachably on sides of the frame. Each windproof shield has at least one engaging element detachably engaging respectively with at least one of the at least two first engaging elements with a magnetic force.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Other objectives, advantages and novel features of the invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description when taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a first embodiment of a pair of windproof glasses in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a partially exploded perspective view of the pair of the windproof glasses in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view of a second embodiment of the pair of the windproof glasses in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a partially exploded perspective view of the pair of the windproof glasses in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a perspective view of a pair of conventional windproof glasses in accordance with the prior art.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 3</figref>, a pair of windproof glasses in accordance with the present invention comprises a frame assembly (<b>10</b>) and a windproof shield assembly (<b>20</b>, <b>20</b><i>a</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">With further reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 4</figref>, the frame assembly (<b>10</b>) has a frame, at least one lens (<b>12</b>), two legs (<b>13</b>) and at least two first engaging elements (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The frame has two opposite sides, a front outer surface (<b>17</b>) and a rear inner surface (<b>16</b>) and may have two lens frame segments (<b>11</b>). In first and second embodiments of the pair of the windproof glasses, the frame (<b>12</b>) has two lens frame segments (<b>11</b>) connected to each other through a connection segment and each lens frame segments (<b>11</b>) has an outside.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The at least one lens (<b>12</b>) is mounted on the frame. In the first and second embodiments of the pair of the windproof glasses, the frame assembly (<b>10</b>) has two lenses (<b>12</b>) mounted respectively on the lens frame segments (<b>11</b>) of the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The legs (<b>13</b>) are mounted respectively on the sides of the frame and may be mounted respectively on the outsides of the two lens frame segments (<b>11</b>). Each leg (<b>13</b>) has a proximal end and a distal end. The proximal end connects to one of the sides of the frame. The distal end is opposite to the proximal end.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The at least two first engaging elements (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>) are made of magnets or metal, are embedded in the frame. In the first embodiment of the pair of the windproof glasses, the frame assembly (<b>10</b>) has two side sets of at least one first engaging element (<b>15</b>) embedded respectively in the lens frame segments (<b>11</b>) of the frame. In the second embodiment of the pair of the windproof glasses, the frame assembly (<b>10</b>) has two side sets of at least one first engaging element (<b>15</b><i>a</i>) embedded respectively in the lens frame segments (<b>11</b>) and a central set of at least one first engaging elements (<b>15</b><i>a</i>) embedded in the connection segment of the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The windproof shield assembly (<b>20</b>, <b>20</b><i>a</i>) is mounted detachably on the frame assembly (<b>10</b>) and has two windproof shields (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) and may have a connection bracket (<b>27</b>) and a face pad (<b>28</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The windproof shields (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) are made of soft material such as fabric, rubber and plastic and are detachably mounted respectively on the sides of the frame to prevent wind and dust. Each windproof shield (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) has an outer surface (<b>217</b>), an inner surface (<b>216</b>), an attachment section and at least one second engaging element (<b>25</b>) and may have a mounting hole (<b>211</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The attachment section detachably abuts the rear inner surface (<b>16</b>) of the frame instead of the front outer surface (<b>17</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The at least one second engaging element (<b>25</b>) is embedded in the attachment section of the windproof shield (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) and detachably engages respectively with at least one of the at least two first engaging elements (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>) on the frame with an magnetic attractive force. Each second engaging element (<b>25</b>) is made of metal when each corresponding first engaging element (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>) is a magnet, or is a magnet when each corresponding first engaging element (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>) is made of metal or a magnet. In the first and second embodiments, that at least one second engaging element (<b>25</b>) detachably engages respectively with the at least one first engaging element (<b>15</b>) of a corresponding side set on the frame.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The mounting hole (<b>211</b>) is defined through the windproof shield (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) and allows a corresponding leg (<b>13</b>) to extend through the mounting hole (<b>211</b>). The distal end of the leg (<b>13</b>) extends backward into the outer surface (<b>217</b>) of the windproof shield (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) and then extends out of the inner surface (<b>216</b>) of the windproof shield (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) when the leg (<b>13</b>) extends through the mounting hole (<b>211</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In the second embodiment of the pair of the windproof glasses, the connection bracket (<b>28</b>) is connected to the windproof shields (<b>21</b><i>a</i>), is mounted detachably on the frame of the frame assembly (<b>10</b>) and has at least one second engaging element (<b>25</b>) embedded in the connection bracket (<b>28</b>) and detachably engaging respectively with the at least one first engaging element (<b>15</b><i>a</i>) of the central set. The face pad (<b>28</b>) is made of resilient material such as foam and is mounted on the connection bracket (<b>27</b>) to softly touch a wearer's face.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Because the first and second engaging elements (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>, <b>25</b>) engages with each other through a magnetic attractive force, a wearer may quickly attach the windproof shields (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) to the frame without sequentially align the first engaging element (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>) with the second engaging elements (<b>25</b>). Furthermore, the first and second engaging elements (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>, <b>25</b>) are embedded in the frame and windproof shields (<b>21</b>, <b>21</b><i>a</i>) instead of protruding out so the wearer may safely wear the pair of the windproof glasses without being hurt by the first and second engaging elements (<b>15</b>, <b>15</b><i>a</i>, <b>25</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Even though numerous characteristics and advantages of the present invention have been set forth in the foregoing description, together with details of the structure and function of the invention, the disclosure is illustrative only. Changes may be made in the details, especially in matters of shape, size, and arrangement of parts within the principles of the invention to the full extent indicated by the broad general meaning of the terms in which the appended claims are expressed.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A pair of windproof glasses comprising:
<claim-text>a frame assembly having
<claim-text>a frame having two opposite sides, a front outer surface and a rear inner surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one lens;</claim-text>
<claim-text>two legs mounted respectively on the sides of the frame, and each leg having
<claim-text>a proximal end connecting to one of the sides of the frame; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a distal end being opposite to the proximal end; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least two first engaging elements embedded in the frame; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a windproof shield assembly mounted detachably on the frame assembly and having
<claim-text>two windproof shields made of soft material, detachably mounted respectively on the sides of the frame and each windproof shield having
<claim-text>an outer surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inner surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an attachment section, being a front outer section and detachably abutting the rear inner surface of the frame;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one second engaging element embedded in the attachment section of the windproof shield and detachably engaging respectively with at least one of the at least two first engaging elements with a magnetic attractive force; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a mounting hole defined through the windproof shield and through which one of the legs extends, and the distal end of the leg extending backward into the outer surface of the windproof shield and then extending out of the inner surface of the windproof shield when the leg extends through the mounting hole.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The pair of windproof glasses as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the frame has two lens frame segments connected to each other through a connection segment;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the frame assembly has two side sets of at least one first engaging element embedded respectively in the lens frame segments and a central set of at lest one first engaging elements embedded in the connection segment of the frame;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the at least one second engaging element of each windproof shield detachably engages respectively with the at least one first engaging element of a corresponding side set on the frame; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the windproof shield assembly further has
<claim-text>a connection bracket connected to the windproof shields, mounted detachably on the frame of the frame assembly and having at least one second engaging element embedded in the connection bracket and detachably engaging respectively with the at least one first engaging element of the central set; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a face pad made of resilient material and mounted on the connection bracket.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The pair of the windproof glasses as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the at least two first engaging elements are made of magnets; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the at least one second engaging element of each windproof shield is made of metal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The pair of the windproof glasses as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the at least two first engaging elements are made of metal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>each one of the at least one second engaging element of each windproof shield is magnetic.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The pair of the windproof glasses as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein each windproof shield is made of fabric.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The pair of the windproof glasses as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein each windproof shield is made of rubber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The pair of windproof glasses as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein each windproof shield is made of plastic.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The pair of the windproof glasses as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the face pad is made of foam.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
