<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297671-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297671</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10988844</doc-number>
<date>20041116</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>290</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>72</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>722</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>510360</main-classification>
<further-classification>510342</further-classification>
<further-classification>510413</further-classification>
<further-classification>510421</further-classification>
<further-classification>510437</further-classification>
<further-classification>510475</further-classification>
<further-classification>510535</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Alkoxy surfactants having increased cloud points and methods of making the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4110268</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Longley et al.</name>
<date>19780800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4118326</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Login</name>
<date>19781000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4212760</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Baur et al.</name>
<date>19800700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>510339</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4430490</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Doerge</name>
<date>19840200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5503764</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Murch et al.</name>
<date>19960400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>510111</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6191315</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Thankachan et al.</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>568621</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>0 677 578</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>1 028 138</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>1 028 138</doc-number>
<kind>A3</kind>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00010">
<othercit>Otten, Jay G. et al, “Anionic Hydrotropes for Industrial and Institutional Rinse Aids,” JAOCS, vol. 63, No. 8 (Aug. 1986), pp. 1078-1081.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>Pandya, Ketan et al, “Effect of Additives on the Clouding Behavior of an Ethylene Oxide-Propylene Oxide Block Copolymer in Aqueous Solution,” J.M.S.—Pure Appln. Chem., A30(1), pp. 1-18 (1993), Jun. 7, 1993.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>Surfactants and Polyalkylene Glycols, Specialty Chemicals by BASF, pp. 1-51, no date given.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>510342</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>510360</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>510413</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>510421</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>510437</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>510475</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>510535</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060105934</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060518</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Thankachan</last-name>
<first-name>Chacko</first-name>
<address>
<city>West Bloomfield</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Betke</last-name>
<first-name>Brian J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Riverview</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Borrego</last-name>
<first-name>Fernando A.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>BASF Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Florham Park</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Mruk</last-name>
<first-name>Brian</first-name>
<department>1751</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Neutralizing a surfactant which is comprised of an alkaline-catalyzed reaction product between a monomeric or polymeric alcohol having at least one active hydrogen group and an alkylene oxide with a fatty acid allows the cloud point of the surfactant to be adjusted.</p>
</abstract>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to the field of surfactants and methods of making the same. In particularly preferred form, the present invention relates to nonionic surfactants having increased cloud points and to methods of making the same.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND AND SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The clouding behavior of surfactants in water with increasing temperature has several practical applications. For example, the defoaming action of surfactants becomes effective just above their cloud point. See Otten et al, “Anionic Hydrotropes for Industrial and Institutional Rinse Aids”, JAOCS; 63(8); 1078; 1986 (the entire content of which is incorporated expressly hereinto by reference). An end user will therefore select a particular surfactant for specific problem solving abilities such as wetting, detergency, foaming, defoaming and the like. In cleaning applications such as machine dish washing, the properties noted above are important. Since the water temperature in dish washing applications is relatively high, the surfactant selected often cannot meet all of the desired performance criteria. As a result, additives are typically included with the surfactant to achieve the desired solubilization. However, often times, when all other properties of the surfactant are in agreement for a specific application, often the surfactant's cloud point is too low. While the cloud point can be engineered by altering the surfactant's chemical structure, such structural alteration usually is accompanied by a change in one of its other properties thereby making it no longer useful for the intended application.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Recently, it has been suggested that certain electrolytes may be added so as to adjust the cloud point of a block copolymer surfactant comprised of an ethylene oxide (EO) and propylene oxide (PO) units. Pandya et al, “Effect of Additives on the Clouding Behavior of an Ethylene Oxide-Propylene Oxide Block copolymer in Aqueous Solution”; J.M.S-Pure Appl. Chem; A30(1); 1; 1993 (the entire content of which is expressly incorporated hereinto by reference). However, the technique described in this paper involves the addition of foreign materials often adding extra cost and unwanted interferences in the surfactant's performance.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Polyether polyol surfactants are typically prepared by the reaction of monomeric or polymeric initiators containing one or more active hydrogen-containing group(s), such as OH, NH<sub>2</sub>, NH, CO<sub>2</sub>H and the like, with alkylene oxides. The alkylene oxide reactions with the active hydrogen-containing compounds are catalyzed with alkaline catalysts such as potassium hydroxide and sodium hydroxide. At the end of the reaction, the catalyst is deactivated by either removing the catalyst physically from the resulting reactant mixture or by adding an acid, such as acetic acid, phosphoric acid, sulfuric acid and the like, in order to neutralize the catalyst. The most cost-effective way of deactivating the alkaline catalyst is by neutralizing the catalyst with an acid and leaving the resulting salt physically in the polyether polyol reaction product.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It has now been surprisingly discovered that, by neutralizing a surfactant which is the alkaline-catalyzed reaction product between a monomeric or polymeric compound (initiator) having at least one active hydrogen group and an alkylene oxide with a fatty acid, the cloud point of the surfactant may be raised as compared to otherwise identical surfactants which have not been neutralized (i.e., non-neutralized surfactants) and/or otherwise identical surfactants that have been neutralized with conventional non-fatty acids, such as acetic acid, phosphoric acid, sulfuric acid and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">These and other aspects and advantages will become more apparent after careful consideration is given to the following detailed description of the preferred exemplary embodiments thereof.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The preferred surfactants employed in the practice of the present invention include the alkaline-catalyzed reaction products between a monomeric or polymeric initiator having at least one active hydrogen-containing group with an alkylene oxide (e.g., polyether polyols). Especially preferred surfactants include at least one of an alcohol alkoxylates and block copolymers of ethylene oxide (EO) and propylene oxide (PO). The preferred alcohol alkoxylates have the general formula:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>R1-(EO)<sub>m</sub>-(PO)<sub>n</sub>-OH,<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
where R1 is a C6-C30 alkyl, alkenyl, alicyclic or aromatic hydrocarbon, and m and n are each, independent of one another, numbers from 0 to 100, provided that the total of m+n is 2 to 100. The alcohol alkoxylates most preferably include an alcohol chain having from 1 to 25 carbon atoms and most preferably include a linear alkyl alcohol alkoxylates and alkylphenol alkoxylates (e.g., dodecyl alcohol ethoxylates, tridecyl alcohol ethoxylates, nonylphenol ethoxylates, octylphenol ethoxylates and the like). Suitable alcohol alkoxylate surfactants are commercially available from BASF Corporation under the trademarks PLURAFAC® and ICONOL™.
</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The preferred block copolymers of EO and PO units will typically have a number average molecular weight of from 500 to 15,000, preferably between 1,000 to 10,000. Suitable block copolymers of EO and PO are commercially available from BASF Corporation under the registered trademark TETRONIC®.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Virtually any saturated or unsaturated fatty acid may be employed in the practice of this invention. Preferably, the fatty acid will have at least 8 carbon atoms in its chain. Most preferably, C8 up to C24 fatty acids are employed. Specific examples of preferred fatty acids include caprylic acid, capric acid, lauric acid, myristic acid, palmitic acid, palmitoleic acid, stearic acid, oleic acid, vaccenic acid, linoleic acid, arachidic acid, behenic acid, erucic acid and lignoceric acid. In addition, the fatty acids may be supplied by natural sources such as tall oil, coconut oil, palm kernel oil, animal fats, olive oil, butter fat, corn oil linseed oil, peanut oil fish oil, rapeseed oil and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The fatty acid is employed in amounts sufficient to neutralize the alkaline catalysts (typically potassium hydroxide, sodium hydroxide or the like) employed in the reaction of monomeric or polymeric alcohols containing one or more active hydrogen-containing group(s) with alkylene oxides. By the term “neutralize” is meant that the resulting surfactant following the addition of the fatty acid has a pH of between about 5.5 to about 8.5, more preferably about 7.0+/−0.9. The fatty acid is preferably employed in an amount which increases the cloud point temperature of the surfactant by between about 2° C. to about 50° C., more preferably, between about 5° C. to about 35° C., as compared to the unneutralized surfactant and/or the surfactant which has been neutralized conventionally (i.e., neutralized with non-fatty acids such as acetic acid, phosphoric acid, sulfuric acid and the like). It should of course be understood that the cloud point temperature increase achieved by the present invention is dependent upon the particular surfactant that is neutralized with the fatty acid. That is, some surfactants will experience a greater cloud point temperature increase as compared to other surfactants. Most preferably, the fatty acid will be employed in amounts sufficient to neutralize the alkaline catalyst used in the production of the surfactant to a pH range of between about 6.5 to about 8.5.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The present invention will be further described by reference to the following non-limiting examples.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The following nonionic surfactants identified as surfactants S1-S5 commercially available from BASF Corporation were employed in the following Examples:</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">S1=TETRONIC® 90R4: A tetrafunctional block ethylene-oxide-propylene oxide copolymer with terminal secondary hydroxyl groups.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">S2=PLURAFAC® D-25: A monofunctional fatty alcohol onto which is added propylene oxide and ethylene oxide.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">S3=PLURAFAC® RA30: A polyoxyethylene-polyoxypropylene block monool a mixture of fatty monohydroxyl alcohols, terminated with oxypropylene units, having an OH number of about 90.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">S4=PLURAFAC® RA40: A polyoxyethylene-polyoxypropylene block monool a mixture of fatty monohydroxyl alcohols, terminated with oxypropylene units, having an OH number of about 69.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">S5=ICONOL™ OP-10: A water-soluble nonionic surfactant composed of a 10-mole adduct of octylphenol.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">S6=ICONOL™ NP-9: A water-soluble nonionic surfactant composed of a 9-mole adduct of nonylphenol.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">A “cloud point” is the temperature at which a surfactant solution becomes cloudy. The cloud points were determined on the samples listed in examples S1-S6 as outlined below. The method was applicable to both neutralized product and in-process samples (unneutralized). The process was terminated often by checking the cloud point of the in-process sample (unneutralized) to the set commercial specification of the product neutralized with conventional acids or after removal of the catalyst. The determined cloud points of the unneutralized process samples were the same for the neutralized commercial samples.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Cloud points were determined by forcing a surfactant solution of known concentration in water or water solvent mixture to cloud by adjusting its temperature. The solution temperature at which the clouding solution becomes clear was recorded was determined to be the cloud point for the surfactant.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">EXAMPLE 1</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Unneutralized samples of nonionic surfactants identified in Table 1 were neutralized with oleic acid and tall oil fatty acid. The cloud points of the samples were measured before and after neutralization. The results appear in Table 1.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0" pgwide="1">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="5">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="35pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="84pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="63pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" rowsep="1">TABLE 1</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Specifications*</entry>
<entry>Measured**</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>Resultant Change</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="7">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="6" colwidth="14pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="7" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>Surfactant</entry>
<entry>pH</entry>
<entry>Cloud Pt. ° C.</entry>
<entry>Cloud Pt. ° C.</entry>
<entry>Fatty Acid</entry>
<entry>pH</entry>
<entry>Cloud Pt. ° C.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="7" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S1</entry>
<entry>7.5–9.5  </entry>
<entry>39–44</entry>
<entry>42.5</entry>
<entry>Oleic</entry>
<entry>7.1</entry>
<entry>45.5</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S2</entry>
<entry>5–6.5</entry>
<entry>52–62</entry>
<entry>55.5</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>7.5</entry>
<entry>69.7</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S3</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>35–39</entry>
<entry>38.2</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>7.8</entry>
<entry>52.0</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S4</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>22–27</entry>
<entry>26.3</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>7.9</entry>
<entry>31.8</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S5</entry>
<entry>6–7.5</entry>
<entry>63–67</entry>
<entry>64.9</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>7.5</entry>
<entry>80.2</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S1</entry>
<entry>7.5–9.5  </entry>
<entry>39–44</entry>
<entry>42.5</entry>
<entry>Tall Oil FA</entry>
<entry>7.3</entry>
<entry>45.4</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S2</entry>
<entry>5–6.5</entry>
<entry>52–62</entry>
<entry>55.5</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>7.6</entry>
<entry>67.9</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S3</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>35–39</entry>
<entry>38.2</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>7.9</entry>
<entry>50.5</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S4</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>22–27</entry>
<entry>26.3</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>7.9</entry>
<entry>33.5</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S5</entry>
<entry>6–7.5</entry>
<entry>63–67</entry>
<entry>64.9</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>7.9</entry>
<entry>77.0</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="7" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="7" align="left" id="FOO-00001">*All cloud points were measured on a 1% aqueous solution of the surfactant. The values given are the specification range for products neutralized with acetic acid or phosphoric acid.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="7" align="left" id="FOO-00002">**These cloud points were measured using the unneutralized surfactants.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The data show that the addition of oleic acid to each of the nonionic surfactants increased their respective cloud points.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">EXAMPLE 2</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Unneutralized samples of surfactant S6 (ICONOL™ NP-9) was neutralized with several fatty acids identified below in Table 2. The pH and 1% aqueous cloud points after neutralization were measured with the results being noted in Table 2 below.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00002" num="00002">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0" pgwide="1">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="5">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="35pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="70pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="42pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="63pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" rowsep="1">TABLE 2</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Specifications*</entry>
<entry>Measured**</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>Resultant Change</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="7">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="35pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="21pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="42pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="6" colwidth="14pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="7" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>Surfactant</entry>
<entry>pH</entry>
<entry>Cloud Pt. ° C.</entry>
<entry>Cloud Pt. ° C.</entry>
<entry>Fatty Acid</entry>
<entry>pH</entry>
<entry>Cloud Pt. ° C.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="7" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>S6</entry>
<entry>5–8</entry>
<entry>52–56</entry>
<entry>52.2</entry>
<entry>Oleic</entry>
<entry>6.9</entry>
<entry>87.2</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>Capric</entry>
<entry>6.2</entry>
<entry>61.4</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>Palmitic</entry>
<entry>6.6</entry>
<entry>90.5</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>″</entry>
<entry>Coconut FA</entry>
<entry>6.3</entry>
<entry>67.1</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="7" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="7" align="left" id="FOO-00003">*All cloud points were measured on a 1% aqueous solution of the surfactant. The values given are the specification range for products neutralized with acetic acid or phosphoric acid.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="7" align="left" id="FOO-00004">**These cloud points were measured using the unneutralized surfactants.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">It was observed that neutralization with fatty acids increased the cloud point of the nonionic surfactant.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">EXAMPLE 3</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Example 2 was repeated except that blends of acetic acid and oleic acid were employed to neutralize an unneutralized sample of surfactant S6. The results appear in Table 3 below.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00003" num="00003">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="3">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="126pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="77pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="14pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="2" rowsep="1">TABLE 3</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Resultant Changes</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="4">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="14pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="112pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="14pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="77pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Surfactant</entry>
<entry>pH</entry>
<entry>Cloud Pt. ° C.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="3" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>S6 neutralized with 5:1 oleic</entry>
<entry>5.8</entry>
<entry>55.1</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>acid:acetic acid by weight</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>S6 neutralized with 17.5:1 oleic</entry>
<entry>6.5</entry>
<entry>73.5</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>acid:acetic acid by weight</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="3" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The data above reveal that higher ratios of the fatty acid are needed in order to achieve a cloud point increase.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">EXAMPLE 4 (COMPARATIVE)</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Various amounts of oleic acid were added to a commercial sample (already neutralized with acetic acid) of surfactant S6. No increase in cloud point was observed.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">While the invention has been described in connection with what is presently considered to be the most practical and preferred embodiment, it is to be understood that the invention is not to be limited to the disclosed embodiment, but on the contrary, is intended to cover various modifications and equivalent arrangements included within the spirit and scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A surfactant composition comprising:
<claim-text>an alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a salt of:
<claim-text>an alkaline catalyst, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a straight-chain fatty acid having from 8 to 24 carbon atoms,</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the pH of said surfactant composition is about 7.0 +/−0.9.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The surfactant composition of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant comprises the reaction product of a monomeric or polymeric alcohol having at least one active hydrogen-containing group and an alkylene oxide in the presence of said alkaline catalyst.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The surfactant composition of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein said active hydrogen-containing group is at least one selected from the group consisting of OH, NH<sub>2</sub>, NH, and CO<sub>2</sub>H.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The surfactant composition of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant comprises at least one of an alcohol alkoxylate and a block copolymer comprised of ethylene oxide and propylene oxide units.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The surfactant composition of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant has the formula:
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>R1-(EO)<sub>m</sub>-(PO)<sub>n</sub>-OH<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>where R1 is a C6-C30 alkyl, alkenyl, alicyclic, or aromatic hydrocarbon, and m and n are each independent of one another numbers from 0 to 100 provided that the total of m+n is 2 to 100.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The surfactant composition of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant comprises a block copolymer comprised of ethylene oxide and propylene oxide units having a number average molecular weight of from 500 to 15,000.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The surfactant composition as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said straight-chain fatty acid is at least one selected from the group consisting of caprylic acid, capric acid, lauric acid, myristic acid, palmitic acid, palmitoleic acid, stearic acid, oleic acid, vaccenic acid, linoleic acid, arachidic acid, behenic acid, erucic acid, and lignoceric acid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The surfactant composition as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said straight-chain fatty acid is derived from at least one of tall oil, coconut oil, palm kernel oil, animal fats, olive oil, butter fat, corn oil, linseed oil, peanut oil, fish oil, and rapeseed oil.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The surfactant composition as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the cloud point temperature of said surfactant is increased by between about 2° C. to about 50° C. as compared to the unneutralized surfactant and/or a surfactant which has been neutralized with non-straight-chain fatty acids.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The surfactant composition as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the cloud point temperature of said surfactant composition is increased by between about 5° C. to about 35° C.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The surfactant of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant comprises at least one of an alcohol alkoxylate of ethylene oxide/propylene oxide or a block copolymer comprised of ethylene oxide and/or propylene oxide units.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method of adjusting the cloud point temperature of a surfactant composition including an alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant formed in the presence of an alkaline catalyst comprising adding to the surfactant composition an amount of a straight-chain fatty acid having from 8 to 24 carbon atoms sufficient to neutralize the alkaline catalyst and achieve a pH of the surfactant composition of about 7.0 +/−0.9 and thereby raise the cloud point temperature of the surfactant composition.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant comprises the reaction product of a monomeric or polymeric alcohol having at least one OH group and an alkylene oxide in the presence of the alkaline catalyst.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant comprises at least one of an alcohol alkoxylate of ethylene oxide/propylene oxide or a block copolymer comprised of ethylene oxide and/or propylene oxide units.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant has the formula:
<claim-text>
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>R1-(EO)<sub>m-(PO)</sub><sub>n</sub>-OH<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>where R1 is a C6-C30 alkyl, alkenyl, alicyclic, or aromatic hydrocarbon, and m and n are each independent of one another numbers from 0 to 100, provided that the total of m+n is 2 to 100.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the alkaline-catalyzed alkoxy surfactant comprises a block copolymer comprised of ethylene oxide and propylene oxide units having a number average molecular weight of from 500 to 15,000.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the straight-chain fatty acid is at least one selected from the group consisting of caprylic acid, capric acid, lauric acid, myristic acid, palmitic acid, palmitoleic acid, stearic acid, oleic acid, vaccenic acid, linoleic acid, arachidic acid, behenic acid, erucic acid, and lignoceric acid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the straight-chain fatty acid is derived from at least one of tall oil, coconut oil, palm kernel oil, animal fats, olive oil, butter fat, corn oil, linseed oil, peanut oil, fish oil, and rapeseed oil.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
