<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298198-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298198</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10575480</doc-number>
<date>20041015</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="regional">
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>03103877</doc-number>
<date>20031021</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>99</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>10</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327536</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Charge pump</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5532653</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Adkins</name>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>331143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5808506</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tran</name>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327537</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6026002</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Viehmann</name>
<date>20000200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>363 60</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>8</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327535</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327536</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327537</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>15</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070063760</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070322</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Stopel</last-name>
<first-name>Rick Franciscus Jozef</first-name>
<address>
<city>Singapore</city>
<country>SG</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>SG</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>SG</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>NXP B.V.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Eindhoven</city>
<country>NL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Zweizig</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey</first-name>
<department>2816</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/IB2004/052114</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20041015</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20060418</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO2005/039032</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20050428</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A charge pump comprises a single voltage multiplier stage (<b>1</b>) which converts an input voltage (VDD) into an output voltage (Vo) under control of a clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO). An oscillator (<b>2</b>) receives the input voltage (VDD) to generate the clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO) having a repetition period (Tr<b>1</b>, Tr<b>2</b>) which is substantially proportional to a squared input voltage (VDD<sup>2</sup>).</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="114.30mm" wi="145.12mm" file="US07298198-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="214.97mm" wi="145.29mm" file="US07298198-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="53.51mm" wi="77.39mm" file="US07298198-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="231.48mm" wi="152.74mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298198-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="163.75mm" wi="133.69mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298198-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="202.61mm" wi="158.58mm" file="US07298198-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention relates to a charge pump, an integrated circuit for a charge pump, a mobile device comprising such a charge pump, and a USB master device comprising such a charge pump.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">U.S. Pat. No. 5,808,506 discloses a MOS charge pump used in a non-volatile memory. A current controlled oscillator generates the clock for the charge pump voltage multiplier. The oscillator period is proportional to the input voltage. If the input voltage decreases, the oscillator period decreases and thus the oscillator frequency increases. If the input voltage decreases, the charge pumped to the output of the charge pump decreases. The corresponding increase of the oscillator frequency compensates for the decrease of the charge. It is required that under the worst case condition of minimum input voltage, the open circuit voltage of the charge pump is above the intended regulated output voltage, and that the increase of the oscillator frequency is adequate to keep the charge pump output current high enough to maintain the output voltage regulated in the loaded state.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">It is a drawback of the known charge pump that the maximum current which is supplied by the charge pump can be relatively large at high input voltages.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">It is an object of the invention to provide a charge pump of which the maximum output current is less dependent on variations of the input voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A first aspect of the invention provides a charge pump as claimed in claim <b>1</b>. A second aspect of the invention provides an integrated circuit as claimed in claim <b>6</b>. A third aspect of the invention provides a mobile device as claimed in claim <b>7</b>. A fourth aspect of the invention provides a USB master device as claimed in claim <b>8</b>. Advantageous embodiments are defined in the dependent claims.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The charge pump in accordance with the first aspect of the invention comprises a single voltage multiplier stage. The single voltage multiplier stage converts an input voltage into an output voltage under control of a clock signal. The oscillator which generates the clock signal receives the input voltage to control a repetition period of the clock signal to be substantially proportional to the squared input voltage. Consequently, the maximum output current of the single voltage multiplier stage is substantially independent of the input voltage. Such an oscillator, which is able to supply a clock signal with a repetition period which is proportional to the squared input control signal, may be constructed in accordance with any of many known implementations. By contrast, in the charge pump disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 5,808,506 the repetition period of the clock signal is proportional to the input voltage to obtain a regulated output voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In the following it will be explained that the output current of the charge pump is substantially independent of the input voltage if the oscillator frequency is inversely proportional to the squared input voltage. The charge pump as such and its operation are well known. In short, during each repetition period of the clock signal, first a capacitor is charged to the input voltage. Then, the charged capacitor is switched in-between the input and the output of the charge pump such that the output voltage is the sum of the input voltage and the voltage across the charged capacitor. The output voltage is larger than the input voltage because the input voltage and the voltage across the capacitor have the same polarity. The energy stored in the charged capacitor is equal to
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>EC=</i>0.5<i>*CP*VDD</i><sup>2 </sup><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
wherein EC is the energy stored in the capacitor CP and VDD is the input voltage.
</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The energy required at the output of the charge pump is
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>EO=Vo*Io*Tclk </i><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
wherein EO is the energy requested at the output of the charge pump, Vo is the output voltage of the charge pump, Io is the output current of the charge pump and Tclk is the repetition period of the clock signal supplied by the oscillator to the charge pump.
</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">When the input charge EC and the output charge EO are in balance:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>Tclk</i>=(0.5<i>*CP*VDD</i><sup>2</sup>)/(<i>Vo*Io</i>).<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Consequently, if a substantially constant output current is desired while the output voltage is substantially stabilized, the repetition period of the clock signal should be substantially proportional to the squared input voltage. Or, the repetition frequency of the clock signal should be substantially inversely proportional to the squared input voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In an embodiment in accordance with the invention as claimed in claim <b>2</b>, the oscillator has an input to receive a control signal. The repetition period of the clock signal supplied by the oscillator is substantially linearly dependent on the control signal. Such an oscillator is well known in the art. A control circuit receives the input voltage and supplies the control signal which is substantially proportional to the squared input voltage. Such a control circuit is well known in the art. For example, the control circuit may be a multiplier which multiplies the input signal with itself, or the control circuit comprises a table look up memory, or a MOSFET arranged as a diode between the input signal and a fixed reference voltage to obtain a current through the MOSFET which is substantially proportional to the squared voltage difference across the MOSFET.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In an embodiment in accordance with the invention as claimed in claim <b>3</b>, the oscillator supplies a clock signal of which the repetition period depends on a charging or discharging bias current supplied to a capacitor. Now the control circuit supplies the bias current which is substantially proportional to the squared input voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In an embodiment in accordance with the invention as claimed in claim <b>4</b>, the charge pump further comprises a duty cycle modulator to modulate a duty cycle of the clock signal in response to the output voltage to obtain a substantially constant output voltage. The duty cycle of the clock signal determines the charging time of the capacitor during the first part of a repetition period of the clock signal and thus the amount of charge stored in the capacitor. At a smaller duty cycle the capacitor is connected to the input voltage during a shorter period of time and thus will be less charged. During the second part of the repetition period of the clock signal, the capacitor is connected in series with the input voltage to supply the output current.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In an embodiment in accordance with the invention as claimed in claim <b>5</b>, the duty cycle modulator comprises a comparator which compares the output voltage of the charge pump with a reference voltage to obtain a comparison signal. A first integrator generates a first saw-tooth signal which has successively a rising and a falling slope dependent on whether the comparison signal indicates that the output voltage is above or below the reference voltage, or the other way around. A second integrator generates a second saw-tooth signal having a slope dependent on the squared input voltage. A comparator compares the first saw-tooth signal and the second saw-tooth signal. This approach has the advantage that the second saw-tooth has a slope proportional to the squared input voltage. The duty cycle control operates optimally, substantially independent of the input voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">These and other aspects of the invention are apparent from and will be elucidated with reference to the embodiments described hereinafter.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In the drawings:</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a charge pump with a single voltage multiplier stage and a block diagram of an oscillator for controlling the switches of the charge pump,</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows signals occurring in the charge pump for elucidating its operation,</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a block diagram of the oscillator,</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a detailed circuit diagram of another embodiment of the oscillator and a control circuit which controls the oscillator,</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a block diagram of a duty cycle modulator in accordance with an embodiment of the invention,</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows signals elucidating the operation of the duty cycle modulator at a relatively low repetition frequency of the oscillator, and</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows signals elucidating the operation of the duty cycle modulator at a relatively high repetition frequency of the oscillator.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a charge pump and a block diagram of an oscillator for controlling the switches of the charge pump. The charge pump <b>1</b> comprises a single voltage multiplier stage. A series arrangement of a switch S<b>3</b>, a capacitor CP and a switch S<b>4</b> is arranged between the input IN and the output OUT of the charge pump <b>1</b>. The input IN receives the input voltage VDD, the output OUT supplies the output voltage Vo and the output current Io to a load (not shown). A switch S<b>2</b> is arranged between the junction of the switch S<b>3</b> and the capacitor CP and ground. The switch S<b>2</b> may be connected to a potential other than ground. A switch S<b>1</b> is arranged between the junction of the capacitor CP and the switch S<b>4</b> and the input IN. A storage capacitor Co is arranged between the output and ground or another reference potential. The oscillator <b>2</b> generates control signals CS<b>1</b> to CS<b>4</b> which are supplied to the switches S<b>1</b> to S<b>4</b>, respectively. The control signals CS<b>1</b> and CS<b>2</b> are connected to the same signal Qn supplied by the oscillator <b>2</b>. The control signals CS<b>3</b> and CS<b>4</b> are connected to the same signal Q supplied by the oscillator <b>2</b>. The signal Qn is the inverted signal Q.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">It is common use to refer to the control signals as CS<b>1</b> to CS<b>2</b> and thus to the clock signal(s) as Q and Qn. The clock signal clocks the charge pump to perform the voltage up-conversion. The oscillator <b>2</b> in accordance with the invention generates a clock signal which has a repetition period which is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>. Thus, in the charge pump shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the clock signal comprises the signal Q and its inverted signal Qn which both have a repetition period which is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>. The operation of the charge pump is elucidated with respect to the signals shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows signals occurring in the charge pump for elucidating its operation. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> shows the signal Qn supplied by the oscillator <b>2</b> at a predetermined value VDD<b>1</b> of the input voltage VDD at which the repetition period of the oscillator is Tr<b>1</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> shows the signal Q which is the inverted signal Qn. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> shows the signal Qn′ supplied by the oscillator <b>2</b> at another, lower predetermined value VDD<b>2</b> of the input voltage VDD at which the repetition period of the oscillator Tr<b>2</b> is shorter than the repetition period Tr<b>1</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref> shows the signal Q′ which is the inverted signal Qn′. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> indicate that the repetition period Tr<b>1</b>, Tr<b>2</b> of the clock signal depends on the level VDD<b>1</b>, VDD<b>2</b> of the input voltage VDD in that the repetition period Tr<b>1</b>, Tr<b>2</b> is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The operation of the charge pump is elucidated with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>, thus when the value of the input voltage VDD is VDD<b>1</b>. It is assumed that a high level of the signals Q and Qn indicates that the associated ones of the switches S<b>1</b> to S<b>4</b> are closed, while a low level indicates that the associated switches are opened. This may, of course, be the other way around depending on the switches used. Usually, the switches are transistors, such as MOSFETs.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">At instant t<b>1</b>, the signal Qn becomes high: the switches S<b>1</b> and S<b>2</b> are closed, and the signal Q becomes low: the switches S<b>3</b> and S<b>4</b> are opened. The input voltage VDD is connected across the capacitor CP and the voltage Vc across the capacitor CP increases. At the instant t<b>2</b>, the signal Qn becomes low: the switches S<b>1</b> and S<b>2</b> are opened, and the signal Q becomes high: the switches S<b>3</b> and S<b>4</b> are closed. Now, the capacitor CP is arranged in series with the input voltage VDD and the output voltage Vo of the charge pump is equal to the input voltage plus the voltage Vc across the capacitor CP.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a block diagram of the oscillator. The oscillator shown comprises an oscillator circuit OC and a control circuit CC. The control circuit CC receives the input voltage VDD and supplies a control signal CS which is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>. The oscillator circuit OC receives the control signal and supplies the clock signal Q, CLKO. The oscillator circuit OC may be any oscillator of which the frequency is controllable by a control signal CS to obtain a repetition frequency of the oscillator signal Q, CLKO which is linearly dependent on the control signal CS.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a detailed circuit diagram of another embodiment of the oscillator and a control circuit which controls the oscillator. The oscillator is obtained by using for example MOSFETs. It is possible to replace the MOSFETs by other suitable semiconductor elements. Preferably the oscillator is integrated in an integrated circuit. MOSFETs referred to as MPi are P-channel MOSFETs, MOSFETs referred to as MNi are N-channel MOSFETs.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The P-channel MOSFET MP<b>1</b> has a main current path arranged between the input voltage VDD of the charge pump and a reference potential VSS which may be considered to be ground potential. The gate of the MOSFET MP<b>1</b> is connected to the reference potential VSS. The MOSFET MP<b>1</b> operates as a diode. The current Id through this diode MP<b>1</b> is
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>Id=K W/L</i>(<i>VDD−Vt</i>)<sup>2 </sup><?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
wherein K is a constant, W/L is the width/length ratio of the MOSFET MP<b>1</b>, and Vt is the threshold voltage.
</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Thus, the current Id is substantially proportional to the squared input voltage VDD. A small inaccuracy is caused by the threshold voltage Vt. This current Id is mirrored by the MOSFET MP<b>2</b> which forms a current mirror with the MOSFET MP<b>1</b>. The current Id<b>1</b> which flows in the main current path of the MOSFET MP<b>2</b> is the mirrored version of the current Id. The current Id<b>1</b> may be equal to, or bear a fixed relation with, the current Id, dependent on the ratio of the width/length ratios of the MOSFETs MP<b>1</b> and MP<b>2</b>. The current Id<b>1</b> is mirrored by the N-channel MOSFETs MN<b>3</b> and MN<b>4</b> to obtain the current Id<b>2</b>. The current Id<b>2</b> is mirrored by the MOSFETs MP<b>3</b> and MP<b>4</b> to obtain the current Isq. All the currents Id, Id<b>1</b>, Id<b>2</b>, Isq have a fixed ratio and thus all are proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The current Isq is supplied to a trans-linear amplifier which comprises the MOSFETs MP<b>5</b>, MP<b>6</b>, MP<b>7</b> and MP<b>8</b>. This trans-linear amplifier supplies at its output a current 1/Isq which is the inverse of the input current Isq of the trans-linear amplifier. A reference current source Iref supplies a current which is mirrored via the MOSFETs MN<b>1</b>, MN<b>2</b> to obtain the reference current Iref. The current Iref through the main current paths of the MOSFETs MP<b>5</b> and MP<b>6</b> is fixed. Thus, a current variation in the main current path of MOSFET MP<b>7</b> results in an opposite variation of the current 1/Isq through the main current path in the MOSFET MP<b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The source of the MOSFET MP<b>8</b> supplies the current 1/Isq to the oscillator which comprises current mirrors obtained by the MOSFETs MN<b>5</b>, MN<b>6</b>, MN<b>7</b> and MN<b>8</b> which supply the mirrored currents Io. The currents Io all are proportional to 1/Isq and thus to 1/VDD<sup>2</sup>. The MOSFETs MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> behave as capacitors. Instead of MOSFETs also internal or external capacitors may be used. The MOSFET's MP<b>9</b> and MP<b>10</b> are switches which connect the capacitors MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> to the input voltage VDD. The MOSFET's MN<b>9</b> and MN<b>10</b> are switches which discharge the capacitors MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> with the current Io. The voltage on the capacitor MP<b>13</b> is referred to as INT<b>1</b>, the voltage on the capacitor MP<b>14</b> is referred to as INT<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The gates of the MOSFETs MN<b>9</b> and MP<b>9</b> receive an inverted clock signal CLKn, the gates of the MOSFETs MP<b>10</b> and MN<b>10</b> receive the clock signal CLK. The voltage DET<b>1</b> at the source of the MOSFET MP<b>11</b> assumes a high level when the voltage INT<b>1</b> drops below a predetermined value. The voltage DET<b>2</b> at the source of the MOSFET MP<b>12</b> assumes a high level when the voltage INT<b>2</b> drops below a predetermined value. The logical circuit which comprises the logical NORs <b>120</b>, <b>121</b>, <b>124</b> and <b>125</b> receives the voltages DET<b>1</b>, DET<b>2</b> and supplies the clock signal CLK and the inverted clock signal CLKn.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The operation of the oscillator is elucidated starting from a low level of the clock signal CLK and thus a high level of the clock signal CLKn. The capacitor MP<b>13</b> is being discharged by the current Io, and the capacitor MP<b>14</b> is connected to VDD. Thus, the voltage INT<b>1</b> on the capacitor MP<b>13</b> is decreasing while the voltage INT<b>2</b> on the capacitor MP<b>14</b> is constant and high. The high voltage on the capacitor MP<b>14</b> causes the voltage DET<b>2</b> to be low because MP<b>12</b> is turned off and the current Io can't flow through MP<b>12</b>. The voltage on the capacitor MP<b>13</b> decreases until the MOSFET MP<b>11</b> trips at the predetermined threshold level VT of the MOSFET. As for the logic NOR gates <b>120</b>, <b>121</b>, <b>124</b>, <b>125</b>, the jump of the voltage DET<b>1</b> from a low value to a high value will result in a low level on the output of the NOR gate <b>120</b>. This low level together with the low level of the voltage DET<b>2</b> will make the level of the output of the NOR <b>121</b> high. The high level on the output of the NOR <b>121</b> will result in a low level on the output of the NOR <b>124</b>. The output of the NOR <b>124</b> is the inverted clock signal CLKn. This low level together with the low level from the output of the NOR <b>120</b> will give a high level at the output of the NOR <b>125</b>. The output of the NOR <b>125</b> is the clock signal CLK. It is demonstrated that the clock signal CLK and inverted clock signal CLKn have a reverse polarity. The sequence will start again, but now the capacitor MP<b>14</b> is discharged by a current Io while the capacitor MP<b>13</b> is switched to the input voltage VDD. It is clear that the high period and the low period of the clock signals CLK and CLKn both are determined by the values of the capacitors MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> and the value of the current Io. If the capacitors MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> have equal values, the duty cycle of the clock signals CLK and CLKn will be 50%.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Because the trip levels of the MOSFETs MP<b>11</b> and MP<b>12</b> are referenced to VDD (the threshold voltage VT of the MOSFETs MP<b>11</b>, MP<b>12</b>) and the period of time required to discharge the capacitors MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> from the input voltage VDD to the trip level is determined by the current Io and the capacitance of the MOSFETs MP<b>13</b>, MP<b>14</b>, (?) the capacitors MP<b>13</b>, MP<b>14</b> are basically integrating capacitors. The time to discharge the capacitors MP<b>13</b>/MP<b>14</b> is T=C<sub>MP13/MP14</sub>*(VT)/Io. Both the capacitors MP<b>13</b>, MP<b>14</b> and the delta voltage across the capacitors MP<b>13</b>, MP<b>14</b> are independent of the input voltage VDD. The current Io is proportional to 1/VDD<sup>2</sup>. Consequently, the repetition period T varies with the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>. Thus, if the input voltage VDD is low, the repetition period T is small to increase the charge supplied at the output of the charge pump.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The MOSFETs MP<b>15</b>, MP<b>16</b>, MN<b>17</b>, MN<b>18</b> form a buffer which buffers the clock signal CLK to obtain the buffered clock signal CLKO which in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 5</figref> is used to generate the signals Q and Qn. The clock signal CLK generated in this manner has a repetition period which is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2 </sup>which has the advantage that the maximum output current is substantially independent of the level of the input voltage VDD.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">It is a further advantageous that the frequency of the oscillator is substantially independent of temperature and process tolerances. This is due to the fact that the diode MP<b>1</b> and the capacitors MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> are all P-channel MOSFETs and thus behave in the same manner, while the current Id through the diode MP<b>1</b> and the current Io through the capacitors MP<b>13</b>, MP<b>14</b> have an inverse behavior. For example, when the temperature decreases, the current Isq increases, and the output current 1/Isq of the trans-linear amplifier decreases. Thus, the bias current Io for the oscillator decreases when the temperature decreases. At a lower temperature, the same discharge curve is obtained if the capacitors MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> are discharged at a slower rate. This is exactly what happens because the bias current Io is smaller at a lower temperature. Also with respect to process variations a compensating effect is present. In a slow process, the current Id is smaller and thus the bias current Io of the oscillator is larger. This higher discharge current of the capacitors MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b> is counteracted by the lower mobility of the MOSFETs MP<b>13</b> and MP<b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a block diagram of a duty cycle modulator. A resistor tap comprises the series arranged resistors R<b>1</b> and R<b>2</b>. This series arrangement is arranged between the output voltage Vo of the charge pump and a reference potential which in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is ground. A comparator COM<b>1</b> has an inverting input which is connected to the junction of the series arranged resistors R<b>1</b> and R<b>2</b> to receive a voltage Vt which is the tapped-in (?) output voltage Vo. The comparator COM<b>1</b> has a non-inverting input which receives a reference voltage Vr. The output signal COS of the comparator COM<b>1</b> controls a switch S<b>5</b> which is arranged in series with a current source CU<b>1</b> which supplies a current 2*Isc. The current source CU<b>1</b> supplies the current 2*Isc to a capacitor C<b>2</b> if the switch S<b>5</b> is closed. A current source CU<b>2</b> is arranged in parallel with the capacitor C<b>2</b> and supplies a current Isc which is withdrawn from the capacitor C<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Thus, the voltage CPO at the capacitor C<b>2</b> will linearly decrease due to the current Isc which is withdrawn from the capacitor C<b>2</b> when the switch S<b>5</b> is open. The voltage CPO will linearly increase due to the current Isc=2*Isc−Isc which flows into the capacitor C<b>2</b> when the switch S<b>5</b> is closed. Consequently, the signal CPO is sawtooth shaped with a rising slope if the tapped-in output voltage Vt is higher than the reference voltage Vr and with a falling slope if the tapped-in output voltage is lower than the reference voltage Vr. Usually, the output voltage Vo is the highest voltage available and it is required to tap-in this output voltage Vo to be able to compare it, by using the comparator COM<b>1</b>, with the reference level Vr. If another, higher voltage is available, or if the comparator COM<b>1</b> is able to compare the output voltage Vo directly with the reference voltage, the tapping-in may be omitted. Instead of providing the switch S<b>5</b> in series with the current source CU<b>1</b>, the current source CU<b>1</b> itself may be switched on and off. It is possible to implement a switch which switches the current 2*Isc to ground when the tapped-in output voltage Vt is below the reference level Vr. It is not essential that the current supplied by the current source CU<b>1</b> is twice as large as the current supplied by the current source CU<b>2</b>. It suffices that the current supplied by the current source CU<b>1</b> is larger than the current supplied by the current source CU<b>2</b>. Of course, the skilled person will have no problems understanding how to construct the complementary circuit, which uses capacitors connected to a high voltage instead of to ground and which has the same effect</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The current Io, which is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>, is fed to a capacitor C<b>3</b> to generate a sawtooth shaped signal RA. A possible manner to generate the current Io is discussed with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The comparator COM<b>2</b> has an inverting input to receive the sawtooth signal CPO and a non-inverting input to receive the sawtooth signal RA. The output of the comparator COM<b>2</b> is connected to a CL input of a Flip-Flop FF. The flip-flop FF has a data input D which is connected to the input voltage VDD to receive a high level, a reset input R which receives a clock signal CLK, an output which supplies the output signal Q and an inverting output which supplies the inverted output signal Qn which is the inverted version of the output signal Q. A logical NAND NA has an input which receives the inverted output signal Q, an input which receives the clock signal CLK, and an output which controls a switch F<b>1</b>. The switch F<b>1</b> is shown to be a MOSFET of which the gate is connected to the output of the NAND NA, and of which the drain-source path is arranged in parallel with the capacitor C<b>3</b>. The clock signal CLKO is an output signal of the oscillator <b>2</b>, which may be generated with the oscillator shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The clock signal CLKO has a repetition period Tr<b>1</b>, Tr<b>2</b> which is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2 </sup>and which has a fixed duty cycle which preferably is 50%.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The operation of the duty cycle modulator will be elucidated with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows signals elucidating the operation of the duty cycle modulator at a relatively low repetition frequency of the oscillator.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> shows the output voltage Vo and the desired level DL of the output voltage Vo. The output voltage Vo crosses the desired level DL at the instant t<b>0</b> and is higher than the desired level DL from the instant t<b>0</b> onwards.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> shows the clock signal CLKO generated by the oscillator of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> with a substantially 50% duty cycle and a repetition period TR<b>1</b>. The clock signal CLKO has rising edges at the instants t<b>1</b> and t<b>4</b>, and falling edges at the instants t<b>3</b> and t<b>6</b>. The repetition period TR<b>1</b> lasts from the instant t<b>1</b> to the instant t<b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref> shows the sawtooth signals CPO and RA, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref> shows the inverted output signal Qn. The sawtooth signal CPO has a falling slope until the instant t<b>0</b> because the output voltage Vo is below the desired level DL. From the instant t<b>0</b> onwards, the output voltage Vo is above the desired level DL and thus the sawtooth signal CPO has a rising slope. During the low level periods of the clock signal CLKO, the NAND NA causes the MOSFET F<b>1</b> to be conductive and the capacitor C<b>3</b> is short circuited. Consequently, the sawtooth signal RA has a low level up to the instant t<b>1</b>, from instant t<b>3</b> to t<b>4</b> and after instant t<b>6</b>. It is assumed that the inverted output signal Qn has a high level at the instants t<b>0</b> and t<b>1</b>. Thus, at the instant t<b>1</b> both the clock signal CLKO and the inverted output signal Qn are high, and the NAND NA controls the FET F<b>1</b> to become non-conductive. The current Isc starts charging the capacitor C<b>3</b> and the sawtooth signal RA starts to increase linearly. At the instant t<b>2</b> the sawtooth signal RA reaches the sawtooth signal CPO. The comparator COM<b>2</b> supplies a positive level to the clock input CL of the flip-flop FF and the high level at the data input D is clocked in. The inverted output signal Qn changes to a low level. The low level of the inverted output signal Qn causes the output signal of the NAND NA to get a high level and the FET F<b>1</b> becomes conductive. Consequently, the sawtooth signal RA has a low level from the instant t<b>2</b> to t<b>3</b> and from the instant t<b>5</b> to t<b>6</b>. At the instant t<b>3</b>, the clock signal CLKO changes to the low level and the flip-flop FF is reset: the inverted output signal Qn becomes high again.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref>, the inverted output signal Qn has a low level, of which the duration depends on the instant the sawtooth signal RA reaches the sawtooth signal CPO. The slope of the sawtooth signal CPO depends on the value of the output voltage Vo. If the output voltage Vo is below the desired level DL, the sawtooth signal CPO linearly decreases due to the current Isc. If the output voltage Vo is above the desired level DL, the sawtooth signal CPO linearly increases with the difference between the current 2*Isc supplied by the current source CU<b>1</b> and the current Isc supplied by the current source CU<b>2</b>. It is not essential to the inventive idea that the current source CU<b>1</b> supplies a current which is twice the current supplied by the current source CU<b>2</b>. It suffices if the current of the current source CU<b>1</b> is larger than the current of the current source CU<b>2</b>. Instead of two current sources CU<b>1</b> and CU<b>2</b> it is also possible to use one current source which is able to generate a bi-directional current.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In the example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the output voltage Vo is higher than the desired level DL from the instant t<b>0</b> onwards. Consequently, the sawtooth voltage CPO continuously rises and the low level periods of the inverted output signal Qn decrease in time: the time difference between the instants t<b>5</b> and t<b>6</b> is smaller than the time difference between the instants t<b>2</b> and t<b>3</b>. During the high level of the inverted output signal Qn, the switches S<b>1</b> and S<b>2</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) are closed and the capacitor CP is charged. Usually, the on-time of the switches S<b>1</b> and S<b>2</b> is selected sufficiently long to charge the capacitor to the input voltage VDD. During the low level of the inverted output signal Qn, the switches S<b>3</b> and S<b>4</b> are closed and the charge stored in the capacitor CP can be supplied to the load. If the time during which the switches S<b>3</b> and S<b>4</b> are closed decreases, the charge which can be supplied to the load decreases. Consequently, the too high output voltage Vo causes less charge to be supplied to the load and thus the output voltage will start decreasing. If the output voltage Vo is lower than the desired level DL (not shown), the sawtooth CPO continuously decreases and the duration of the low period of the inverted output signal Qn increases. A larger part of the charge in the capacitor CP will be supplied to the load and the output voltage Vo will start rising.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows signals elucidating the operation of the duty cycle modulator at a relatively high repetition frequency of the oscillator. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A to 7C</figref> are comparable to FIGS. <b>6</b>B to <b>6</b>D, respectively. The differences are that the repetition frequency TR<b>2</b> is shorter than the repetition frequency TR<b>1</b>, and that the current Io is larger.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref> shows the clock signal CLKO generated by the oscillator shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> at an input voltage VDD which is lower than the input voltage VDD to which <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6B to 6D</figref> are associated. In accordance with the invention, the repetition period TR<b>1</b>, TR<b>2</b> is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>. Thus, the repetition period TR<b>2</b> at a lower value of the input voltage VDD is shorter than the repetition period TR<b>1</b> at a higher input voltage VDD. The clock signal CLKO has rising edges at the instants t<b>10</b>, t<b>13</b>, t<b>16</b>, t<b>19</b> and falling edges at the instants t<b>12</b>, t<b>15</b>, t<b>18</b>, t<b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref> the sawtooth signals CPO and RA are shown. Again, the sawtooth signal CPO is linearly increasing because the output voltage Vo is higher than the desired level DL. The slope of the sawtooth signal CPO is identical to the slope at the higher input voltage VDD because the currents supplied by the current sources CU<b>1</b> and CU<b>2</b> are constant. The sawtooth signal RA again starts at the rising edges of the clock signal CLKO. The slope of the sawtooth signal RA is steeper that in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref> because the current Io which charges the capacitor C<b>3</b> is proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>. At the instant the sawtooth signals RA and CPO become equal, the inverted output signal Qn becomes low. The inverted output signal Qn stays low until the next falling edge of the clock signal CLKO occurs. Thus, the inverted output signal Qn has a low level during a period in time which gradually decreases (see the time periods t<b>11</b> to t<b>12</b>, t<b>14</b> to t<b>15</b>, t<b>17</b> to t<b>18</b>, t<b>20</b> to t<b>21</b>), in the same manner as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6D</figref>. Thus, again the period in time during which the charge in the capacitor CP can be transferred to the load becomes shorter as the time during which the output voltage Vo is higher than the desired level DL is longer.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">As becomes clear from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the duty cycle control, which regulates the output voltage Vo, is adapted to optimally perform at different input voltages VDD at which different repetition periods TR<b>1</b>, TR<b>2</b> of the clock signal CLKO are generated by the oscillator. The repetition periods TR<b>1</b>, TR<b>2</b> are proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>. The current Isc which charges the capacitor C<b>3</b> is also made proportional to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2</sup>. Consequently, still the whole high period of the clock signal CLKO is available for the duty cycle control independent of the actual value of the input voltage VDD and thus the actual clock repetition period TR<b>1</b>, TR<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">It has to be noted that the duty cycle control is independent of the actual repetition period TR<b>1</b>, TR<b>2</b>. The duty cycle control operates to regulate the output voltage Vo independent of the actual value of the input voltage VDD. The repetition period TR<b>1</b>, TR<b>2</b> is controlled proportionally to the squared input voltage VDD<sup>2 </sup>to obtain a substantially constant maximum output current Io of the charge pump. It is especially important to limit the output current Io of the charge pump if the charge pump is used in a mobile application which is battery powered, to extend the life of the battery.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">It should be noted that the above-mentioned embodiments illustrate rather than limit the invention, and that those skilled in the art will be able to design many alternative embodiments without departing from the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In the claims, any reference signs placed between parentheses shall not be construed as limiting the claim. Use of the verb “comprise” and its conjugations does not exclude the presence of elements or steps other than those stated in a claim. The article “a” or “an” preceding an element does not exclude the presence of a plurality of such elements. The invention may be implemented by means of hardware comprising several distinct elements, and by means of a suitably programmed computer. In the device claim enumerating several means, several of these means may be embodied by one and the same item of hardware. The mere fact that certain measures are recited in mutually different dependent claims does not indicate that a combination of these measures cannot be used to advantage.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A charge pump comprising:
<claim-text>a single voltage multiplier stage (<b>1</b>) for converting an input voltage (VDD) into an output voltage (Vo) under control of a clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an oscillator (<b>2</b>) for receiving the input voltage (VDD) to generate the clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO) having a repetition period (Tr<b>1</b>, Tr<b>2</b>) being substantially proportional to a squared input voltage (VDD<sup>2</sup>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A charge pump as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the oscillator (<b>2</b>) comprises:
<claim-text>a control circuit (CC) for receiving the input voltage (VDD) to supply a control signal (CS) being substantially proportional to the squared input voltage (VDD<sup>2</sup>), and wherein the repetition period of the oscillator (<b>2</b>) is substantially linearly dependent on the control signal (CS).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A charge pump as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the oscillator (<b>2</b>) comprises:
<claim-text>a capacitor (MP<b>13</b>, MP<b>14</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>a current source (MN<b>7</b>) for supplying a current (Io) to charge or discharge the capacitor (MP<b>13</b>, MP<b>14</b>),</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control circuit (MP<b>1</b>) for receiving the input voltage (VDD) to supply a further current (<b>1</b><i>d</i>) being substantially proportional to the squared input voltage (VDD<sup>2</sup>), wherein the first mentioned current (Io) and the further current (<b>1</b><i>d</i>) have a fixed ratio.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A charge pump as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the charge pump further comprises a duty cycle modulator (<b>3</b>) for modulating a duty cycle of the clock signal (CLKO), the duty cycle modulator (<b>3</b>) comprises an input for receiving the output voltage (Vo) to adapt the duty cycle to obtain a substantially constant output voltage (Vo).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A charge pump as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the duty cycle modulator (<b>3</b>) comprises:
<claim-text>a first comparator (COM<b>1</b>) for comparing the output voltage (Vo) with a reference voltage (Vr) to supply a comparison signal (COS),</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first integrator (C<b>2</b>) for generating a first saw-tooth signal (CPO) having a rising or falling slope dependent on whether the comparison signal (COS) indicates that the output voltage (Vo) is above or below the reference voltage (Vr), or the other way around,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second integrator (C<b>3</b>) for generating a second saw-tooth signal (RA) having a slope dependent on the squared input voltage (VDD<sup>2</sup>), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second comparator (COM<b>2</b>) for comparing the first saw-tooth signal (CPO) and the second saw-tooth signal (RA), the duty cycle being dependent on an instant the first saw-tooth signal (CPO) reaches the second saw-tooth signal (RA).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An integrated circuit for use in a charge pump comprising a single voltage multiplier stage (<b>1</b>) for converting an input voltage (VDD) into an output voltage (Vo) under control of a clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO), the integrated circuit comprising:
<claim-text>an oscillator (<b>2</b>) for receiving the input voltage (VDD) to generate the clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO) having a repetition period (Tr<b>1</b>, Tr<b>2</b>) being substantially proportional to a squared input voltage (VDD<sup>2</sup>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A mobile device having a charge pump comprising:
<claim-text>a single voltage multiplier stage (<b>1</b>) for converting an input voltage (VDD) supplied by a battery into an output voltage (Vo) under control of a clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an oscillator (<b>2</b>) for receiving the input voltage (VDD) to generate the clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO) having a repetition period (Tr<b>1</b>, Tr<b>2</b>) being substantially proportional to a squared input voltage (VDD<sup>2</sup>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A USB master device having a charge pump comprising:
<claim-text>a single voltage multiplier stage (<b>1</b>) for converting an input voltage (VDD) into an output voltage (Vo) for a USB slave device under control of a clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO), and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an oscillator (<b>2</b>) for receiving the input voltage (VDD) to generate the clock signal (Q, Qn; CLKO) having a repetition period (Tr<b>1</b>, Tr<b>2</b>) being substantially proportional to a squared input voltage (VDD<sup>2</sup>).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
