<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296890-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296890</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11257981</doc-number>
<date>20051025</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351160R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Contact lens with controlled shape</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6082856</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dunn et al.</name>
<date>20000700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351160 H</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6406145</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Jubin</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351177</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6808262</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chapoy et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351161</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6896368</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Baugh</name>
<date>20050500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351161</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6902273</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Suzaki et al.</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351177</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0146678</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chou et al.</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351160</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351160 R-167</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>12</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070091259</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070426</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Svochak</last-name>
<first-name>Jan Barry</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hurst</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Dixon</last-name>
<first-name>William Donald</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fort Worth</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yee</last-name>
<first-name>Duke W.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fay, III</last-name>
<first-name>Theodore D.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>TruForm Optics</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Euless</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Sugarman</last-name>
<first-name>Scott J.</first-name>
<department>2873</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Collins</last-name>
<first-name>Darryl J.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A contact lens including a single component lens sized and dimensioned for placement on a cornea of an eye. The single component lens includes a first base curve for the back surface of the single component lens, wherein the first base curve is associated with the first sub-axis; a second base curve for the back surface, wherein the second base curve is associated with the second sub-axis; a third base curve for back surface, wherein the third base curve is associated with the third sub-axis; and a fourth base curve for the back surface, wherein the fourth base curve is associated with the fourth sub-axis. The first base curve, the second base curve, the third base curve, and the fourth base curve are selected to form a shape for the back surface of the single component lens that conforms to a measured shape of the cornea.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="79.42mm" wi="82.89mm" file="US07296890-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="247.06mm" wi="160.78mm" file="US07296890-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="233.68mm" wi="161.37mm" file="US07296890-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="236.90mm" wi="151.05mm" file="US07296890-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Technical Field</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention is directed generally toward a contact lens and a method for making a contact lens. More specifically, the present invention is directed to a contact lens having a base curve that conforms closely to the shape of a cornea of an eye.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Contact lenses are becoming increasingly sophisticated in their optical characteristics. The optical characteristics of a contact lens are created by changing the nature of the front side of the contact lens. For example, a multi-focal soft contact lens that has a main carrier lens and a smaller near vision lenslet supported on the carrier lens is known. Other contact lenses change the wavefront properties of the front side of the contact lens for correcting high order aberrations. Furthermore, contact lenses may be made that are specifically tailored to an individual person's eyes.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, a problem associated with known contact lenses is maintaining the position of a contact lens on the human eye. As a person blinks and moves his or her eyes, the contact lens will move. This movement causes the contact lens to shift on the person's eye. This shift typically causes rotation of the contact lens towards the person's nose. The result of this type of rotation is that the optical axis of the contact lens no longer matches the optical axis of the eye. Because the contact lens has specially tailored optical properties that depend on the orientation of the visual axis vis-à-vis the person's eye, the movement of the contact lens can cause the person's vision to become distorted. In addition, the shifting of the contact lens can cause discomfort in the person's eye. These two factors cause many patients to be reluctant to wear specially tailored contact lenses.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The problem of fitting a contact lens on a patient's eye so that the visual axis of the contact lens matches the patient's visual axis is known. One known method of addressing the problem is to use large diameter soft contact lenses. These contact lenses use a plastic portion outside of the visual portion, or central region, of the contact lens to orient the contact lens on the patient's eye. The plastic portion increases the amount of contact lens contacting the cornea. The plastic portion also may be formed to rest against or contact the patient's eyelid or eyelids to help maintain the contact lens in a particular orientation. However, this type of contact lens is often uncomfortable for the patient.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Another presently used method of addressing the problem of sitting contact lenses is to create a toric base curve on the contact lens to create a toric lens. Generally, the base curve is the shape of the back surface of a contact lens at any particular point or associated with any particular axis defined with respect to the contact lens. The base curve of a toric lens may be defined by two perpendicular meridians that each define a spherical curve, though the radius of curvature for each meridian is different. However, the patient must have a significant amount of astigmatism or corneal deformation for this type of lens to be a viable option. In addition, a contact lens with a toric base curve will induce astigmatism that must be negated on the front surface of the lens. Further, a patient who requires only a slightly toric lens would experience more lens rotation while wearing the contact lens and which would create more visual problems. Based on the distribution of high astigmatism in the population, this type of contact lens is only suitable for between about ten percent and about twenty percent of the population.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The problems associated with seating specially tailored contact lenses have resulted in patients with unmet optical needs. Furthermore, the business of specially tailored contact lenses is limited because only a relatively small fraction of patients can or will use these types of specially tailored contact lenses. Therefore, it would be advantageous to have an improved contact lens for seating a contact lens on the cornea of an eye.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The present invention provides a contact lens. The contact lens includes a single component lens sized and dimensioned for placement on a cornea of an eye, said single component lens having a front surface and a back surface, wherein the back surface is formed to fit the cornea of the eye. The single component lens also includes a first axis defined with respect to the single component lens, wherein the first axis has a first sub-axis and a second sub-axis. The single component lens also includes a second axis defined with respect to the single component lens, wherein the second axis has a third sub-axis and a fourth sub-axis. The first axis and the second axis are orthogonal to each other. The single component lens also includes a first base curve for the back surface, wherein the first base curve is associated with the first sub-axis. The single component lens also includes a second base curve for the back surface, wherein the second base curve is associated with the second sub-axis. The single component lens also includes a third base curve for back surface, wherein the third base curve is associated with the third sub-axis. The single component lens also includes a fourth base curve for the back surface, wherein the fourth base curve is associated with the fourth sub-axis. The first base curve, the second base curve, the third base curve, and the fourth base curve are selected to form a shape for the back surface of the single component lens that conforms to a measured shape of the cornea.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The novel features believed characteristic of the invention are set forth in the appended claims. The invention itself, however, as well as a preferred mode of use, further objectives and advantages thereof, will best be understood by reference to the following detailed description of an illustrative embodiment when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a prior art method of a human placing a contact lens on the cornea of the eye, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a reference system for describing the shape of a contact lens, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a contact lens, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a cross section of a contact lens, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows a contact lens, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows a device for mapping the shape of a cornea of a human eye, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows a device for manufacturing a contact lens, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">With reference now to the figures and in particular with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a prior art method of a human <b>100</b> placing contact lens <b>102</b> on cornea <b>104</b> of eye <b>106</b>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. Contact lens <b>102</b> of the present invention may be placed onto cornea <b>104</b> of eye <b>106</b> by any convenient method, aside from using finger <b>108</b> as shown. The contact lenses of the present invention may also be sized and dimensioned for use on animal eyes, or may be sized and dimensioned as optical lenses on optical devices.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a reference system <b>200</b> for describing the shape of contact lens <b>202</b>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. Contact lens <b>202</b> may correspond to contact lens <b>102</b>. Reference system <b>200</b> includes X-axis <b>204</b>, Y-axis <b>206</b>, and Z-axis <b>208</b>. Each axis is orthogonal (perpendicular) to the other, such that a ninety degree angle exists between each axis. Any two axes are in the same plane and one axis is always perpendicular to the other two axes. Within the limits already described, each axis may be oriented in any particular manner with regard to a contact lens. However, for purposes of describing contact lenses herein, Z-axis <b>208</b> is considered to lie along the visual axis of the contact lens, such as visual axis <b>110</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>. X-axis <b>204</b> and Y-axis <b>206</b> lie in a plane in which the lowest point of the edge of the contact lens is also located, although contact lens <b>202</b> and coordinate system <b>200</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> are separated to better show the both contact lens <b>202</b> and the coordinate system <b>200</b>. The coordinate system described by X-axis <b>204</b>, Y-axis <b>206</b>, and Z-axis <b>208</b> is known as a Cartesian coordinate system.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The shape of a contact lens may also be described using other coordinate systems. For example, as further shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the shape of contact lens <b>202</b> may be described using a spherical coordinate system. A spherical coordinate system uses three terms relative to the Cartesian coordinate system. The first term is R <b>210</b>, which represents the distance between central point <b>212</b> to some other point <b>214</b>, such as a point on a contact lens. The second term is Φ <b>216</b>, which represents the angle between Z-axis <b>208</b> and R <b>210</b>. The angle Φ <b>216</b> may also be described as the polar angle. The second term Θ <b>218</b> represents the angle between X-axis <b>204</b> and line <b>220</b>. Line <b>220</b> lies in the X-Y plane defined by X-axis <b>204</b> and Y-axis <b>206</b>. Line <b>220</b> is drawn between central point <b>212</b> and second point <b>222</b>. Second point <b>222</b> lies at the intersection between second line <b>224</b> drawn between point <b>214</b> and the X-Y plane. Thus, line <b>220</b>, line <b>224</b>, and R <b>210</b> form a right triangle. The angle Θ <b>218</b> may also be referred to as the azimuth angle.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">If the values of R <b>210</b>, Φ <b>216</b>, and Θ <b>218</b> are known, then the exact point on a contact lens may be determined. Thus, the spherical coordinate system may be used to describe the shape of a contact lens.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In addition to the Cartesian coordinate system and the spherical coordinate systems described above, other coordinate systems may also be used. For example, the shape of contact lens <b>202</b> may be described using a cylindrical coordinate system, as is known in the art. Other coordinate systems may also be used to describe the shape of the contact lens. The contact lenses of the present invention are not intended to be limited by the mathematical method by which their shape is described.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a contact lens <b>300</b>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. Contact lens <b>300</b> may correspond to contact lens <b>202</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Contact lens <b>300</b> may be any type of contact lens, such as a hard contact lens, soft contact lens, or any other type of contact lens. As described further below, the base curve of contact lens <b>300</b> may be adapted to exactly conform to the shape of a particular eye. The base curve is the shape of the back surface of contact lens <b>300</b> at any particular point or associated with any particular axis.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As used herein, shape of the back surface of a contact lens is “associated with” a particular axis or sub-axis if the shape of the back surface of the contact lens varies according to a single pre-selected mathematical formula for each point along the particular axis or sub-axis. If multiple formulae are associated with multiple axes or sub-axes of the contact lens, then the overall base curve varies according to the combination of all of the formulae associated with each axis or sub-axis. Thus, the overall shape of the back surface of the contact lens may be described as a combination of sub-formulae which each define the shape of the lens associated with a given axis. This principle is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, below. Examples of formulae that describe the base curve are provided in the description of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Contact lens <b>300</b> has a base curve that is modified in sections to provide rotational stability. When a patient wears the contact lens of the present invention, the contact lens will often rotate or shift, but naturally will be urged back into alignment with the person's visual axis because the base curve of the contact lens matches the shape of the patient's cornea. Thus, rotational stability allows the lens to better fit an individual patient's eye. Rotational stability also allows the contact lens to correct high order aberrations because the ability of a contact lens to correct high order aberrations is limited by the movement of the lens on the eye.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. Contact lens <b>400</b> corresponds to contact lens <b>300</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the cross section of contact lens <b>300</b> defined along the line <b>4</b>—<b>4</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Line <b>4</b>—<b>4</b> may also be referred to as a first meridian and may be considered to lie along the Y-axis. Contact lens <b>400</b> has a height, “X,” as indicated by arrows <b>402</b>. The term “height” describes a distance along visual axis <b>404</b>. Visual axis <b>404</b> shows the orientation of the contact lens with respect to an eye. Visual axis <b>404</b> may be considered to lie along the Z-axis. Contact lens <b>400</b> has a varying thickness in this example. The thickness is defined as the distance between the back surface and the front surface. A change in the thickness of contact lens <b>400</b> changes the optical properties of contact lens <b>400</b>. The thickness of contact lens <b>400</b> is determined according to the desired optical properties of contact lens <b>400</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The shape of the cross section of contact lens <b>400</b> is aspherical. Base curve <b>406</b> of contact lens <b>400</b> is the curve defined by the shape of the back surface of the contact lens. The back surface of the contact lens is the surface that rests against and is disposed on the cornea of the eye when contact lens <b>400</b> is placed on the eye during normal use. Base curve <b>406</b> of contact lens <b>400</b> is defined by a mathematical sub-formula that defines an aspherical curve. For example, base curve <b>406</b> may be an ellipse, though base curve <b>406</b> may have any shape, including an irregular shape.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a single cross section of contact lens <b>300</b> along first meridian <b>4</b>—<b>4</b>. In addition, a series of cross sections drawn along lines parallel to first meridian <b>4</b>—<b>4</b> are governed by the same mathematical sub-formula that defines base curve <b>406</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Thus, the shape of base curve <b>406</b> along any cross section drawn parallel to first meridian <b>4</b>—<b>4</b> corresponds to the shape of base curve <b>406</b> at first meridian <b>4</b>—<b>4</b>. Thus, the entire back surface of contact lens <b>300</b> associated with the Y-axis has an aspherical shape.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens <b>500</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. Contact lens <b>500</b> corresponds to contact lens <b>300</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows the cross section of contact lens <b>300</b> defined along the line <b>5</b>—<b>5</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Line <b>5</b>—<b>5</b> may also be referred to as a second meridian and may be considered to lie along the X-axis. First meridian <b>4</b>—<b>4</b> intersects second meridian <b>5</b>—<b>5</b> in the visual center, or apex, of contact lens <b>300</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. First meridian <b>4</b>—<b>4</b> and second meridian <b>5</b>—<b>5</b> are orthogonal, or perpendicular, to each other. Contact lens <b>500</b> has a height, “X,” as indicated by arrows <b>502</b>. The term “height” describes a distance along visual axis <b>504</b>. The height, “X” in both <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is the same to indicate that the highest point along the visual axis in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is the same as the highest point along the visual axis shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Visual axis <b>504</b> shows the orientation of the contact lens with respect to an eye. Visual axis <b>504</b> may be considered to lie along the Z-axis. Contact lens <b>500</b> has a varying thickness, wherein the thickness is defined as the distance between the back surface and the front surface as measured along a line perpendicular to the back surface of contact lens <b>500</b>. A change in the thickness of contact lens <b>500</b> changes the optical properties of contact lens <b>500</b>. The thickness of contact lens <b>500</b> is determined according to the desired optical properties of contact lens <b>500</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The shape of the cross section of contact lens <b>500</b> is spherical in this example. Thus, base curve <b>506</b> of contact lens <b>500</b> cross section <b>5</b>—<b>5</b> is defined as part of a sphere. Base curve <b>506</b> of contact lens <b>500</b> is the curve defined by the back surface of the contact lens. The back surface of the contact lens is the surface that rests against and is disposed on the cornea of the eye when contact lens <b>500</b> is placed on the eye. Base curve <b>506</b> of contact lens <b>500</b> is defined by a mathematical sub-formula that defines a spherical curve.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a single cross section of contact lens <b>300</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> along second meridian <b>5</b>—<b>5</b>. In addition, a series of cross sections drawn along lines parallel to second meridian <b>5</b>—<b>5</b> are governed by the same mathematical sub-formula that defines base curve <b>506</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. Thus, the shape of base curve <b>506</b> along any cross section drawn parallel to second meridian <b>5</b>—<b>5</b> corresponds to the shape of base curve <b>506</b> at second meridian <b>5</b>—<b>5</b>. Thus, the entire back surface of contact lens <b>300</b> associated with the X-axis has a spherical shape.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Contact lens <b>300</b> described in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> through <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> has a spherical base curve associated with the X-axis and an aspherical base curve associated with the Y-axis. Thus, contact lens <b>300</b> may be described as a spherical-aspherical contact lens. A spherical-aspherical contact lens may be used by patients having astigmatism or other deformity of the eye. Because the mathematical sub-formulae that control the base curves along the two meridians are known, the exact shape of spherical-aspherical contact lens may be precisely controlled. The base curve of spherical-aspherical contact lens <b>300</b> will more closely conform to the shape of the patient's eye relative to the base curve of known contact lenses. Thus, not only will the patient be more comfortable with the contact lens on the patient's eye, but the orientation of the contact lens while on the eye will be less likely to shift. For this reason, any wavefront properties created on the front surface, or the surface opposite the back surface, of contact lens <b>300</b> will maintain a desired orientation. Wavefront properties correct for higher order aberrations, such as coma, spherical aberration, and other aberrations that affect the person's vision. Accordingly, patients who use the contact lens of the present invention are less likely to see visual disturbances caused by a shift in orientation of contact lens <b>300</b> and are likely to have their vision corrected by contact lens <b>300</b> in a desired manner. Additionally, contact lens <b>300</b> is more comfortable to wear because contact lens <b>300</b> conforms to the shape of the particular patient's cornea.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a cross section of a contact lens <b>600</b>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the cross section shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is drawn along meridian <b>4</b>—<b>4</b>, though contact lens <b>600</b> is different than contact lens <b>300</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Like contact lens <b>300</b>, contact lens <b>600</b> has a base curve <b>604</b> that is aspherical. However, the thickness and the shape of the front surface <b>606</b> of contact lens <b>600</b> vary in an irregular manner. For example, the thickness of contact lens <b>600</b> abruptly changes at the areas generally indicated by area <b>608</b> and area <b>610</b>. The thickness and shape of contact lens <b>600</b> changes more abruptly at area <b>608</b> relative to area <b>610</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The purpose of the change in thickness in contact lens <b>600</b> is to provide the optical properties required to correct the vision of one eye of a particular patient. However, the optical properties of contact lens <b>600</b>, vis-à-vis the eye of the patient, depend on the orientation of contact lens <b>600</b> on the eye. Thus, base curve <b>604</b> of contact lens <b>600</b> is controlled, as described in relation to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, such that contact lens <b>600</b> conforms to the shape of the eye of the patient. Accordingly, visual axis <b>602</b> of contact lens <b>600</b> will tend to maintain an alignment with the visual axis of the patient's eye. For this reason, the optical effect of contact lens <b>600</b> tends to maintain a desired effect as long as contact lens <b>600</b> is worn.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the cross section shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is drawn along meridian <b>4</b>—<b>4</b>, though contact lens <b>700</b> is different than contact lens <b>300</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Like contact lens <b>300</b>, contact lens <b>700</b> has a base curve <b>704</b> that is spherical. However, the thickness and the shape of the front surface <b>706</b> of contact lens <b>700</b> vary in an irregular manner. For example, the thickness of contact lens <b>700</b> abruptly changes at the areas generally indicated by area <b>708</b> and area <b>710</b>. The thickness and shape of contact lens <b>700</b> changes more abruptly at area <b>708</b> relative to area <b>710</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The purpose of the change in thickness in contact lens <b>700</b> is to provide the exact optical properties required to correct the vision of one eye of a particular patient. However, the optical effect of contact lens <b>700</b>, vis-à-vis the eye of the patient, depends on the orientation of contact lens <b>700</b> on the eye. Thus, base curve <b>704</b> of contact lens <b>700</b> is controlled, as described in relation to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, such that contact lens <b>700</b> conforms to the shape of the eye of the patient. Also as described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, contact lens <b>600</b>/<b>700</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> may be referred to as a spherical-aspherical contact lens. The spherical-aspherical shape of back curve <b>604</b>/<b>704</b> helps visual axis <b>702</b> of contact lens <b>700</b> to maintain an alignment with the visual axis of the patient's eye. For this reason, the optical effect of contact lens <b>700</b> tends to maintain a desired effect as long as contact lens <b>700</b> is worn.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows a contact lens <b>800</b>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. The contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows that the meridians shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> may be further subdivided into sub-meridians or sub-axes. Axis <b>802</b> is perpendicular or orthogonal to axis <b>804</b>. Axis <b>802</b> may be subdivided into sub-axis <b>806</b> and sub-axis <b>808</b>. Likewise, axis <b>804</b> may be subdivided into sub-axis <b>810</b>, and sub-axis <b>812</b>. Sub-axis <b>806</b> and sub-axis <b>808</b> are bisected by axis <b>804</b>. Similarly, sub-axis <b>810</b> and sub-axis <b>812</b> are bisected by axis <b>802</b>. The back surface of the contact lens has a first base curve associated with the first sub-axis. The back surface of the contact lens has a second base curve associated with the second sub-axis. The back surface of the contact lens has a third base curve associated with the third sub-axis. The back surface of the contact lens has a fourth base curve associated with the fourth sub-axis. In the contact lens in aspects of the present invention, the first base curve, the second base curve, the third base curve, and the fourth base curve are individually controlled such that a shape of the back surface of the contact lens conforms to a measured shape of a cornea of a human.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Contact lens <b>800</b> may also be considered to be subdivided into four sections, section A <b>810</b>, section B <b>812</b>, section C <b>814</b>, and section D <b>816</b>. The base curve of contact lens <b>800</b> may be individually controlled in each section by controlling mathematical equations that describe the shape of contact lens <b>800</b> associated with any given sub-axis. Thus, as a whole, the base curve of contact lens <b>800</b> conforms very closely to the cornea of an eye of a patient. The very close fit of the contact lens increases the usefulness of the optical properties of the contact lens, because the position of the contact lens on the eye is more likely to cause the visual axis of the contact lens to remain in a constant position relative to the visual axis of the patient.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In addition, each sub-axis may be further sub-divided into smaller sub-axes. Further sub-dividing each axis increases the level of control a manufacturer has when defining or manufacturing the base curve of the contact lens. Each individual sub-axis will have a curvature associated with it, such that the base curve can be controlled exactly at any point on contact lens <b>800</b>. Similarly, further sub-dividing each axis creates a larger number of sectors, other than the four sectors <b>814</b>, <b>816</b>, <b>818</b>, and <b>820</b> shown. Further sub-dividing each axis creates sectors defined by portions of circular sectors, where a particular sector is defined by the circular sector defined by the farthest points on two adjacent sub-axes less than the circular sector defined by the closest points on two adjacent axes. The terms “farthest” and “closest” are relative to the center of contact lens <b>800</b>. Each particular sector may have a different base curve associated with it.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Still further, each individual axis <b>802</b> and <b>804</b> need not be divided evenly, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. Similarly, if each sub-axis <b>814</b>, <b>816</b>, <b>818</b>, and <b>820</b> is further sub-divided, then each sub-division need not be divided evenly. Thus, a portion of each sub-axis may be longer than another portion. Each portion of a sub-axis may have an individual curvature associated with it, such that the base curve can be controlled in the manner described above.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">In one example, the curvature of the base curve associated with sub-axis <b>806</b> is the same as the curvature of the base curve associated with sub-axis <b>808</b> such that the curvature of the base curve associated with axis <b>802</b> is spherical. In this case, the radius of curvature in Cartesian coordinates is r=SQRT(x^2+y^2). For the same contact lens, the curvature of the base curve associated with sub-axis <b>810</b> is the same as the curvature of the base curve associated with sub-axis <b>812</b> such that the curvature of the base curve associated with axis <b>804</b> is aspherical. In this case, the radius of curvature in Cartesian coordinates is r=(p*x^2+y^2)/2x where p=1−e and e is the eccentricity. In the case where e=0, the aspherical equation yields a sphere. Thus, r is the same at the center of the contact lens, as defined by the visual axis. In another example, the base curve associated with both axis <b>802</b> and axis <b>804</b> may be defined by the aspherical equation.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In another example, the equations for defining the base curve of a contact lens may be expressed in terms of R, the apical radius, D, the diameter of the contact lens, e, the eccentricity, p, which is defined as 1−e^2, and Z, the sagittal of the lens at X where X−D/2. In this case for a spherical meridian, Z=R−SQRT(R^2−(D/2)^2). For an aspherical meridian, Z=(R−SQRT(R^2−p*(D/2)^2))/p</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Contact lens <b>800</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> may be reduced to contact lens <b>300</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. In this case, the first base curve, associated with sub-axis <b>806</b>, is the same as the second base curve, associated with sub-axis <b>808</b>, such that contact lens <b>800</b> has a base curve defined associated with axis <b>802</b> according to a single mathematical formula. Similarly, the third base curve, associated with axis <b>810</b>, is the same as the fourth base curve, associated with axis <b>810</b>, such that contact lens <b>800</b> has a base curve defined associated with axis <b>804</b> according to a single, though different, mathematical formula. For the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the base curve associated with axis <b>802</b> is spherical. The base curve associated with axis <b>804</b> is aspherical. Accordingly, contact lens <b>800</b> may be reduced to the spherical-aspherical contact lens <b>300</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">However, contact lens <b>800</b> shows a general method of defining and controlling the base curve of a contact lens in these illustrative examples. For example, the base curve associated with each sub-axis may be different relative to the base curve associated with each other sub-axis. The base curve associated with first sub-axis <b>806</b> may be different than the base curve associated with second sub-axis <b>808</b>. The base curve associated with third sub-axis <b>810</b> may be different than the fourth base curve associated with sub-axis <b>812</b>. The base curve associated with any of sub-axes <b>806</b>, <b>808</b>, <b>810</b>, or <b>812</b> may be irregular, uniform, spherical, aspherical, or adapted to conform to any mathematical equation that defines a surface in any given coordinate system. Thus, for example, the base curve of contact lens <b>800</b> may be different in sector A <b>814</b>, sector B <b>816</b>, sector C <b>818</b>, and sector D <b>820</b>. In a more specific example, the base curve in sector A <b>814</b> is steepened, the base curve in sector C <b>818</b> is flatter, and the base curve in sector B <b>816</b> and sector D <b>820</b> are the same, though different than the base curve s in sector A <b>814</b> and sector D <b>820</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Contact lens <b>800</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> and contact lens <b>300</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> also may be described in terms of spherical coordinates. Because a contact lens described in terms of polar coordinates is the same as the same contact lens described in terms of Cartesian coordinates, the contact lens has a back surface which is disposed on the cornea of the eye when the contact lens is placed on the eye. The contact lens also has a front surface opposite the back surface. The shape of the back surface is mapped according to spherical coordinates. As described above, spherical coordinates for a contact lens include a radius defined by a distance between a fixed point and a point on the back surface of the contact lens, an azimuth angle defined relative to a first axis associated with the contact lens and a second fixed axis associated with the contact lens, and a polar angle defined relative to a third axis associated with the contact lens. In the example shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the fixed point is the intersection of all three axes, the first axis is X-axis <b>204</b>, the second axis is Y-axis <b>206</b>, and the third axis is Z-axis <b>208</b>. However, the designation of which axis is “X,” “Y,” and “Z” may vary as the orientations of the axes only change how the shape of the contact lens is described, and do not change the actual shape of the contact lens. In any case, the radius varies according to a first formula as the azimuth angle is varied. The radius varies according to a second formula as the polar angle is varied. If the first formula and the second formula are different, then the back surface of the contact lens may have, for example, a spherical-aspherical shape as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In another example, the first formula and/or the second formula may include sub-formulae that change at the instant that the polar angle and/or the azimuth angle reach specified values. For example, the first formula may include a first sub-formula and a second sub-formula. The first sub-formula applies when the azimuth angle varies between 0 degrees and 90 degrees and the second sub-formula applies when the azimuth angle varies between 90 degrees and 180 degrees. Similarly, the second formula may include a third sub-formula and a fourth sub-formula. The third sub-formula applies when the polar angle varies between −90 degrees and 0 degrees. The fourth sub-formula applies when the polar angle varies between 1 degree and 90 degrees. By controlling which equations apply to each different sector on the contact lens, the base curve may be precisely controlled. Thus, for example, the base curve of contact lens <b>800</b> may be different in sector A <b>914</b>, sector B <b>816</b>, Sector C <b>818</b>, and Sector D <b>820</b>, as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Thus, in an exemplary contact lens, the apex of the contact lens is at the point where the radius intersects the contact lens and the polar angle is 90 degrees. In the exemplary contact lens, the first formula comprises a first sub-formula, a second sub-formula, a third sub-formula, and a fourth sub-formula. The radius varies according to the first sub-formula as the azimuth angle varies and wherein the azimuth angle is between about 0 degrees about 90 degrees and the polar angle is between about 0 degrees and about 90 degrees. The radius varies according to the second sub-formula as the azimuth angle varies and wherein the azimuth angle is between about 90 degrees about 180 degrees and the polar angle is between about 0 degrees and about 90 degrees. The radius varies according to the third sub-formula as the azimuth angle varies and wherein the azimuth angle is between about 180 degrees about 270 degrees and the polar angle is between about 0 degrees and about 90 degrees. The radius varies according to the fourth sub-formula as the azimuth angle varies and wherein the azimuth angle is between about 270 degrees about 360 degrees and the polar angle is between about 0 degrees and about 90 degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">For the above description of contact lens <b>800</b> in terms of spherical coordinates, the base curve of the contact lens may be considered to vary according to four different formulae across four sub-meridians because the exemplary angles described above vary exactly along meridian lines <b>802</b> and <b>804</b>. Similarly, the exemplary angles described above vary exactly along sub-meridians <b>806</b>, <b>808</b>, <b>810</b>, and <b>812</b>. Thus, the same contact lens described vis-à-vis <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> may be described using spherical coordinates.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. Exemplary contact lens <b>900</b> corresponds to contact lens <b>800</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> and the cross section of contact lens <b>900</b> is shown along line <b>9</b>—<b>9</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. Thus, sector A <b>902</b> corresponds to sector A <b>814</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> and sector B <b>904</b> corresponds to sector D <b>820</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. Axis <b>906</b> corresponds to the visual axis of contact lens <b>900</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Exemplary contact lens <b>900</b> has a front surface <b>906</b> that has a relatively constant curvature. However, the back surface <b>908</b> has a base curve that varies. Specifically, the base curve in sector D <b>904</b> is greater than the base curve in sector A <b>902</b>. Thus, the portion of the contact lens in sector D <b>904</b> is thicker than the portion of the contact lens in sector A <b>902</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Contact lens <b>900</b> may be formed by controlling the base curve according to the methods described vis-à-vis <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> through <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> and in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>. The base curve of contact lens <b>900</b>, in this example, has a shape that exactly conforms to the measured shape of a particular patient's eye. Thus, contact lens <b>900</b> will rest comfortably on the patient's eye and tend to maintain the same orientation on the eye.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows a cross section of the contact lens shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. Exemplary contact lens <b>1000</b> corresponds to contact lens <b>800</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> and the cross section of contact lens <b>1000</b> is shown along line <b>10</b>—<b>10</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. Thus, sector B <b>1002</b> corresponds to sector B <b>816</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> and sector C <b>1004</b> corresponds to sector C <b>818</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. Axis <b>1006</b> corresponds to the visual axis of contact lens <b>1000</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Exemplary contact lens <b>1000</b> has a front surface <b>1006</b> that has a relatively constant curvature, though the front side may have a different curvature or may be provided with different components to modify the optical properties of contact lens <b>1000</b>. Similarly, back surface <b>1008</b> has a relatively constant base curve. Thus, the portion of the contact lens in sector B <b>1002</b> has the same thickness as the portion of the contact lens in sector C <b>1004</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Contact lens <b>800</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> through <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows that one may control the base curve of a contact lens exactly. Control over the base curve of contact lens <b>800</b> is accomplished by controlling how the shape of the back surface is formed along meridians <b>802</b> and <b>804</b> and along sub-meridians <b>806</b>, <b>808</b>, <b>810</b>, and <b>812</b>. Each individual sub-meridian <b>806</b>, <b>808</b>, <b>810</b>, and <b>812</b> has a base curve associated with it. The first base curve, the second base curve, the third base curve, and the fourth base curve are individually controlled such that a shape of the back surface of the contact lens conforms to a measured shape of a cornea of a human. Similarly, the shape of the back surface of contact lens <b>800</b> may be controlled according to a spherical coordinate system, as described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> through <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows a device for mapping the shape of a cornea of a human eye, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. A human <b>1100</b> presses his face into visor <b>1002</b> of device <b>1004</b>, with the eyes looking straight into visor <b>1002</b>. Device <b>1004</b> is adapted to measure the exact shape of the cornea of each of the human's eyes. Device <b>1004</b> produces a corneal shape map for each eye. Using the methods and devices described herein, a contact lens may be formed wherein the base curve of the contact lens has a shape corresponding to the corneal shape map. For example, the base curve associated with each meridian of the contact lens may be controlled such that the contact lens matches a spherical-aspherical corneal shape map, such as when the patient has an astigmatism, or may be controlled such that the contact lens matches an irregular corneal shape map, such as when the patient has a condition that deforms the shape of the cornea.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">In addition, the device shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> may measure other qualities of a patient's eye. For example, device <b>1104</b> may map the wavefront profile of the eye using a wavefront analyzer. Similarly, device <b>1104</b> may include an aberrometer for precisely measuring the higher order aberrations seen by a patient. Device <b>1104</b> may also produce a power map showing the optical corrections needed for a particular patient. Thus, a map of the shape of the cornea may also include a power map and may include other information describing the wavefront profile of the eye. A wavefront profile may be expressed as a Zernike polynomial. An example of a Zernike polynomial is SQRT(5)*[6r^4−6(1+e^2)r^2+(1+e^2+e^4)]/(1−e^2)^2 where r is the radius of the pupil and e is the annulus of the optical element. Additional information on Zernike polynomials may be found in reference texts.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows a device for manufacturing a contact lens, in accordance with an illustrative embodiment of the present invention. Device <b>1200</b> is capable of manufacturing contact lenses. Device <b>1200</b> may be modified and adapted to manufacture contact lenses according to the methods described herein. Device <b>1200</b> includes a lathe <b>1202</b> and one or more anvils <b>1206</b>, <b>1208</b>, and <b>1200</b>. Contact lens <b>1204</b> rests on the end of lathe <b>1202</b>. A motor within device <b>1200</b> rotates lathe <b>1202</b>. Other components are provided such that lathe <b>1202</b> may translate inwardly and outwardly as well as transversely with respect to anvils <b>1206</b>, <b>1208</b>, and <b>1210</b>. Computer programs or software control the motion and operation of device <b>1200</b> such that the base curve of a contact lens may be precisely controlled according to the methods described herein. Computer programs for controlling the lathe may be stored on a physical computer usable medium and executed by a processor. The physical computer usable medium and the processor are connected by a bus such that the hardware components may communicate with each other. The processor, bus, and physical computer usable medium together form a computer. The computer is also operably connected to lathe <b>1202</b> or built into lathe <b>1202</b> such that the computer program together with the computer may control the movement and actions of lathe <b>1202</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Regarding the software for controlling the manufacturing process for the content lens of the present invention, the present invention can take the form of an entirely hardware embodiment, an entirely software embodiment or an embodiment containing both hardware and software elements. In an illustrative embodiment, the invention is implemented in software, which includes but is not limited to firmware, resident software, microcode, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Furthermore, the invention can take the form of a computer program product accessible from a computer-usable or computer-readable medium providing program code for use by or in connection with a computer or any instruction execution system. For the purposes of this description, a computer-usable or computer readable medium can be any apparatus that can contain, store, communicate, propagate, or transport the program for use by or in connection with the instruction execution system, apparatus, or device.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The medium can be an electronic, magnetic, optical, electromagnetic, infrared, or semiconductor system (or apparatus or device) or a propagation medium. Examples of a computer-readable medium include a semiconductor or solid state memory, magnetic tape, a removable computer diskette, a random access memory (RAM), a read-only memory (ROM), a rigid magnetic disk and an optical disk. Current examples of optical disks include compact disk—read only memory (CD-ROM), compact disk—read/write (CD-R/W) and DVD.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">A data processing system suitable for storing and/or executing program code will include at least one processor coupled directly or indirectly to memory elements through a system bus. The memory elements can include local memory employed during actual execution of the program code, bulk storage, and cache memories which provide temporary storage of at least some program code in order to reduce the number of times code must be retrieved from bulk storage during execution. Thus, memory elements such as RAM, ROM, and various other forms of memory may be storage devices connected to a bus.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Input/output or I/O devices (including but not limited to keyboards, displays, pointing devices, etc.) can be coupled to the system either directly or through intervening I/O controllers.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Network adapters may also be coupled to the system to enable the data processing system to become coupled to other data processing systems or remote printers or storage devices through intervening private or public networks. Modems, cable modem and Ethernet cards are just a few of the currently available types of network adapters.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Although device <b>1200</b> is adapted to manufacture hard contact lenses, the methods and devices described herein may be adapted to manufacture soft contact lenses and other kinds of optical lenses. Thus, the description of the present invention has been presented for purposes of illustration and description, and is not intended to be exhaustive or limited to the invention in the form disclosed. Many modifications and variations will be apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art. The embodiment was chosen and described in order to best explain the principles of the invention, the practical application, and to enable others of ordinary skill in the art to understand the invention for various embodiments with various modifications as are suited to the particular use contemplated.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A single component contact lens comprising:
<claim-text>a front surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a back surface formed to fit a cornea of an eye;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first axis, wherein the first axis has a first sub-axis and a second sub-axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second axis, wherein the first axis and the second axis are orthogonal to each other and wherein the second axis has a third sub-axis and a fourth sub-axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first base curve for the back surface, wherein the first base curve is associated with the first sub-axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second base curve for the back surface, wherein the second base curve is associated with the second sub-axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third base curve for back surface, wherein the third base curve is associated with the third sub-axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth base curve for the back surface, wherein the fourth base curve is associated with the fourth sub-axis, wherein the first base curve, the second base curve, the third base curve, and the fourth base curve are selected to form a shape for the back surface that conforms to a measured shape of the cornea.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the first base curve and the second base curve are equal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first base curve and the second base curve are spherical;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the third base curve and the fourth base curve are equal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the third base curve and the fourth base curve are aspherical.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first base curve is different than the second base curve and the third base curve is different than the fourth base curve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first base curve is irregular and the second base curve is uniform.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the third base curve is irregular and the fourth base curve is uniform.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first base curve is aspherical and the second base curve is spherical.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the third base curve is aspherical and the second base curve is spherical.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A single component contact lens comprising:
<claim-text>a front surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a back surface formed to fit a cornea of an eye; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shape for the back surface that is mapped according to spherical coordinates, wherein the spherical coordinates comprises a radius defined by a distance between a fixed point and a point on the back surface, an azimuth angle defined relative to a first fixed axis associated with the single component lens and a second fixed axis associated with the single component lens, and a polar angle defined relative to a third axis associated with the single component lens, wherein the radius varies according to a first formula as the azimuth angle is varied, wherein the radius varies according to a second formula as the polar angle is varied, and wherein the first formula and the second formula are different.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the first formula results in the back surface having a spherical base curve as the azimuth angle is varied.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the second formula results in the back surface having an aspherical base curve as the polar angle is varied.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the first formula results in the back surface having an irregular base curve as the azimuth angle is varied.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein the second formula results in the back surface having an irregular base curve as the polar angle is varied.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the first formula and the second formula are individually defined such that the shape of the back surface of the single component lens conforms to the measured shape of a cornea of a human.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the center of the single component lens is at the point where the radius intersects the single component lens and where the polar angle is 90 degrees;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first formula comprises a first sub-formula, a second sub-formula, a third sub-formula, and a fourth sub-formula;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the radius varies according to the first sub-formula as the azimuth angle varies and wherein the azimuth angle is between about 0 degrees about 90 degrees and the polar angle is between about 0 degrees and about 90 degrees;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the radius varies according to the second sub-formula as the azimuth angle varies and wherein the azimuth angle is between about 90 degrees about 180 degrees and the polar angle is between about 0 degrees and about 90 degrees;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the radius varies according to the third sub-formula as the azimuth angle varies and wherein the azimuth angle is between about 180 degrees about 270 degrees and the polar angle is between about 0 degrees and about 90 degrees; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the radius varies according to the fourth sub-formula as the azimuth angle varies and wherein the azimuth angle is between about 270 degrees about 360 degrees and the polar angle is between about 0 degrees and about 90 degrees.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the first sub-formula, the second sub-formula, the third sub-formula, and the fourth sub-formula are all different.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The single component contact lens of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the first sub-formula, the second sub-formula, the third sub-formula, and the fourth sub-formula are individually defined such that a shape of the back surface of the single component lens will conform to a measured shape of a cornea of a human.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
