<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297956-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297956</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11189453</doc-number>
<date>20050726</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>232</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>T</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>25036308</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Methods and apparatus for small footprint imaging system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4209706</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nunan</name>
<date>19800600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>378189</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4426578</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bradcovich et al.</name>
<date>19840100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>25036308</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5577094</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fudamoto</name>
<date>19961100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>378197</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6147352</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ashburn</name>
<date>20001100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6160258</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Maor</name>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6180943</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lange</name>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>25036305</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>31</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378189</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378197</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>378198</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>25036308</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>25036305</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070025522</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070201</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fenster</last-name>
<first-name>Paul</first-name>
<address>
<city>Petach Tikva</city>
<country>IL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>IL</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>IL</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kariv</last-name>
<first-name>Dov</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kfar Vradim</city>
<country>IL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>IL</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>IL</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Small</last-name>
<first-name>Dean D.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Small Patent Law Group</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>General Electric Company</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Schenectady</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hannaher</last-name>
<first-name>Constantine</first-name>
<department>2884</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method and system for imaging a patient is provided. The system includes an arcuate detector transport member that extends circumferentially about an examination axis, a base comprising an arcuate transport element configured to receive the detector transport member wherein the base is configured to translate the arcuate detector transport member in an arcuate path about the examination axis, and at least one gamma camera detector coupled to the detector transport member.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="165.86mm" wi="137.75mm" file="US07297956-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="191.26mm" wi="145.71mm" file="US07297956-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="167.39mm" wi="115.65mm" file="US07297956-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="187.20mm" wi="137.92mm" file="US07297956-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates generally to imaging systems, and more particularly to a movable imaging system detector support apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Imaging devices, such as gamma cameras and computed tomography (CT) imaging systems, are used in the medical field to detect radioactive emission events emanating from an object, and to detect transmission x-rays or transmission gamma rays attenuated by the object, respectively. An output, typically in the form of an image that graphically illustrates the distribution of the emissions within the object and/or the distribution of attenuation of the object is formed from these detections. An imaging device may have one or more detectors that detect the number of emissions, for example, gamma rays in the range of about seventy keV to about six hundred keV, and may have one or more detectors to detect x-rays and/or gamma rays that have passed through the object.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Some known imaging systems include a closed ring gantry. To image a patient using a closed ring gantry, the patient ingresses and egresses the viewing area using a long travel bed that moves the patient longitudinally along an examination axis. However, such an ingress/egress configuration requires additional examining room floor space. This additional floor space is not usable during an imaging scan, but must be available during a scan to allow egress of the patient at the completion of the scan. A closed-ring gantry is also known to be less comfortable for the patient due to the claustrophobically close clearances of the gantry to the patient.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">U.S. Pat. No. 6,147,352 describes a gamma camera comprising a gamma camera head. The head is enclosed within a stationary carrier which extends more than 180 degrees (but less than 360°) around the patient. The gamma camera head moves along rails within the carrier to provide nuclear medicine images having views over 180° around the patient.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Nucline™ Cardio-C marketed by Medisco Medical Imaging Systems of Budapest, Hungary, is a dual head gamma camera in which the heads are enclosed within a stationary carrier. The dual heads rotate at least 90° about the patent along rails within the stationary carrier to provide views over a range of 180°.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In one embodiment, a medical imaging system is provided. The medical imaging system includes an arcuate detector transport member that extends circumferentially about an examination axis, a base including an arcuate transport element configured to receive the detector transport member such that the detector transport member is supported by a rolling member wherein the base is configured to translate the arcuate detector transport member along the rolling member in an arcuate path about the examination axis, and at least one gamma camera detector coupled to the detector transport member.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In another embodiment, a method of imaging a patient is provided. The method includes coupling at least one detector to a detector transport member, the at least one detector configured to move with the detector transport member, the detector transport member spanning an arc of less than about one hundred eighty degrees about an examination axis, supporting the detector transport member with a base having a support assembly that includes rolling elements wherein the support assembly is configured to engage the detector transport member, and rotating the detector transport member on the rolling elements through a predetermined path about the examination axis to a plurality of imaging positions.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In yet another embodiment, a method for medical imaging is provided. The method includes coupling at least one nuclear medicine detector to a detector transport member, supporting the detector transport member with an arcuate base having an arcuate support assembly configured to receive the detector transport member, the base remaining stationary with respect to an examination axis, and translating the detector transport member along an arcuate path about the examination axis.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side elevation view of an imaging system in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention in a first imaging position;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a side elevation view of the imaging system shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in an exemplary second imaging position; and</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevation view of the imaging system shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in an exemplary third imaging position.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a side elevation view of an imaging system <b>100</b> in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention. Imaging system <b>100</b> includes a base <b>102</b> that may be configured to be fixedly coupled to, for example, a floor surface <b>104</b>, a ceiling surface <b>106</b>, and/or a wall surface <b>108</b> or by simply resting base <b>102</b> on floor surface <b>104</b> such that imaging system <b>100</b> is balanced and stable. Base <b>102</b> may be coupled to floor surface <b>104</b>, ceiling surface <b>106</b>, and/or wall surface <b>108</b> by, for example, welding, threaded fasteners, and/or clamping fasteners. Imaging system <b>100</b> may weigh several thousand pounds. In a configuration wherein imaging system <b>100</b> is coupled to ceiling surface <b>106</b>, and/or wall surface <b>108</b>, an additional support (not shown) may be used to further support base <b>102</b> from floor surface <b>104</b>. Base <b>102</b> includes a support portion <b>110</b> and a stator portion <b>112</b>. In the exemplary embodiment, stator portion <b>112</b> is substantially arcuately-shaped about an examination axis <b>114</b> of an examination area <b>116</b> that is generally circular about examination axis <b>114</b>. A portion of stator portion <b>112</b> is open such that a subject may enter the examination area <b>116</b> perpendicularly to examination axis <b>114</b>. A transport base structure <b>117</b> may be coupled to stator portion <b>112</b> to provide an arcuate path of motion for a detector transport member <b>122</b>, in a direction <b>152</b> that partially circumscribes examination area <b>116</b>. In the exemplary embodiment, transport element is defined by a plurality of rolling members, such as, radially outer leading wheels <b>118</b> and radially inner leading wheels <b>120</b> that are rotatably coupled to stator portion <b>112</b> in two substantially concentric arcs about examination axis <b>114</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Detector transport member <b>122</b> includes an arcuately-shaped body having guide members, such as a radially outer peripheral edge <b>126</b> and a radially inner peripheral edge <b>128</b>. Transport base element <b>117</b> is configured to engage detector transport member <b>122</b> to permit detector transport member <b>122</b> to move in an arcuate path about examination area <b>116</b>. In the exemplary embodiment, wheels <b>118</b> and <b>120</b> may engage outer peripheral edge <b>126</b> and inner peripheral edge <b>128</b> in rolling engagement. In an alternative embodiment, a guide member, such as an interior edge (not shown) is formed along detector transport member <b>122</b> between outer peripheral edge <b>126</b> and inner peripheral edge <b>128</b> and wheels <b>118</b> and <b>120</b> engage the interior edge. A detector transport drive <b>129</b> includes a prime mover, such as a motor and a means to transfer rotational power from the motor to detector transport member <b>122</b>. In one embodiment, detector transport drive <b>129</b> includes a motor mounted to stator <b>112</b>. The motor includes a pinion (not shown) coupled to the motor shaft and detector transport drive <b>129</b> also includes a rack (not shown) coupled to detector transport member <b>122</b>. In combination, the pinion and rack transfer rotational power from the motor to detector transport member <b>122</b> to drive detector transport member <b>122</b> through an arcuate path about examination area <b>116</b> during a scan. In other various embodiments, detector transport drive <b>129</b> includes other drive components, such as a belt and sheave arrangement or a chain and sprocket drive.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In the exemplary embodiment, two gamma camera radiation detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> each optionally having a substantially rectangular polyhedrally shaped body are mounted on or otherwise coupled to detector transport member <b>122</b>. An edge <b>144</b> of a detecting face <b>146</b> of gamma camera radiation detector <b>140</b> is optionally arranged to be proximate an edge <b>148</b> of a detecting face <b>150</b> of gamma camera radiation detector <b>142</b> wherein detecting faces <b>146</b> and <b>150</b> are oriented substantially perpendicular with respect to each other. In an alternative embodiment, gamma camera radiation detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> may be oriented in an angle other than ninety degrees with respect to each other. In another alternative embodiment, only one of gamma camera radiation detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> is used such that imaging system <b>100</b> only includes a single gamma camera radiation detector <b>140</b>. Generally, either or both of gamma camera radiation detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> are oriented such that a normal centerline of a face of the at least one detector is oriented substantially orthogonally to examination axis <b>114</b>, but gamma camera radiation detector <b>140</b> may be oriented at other angles with respect to examination axis <b>114</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In the exemplary embodiment, both of detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> are used for emission imaging. Detector <b>142</b> and/or detector <b>140</b> may be simultaneously used for transmission imaging with a source (not shown), for example, but, not limited to a transmission x-ray source and/or a transmission gamma source positioned opposite the detector, providing x-ray photons and/or transmission gamma rays at an energy level that may be different than the emission gamma energy levels. The detector collects both emission gammas and transmission x-ray photons and/or transmission gamma rays, identifies the different photon energy levels and generates transmission data simultaneously. The two detector arrangement allows performing a scan of about one hundred eighty degrees about examination axis <b>114</b> while moving detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> only through about ninety degrees of rotation about examination axis <b>114</b>. The two detector arrangement also allows performing a scan of a region of a patient from two view angles simultaneously.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Detector transport member <b>122</b> is configured to translate gamma camera radiation detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> along arcuate path <b>152</b> at least partially circumscribing examination axis <b>114</b>. Detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> may include a tilting base (not shown) configured to modify the alignment of detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> with respect to examination axis <b>114</b>. Detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> may be coupled to detector transport member <b>122</b> such that detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> move along an arcuate path with detector transport member <b>122</b> and do not substantially move along the arcuate path with respect to detector transport member <b>122</b>. Detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> may include radiation detectors constructed from, for example, scintillation materials such as sodium iodide or cesium iodide with associated photomultiplier tubes or other photo-detectors such as solid state photodiodes, radiation-sensitive scintillation material and a light detecting device, or may be fabricated from a semiconductor radiation detector including, for example, but not limited to, cadmium zinc telluride (CZT).</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In a first position <b>170</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, detector transport member <b>122</b> may be positioned such that detector <b>140</b> is located beneath examination axis <b>114</b> and detector <b>142</b> is located in an adjacent position.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a side elevation view of imaging system <b>100</b> in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention. In a second position <b>200</b>, detector transport member <b>122</b> may be positioned such that detector <b>140</b> and detector <b>142</b> are both located on the side of examination axis <b>114</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevation view of imaging system <b>100</b> in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention. In a third position <b>300</b>, detector transport member <b>122</b> may be positioned such that detector <b>142</b> is located in a position opposite that of detector <b>140</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. In an alternative embodiment, because, in the position shown, detector <b>142</b> provides information similar to that provided by detector <b>140</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the final position of detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> is counter-clockwise to the position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In operation, detector transport member <b>122</b> begins a scan in a first position <b>170</b>. Detector transport drive <b>129</b> may be controlled to rotate in a direction that causes detector transport member <b>122</b> to move along arcuate path <b>152</b> from position <b>170</b> to position <b>300</b> or any intermediate position therebetween. If a tomographic image (such as a SPECT image) is desired, the detector optionally pauses at increments along the path and acquires emission data from a patient. Alternatively, imaging may start at any other position and progress in any direction. A scan may include motion in one or more portions along path <b>152</b> in any direction.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The emission data may be acquired at only a single position. This is especially useful when the detectors <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> are oriented at 90° to each other, for viewing the heart from two directions. The imaging system is also configured to be used for planar imaging or biplane imaging of the heart or other portions of the body.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The acquired data is passed to an imaging computer (not shown) for generation of images from the emission data and their display on a display (not shown) as is well known in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The above-described embodiments of an imaging system provide a cost-effective and reliable means for examining a patient. More specifically, the imaging system includes a relatively small floor space requirement by using an open gantry that allows patient ingress to and egress from an imaging system <b>100</b> viewing area through a gap in the gantry. A detector transport member <b>122</b> of the imaging system <b>100</b> is moved away from a patient's ingress path by retracting the detector support member <b>122</b> in telescoping fashion adjacent to an imaging system base <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Exemplary embodiments of imaging system methods and apparatus are described above in detail. The imaging system components illustrated are not limited to the specific embodiments described herein, but rather, components of each imaging system may be utilized independently and separately from other components described herein. For example, the imaging system components described above may also be used in combination with different imaging systems. A technical effect of the various embodiments of the systems and methods described herein include at least one of facilitating reducing imaging system sitting requirements by reducing a floor space requirement of the imaging system.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">While the invention has been described in terms of various specific embodiments, those skilled in the art will recognize that the invention can be practiced with modification within the spirit and scope of the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A medical imaging system comprising:
<claim-text>an arcuate detector transport member that extends circumferentially about an examination axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base comprising an arcuate transport element configured to receive said detector transport member such that said detector transport member is supported by a rolling member, said base configured to translate said arcuate detector transport member along said rolling member in an arcuate path about said examination axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one gamma camera detector coupled to said detector transport member, wherein a face of the detector is oriented orthogonally to said examination axis.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said detector transport member extends less than about two hundred seventy degrees circumferentially about said examination axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein said arcuate detector transport member extends less than about one hundred eighty degrees circumferentially about said examination axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said detector transport member is moveable along an arc defined by said transport element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said base further comprises a pinion gear coupled to a motor, said detector transport member further comprises a toothed rack configured to engage said pinion gear, said rack and said pinion configured to transmit a force from said motor to said detector transport member that causes said detector transport member to move relative to said base.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein said pinion gear is powered from an electric motor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said electric motor is powered from an electrical source located in said base.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said detector transport member comprises a guide member configured to engage a plurality of rolling members, said guide member configured to guide said detector transport member along an arcuate path.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein said plurality of rolling members comprises a groove and wherein said guide member comprises an edge, said edge configured to engage said groove.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein said plurality of rolling members comprises an edge and wherein said guide member comprises a groove, said edge configured to engage said groove.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said base is configured to rotate said arcuate detector transport member about said examination axis through an arc of less than about one hundred eighty degrees.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said base is configured to rotate said arcuate detector transport member about said examination axis through an arc of about ninety degrees.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said base is configured to rotate said arcuate detector transport member about said examination axis through an arc of less than about ninety degrees.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least one detector comprises cadmium zinc telluride (CZT).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least one detector is configured to receive emission gamma rays at each of said at least one of a plurality of imaging positions, said emission gamma rays emitted from an imaging volume proximate said examination axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A medical imaging system in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least one detector comprises two detectors, each detector oriented at about ninety degrees with respect to the other.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method of imaging a patient comprising:
<claim-text>coupling at least one detector to a detector transport member, the at least one detector configured to move with the detector transport member, the detector transport member spanning an arc of less than about one hundred eighty degrees about an examination axis, wherein a face of the detector is oriented orthogonally to the examination axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>supporting the detector transport member with a base including a support assembly that includes rolling elements, the support assembly configured to engage the detector transport member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>rotating the detector transport member on the rolling elements through a predetermined path about the examination axis to a plurality of imaging positions, wherein the at least one detector includes a detecting face having an edge and wherein coupling at least one detector to a detector transport member comprises coupling a pair of radiation detectors together such that the edge of a first of the pair of radiation detectors is proximate and parallel the edge of a second of the pair of radiation detectors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method of imaging a patient accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein coupling a pair of radiation detectors together comprises coupling the detectors such that the detecting faces are oriented substantially perpendicular with respect to each other.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein coupling at least one detector to a detector transport member comprises coupling at least one gamma camera to the detector transport member.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein coupling at least one detector to a detector transport member comprises coupling the at least one detector to the detector transport member such that a normal centerline of a face of the at least one detector is oriented substantially orthogonally to the examination axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> further comprising positioning a patient through a gap in the detector transport member where the patient is substantially aligned with the examination axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein the detector transport member includes a rack and the base includes a complementary pinion and wherein rotating the detector transport member about the examination axis comprises controlling the rotation of an electrical motor coupled to the pinion to at least one of move the detector transport member between a plurality of imaging positions and maintain the detector transport member substantially stationary at an imaging position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> further comprising powering the motor from an electrical source located in the base.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein rotating the detector transport member about the examination axis comprises rotating the detector transport member less than about one hundred eighty degrees while imaging the patient.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein rotating the detector transport member about the examination axis comprises rotating the detector transport member about ninety degrees while imaging the patient.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref> wherein rotating the detector transport member about the examination axis comprises rotating the detector transport member about ninety degrees while receiving images corresponding to an about one hundred eighty degree scan of the patient.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. A method of imaging a patient in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> further comprising receiving at least one of transmission x-ray photons, transmission gamma rays, and emission gamma rays using the at least one detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. A method for medical imaging comprising:
<claim-text>coupling at least one nuclear medicine detector to a detector transport member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>supporting the detector transport member with an arcuate base having an arcuate support assembly that includes rolling elements configured to receive the detector transport member, the base remaining stationary with respect to an examination axis; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>translating the detector transport member, using the rolling elements, along an arcuate path about the examination axis, wherein a face of the detector is oriented orthogonally to the examination axis.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. A method for medical imaging in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00028">claim 28</claim-ref> further comprising coupling a pair of nuclear medicine detectors to the detector transport member such that an edge of a detecting face of a first of the pair of nuclear medicine detectors is proximate an edge of a detecting face of a second of the pair of nuclear medicine detectors wherein the detecting faces are oriented substantially perpendicular with respect to each other.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. A method for medical imaging in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00028">claim 28</claim-ref> wherein said rotating a detector transport member comprises at least one of rotating the detector transport member intermittently between a plurality of imaging positions and rotating the detector transport member continuously from a imaging start position to a imaging finish position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00031" num="00031">
<claim-text>31. A method for medical imaging in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00030">claim 30</claim-ref> wherein said rotating a detector transport member comprises rotating the detector transport member through an arc of less than about one hundred eighty degrees about the examination axis from the imaging start position to the imaging finish position.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
