<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296490-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296490</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11021578</doc-number>
<date>20041223</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>225</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>59</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 74335</main-classification>
<further-classification> 744733</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Switch assembly for selecting among plurality of shift schedules on an electronically controlled transmission</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3674953</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Brevick</name>
<date>19720700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>200548</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6105453</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ooyama et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 744733</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6295887</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>DeJonge et al.</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 744733</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6564661</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>DeJonge</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 74335</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 74335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 744733</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>200 6191</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>200553</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060142116</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060629</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Mashkevich</last-name>
<first-name>Michael</first-name>
<address>
<city>West Bloomfield</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hendry</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey C</first-name>
<address>
<city>Waterford</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Porrone</last-name>
<first-name>Laura</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sterling Heights</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Smith</last-name>
<first-name>Ralph E.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Chrysler LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Auburn Hills</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ho</last-name>
<first-name>Ha D.</first-name>
<department>3681</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electrical switch assembly is provided for an electronically controlled transmission that allows user selection between a plurality of shift schedules for the transmission. The switch assembly provides a signal for selecting among the plurality of shift schedules and has a housing. A first set of electrical contacts are positioned within the housing, and selectively closable to cause the input signal to be indicative of a selection of a first shift schedule. A second set of electrical contacts are positioned within the housing and are selectively closable to cause input signal to be indicative of a selection of a second shift schedule.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="78.91mm" wi="92.79mm" file="US07296490-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="220.47mm" wi="156.97mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296490-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="214.04mm" wi="122.26mm" file="US07296490-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to electronically controlled transmissions having a plurality of shift schedules, and more particularly to a device for selecting from the shift schedules.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In the field of automotive design, electronically powered transmissions having a plurality of shift schedules are controlled by switch assemblies receiving input from the vehicle operator regarding the desired shift schedule engagement. For example, a vehicle can be provided with separately located switch assemblies for selecting a tow/haul modified shift schedule, and an overdrive shift schedule in the transmission control module. Such separately located switch assemblies are ergonomically less desirable and increase the quantity of electrical wire needed for communicating with the transmission controller.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Therefore, there exists a need in the art to provide a switch assembly that reduces the quantity of wire needed for communication between the switches and the transmission control module and improves ergonomics over known arrangements.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In accordance with the needs identified above, an electrical switch assembly is provided for an electronically controlled transmission having a transmission controller arranged to provide a plurality of shift schedules for the transmission. The switch assembly provides a signal for selecting among the plurality of shift schedules and has a housing. A first set of electrical contacts are positioned within the housing, and selectively closable by operation of an input member to cause the input signal to be indicative of a selection of a first shift schedule. A second set of electrical contacts are positioned within the housing and are selectively closable by operation of the input member to cause the input signal to be indicative of a selection of a second shift schedule.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will become apparent from the detailed description of the presently preferred embodiments when read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings. The detailed description and drawings, while indicating the preferred embodiment of the invention, are intended for purposes of illustration only and are not intended to limit the scope of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic of a switch assembly;</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of a switch assembly; and</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flow diagram illustrating a method of selecting among a plurality of shift schedules.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT(S)</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The following description of the preferred embodiment(s) is merely exemplary in nature and is in no way intended to limit the invention, its application, or uses.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a schematic representation of a switch assembly <b>10</b> and associated vehicle components is depicted in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention. The switch assembly <b>10</b> is connected to an engine controller module (ECM) <b>30</b> comprised of a microcontroller <b>22</b> having a digital to analog converter (A/D) pin. The ECM <b>30</b> regulates the inputs and outputs (including fuel, spark, coolant temperature, and throttle position) <b>34</b> of the engine <b>32</b> as is well known in the art. The ECM <b>30</b> communicates with a transmission controller module (TCM) <b>40</b> by means of a communication link <b>24</b>. The TCM has a transmission microcontroller <b>50</b> that regulates the inputs and outputs (including shaft speeds and gear select solenoids) <b>44</b> of the transmission <b>42</b> which includes a transmission output shaft <b>48</b> having an output torque, T<sub>O</sub>, and a transmission input shaft <b>46</b> connected to the engine <b>32</b> having an input torque, T<sub>I</sub>, as is well known in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The ECM <b>30</b> monitors an output <b>20</b> that carries an electrical voltage indicative of whether an operator is pressing either end of a rocker <b>12</b>. The rocker <b>12</b> is used by the operator is indicate whether the overdrive shift schedule should be disabled, or the tow/haul modified shift schedule should be engaged. As shown, switch assembly <b>10</b> is an example of such an assembly that is implemented in a resistive-multiplexed (R-mux) configuration. While the R-mux switch is discussed in more detail below, such a switch arrangement is not to be construed as limiting.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">R-mux switch assembly <b>10</b> is referenced to ground <b>18</b> and has an output <b>20</b> connected to a microcontroller <b>22</b> having an analog-to-digital converter (A/D) pin. The A/D is referenced to voltage (+V) as is known in the art. An operator presses rocker <b>12</b> in a first direction which causes switch <b>14</b> to close to indicate that engagement of a first shift schedule, such as a tow/haul shift schedule, is desired. Rocker <b>12</b> may be pressed in a second direction which causes switch <b>16</b> to close, thereby indicating that a second shift schedule, such as one which disables engagement of an overdrive gear ratio, is desired. Both switches <b>14</b> and <b>16</b> are normally open.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">When neither switch <b>14</b> nor switch <b>16</b> is closed, pin <b>22</b> is at a first voltage level that can be expressed as follows:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>V</i><sub>OPEN</sub><i>=+V</i>*(<i>R</i><sub>3</sub>/(<i>R</i><sub>3</sub><i>+R</i><sub>4</sub>)).<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Pressing rocker <b>12</b> in the first direction closes switch <b>14</b> and causes a voltage level corresponding to the first shift schedule enable to appear at pin <b>22</b>. This voltage level can be expressed as:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>V</i><sub>TOW</sub><i>=+V</i>*(<i>R</i><sub>2</sub><i>R</i><sub>3</sub>)/(<i>R</i><sub>2</sub><i>R</i><sub>3</sub><i>+R</i><sub>4</sub>).<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Pressing rocker <b>12</b> in the second direction closes switch <b>16</b> and causes a voltage level corresponding to the second shift schedule to appear at pin <b>22</b>. This voltage level can be expressed as:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>V</i><sub>OD</sub><i>=+V</i>*(<i>R</i><sub>1</sub><i>R</i><sub>3</sub>)/(<i>R</i><sub>1</sub><i>R</i><sub>3</sub><i>+R</i><sub>4</sub>).<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Turning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a perspective view of a switch assembly <b>10</b> is shown. A housing <b>17</b> contains the switches <b>14</b>, <b>16</b> and resistors R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2 </sub>and R<sub>3</sub>. The rocker <b>12</b> is pivotally mounted in the housing <b>17</b> such that it may be pressed by the vehicle operator. The rocker <b>12</b> may be provided with first and second indicia <b>13</b>, <b>15</b> to facilitate an understanding of the switch operation. The switch assembly <b>12</b> is preferably mounted ergonomically such that the vehicle operator may operate the rocker <b>12</b> without removing a hand from the steering wheel. Mounting the switch assembly <b>10</b> on a stalk extending from the steering column is preferred. Such a mounting arrangement positions the switch assembly <b>10</b> behind the steering wheel and within comfortable reach of the operator's fingertips.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The ECM <b>30</b> responds to the switch assembly <b>10</b> by relaying instructions to the transmission microcontroller <b>50</b> housed in the transmission controller module (TCM) <b>40</b> regarding the desired engagement status of the transmission's <b>42</b> shift schedules in response to operator's use of the momentary rocker switch <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In the preferred embodiment of the invention, the control module is accomplished through an engine controller module <b>30</b> connected to the transmission controller module <b>50</b> by means of a communication link <b>24</b>. However, it is also known to those skilled in the art that the control module can be accomplished by a powertrain control module.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the method <b>200</b> of the invention. In the embodiment depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the ECM <b>30</b> is programmed to execute <b>200</b>, however it may be executed by any electrical module that has access to information regarding the switch states (such as voltages V<sub>OPEN</sub>, V<sub>TOW</sub>, and V<sub>OD</sub>). For example, a body control module may be substituted for the ECM <b>30</b>. In yet another configuration, the switch may be connected directly to the transmission controller <b>40</b>, providing the transmission controller <b>40</b> has a suitable input, and the transmission controller <b>40</b> would then execute the method.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The method is executed periodically, for example every 12 milliseconds. The method starts in decision block <b>210</b> and proceeds to decision block <b>220</b> where it reads the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b>. If the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b> is below a predetermined diagnostic voltage, which is lower than V<sub>OPEN</sub>, then the method proceeds through blocks <b>310</b> and <b>320</b> and selects a default shift schedule from the plurality of shift schedules. In the exemplary embodiment, the default shift schedule includes enabling selection of an overdrive gear ratio and deselecting the tow/haul schedule. Returning to block <b>220</b>, if the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b> is above a predetermined diagnostic voltage, then the method proceeds to decision block <b>230</b> and determines whether the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b> equals V<sub>OD</sub>. If so, then the method then proceeds to block <b>240</b> and toggles selection of the overdrive enable shift schedule between overdrive engaged or overdrive disengaged. Returning to decision block <b>230</b>, if the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b> is not equal to V<sub>OD</sub>, the method then proceeds to decision block <b>250</b>. At decision block <b>250</b>, the method whether the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b> is equal to V<sub>TOW</sub>. If not, then the method proceeds to block <b>270</b> and terminates until the next execution. Returning to decision block <b>250</b>, if the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b> is determined to be equal to V<sub>TOW</sub>, the method proceeds to block <b>260</b> and toggles selection of the tow/haul shift schedule between engagement and disengagement.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Returning now to decision block <b>250</b>, in an alternate embodiment, the method may sequence instead through blocks <b>310</b> and <b>320</b> if the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b> is determined to be unequal to V<sub>TOW</sub>. This allows the method to select the default shift schedule when the method is unable to determine, from the voltage at the switch output <b>20</b>, which switch is closed.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The description of the invention is merely exemplary in nature and, thus, variations that do not depart from the gist of the invention are intended to be within the scope of the invention. Such variations are not to be regarded as a departure from the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electrical switch assembly for an electronically controlled transmission having a transmission controller arranged to provide a plurality of shift schedules for the transmission, the switch assembly providing an input signal to the transmission controller for selecting among the plurality of shift schedules, the switch assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a housing:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first set of electrical contacts positioned within said housing, said first set of electrical contacts being selectively closeable by operation of an input member to cause the input signal to be indicative of a selection of a first shift schedule; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second set of electrical contacts positioned within said housing, said second set of electrical contacts being selectively closeable by operation of the input member to cause the input signal to be indicative of a selection of a second shift schedule;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the input member comprises a rocker positioned in said housing, a first end of said rocker effecting closure of said first set of electrical contacts and a second end of said rocker effecting closure of said second set of electrical contacts.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The switch assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said first shift schedule is an overdrive disengaged mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The switch assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said second shift schedule is a tow/haul mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The switch assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the shift selections are achieved by toggling between engagement and disengagement of the selected schedules.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An electrical switch assembly for an electronically controlled transmission having a transmission controller arranged to provide a plurality of shift schedules for the transmission, the switch assembly providing an input signal to the transmission controller for selecting among the plurality of shift schedules, the switch assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a housing:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first set of electrical contacts positioned within said housing, said first set of electrical contacts being selectively closeable by operation of an input member to cause the input signal to be indicative of a selection of a first shift schedule;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second set of electrical contacts positioned within said housing, said second set of electrical contacts being selectively closeable by operation of the input member to cause the input signal to be indicative of a selection of a second shift schedule; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a resistively multiplexed switch having one end of a first resistor connected in series with said first set of electrical contacts; one end of a second resistor connected in series with said second set of electrical contacts; and opposite ends of said first and second resistors being connected and producing the input signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The switch assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> further comprising a diagnostic resister in series with said connection between said opposite ends of said first and second resistors and an electric terminal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The switch assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein said first shift schedule is an overdrive disengaged mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The switch assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein said second shift schedule is a tow/haul mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The switch assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the shift selections are achieved by toggling between engagement and disengagement of the selected schedules.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
