<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297232-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297232</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10380766</doc-number>
<date>20020718</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-223626</doc-number>
<date>20010724</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>D</section>
<class>21</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>162218</main-classification>
<further-classification>162221</further-classification>
<further-classification>162224</further-classification>
<further-classification>162226</further-classification>
<further-classification>264335</further-classification>
<further-classification>425116</further-classification>
<further-classification>425145</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Production method and device for fiber molding</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2961043</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hicks</name>
<date>19601100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6875384</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Whitney</name>
<date>20050400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>264 405</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>1219748</doc-number>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>08-209600</doc-number>
<date>19960800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>10-227000</doc-number>
<date>19980800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-34700</doc-number>
<date>20000200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-106220</doc-number>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>01-11141</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>162218</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>162221</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>162224</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>162226</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>264335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425116</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425145</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>16</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040041305</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040304</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tsuura</last-name>
<first-name>Tokuo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tochigi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Osaki</last-name>
<first-name>Masayuki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tochigi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Oblon, Spivak, McClelland, Maier &amp; Neustadt, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Kao Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Halpern</last-name>
<first-name>Mark</first-name>
<department>1731</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/JP02/07317</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20020718</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20030813</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO03/010386</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20030206</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method for producing a fiber molded article comprising the step of transferring a fiber molded article <b>10</b> formed in a papermaking mold <b>2</b> composed of splits <b>20</b> and <b>20′</b> to a split <b>30′</b> of a drying mold <b>3</b>, in which the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is once opened while attracting the fiber molded article <b>10</b> to the inner surface of the split <b>20′</b> by suction to separate the fiber molded article <b>10</b> from the inner surface of the split <b>20</b>, the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is closed, the suction by the split <b>20′</b> is stopped, the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is opened again while attracting the fiber molded article <b>10</b> to the inner surface of the split <b>20</b> to separate the fiber molded article <b>10</b> from the split <b>20′</b>, the split <b>20</b> is joined with the split <b>30′</b>, the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is attracted to the inner surface of the split <b>30′</b> by suction, and the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is separated from the split <b>20. </b></p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="56.98mm" wi="68.58mm" file="US07297232-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="238.25mm" wi="121.16mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297232-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="207.94mm" wi="97.79mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297232-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="192.28mm" wi="96.01mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297232-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a 371 of PCT/JP02/07317 filed 18 Jul. 2002.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a method of producing a fiber molded article comprising a step of transferring a fiber molded article formed in a papermaking mold composed of a set of splits to another mold and an apparatus therefor.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND ART</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Some methods of producing pulp molded articles involve a step of transferring a molded article having been formed and dewatered in a papermaking mold to a drying mold for drying the molded article. The technique described in JP-A-10-227000 is included under this type of methods.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">According to the technique disclosed, a papermaking mold (upper mold) is immersed in a raw material slurry, and the slurry is sucked up to deposit the pulp component on the inner surface (a papermaking screen) of the papermaking mold. The papermaking mold is pulled out of the slurry, and the suction is continued to dewater the pulp component to obtain a molded article having a prescribed water content. The papermaking mold is joined with another mold (lower mold). The suction through the papermaking mold is stopped so that the molded article is transferred to the other mold by its own weight. The other mold is then joined with a drying mold (another upper mold) to dry the molded article.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, the operation of transferring a pulp molded article from a papermaking mold to another mold sometimes fails because the molded article has been brought into intimate contact with the inner surface of the papermaking mold (papermaking screen) by the suction force exerted for dewatering. Where, in particular, a hollow bottle-shaped pulp molded article is formed and dewatered on a papermaking mold composed of a set of splits and then transferred to another mold by (i) opening the split papermaking mold with the molded article stuck to one of the splits and (ii) attracting the molded article to the other mold by suction, the papermaking screens provided on the inner surface of the splits leaves their mesh marks on the outer surface of the molded article during dewatering. The mesh marks cause a gap between the molded article and the other mold. As a result, the suction force exerted between the other mold and the molded article tends to be insufficient for stably transferring the molded article between the two molds.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Accordingly, an object of the present invention is to provide a method and an apparatus for producing a fiber molded article in which a fiber molded article formed in a papermaking mold can be transferred to another mold stably and securely.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The present invention accomplishes the above object by providing a method of producing a fiber molded article comprising the step of transferring a fiber molded article formed in a papermaking mold composed of a set of splits to another mold other than the papermaking mold, wherein the step of transferring is carried out by opening the papermaking mold while attracting the fiber molded article to the inner surface of one of the splits by suction to separate the fiber molded article from the other split, closing the papermaking mold, releasing the molded article from attraction to the inner surface of the one of the splits, opening the papermaking mold again while attracting the fiber molded article to the inner surface of the other split by suction, joining the other split with the another mold, attracting the fiber molded article to the inner surface of the another mold by suction, and separating the fiber molded article from the other split.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention also accomplishes the above object by providing an apparatus for producing a fiber molded article comprising a papermaking mold composed of a set of splits, another mold other than the papermaking mold for receiving the molded article formed in the papermaking mold, a moving means for moving the set of splits and the another mold, a suction means for attracting the fiber molded article to the inner surface of the splits and the inner surface of the another mold, and a control means for controlling the moving means and the suction means, wherein the control means controls the moving means and the suction means such that:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">the papermaking mold is opened while attracting the fiber molded article to the inner surface of one of the splits of the papermaking mold by suction to separate the fiber molded article from the other split,</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">the papermaking mold is closed, and the molded article is released from attraction to the inner surface of the papermaking mold,</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">the papermaking mold is opened again while attracting the fiber molded article to the inner surface of the other split by suction to separate the fiber molded article from the inner surface of the one of the splits,</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">the other split is joined with the another mold, and the fiber molded article is attracted to the inner surface of the another mold by suction, and</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">the fiber molded article is separated from the other split.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1(</figref><i>a</i>) through <b>1</b>(<i>h</i>) are plan views schematically illustrating the step of transferring a fiber molded article from a papermaking mold to a drying mold in an embodiment of the method for producing a fiber molded article according to the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>a</i>) shows the state after papermaking. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>b</i>) shows the papermaking mold in an opened state. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>c</i>) shows the papermaking mold in a re-closed state. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>d</i>) shows the molded article attracted to one split. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>e</i>) shows the split of the papermaking mold and a split of the drying mold facing each other. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>f</i>) shows the papermaking mold split and the drying mold split joined together. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>g</i>) shows the molded article having been transferred to the drying mold split. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>h</i>) shows the state immediately before joining a pair of drying mold splits.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2(</figref><i>a</i>) through <b>2</b>(<i>d</i>) are partial cross-sections schematically illustrating the step of separating a molded article from the papermaking mold in the embodiment. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>) illustrates the state after papermaking. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>b</i>) shows the papermaking mold in an once opened state. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>c</i>) shows the papermaking mold in a re-closed state. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>d</i>) shows the molded article attracted to one of the splits by suction.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) to <b>3</b>(<i>d</i>) schematically illustrate the step of drying in the embodiment. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) shows the molded article placed in the drying mold. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>b</i>) shows a pressing member which is being inserted into the molded article. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>c</i>) shows the pressing member expanded to press and dry the molded article. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>d</i>) shows the drying mold in an opened state.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BEST MODE FOR CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The present invention will be described based on its preferred embodiment by referring to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 3</figref> schematically illustrate the steps involved in the production of a fiber molded article by use of an embodiment of the apparatus according to the present invention. In the Figures, numeral <b>1</b> indicates an apparatus for producing a fiber molded article (hereinafter simply referred to as “the apparatus”), and numeral <b>10</b> indicates a fiber molded article.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the apparatus <b>1</b> comprises a papermaking mold <b>2</b> composed of a pair of splits <b>20</b> and <b>20</b>′, a drying mold <b>3</b> composed of a pair of splits <b>30</b> and <b>30</b>′ which receives the fiber molded article <b>10</b> formed in the papermaking mold <b>2</b>, a moving means (not shown) for moving the splits <b>20</b>, <b>20</b>′, <b>30</b>, and <b>30</b>′, a suction means (not shown) for attracting the fiber molded article <b>10</b> toward the inner surfaces of the papermaking mold and the drying mold, and a control means (not shown) for controlling the moving means and the suction means.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In the apparatus <b>1</b>, the papermaking mold <b>2</b> and the drying mold <b>3</b> are adjacent to each other. The split <b>20</b> and the split <b>30</b> are fixed to a carriage <b>4</b> which is movable in the direction perpendicular to the opening and closure direction of the papermaking mold <b>2</b> and the drying mold <b>3</b>. The split <b>20</b>′ and the split <b>30</b>′ are disposed to face the mating splits <b>20</b> and <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The moving means has a driving mechanism (not shown) for moving the carriage <b>4</b> and a mold clamping mechanism (not shown) for joining and clamping the splits <b>20</b> and <b>20</b>′ and the splits <b>30</b> and <b>30</b>′. The mold clamping mechanism moves the splits in the direction perpendicular to the carriage <b>4</b> moving direction to open or close the papermaking mold <b>2</b> and the drying mold <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the splits <b>20</b> and <b>20</b>′ constituting the papermaking mold <b>2</b> are joined to form a bottle-shaped cavity C.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The split <b>20</b> and the split <b>20</b>′ are symmetric and have the same configuration. Therefore, the splits will be described only with reference to the split <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The split <b>20</b> is composed of a main body <b>200</b> and a frame <b>210</b> surrounding the main body <b>200</b>. There is a space between the main body <b>200</b> and the frame <b>210</b>, which is divided into three chambers S<b>1</b>, S<b>2</b>, and S<b>3</b> by partitions <b>220</b>. The main body <b>200</b> has a large number of through-holes <b>201</b> interconnecting the space and the cavity C.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Flow channels <b>203</b> of prescribed width are engraved in a checkered pattern on the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b> of the split <b>20</b> to connect the through-holes <b>201</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The total open area ratio of the flow channels <b>203</b> to the total surface area of the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b> of the split <b>20</b> is preferably 10 to 85%, more preferably 40 to 80%, for stably performing the transfer of the molded article from the split of the papermaking mold <b>2</b> and the split of the drying mold <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">A papermaking screen (not shown) having a prescribed opening size and a prescribed wire width is disposed on the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b> of the main body <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The frame <b>210</b> has flow passageways <b>211</b> which lead the chambers S<b>1</b>, S<b>2</b>, and S<b>3</b> to the outside. Each flow passageway <b>211</b> is connected to a pipe line (not shown) leading to an evacuation source or a compressor. The cavity is evacuated by suction through the through-holes <b>201</b> and the flow passageways <b>211</b>, and a pressurized fluid is fed into the cavity through the same route. Since such a single route serves for both evacuation by suction of the cavity and pressurized fluid feed into the cavity, the apparatus can be designed to have a reduced size.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The drying mold <b>3</b> has a heating means (not shown). It has the same configuration as the papermaking mold <b>2</b> except for having no papermaking screen.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the splits <b>30</b> and <b>30</b>′ are joined to form the drying mold <b>3</b> having a bottle-shaped cavity C′.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The splits <b>30</b> and <b>30</b>′ have basically the same design except for being opposite so that only the split <b>30</b> will be described further.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The split <b>30</b> has a main body <b>300</b> and a frame <b>310</b> surrounding the main body <b>300</b>. Partitions <b>320</b> are provided in the space between the main body <b>300</b> and the frame <b>310</b> to divide the space into three chambers S<b>10</b>, S<b>20</b>, and, S<b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The main body <b>300</b>, which is conformed to the shapes of the neck, body and bottom of the molded article, has a large number of through-holes <b>301</b> connecting the space and the cavity C′.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The total open area ratio of the through-holes <b>301</b> on the cavity-forming surface (the ratio of the total open area to the total surface area of the cavity-forming surface) is preferably 0.5 to 20%, more preferably 0.8 to 10%, for stably transferring the molded article between the split of the papermaking mold <b>2</b> and the split of the drying mold <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The frame <b>310</b> has flow passageways <b>311</b> which lead the chambers S<b>10</b>, S<b>20</b>, and S<b>30</b> to the outside. Each flow passageway <b>311</b> is connected to a pipe line (not shown) leading to an evacuation source or a compressor. The cavity is evacuated by suction through the through-holes <b>301</b> and the flow passageways <b>311</b>, and a pressurized fluid is fed into the cavity through the same route. Since such a single route serves for both evacuation by suction of the cavity and pressurized fluid feed into the cavity, the apparatus can be designed to have a reduced size.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The control means has a sequence controller. The papermaking mold <b>2</b> is once opened while having the fiber molded article <b>10</b> attracted to the inner surface of the split <b>20</b>′ by suction, whereupon the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is separated from the inner surface of the split <b>20</b>. The papermaking mold <b>2</b> is then closed, and the suction for attracting the fiber molded article <b>10</b> by the split <b>20</b>′ is stopped. The papermaking mold <b>2</b> is reopened while having the fiber molded article <b>10</b> attracted to the inner surface of the split <b>20</b> by suction. The split <b>20</b> is joined with the split <b>30</b>′, and the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is attracted onto the inner surface of the split <b>30</b>′ by suction. The split <b>30</b> is moved to face the split <b>30</b>′. These operations (suction and movement) are carried out under control by the sequence controller.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>b</i>), the apparatus <b>1</b> has sensing means <b>5</b> and <b>6</b> for monitoring the transfer of the fiber molded article <b>10</b> between the splits <b>20</b> and <b>20</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The sensing means <b>5</b> comprises an optical sensor <b>50</b> having an emitter and a receptor and a reflector <b>51</b> which reflects the light from the emitter. The sensing means <b>5</b> detects whether there is any fiber molded article <b>10</b> in the split <b>20</b>′. The optical sensor <b>50</b> and the reflector <b>51</b> are attached to the respective sides of the split <b>20</b>′ to face each other.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The sensing means <b>6</b> also comprises an optical sensor <b>60</b> and a reflector <b>61</b>. The sensing means <b>6</b> detects whether there is any fiber molded article <b>10</b> in the split <b>20</b>. The optical sensor <b>60</b> and the reflector <b>61</b> are attached to the outer side of the split <b>20</b> and the outer side of the split <b>30</b>, respectively, so that they may face each other.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The apparatus <b>1</b> additionally has a sensing means <b>7</b> which, in cooperation with the sensing means <b>6</b>, monitors the movement of the fiber molded article <b>10</b> between the split <b>20</b>′ and the split <b>30</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The sensing means <b>7</b> comprises an optical sensor <b>70</b> and a reflector <b>71</b>. The sensing means <b>7</b> detects whether there is any fiber molded article <b>10</b> in the split <b>30</b>′ and is attached to both sides of the split <b>30</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the apparatus <b>1</b>, the control means is adapted to control the transfer means and the suction means in response to the detection output from these sensing means <b>5</b> to <b>7</b> as described infra.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">A preferred embodiment of the method for producing a fiber molded article according to the present invention will be described based on the method of producing the fiber molded article <b>10</b> by using the apparatus <b>1</b> by referring to the drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>), the splits <b>20</b> and <b>20</b>′ are assembled to form the cavity C. A pulp slurry is injected under pressure into the cavity from the opening <b>21</b> at the top of the papermaking mold <b>2</b>. The pulp slurry is injected by means of, for example, a pressure pump. The pulp slurry injection pressure is preferably 0.01 to 5 MPa, more preferably 0.01 to 3 MPa.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">On injecting a predetermined amount of the pulp slurry into the cavity C, suction of the pulp slurry starts through the flow channels <b>203</b>, the through-holes <b>201</b>, and the flow passageways <b>211</b>. The water content of the pulp slurry is thereby discharged out of the papermaking mold <b>2</b>, while pulp fiber is deposited on the papermaking screen to build up a hollow bottle-shaped fiber molded article <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The pulp slurry is prepared by using pulp fiber generally employed in this type of pulp molded article fabrication. The pulp slurry is made solely of pulp fiber and water or may contain inorganic substances, such as talc and kaolinite, inorganic fibers, such as glass fiber and carbon fibers, particulate or fibrous thermoplastic resins, such as polyolefins, non-wood or plant fibers, and polysaccharides. The amount of the other components is preferably 1 to 70% by weight, more preferably 5 to 50% by weight, based on the total amount of the pulp fiber and these components.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">After the fiber molded article <b>10</b> of prescribed thickness is formed, compressed air (heated air) is fed into the cavity C through the opening <b>21</b> while continuing the evacuation by suction of the cavity C through the flow channels <b>203</b> and <b>203</b>′, the through-holes <b>201</b> and <b>201</b>′, and the flow passageways <b>211</b> and <b>211</b>′. The fiber molded article is thus dewatered to a prescribed water content. The pressure of the compressed air to be fed into the cavity C is preferably 0.01 to 5 MPa, more preferably 0.1 to 3 MPa.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The water content of the dewatered fiber molded article <b>10</b> is preferably 30 to 95%, more preferably 50 to 85%. The fiber molded article <b>10</b> with a water content less than 30% can fail to acquire sufficient surface properties during the drying step. If the water content exceeds 95%, the fiber molded article <b>10</b> needs a long time to dry in the drying step, which can result in reduced production efficiency or difficulty in transferring the fiber molded article <b>10</b> to the drying mold <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The soaking wet fiber molded article <b>10</b> is thus dewatered from the inside of the cavity C by feeding air into the cavity C while evacuating the cavity C by suction, the step of joining separately molded parts as required in conventional pulp molding techniques is unnecessary. Therefore, the resulting fiber molded article <b>10</b> has no joint seams. As a result, a finally obtained fiber molded article <b>10</b> has an enhanced strength and a good appearance.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">After the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is dewatered to a prescribed water content, the compressed air feed into the cavity C through the opening <b>21</b> and the suction of the cavity C through the through-holes <b>201</b> and <b>201</b>′ and the flow passageways <b>211</b> and <b>211</b>′ are stopped.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The fiber molded article <b>10</b> formed in the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is then transferred to the drying mold <b>3</b> as described hereunder.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1(</figref><i>b</i>) and <b>2</b>(<i>b</i>), the cavity is evacuated by suction through the flow channels <b>203</b>′, the through-holes <b>201</b>′, and the flow passageways <b>211</b>′, whereby the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is attracted to the cavity-forming surface (inner surface) <b>202</b>′ of the split <b>20</b>′. At the same time, compressed air is blown from the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b> of the split <b>20</b> to the fiber molded article <b>10</b> through the through-holes <b>201</b> and the flow passageway <b>211</b>. In order to separate the fiber molded article <b>10</b> from the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b> of the split <b>20</b>, the split <b>20</b>′ is moved to once open the papermaking mold <b>2</b>. When the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is opened, compressed air blowing to the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is stopped. By releasing the intimate contact between the fiber molded article <b>10</b> and the papermaking screen on the inner side of the split <b>20</b> in this way, the fiber molded article <b>10</b> can be smoothly shifted from the split <b>20</b> to the split <b>30</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">For stable transfer of the fiber molded article <b>10</b>, the suction force for attracting the fiber molded article to the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b>′ of the split <b>20</b>′ is preferably −20 to −95 kPa, more preferably −30 to −80 kPa. The pressure of compressed air blown from the split <b>20</b> to the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is preferably 0.1 to 0.6 MPa, more preferably 0.3 to 0.5 MPa, for assuring the stable transfer and for preventing damage to the fiber molded article <b>10</b> by compressed air.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1(</figref><i>c</i>) and <b>2</b>(<i>c</i>), the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is closed, and the suction for attracting the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is stopped. The cavity C is sucked through the through-holes <b>201</b> and the flow passageways <b>211</b> to attract the fiber molded article <b>10</b> to the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b> of the split <b>20</b>. At the same time, compressed air is blown from the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b>′ of the split <b>20</b>′ to the fiber molded article <b>10</b> through the flow passageway <b>211</b>′ and the through-holes <b>201</b>′, and the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is again opened to separate the fiber molded article <b>10</b> from the split <b>20</b>′ as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1(</figref><i>d</i>) and <b>2</b>(<i>d</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The suction force for attracting the fiber molded article <b>10</b> to the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b> of the split <b>20</b> is preferably −20 to −95 kPa, more preferably −30 to −80 kPa, for the same reasons as described supra. The pressure of the compressed air blown from the split <b>20</b>′ toward the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is preferably 0.1 to 0.6 MPa, more preferably 0.3 to 0.5 MPa, for the same reasons as described supra.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">When the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is re-opened, the sensing means <b>5</b> and <b>6</b> detect whether the fiber molded article <b>10</b> has been properly transferred from the split <b>20</b>′ to the split <b>20</b>. Where the light emitted from the emitter of the optical sensor <b>60</b> and reflected on the reflector <b>61</b> is no more detected by the receptor of the optical sensor <b>60</b>, it is judged that the transfer has been done successfully. Where the light emitted from the emitter of the optical sensor <b>50</b> and reflected on the reflector <b>51</b> is not detected by the receptor of the optical sensor <b>50</b>, it is judged that the transfer operation has failed. In this case, the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is again closed to repeat the transfer operation. If both the receptors of the optical sensors <b>50</b> and <b>60</b> detect light, it is judged that the fiber molded article <b>10</b> has fallen from the split <b>20</b> or <b>20</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">When the transfer has been done successfully, the carriage <b>4</b> moves the split <b>20</b> to a position where it faces the split <b>30</b>′ as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>e</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>f</i>), the split <b>30</b>′ is brought closer to the split <b>20</b> and joined to the split <b>20</b>. The fiber molded article <b>10</b> is then attracted to the cavity-forming surface <b>302</b>′ of the split <b>30</b>′ by suction through the through-holes <b>301</b>′ and the flow passageways <b>311</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The suction force for attracting the fiber molded article <b>10</b> to the cavity-forming surface <b>302</b>′ of the split <b>30</b>′ is preferably −20 to −95 kPa, more preferably −30 to −80 kPa, for the same reasons as described supra. The pressure of the compressed air blown from the split <b>20</b> toward the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is preferably 0.1 to 0.6 MPa, more preferably 0.3 to 0.5 MPa, for the same reasons as described supra.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The split <b>30</b>′ is moved away from the split <b>20</b> thereby to release the fiber molded article <b>10</b> from the split <b>20</b> as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>g</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">In this stage of moving the split <b>30</b>′, the sensing means <b>6</b> and <b>7</b> detect whether the fiber molded article <b>10</b> has been properly transferred from the split <b>20</b> to the split <b>30</b>′. Where the light emitted from the emitter of the optical sensor <b>70</b> and reflected on the reflector <b>71</b> is no more detected by the receptor of the optical sensor <b>70</b>, it is judged that the transfer has been done successfully. Where the light emitted from the emitter of the optical sensor <b>60</b> and reflected on the reflector <b>61</b> is not detected by the receptor of the optical sensor <b>60</b>, it is judged that the transfer operation has failed. In this case, the transfer operation is repeated. If both the receptors of the optical sensors <b>60</b> and <b>70</b> detect light, it is judged that the fiber molded article <b>10</b> has fallen from the split <b>20</b> or <b>30</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">When the transfer has been done successfully, the carriage <b>4</b> moves to its original position to move the split <b>20</b> and the split <b>30</b> to positions where they face the mating split <b>20</b>′ and the mating split <b>30</b>′, respectively, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>h</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The step of drying the undried fiber molded article by pressing will now be described with reference to the drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The split <b>30</b>′ shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1(</figref><i>h</i>) is brought closer to the split <b>30</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>a</i>), the two splits <b>30</b> and <b>30</b>′ are joined together to form the cavity C′ in which the undried fiber molded article <b>10</b> is fitted. The drying mold <b>3</b> has previously been heated and maintained at a prescribed temperature.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>b</i>), a hollow bag-like pressing member <b>8</b> is inserted into the inside of the fiber molded article <b>10</b> while the inside of the drying mold <b>3</b> is evacuated by suction through the through-holes <b>301</b> and <b>301</b>′ and the flow passageways <b>311</b> and <b>311</b>′. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>c</i>), a pressurizing fluid is fed into the pressing member <b>8</b> to expand it. The expanded pressing member <b>8</b> presses the undried fiber molded article <b>10</b> toward the cavity-forming surfaces <b>302</b> and <b>302</b>′. The pressing member <b>8</b> is preferably made of a film of a flexible material excellent in tensile strength, impact resilience, extensibility, and the like, such as fluororubber, silicone rubber or other elastomer.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The pressurizing fluid which can be used to expand the pressing member <b>8</b> includes gases and liquids, such as compressed air (heated air) and oil (heated oil). The pressure of the pressurizing fluid is preferably 0.01 to 5 MPa, particularly 0.1 to 3 MPa. Pressures lower than 0.01 MPa achieve reduced drying efficiency and can result in poor surface properties of the fiber molded article. Pressures exceeding 5 MPa necessitate scaling up the apparatus without offering further advantages in terms of drying efficiency or surface properties.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">The expanded pressing member <b>8</b> presses the fiber molded article <b>10</b> toward the cavity-forming surfaces. As a result, the water of the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is removede from the through-holes <b>301</b> and <b>301</b>′, the flow passageways <b>311</b> and <b>311</b>′ as steam. Simultaneously with the progress of drying, the structure of the cavity-forming surfaces <b>302</b> and <b>302</b>′ is transferred onto the outer surface of the fiber molded article <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Since the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is pressed to the cavity-forming surfaces <b>302</b> and <b>302</b>′, it dries efficiently even if the cavity C′ configuration may be complicated. Moreover, the structure of the cavity-forming surfaces <b>302</b> and <b>302</b>′ is transferred to the outer surface of the fiber molded article <b>10</b> with high precision.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">On drying the fiber molded article <b>10</b> to a prescribed water content, the pressurizing fluid is withdrawn from the pressing member <b>8</b> to let the pressing member <b>8</b> shrink. The shrunken pressing member <b>8</b> is removed from the fiber molded article <b>10</b>. The drying mold <b>3</b> is opened to take out the dried fiber molded article <b>10</b> from the drying mold as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>d</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">As described above, in the method of producing a fiber molded article by use of the apparatus <b>1</b> according to this embodiment, the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is once released from the cavity-forming surface <b>202</b> of the split <b>20</b> before it is attracted to the split <b>20</b> by suction, and the fiber molded article <b>10</b> is then transferred from the split <b>20</b> to the split <b>30</b>′ of the drying mold <b>3</b>. Therefore, the fiber molded article <b>10</b> formed in the papermaking mold <b>2</b> is transferred from the papermaking mold <b>2</b> to the drying mold <b>3</b> without fail.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">The present invention is by no means limited to the above-described embodiment, and appropriate changes and modifications can be made therein without departing from the spirit and scope thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">While the present invention is preferably carried out by using sensing means equipped with an optical sensor and a reflector to monitor the transfer of a fiber molded article between the papermaking mold and the drying mold as in the embodiment, the sensor to be used is not particularly limited in type. For example, other types of sensors such as infrared sensors may be employed.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">While the present invention is conveniently applied to the method in which a papermaking mold for forming a bottle-shaped fiber molded article is used, it is also applicable to the production of a fiber molded article by using a papermaking mold composed of a male and a female.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">While the mold used in the embodiment for receiving a fiber molded article is a split constituting a drying mold, it may be replaced with an intermediate mold which mediates the transfer of a fiber molded article to a drying mold.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">While, as in the embodiment, it is preferred to carry out both evacuation by suction and gas blowing for implementing transfer of a molded article between splits, gas blowing could be omitted if desired.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">While, as in the embodiment, it is preferred that pressing of a fiber molded article by a pressing member is carried out only in the drying step, such pressing may be performed in the dewatering step.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">While it is preferred that suction of the cavity and pressurizing fluid feed into the cavity be carried out through the same route as in the embodiment, these operations may be effected through separate routes.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">INDUSTRIAL APPLICABILITY</heading>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">The present invention provides a method and an apparatus for producing a fiber molded article in which a fiber molded article formed in a papermaking mold can securely be transferred to another mold.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of producing a fiber molded article comprising the step of transferring the fiber molded article formed in a papermaking mold composed of a first split and a second split to a second mold composed of a third split and a fourth split, wherein the step of transferring is carried out by opening said papermaking mold while attracting the fiber molded article to an inner surface of said first split by suction to separate the fiber molded article from the second split, closing the papermaking mold, releasing the molded article from attraction to the inner surface of said first split, opening the papermaking mold again while attracting the fiber molded article to an inner surface of said second split by suction, joining said second split with said third split of said second mold, attracting the fiber molded article to an inner surface of said third split by suction, and separating the fiber molded article from said second split,
<claim-text>wherein each of the first to fourth splits has flow passageways leading to an evacuation source or a compressor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a gas is blown from the inner surface of said second split toward the fiber molded article.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said second mold includes a drying mold.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said second mold includes a drying mold.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>monitoring said transferring of said fiber molded article when said fiber molded article is received by said third split.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said monitoring includes monitoring said transferring of said fiber molded article with at least one optical sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An apparatus for producing a fiber molded article comprising a papermaking mold composed of a first split and a second split, a second mold for receiving the molded article formed in the papermaking mold, said second mold composed of a third split and a fourth split, a moving means for moving the second and fourth splits, suction means for attracting the fiber molded article to an inner surface of each of the first, second, and third splits, and a control means for controlling the moving means and the suction means, wherein the control means controls the moving means and the suction means such that:
<claim-text>the papermaking mold is opened while attracting the fiber molded article to the inner surface of said first split of the papermaking mold by suction to separate the fiber molded article from the second split,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the papermaking mold is closed, and the molded article is released from attraction to the inner surface of the first split,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the papermaking mold is opened again while attracting the fiber molded article to the inner surface of said second split by suction to separate the fiber molded article from the inner surface of said first split,</claim-text>
<claim-text>said second split is joined with said third split, and the fiber molded article is attracted to the inner surface of said third split, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the fiber molded article is separated from said second split,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the first to fourth splits has flow passageways leading to an evacuation source or a compressor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The apparatus for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, which has a sensing means for monitoring the transfer of the fiber molded article when the fiber molded article is received by said second mold, and said control means controls said moving means and said suction means in response to an output from said sensing means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An apparatus for producing a fiber molded article, the apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a papermaking mold comprising a first split and a second split, said first split including a first suction element configured to attract and hold said molded article to an inner surface of said first split, said second split including a second suction element configured to attract and hold said molded article to an inner surface of said second split, and each of the first and second splits having flow passageways leading to an evacuation source or a compressor, each of said first split and said second splits including flow channels engraved on the inner surface thereof, a total open area ratio of the flow channels to a total surface area of the inner surface of each split is from 10% to 85%;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second mold comprising a third split and a fourth split, said third split including a third suction element configured to attract and hold said molded article to an inner surface of said third split, and each of the third and fourth splits having flow passageways leading to an evacuation source or a compressor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a moving element configured to move said second and fourth splits; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller configured to control said moving element and said first, second, and third suction elements.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The apparatus for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a first optical sensor configured to detect said article in said first split.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The apparatus for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a second optical sensor configured to detect said article in said second split.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The apparatus for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a third optical sensor configured to detect said article in said third split.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The apparatus for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a pressing member configured to be inserted in said article when said article is in said second mold, said member including a cavity configured to receive a pressurizing fluid to press said article against inner surfaces of said second mold.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The apparatus for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said pressurizing fluid is air.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The apparatus for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein said pressurizing fluid is oil.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method of producing a fiber molded article, the method comprising:
<claim-text>transferring a fiber molded article formed in a papermaking mold comprising a first split and a second split to a second mold comprising a third split and a fourth split, each of the first to fourth splits having flow passageways leading to an evacuation source or a compressor, wherein said transferring includes,</claim-text>
<claim-text>opening said papermaking mold while attracting said fiber molded article to an inner surface of said first split by suction to separate said fiber molded article from said second split,</claim-text>
<claim-text>closing said papermaking mold,</claim-text>
<claim-text>releasing said molded article from attraction to said inner surface of said first split,</claim-text>
<claim-text>opening said papermaking mold again while attracting said fiber molded article to an inner surface of said second split by suction,</claim-text>
<claim-text>joining said second split with said third split of said second mold,</claim-text>
<claim-text>attracting said fiber molded article to an inner surface of said third split by suction, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>separating said fiber molded article from said second split.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, further comprising blowing a gas from said inner surface of said second split toward said fiber molded article when separating said fiber molded article from said second split.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein said second mold includes a drying mold.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>monitoring said transferring of said fiber molded article when said fiber molded article is received by said third split.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method for producing a fiber molded article according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein said monitoring includes monitoring said transferring of said fiber molded article with at least one optical sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
