<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298187-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298187</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11407682</doc-number>
<date>20060419</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>CN</country>
<doc-number>2006 1 0024670</doc-number>
<date>20060310</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>55</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>327143</main-classification>
<further-classification>327142</further-classification>
<further-classification>327198</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">System and method for power on reset and under voltage lockout schemes</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5313112</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Macks</name>
<date>19940500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327143</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>26</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070210840</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070913</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zhu</last-name>
<first-name>Zhen</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ye</last-name>
<first-name>Jun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Zhiliang</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fang</last-name>
<first-name>Lieyi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Townsend and Townsend and Crew LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>On-Bright Electronics (Shanghai) Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Shanghai</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Wells</last-name>
<first-name>Kenneth B.</first-name>
<department>2816</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Luu</last-name>
<first-name>An T.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A system and method for power-on reset and under-voltage lockout schemes. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal, the second terminal being biased to a predetermined voltage. The system includes a second transistor, which include a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being configured to receive an input voltage. The system includes a first resistor that is associated with a first resistance. The first resistor includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage. The system includes a second resistor that is associated with a second resistance. The second resistor includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal. The system includes a first Zener diode that is associated with a first Zener voltage.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="126.15mm" wi="158.58mm" file="US07298187-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="162.56mm" wi="133.94mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298187-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="161.37mm" wi="153.50mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298187-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="128.61mm" wi="104.31mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298187-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="134.87mm" wi="102.36mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298187-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="122.26mm" wi="112.18mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298187-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="169.33mm" wi="143.51mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298187-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="157.90mm" wi="130.98mm" file="US07298187-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="130.30mm" wi="124.97mm" file="US07298187-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="146.47mm" wi="121.24mm" file="US07298187-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCES TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority to Chinese Patent Application No. 200610024670.2, filed Mar. 10, 2006, titled “System and Method for Power On Reset and Under Voltage Lockout Schemes,” by inventors Zhen Zhu, Jun Ye, Zhiliang Chen, and Lieyi Fang, commonly assigned, incorporated by reference herein for all purposes.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates in general to integrated circuits. More specifically, the invention provides a system and method for power-on reset (POR) and under-voltage lockout (UVLO) schemes. Merely by way of example, the invention is described as it applies to electronic power systems, but it should be recognized that the invention has a broader range of applicability.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Power-on reset (POR) and under-voltage lockout (UVLO) circuits have a wide range of applications. For example, in an electronic system during power on and off transitions, the power supply voltage, typically in order of several to tens of volts, often falls into an invalid state. During an initialization or power-up stage, which usually takes place when the supply voltage for the electronic system is switched on, the supply voltage rises from zero to an operational supply voltage. The operational supply voltage is often within a range associated with a source impedance or source current. During the process when the supply voltage rises from zero to an operational supply voltage, the supply voltage is less than a certain minimum voltage at which the electronic system is designed to properly function. Therefore it is often desirable to prevent any functioning of the electronic system when the supplied voltage is less than the minimum voltage. Generally, the electronic system should be in a reset mode when the supplied voltage is less than a threshold voltage, which is often the minimum voltage. When the electronic system is in the reset mode, components of the electronic system generally stay in their well-defined initial states, ready to properly function after the electronic system starts.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">To ensure that an electronic system properly initializes, a voltage detection circuit is often used to generate an output signal to indicate whether the supply voltage has reached a threshold or minimum voltage level. The output signal of the voltage detection circuit is accordingly used to enable or disable the functioning of circuit components.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Often POR and UVLO (POR/UVLO) circuits are used as a voltage detection circuit. In application, a POR/UVLO circuit in an electronic system monitors power supply voltage. When the power supply voltage reaches a predetermined voltage level, which could be a minimum supply voltage or a first threshold voltage, the POR/UVLO circuit generates a POR signal. The POR signal is an indicator to other components of the electronic system that the electronic system has been turned on. In certain instances, the POR/UVLO circuit generates a power-on reset indication when the system power ramps up to the first threshold level that allows the electronic system to operate. In response to the power-on reset indication, other components of the electronic system perform various useful functions. For example, the system components can reset latches and perform start-up operations. When the power supply voltage drops under a second threshold voltage, which may be substantially equally to the first threshold voltage or may be different, the POR/UVLO circuit indicates to the electronic system by generating a UVLO signal. In response to the UVLO signal, the electronic system may shuts down some or all of its components in order to protect the system.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an example of conventional system for power switching with POR/UVLO functions. The power switching system <b>100</b> includes, inter alia, a power supply <b>101</b> and a pulse width modulation (PWM) controller circuit <b>120</b>. The power supply <b>101</b> includes an alternative current (AC) source <b>102</b>, a rectifier <b>105</b>, and a start up resistor <b>110</b>. The PWM controller circuit <b>120</b> includes, inter alia, a PWM generator <b>122</b> and a POR/UVLO circuit <b>124</b>. During operation, the power supply <b>101</b> supplies voltages to the PWM controller circuit <b>120</b>, and the AC source <b>102</b> feeds an alternating current, which is rectified by the rectifier <b>105</b> and runs through the start up resistor <b>110</b>. The PWM controller circuit <b>120</b> often uses the start up resistor <b>110</b> to start the PWM generator <b>122</b>. The POR/UVLO circuit <b>124</b> provides indication signals to the PWM generator <b>122</b> to ensure that power switching system <b>100</b> is operating properly.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A POR/UVLO system is a useful application. However, conventional POR/UVLO systems, such as the conventional system illustrated on <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, generally consume a great amount of power due to high impedance. More specifically, the start up resistor <b>110</b> can be a source of significant energy inefficiency. This is because the voltage drop caused by the start up resistor <b>110</b>, which is the difference between the output voltage <b>106</b> and the low voltage supply (VDD) <b>112</b>, is large. As an example, the output voltage <b>106</b> is 370 volts DC, while the VDD <b>112</b> is only at 12 volts DC. Under light load or low load conditions, the power loss caused by the large voltage drop is great. To improve energy efficiency, a large start up resistor <b>110</b>, whose resistance may be in order of mega ohms, is often used. However, the larger resistance not only improves energy efficiency, but also, as being a drawback, significantly lowers the source current, which can be as low as several tens of micro amps, being supplied to the PWM generator <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Hence it is highly desirable to improve techniques for power-on reset and under-voltage lockout schemes.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The present invention relates in general to integrated circuits. More specifically, the invention provides a system and method for POR and UVLO schemes. Merely by way of example, the invention is described as it applies to electronic power systems, but it should be recognized that the invention has a broader range of applicability.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According to an embodiment, the present invention presents a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal, the second terminal being biased to a predetermined voltage. The system also includes a second transistor, which include a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being configured to receive an input voltage. Additionally, the system includes a first resistor that is associated with a first resistance. The first resistor includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage. The system also includes a second resistor that is associated with a second resistance. The second resistor includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal. In addition, the system includes a first Zener diode that is associated with a first Zener voltage. The first Zener diode includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage. Moreover, the system includes a second Zener diode that is associated with a second Zener voltage. The second Zener diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. the system additionally includes a third resistor that is associated with a third resistance. The third resistor includes a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal, the fourteenth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage. At the system, the first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal to generate a first signal. The first signal is capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout. The second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal. And the first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to an alternative embodiment, the present invention provides a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal, the second terminal being biased to a predetermined voltage. The system additionally includes a second transistor, which includes a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being configured to receive an input voltage. In addition, the system includes a first resistor that is associated with a first resistance. The first resistor includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage. The system also includes a second resistor that is associated with a second resistance. The second resistor includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal. In addition, the system includes a first Zener diode that is associated with a first Zener voltage. The first Zener diode includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a second Zener diode that is associated with a second Zener voltage. The second Zener diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. The system additionally includes a third resistor that is associated with a third resistance. The third resistor includes a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal, the fourteenth terminal coupled to the second terminal. Moreover, the system includes a third transistor, which includes a third gate, a fifteenth terminal, and a fourteenth terminal. The fifteenth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage, and sixteenth terminal are coupled to the sixth terminal. The system additionally includes a first inverter that includes a first inverter input and a first inverter output. The system also includes a second inverter that includes a second inverter input and a second inverter output. The second inverter input is coupled to the first inverter output, and the second inverter output is coupled to the third gate. At the system, the first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal. The second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal. The first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other. The second inverter output is configured to generate a signal, the signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to another alternative embodiment, the present invention provides a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first source, and a first drain. The first source is biased at a predetermined voltage. The system also includes a second transistor that includes a second gate, a second source, and a second drain. The second gate is coupled to the first drain, and the second source being biased at the predetermined voltage. In addition, the system includes a third transistor, which includes a third gate, a third source, and a third drain. The third source is biased at a predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a first resistor that includes a first terminal and a second terminal. The first terminal is biased at the predetermined voltage. The system also includes a second resistor. The second resistor includes a third terminal and a fourth terminal. The third terminal is coupled to the second terminal. The fourth terminal is coupled to the first gate. The system also includes a third resistor. The third resistor includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal. The fifth terminal is coupled to the fourth terminal. The system additionally includes a fourth resistor, which includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal. The eighth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. The seventh terminal being coupled to the second gate. The system additionally includes a first Zener diode that includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal. The ninth terminal is coupled to the sixth terminal. The tenth terminal is coupled to the second drain. They system also includes a second Zener diode. The second diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. The eleventh terminal is coupled to the tenth terminal. The twelfth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. The system also includes a first inverter that includes a first inverter input and a first inverter output. The first inverter input is coupled to the first drain. Additionally, the system includes a second inverter, which includes a second inverter input and a second inverter output. The second inverter input is coupled to the first inverter output. The second inverter output is coupled to the third gate. At the system, the second inverter output is configured to generate a signal. The signal is capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset and an under-voltage lockout.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to another alternative embodiment, the present invention provides a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal. The second terminal is biased to a predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a second transistor, which includes a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal. The third terminal is configured to receive an input voltage. The system also includes a first diode associated with a forward voltage. The first diode includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal. The fifth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. In addition, the system includes a second resistor associated with a second resistance. The second resistor includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal. The seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal. The system additionally includes a first Zener diode associated with a first Zener voltage. The first Zener diode includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal. The ninth terminal is biased to the predetermined voltage. The system also includes a second Zener diode associated with a second Zener voltage. The second Zener diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. Additionally, the system includes a third resistor associated with a third resistance. The third resistor includes a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal. The fourteenth terminal is coupled to the second terminal. Additionally, the system includes a third transistor, which includes a third gate, a fifteenth terminal, and a fourteenth terminal. The fifteenth terminal is configured to received the input voltage. The sixteenth terminal is coupled to the sixth terminal. The system also includes a first inverter, which includes a first inverter input and a first inverter output. Moreover, the system includes a second inverter, which includes a second inverter input and a second inverter output. The second inverter input is coupled to the first inverter output. The second inverter output is coupled to the third gate. The first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal. The second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal. The first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other. The second inverter output is configured to generate a signal, the signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to another alternative embodiment, the present invention provides a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first source, and a first drain. The first source is biased at a predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a second transistor, which includes a second gate, a second source, and a second drain. The second gate is coupled to the first drain. The second source is configured to receive an input voltage. The system also includes a third transistor, which includes a third gate, a third source, and a third drain. The third source is biased at the predetermined voltage. The system also includes a first diode, which includes a first terminal and a second terminal. The first terminal is biased at the predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a second resistor. The second resistor includes a third terminal and a fourth terminal. The third terminal is coupled to the second terminal. The fourth terminal is coupled to the first gate. The system also includes a third resistor, which includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal. The fifth terminal is coupled to the fourth terminal. Moreover, the system includes a fourth resistor, which includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal. The eighth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. The seventh terminal is coupled to the second gate. The system also includes a first Zener diode, which includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal. The ninth terminal is coupled to the sixth terminal, and the tenth terminal is coupled to the second drain. Additionally the system includes a second Zener diode. The second Zener diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. The eleventh terminal is coupled to the tenth terminal. The twelfth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. The system additionally includes a first inverter. The first inverter includes a first inverter input and a first inverter output. The first inverter input is coupled to the first drain. The system also includes a second inverter, which includes a second inverter input and a second inverter output. The second inverter input is coupled to the first inverter output. The second inverter output is coupled to the third gate. The second inverter output is configured to generate a signal. The signal is capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset and an under-voltage lockout.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Many benefits are achieved by way of the present invention over conventional techniques. It is to be appreciated that certain embodiments of the present invention provide a system and method for POR/UVLO schemes that provide lower power consumption and better reliability. According to an embodiment of the present invention, two positive feedback loops are used to ensure the reliability of the UVLO function.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Depending upon embodiment, one or more of these benefits may be achieved. These benefits and various additional objects, features and advantages of the present invention can be fully appreciated with reference to the detailed description and accompanying drawings that follow.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an example of conventional system for power switching with POR/UVLO functions;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a simplified diagram of an embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>a </i>is a timing diagram showing the voltages level at an NMOS and a second inverter according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>b </i>is a timing diagram illustrating the voltages levels at an NMOS and a second inverter according to another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>c </i>is a timing diagram illustrating the voltages levels at an NMOS, a first PMOS, and a second inverter according to yet another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a simplified diagram of an alternative embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a simplified diagram of an alternative embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes implemented with two NMOS and one PMOS;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a simplified diagram of an alternative embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes; and</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a simplified diagram of an alternative embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes implemented with two NMOS and one PMOS.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The present invention relates in general to integrated circuits. More specifically, the invention provides a system and method for POR and UVLO schemes. Merely by way of example, the invention is described as it applies to electronic power systems, but it should be recognized that the invention has a broader range of applicability.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a simplified diagram of an embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a POR/UVLO system <b>220</b> is connected to a power source <b>210</b>. The power source <b>210</b> includes a voltage source <b>212</b>, a start up resistor <b>216</b>, and a capacitor <b>214</b>. The POR/UVLO system <b>220</b> includes a first resistor <b>222</b>, a second resistor <b>226</b>, a third resistor <b>242</b>, a fourth resistor <b>229</b>, a first Zener diode <b>230</b>, a second Zener diode <b>234</b>, a first PMOS <b>252</b>, a second PMOS <b>254</b>, an NMOS <b>240</b>, a first inverter <b>246</b>, and a second inverter <b>250</b>. As an example, the first Zener diode is characterized by a first Zener voltage and the second Zener diode is characterized by a second Zener voltage. Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. Depending upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with other replaced.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">According to an embodiment of the invention, at the power source <b>210</b>, the voltage source <b>212</b> is connected to the start up resistor <b>216</b> at one end. The other end of the start up resistor <b>216</b> is connected to a node <b>218</b>. The capacitor <b>214</b> is grounded at one end and connected to the node <b>218</b> at the other end. The output of the power source <b>210</b> is connected to the node <b>218</b>. The POR/UVLO system <b>220</b> receives power at the node <b>218</b>. The first resistor <b>222</b> is connected to the power source <b>210</b> at the node <b>218</b> and the second resistor <b>226</b> at the node <b>224</b>. Also connected to the node <b>218</b> is the source of the first PMOS <b>252</b>. The drain of the first PMOS <b>252</b> is connected to the node <b>224</b>. For example, when there is a proper amount of voltage at the gate of the first PMOS <b>252</b>, there is little resistance between the source and the drain of the first PMOS <b>252</b> and the resistor <b>222</b> is essentially shorted. The second resistor <b>226</b> is connected to the gate of the second PMOS <b>254</b> and the fourth resistor <b>229</b> at the node <b>228</b>. The fourth resistor is connected to the first Zener diode <b>230</b> at the node <b>231</b>. The first Zener diode <b>230</b> is connected to the second Zener diode <b>234</b> at the node <b>232</b>. The second Zener diode <b>234</b> is grounded at the node <b>236</b>. Also connected to the node <b>232</b> is drain of the NMOS <b>240</b>, which is connected to the ground at its source. The gate of the NMOS <b>240</b> is connected to the third resistor <b>242</b> at the node <b>244</b>. The third resistor <b>242</b> is connected to the ground at the node <b>246</b>. For example, when there is a proper amount of voltage at the gate of the NMOS <b>240</b>, there is little resistance between the source and the drain of the NMOS <b>240</b> and the second Zener diode <b>234</b> is essentially shorted. The gate of the NMOS <b>240</b> is also connected to the first inverter <b>246</b> and the drain of the second PMOS <b>254</b> at the node <b>244</b>. The source of the second PMOS <b>254</b> is connected to the node <b>218</b>. The gate of the second PMOS <b>254</b> is connected to the node <b>228</b>. The first inverter <b>246</b> is connected to the second inverter <b>250</b> at the node <b>248</b>. The second inverter <b>250</b> is connected to the gate of the first PMOS <b>252</b> at the node <b>256</b>. The second inverter <b>250</b> provides an output signal for the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">According to an embodiment of the present invention, the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b> operates as two positive feedback loops. A first loop includes the second PMOS <b>254</b>, the NMOS <b>240</b>, the first Zener diode <b>230</b>, the second Zener diode <b>234</b>, the second resistor <b>226</b>, the third resistor <b>242</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>229</b>. A second loop includes the first PMOS <b>252</b>, the second PMOS <b>254</b>, the NMOS <b>240</b>, the first inverter <b>246</b>, the second inverter <b>250</b>, the second Zener diode <b>230</b>, the first resistor <b>222</b>, the second resistor <b>226</b>, the third resistor <b>242</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>229</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">As an example, when power source <b>210</b> starts up, the voltage source <b>212</b> charges the capacitor <b>214</b> through the start up resistor <b>216</b>. During the start up, the voltage at node <b>218</b> ramps up from zero voltage. When the voltage at node <b>218</b> is lower than the sum of the first and the second Zener voltages, no current flows between the node <b>218</b> and the node <b>224</b>. As a result, the first PMOS <b>252</b> is turned on, the second PMOS <b>254</b> is turned off, the NMOS <b>240</b> is turned off, the output of the first inverter <b>246</b> is logic high, and the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> is logic low.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Once the voltage at node <b>218</b> reaches a predetermined threshold voltage Vstart, the second PMOS <b>254</b> is turned on and begins conducing current. According an embodiment of the present invention, the threshold voltage Vstart may be determined by the following equation.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">
<maths id="MATH-US-00001" num="00001">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mi>Vstart</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Vzd1</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vzd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <mi>R2</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R3</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mi>R2</mi>
            </mfrac>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mstyle>
              <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
            </mstyle>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mi>VT_M0</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>1</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">According to Equation 1, Vdz1 and Vzd2 are the first Zener voltage and the second Zener voltage, R2 is the resistance of the second resistor <b>226</b>, R3 is the resistance of the fourth resistor <b>229</b>, and VT_M0 is the threshold voltage of the second PMOS <b>254</b>. Once the threshold voltage Vstart is reached, the second PMOS <b>254</b> is turned on and starts conducting current. As a result, a voltage Vr<b>0</b> starts rising up between the node <b>244</b> and the ground <b>246</b>. Once the voltage Vr<b>0</b> reaches the threshold voltage of the NMOS <b>240</b>, the NMOS <b>240</b> is turned on and begins conducting current. The current being conducted by the first NMOS <b>240</b> increases as the gate voltage (at the node <b>242</b>) of the NMOS <b>240</b>. As a result of the increased current flow across the NMOS <b>240</b>, the Vgs (voltage between gate and source, or voltage difference between the node <b>218</b> and the node <b>228</b>) of the second PMOS <b>254</b> builds up due to current flowing through the second resistor <b>226</b>. As the Vgs of the second PMOS <b>254</b> increases, more electrical current flows through the third resistor <b>242</b>, thus increasing the voltage at the node <b>244</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In short, the first positive feedback loop is formed according to the present embodiment of the invention: a higher voltage from the voltage source <b>210</b> causes the second PMOS <b>254</b> to conduct current, the current conducted by the second PMOS <b>254</b> causes the NMOS <b>240</b> to conduct current, the current conducted by the NMOS <b>240</b> causes the second PMOS <b>254</b> to conduct more current, and the positive feedback process continues. When the NMOS <b>240</b> is fully turned on, the second Zener diode <b>234</b> is shorted by the first NMOS <b>240</b>. As a result of the second Zener diode <b>234</b> being shorted, the gate voltage Vgs of the second PMOS <b>254</b> is large enough to ensure that the voltage at the node <b>244</b> is substantially equal to the voltage at the node <b>218</b>. Because of the voltage at the node <b>244</b>, the output of the first inverter <b>245</b> is logic low and the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> is logic high. The output of the second inverter <b>250</b> is provided at the node <b>256</b> to the first PMOS <b>252</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As discussed above, a second loop includes the first PMOS <b>252</b>, the second PMOS <b>254</b>, the NMOS <b>240</b>, the first inverter <b>246</b>, the second inverter <b>250</b>, the second Zener diode <b>230</b>, the first resistor <b>222</b>, the second resistor <b>226</b>, the third resistor <b>242</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>229</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention. The voltage at the node <b>256</b>, provided by the second inverter <b>250</b>, turns the first PMOS <b>252</b> on or off. When the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> is logic high, the first PMOS <b>252</b> is turned off. For example, the first PMOS <b>252</b> is not conducting current. The first PMOS <b>252</b> being turned off ensures that the second PMOS <b>254</b> stays on and continues conducting current, and the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> stays at logic high. In short, the second feedback loop is formed according to the present embodiment of the invention: the high logic output from the second inverter <b>250</b> ensures that the first PMOS <b>252</b> is turned off, the first PMOS <b>252</b> being turned off allows the second PMOS <b>254</b> to continue conducting current, the current conducted by the second PMOS <b>254</b> ensures that the voltage at the node <b>244</b> stays high and thus the output from the second inverter <b>250</b> stays high, and the positive feedback process continuous.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">As an example, the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b> is used in conjunction with other electronic components, such as a PWM generator and a gate driver. In one embodiment, the output provided by the second inverter <b>250</b> at logic high may be used to turn on these components and ensure these components remain functional.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Under certain conditions according to an embodiment of the present invention, components such as the PWM generator may consume more current than that provided by the power source <b>210</b>. For example, where a PWM generator receives power from the power source <b>210</b> at the node <b>218</b>, the PWM generator may, at times, consume more power than the power that the power source <b>210</b> is capable to supply. Consequentially, the voltage at the node <b>218</b> starts falling from the high voltage at which the PWM generator operates. Once the voltage at the node <b>218</b> falls below a predetermined voltage Vuvlo, the first PMOS <b>254</b> begins turning off. According to an embodiment of the present invention, the voltage Vuvlo is expressed by the following equation.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">
<maths id="MATH-US-00002" num="00002">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mi>Vuvlo</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Vzd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <mi>R1</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R2</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R3</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mrow>
                <mi>R1</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R2</mi>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mstyle>
              <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
            </mstyle>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mi>VT_M0</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>2</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">According to Equation 2, Vdz2 is the second Zener voltage, R1 is the resistance of the first resistor <b>222</b>, R2 is the resistance of the second resistor <b>226</b>, R3 is the resistance of the fourth resistor <b>229</b>, and VT_M0 is the threshold voltage of the second PMOS <b>254</b>. When the second PMOS <b>254</b> decreases conducting current, the current that flows through the third resistor <b>242</b> decreases, causing the voltage at the node <b>244</b> to drop. Due to the voltage drop at the node <b>244</b>, which is connected to the gate of the NMOS <b>240</b>, the NMOS <b>240</b> decreases the current being conducted. As a part of the first positive feedback loop, the decreased current being conducted by the NMOS <b>240</b> decreases the voltage Vgs of the first PMOS <b>254</b>. As the first positive feedback loops continues in operation, the first PMOS <b>254</b> eventually turns off, and the voltage at node <b>244</b> decreases to zero. As a result, the output of the first inverter <b>246</b> is at logic high and the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> is at logic low. In one embodiment, the output provided by the second inverter <b>250</b> at logic low may be used to turn off other electronic components, such as a PWM generator and a gate driver.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">It is to be appreciated that the present embodiment of the invention further provides the second positive feedback loop to ensure reliable UVLO. The voltages at the first NMOS <b>240</b> and the output of second inverter <b>250</b>, as operating under the condition set by an embodiment of the present invention, is shown on <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>a </i>is a timing diagram showing the voltages level at an NMOS and a second inverter according to an embodiment of the present invention. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>a </i>shows a first voltage profile <b>310</b> for the gate of the first NMOS <b>240</b> and a second voltage profile <b>320</b> for the output of the second inverter <b>250</b>. As can be seen, the voltage according to the second voltage profile usually only drops from high to low after the voltage according to the first voltage profile has dropped from high to low first. As an example applied to an embodiment of the present invention, the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> is turned to logic low after the second PMOS <b>240</b> has already been turned off. However, it is often not possible to always turn off PMOS <b>240</b> before obtaining a logic low at the output of the second inverter <b>250</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>b </i>is a timing diagram illustrating the voltages levels at an NMOS and a second inverter according to another embodiment of the present invention. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>b </i>shows a first voltage profile <b>330</b> for the gate of the first NMOS <b>240</b> and a second voltage profile <b>340</b> for the output of the second inverter <b>250</b>. In contrast to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>a</i>, the output voltage of the second inverter drops to low before the voltage level at the first NMOS reaches low. As can be seen on <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>b</i>, the voltage profile <b>340</b> for the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> drops from high to low first. As a result, the voltage profile <b>340</b> is not in synchronization with the voltage profile <b>330</b> for the first NMOS <b>240</b>, and the first NMOS <b>240</b> may fall into an invalid state <b>350</b> if the second feedback loop is not included in the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b>. For example, when the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> produces a logic low, this output is used to turn off a PWM generator. However, because the first NMOS <b>240</b> is not turned off, the voltage source <b>210</b> continues to deliver current. The capacitor <b>214</b> and the start up resistor <b>216</b> recharges voltage at the node <b>218</b>. Due to the voltage at the node <b>218</b>, the second PMOS <b>254</b> may be turned on. With PMOS <b>254</b> turned on, the voltage at node <b>218</b> may falls between Vstart and Vuvlo, i.e., lower than the start up voltage but higher than the UVLO voltage. The output of the second inverter <b>250</b> stays at logic low, and the first NMOS <b>240</b> goes into an indefinite state, i.e., neither fully on or fully off. Therefore, the first feedback loop by itself does not provide a reliable UVLO function. According to an embodiment, the second feedback loops is used to help prevent indefinite state and ensure proper function of the PWM generator. As a result, the PWM generator is turned off and cannot be restarted. It is to be appreciated that the present invention presents a novel system for providing a reliable UVLO function. According to an embodiment of the present invention, the second positive feedback loop is used to ensure the reliability of the UVLO function.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>c </i>is a timing diagram illustrating the voltages levels at an NMOS, a first PMOS, and a second inverter according to yet another embodiment of the present invention. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. A second positive feedback loop is used to ensure the reliability of the UVLO function as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>c </i>shows a first voltage profile <b>360</b> for the NMOS <b>240</b>, a second voltage profile <b>370</b> for the output of the second inverter <b>250</b>, and a third voltage profile <b>380</b> for the first PMOS <b>252</b>. As an example, if the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> drops from high to low before the first NMOS <b>240</b> drops from high to low, the PWM generator is turned off by the logic low at the output of the second inverter <b>250</b>. When the PWM generator is turned off and consumes no current, the capacitor <b>214</b> and the start up resistor <b>216</b> recharges voltage at the node <b>218</b>, causing the voltage at the node <b>218</b> to ramp up again. At the same time, the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> at logic low turns on the first PMOS <b>252</b> and decreases the voltage Vgs of the second PMOS <b>254</b>. Due to the decreased voltage at Vgs, the second PMOS delivers less current to the third resistor <b>242</b>, and the voltage at the node <b>244</b> decreases. The decrease of voltage at node <b>244</b> decreases the Vgs of the NMOS <b>240</b>. As the second feedback loop continues in operation, the NMOS <b>240</b> and the second PMOS <b>254</b> become fully turned off, the first PMOS <b>252</b> is turned on, and the output of the second inverter <b>250</b> stays at logic low. The POR/UVLO system <b>220</b> is itself shut off and turns off other components such as the PWM generator, along with other components.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As discussed above and further emphasized here, although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. During upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with other replaced. For example, the fourth resistor <b>229</b> may be removed from the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b>. In another example, additional diodes may be used to modify start up voltage and the UVLO voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a simplified diagram of an alternative embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b> is connected to a power source <b>1210</b>. The power source <b>1210</b> includes a voltage source <b>1212</b>, a start up resistor <b>1216</b>, and a capacitor <b>1214</b>. The POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b> includes a first resistor <b>1222</b>, a second resistor <b>1226</b>, a third resistor <b>1242</b>, a fourth resistor <b>1229</b>, a first Zener diode <b>1230</b>, a second Zener diode <b>1234</b>, a first diode <b>1235</b>, a second diode <b>1237</b>, a first PMOS <b>1252</b>, a second PMOS <b>1254</b>, an NMOS <b>1240</b>, a first inverter <b>1246</b>, and a second inverter <b>1250</b>. As an example, the first Zener diode is characterized by a first Zener voltage and the second Zener diode is characterized by a second Zener voltage. Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. During upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with other replaced.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">According to an embodiment of the invention, at the power source <b>1210</b>, the voltage source <b>1212</b> is connected to the start up resistor <b>1216</b> at one end. The other end of the start up resistor <b>1216</b> is connected to a node <b>1218</b>. The capacitor <b>1214</b> is grounded at one end and connected to the node <b>1218</b> at the other end. The output of the power source <b>1210</b> is connected to the node <b>1218</b>. The POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b> receives power at the node <b>1218</b>. The first resistor <b>1222</b> is connected to the power source <b>1210</b> at the node <b>1218</b> and the second resistor <b>1226</b> at the node <b>1224</b>. Also connected to the node <b>1218</b> is the source of the first PMOS <b>1252</b>. The drain of the first PMOS <b>1252</b> is connected to the node <b>1224</b>. For example, when there is a proper amount of voltage at the gate of the first PMOS <b>1252</b>, there is little resistance between the source and the drain of the first PMOS <b>1252</b> and the resistor <b>1222</b> is essentially shorted. The second resistor <b>1226</b> is connected to the gate of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> and the fourth resistor <b>1229</b> at the node <b>1228</b>. The fourth resistor is connected to the first Zener diode <b>1230</b> at the node <b>1231</b>. The first Zener diode <b>1230</b> is connected to the first diode <b>1237</b> in series. The first diode <b>1237</b>, at the other end, is connected to the second Zener diode <b>1234</b> at the node <b>1232</b>. The second Zener diode <b>1234</b> is connected to the second diode <b>1235</b> in series. The second diode <b>1235</b>, at the other end, is grounded at the node <b>1236</b>. Also connected to the node <b>1232</b> is drain of the NMOS <b>1240</b>, which is connected to the ground at its source. The gate of the NMOS <b>1240</b> is connected to the third resistor <b>1242</b> at the node <b>1244</b>. The third resistor <b>1242</b> is connected to the ground at the node <b>1246</b>. For example, when there is a proper amount of voltage at the gate of the NMOS <b>1240</b>, there is little resistance between the source and the drain of the NMOS <b>1240</b> and the second Zener diode <b>1234</b> is essentially shorted. The gate of the NMOS <b>1240</b> is also connected to the first inverter <b>1246</b> and the drain of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> at the node <b>1244</b>. The source of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> is connected to the node <b>1218</b>. The gate of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> is connected to the node <b>1228</b>. The first inverter <b>1246</b> is connected to the second inverter <b>1250</b> at the node <b>1248</b>. The second inverter <b>1250</b> is connected to the gate of the first PMOS <b>1252</b> at the node <b>1256</b>. The second inverter <b>1250</b> provides an output signal for the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">According to an embodiment of the inventions, the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b> operates as two positive feedback loops. A first loop includes the second PMOS <b>1254</b>, the first NMOS <b>1240</b>, the first Zener diode <b>1230</b>, the second Zener diode <b>1234</b>, the first diode <b>1235</b>, the second diode <b>1237</b>, the second resistor <b>1226</b>, the third resistor <b>1242</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>1229</b>. A second loop includes the first PMOS <b>1252</b>, the second PMOS <b>1254</b>, the NMOS <b>1240</b>, the first inverter <b>1246</b>, the second inverter <b>1250</b>, the second Zener diode <b>1230</b>, the first diode <b>1235</b>, the first resistor <b>1222</b>, the second resistor <b>1226</b>, the third resistor <b>1242</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>1229</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As a example, when power source <b>1210</b> starts up, the voltage source <b>1212</b> charges the capacitor <b>1214</b> through the start up resistor <b>1218</b>. During the start up, the voltage at node <b>1218</b> ramps up from zero voltage. When the voltage at node <b>1218</b> is lower than the sum of the first and the second Zener voltages and the forward voltages of the first diode <b>1235</b> and the second diode <b>1237</b>, no current flows between the node <b>1218</b> and the node <b>1224</b>. As a result, the first PMOS <b>1252</b> is turned on, the second PMOS <b>1254</b> is turned off, the NMOS <b>1240</b> is turned off, the first inverter <b>1246</b> is logic high, and the second inverter <b>1250</b> is logic low.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Once the voltage at node <b>1218</b> reaches a predetermined threshold voltage Vstart, the second PMOS <b>1254</b> is turned on and begins conducing current. According an embodiment of the present invention, the threshold voltage Vstart may be determined by the following equation.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">
<maths id="MATH-US-00003" num="00003">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mi>Vstart</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Vzd1</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vzd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vd1</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <mi>R2</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R3</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mi>R2</mi>
            </mfrac>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mstyle>
              <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
            </mstyle>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mi>VT_M0</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>3</mn>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mi>a</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">According to Equation 3a, Vdz1 and Vzd2 are the first Zener voltage and the second, Zener voltage, Vd1 is the forward voltage of the first diode <b>1235</b>, Vd2 is the forward voltage of the second diode <b>1237</b>, R2 is the resistance of the second resistor <b>1226</b>, R3 is the resistance of the fourth resistor <b>1229</b>, and VT_M0 is the threshold voltage of the second PMOS <b>1254</b>. It is to be appreciated that additional diodes may be added to the system <b>1220</b> to modify the value of the start up voltage. Once the threshold voltage is reached, the second PMOS <b>1254</b> is turned on and start conducting current. As a result, a voltage Vr<b>0</b> starts rising up between the node <b>1242</b> and the ground <b>1246</b>. Once the voltage Vr<b>0</b> reaches the threshold voltage of the NMOS <b>1240</b>, the NMOS <b>1240</b> is turned on and begins conducting current. The current being conducted by the NMOS <b>1240</b> increases as the gate voltage (at the node <b>1242</b>) of the first NMOS <b>1240</b>. As a result of the increased current flow across the NMOS <b>1240</b>, the Vgs (voltage between gate and source, or voltage difference between the node <b>1218</b> and the node <b>1228</b>) of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> builds up due to current flowing through the second resistor <b>1226</b>. As the Vgs of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> increases, more electrical current flows through the third resistor <b>1242</b>, thus increasing the voltage at the node <b>1244</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In short, the first positive feedback loop is formed according to the present embodiment of the invention: a higher from the voltage source <b>1210</b> causes the second PMOS <b>1254</b> to conduct current, the current conducted by the second PMOS <b>1254</b> causes the NMOS <b>1240</b> to conduct current, the current conducted by the NMOS <b>1240</b> causes the second PMOS <b>1254</b> to conduct more current, and the positive process continues. When the first NMOS <b>1240</b> is fully turned on, the second Zener diode <b>1234</b> is shorted by the NMOS <b>1240</b>. As a result of the second Zener diode <b>1234</b> being shorted, the gate voltage Vgs of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> is large enough to ensure that the voltage at the node <b>1244</b> is substantially equal to the voltage at the node <b>1218</b>. Because of the voltage at the node <b>1244</b>, the first inverter <b>1245</b> is logic low and the second inverter <b>1250</b> is logic high. The output of the second inverter <b>1250</b> is provided at the node <b>1256</b> to the first PMOS <b>1252</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The voltage at the node <b>1256</b>, provided by the second inverter <b>1250</b>, turns the first PMOS <b>1252</b> on or off. When the output of the second inverter <b>1250</b> is logic high, the first PMOS <b>1252</b> is turned on, i.e., the first PMOS <b>1252</b> is not conducting current. The first PMOS <b>1252</b> being turned off ensures that the second PMOS <b>1254</b> stays on and continues conducting current, and the output of the second inverter <b>1250</b> stays at logic high. In short, the second feedback loop is formed according to the present embodiment of the invention: the high logic output from the second inverter <b>1250</b> ensures that the first PMOS <b>1252</b> is turned off, the first PMOS <b>1252</b> being turned off allows the second PMOS <b>1254</b> to continue conducting current, the current conducted by the second PMOS <b>1254</b> ensures that the voltage at the node <b>1244</b> stays high and thus the output from the second inverter <b>1250</b> stays high, and the positive feedback process continuous.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As an example, the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b> is used in conjunction with other electronic components, such as a PWM generator and a gate driver. The output provided by the second inverter <b>1250</b> at logic high may be used to turn out these components and ensure these components remain functional.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">According to an embodiment of the present invention, components such as the PWM generator may consume more current than that provided by the power source <b>1210</b>. Consequentially, the voltage at the node <b>1218</b> starts falling from the high voltage at which the PWM generator operates. Once the voltage at the node <b>1218</b> falls below a predetermined voltage Vuvlo, the first PMOS <b>1254</b> begins turning off. According to an embodiment of the present invention, the voltage Vuvlo is expressed by the following equation.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">
<maths id="MATH-US-00004" num="00004">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mi>Vuvlo</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Vzd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <mi>R1</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R2</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R3</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mrow>
                <mi>R1</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R2</mi>
              </mrow>
            </mfrac>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mstyle>
              <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
            </mstyle>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mi>VT_M0</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>4</mn>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mi>a</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">According to Equation 4a, Vdz2 is the second Zener voltage, Vd2 is the forward voltage of the second diode <b>1237</b>, R1 is the resistance of the first resistor <b>1222</b>, R2 is the resistance of the second resistor <b>1226</b>, R3 is the resistance of the fourth resistor <b>1229</b>, and VT_M0 is the threshold voltage of the second PMOS <b>1254</b>. When the second PMOS <b>1254</b> decreases conducting current, the current that flows through the third resistor <b>1242</b> decreases, causing the voltage at the node <b>1244</b> to drop. Due to the voltage drop at the node <b>1244</b>, which is connected to the gate of the NMOS <b>1240</b>, the NMOS <b>1240</b> decreases the current being conducted. As a part of the first positive feedback loop, the decreased current being conducted by the NMOS <b>1240</b> decreases the voltage Vgs of the first PMOS <b>1254</b>. As the first positive feedback loops continues in operation, the first PMOS <b>1254</b> eventually turns off, and the voltage at node <b>1244</b> decreases to zero. As a result, the first inverter <b>1246</b> is at logic high and the second inverter <b>1250</b> is at logic low.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. During upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with other replaced. For example, the fourth resistor <b>1229</b> may be removed from the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b>. In another example, the first diode <b>1235</b> and the second diode <b>1237</b> may be removed from the system <b>1220</b> to obtain an alternative embodiment of the present invention. In yet another example, the additional diodes may be added in series to the first and second diode to modify the operation parameters of the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b>. Additionally, PMOS and NMOS in alternative configurations may be used to implement an alternative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a simplified diagram of an alternative embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes implemented with two NMOS and one PMOS. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. The system <b>500</b> includes a power source <b>510</b> and a POR/UVLO system <b>550</b>. The power source includes a voltage source <b>504</b>, a start up resistor <b>506</b>, and a capacitor <b>502</b>. The POR/UVLO system <b>550</b> includes a first diode <b>514</b>, a second diode <b>518</b>, a first Zener diode <b>512</b>, a second Zener diode <b>516</b>, a first resistor <b>524</b>, a second resistor <b>522</b>, a third resistor <b>520</b>, a fourth resistor <b>530</b>, a PMOS <b>532</b>, a first NMOS <b>528</b>, a second NMOS <b>526</b>, a first inverter <b>534</b>, and a second inverter <b>536</b>. Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the POR/UVLO system <b>550</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. During upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with other replaced. For example, the first diode <b>514</b> and the second diode <b>518</b> may be removed.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">According to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the power source <b>510</b> is connected supplies power to the POR/UVLO system <b>550</b> at the node <b>511</b>. The voltage source <b>504</b> is connected in series to the start up resistor <b>506</b>, which is connected to the capacitor <b>502</b> and the node <b>511</b>. The node <b>511</b> is connected to the first Zener diode <b>512</b>, the source of the PMOS <b>532</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>540</b>. The first Zener diode <b>512</b> is connected in series with the first diode <b>514</b>. The first diode <b>514</b> is connected in series with the second Zener diode <b>516</b>. The Zener diode <b>516</b> is connected in series with the second diode <b>518</b>. The second diode <b>518</b> is connected in series with the third resistor <b>520</b>. The third resistor <b>520</b> is connected to the second resistor <b>522</b> and the gate for the first NMOS <b>528</b>. The source of the first NMOS <b>528</b> is connected to the ground. The drain of the first NMOS <b>528</b> is connected to the fourth resistor <b>540</b>, the gate of the PMOS <b>532</b>, and the input of the first inverter <b>534</b>. The second resistor is connected to the drain of the second NMOS <b>526</b> and the first resistor <b>524</b>. The first resistor <b>524</b> is connected to the ground. The source of the second NMOS <b>526</b> is connected to the ground. The gate of the second NMOS <b>526</b> is connected to the output of the second inverter <b>526</b>. The input of the second inverter <b>526</b> is connected to the output of the first inverter <b>534</b>. The second inverter <b>526</b> provides an output signal for the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">According to an embodiment of the invention, the POR/UVLO system <b>550</b> operates in essentially the same manner as the POR/UVLO system <b>220</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, utilizing two positive feedback loops. For example, the first feedback loop includes the first Zener Diode <b>512</b>, the first diode <b>514</b>, the second Zener diode <b>516</b>, the second diode <b>518</b>, the third resistor <b>520</b>, the first resistor <b>524</b>, the second resistor <b>522</b>, the fourth resistor <b>540</b>, the PMOS <b>532</b>, and the first NMOS <b>528</b>. The second feedback loop includes the first Zener Diode <b>512</b>, the first diode <b>514</b>, the third resistor <b>520</b>, the first resistor <b>524</b>, the second resistor <b>522</b>, the fourth resistor <b>540</b>, the PMOS <b>532</b>, the first NMOS <b>528</b>, the second NMOS <b>526</b>, the first inverter <b>534</b>, and the second inverter <b>536</b>. According to one embodiment, the operation of the two feedback loop is substantially the same as the two feedback loops according an embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a simplified diagram of an alternative embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b> is connected to a power source <b>2210</b>. The power source <b>2210</b> includes a voltage source <b>2212</b>, a start up resistor <b>2216</b>, and a capacitor <b>2214</b>. The POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b> includes, a second resistor <b>1226</b>, a third resistor <b>1242</b>, a fourth resistor <b>1229</b>, a first Zener diode <b>1230</b>, a second Zener diode <b>1234</b>, a first diode <b>1235</b>, a second diode <b>1237</b>, a third diode <b>1222</b>, a first PMOS <b>1252</b>, a second PMOS <b>1254</b>, an NMOS <b>1240</b>, a first inverter <b>1246</b>, and a second inverter <b>1250</b>. As an example, the first Zener diode is characterized by a first Zener voltage and the second Zener diode is characterized by a second Zener voltage. Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. During upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with other replaced.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">According the present embodiment of the invention, at the power source <b>2210</b>, the voltage source <b>2212</b> is connected to the start up resistor <b>2216</b> at one end. The other end of the start up resistor <b>2216</b> is connected to a node <b>2218</b>. The capacitor <b>2214</b> is grounded at one end and connected to the node <b>2218</b> at the other end. The output of the power source <b>2210</b> is connected to the node <b>2218</b>. The POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b> receives power at the node <b>2218</b>. The third diode <b>2222</b> is connected to the power source <b>2210</b> at the node <b>2218</b> and the second resistor <b>2226</b> at the node <b>2224</b>. Also connected to the node <b>2218</b> is the source of the first PMOS <b>2252</b>. The drain of the first PMOS <b>2252</b> is connected to the node <b>2224</b>. For example, when there is a proper amount of voltage at the gate of the first PMOS <b>2252</b>, there is little resistance between the source and the drain of the first PMOS <b>2252</b> and the third diode <b>2222</b> is essentially shorted. The second resistor <b>2226</b> is connected to the gate of the second PMOS <b>2254</b> and the fourth resistor <b>2229</b> at the node <b>2228</b>. The fourth resistor is connected to the first Zener diode <b>2230</b> at the node <b>2231</b>. The first Zener diode <b>2230</b> is connected to the first diode <b>2237</b> in series. The first diode <b>2237</b>, at the other end, is connected to the second Zener diode <b>2234</b> at the node <b>2232</b>. The second Zener diode <b>2234</b> is connected to the second diode <b>2235</b> in series. The second diode <b>2235</b>, at the other end, is grounded at the node <b>2236</b>. Also connected to the node <b>2232</b> is drain of the NMOS <b>2240</b>, which is connected to the ground at its source. The gate of the NMOS <b>2240</b> is connected to the third resistor <b>2242</b> at the node <b>2244</b>. The third resistor <b>2242</b> is connected to the ground at the node <b>2246</b>. For example, when there is a proper amount of voltage at the gate of the NMOS <b>2240</b>, there is little resistance between the source and the drain of the NMOS <b>2240</b> and the second Zener diode <b>2234</b> is essentially shorted. The gate of the NMOS <b>2240</b> is also connected to the first inverter <b>2246</b> and the drain of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> at the node <b>2244</b>. The source of the second PMOS <b>1254</b> is connected to the node <b>1218</b>. The gate of the second PMOS <b>2254</b> is connected to the node <b>2228</b>. The first inverter <b>1246</b> is connected to the second inverter <b>2250</b> at the node <b>2248</b>. The second inverter <b>1250</b> is connected to the gate of the first PMOS <b>2252</b> at the node <b>2256</b>. The second inverter <b>2250</b> provides an output signal for the POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">According to the present embodiment of the inventions, the POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b> operates as two positive feedback loops. A first loop includes the second PMOS <b>2254</b>, the first NMOS <b>2240</b>, the first Zener diode <b>2230</b>, the second Zener diode <b>2234</b>, the first diode <b>2235</b>, the second diode <b>2237</b>, the second resistor <b>2226</b>, the third resistor <b>2242</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>2229</b>. A second loop includes the first PMOS <b>2252</b>, the second PMOS <b>2254</b>, the NMOS <b>2240</b>, the first inverter <b>2246</b>, the second inverter <b>2250</b>, the second Zener diode <b>2230</b>, the first diode <b>2235</b>, the third diode <b>2222</b>, the second resistor <b>2226</b>, the third resistor <b>2242</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>2229</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">As a example, when power source <b>2210</b> starts up, the voltage source <b>2212</b> charges the capacitor <b>2214</b> through the start up resistor <b>2218</b>. During the start up, the voltage at node <b>2218</b> ramps up from zero voltage. When the voltage at node <b>2218</b> is lower than the sum of the first and the second Zener voltages and the forward voltages of the first diode <b>2235</b> and the second diode <b>1237</b>, no current flows between the node <b>2218</b> and the node <b>2224</b>. As a result, the first PMOS <b>2252</b> is turned on, the second PMOS <b>2254</b> is turned off, the NMOS <b>2240</b> is turned off, the first inverter <b>2246</b> is logic high, and the second inverter <b>2250</b> is logic low.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Once the voltage at node <b>2218</b> reaches a predetermined threshold voltage Vstart, the second PMOS <b>2254</b> is turned on and begins conducing current. According an embodiment of the present invention, the threshold voltage Vstart may be determined by the following equation.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">
<maths id="MATH-US-00005" num="00005">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mi>Vstart</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Vzd1</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vzd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vd1</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vd3</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <mi>R2</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R3</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mi>R2</mi>
            </mfrac>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mstyle>
              <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
            </mstyle>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mi>VT_M0</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>3</mn>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mi>b</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">According to Equation 3b, Vdz1 and Vzd2 are the first Zener voltage and the second Zener voltage, Vd1 is the forward voltage of the first diode <b>2235</b>, Vd2 is the forward voltage of the second diode <b>2237</b>, Vd3 is the forward voltage of the third diode <b>2222</b>, R2 is the resistance of the second resistor <b>2226</b>, R3 is the resistance of the fourth resistor <b>2229</b>, and VT_M0 is the threshold voltage of the second PMOS <b>2254</b>. It is to be appreciated that additional diodes may be added to the system <b>2220</b> to modify the value of the start up voltage. Once the threshold voltage is reached, the second PMOS <b>2254</b> is turned on and start conducting current. As a result, a voltage Vr<b>0</b> starts rising up between the node <b>2242</b> and the ground <b>1246</b>. Once the voltage Vr<b>0</b> reaches the threshold voltage of the NMOS <b>2240</b>, the NMOS <b>2240</b> is turned on and begins conducting current. The current being conducted by the NMOS <b>2240</b> increases as the gate voltage (at the node <b>2242</b>) of the first NMOS <b>2240</b>. As a result of the increased current flow across the NMOS <b>2240</b>, the Vgs (voltage between gate and source, or voltage difference between the node <b>2218</b> and the node <b>2228</b>) of the second PMOS <b>2254</b> builds up due to current flowing through the second resistor <b>2226</b>. As the Vgs of the second PMOS <b>2254</b> increases, more electrical current flows through the third resistor <b>2242</b>, thus increasing the voltage at the node <b>2244</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">In short, the first positive feedback loop is formed according to the present embodiment of the invention: a higher from the voltage source <b>2210</b> causes the second PMOS <b>2254</b> to conduct current, the current conducted by the second PMOS <b>2254</b> causes the NMOS <b>2240</b> to conduct current, the current conducted by the NMOS <b>2240</b> causes the second PMOS <b>2254</b> to conduct more current, and the positive process continues. When the first NMOS <b>2240</b> is fully turned on, the second Zener diode <b>2234</b> is shorted by the NMOS <b>2240</b>. As a result of the second Zener diode <b>2234</b> being shorted, the gate voltage Vgs of the second PMOS <b>2254</b> is large enough to ensure that the voltage at the node <b>2244</b> is substantially equal to the voltage at the node <b>2218</b>. Because of the voltage at the node <b>2244</b>, the first inverter <b>2245</b> is logic low and the second inverter <b>2250</b> is logic high. The output of the second inverter <b>2250</b> is provided at the node <b>2256</b> to the first PMOS <b>2252</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The voltage at the node <b>2256</b>, provided by the second inverter <b>2250</b>, turns the first PMOS <b>2252</b> on or off. When the output of the second inverter <b>2250</b> is logic high, the first PMOS <b>2252</b> is turned on, i.e., the first PMOS <b>2252</b> is not conducting current. The first PMOS <b>1252</b> being turned off ensures that the second PMOS <b>1254</b> stays on and continues conducting current, and the output of the second inverter <b>1250</b> stays at logic high. In short, the second feedback loop is formed according to the present embodiment of the invention: the high logic output from the second inverter <b>2250</b> ensures that the first PMOS <b>2252</b> is turned off, the first PMOS <b>2252</b> being turned off allows the second PMOS <b>2254</b> to continue conducting current, the current conducted by the second PMOS <b>2254</b> ensures that the voltage at the node <b>2244</b> stays high and thus the output from the second inverter <b>2250</b> stays high, and the positive feedback process continuous.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">As an example, the POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b> is used in conjunction with other electronic components, such as a PWM generator and a gate driver. The output provided by the second inverter <b>2250</b> at logic high may be used to turn out these components and ensure these components remain functional.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">According to an embodiment of the present invention, components such as the PWM generator may consume more current than that provided by the power source <b>2210</b>. Consequentially, the voltage at the node <b>2218</b> starts falling from the high voltage at which the PWM generator operates. Once the voltage at the node <b>2218</b> falls below a predetermined voltage Vuvlo, the first PMOS <b>2254</b> begins turning off. According to an embodiment of the present invention, the voltage Vuvlo is expressed by the following equation.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">
<maths id="MATH-US-00006" num="00006">
<math overflow="scroll">
<mtable>
  <mtr>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mi>Vuvlo</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Vzd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vd2</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mi>Vd3</mi>
          <mo>+</mo>
          <mrow>
            <mfrac>
              <mrow>
                <mi>R2</mi>
                <mo>+</mo>
                <mi>R3</mi>
              </mrow>
              <mi>R2</mi>
            </mfrac>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mstyle>
              <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
            </mstyle>
            <mo>⁢</mo>
            <mi>VT_M0</mi>
          </mrow>
        </mrow>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
    <mtd>
      <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
          <mi>Equation</mi>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mstyle>
            <mspace width="0.8em" height="0.8ex"/>
          </mstyle>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mn>4</mn>
          <mo>⁢</mo>
          <mi>b</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
    </mtd>
  </mtr>
</mtable>
</math>
</maths>
</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">According to Equation 4b, Vdz2 is the second Zener voltage, Vd2 is the forward voltage of the second diode <b>2237</b>, Vd3 is the forward voltage of the third diode <b>2222</b>, R2 is the resistance of the second resistor <b>2226</b>, R3 is the resistance of the fourth resistor <b>2229</b>, and VT_M0 is the threshold voltage of the second PMOS <b>2254</b>. When the second PMOS <b>2254</b> decreases conducting current, the current that flows through the third resistor <b>2242</b> decreases, causing the voltage at the node <b>2244</b> to drop. Due to the voltage drop at the node <b>2244</b>, which is connected to the gate of the NMOS <b>2240</b>, the NMOS <b>2240</b> decreases the current being conducted. As a part of the first positive feedback loop, the decreased current being conducted by the NMOS <b>2240</b> decreases the voltage Vgs of the first PMOS <b>2254</b>. As the first positive feedback loops continues in operation, the first PMOS <b>2254</b> eventually turns off, and the voltage at node <b>2244</b> decreases to zero. As a result, the first inverter <b>2246</b> is at logic high and the second inverter <b>2250</b> is at logic low.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. During upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with other replaced. For example, the fourth resistor <b>2229</b> may be removed from the POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b>. In another example, the first diode <b>2235</b> and the second diode <b>1237</b> may be removed from the system <b>2220</b> to obtain an alternative embodiment of the present invention. In yet another example, the additional diodes may be added in series to the first and second diode to modify the operation parameters of the POR/UVLO system <b>2220</b>. Additionally, PMOS and NMOS in alternative configurations may be used to implement an alternative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a simplified diagram of an alternative embodiment of the present invention for a system for POR/UVLO schemes implemented with two NMOS and one PMOS. This diagram is merely an example, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. The system <b>1500</b> includes a power source <b>1510</b> and a POR/UVLO system <b>1550</b>. The power source includes a voltage source <b>1504</b>, a start up resistor <b>1506</b>, and a capacitor <b>1502</b>. The POR/UVLO system <b>1550</b> includes a first diode <b>1514</b>, a second diode <b>1518</b>, a third diode <b>1524</b>, a first Zener diode <b>1512</b>, a second Zener diode <b>1516</b>, a second resistor <b>1522</b>, a third resistor <b>1520</b>, a fourth resistor <b>1530</b>, a PMOS <b>1532</b>, a first NMOS <b>1528</b>, a second NMOS <b>1526</b>, a first inverter <b>1534</b>, and a second inverter <b>1536</b>. Although the above has been shown using a selected group of components for the POR/UVLO system <b>1550</b>, there can be many alternatives, modifications, and variations. For example, some of the components may be expanded and/or combined. Other components may be inserted to those noted above. During upon the embodiment, the arrangement of components may be interchanged with other replaced. For example, the first diode <b>1514</b> and the second diode <b>1518</b> may be removed.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">According to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the power source <b>1510</b> is connected supplies power to the POR/UVLO system <b>1550</b> at the node <b>1511</b>. The voltage source <b>1504</b> is connected in series to the start up resistor <b>1506</b>, which is connected to the capacitor <b>1502</b> and the node <b>1511</b>. The node <b>1511</b> is connected to the first Zener diode <b>1512</b>, the source of the PMOS <b>1532</b>, and the fourth resistor <b>1540</b>. The first Zener diode <b>1512</b> is connected in series with the first diode <b>1514</b>. The first diode <b>1514</b> is connected in series with the second Zener diode <b>1516</b>. The Zener diode <b>1516</b> is connected in series with the second diode <b>1518</b>. The second diode <b>1518</b> is connected in series with the third resistor <b>1520</b>. The third resistor <b>1520</b> is connected to the second resistor <b>1522</b> and the gate for the first NMOS <b>1528</b>. The source of the first NMOS <b>1528</b> is connected to the ground. The drain of the first NMOS <b>1528</b> is connected to the fourth resistor <b>1540</b>, the gate of the PMOS <b>1532</b>, and the input of the first inverter <b>1534</b>. The second resistor is connected to the drain of the second NMOS <b>1526</b> and the third diode <b>1524</b>. The third diode <b>1524</b> is connected to the ground. The source of the second NMOS <b>1526</b> is connected to the ground. The gate of the second NMOS <b>1526</b> is connected to the output of the second inverter <b>1526</b>. The input of the second inverter <b>526</b> is connected to the output of the first inverter <b>1534</b>. The second inverter <b>1526</b> provides an output signal for the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">According to an embodiment of the invention, the POR/UVLO system <b>1550</b> operates in essentially the same manner as the POR/UVLO system <b>1220</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, utilizing two positive feedback loops. For example, the first feedback loop includes the first Zener Diode <b>1512</b>, the first diode <b>1514</b>, the second Zener diode <b>1516</b>, the second diode <b>1518</b>, the third resistor <b>1520</b>, the third diode <b>1524</b>, the second resistor <b>1522</b>, the fourth resistor <b>1540</b>, the PMOS <b>1532</b>, and the first NMOS <b>1528</b>. The second feedback loop includes the first Zener Diode <b>1512</b>, the first diode <b>1514</b>, the third resistor <b>1520</b>, the third diode <b>1524</b>, the second resistor <b>1522</b>, the fourth resistor <b>1540</b>, the PMOS <b>1532</b>, the first NMOS <b>1528</b>, the second NMOS <b>1526</b>, the first inverter <b>1534</b>, and the second inverter <b>1536</b>. According to an embodiment, the operation of the two feedback loop is substantially the same as the two feedback loops according an embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">As discussed above and further emphasized here, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref>, <b>4</b>, <b>5</b>, <b>6</b>, and <b>7</b> are merely examples, which should not unduly limit the scope of the claims. One of ordinary skill in the art would recognize many variations, alternatives, and modifications. For example, some or all Zener diodes in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref>, <b>4</b>, and/or <b>5</b> can be replaced by other types of voltage-regulator diodes. In one embodiment, a voltage-regulator diode is a Zener diode. In another embodiment, a voltage-regulator diode is a breakdown diode.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">According to an embodiment, the present invention presents system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal, the second terminal being biased to a predetermined voltage. The system also a second transistor, which include a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being configured to receive an input voltage. Additionally, the system includes a first resistor that is associated with a first resistance. The first resistor includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage. The system also a second resistor that is associated with a second resistance. The second resistor includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal. In addition, the system includes a first Zener diode that is associated with a first Zener voltage. The first Zener diode includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage. Moreover, the system includes a second Zener diode that is associated with a second Zener voltage. The second Zener diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. The system additionally includes a third resistor that is associated with a third resistance. The third resistor includes a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal, the fourteenth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage. At the system, the first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal to generate a first signal. The first signal is capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout. The second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal. And the first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other. For example, the system is implemented according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref> and/or <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">According to an alternative embodiment, the present invention provides a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal, the second terminal being biased to a predetermined voltage. The system additionally includes a second transistor, which includes a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being configured to receive an input voltage. In addition, the system includes a first resistor that is associated with a first resistance. The first resistor includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage. The system also includes a second resistor that is associated with a second resistance. The second resistor includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal. In addition, the system includes a first Zener diode that is associated with a first Zener voltage. The first Zener diode includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a second Zener diode that is associated with a second Zener voltage. The second Zener diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. The system additionally includes a third resistor that is associated with a third resistance. The third resistor includes a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal, the fourteenth terminal coupled to the second terminal. Moreover, the system includes a third transistor, which includes a third gate, a fifteenth terminal, and a fourteenth terminal. The fifteenth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage, and sixteenth terminal are coupled to the sixth terminal. The system additionally includes a first inverter that includes a first inverter input and a first inverter output. The system also includes a second inverter that includes a second inverter input and a second inverter output. The second inverter input is coupled to the first inverter output, and the second inverter output is coupled to the third gate. At the system, the first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal. The second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal. The first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other. The second inverter output is configured to generate a signal, the signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout. For example, the system is implemented according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref> and/or <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">According to another alternative embodiment, the present invention provides a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first source, and a first drain. The first source is biased at a predetermined voltage. The system also includes a second transistor that includes a second gate, a second source, and a second drain. The second gate is coupled to the first drain, and the second source being biased at the predetermined voltage. In addition, the system includes a third transistor, which includes a third gate, a third source, and a third drain. The third source is biased at a predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a first resistor that includes a first terminal and a second terminal. The first terminal is biased at the predetermined voltage. The system also includes a second resistor. The second resistor includes a third terminal and a fourth terminal. The third terminal is coupled to the second terminal. The fourth terminal is coupled to the first gate. The system also includes a third resistor. The third resistor includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal. The fifth terminal is coupled to the fourth terminal. The system additionally includes a fourth resistor, which includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal. The eighth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. The seventh terminal is coupled to the second gate. The system additionally includes a first Zener diode that includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal. The ninth terminal is coupled to the sixth terminal. The tenth terminal is coupled to the second drain. They system also includes a second Zener diode. The second diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. The eleventh terminal is coupled to the tenth terminal. The twelfth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. The system also includes a first inverter that includes a first inverter input and a first inverter output. The first inverter input is coupled to the first drain. Additionally, the system includes a second inverter, which includes a second inverter input and a second inverter output. The second inverter input is coupled to the first inverter output. The second inverter output is coupled to the third gate. At the system, the second inverter output is configured to generate a signal. The signal is capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset and an under-voltage lockout. For example, the system is implemented according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">According to another alternative embodiment, the present invention provides a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal. The second terminal is biased to a predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a second transistor, which includes a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal. The third terminal is configured to receive an input voltage. The system also includes a first diode associated with a forward voltage. The first diode includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal. The fifth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. In addition, the system includes a second resistor associated with a second resistance. The second resistor includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal. The seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal. The system additionally includes a first Zener diode associated with a first Zener voltage. The first Zener diode includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal. The ninth terminal is biased to the predetermined voltage. The system also includes a second Zener diode associated with a second Zener voltage. The second Zener diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. Additionally, the system includes a third resistor associated with a third resistance. The third resistor includes a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal. The fourteenth terminal is coupled to the second terminal. Additionally, the system includes a third transistor, which includes a third gate, a fifteenth terminal, and a fourteenth terminal. The fifteenth terminal is configured to received the input voltage. The sixteenth terminal is coupled to the sixth terminal. The system also includes a first inverter, which includes a first inverter input and a first inverter output. Moreover, the system includes a second inverter, which includes a second inverter input and a second inverter output. The second inverter input is coupled to the first inverter output. The second inverter output is coupled to the third gate. The first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal. The second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal. The first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other. The second inverter output is configured to generate a signal, the signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout. For example, the system is implemented according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">According to another alternative embodiment, the present invention provides a system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals. The system includes a first transistor, which includes a first gate, a first source, and a first drain. The first source is biased at a predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a second transistor, which includes a second gate, a second source, and a second drain. The second gate is coupled to the first drain. The second source is configured to receive an input voltage. The system also includes a third transistor, which includes a third gate, a third source, and a third drain. The third source is biased at the predetermined voltage. The system also includes a first diode, which includes a first terminal and a second terminal. The first terminal is biased at the predetermined voltage. Additionally, the system includes a second resistor. The second resistor includes a third terminal and a fourth terminal. The third terminal is coupled to the second terminal. The fourth terminal is coupled to the first gate. The system also includes a third resistor, which includes a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal. The fifth terminal is coupled to the fourth terminal. Moreover, the system includes a fourth resistor, which includes a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal. The eighth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. The seventh terminal is coupled to the second gate. The system also includes a first Zener diode, which includes a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal. The ninth terminal is coupled to the sixth terminal, and the tenth terminal is coupled to the second drain. Additionally the system includes a second Zener diode. The second Zener diode includes an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal. The eleventh terminal is coupled to the tenth terminal. The twelfth terminal is configured to receive the input voltage. The system additionally includes a first inverter. The first inverter includes a first inverter input and a first inverter output. The first inverter input is coupled to the first drain. The system also includes a second inverter, which includes a second inverter input and a second inverter output. The second inverter input is coupled to the first inverter output. The second inverter output is coupled to the third gate. The second inverter output is configured to generate a signal. The signal is capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset and an under-voltage lockout. For example, the system is implemented according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">Many benefits are achieved by way of the present invention over conventional techniques. It is to be appreciated that certain embodiments of the present invention provide a system and method for POR/UVLO schemes that provide lower power consumption and better reliability. According to an embodiment of the present invention, two positive feedback loops are used to ensure the reliability of the UVLO function.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">It is understood the examples and embodiments described herein are for illustrative purposes only and that various modifications or changes in light thereof will be suggested to persons skilled in the art and are to be included within the spirit and purview of this application and scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00001" nb-file="US07298187-20071120-M00001.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00001" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298187-20071120-M00001.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00002" nb-file="US07298187-20071120-M00002.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00002" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298187-20071120-M00002.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00003" nb-file="US07298187-20071120-M00003.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00003" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298187-20071120-M00003.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00004" nb-file="US07298187-20071120-M00004.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00004" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298187-20071120-M00004.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00005" nb-file="US07298187-20071120-M00005.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00005" he="10.58mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298187-20071120-M00005.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-math idrefs="MATH-US-00006" nb-file="US07298187-20071120-M00006.NB">
<img id="EMI-M00006" he="6.35mm" wi="76.20mm" file="US07298187-20071120-M00006.TIF" alt="embedded image " img-content="math" img-format="tif"/>
</us-math>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a first transistor including a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal, the second terminal being biased to a predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second transistor including a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being configured to receive an input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first resistor associated with a first resistance, the first resistor including a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second resistor associated with a second resistance, the second resistor including a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first Zener diode associated with a first Zener voltage, the first Zener diode including a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second Zener diode associated with a second Zener voltage, the second Zener diode including an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third resistor associated with a third resistance, the third resistor including a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal, the fourteenth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein:
<claim-text>the first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal to generate a first signal, the first signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the input voltage is higher than the predetermined voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first transistor is an NMOS transistor, and the second transistor is a PMOS transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first Zener voltage and the second Zener voltage are the same.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first Zener voltage and the second Zener voltage are different.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the predetermined voltage is a ground voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the first terminal is a first drain and the second terminal is a first source;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the third terminal is a second source and the fourth terminal is a second drain.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein if the input voltage is below a first threshold voltage, the first signal is associated with a first state.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein if the input voltage is above a second threshold voltage, the first signal is associated with a second state, the second threshold voltage being higher than the first threshold voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the first state is related to turning off one or more devices coupled to the system, the second state is related to turning on the one or more components coupled to the system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a power source, wherein the power source comprises:
<claim-text>a start up resistor associated with a start up resistance, the start up resistor including a fifteenth terminal and a sixteenth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a capacitor associated with a capacitance, the capacitor including a seventeenth terminal and an eighteenth terminal, the seventeenth terminal being coupled to the sixteenth terminal, the eighteenth terminal being biased at the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the power source provides the input voltage at the sixteenth terminal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a third transistor including a third gate, a fifteenth terminal, and a sixteenth terminal, the fifteenth terminal being configured to received the input voltage, and sixteenth terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first inverter including a first inverter input and a first inverter output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second inverter including a second inverter input and a second inverter output, the second inverter input being coupled to the first inverter output, and the second inverter output being coupled to the third gate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein if the input voltage is below a first threshold voltage, the second inverter output provides a second signal indicating a first state, the first state being related to turning off one or more devices coupled to the system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein if the input voltage is above a second threshold voltage, the second inverter output provides the second signal indicating a second state, the second state being related to turning on the one or more devices coupled to the system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein the first threshold voltage is lower than the second threshold voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a first diode wherein the first terminal is coupled to the tenth terminal through the first diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> further comprising a second diode wherein the ninth terminal is coupled to the second terminal through the second diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a first transistor including a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal, the second terminal being biased to a predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second transistor including a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being configured to receive an input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first resistor associated with a first resistance, the first resistor including a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second resistor associated with a second resistance, the second resistor including a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first Zener diode associated with a first Zener voltage, the first Zener diode including a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second Zener diode associated with a second Zener voltage, the second Zener diode including an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third resistor associated with a third resistance, the third resistor including a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal, the fourteenth terminal being coupled to the second terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third transistor including a third gate, a fifteenth terminal, and a fourteenth terminal, the fifteenth terminal being configured to received the input voltage, and sixteenth terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first inverter including a first inverter input and a first inverter output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second inverter including a second inverter input and a second inverter output, the second inverter input being coupled to the first inverter output, and the second inverter output being coupled to the third gate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein:
<claim-text>the first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second inverter output is configured to generate a signal, the signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>if the input voltage is below a first threshold voltage, the signal is related to turning off one or more devices coupled to the system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>if the input voltage is above a second threshold voltage, the signal is related to turning on the one or more devices coupled to the system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first threshold voltage is lower than the second threshold voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a first transistor including a first gate, a first source, and a first drain, the first source being biased at a predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second transistor including a second gate, a second source, and a second drain, the second gate being coupled to the first drain, and the second source being configured to receive an input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third transistor including a third gate, a third source, and a third drain, the third source being biased at the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first resistor including a first terminal and a second terminal, the first terminal being biased at the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second resistor including a third terminal and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being coupled to the second terminal, and the fourth terminal being coupled to the first gate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third resistor including a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being coupled to the fourth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth resistor including a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the eighth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage, and the seventh terminal being coupled to the second gate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first Zener diode including a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal, and the tenth terminal being coupled to the second drain;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second Zener diode including an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal, the eleventh terminal being coupled to the tenth terminal, and the twelfth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first inverter including a first inverter input and a first inverter output, the first inverter input being coupled to the first drain;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second inverter including a second inverter input and a second inverter output, the second inverter input being coupled to the first inverter output, and the second inverter output being coupled to the third gate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second inverter output is configured to generate a signal, the signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset and an under-voltage lockout.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The system of <b>20</b> wherein:
<claim-text>the first transistor and the third transistor are NMOS transistors;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second transistor is a PMOS transistor.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The system of <b>20</b> wherein:
<claim-text>if the input voltage is above a first threshold voltage, the signal indicates a first state, the first state being associated with turning on a plurality of components coupled to the system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>if the input voltage is below a second threshold voltage, the signal indicates a second state, the second state being associated with turning off the plurality of components coupled to the system;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first threshold voltage is higher than the second threshold voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The system of <b>20</b> further comprising a first diode wherein the tenth terminal is coupled to the eleventh terminal through the first diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The system of <b>23</b> further comprising a second diode wherein the ninth terminal is coupled to the sixth terminal through the second diode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. A system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a first transistor including a first gate, a first terminal, and a second terminal, the second terminal being biased to a predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second transistor including a second gate, a third terminal, and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being configured to receive an input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first diode associated with a forward voltage, the first diode including a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second resistor associated with a second resistance, the second resistor including a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the seventh terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first Zener diode associated with a first Zener voltage, the first Zener diode including a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being biased to the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second Zener diode associated with a second Zener voltage, the second Zener diode including an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third resistor associated with a third resistance, the third resistor including a thirteenth terminal and a fourteenth terminal, the fourteenth terminal being coupled to the second terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third transistor including a third gate, a fifteenth terminal, and a fourteenth terminal, the fifteenth terminal being configured to received the input voltage, and sixteenth terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first inverter including a first inverter input and a first inverter output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second inverter including a second inverter input and a second inverter output, the second inverter input being coupled to the first inverter output, and the second inverter output being coupled to the third gate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein:
<claim-text>the first gate is coupled to the fourth terminal and the thirteenth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second gate is coupled to the eighth terminal and the twelfth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first terminal, the tenth terminal and the eleventh terminal are coupled to each other;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second inverter output is configured to generate a signal, the signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset or an under-voltage lockout.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. A system for providing power-on reset and under-voltage lockout signals, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a first transistor including a first gate, a first source, and a first drain, the first source being biased at a predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second transistor including a second gate, a second source, and a second drain, the second gate being coupled to the first drain, and the second source being configured to receive an input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third transistor including a third gate, a third source, and a third drain, the third source being biased at the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first diode including a first terminal and a second terminal, the first terminal being biased at the predetermined voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second resistor including a third terminal and a fourth terminal, the third terminal being coupled to the second terminal, and the fourth terminal being coupled to the first gate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third resistor including a fifth terminal and a sixth terminal, the fifth terminal being coupled to the fourth terminal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fourth resistor including a seventh terminal and an eighth terminal, the eighth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage, and the seventh terminal being coupled to the second gate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first Zener diode including a ninth terminal and a tenth terminal, the ninth terminal being coupled to the sixth terminal, and the tenth terminal being coupled to the second drain;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second Zener diode including an eleventh terminal and a twelfth terminal, the eleventh terminal being coupled to the tenth terminal, and the twelfth terminal being configured to receive the input voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first inverter including a first inverter input and a first inverter output, the first inverter input being coupled to the first drain;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second inverter including a second inverter input and a second inverter output, the second inverter input being coupled to the first inverter output, and the second inverter output being coupled to the third gate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second inverter output is configured to generate a signal, the signal capable of being associated with at least one of a power-on reset and an under-voltage lockout.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
