<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296767-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296767</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11141631</doc-number>
<date>20050531</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>43</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>64</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>244 1711</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Variable speed transmission for a rotary wing aircraft</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2491191</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Maillard et al.</name>
<date>19491200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>416 43</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3362255</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>De Rocca et al.</name>
<date>19680100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 74665 L</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3782223</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Watson</name>
<date>19740100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 74665 L</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4783023</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jupe</name>
<date>19881100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>244  6</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5271295</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Marnot</name>
<date>19931200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 74665 B</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6042499</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Goi et al.</name>
<date>20000300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475215</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6254504</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Goi et al.</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475216</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0145076</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Alford</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>244 60</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>244 1711</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>244 60</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>244 53 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 60</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416 37</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>416170 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060269414</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061130</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Palcic</last-name>
<first-name>Peter Xavier</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hamden</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Garcia</last-name>
<first-name>Todd</first-name>
<address>
<city>Milford</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gmirya</last-name>
<first-name>Yuriy</first-name>
<address>
<city>Woodbridge</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Carlson, Gaskey &amp; Olds</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sikorsky Aircraft Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Stratford</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Dinh</last-name>
<first-name>Tien</first-name>
<department>3644</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A transmission gearbox for a rotary-wing aircraft includes a main gearbox and a variable speed gearbox in meshing engagement with the main rotor gearbox. The variable speed gearbox permits at least two different RPMs for the main rotor system without disengaging the engine(s) or changing engine RPMs. The variable speed gearbox includes a clutch, preferably a multi-plate clutch, and a freewheel unit for each engine. A gear path drives the main gearbox in a “high rotor speed mode” when the clutch is engaged to drive the main rotor system at high rotor rpm for hover flight profile. A reduced gear path drives the main gearbox in a “low rotor speed mode” when the clutch is disengaged and power is transferred through the freewheel unit, to drive the main rotor system at lower rotor rpm for high speed flight. The variable speed gearbox may be configured for a tail drive system that operates at a continuous speed, a tail drive system that changes speed with the main rotor shaft or for no tail drive system.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="156.72mm" wi="248.75mm" file="US07296767-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="221.57mm" wi="172.38mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296767-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="241.30mm" wi="110.57mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296767-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="249.17mm" wi="158.41mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296767-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="252.05mm" wi="162.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296767-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="221.06mm" wi="148.84mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296767-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a rotary-wing aircraft, and more particularly to a rotary wing transmission gearbox system which provides variable speeds to facilitate high speed and low speed flight profiles.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The forward airspeed of a conventional rotary wing aircraft is limited by a number of factors. Among these is the tendency of the retreating blade to stall at high forward airspeeds. As the forward airspeed increases, the airflow velocity across the retreating blade slows such that the blade may approach a stall condition. In contrast, the airflow velocity across the advancing blade increases with increasing forward speed. Dissymmetry of lift is thereby generated as forward air speed increases.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">This dissymmetry of lift may create an unstable condition if not equalized across the advancing and retreating sectors of the rotor disc. Typically, blade flapping and feathering are utilized to substantially equalize the lift.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">However, as the forward airspeed is increased beyond a given point for a given rotor rpm, the flapping and feathering action eventually becomes inadequate to maintain substantial equality of lift over the rotor disc. At this point, reverse airflow across the retreating sector creates negative lift and, depending on the forward speed, creates a stalling or negative lift condition that travels outwardly across the blade as airspeed increases. Conventional rotors must be operated at airspeeds lower than those which cause reverse airflow across a substantial part of the retreating blade and at an rpm low enough to alleviate any potential compressibility Mach number problems at the tip of the advancing blade. This has effectively limited forward airspeeds of conventional helicopters to approximately 180 knots.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A rotary wing aircraft with a coaxial counter-rotating rigid rotor system is capable of higher speeds as compared to conventional single rotor helicopters partly due to the balance of lift between the advancing sides of the main rotor blades on the upper and lower rotor systems. In addition, the retreating side of the rotor discs are also generally free from classic retreating blade stall due to offloading of the retreating disc sector with increasing airspeed to obtain roll equilibrium by balancing the net effects of the equal and opposite moments produced by the advancing sectors of the upper and lower counter-rotating rotor systems. To still further increase airspeed, a compound rotary wing aircraft may incorporate supplemental translational thrust.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In high speed flight, the main rotor system may be unloaded from the turbojets, and rotor RPM may be controlled by adjusting collective pitch. For any rotary-wing aircraft, increasing collective pitch slows the rotational speed and decreasing collective pitch increases rotational speed. For a rotary wing aircraft in a high speed flight profile, however, rotor RPM needs to be decreased to prevent the rotor blade tips on the advancing sides of the rotor discs from entering a supersonic region as aircraft airspeed increases. Thus, as forward airspeed increases, collective pitch must be increased to prevent the rotor RPM from increasing to an undesirable level. However, as the forward airspeed is increased beyond a given point for a given rotor rpm, adjusting collective pitch eventually becomes inadequate.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The aerodynamics of high-speed rotary wing aircraft show a noticeable benefit by reducing rotor RPM in high speed cruise flight. The RPM reduction from a hover profile to a high speed flight profile is typically on the order of about 30%. Such a reduction at the engine, however, may cause problems with auxiliary systems, engine operation and available power while, a rotary-wing aircraft, which always operates at a relatively low rotor RPM, may present penalties in rotor and transmission weight, as well as maneuverability constraints. Thus, there is a need for a rotary-wing transmission gearbox system, which provides variable rotor system speeds.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Accordingly, it is desirable to provide a variable speed gearbox system for a rotary-wing aircraft that provides a “high rotor speed mode” and “low rotor speed mode” to maximize aircraft performance during a hover flight profile and a high speed cruise flight profile, respectively.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A transmission gearbox system of a rotary-wing aircraft according to the present invention includes a main gearbox and a variable speed gearbox in meshing engagement with the main gearbox. The variable speed gearbox permits at least two different main rotor system RPMs without disengaging the engines or changing engine RPM. The variable speed gearbox facilitates different flight spectrums, such as a hover flight profile and a high speed cruise flight profile for any rotary wing aircraft. Typically during landing, take-off, hover and low speed flight profiles, a higher main rotor speed is required for increased lifting capabilities while in a high speed cruise flight profile a lower main rotor speed is desired for improved rotor performance and higher forward airspeed.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The variable speed gearbox includes a clutch, preferably a multi-plate clutch, and a freewheel unit for each engine. In a “high rotor speed mode,” when the clutch is engaged to drive the main rotor system at high rotor rpm, a gear path drives the main gearbox in a direct drive (1 to 1 ratio). For a high speed cruise flight profile with a lower rotor RPM in a “low rotor speed mode,” the clutch is disengaged and power is transferred through a reduced gear path, preferably by way of a two-stage gear reduction, a freewheel unit and into the main rotor gearbox.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The variable speed gearbox may be configured for a tail drive system that operates at a continuous speed, a tail drive system that changes speed with the main rotor shaft or with no tail drive system. For aircraft models that require a continuous tail speed, the tail drive system may be in meshing engagement with the input side of the clutch and freewheel unit. For aircraft models that would benefit from a tail drive system which changes speed commensurate with the main rotor system, the tail drive system may be in meshing engagement with the output side of the clutch and freewheel unit or directly to the main gearbox to maintain a fixed gear ratio relative to the engine.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present invention therefore provides a variable speed gearbox system for a rotary-wing aircraft that provides a “high rotor speed mode” and “low rotor speed mode” to maximize aircraft performance during a hover flight profile and a high speed cruise flight profile, respectively.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The various features and advantages of this invention will become apparent to those skilled in the art from the following detailed description of the currently preferred embodiment. The drawings that accompany the detailed description can be briefly described as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a general phantom side view of an exemplary rotary wing aircraft embodiment for use with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> is a general phantom top view of the exemplary rotary wing aircraft embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref> is a general side views of a rotary wing aircraft with an anti-torque tail rotor embodiment for use with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a block diagram of a transmission gearbox system of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a block diagram of an alternative transmission gearbox system of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> is a block diagram of an alternative transmission gearbox system of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref> illustrate a vertical takeoff and landing (VTOL) rotary-wing aircraft <b>10</b> having a main rotor system <b>12</b>. The main rotor system <b>12</b> is preferably a dual, counter-rotating, coaxial rotor system, however, any other rotor system known in the art including, but not limited to, single, tandem and dual rotor systems may also be used with the present invention. That is, although the present invention is being described in combination with a high speed compound rotary wing aircraft, other aircraft configurations, including a more conventional configuration with a single main rotor system <b>12</b>′ and an anti-torque tail rotor system <b>32</b>′ (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref>) will also benefit from the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As shown, the aircraft <b>10</b> includes an airframe <b>14</b> which supports the main rotor system <b>12</b>. The aircraft <b>10</b> may also incorporate a tail drive system <b>30</b>. The tail drive system <b>30</b> is preferably a translational thrust system <b>32</b> that provides translational thrust generally parallel to an aircraft longitudinal axis L.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The main rotor system <b>12</b> preferably includes a first rotor system <b>16</b> and a second rotor system <b>18</b>. Each rotor system <b>16</b>, <b>18</b> includes a plurality of rotor blades <b>20</b> mounted to a rotor hub <b>22</b>, <b>24</b> for rotation about a rotor axis of rotation R. A drive system <b>35</b> drives the main rotor system <b>12</b>. The translational thrust system <b>32</b> preferably includes a pusher propeller <b>34</b> having a propeller rotational axis P oriented substantially horizontal and parallel to the aircraft longitudinal axis L to provide thrust for high-speed flight. Preferably, the pusher propeller <b>32</b> is mounted within an aerodynamic cowling <b>36</b> mounted to the rear of the airframe <b>14</b>. The translational thrust system <b>32</b> is preferably driven by the same drive system <b>35</b> which drives the main rotor system <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, the drive system <b>35</b> of the aircraft <b>10</b> is schematically illustrated. A gearbox <b>26</b> is preferably interposed between one or more gas turbine engines (illustrated schematically at E), the main rotor system <b>12</b> and the translational thrust system <b>32</b>. Preferably, the gearbox <b>26</b> includes a main gearbox <b>38</b> and a variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> in meshing engagement with the main gearbox <b>38</b>. For further understanding of a main gearbox and associated components thereof, which may be used in connection with the present invention, attention is directed to U.S. patent application Ser. No. 11/140,762 entitled SPLIT TORQUE GEARBOX FOR ROTARY WING AIRCRAFT WITH TRANSLATIONAL THRUST SYSTEM which is assigned to the assignee of the instant invention and which is hereby incorporated by reference in its entirety.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Each engine E preferably drives the variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> through an engine freewheel unit <b>42</b> as generally understood by one of ordinary skill in the art to permit single engine operation and autorotation should all engines fail. Although only the gear train from engine #<b>1</b> will be discussed in detail herein, the gear train from engine #2 is identical and it should be understood that any number of engines E may be utilized with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> of the present invention permits at least two different rotor speeds for the main rotor system <b>12</b> without disengaging the engines E or changing engine RPM. The variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> facilitates different flight profiles, such as a low speed flight profile and a high speed flight profile for any rotary wing aircraft. Typically during landing, take-off, hover and low speed flight profiles, a higher main rotor speed is required for increased lifting capabilities while in a high speed cruise flight profile, a lower main rotor speed is desired for improved rotor performance and increased airspeed.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> includes a clutch, preferably a multi-plate clutch <b>44</b>, and a freewheel unit <b>46</b> for each engine E. The multi-plate clutch <b>44</b> and the freewheel unit <b>46</b> are driven in parallel. A high speed input shaft <b>48</b> from the engine freewheel unit <b>42</b> drives the variable speed gearbox <b>38</b> primarily through a gear path <b>50</b>, (illustrated schematically as shafts <b>48</b>, <b>44</b><i>i</i>, and <b>44</b><i>o</i>) when the clutch <b>44</b> is engaged and primarily through a reduced gear path <b>52</b>, preferably through a two-stage gear reduction <b>52</b><i>a</i>, <b>52</b><i>b </i>(reduced gear path <b>52</b> illustrated schematically herein as the gear path of <b>48</b>, <b>52</b><i>a</i>, <b>46</b><i>i</i>, <b>46</b><i>o</i>, <b>52</b><i>b</i>) when the clutch <b>44</b> is disengaged. It should be understood that various gear ratios will be usable with the present invention and that “gear path” as discussed herein is with reference to a first gear path which drives the main rotor system <b>12</b> in a direct drive which includes a clutch and that “reduced gear path” as discussed herein is with reference to a second gear path which includes a freewheel unit and a gear reduction, but are not otherwise limiting.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> preferably drives the main gearbox <b>38</b> in a direct drive (1 to 1 ratio) “high rotor speed mode” when the clutch <b>44</b> is engaged to drive the main rotor system <b>12</b> at high rotor rpm. In this mode, a freewheel output <b>46</b><i>o </i>of the freewheel unit <b>46</b> is rotating faster than a freewheel input <b>46</b>i of the freewheel unit <b>46</b>, so that the freewheel unit <b>46</b> overruns and does not transmit power. A relatively lower torque at relatively higher RPM is thereby transmitted for a given engine horsepower.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">For the high speed cruise flight profile with a lower rotor RPM in a “low rotor speed mode,” the clutch <b>44</b> is disengaged and power is transferred preferably from the input shaft <b>48</b>, to an initial gear reduction <b>52</b><i>a </i>through the freewheel unit <b>46</b> to another gear reduction <b>52</b><i>b</i>, and into the main gearbox <b>38</b>. It should be understood that “high rotor speed mode” and “low rotor speed mode” are utilized herein only as relative terms regarding the speed of the main gearbox <b>38</b> due to operation of the variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> and should not be considered otherwise limiting. With the clutch <b>44</b> disengaged, a clutch input <b>44</b><i>i </i>of the clutch <b>44</b> is spinning at the same speed as the engine E and a clutch output <b>44</b><i>o </i>of the clutch <b>44</b> is spinning at a reduced speed as a result of the gear reduction as connected by the freewheel unit <b>46</b>. A relatively higher torque at a lower RPM is thereby transmitted for a given engine horsepower.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Notably, both the gear path <b>50</b> and the reduced gear path <b>52</b> continue to rotate irrespective of engagement/disengagement of the clutch <b>44</b> so that the clutch <b>44</b> and freewheel unit <b>46</b> need only accommodate the relative difference in speed and inertia between the gear ratios of the gear path <b>50</b> and the reduced gear path <b>52</b>. This provides a lightweight and rapid reacting system compared to a conventional transmission which must accelerate or decelerate part of the drive system from or to zero speed.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The gearbox configuration of the present invention provides a lightweight system while assuring operation in the event of a clutch seizure or complete clutch slip. In the event of a clutch seizure, power is still transmitted from the engine to the main gearbox. In the event of a clutch slipping, power is automatically diverted through the freewheel unit to the main gearbox.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Transition from “low rotor speed mode” back to the “high rotor speed mode” such as when an aircraft is decelerating from cruise flight to a hover, requires engaging the clutch <b>44</b> and allowing the main rotor speed to increase until the clutch output <b>44</b><i>o </i>matches the speed of the clutch input <b>44</b><i>i </i>and the clutch <b>44</b> fully locks. The clutch <b>44</b> may be operated in an on/off manner or in a feathering manner in which engagement/disengagement is gradually applied.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Transitions between the “low rotor speed mode” and the “high rotor speed mode” are alternatively assisted through aircraft flight control methods. Preferably, main rotor speed is increased or decreased via rotor collective pitch control and aircraft flight attitude. That is, to change the amount of lift generated by the rotor system, either the speed and/or the blade angle of attack may be changed. If the angle of attack and the speed are changed in such a way that those changes cancel each other out, the same amount of lift is produced. Therefore, when transitioning from “low rotor speed mode” to “high rotor speed mode,” collective pitch is modulated to lower the angle of attack of the blades as the rotor speed increases to provide the same amount of lift throughout the transition. In addition, when the angle of attack is decreased, the amount of drag produced is also decreased which increases rotor speed for equivalent power. For the transition from a “high rotor speed mode” to a “low rotor speed mode,” the opposite generally occurs. With aircraft flight control methods, transitions are rapidly facilitated with less inertia loads applied to the clutch.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> may also be configured for a tail drive system <b>30</b> that operates at a continuous speed (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>), a tail drive system that changes speed with the main rotor system <b>12</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>) or with no tail drive system <b>30</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>). <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> are preferably utilized with either a high speed compound rotary wing aircraft <b>10</b> having an optional translational thrust system <b>32</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A and 1B</figref>) or the more conventional aircraft <b>10</b>′ configurations (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref>) with an anti-torque tail rotor system <b>32</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The variable speed gearbox <b>40</b> may drive the tail drive system <b>30</b> through a tail drive gear reduction <b>54</b> in meshing engagement therewith. For aircraft that require a continuous tail speed, the tail drive system <b>30</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is preferably utilized in which the tail drive system is in meshing engagement with the input side of the clutch <b>44</b> and freewheel unit <b>46</b> to thereby maintain a fixed gear ratio relative the engine E. For aircraft that would benefit from a tail drive system <b>30</b> which changes speed commensurate with the main rotor system <b>12</b>, the tail drive system <b>30</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is preferably utilized in which the tail drive system is in meshing engagement with the output side of the clutch <b>44</b><i>o </i>and freewheel unit <b>46</b><i>o </i>or directly to the main gearbox <b>26</b> to thereby maintain a fixed gear ratio relative the main rotor shaft.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The choice of tail drive system <b>30</b> configuration is determined by several factors including tail rotor efficiency, noise requirements, performance objectives, etc. The amount of force the anti torque tail rotor is required to generate in order to counteract the torque of the main rotor must change when the main rotor speed changes, and as a result torque, changes. To compensate for a change in main rotor torque, the tail rotor can either change its angle of attack and maintain the same speed (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>), maintain the same angle of attack and change speed (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>), or change both (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>). The <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> configuration may alternatively be utilized with a compound helicopter where the tail rotor changes orientation to provide force to counteract the main rotor torque in hover and then transition to a pusher propeller orientation to provide translational thrust during a high speed flight profile.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">It should be understood that relative positional terms such as “forward,” “aft,” “upper,” “lower,” “above,” “below,” and the like are with reference to the normal operational attitude of the vehicle and should not be considered otherwise limiting.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">It should be understood that although a particular component arrangement is disclosed in the illustrated embodiment, other arrangements will benefit from the instant invention.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Although particular step sequences are shown, described, and claimed, it should be understood that steps may be performed in any order, separated or combined unless otherwise indicated and will still benefit from the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The foregoing description is exemplary rather than defined by the limitations within. Many modifications and variations of the present invention are possible in light of the above teachings. The preferred embodiments of this invention have been disclosed, however, one of ordinary skill in the art would recognize that certain modifications would come within the scope of this invention. It is, therefore, to be understood that within the scope of the appended claims, the invention may be practiced otherwise than as specifically described. For that reason the following claims should be studied to determine the true scope and content of this invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of controlling a speed of a main rotor system of a rotary-wing aircraft comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>(1) engaging a clutch driven in parallel with a freewheel unit, the clutch, and the freewheel unit driven by a single engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(2) overrunning a freewheel output over a freewheel input of a freewheel unit in response to said step (1) to drive a main gearbox of the main rotor system at a first speed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(3) disengaging the clutch; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(4) running a clutch input separately from a clutch output in response to said step (3) to drive the main gearbox of the main rotor system at a second speed through the freewheel unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said step (4) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving an output of a gear path and an output of a reduced gear path at a speed equivalent to the freewheel output to drive the main gearbox of the rotor system at the second speed.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said step (4) further comprises:
<claim-text>(b) driving the clutch output at a speed equivalent to the output of the gear path, the output of the reduced gear path and the freewheel output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said step (4) further comprises:
<claim-text>(b) driving a clutch input at a speed equivalent to an engine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said step (4) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving the freewheel output by the freewheel input.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>(5) driving a tail drive output at a constant speed through a tail drive gear reduction in meshing engagement with the freewheel input of the first freewheel unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said step (5) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving a translational thrust system with the tail drive output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said step (5) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving an anti-torque rotor with the tail drive output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>(5) driving a tail drive output at a variable speed through a tail drive gear reduction in meshing engagement with the freewheel output of the first freewheel unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said step (5) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving a translational thrust system with the tail drive output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said step (5) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving an anti-torque rotor with the tail drive output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said step (5) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving an anti-torque rotor with the tail drive output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said step (1) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving the first and second engine in parallel.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said step (1) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving the first clutch and first freewheel output in parallel with the second clutch and the second freewheel unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein said step (1) further comprises:
<claim-text>(b) driving the first and second engine in parallel.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method of controlling a speed of a main rotor system of a rotary-wing aircraft comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>(1) engaging a first clutch driven in parallel with a first freewheel output, the first clutch and the first freewheel unit driven by a first engine and engaging a second clutch driven in parallel with a second freewheel output, the second clutch and the second freewheel unit driven by a second engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(2) overrunning the first and second freewheel output over a first and second freewheel input of the respective first and second freewheel unit in response to said step (1) to drive a main gearbox of the main rotor system at a first speed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(3) disengaging the first and second clutch; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(4) running a first and second clutch input separately from a first and second clutch output in response to said step (3) to drive the main gearbox of the main rotor system at a second speed through the first and second freewheel unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>(5) driving a tail drive output at a constant speed through a tail drive gear reduction in meshing engagement with the first and second freewheel input.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein said step (5) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving a translational thrust system with the tail drive output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein said step (5) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving an anti-torque rotor with the tail drive output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of:
<claim-text>(5) driving a tail drive output at a variable speed through a tail drive gear reduction in meshing engagement with the first and second freewheel output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein said step (5) further comprises:
<claim-text>(a) driving a translational thrust system with the tail drive output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
