<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298486-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298486</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11026726</doc-number>
<date>20041230</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>269</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356438</main-classification>
<further-classification>324 714</further-classification>
<further-classification> 73 281</further-classification>
<further-classification> 73 2804</further-classification>
<further-classification>356335</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Aerosol mobility size spectrometer</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6941005</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lary et al.</name>
<date>20050900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>382133</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7029921</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lee et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>436148</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00003">
<othercit>Zhang et al.; “Resolution of the Radial Differential Mobility Analyzer for Ultrafine Particles”; <i>J. Aerosol Sci</i>. vol. 27, No. 8, pp. 1179-1200; 1996.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00004">
<othercit>Tammet et al.; “Electrical Aerosol Spectrometer ofTartu University”; <i>Atmospheric Research</i>, vol. 62, pp. 315-324; 2002.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00005">
<othercit>Russell et al; “Radially classified aerosol detector for aircraft-based submicron aerosol measurements”; <i>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</i>; 13 (3): pp. 598-609 Jun. 1996.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>Zhang et al.; “Radial Differential Mobility Analyzer”; <i>Aerosol Science and Technology</i>; 23 (3): pp. 357-372 Oct. 1995.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>Chen et al.; “Design and Evaluation of a Nanometer Aerosol Differential Mobility Analyzer”; <i>J. Aerosol Sci.</i>, vol. 29., No. 5, pp. 497-509, 1998.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Knutson et al. “Aerosol classification by electric mobility: apparatus, theory, and applications” <i>Journal of Aerosol Science</i>, vol. 6, Issue 6, pp. 443-451, Nov. 1975.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356 36</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356 37</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356437</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356438</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>436148</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>436146</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>436174</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>436179</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>422100</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>422 83</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>422 73</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>422 81</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73 2801</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73 2804</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73 281</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324 714</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060146327</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060706</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wang</last-name>
<first-name>Jian</first-name>
<address>
<city>Port Jefferson</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kulkarni</last-name>
<first-name>Pramod</first-name>
<address>
<city>Port Jefferson Station</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Neiger</last-name>
<first-name>Lori-Anne</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Brookhaven Science Associates, LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Upton</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Toatley, Jr.</last-name>
<first-name>Gregory J</first-name>
<department>2877</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nur</last-name>
<first-name>Abdullahi</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A device for measuring aerosol size distribution within a sample containing aerosol particles. The device generally includes a spectrometer housing defining an interior chamber and a camera for recording aerosol size streams exiting the chamber. The housing includes an inlet for introducing a flow medium into the chamber in a flow direction, an aerosol injection port adjacent the inlet for introducing a charged aerosol sample into the chamber, a separation section for applying an electric field to the aerosol sample across the flow direction and an outlet opposite the inlet. In the separation section, the aerosol sample becomes entrained in the flow medium and the aerosol particles within the aerosol sample are separated by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams under the influence of the electric field. The camera is disposed adjacent the housing outlet for optically detecting a relative position of at least one aerosol flow stream exiting the outlet and for optically detecting the number of aerosol particles within the at least one aerosol flow stream.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="226.82mm" wi="358.31mm" file="US07298486-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="232.66mm" wi="167.05mm" file="US07298486-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="228.09mm" wi="112.44mm" file="US07298486-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="231.06mm" wi="173.91mm" file="US07298486-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="231.90mm" wi="164.76mm" file="US07298486-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="226.57mm" wi="172.38mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298486-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?GOVINT description="Government Interest" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention was made with Government support under contract number DE-AC02-98CH10886, awarded by the U.S. Department of Energy. The Government has certain rights in the invention.</p>
<?GOVINT description="Government Interest" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to devices and methods for measuring ambient aerosol distributions and properties, and more particularly, to a device and method capable of accurately measuring submicron aerosol size distributions with high time resolution and signal to noise ratio.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Aerosols refer to particles including solids, liquids and mixtures thereof suspended in a gas. Recent research has clearly demonstrated the significance of atmospheric aerosols on climate and air quality over regional and global scales. Atmospheric aerosols affect the climate by scattering and absorbing sunlight (direct effect) and by changing the microphysical structure, lifetime, and amount of clouds (indirect effect). The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) estimated that the direct and indirect effects of aerosols remain the most uncertain components in the climate system.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Prediction and mitigation of these effects require the knowledge of the spatial and temporal distributions, as well as the sources and governing processes, of the atmospheric aerosols. Among the aerosol properties needed for assessing climate impacts are size distributions and hygroscopicity. These variables determine climate forcing through their effects on light scattering and cloud formation. Particle size is also an important determinant for the study of penetration into bronchial airways and associated health effects.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Understanding and predicting the effects of aerosols on climate and air quality requires detailed characterization of ambient aerosol distributions and properties. However, due to its short lifetime, the spatial and temporal distributions of atmospheric aerosol are highly inhomogeneous. The current incomplete understanding of ambient aerosol properties, coupled with changing aerosol sources and sinks, necessitates further intensive field projects involving aircraft-based measurements. The advantages of aircraft-based measurements are obvious. These advantages include the ability to characterize 3-dimensional spatial distributions of aerosols and the ability to sample a large spatial domain within a short time. However, aircraft-base measurements are often compromised by the poor time resolution of current aerosol measurement techniques.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Conventional instruments for aerosol size distribution measurements include optical particle counter (OPC) systems and scanning mobility particle sizer (SMPS) systems, whose major component is a differential mobility analyzer (DMA). Conventional SMPS systems typically have time resolutions of about 50 seconds. The low speed of a conventional SMPS system of the prior art is a result of the system's sequential measurement method. Inside a DMA, charged aerosols migrate across flow streamlines under the influence of an electric field, and only aerosols of one size are selected and measured at one time. To obtain a complete submicron aerosol size distribution, which ranges approximately from 5 to 1000 nm, the electrical field inside the DMA has to be scanned through a wide dynamic range, and as many as 50 measurements of aerosols with different sizes are required. This takes about 50 seconds. Moreover, since only a small fraction of the aerosol is selected and measured, the counting rate of a SMPS system is very poor, which further slows down the measurements.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Even when efficiently automated, the time delay for completing a full measurement with a conventional DMA has its drawbacks. For example, a typical research aircraft travels several kilometers within a 50-second time period. Thus, accurate measurements of highly localized aerosol distributions, such as aerosols in the vicinity of a particular cloud formation or inside a pollution plume, are impossible since the aircraft will have traveled away from the localized aerosol source between the time the measurement begins to the time the measurement ends. Furthermore, due to the low sampling rate of DMA systems, measurements in clean environments are further restricted by the time required to obtain statistically significant numbers. Moreover, current SMPS systems are inadequate for detecting or measuring fast-changing size distributions of aerosol particles emitted by diesel engines and vehicles.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Other conventional aerosol measurement devices also have drawbacks. For example, conventional optical particle counters using light scattering techniques are generally only effective for measuring particle sizes greater than 200 nm. Aerosol hygroscopic property measurements, which are made using a tandem differential mobility analyzer (TDMA) system, also suffer from low time resolution and are rarely deployed in airborne studies.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Accordingly, it would be desirable to provide a measurement device which improves upon conventional DMA systems by simultaneously detecting aerosols of different sizes, thereby significantly improving measurement speed.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention is a device for measuring aerosol size distribution within a sample containing aerosol particles. The device generally includes a spectrometer housing defining an interior chamber and an optical detector, such as a camera, for recording aerosol streams exiting the chamber along different flow streams. The housing includes an inlet for introducing a flow medium into the chamber in a flow direction, an aerosol injection port adjacent the inlet for introducing a charged aerosol sample into the chamber, a separation section for applying an electric field to the aerosol sample across the flow direction and an outlet opposite the inlet. In the separation section, the aerosol sample becomes entrained in the flow medium and the aerosol particles within the aerosol sample are separated by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams under the influence of the electric field. The camera is disposed adjacent the housing outlet for optically detecting a relative position of at least one aerosol flow stream exiting the outlet and for optically detecting the number of aerosol particles within the at least one aerosol flow stream.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In a preferred embodiment, the device further includes an aerosol charger disposed adjacent the aerosol injection port of the housing and a laser source disposed adjacent the outlet. The aerosol charger imparts a predictable electrical charge distribution to the aerosol sample and the laser source illuminates the plurality of separated aerosol flow steams exiting said outlet. Also, the housing preferably has two substantially parallel walls, wherein the electric field is applied across the parallel walls and the relative position of the at least one aerosol flow stream exiting the housing outlet is optically detected relative to the parallel walls.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Additionally, the device further preferably includes a means for saturating and growing the aerosol particles through a condensation process to facilitate detecting the particles. In this regard, the housing preferably includes a growth section having a thermoelectric cooler disposed downstream of the separation section for increasing the size of saturated aerosol particles within the separated aerosol flow streams using a condensation process.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">For saturating the aerosol particles, the device may include a saturator disposed adjacent the inlet of the housing for introducing a working vapor into the flow medium. The working vapor subsequently condenses on the aerosol particles within the growth section, whereby the aerosol particles increase in size. The saturator may include a reservoir for holding a working liquid, an inlet in fluid communications with the reservoir for introducing the flow medium into the reservoir, a heater adjacent the reservoir for heating the working liquid to produce the working vapor and an outlet connected to the housing inlet for introducing the working vapor and the flow medium into the interior chamber of the housing.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Alternatively, saturation may take place within a saturation section disposed between the separation section and the growth section of the housing. In this case, the saturation section of the housing may include a wick in fluid communication with the interior chamber of the housing and a heater in thermal contact with the wick. The wick is saturated with a working liquid and the heater heats the working liquid to produce the working vapor.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The housing of the present invention may be combined with other housings operating at different voltages to provide an apparatus having increased size range measurement capabilities. Specifically, the measuring apparatus of the present invention may include a first housing defining a first interior chamber and a second housing defining a second interior chamber. The first housing has a separation section for applying a first electrical field to the aerosol sample and the second housing has a separation section for applying a second electrical field to the aerosol sample. The aerosol particles within the first housing are separated by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams having a first size range and the aerosol particles within the second housing are separated by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams having a second size range. A camera system is disposed adjacent the outlets of the first and second housings for optically detecting a relative position of at least one aerosol flow stream from the first size range and at least one aerosol flow stream from the second size range.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Moreover, the present invention can be combined with conventional components to produce an apparatus for measuring aerosol hygroscopicity and volatility. Such an apparatus includes an aerosol charger for imparting a predictable electrical charge distribution to an aerosol sample, a differential mobility analyzer for selecting dry aerosols of a desired size, a humidifier for increasing the humidity of the dry aerosols selected by the differential mobility analyzer to produce a humidified aerosol sample, a spectrometer housing as described above for separating the aerosol particles by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams under the influence of an electric field and a camera for optically detecting a relative position of at least one aerosol flow stream exiting the housing and for optically detecting the number of aerosol particles within the at least one aerosol flow stream. For volatility measurements, the apparatus further includes a thermal denuder connected adjacent the humidifier to be operated alternatively with the humidifier.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The present invention further involves a method for measuring aerosol size distribution within a sample containing aerosol particles. The method generally includes the step of applying an electric field across a charged aerosol sample flow, wherein the electric field separates the aerosol particles within the sample flow by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams. The relative position of at least one aerosol flow stream is optically detected and, preferably, the number of aerosol particles within that aerosol flow stream is optically counted.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Preferably, the method of the present invention further includes the steps of illuminating the plurality of aerosol flow streams and increasing the size of the aerosol particles within the separated aerosol flow streams using a condensation process to facilitate optical detection. The condensation process preferably involves introducing a working vapor into the charged aerosol flow either before or after application of the electric field. The working vapor condenses on the aerosol particles during the condensation process to increase the size of the aerosol particles. Moreover, the electric field may be varied to produce separated aerosol flow streams of a desired range.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">As a result of the present invention, a device is provided that is capable of measuring submicron aerosol size distributions and aerosol hygroscopicities within 1 second, a factor of 50 improvement in time resolution over state of the art research instruments. Thus, the device of the present invention significantly improves the ability to study the effect of atmospheric aerosol on global climate. The present invention also has significant application for studies of air pollution, combustion engine emissions, nano-material fabrication and characterization.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">These and other objects, features, and advantages of this invention will become apparent from the following detailed description of illustrative embodiments thereof, which is to be read in connection with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of a preferred embodiment of an aerosol mobility size spectrometer formed in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic cross-sectional view of an alternative embodiment of an aerosol mobility size spectrometer of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a graphical representation of a typical aerosol measurement taken by the aerosol mobility size spectrometer of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of an apparatus for measuring aerosol size distribution using three aerosol mobility size spectrometers of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block diagram of an aerosol hygroscopicity/volatility spectrometer (AHVS) formed in accordance with the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Referring first to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a schematic cross-section of a preferred form of an aerosol mobility size spectrometer <b>10</b>, formed in accordance with the present invention, is shown. The spectrometer <b>10</b> generally includes a housing <b>12</b> and a camera <b>28</b> for detecting aerosol streams exiting the housing. The housing <b>12</b> defines an inner chamber <b>14</b> and includes an inlet <b>16</b>, an outlet <b>18</b> and an aerosol injection port <b>20</b> adjacent the inlet. The inlet <b>16</b>, the outlet <b>18</b> and the aerosol injection port <b>20</b> all communicate with the inner chamber <b>14</b>. The housing <b>12</b> further includes a separation section <b>22</b>, which applies an electric field E across the interior chamber <b>14</b>, as will be described in further detail below.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The housing <b>12</b> may take various forms, but in the preferred embodiment, the housing includes two parallel walls <b>24</b> and <b>25</b> that are spaced apart a known distance. The spacing between the plates <b>24</b> and <b>25</b> is preferably about 1 cm and the widths of the plates are preferably about 10.0 cm. The plates <b>24</b> and <b>25</b> may be fixed to lateral walls (not shown) on their sides to enclose the inner chamber <b>14</b> and a hood <b>26</b> including a transparent window <b>30</b> may be attached to the outlet <b>18</b> of the housing <b>12</b>. In this form, the aerosol injection port <b>20</b> takes the form of a narrow slit extending across the entire width of the plates <b>24</b> and <b>25</b> to ensure a laminar flow.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In a preferred embodiment, the spectrometer device <b>10</b> further includes an aerosol charger <b>32</b> connected to the aerosol injection port <b>20</b> of the housing <b>12</b> for imparting a predictable electrical charge distribution to an air sample being measured. In particular, a collected air sample containing aerosol particles is fed to the aerosol charger <b>32</b> where it is charged prior to being delivered to the aerosol injection port <b>20</b> of the housing <b>12</b>. The aerosol sample flow rate through the aerosol charger <b>32</b> is preferably about 0.3 L/min. Suitable aerosol chargers or neutralizers are TSI Model No. 3077, which can be purchased from TSI, Inc.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Preferably, a portion <b>34</b> of the collected air sample is diverted to the inlet <b>16</b> of the housing <b>12</b> to provide a flow medium <b>36</b> within the interior chamber <b>14</b> of the housing. The diverted air portion <b>34</b> is preferably forced through a high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter <b>38</b> to eliminate the aerosol particles in the air. The particle-free flow medium <b>36</b> preferably has a flow rate entering the inlet <b>16</b> of about 15.0 L/min and may be driven by a pump <b>40</b> connected to the housing hood <b>26</b> at the opposite outlet <b>18</b> of the housing. The volumetric flow rate of the flow medium <b>36</b> is preferably about 15.0 L/min and may include additional minor sheath flows through both sides of the narrow aerosol injection port slit <b>20</b> to confine the aerosol flow to the region where the flow velocity is uniform. Therefore, particles of the same size, but introduced at different locations of the injection port slit <b>20</b>, experience the same electric and flow field, and travel the same distance in the direction of the electric field inside the separation section <b>22</b> discussed below.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The diverted portion <b>34</b> of the collected air sample is further preferably passed through a saturator <b>42</b> for introducing a working vapor to the flow medium <b>36</b>. The saturator <b>42</b> is disposed downstream of the HEPA filter <b>38</b> and generally includes a reservoir <b>44</b>, an inlet <b>46</b> and an outlet <b>48</b> in fluid communication with the reservoir and a heater <b>50</b> adjacent the reservoir. The reservoir <b>44</b> holds a working liquid <b>45</b> therein, which produces a vapor when heated by the heater <b>50</b>. The working liquid <b>45</b> is preferably one that produces a very inert vapor upon heating so that the vapor will not react with the aerosol before reaching the growth section described below. Suitable working liquids include n-butanol and Fluoriner™ produced by 3M Corp. When butanol is used, the heater <b>50</b> preferably heats the butanol to about 30° C. The heater <b>50</b> may be a strip-type heater having a self-adhesive backing and electrically connected to a temperature controller to maintain temperature. Such heaters are produced by Minco Products, Inc. Thus, the inlet <b>46</b> of the saturator <b>42</b> introduces the diverted air <b>34</b> into the reservoir <b>44</b> where it becomes mixed with the working vapor produced as a result of heating the working liquid <b>45</b>. The mixed working vapor and particle-free air exits the outlet <b>48</b> of the saturator <b>42</b> and becomes the flow medium <b>36</b> provided to the housing inlet <b>16</b>. The flow medium <b>36</b> may further be passed through a screen (not shown) to ensure a smooth laminar flow in the housing interior chamber <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Upon exiting the aerosol charger <b>32</b>, the charged aerosols <b>52</b> are injected through the aerosol injection port <b>20</b> into the separation section <b>22</b> of the housing <b>12</b>, where it becomes entrained with the sheath flow medium <b>36</b> within the interior chamber <b>14</b>. The separation section <b>22</b> of the housing <b>12</b> is preferably about 20 cm in length and includes a negative voltage source <b>54</b> for applying a constant electric field E perpendicular to the flow direction of the flow medium <b>36</b>. Under the influence of this electric field E, the charged aerosols <b>52</b> are separated by size into different flow streams based on the aerosol's electrical mobility. Simply put, the smaller more mobile particles are influenced by the electric field greater than the larger particles and will, therefore, migrate further toward the charged electrode plate <b>25</b>. As an example, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows five flow streams <b>52</b><i>a</i>, <b>52</b><i>b</i>, <b>52</b><i>c</i>, <b>52</b><i>d </i>and <b>52</b><i>e</i>. However, the number of actual flow streams which can be detected is much higher.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">To increase the size of the aerosol particles and, therefore, to improve detectability, particularly in the smaller ranges, the housing <b>12</b> of the present invention further preferably includes a growth section <b>56</b> disposed downstream from the separation section <b>22</b>. After leaving the separation section <b>22</b>, the saturated aerosol sample streams <b>52</b><i>a</i>, <b>52</b><i>b</i>, <b>52</b><i>c</i>, <b>52</b><i>d </i>and <b>52</b><i>e </i>enter the growth section <b>56</b> of the housing <b>12</b> where the particles in each stream are increased in size through a condensation process. The growth section <b>56</b> is essentially a condenser having a length of about 25 cm and including at least one thermoelectrical cooler <b>58</b> disposed on at least one of the parallel walls <b>24</b> and <b>25</b> of the housing <b>12</b> for cooling the aerosol sample flowing within the interior chamber <b>14</b> down to about 5° C. Suitable TEC Module thermoelectric coolers of various wattages can be obtained from Melcor, Inc.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The structure of the growth section <b>56</b> should be electrically and thermally isolated from the separation section <b>22</b> of the housing <b>12</b>. To accomplish this, the parallel plates <b>24</b> and <b>25</b> may consist of plate portions <b>24</b><i>a </i>and <b>25</b><i>a </i>making up the separation section <b>22</b> and plate portions <b>24</b><i>b </i>and <b>25</b><i>b </i>making up the growth section <b>56</b> of the housing <b>12</b>. All of the plate portions <b>24</b><i>a</i>, <b>24</b><i>b</i>, <b>25</b><i>a </i>and <b>25</b><i>b </i>are made from thermally and electrically conductive materials, such as stainless steel or aluminum. The plate portions <b>24</b><i>a </i>and <b>25</b><i>a </i>of the separation section <b>22</b> can be connected to the plate portions <b>24</b><i>b </i>and <b>25</b><i>g </i>of the growth section <b>56</b> by insulative couplers or flanges <b>60</b> to thermally and electrically isolate the two sections.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The growth section <b>56</b> further preferably includes at least one condensation wick <b>62</b> to absorb any excess condensation accumulating in the growth section. The condensation wick <b>62</b> may simply be a porous metal strip embedded in a recess or otherwise fixed at the bottom of the growth section wall portions <b>24</b><i>b </i>and <b>25</b><i>b </i>near the housing outlet <b>18</b> so that condensation collecting on the wall portions will be drawn downwardly toward the wick under the influence of gravity. A condensation outlet <b>64</b> is preferably in fluid communication with the wick <b>62</b> to draw condensation out of the wick. A peristaltic pump (not shown) can be used to facilitate the removal of the condensation from the wick <b>62</b> through the condensation outlet <b>64</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The subsequent cooling of the flow medium <b>36</b> inside the growth section <b>56</b> causes the vapor generated by the saturator <b>42</b> to condense on the aerosol particle nuclei to form droplets that are subsequently easily viewed and counted by the camera <b>28</b>. The growth section <b>56</b> of the present invention generates high supersaturation that activates particles as small as 5 nm in diameter. In this manner, the aerosol particles grow into supermicron droplets.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The growth section <b>56</b> terminates at the outlet end <b>18</b> of the housing <b>12</b>, where the aerosol streams <b>52</b><i>a</i>-<i>e </i>exit the housing in different relative positions due to the known electric field E applied to the flow medium <b>36</b> in the separation section <b>22</b>. As mentioned above, connected at the outlet end <b>18</b> of the housing <b>12</b> is a hood <b>26</b> having a window <b>30</b>. The camera <b>28</b> is positioned adjacent the outlet <b>18</b> of the housing in such a manner as to simultaneously view the aerosol streams <b>52</b><i>a</i>-<i>e </i>through the window <b>30</b> of the hood <b>26</b>. The window <b>30</b> prevents deposition of grown particles onto the camera lens. Additionally, a small purge may be directed at the window so that incoming droplets will not accumulate on the window.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The major components of the camera <b>28</b> are a custom designed lens system and a frame transfer CCD. The frame transfer CCD preferably has an active area of about 12.3 mm×12.3 mm, which consists of 1024×1024 pixels, wherein each pixel is 12 μm×12 μm. The lens system preferably has a magnification ratio of 0.22 and projects a 5.6 cm×1 cm viewing area on an area of 1.23 cm×0.22 cm (1024×182=186,368 pixels) on the CCD. It has been found that this arrangement produces a spot size of the particle image that is less than 24 μm in diameter, which is about 4 (2×2) pixels on the CCD. A suitable high-speed digital camera for use with the present invention is DALSA Model No. DS-21-01-M60.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Preferably, a laser source <b>66</b> is provided to direct a collimated sheet of light <b>67</b> perpendicular to the aerosol flow streams <b>52</b><i>a</i>-<i>e </i>exiting the outlet end <b>18</b> of the spectrometer housing <b>12</b>, which illuminates the particles as they cross. The cross-section of the light sheet after collimation is preferably about 1 cm×1 mm. Any available 30-50 mWatt CW laser source providing a green laser of 532 nm wavelength can be used with the present invention. Based on the preferred geometry and flow settings, the maximum velocity of an aerosol particle is calculated to be about 38 cm/sec, whereby the grown particles will be illuminated for a minimum of 3 milliseconds as it crosses the 1 mm thick light sheet. The thus illuminated supermicron aerosol droplets are then easily detected by the camera <b>28</b> and can be counted by a data acquisition system <b>68</b> connected to the camera <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">An alternative embodiment of the present invention is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, wherein like parts have the same reference numerals. In the alternative device <b>70</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the saturation function for introducing a working vapor to the flow medium <b>36</b> has been incorporated within the spectrometer housing. In particular, the housing <b>72</b> of this device <b>70</b> includes a saturation section <b>74</b> disposed between the separation section <b>22</b> and the growth section <b>56</b>. The saturation section <b>74</b> is preferably about 45 cm in length and includes thermally conductive parallel plate portions <b>24</b><i>c </i>and <b>25</b><i>c</i>, which, together with the plate portions <b>24</b><i>a </i>and <b>25</b><i>a </i>of the separation section and the plate portions <b>24</b><i>b </i>and <b>25</b><i>b </i>of the growth section, define the interior chamber <b>14</b> of the housing <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Again, it is important to electrically and thermally isolate the saturation section <b>74</b> from both the separation section <b>22</b> and the growth section <b>56</b>. This is again accomplished by connecting respective wall portions with insulative couplings <b>60</b>. Also, the wall portions <b>24</b><i>c </i>and <b>25</b><i>c </i>of the saturation section are preferably electrically grounded.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The saturation section <b>74</b> of this embodiment includes at least one wick <b>76</b> disposed on the inner surface of at least one of the parallel wall portions <b>24</b><i>c </i>and <b>25</b><i>c </i>and at least one heating tape <b>78</b> disposed adjacent the wick, for example, on the outer surface of the parallel wall. The wick <b>76</b> is soaked with an organic liquid such as n-butanol, which becomes vaporized upon heating by the heating tape <b>78</b> to a temperature of about 30° C. Here too, the wick <b>76</b> may be made from a porous or semi-porous metal sheet having pores to absorb the working fluid. The wick may be embedded in a recess or otherwise fixed on the inner surface of the wall portions <b>24</b><i>c </i>and <b>25</b><i>c </i>facing the interior chamber <b>14</b> of the housing <b>12</b>. A saturation liquid injection port <b>80</b> in fluid communication with the wick <b>76</b> may be provided for injecting the working liquid into the wick. Similarly, a saturation liquid evacuation port <b>82</b> in fluid communication with the wick <b>76</b> may be provided for withdrawing excess working liquid from the wick.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Like the saturator <b>42</b> described above, the saturation section <b>74</b> of the housing works to introduce a working vapor into the flow medium <b>36</b>, which subsequently condenses on the aerosol particles in the growth section <b>56</b> to increase the size of the particles for easy detection. However in this case, the flow medium <b>36</b> is saturated with the organic vapor after separation into size-dependent aerosol streams <b>52</b><i>a</i>, <b>52</b><i>b </i>and <b>52</b><i>c</i>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In both embodiments, the imaging system <b>28</b> and <b>68</b> records size-dependent particle positions and their numbers, which are then used to derive particle size distribution spectrum, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Specifically, the camera <b>28</b> records a CCD image of all of the particle streams <b>52</b><i>a</i>-<b>52</b><i>e </i>exiting the outlet <b>18</b> of the spectrometer housing <b>12</b>. The relative position of each stream <b>52</b><i>a</i>-<b>52</b><i>e </i>between the parallel walls <b>24</b> and <b>25</b> of the housing <b>12</b> can be determined and the number of aerosol particles at each position can be counted based on image pixel distribution using suitable data acquisition software. The digital camera <b>28</b> is preferably operated at a readout speed of 10 fps so that the probability that two particles are detected at the same location during the 0.1 second exposure time is very small. Also, at a readout speed of 10 fps, the signal to noise ratio for grown particles of 20 microns in diameter is about 200. Therefore, grown particles can be reliably detected using the imaging system of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Thus, the aerosol mobility size spectrometer of the present invention addresses the need to improve measurement speed through a new approach. Specifically, particles of different sizes are simultaneously measured, wherein the size of the particles and the number of particles of each size can be determined. By eliminating the necessity to scan through the wide range of particles sizes, complete size distributions can be obtained in 1 second or less. Additionally, since all charged particles are measured simultaneously, the AMSS of the present invention has a much better counting rate than conventional DMA systems.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The aerosol mobility size spectrometer (AMSS) of the present invention is able to simultaneously measure aerosols spanning one-decade in electrical mobility range (i.e. the maximum mobility of particle is 10 times the minimum mobility of particles measured by the AMSS). However, the electric field E applied across the separation section <b>14</b> can vary depending on the aerosol measurement range desired. For example, it has been found that an electric field E of about −116 V is preferred for a spectrometer device measuring aerosols in the range of about 15-47 nm, an electric field E of about −1,157 V is preferred for a spectrometer measuring aerosols in the range of about 46-176 nm and an electric field E of about −11,570 V is preferred for a spectrometer measuring aerosols in the range of about 173-1,000 nm. Thus, the device can be utilized in a sequential fashion in which an aerosol sample can be injected into a single device and subjected to a first electric field E<sub>1 </sub>for a first predetermined period of time and then subjected to a second electric field E<sub>2</sub>, for a second predetermined period of time and so on.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">However, to eliminate the time required for successive testing, in a preferred embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the device of the present invention can be utilized as part of a system or apparatus <b>84</b> having three or more housings <b>12</b><i>a</i>, <b>12</b><i>b </i>and <b>12</b><i>c </i>operating simultaneously at different respective voltages E<b>1</b>, E<b>2</b> and E<b>3</b>. In particular, to cover the complete size range of aerosols, a first housing <b>12</b><i>a </i>operating at a first voltage E<b>1</b> of −115V measures aerosols with a first size range of about 15-48 nm. The first housing is preferably operated in parallel with a second housing <b>12</b><i>b </i>operating at a second voltage E<b>2</b> of −1,157V and measuring aerosols with a second size range of about 48-180 nm. Finally, a third housing <b>12</b><i>c </i>is operated in parallel with the first and second housings <b>12</b><i>a </i>and <b>12</b><i>b </i>and applies a third voltage E<b>3</b> of −11,570V and measures aerosols having a third size range of about 180-1000 nm. A single camera system or three cameras <b>28</b><i>a</i>, <b>28</b><i>b </i>and <b>28</b><i>c </i>can be utilized to record the aerosol flow streams exiting their respective housings. Aerosol sizes greater than 1000 nm can be measured by a conventional optical particle counter, which may be operated in parallel with the three AMSS housing system of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Moreover, as schematically shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the present invention <b>10</b>, <b>70</b> may also be combined with a conventional differential mobility analyzer (DMA) <b>90</b> and a humidifier <b>92</b> to form an aerosol hygroscopicity/volatility spectrometer (AHVS) <b>94</b>, which measures growth of dry aerosols when they are exposed to high relative humidity and further measures the particles' volatility. Generally, the differential mobility analyzer (DMA) <b>90</b> selects dry aerosols <b>96</b> of a desired size in a known manner. These classified aerosols <b>96</b> are delivered to a conventional humidifier <b>92</b> where they are subsequently humidified to a high relative humidity (e.g. 85%). Although starting at the same size, the aerosols <b>96</b> of different chemical composition will grow to different final sizes when subjected to a high relative humidity. The resulting humidified aerosols <b>98</b> of varying sizes can be introduced to the AMSS <b>10</b>, <b>70</b> of the present invention where the resulting size distribution of these aerosols after humidification can then measured.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">More specifically, an aerosol sample is first dried in a nafion dryer <b>98</b> and then introduced into an aerosol charger <b>100</b>, where the aerosol reaches a steady state charging distribution. A conventional DMA <b>90</b> can be used to select a dry monodisperse aerosol at a specified size. The monodispersed aerosol is then split into two flows. One of the two flows is sent to a condensation particle counter (CPC) <b>102</b> that monitors the concentration of the monodispersed aerosol. The other flow is directed to a conventional humidifier <b>92</b> where the dry monodisperse aerosol is humidified to 85% relative humidity (RH). Connected downstream of the humidifier is the aerosol mobility size spectrometer (AMSS) <b>10</b>, <b>70</b> of the present invention which measures the size distribution of the humidified aerosol. The aerosol hygroscopicity is derived from the size of the mondispersed dry aerosol and its size distribution after humidification.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The apparatus <b>94</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> can also be adapted for aerosol volatility measurements (AHVS). In this case, a thermal denuder <b>104</b> is connected adjacent the humidifier <b>92</b> to be operated alternatively with the humidifier. Monodispersed aerosol is heated inside the thermal denuder <b>104</b> to evaporate nonrefractory species. The size distribution of remaining refractory species is then measured downstream by the AMSS <b>10</b>, <b>70</b>. Computer-controlled valves <b>106</b> will direct aerosol to the humidifier <b>92</b> and the thermal denuder <b>104</b> alternately, and another set of valves <b>108</b> will switch sheath flow for the AMSS <b>10</b>, <b>70</b> between a humidifier <b>110</b> and a dryer <b>112</b> accordingly.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The thermal denuder <b>104</b> is preferably operated at about 300° C. to evaporate nonrefractory species such as sulfate, nitrate, and organics. Species surviving the thermal denuder will be mainly EC, sea salt, and mineral dust. Different refractory species can be inferred from their sizes and measurement conditions. For example, refractory species in fine particles is mostly elemental carbon while refractory species found in coarse particles are more likely to be sea salt or mineral dust depending on location. Since the size distribution of atmospheric aerosol is much broader than the DMA transfer function, the size distribution of monodispersed aerosol can be derived from the DMA transfer function and concentration measured by the CPC <b>102</b>. By comparing size distributions of selected aerosol before and after the thermal denuder, aerosol volatility and concentrations of refractory species are obtained.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Similarly, hygroscopicity measurements can also be used to infer aerosol chemical composition as various major aerosol species have different water uptake at 85% RH. By combining the hygroscopicity and volatility measurements, concentrations of major aerosol species can be derived. These include sulfate (hydrophilic and volatile), organics (largely hydrophobic and volatile), sea salt (hydrophilic and refractory), elemental carbon, and mineral dust (both hydrophobic and refractory, but likely to appear in different particles sizes).</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Aerosol hygroscopicity and volatility measurements will also provide aerosol-mixing state, which is important for determining aerosol absorption. A bimodal (or multimodal) distribution after the monodispersed aerosol is humidified or heated indicates the aerosol is externally mixed, while a unimodal distribution is often associated with internally mixed aerosols. Combined with current composition measurements onboard a research aircraft, the chemical composition mixing state inferred from AHVS measurements will provide a more complete picture of the aerosol composition, which is critical to understand radiative effects of atmospheric aerosols.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">For most atmospheric aerosol, the growth factor at 85% RH ranges from 0.8 to 2.2. (The growth factor is the ratio of particle diameter at 85% RH to the diameter of dry particles). As discussed above, the measurement range of a single AMSS unit is 1 decade in electrical mobility, which is sufficient to cover the entire size spectrum of the humidified aerosol. To obtain size-resolved aerosol hygroscopicity, the voltage of the classifying DMA is ramped exponentially (similar to SMPS measurements) to select monodispersed aerosol of different sizes. At the same time, the voltage applied to the AMSS <b>10</b>, <b>70</b> will be ramped accordingly so that the measurement range of the AMSS covers the entire size spectrum of the humidified aerosol. The same method will be used for volatility measurements.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">By utilizing the AMSS <b>10</b>, <b>70</b> of the present invention downstream of a conventional DMA <b>90</b>, the AHVS <b>94</b> substantially increases the speed of hygroscopicity and volatility measurements. Moreover, since atmospheric aerosols have growth factors ranging from about 0.8 to 2.2 (at 85% relative humidity, a single AMSS <b>10</b>, <b>70</b> of the present invention will generally cover the size range of humidified aerosols.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Although illustrative embodiments of the present invention have been described herein with reference to the accompanying drawings, it is to be understood that the invention is not limited to those precise embodiments, and that various other changes and modifications may be effected therein by one skilled in the art without departing from the scope or spirit of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A device for measuring aerosol size distribution within a sample containing aerosol particles, the device comprising:
<claim-text>a chamber including an inlet for introducing a flow medium therein in a flow direction, an aerosol injection port adjacent said inlet for introducing a charged aerosol sample into said chamber wherein the aerosol sample becomes entrained in said flow medium, a separation section for applying an electric field to the aerosol sample across said flow direction wherein the aerosol particles within the aerosol sample are separated by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams under the influence of said electric field, and an outlet opposite said inlet for transporting said plurality of separated aerosol flow streams out of said chamber; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an optical detector disposed adjacent said chamber outlet for optically detecting a relative position of at least one aerosol flow stream exiting said outlet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising an aerosol charger disposed adjacent said aerosol injection port of said chamber for imparting a predictable electrical charge distribution to said aerosol sample.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a laser source disposed adjacent said outlet of said chamber for illuminating said plurality of separated aerosol flow steams exiting said outlet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said chamber is defined by a housing having two substantially parallel walls, said electric field being applied across said parallel walls and said relative position of said at least one aerosol flow stream exiting said housing outlet being optically detected relative to said parallel walls.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said chamber further includes a growth section disposed downstream of said separation section for increasing the size of the aerosol particles within said separated aerosol flow streams using a condensation process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said growth section of said chamber comprises a thermoelectric cooler for driving said condensation process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising a saturator disposed adjacent said inlet of said chamber for introducing a working vapor into said flow medium, said working vapor condensing on the aerosol particles within said growth section, whereby the aerosol particles increase in size.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said saturator comprises a reservoir for holding a working liquid, an inlet in fluid communications with said reservoir for introducing said flow medium into said reservoir, a heater adjacent said reservoir for heating said working liquid to produce said working vapor and an outlet connected to said chamber inlet for introducing said working vapor and said flow medium into said chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said chamber further includes a saturation section disposed between said separation section and said growth section for introducing a working vapor into said separated aerosol flow streams, said working vapor condensing on the aerosol particles within said growth section whereby the aerosol particles increase in size.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A device as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said saturation section of said chamber comprises a wick and a heater in thermal contact with said wick, said wick being saturated with a working liquid and said heater heating said working liquid to produce said working vapor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method for measuring aerosol size distribution within a sample containing aerosol particles, the method comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>applying an electric field across a flow of charged aerosol particles, said electric field separating said charged aerosol particles to form a plurality of aerosol flow streams, each of said aerosol flow streams containing particles of substantially the same size; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>optically detecting a relative position of at least one said flow stream of charged aerosol particles.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> further comprising the step of optically detecting the number of aerosol particles within said at least one aerosol flow stream.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of illuminating said plurality of aerosol flow streams to facilitate optical detection.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of increasing the size of the aerosol particles within said separated aerosol flow streams using a condensation process to facilitate optical detection.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of introducing a working vapor into said charged aerosol flow before application of said electric field, said working vapor condensing on said aerosol particles during said condensation process to increase the size of the aerosol particles.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of introducing a working vapor into said separated aerosol flow streams after application of said electric field, said working vapor condensing on said aerosol particles during said condensation process to increase the size of the aerosol particles.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein said electric field is applied across two substantially parallel walls on opposite sides of said aerosol sample flow and said relative position of said at least one aerosol flow stream is optically detected relative to said parallel walls.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of varying said electrical field to produce separated aerosol flow streams of a desired range.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. An apparatus for measuring aerosol size distribution within a sample containing aerosol particles, the device comprising:
<claim-text>a first housing defining a first interior chamber, said first housing including an inlet for introducing a flow medium into said first chamber in a flow direction, an aerosol injection port adjacent said inlet for introducing a charged aerosol sample into said first chamber wherein the aerosol sample becomes entrained in said flow medium, a separation section for applying a first electrical field to the aerosol sample across said flow direction wherein the aerosol particles within the aerosol sample are separated by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams having a first size range under the influence of said first electric field, and an outlet opposite said inlet for transporting said plurality of separated aerosol flow steams having said first size range out of said first interior chamber;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second housing defining a second interior chamber, said housing including an inlet for introducing a flow medium into said second chamber in a flow direction, an aerosol injection port adjacent said inlet for introducing a charged aerosol sample into said second chamber wherein the aerosol sample becomes entrained in said flow medium, a separation section for applying a second electrical field to the aerosol sample across said flow direction wherein the aerosol particles within the aerosol sample are separated by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams having a second size range under the influence of said second electric field, and an outlet opposite said inlet for transporting said plurality of separated aerosol flow steams having said second size range out of said second interior chamber; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a camera system disposed adjacent said first and second housing outlets for optically detecting a relative position of at least one aerosol flow stream from said first size range and at least one aerosol flow stream from said second size range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. An apparatus for measuring the growth of dry aerosols exposed to high relative humidity comprising:
<claim-text>an aerosol charger for imparting a predictable electrical charge distribution to an aerosol sample;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a differential mobility analyzer for selecting dry aerosols of a desired size from said charged aerosol sample;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a humidifier for increasing the humidity of the dry aerosols selected by said differential mobility analyzer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a housing defining an interior chamber, said housing including an inlet for introducing a flow medium into said chamber in a flow direction, an aerosol injection port adjacent said inlet for introducing the charged aerosols into said chamber, a separation section for applying an electric field to the charged aerosols across said flow direction wherein the charged aerosols are separated by size into a plurality of aerosol flow streams under the influence of said electric field, and an outlet opposite said inlet for transporting said plurality of separated aerosol flow streams out of said interior chamber; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a camera disposed adjacent said housing outlet for optically detecting a relative position of at least one aerosol flow stream exiting said outlet and for optically detecting the number of aerosol particles within said at least one aerosol flow stream.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. An apparatus as defined in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref>, further comprising a thermal denuder for adapting the apparatus for aerosol volatility measurements.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
