<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296533-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296533</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10343221</doc-number>
<date>20010803</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-236716</doc-number>
<date>20000804</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>230</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>23</class>
<subclass>C</subclass>
<main-group>16</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>118723MW</main-classification>
<further-classification>118723 MA</further-classification>
<further-classification>15634536</further-classification>
<further-classification>15634541</further-classification>
<further-classification>15634542</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Radial antenna and plasma device using it</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5698036</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ishii et al.</name>
<date>19971200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-67492</doc-number>
<date>19990300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-067492</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19990300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-164394</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20000600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-164394</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20000600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>8</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>118723 MW</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>118723 MA</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>118723 ME</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>118723 MR</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>118723 AN</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>15634536</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>15634541</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>15634542</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>17</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040045674</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040311</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ishii</last-name>
<first-name>Nobuo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hyogo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Shinohara</last-name>
<first-name>Kibatsu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kanagawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Crowell &amp; Moring LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Tokyo Electron Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hassanzadeh</last-name>
<first-name>Parviz</first-name>
<department>1763</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Crowell</last-name>
<first-name>Michelle</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/JP01/06698</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20010803</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20030618</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO02/13250</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20020214</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A plasma device includes a first conductive plate (<b>31</b>) in which a plurality of slots (<b>36</b>) are formed, a second conductive plate (<b>32</b>) having a microwave inlet (<b>35</b>) and disposed opposite to the first conductive plate (<b>31</b>), a ring member (<b>34</b>) for connecting peripheral edges of the first and second conductive plates (<b>31, 32</b>), and a conductive adjusting member (<b>37</b>) provided on said second conductive plate (<b>32</b>) within a radial waveguide (<b>33</b>) formed by the first and second conductive plates (<b>31, 32</b>) and serving to adjust a distance (d1, d2) up to the first conductive plate (<b>31</b>). With this arrangement, a desired electric field radiation distribution can be obtained without inducing abnormal discharge.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="173.74mm" wi="150.62mm" file="US07296533-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="198.29mm" wi="155.02mm" file="US07296533-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="228.85mm" wi="155.02mm" file="US07296533-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="202.78mm" wi="128.27mm" file="US07296533-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="207.01mm" wi="143.93mm" file="US07296533-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="233.43mm" wi="153.33mm" file="US07296533-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="235.63mm" wi="156.55mm" file="US07296533-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a radial antenna and a plasma device using it.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In the manufacture of a semiconductor device, plasma devices are used often to perform processes such as formation of an oxide film, crystal growth of a semiconductor layer, etching, and ashing. Among the plasma devices, a microwave plasma device is available which produces a high-density plasma by introducing a microwave into a processing vessel through a radial antenna. As a characteristic feature of the microwave plasma device, it has wide applications because it can stably produce a plasma even if the pressure is comparatively low.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> includes views showing the arrangement of an example of a radial antenna conventionally used in the microwave plasma device, and the distribution of its electric field radiation. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>a</i>) is a conceptual view showing the radiation surface of the radial antenna, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>b</i>) is a sectional view taken along the line VIIb-VIIb′ of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>a</i>), and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>c</i>) is a conceptual view showing the distribution of the electric field radiated by the radial antenna. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>c</i>), the axis of abscissa represents the distance from the center of the radial antenna in the radial direction, and the axis of ordinate represents the strength of the electric field radiated from the radial antenna. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a view showing the shape of a slot formed in the radiation surface of the radial antenna shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>b</i>), a radial antenna <b>230</b> conventionally used in the plasma device is formed of two parallel conductive plates <b>231</b> and <b>232</b> which form a radial waveguide <b>233</b>, and a ring member <b>234</b> which connects the peripheral edges of the conductive plates <b>231</b> and <b>232</b>. A microwave inlet <b>235</b> is formed at the center of the conductive plate <b>232</b> to introduce a microwave from a microwave generator (not shown). The conductive plate <b>231</b> also has a large number of slots <b>236</b> to radiate the microwave propagating in the radial waveguide <b>233</b> to a processing vessel (not shown). When the influence on the electromagnetic field in the radial waveguide <b>233</b> is considered, the smaller a width W<b>2</b> of each slot <b>236</b>, the better. If, however, the width W<b>2</b> is excessively small, it may cause abnormal discharge. Thus, the width W<b>2</b> is usually set to about 2 mm (W2≦λg/4 where λg is the wavelength of the microwave in the radial waveguide <b>233</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The microwave introduced from the microwave inlet <b>235</b> propagates radially from the center toward the peripheral portion of the radial waveguide <b>233</b>. As the microwave is radiated little by little from the large number of slots <b>236</b>, the power density in the radial waveguide <b>233</b> gradually decreases toward the peripheral portion of the radial waveguide <b>233</b>. The electric field radiation efficiency of the slots <b>236</b> gradually increases as their length or slot length L<b>2</b> increases from 0 (zero), and reaches the maximum when the slot length L<b>2</b> corresponds to λg/2.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Under these conditions, in order to obtain the radiated electric field distribution as shown in, e.g., <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>c</i>), conventionally, the slot length L<b>2</b> was adjusted, so the radiated electric field strength was controlled. More specifically, the further away from the center of the conductive plate <b>231</b>, the larger the slot length L<b>2</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>a</i>), so the slot length L<b>2</b> at the peripheral portion where the power density was small was set close to a length corresponding to λg/2, thus realizing the radiated electric field distribution as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>c</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">When, hover, W<b>2</b>=λg/2 where the electric field radiation efficiency of the slot <b>236</b> becomes maximum, the microwave resonates. Particularly, when the width W<b>2</b> of the slot <b>236</b> is as small as 2 mm, abnormal discharge is induced. When this discharge heats the portion around the slot <b>236</b>, the surrounding portion of the slot <b>236</b> is distorted, or starts to melt.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention has been made to solve the above problems, and has as its object to obtain a desired electric field radiation distribution without inducing abnormal discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In order to achieve the above object, a radial antenna according to the present invention is characterized by comprising a first conductive plate in which a plurality of slots are formed, a second conductive plate having a microwave inlet and disposed opposite to the first conductive plate, a ring member for connecting peripheral edges of the first and second conductive plates, and a conductive adjusting member provided on the second conductive plate in a radial waveguide formed by the first and second conductive plates and serving to adjust a distance up to the first conductive plate. When the distance from the second conductive plate to the first conductive plate is decreased, the power density between the first and second conductive plates can be increased. Thus, even when the slot length of slots formed in the first conductive plate is decreased to be sufficiently smaller than a length corresponding to λg/2, the radiated electric field strength can be increased.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A plurality of conductive adjusting members may be disposed radially when viewed from the top. Alternatively, one or a plurality of adjusting members may be disposed along the periphery of the second conductive plate.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The conductive member may be set to become higher as it is further away from the center of the second conductive plate. Then, the power density in the radial waveguide in the radial direction can be changed.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In the radial antenna descried above, when the slots are substantially rectangular or arcuate, the slot length is preferably decreased to be smaller than a length corresponding to λg/3. Then, even if the widths of the slots are narrow, induction of abnormal discharge can be prevented effectively.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A plasma device according to the present invention is characterized by comprising a susceptor for placing a target object thereon, a processing vessel for accommodating the susceptor, exhaust means for evacuating an interior of the processing vessel, gas supply means for supplying a gas into the processing vessel, and antenna means which is arranged to oppose that surface of the susceptor where the target object is to be placed and which supplies a microwave into the processing Vessel, wherein the radial antenna described above is used as the antenna means.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a view showing the arrangement of an etching apparatus according to the first embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> includes views showing the arrangement of an example of the radial antenna and the distribution of its electric field radiation;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> includes views showing the shapes of slots formed in the radial antenna shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> includes plan views showing the arrangements of examples of a conductive plate that forms a radiation surface;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a sectional view showing a modification of ridges;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> includes views showing the arrangement of another example of the radial antenna and the distribution of its electric field radiation;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> includes views showing the arrangement of an example of a radial antenna conventionally used in a microwave plasma device, and the distribution of its electric field radiation; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a view showing the shape of a slot formed in the radial antenna shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The embodiments of the present invention will be described in detail with reference to the drawings. A description will be made by way of examples in which a plasma device using a radial antenna according to the present invention is applied to etching apparatuses.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a view showing the arrangement of an etching apparatus according to the first embodiment of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the sectional structure of part of the arrangement is shown.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The etching apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> has a cylindrical processing vessel <b>11</b> with an upper opening. This processing vessel <b>11</b> is made of a conductive member such as aluminum.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Exhaust ports (exhaust means) <b>14</b> communicating with a vacuum pump (not shown) are formed in the bottom of the processing vessel <b>11</b>, so the interior of the processing vessel <b>11</b> can be evacuated to a predetermined vacuum degree.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">A plasma gas supply nozzle <b>15</b> for introducing a plasma gas such as Ar into the processing vessel <b>11</b>, and a process gas supply nozzle <b>16</b> for introducing an etching gas are formed in the upper and lower portions, respectively, of the side wall of the processing vessel <b>11</b>. The nozzles (gas supply means) <b>15</b> and <b>16</b> are formed of quartz pipes or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The processing vessel <b>11</b> accommodates a susceptor <b>22</b> for placing an etching target substrate (target object) <b>21</b> on its upper surface. The susceptor <b>22</b> is fixed on a support table <b>23</b> which is fixed to the bottom of the processing vessel <b>11</b> through an insulating plate <b>24</b>. The susceptor <b>22</b> is also connected to a bias RF power supply <b>26</b> through a matching box <b>25</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">A flat plate-like dielectric plate <b>13</b> is horizontally arranged in the upper opening of the processing vessel <b>11</b>. Silica glass or a ceramic material (e.g., Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3 </sub>or AlN) with a thickness of about 20 mm to 30 mm is used to form the dielectric plate <b>13</b>. A seal member <b>12</b> such as an O-ring is disposed at the bonding portion between the processing vessel <b>11</b> and dielectric plate <b>13</b>. This assures the hermeticity in the processing vessel <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">A radial antenna <b>30</b> is disposed on the dielectric plate <b>13</b> with its radiation surface (conductive plate <b>31</b> to be described later) facing down. The radial antenna <b>30</b> is an antenna means that supplies a microwave MW into the processing vessel <b>11</b> through the dielectric plate <b>13</b>. The dielectric plate <b>13</b> is opposed to the radiation surface of the radial antenna <b>30</b>, and covers the radiation surface entirely. Hence, the radial antenna <b>30</b> is protected from a plasma generated in the processing vessel <b>11</b>. The circumferential surfaces of the dielectric plate <b>13</b> and radial antenna <b>30</b> are covered by a shield material <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> includes views showing the arrangement of the radial antenna <b>30</b> and the distribution of its electric field radiation, in which <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>) is a plan view showing the radiation surface of the radial antenna <b>30</b>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>b</i>) is a sectional view taken along the line IIb-IIb′ of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>), and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>c</i>) is a conceptual view showing the distribution of the electric field radiated by the radial antenna <b>30</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>) is shown conceptually to clarify the characteristic feature of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>c</i>), the axis of abscissa represents the distance from the center of the radial antenna <b>30</b> in the radial direction, and the axis of ordinate represents the strength of the electric field radiated from the radial antenna <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>b</i>), the radial antenna <b>30</b> is formed of the first conductive plate <b>31</b> constituting the radiation surface, a second conductive plate <b>32</b> arranged above the conductive plate <b>31</b> to oppose it, and a ring member <b>34</b> for connecting the peripheral edges of the conductive plates <b>31</b> and <b>32</b>. The ring member <b>34</b> holds the gap between the conductive plates <b>31</b> and <b>32</b> to dl. The radial antenna <b>30</b> with this arrangement has a hollow cylindrical shape. The two conductive plates <b>31</b> and <b>32</b> form a radial waveguide <b>33</b> which guides the microwave MW. The conductive plates <b>31</b> and <b>32</b>, and ring member <b>34</b> are made of a conductor such as copper or aluminum.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">A microwave inlet <b>35</b> through which the microwave MW is introduced is formed at the center of the conductive plate <b>32</b>. A large number of slots <b>36</b> extending in the circumferential direction are concentrically formed in the conductive plate <b>31</b> which forms the radiation surface, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> includes views showing examples of the shapes of the slots <b>36</b>. The shapes of the slots <b>36</b> may be rectangular as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>a</i>), or arcuate as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>c</i>). The four corners of each of the slots <b>36</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>3</b>(<i>c</i>) may be rounded as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>b</i>) and <b>3</b>(<i>d</i>). In each of the slots <b>36</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) to <b>3</b>(<i>d</i>), the size in the longitudinal direction, i.e., the slot length, is defined as L<b>1</b> and the size in the widthwise direction, i.e., the width, is defined as W<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>), the slot lengths L<b>1</b> of the slots <b>36</b> increase in principle as the slots <b>36</b> are further away from the center from the conductive plate <b>31</b>. Note that in the radial direction, the slot lengths L<b>1</b> are discontinuous across the boundary between a region A<b>1</b> that does not oppose ridges <b>37</b> (to be described later) and a region A<b>2</b> that opposes them. Assuming that the wavelength of the microwave MW in the radial waveguide <b>33</b> is λg, the slot length L<b>1</b> is set sufficiently smaller than a length corresponding to λg/2 at maximum. In this radial antenna <b>30</b>, the maximum slot length L<b>1</b> is set to λg/3.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The width W<b>1</b> of each slot <b>36</b> is set to about 2 mm considering the influence on the electromagnetic field in the radial waveguide <b>33</b> and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The pitch among the slots <b>36</b> in the radial direction is set on the basis of λg. To realize a radiation type antenna as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4(</figref><i>a</i>), the pitch is set to about a length corresponding to λg. To realize a leak antenna as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4(</figref><i>b</i>), the pitch is set to about a length corresponding to λg/20 to λg/30.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a coaxial cable <b>41</b> is connected to the center of the radial antenna <b>30</b>. An outer conductor <b>41</b>A of the coaxial cable <b>41</b> is connected to the microwave inlet <b>35</b> of the conductive plate <b>32</b>. The distal end of a central conductor <b>41</b>B of the coaxial cable <b>41</b> forms a circular cone, and the bottom of the circular cone is connected to the center of the conductive plate <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The coaxial cable <b>41</b> connected to the radial antenna <b>30</b> in this manner is connected to a microwave generator <b>45</b> through a rectangular coaxial converter <b>42</b> and rectangular waveguide <b>43</b>. The microwave generator <b>45</b> generates the microwave MW of, e.g., 2.45 GHz. The frequency of the microwave MW suffices if it falls within the range of 1 GHz to 10-odd GHz. A matching circuit <b>44</b> for impedance matching is connected midway along the rectangular waveguide <b>43</b>, so that the power use efficiency can be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>b</i>), in the radial waveguide <b>33</b>, a plurality of ridges <b>36</b> are fixed to the lower surface of the conductive plate <b>32</b>. These ridges <b>37</b> are made of a conductor such as copper or aluminum, and are fixed with machine screws from the conductive plate <b>36</b> side. The ridges <b>37</b> are quadrangular prismatic members with a height h smaller than d<b>1</b>, and operate as adjusting members for adjusting the distance up to the upper surface of the conductive plate <b>31</b>. Of the edges of each ridge <b>37</b>, an edge <b>37</b>E which is the closest to the center of the radial waveguide <b>33</b> is chamfered as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>b</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>a</i>), the ridges <b>37</b> are disposed radially in that region A<b>2</b> which is away from the center of the conductive plate <b>32</b> by a predetermined distance or more and where the radiated electric field strength is to be increased. At this time, the ridges <b>37</b> are disposed on a region opposing the slots <b>36</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>4</b>(<i>b</i>), when slots <b>36</b>A and <b>36</b>B are formed in the entire region of the conductive plate <b>31</b> excluding the central portion, the ridges <b>37</b> are arranged continuously in the circumferential direction.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">At the region A<b>1</b> where no ridges <b>37</b> are disposed, the height of the radial waveguide <b>33</b> corresponds to the distance dl from the conductive plate <b>32</b> to the conductive plate <b>31</b>. In contrast to this, at the region A<b>2</b> where the ridges <b>37</b> are disposed, the height of the radial waveguide <b>33</b> corresponds to a distance d<b>2</b> (=d<b>1</b>−h (&lt;d<b>1</b>)) from the ridges <b>37</b> to the conductive plate <b>31</b>. At the region A<b>2</b> where the height of the radial waveguide <b>33</b> is small due to the presence of the ridges <b>37</b>, the power density increases. Therefore, at the region A<b>2</b> provided with the ridges <b>37</b>, the radiated electric field strength can be increased even when the slot length L<b>1</b> is decreased to be sufficiently smaller than a length corresponding to λg/2.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Resonance can be suppressed if the slot length L<b>1</b> is decreased to be sufficiently smaller than a length corresponding to λg/2. Thus, even if the width W<b>1</b> of each slot <b>36</b> is as small as 2 mm, induction of abnormal discharge can be prevented. More preferably, when L<b>1</b>&lt;λg/3, induction of abnormal discharge can be prevented effectively.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Furthermore, when the slot length L<b>1</b> of each slot <b>36</b> is adjusted in accordance with the distance from the center of the conductive plate <b>32</b> so that the radiated electric field strength is controlled, an electric field radiation distribution as shown in, e.g., <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2(</figref><i>c</i>), can be obtained without inducing abnormal discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">A delay member made of a dielectric material such as a ceramic material with a relative dielectric constant larger than 1 may be arranged in the radial waveguide <b>33</b>. When the delay member is used, the electric field radiation efficiency can be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The operation of the etching apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The substrate <b>21</b> is placed on the upper surface of the susceptor <b>22</b>, and the interior of the processing vessel <b>11</b> is set to a vacuum degree of, e.g., about 0.01 Pa to 10 Pa. While maintaining this vacuum degree, Ar is supplied as the plasma gas from the plasma gas supply nozzle <b>15</b>, and an etching gas such as CF<sub>4 </sub>is supplied from the process gas supply nozzle <b>16</b> under flow rate control.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">With the plasma gas and etching gas being supplied into the processing vessel <b>11</b>, the microwave MW from the microwave generator <b>45</b> is supplied to the radial antenna <b>30</b> through the rectangular waveguide <b>43</b>, rectangular coaxial converter <b>42</b>, and coaxial cable <b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The microwave MW supplied to the radial antenna <b>30</b> propagates radially from the center toward the periphery of the radial waveguide <b>33</b> formed of the conductive plates <b>31</b> and <b>32</b>. At this time, the microwave MW is radiated gradually from the slots <b>36</b>, so the power of the microwave MW propagating in the radial waveguide <b>33</b> decreases gradually toward the periphery of the radial waveguide <b>33</b>. At the region A<b>2</b> which is away from the center of the conductive plate <b>32</b> by the predetermined distance or more and on which the ridges <b>37</b> are disposed, however, the height of the radial waveguide <b>33</b> changes from d<b>1</b> to d<b>2</b> with a decrease corresponding to the height h of the ridges <b>37</b>, so the power density in the radial waveguide <b>33</b> does not become so small as in the conventional case. Hence, even when the slot length L<b>1</b> is shorter than a length corresponding to λg/3, the electric field strength of the microwave MW radiated from all the slots <b>36</b> becomes sufficiently large.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">On the other hand, since L<b>1</b>&lt;λg/3, even if the width W<b>1</b> of each slot <b>36</b> is as small as 2 mm, abnormal discharge is not induced. Therefore, the portion around the slot <b>36</b> is not distorted or dissolved by discharge unlike in the conventional case.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The microwave MW radiated from the radial antenna <b>30</b> is transmitted through the dielectric plate <b>13</b> and is introduced into the processing vessel <b>11</b>. The microwave MW forms an electric field in the processing vessel <b>11</b> to ionize Ar, thus producing a plasma in a space S<b>1</b> above the substrate <b>11</b> as the processing target.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In this etching apparatus, since the susceptor <b>22</b> is biased with a negative potential, ions are extracted from the produced plasma to etch a substrate <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The radial antenna <b>30</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> uses the ridges <b>37</b> with the constant height h. Alternatively, as in a radial antenna <b>30</b>A shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, ridges <b>37</b>A with a height that changes continuously in the radial direction may be disposed on the lower surface of the conductive plate <b>32</b>, so that the lower surface opposing the conductive plate <b>31</b> inclines. At this time, the inclination of the ridges <b>37</b>A is designed by considering the impedance matching inside and outside the radial antenna <b>30</b>A.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In the radial antenna <b>30</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the ridges <b>37</b> are disposed radially. Alternatively, the ridges may be disposed along the periphery of the conductive plate <b>32</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> includes views showing the arrangement of a radial antenna in which ridges are disposed in this manner. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>a</i>) is a plan view showing the radiation surface of the radial antenna, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>b</i>) is a sectional view taken along the line VIb-VIb′ of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>a</i>). <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>a</i>) is shown conceptually to clarify the characteristic feature of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the same portions as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> are denoted by the same reference numerals, and a description thereof will be omitted as required.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, three ridges <b>137</b>A, <b>137</b>B, and <b>137</b>C serving as adjusting members are fixed along the periphery of the lower surface of a conductive plate <b>32</b> in a radial waveguide <b>133</b>. The ridges <b>137</b>A to <b>137</b>C form concentric circles conforming to the periphery of the conductive plate <b>32</b>, and are disposed in this order from the inner side. Assuming that the heights of the ridges <b>137</b>A, <b>137</b>B, and <b>137</b>C are h<b>1</b>, h<b>2</b>, and h<b>3</b>, respectively, h<b>1</b>&lt;h<b>2</b>&lt;h<b>3</b> holds. Namely, the ridges <b>137</b>A to <b>137</b>C become higher as they are further away from the center of the conductive plate <b>32</b>. Hence, the radial waveguide <b>133</b> becomes lower as it is further away from the center of the radial waveguide <b>133</b>. This can change the power density in the radial waveguide <b>133</b> in the radial direction.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Therefore, in the same manner as in the radial antenna <b>30</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, even when a slot length L<b>1</b> is set to a length sufficiently smaller than a length corresponding to λg/2, e.g., to be sufficiently smaller than a length corresponding to λg/3, if the ridges <b>137</b>A to <b>137</b>C are provided, the radiated electric field strength can be increased. Even when a width W<b>1</b> of each slot <b>36</b> is as small as 2 mm, induction of abnormal discharge can be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Having described a case in which the three ridges <b>137</b>A to <b>137</b>C are disposed concentrically, the number of ridges is not limited to three.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">While the heights h<b>1</b>, h<b>2</b>, h<b>3</b> of the respective ridges <b>137</b>A, <b>137</b>B, and <b>137</b>C are each constant, they may change continuously in the radial direction in the same manner as in the ridges <b>37</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">As has been described above, in the above embodiments, adjusting members for adjusting the distance from the second conductive plate to the first conductive plate, which two conductive plates forming the radial waveguide, are provided. At the periphery of the radial waveguide where the power density conventionally decreases, the power density can be increased by decreasing the height of the radial waveguide. Even when the slot length is decreased to be sufficiently smaller than a length corresponding to λg/2, the radiated electric field strength can be increased. Hence, when adjusting members are provided to correspond to a region where the radiated electric field strength is to be increased, a desired electric field distribution can be obtained without inducing abnormal discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The plasma device using the radial antenna according to the present invention can be applied not only to the etching apparatus described above but also to other plasma devices such as a plasma CVD apparatus or ashing apparatus. The application of the radial antenna according to the present invention is not limited to the plasma device described above. For example, the radial antenna according to the present invention may be applied to a communication antenna, particularly, a distributor/synthesizer which distributes and synthesizes a transmission/reception signal of an array antenna.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A radial antenna comprising:
<claim-text>a first conductive plate in which a plurality of slots are formed,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second conductive plate in which a microwave inlet is formed at a central portion thereof, the second conductive plate disposed opposite to said first conductive plate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a ring member for connecting peripheral edges of said first and second conductive plates, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a conductive adjusting member attached to the second conductive plate in a region excluding the central portion of said second conductive plate in which the microwave inlet is formed, the conductive adjusting member disposed in a radial waveguide formed by said first and second conductive plates such that a distance between the conductive adjusting member and said first conductive plate is smaller than a distance between the second conductive plate and the first conductive plate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the conductive adjusting member comprises an electrically conductive adjusting member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A radial antenna according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that said conductive adjusting member is disposed at an outer peripheral portion of said second conductive plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A radial antenna according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that said adjusting member is disposed along the peripheral edge of said second conductive plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A radial antenna according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that said adjusting member is set to become higher as being further away from a center of said second conductive plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A radial antenna according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the slots are substantially rectangular or arcuate, and
<claim-text>a slot length of the slots is smaller than a length corresponding to ⅓ the wavelength of a microwave propagating in said radial waveguide.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A plasma device characterized by comprising
<claim-text>a susceptor for placing a target object thereon,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a processing vessel for accommodating said susceptor,</claim-text>
<claim-text>exhaust means for evacuating an interior of said processing vessel,</claim-text>
<claim-text>gas supply means for supplying a gas into said processing vessel, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>antenna means which is arranged to oppose that surface of said susceptor where the target object is to be placed and which supplies a microwave into said processing vessel,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said antenna means comprises a radial antenna according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A radial antenna according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the conductive adjusting member is configured to increase a power density at a peripheral portion of the radial waveguide.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A radial antenna according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that a plurality of said conductive adjusting members are disposed radially when viewed from top.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
