<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296600-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296600</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10955298</doc-number>
<date>20040930</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>388</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>65</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>30</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>141 94</main-classification>
<further-classification>141 46</further-classification>
<further-classification>141 59</further-classification>
<further-classification>141 83</further-classification>
<further-classification>141302</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Valve assembly and refueling sensor</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5579802</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tuckey</name>
<date>19961200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5878725</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Osterbrink</name>
<date>19990300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>123516</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6145532</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tuckey et al.</name>
<date>20001100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6199574</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Harris</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>137199</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6443190</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Enge</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>141  7</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6533002</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kobayashi et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>141302</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>23</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>141 59</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>141 83</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>141 94</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>141 44</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>141 46</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>141285</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>141302</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137199</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137 43</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060065324</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060330</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ferreria</last-name>
<first-name>David M.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Orange</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Forgue</last-name>
<first-name>John R.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Cheshire</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Johansen</last-name>
<first-name>Mark R.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wallingford</city>
<state>CT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Reising, Ethington, Barnes, Kisselle, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>TI Group Automotive Systems, L.L.C.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Warren</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Maust</last-name>
<first-name>Timothy L.</first-name>
<department>3751</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A valve assembly includes a housing having a valve seat defining at least part of a vent passage, a pressure responsive member carried by the housing and defining at least part of a pressure chamber, and a valve carried by the housing and having a closure movable relative to the valve seat between an open position permitting fluid flow through the vent passage and a closed position at least substantially restricting fluid flow through the vent passage. The closure is moved by the pressure responsive member in response to changes in pressure in the pressure chamber. A control passage communicates at one end with a pressure source and at its other end with the pressure chamber and an electrically operated valve is movable from a first position permitting a pressure signal to develop within the pressure chamber and a second position permitting pressure within the pressure chamber to vent.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="88.39mm" wi="157.82mm" file="US07296600-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="183.05mm" wi="161.80mm" file="US07296600-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="175.34mm" wi="156.55mm" file="US07296600-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="232.66mm" wi="145.03mm" file="US07296600-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to fuel systems and more particularly to a sensor and valve for detecting a refueling event and venting fuel vapors from a fuel tank.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Environmental concerns and governmental regulations require reduced emissions to the atmosphere of volatile hydrocarbon fuel vapors. One source of hydrocarbon fuel vapors is the fuel tanks of vehicles using gasoline or other hydrocarbon fuels. Fuel vapor can escape to the atmosphere during the filling of the tanks and usually even after the tanks are filled. The use of an onboard vapor recovery system to remove excess fuel vapor from the fuel tank is one solution to the problem. Typically, a canister with activated charcoal therein receives fuel vapors through a valve assembly mounted to the fuel tank. The vapor canister communicates with the intake manifold of a vehicle engine for exhausting fuel vapor from the canister during operation. The valve assembly usually has a valve responsive to the level of liquid fuel in the tank that enables the valve to stay open at a sufficiently low fuel level to permit fuel vapors to flow freely from the fuel tank into the canister. As the fuel level rises during filling to approach the desired maximum level of fuel in the tank, a float is raised to close the valve and prevent liquid fuel from flowing through the valve and into the vapor canister.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In certain circumstances it is desirably or required to be able to detect the addition of liquid fuel to the fuel tank. For example, OBD-II tank leak testing requires knowledge of a refilling event for proper testing of tank pressure and leak integrity. Likewise, electronic fuel level control within the fuel tank may also require knowledge of a refueling action such as to control the maximum fuel level obtained during the refueling event and thereby control the automatic shut off of a refueling pump nozzle. It has been previously proposed to sense the refueling event by sensing removal of a fill cap from a fill tube of the fuel tank, or by sensing insertion of a refueling pump nozzle into the fill tube, such as by actuation of a switch on a filler door in the fill tube. These methods require hardware located outside of the fuel tank including the sensors switches and appropriate wiring from the sensor or switches to the control mechanism. Additionally, fuel fill caps can be lost or the vehicle may be operated with the fill cap removed, the fill door may become stuck in an open position at least temporarily, and the integrity of the wires and their connections may become compromised.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A valve assembly includes a housing having a valve seat defining at least part of a vent passage, a pressure responsive member carried by the housing and defining at least part of a pressure chamber, and a valve carried by the housing and having a closure movable relative to the valve seat between an open position permitting fluid flow through the vent passage and a closed position at least substantially restricting fluid flow through the vent passage. The closure is moved by the pressure responsive member in response to changes in pressure in the pressure chamber. A control passage communicates at one end with a pressure source and at its other end with the pressure chamber and an electrically operated valve is movable from a first position permitting a pressure signal to develop within the pressure chamber and a second position permitting pressure within the pressure chamber to vent.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In one presently preferred implementation, the pressure responsive member is a flexible diaphragm and the pressure chamber is in communication with the interior of the fuel tank in the area normally containing fuel vapor. Changes in the pressure within the fuel tank, such as may be caused by initiation of a refueling event wherein fuel vapor is rapidly displaced by liquid fuel being added to the fuel tank, create an increased pressure in the pressure chamber that acts to displace the diaphragm to open the valve closure and permit the fuel vapor to rapidly vent from the fuel tank. This movement of the diaphragm can be sensed such as by a sensor or switch, to provide an indication that a refueling event is taking place. The electrically operated valve can be actuated to cause a reduction in pressure in the pressure chamber to thereby cause a subsequent movement of the diaphragm that preferably closes the valve closure to at least substantially restrict fluid flow through the vent passage. In traditional automotive fuel systems, the pressure within the fuel tank may then rapidly rise causing liquid fuel to back up or fill a fill tube and cause an automatic shut off a refueling pump nozzle, as is generally known in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Accordingly, in this implementation, the refueling event can be sensed by movement of the diaphragm due to an increase in tank pressure acting on the diaphragm and the refueling even can be terminated by actuation of the electrically operated valve which moves the valve closure onto the valve seat and may also return the diaphragm to its unflexed or starting position.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to one presently preferred aspect of the present invention, a method of sensing a refueling event is provided. The method includes the steps of disposing a pressure responsive member in communication with a fuel tank so that the pressure responsive member is movable in response to a pressure in the fuel tank above a threshold pressure, sensing movement of the pressure responsive member, providing a signal in response to movement of the pressure responsive member, and receiving the signal to indicate the occurrence of a refueling event.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Objects, features and advantages of at least some presently preferred embodiments of the present invention include providing accurate indication of a refueling event, sensing a refueling event with in-tank components, facilitating fuel tank pressure and leak testing, facilitating electronic fill level control, providing a relatively rapid venting of fuel from the fuel tank during a refueling event, and providing a valve assembly that is of a relatively simple design, and economical manufacture and assembly, and has a long and useful in-service life.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">These and other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will be apparent from the following detailed description of the preferred embodiments and best mode, appended claims and accompanying drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a fragmentary sectional view of a valve assembly according to one presently preferred embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a fragmentary sectional view of the valve assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> showing the valve in a closed position;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a somewhat diagrammatic sectional view of a valve assembly according to an alternate embodiment of the present invention illustrating the valve in its closed position;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrating the valve assembly in its open position such as during a refueling event in a fuel tank;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a view like <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref> illustrating the valve assembly in its closed position to cause a shut off in a refueling event; and</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrating a roll over valve used in combination with the valve assembly in a closed position.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Referring in more detail to the drawings, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-4</figref> illustrate one presently preferred embodiment of a valve assembly <b>10</b> such as for a vehicle fuel system that includes a refueling sensor to determine when fuel is being added to a fuel tank <b>12</b> of the fuel system. The assembly <b>10</b> includes a vent valve <b>14</b> that selectively opens a vent outlet <b>16</b> to permit fuel vapor within the fuel tank <b>12</b> to be vented from the fuel tank <b>12</b>, such as to a fuel vapor canister <b>18</b> or other fuel vapor receiver. The valve <b>14</b> is preferably coupled to a pressure responsive member <b>20</b>, such as a flexible diaphragm, and is movable in response to a pressure signal applied to the pressure responsive member <b>20</b>. Desirably, an electronic valve <b>22</b> controls application of a pressure signal to the pressure responsive member <b>20</b> to thereby control movement of the pressure responsive member <b>20</b> and hence, of the valve <b>14</b>. A sensor, switch or other device may be associated with the valve <b>14</b> or the pressure responsive member <b>20</b> so that movement of one or both of them can be detected at least in part to determine when fuel is being added to the fuel tank.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The electronic valve <b>22</b> may also be operable to control movement of the valve <b>14</b>, such as to close the valve and prevent further venting of the fuel tank. With the valve <b>14</b> closed during a refueling event, the pressure within the fuel tank <b>12</b> will rise to cause a termination of the refueling event such as by causing liquid fuel to actuate an automatic shut-off of a refueling pump nozzle. Accordingly, in one presently preferred implementation the system both determines the occurrence of a refueling event, and can control termination of the refueling event to control the maximum fill level achieved during refueling, among other things.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The valve assembly <b>14</b> includes a valve body <b>24</b> having a radially outwardly extending flange <b>26</b> adapted to overlie and be sealed or otherwise connected to a wall <b>28</b> of a fuel tank <b>12</b>. A depending, cylindrical sidewall <b>30</b> extends generally axially from the flange <b>26</b> and preferably is adapted to be disposed within an interior volume <b>32</b> of the fuel tank <b>12</b>. The sidewall <b>30</b> preferably terminates at a bottom wall <b>34</b> spaced axially from the flange <b>26</b> and defining at least part of a vent chamber <b>36</b>. The sidewall <b>30</b> preferably includes one or more openings <b>38</b> through which vapor may enter the vent chamber <b>36</b> from the fuel tank <b>12</b>. The valve body <b>24</b> and related components preferably define a convoluted or serpentine path to permit gaseous fluid flow but greatly inhibit or prevent liquid fuel from flowing through the vent outlet <b>16</b>. The bottom wall <b>34</b> preferably has one or more openings <b>40</b> therethrough to permit any liquid fuel which accumulates or finds its way into the vent chamber <b>36</b> to drain back into the fuel tank <b>12</b>. An appropriate valve or valves (not shown) may be employed to control the fluid flow through the openings <b>40</b>, as desired. Axially spaced from the bottom wall <b>34</b>, a valve seat <b>42</b> is defined by the valve body <b>24</b>. The valve seat <b>42</b> defines part of a vent passage <b>44</b> that is in communication with a vent outlet <b>16</b> preferably also defined by the body <b>24</b> and preferably including a nipple or stem <b>47</b> adapted to receive a fluid conduit <b>45</b> leading to the fuel vapor canister <b>18</b> or other fuel vapor receiver.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The valve body <b>24</b> may also include a cylindrical projection <b>46</b> extending generally axially from the flange <b>26</b> and defining at least a portion of the vent passage <b>44</b>. A cover <b>48</b> is preferably secured to the valve body <b>24</b>, and preferably is secured in the area of or onto the projection <b>46</b>. A pressure responsive member, such as a flexible diaphragm <b>20</b> is preferably carried by the valve <b>14</b> and may have its periphery trapped between the valve body <b>24</b> and the cover <b>48</b>. On one side, the diaphragm <b>20</b> defines part of a pressure chamber <b>50</b> with the cover <b>48</b>, and on its other side, the diaphragm <b>20</b> preferably defines part of the vent passage <b>44</b>. A vent <b>52</b> is preferably provided through the diaphragm <b>20</b> providing a controlled flow rate of fluid between the pressure chamber <b>50</b> and vent passage <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A secondary vent passage <b>54</b> communicates with the interior <b>32</b> of the fuel tank <b>12</b> at one end and with the pressure chamber <b>50</b> at its other end. The secondary vent passage <b>54</b> may also be communicated with the fuel vapor canister <b>18</b> or other fuel vapor receiver, through a valve seat <b>56</b> that is selectively closed by a valve head <b>58</b> of the electrically actuated valve <b>22</b>. The valve head <b>58</b> is preferably movable between a closed position and an open position and preferably is electrically operated, such as by a solenoid <b>60</b>. As such, the valve head <b>58</b> preferably is carried by a plunger <b>62</b> of the solenoid valve. In its closed position, the valve head <b>58</b> is generally engaged with the valve seat <b>56</b> and prevents fluid flow from the secondary vent passage <b>54</b> to the vapor canister <b>18</b>. In its open position, the valve head <b>16</b> is preferably removed from the valve seat <b>56</b> and permits fluid flow between the vapor canister <b>18</b> and both the secondary vent passage <b>54</b> and the pressure chamber <b>50</b> through the valve seat <b>46</b>. A second valve <b>64</b> may selectively close the secondary vent passage <b>54</b>, if desired. In the presently preferred implementation, a so-called rollover vent valve <b>64</b> is disposed within a depending skirt <b>66</b> preferably carried by or formed in the valve body <b>24</b>. The rollover valve <b>64</b> is operable to close the secondary vent passage <b>54</b> when the valve <b>14</b> is inclined more than a threshold amount, such as may occur during a rollover or inversion of a vehicle in which the valve <b>14</b> is used. As best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the rollover valve <b>64</b> is preferably also responsive to the level of liquid fuel in the fuel tank <b>12</b> and preferably closes the secondary vent passage <b>54</b> in the presence of liquid fuel above a threshold level and acting on the rollover valve <b>64</b>. The valve <b>64</b> may include a float <b>68</b> buoyant in liquid fuel and may have a closure <b>70</b> integral with or carried by the float <b>68</b> to engage its valve seat <b>72</b>. The float <b>68</b> may also be yieldably biased towards its closed position by a spring <b>74</b>, as is known generally in the art, and the spring <b>74</b> may assist in maintaining the valve <b>64</b> closed even when it is immersed in liquid fuel during a vehicle rollover event.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The main vent valve <b>14</b> is carried by the valve body <b>24</b> and is movable between open and closed positions to control at least in part the fluid flow through the valve seat <b>42</b> and vent outlet <b>16</b>. The valve <b>14</b> preferably includes a closure or valve head <b>82</b> movable to a closed position wherein it engages and closes the valve seat <b>42</b> to prevent fluid flow therethrough. The valve head <b>82</b> preferably is biased to its closed position by a spring <b>84</b> or other biasing member disposed between the valve head <b>82</b> and the bottom wall <b>34</b> so that the valve <b>14</b> is normally closed. The valve head <b>82</b> is also movable to an open position spaced from the valve seat <b>42</b> to permit fluid flow therethrough. The valve head <b>82</b> is preferably coupled to a valve stem <b>86</b> that in turn is coupled to or associated with the diaphragm <b>20</b> so that movement of the diaphragm <b>20</b> causes a corresponding movement of the valve head <b>82</b> relative to the valve seat at least until the valve head <b>82</b> engages the valve seat <b>42</b>. Accordingly, movement of the valve head <b>82</b> between its closed and open positions is controlled at least in part by the effect of gravity on the diaphragm <b>20</b>, valve stem <b>86</b> and valve head <b>82</b>, the pressure within the pressure chamber <b>50</b>, the pressure within the fuel tank <b>12</b>, the pressure within the vent passage <b>44</b>, the resistance to deflection or movement of the diaphragm <b>20</b>, and the force of the spring <b>84</b> acting on the valve head <b>82</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">A sensor <b>90</b>, switch or other mechanism is preferably associated with at least one of the diaphragm <b>20</b> and valve <b>14</b> to determine movement or at least one position of the diaphragm <b>20</b> and/or the valve <b>14</b>. The mechanism <b>90</b> may include a base <b>92</b> for example including a reed switch and a magnet <b>94</b>, for example, with the magnet <b>94</b> coupled to or carried by the diaphragm <b>20</b> and the base or reed switch <b>92</b> carried by the cover <b>48</b>, although other switches or sensors could be used including an optical sensor or switch, a magnet and a hall device, or simple electrical contacts movable between open and closed positions, by way of examples without limitation. In the example of a switch, the switch can be arranged to change state as the valve <b>14</b> moves from one position to another.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In operation, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the valve head <b>82</b> is biased to its closed position at least substantially preventing fluid flow through the valve seat <b>42</b> and to the vent outlet <b>16</b>. The electronic valve <b>22</b> may also be in its closed position with the valve head <b>58</b> closed on its valve seat <b>56</b> and preventing significant venting of the fuel tank <b>12</b> through the secondary vent passage <b>54</b>. Minimal venting may occur through the secondary vent passage <b>54</b> by way of the pressure chamber <b>50</b> and vent opening <b>52</b>. Desirably, the pressure within the fuel tank <b>12</b> during normal vehicle operating conditions is insufficient to significantly move the valve head <b>82</b> relative to the valve seat <b>42</b> so that the valve head <b>82</b> remains generally closed.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">When liquid fuel is added to the fuel tank <b>12</b> during a refueling event, a rapid rise in pressure within the tank <b>12</b> occurs due to the relatively rapid displacement of gaseous phase fluids from the fuel tank <b>12</b>. This rise in pressure is communicated to the pressure chamber <b>50</b> by way of the secondary vent passage <b>54</b> and causes the diaphragm <b>20</b> and valve head <b>82</b> to move to their second and open positions, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. This permits a relatively rapid fluid flow rate through the valve seat <b>42</b> and vent outlet <b>16</b> providing a desired venting of the fuel tank <b>12</b> during the refueling event. Movement of the diaphragm <b>20</b> can be detected by a change in state of the switch, sensor or other mechanism <b>90</b>, such as by movement of the magnet <b>94</b> away from the reed switch <b>92</b> in the illustrated embodiment. This, in turn, can be relayed to a controller to indicate the occurrence of the refueling event, and this information may be relayed to other vehicle systems or assemblies as needed. For example, current fuel system regulations require onboard diagnostic testing, such as fuel tank leak testing, and knowledge of a refueling event is important to proper tank leak testing, among other things. Knowledge of a refueling event is also desirable to facilitate electronic fill level control, venting schemes, and/or other fuel system or vehicle schemes or control functions.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The maximum desired fuel level within the fuel tank <b>12</b> can be controlled electronically with this valve assembly <b>14</b>. As best shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, at or near a desired maximum fill level within the fuel tank <b>12</b>, the electronic valve <b>22</b> can be actuated to move its valve head <b>58</b> off its valve seat <b>56</b> to thereby communicate the pressure chamber <b>50</b> and secondary vent passage <b>54</b> with the vapor canister <b>18</b>. Preferably, the flow rate between the pressure chamber <b>50</b> and secondary vent passage <b>54</b> is such that the pressure within the pressure chamber <b>50</b> is less than that required to move or hold the valve head <b>82</b> off of the valve seat <b>42</b> so that the valve head <b>82</b> closes on the valve seat <b>42</b> and prevents significant further venting of the fuel tank <b>12</b> through the main valve seat <b>42</b>. The flow rate through the secondary vent passage <b>54</b> is preferably less than the flow rate through the main valve seat <b>42</b> so that the pressure within the fuel tank <b>12</b> rises sufficiently when the main valve head <b>82</b> is closed to cause an automatic shutoff of a refueling pump nozzle and thereby terminate the refueling event.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">So-called “trickle filling” or “rounding-up” of the fuel tank <b>12</b> can be permitted by closing the valve seat <b>56</b> with the electronic valve <b>22</b> to permit repressurization of the pressure chamber <b>50</b> which opens the valve head <b>82</b> and permits additional venting of fuel vapor from the fuel tank <b>12</b>. Subsequent shutoffs or refueling event terminations can be achieved by again opening the electronic valve <b>22</b> to reduce the pressure within the pressure chamber <b>50</b> and cause the valve head <b>82</b> to close on the valve seat <b>42</b> as previously described.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">An alternate embodiment valve assembly <b>100</b> and refueling event monitor is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref>. This valve assembly <b>100</b> includes a valve body <b>102</b> adapted to be mounted to a vehicle fuel tank <b>12</b> and defining a vent chamber <b>104</b> in communication with the interior <b>32</b> of the fuel tank <b>12</b> and separated from a second chamber <b>106</b> by a main vent valve <b>108</b> and associated valve seat <b>109</b>. The second chamber <b>106</b> communicates or defines in part a vent passage <b>110</b> leading to a vent outlet <b>16</b> through which fuel vapor exits the valve <b>100</b> and is preferably directed to a fuel vapor canister <b>18</b> through a suitable conduit.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The main vent valve <b>108</b> preferably includes a valve stem or holder <b>112</b> that carries a closure or valve head <b>114</b> and is operably associated with a pressure responsive member, such as a flexible diaphragm <b>116</b>, as generally set forth with regard to the first embodiment valve assembly <b>10</b>. One end of the valve holder <b>112</b> is maintained generally adjacent to the diaphragm <b>116</b> by a spring <b>118</b> disposed around a projection <b>120</b> on a valve body upper wall <b>122</b> and against a radially outwardly extending flange <b>124</b> of the holder <b>112</b>. The flange <b>124</b> may have a generally planar surface that may directly engage or be connected to the diaphragm <b>116</b>. The holder <b>112</b> may also be indirectly engaged or associated with the diaphragm <b>116</b>, as desired. The valve head <b>114</b>, holder <b>112</b>, and diaphragm <b>116</b> preferably include aligned bores <b>126</b>, <b>128</b>, <b>130</b>, respectively, that define a secondary vent passage <b>132</b> through which the vent chamber <b>104</b> is selectively communicated with a pressure chamber <b>134</b> defined in part by the diaphragm <b>116</b> on its face opposite the valve holder <b>112</b> and a cover <b>135</b> that traps the diaphragm <b>116</b> against the valve body <b>102</b>. A vent <b>136</b> is provided downstream of the main valve head <b>114</b>, and may be formed in the valve holder <b>112</b> or through the diaphragm <b>116</b> as desired. The vent <b>136</b> communicates the pressure chamber <b>134</b> with the vent outlet <b>16</b> and preferably is open at all times to permit a controlled flow rate of fluid therethrough. The valve head <b>114</b> includes a tubular boss with a radially outwardly extending flange <b>138</b> and may be press-fit into the bore <b>128</b> in the holder <b>112</b> and retained therein by a radially inwardly extending flange <b>140</b> of the holder <b>112</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">An electrically operated valve, such as a solenoid valve <b>142</b>, includes a plunger <b>144</b> carried for reciprocation by a solenoid valve body <b>146</b> between first and second positions. In its first position, a valve head <b>148</b> disposed at one end of the plunger <b>144</b> is spaced from a valve seat <b>150</b> surrounding the through bore <b>126</b> in the valve head <b>114</b> to permit fluid flow therethrough. In its second position, the valve head <b>148</b> engages the valve seat <b>150</b> to prevent or at least substantially restrict fluid flow through the bore <b>126</b> in the valve head <b>114</b>. Accordingly, when the solenoid valve <b>142</b> is in its second position the valve head at least substantially prevents communication between the vent chamber <b>104</b> and the pressure chamber <b>134</b>. A clip <b>152</b> coupled to the plunger <b>144</b> engages one side of the valve head <b>114</b> to limit movement of the plunger <b>144</b> away from the solenoid valve body <b>146</b> but does not significantly inhibit fluid flow through the secondary vent passage <b>132</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In this embodiment, during normal operation wherein the internal fuel tank pressure is below a threshold value, the main vent valve head <b>114</b> is closed on its valve seat <b>109</b> closing the main vent outlet and at least substantially restricting the venting of fuel vapor from the fuel tank <b>12</b>. Nominal or controlled venting of the tank <b>12</b> may occur through the secondary vent passage that includes the aligned bores <b>126</b>, <b>128</b>, <b>130</b> in the valve head <b>114</b>, valve holder <b>112</b> and diaphragm <b>116</b>, and through the vent <b>136</b>, which in the illustrated embodiment, is formed in the valve holder <b>112</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">During a refueling event, the pressure within the fuel tank <b>12</b> increases relatively rapidly as liquid fuel is added to the tank at a relatively high flow rate and thereby displaces fuel vapor at a relatively high flow rate. Displaced vapor flows through the secondary vent passage <b>132</b> into the pressure chamber <b>134</b> and acts on and displaces the diaphragm <b>116</b> which displaces the valve holder <b>112</b> and valve head <b>114</b> against the bias of the spring <b>118</b> to move the valve head <b>114</b> to its open position. In this position, fuel vapor can vent at a relatively rapid rate through the main valve seat <b>109</b> and vent outlet <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The refueling event can be sensed through an appropriate switch, sensor and/or other mechanism <b>90</b> responsive to movement of the diaphragm <b>116</b> or other valve component, as described with reference to the first embodiment vent valve <b>10</b>. Also, movement of the solenoid plunger <b>144</b> can be detected by monitoring the position of the plunger <b>144</b> or the excitation of a solenoid wire coil of the solenoid valve <b>142</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">To terminate the refueling event, the solenoid valve <b>142</b> can be moved to its second position closing the valve head <b>148</b> on its valve seat <b>150</b> and thereby preventing or substantially restricting communication between the vent chamber <b>104</b> and the pressure chamber <b>134</b>. The fuel vapor within the pressure chamber <b>134</b> vents through the vent opening <b>136</b>, and the pressure within the pressure chamber <b>134</b> decreases allowing the main valve head <b>114</b> to return to its closed position under the force of the spring <b>118</b> to thereby prevent further venting of fuel vapor from the fuel tank <b>12</b>. This will cause the pressure within the fuel tank <b>12</b> to rise relatively rapidly as the refueling event continues until an automatic shutoff of a refueling pump nozzle occurs to terminate the refueling event. In addition to the force of the spring <b>118</b>, the main valve head <b>114</b> may be returned to its closed position with the force of the solenoid valve <b>142</b> it is moved to its second position. Trickle fill or so-called roundup filling of the fuel tank <b>12</b> can be permitted by moving the solenoid valve <b>142</b> to its first position permitting tank pressure to be applied to the diaphragm <b>116</b> from within the pressure chamber <b>134</b>, thereby reopening the main vent valve <b>108</b> and permit further filling of the fuel tank <b>12</b>. Subsequent refueling event terminations can be accomplished in the same manner previously described.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Accordingly, in this embodiment of the valve assembly <b>100</b> the refueling event can be sensed and determined by monitoring the solenoid valve <b>142</b>, or with an appropriate switch or sensor <b>90</b>. Also, the assembly <b>100</b> can be relatively compact with the secondary vent passage <b>132</b> formed in a portion of the main vent valve <b>108</b> that is not used for the primary fuel vapor venting. Desirably, the refueling event sensing and vapor venting can occur within a single valve assembly <b>100</b> and entirely within or closely adjacent to the fuel tank <b>12</b>. Desirably, external mechanisms to sense or to terminate the refueling event are not needed. And wiring from fill cap or fill tube sensors are not needed. Further, the increase in pressure in the fuel tank associated with a refueling event is sensed and responded to mechanically, by the pressure responsive member. This avoids the need for continuous or frequent monitoring of the fuel tank pressure and for the need for a fuel tank pressure monitor (such as an OBD-II tank pressure sensor) to respond to a positive pressure of the magnitude associated with a refueling event.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">While certain preferred embodiments have been shown and described, persons of ordinary skill in this art will readily recognize that the preceding description has been set forth in terms of description rather than limitation, and that various modifications and substitutions can be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. By way of example without limitation, while the main vent valve <b>14</b>, <b>108</b> in both described embodiments has been set forth as normally closed, it may be normally open, and for example, further opened or moved by the increase in pressure associated with a refueling event. Of course, still other modifications and substitutions can be made. The invention is defined by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A vent valve for a fuel tank of a vehicle, comprising:
<claim-text>a housing having a valve seat defining at least part of a vent passage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pressure responsive member carried by the housing and defining at least part of a pressure chamber;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a valve carried by the housing and having a closure movable relative to the valve seat between an open position permitting fluid flow through the vent passage and a closed position at least substantially restricting fluid flow through the vent passage, the closure being moved by the pressure responsive member in response to changes in pressure in the pressure chamber;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control passage communicating the pressure chamber with the interior of the fuel tank; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a sensor associated with at least one of the pressure responsive member and the valve, the sensor being responsive to a change in position of at least one of the pressure responsive member and the valve and operable to send an electric signal in response to said change in position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> which also comprises an electrically operated valve movable from a first position permitting a pressure signal to develop within the pressure chamber and a second position permitting pressure within the pressure chamber to vent.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the pressure responsive member is a diaphragm that moves the valve in response to a change in pressure in the pressure chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the diaphragm moves the closure to its open position in response to a pressure in the pressure chamber above a threshold value.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the valve is yieldably biased to position the closure in its closed position when the biasing force is greater than the force on the valve from the diaphragm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the electrically operated valve moves the closure to its closed position when the electrically operated valve moves to its second position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the electrically operated valve includes a solenoid and a plunger movable between first and second positions by the solenoid and operably associated with the valve to move the valve as the plunger is moved to its second position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> which also comprises a valve seat defining at least part of said control passage and wherein said electrically operated valve selectively closes the valve seat to prevent fluid flow through the valve seat.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein said electrically operated valve closes the valve seat to permit an increased pressure to develop in the pressure chamber and opens the valve seat to dissipate pressure from the pressure chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the valve seat is disposed between the pressure chamber and a vent and when the valve seat is open it communicates the pressure chamber with the vent.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the vent includes a fuel vapor canister.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein said electrically operated valve permits fluid flow into the pressure chamber to permit an increased pressure to develop in the pressure chamber, and closes the valve seat to dissipate pressure from the pressure chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the valve seat is disposed between the pressure source and pressure chamber.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> which also includes a vent communicating with the pressure chamber downstream of the valve seat.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the sensor includes a switch having first and second states and being switched between these states by movement of at least one of the pressure responsive member and the valve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the switch includes a magnet and a base and the proximity of the magnet to the base determines the state of the switch.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the switch includes a pair of electrical contacts with at least one of the electrical contacts being movable relative to the other to selectively engage the contacts in response to movement of at least one of the pressure responsive member and the valve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The valve of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> which also comprises a sensor responsive to movement of the plunger.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method of sensing a refueling event in a fuel tank, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>disposing a pressure responsive member in communication with the interior of a fuel tank so that the pressure responsive member is exposed to fuel vapor in the fuel tank and is movable in response to a pressure in the fuel tank above a threshold pressure;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a vent valve communicating with the fuel tank and movable to open and closed states, the vent valve being normally closed and moved to its open state by the pressure responsive member when the pressure in the fuel tank is above the threshold pressure;</claim-text>
<claim-text>sensing movement of the pressure responsive member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing an electric signal in response to movement of the pressure responsive member to open the vent valve; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving said electric signal to indicate the occurrence of a refueling event as a function of increased pressure in the fuel tank such as occurs due to the displacement of fuel vapor in the tank by liquid fuel being added to the fuel tank.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> which also comprises the step of relieving the pressure signal acting on the pressure responsive member to permit the pressure responsive member to return to its closed position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A method of sensing a refueling event in a fuel tank for a vehicle, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>providing a vent valve in fluid communication with the interior of a fuel tank and movable to open and closed states;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a pressure responsive member in fluid communication with the interior of the fuel tank and movable to change the state of the vent valve in response to a pressure of fuel vapor in the fuel tank above a threshold pressure;</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing an electric sensor producing an electric signal in response to movement of at least one of the vent valve and the pressure responsive member to change the state of the vent valve; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving the electric signal to indicate the occurrence of a refueling event as a function of an increase in pressure of fuel vapor in the fuel tank to above the threshold pressure such as occurs in the fuel tank by liquid fuel being added to the fuel tank.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref> which also comprises when the pressure in the fuel tank is above the threshold pressure, relieving the pressure acting on the pressure responsive member to below the threshold pressure to change the state of the vent valve.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref> wherein the vent valve is normally in its closed state and is moved by the pressure responsive member to its open state when the pressure in the fuel tank rises above the threshold pressure due to liquid fuel being added to the fuel tank.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
