<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296938-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296938</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11440936</doc-number>
<date>20060525</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>6</main-group>
<subgroup>36</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>6</main-group>
<subgroup>38</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 92</main-classification>
<further-classification>385 88</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 94</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 76</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 77</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 78</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 81</further-classification>
<further-classification>385 84</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Fiber node with active optical to RF interface connector</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4547039</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Caron et al.</name>
<date>19851000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 88</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4632507</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mignien et al.</name>
<date>19861200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385135</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4744626</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mery</name>
<date>19880500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 90</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5515469</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Zarem et al.</name>
<date>19960500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 92</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6065882</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Roller et al.</name>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 92</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0180012</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Deane et al.</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 92</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>AMP drawing No. 502585 (1 sheet).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Zarlink Semiconductor's Drawing No. 101514 (1 sheet).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>26</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>385 92</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>15</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>23</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Shapson</last-name>
<first-name>Jay F.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Englishtown</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Romerein</last-name>
<first-name>Robert L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Pontypool</city>
<country>CA</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CA</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CA</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Watov &amp; Kipnes, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Watov</last-name>
<first-name>Kenneth</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Extreme Broadband Engineering, LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Englishtown</city>
<state>NJ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Font</last-name>
<first-name>Frank G.</first-name>
<department>2883</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Lepisto</last-name>
<first-name>Ryan</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An optical to RF interface connector has a cellular housing that has a back most portion configured for press fitting into a hole of the housing of an electro-optical apparatus, with the hole and back most portion of the shell being key to one another to insure proper orientation of the connector. The press fitting is further configured for providing both an RF seal, and moisture seal. The frontmost portion of the connector shell is configured for securely coupling to an optical interface male connector that is attached to an end of a fiber optic cable. The innermost portion of a connector shell is further configured for receiving and retaining therein either a auto detector or light detecting device for converting optical signals received from the fiber optic cable into electrical signals for processing, or is light transmitting device for converting electrical signals into optical signals for transmission over the associated fiber optic cable. A light mark is provided between within the connector shell between the light detecting transmitting device and a optical fiber terminating end of the male connector for permitting the passage of optical signals therebetween. The back most portion of the connecter shell is further configured for receiving the light detecting or transmitting device in an augmentation associated with the key position of the back most portion of press fit into the electro optical apparatus housing, for insuring that electrical leads of the light transmitting or light receiving device do not interfere with one another in being connected either to a printed circuit board or other termination within the housing of the associated apparatus.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="121.41mm" wi="135.64mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="133.60mm" wi="136.14mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="216.49mm" wi="128.95mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="223.86mm" wi="90.09mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="141.22mm" wi="139.87mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="209.63mm" wi="99.23mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="206.59mm" wi="84.07mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="127.00mm" wi="152.48mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="205.74mm" wi="162.81mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296938-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="169.93mm" wi="161.04mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="197.53mm" wi="152.57mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296938-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="206.16mm" wi="165.02mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296938-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="195.07mm" wi="118.96mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296938-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00013" num="00013">
<img id="EMI-D00013" he="155.28mm" wi="131.83mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296938-20071120-D00013.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00014" num="00014">
<img id="EMI-D00014" he="207.35mm" wi="137.33mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00014.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00015" num="00015">
<img id="EMI-D00015" he="223.01mm" wi="135.47mm" file="US07296938-20071120-D00015.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to electrical and RF connectors, and more specifically relates to both connectors for use at an interface between the end of a fiber optic cable and a photodetector or a light transmitting device, or in the former converting light from the cable into an electrical signal, and for the latter converting an electrical signal into an optical signal for transmission over the fiber optic cable, and also relates to a fiber node including such connectors.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Optical transmission of television and data signals has been rapidly expanded for use in television, and telecommunication systems. In cable television systems, fiber optic cable is now being employed in many systems from the point of transmission of television and data signals to the subscriber's premises. The use of coaxial cable for television and telecommunication systems is rapidly being replaced by the use of fiber optic cables because optical signals travel greater distances and require less repeater amplification than electrical signals transmitted via coaxial cable. Fiber optic signal distribution systems are also immune to electromagnetic interference either as ingress or egress.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">As one example of usage of fiber optic cables in cable television systems, such cables consist of numerous single optical fibers, each capable of carrying a full spectrum of television and data information services. It is possible to allocate each fiber in a fiber optic cable at the subscriber end of a distribution system to an individual subscriber. Typically, a male connector is attached to the end of each fiber to enable the fibers to be connected to terminal equipment in a subscriber's home or business. The terminal equipment permits bi-directional communication between a subscriber and the cable television provider. In this example, the terminal equipment converts optical signals from the provider into electrical radio frequency signals for use by the subscriber, and also converts the electrical signals generated by the subscriber or the subscriber's equipment into optical signals for transmission over the optical cable to the provider.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Known terminal equipment typically employs an optical to RF interface connector configured for direct attachment to a printed circuit board within the housing of the terminal equipment. The fiber optic cable at the subscriber's end typically has a male connector attached to it, whereby the connector in a portion of the associated fiber optic cable must be passed through a hole in the housing of the terminal equipment, and plugged into the female optical to RF interface connector mounted on the printed circuit board. Interconnecting the terminal end of a fiber optic cable to a subscriber's terminal equipment is time consuming, and sometimes involves coiling of the fiber optic cable within the housing of the terminal equipment, that may attenuate the optical signal, or in a worse case may interrupt the signal, all of which increases the installation time to insure proper operation. The present inventors recognize that there is a need in the art for improved optical to RF interface connectors and connection systems.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">One embodiment of the invention is an optical to RF interface connector that includes a housing or shell having a back portion configured for retaining a light detector device or light/laser transmitter device, and a front portion configured for receiving and securing to a terminating connector mounted on an end of a fiber optic cable, for permitting optical signals to pass between the fiber optic cable and the light detector or light/laser transmitter. The housing or shell is further configured for pressing a back portion into the housing of an associated electrical device. The electrical leads of the light detecting or light transmitting device protrude from the back portion of the shell in a manner facilitating connection of the leads to a printed circuit board located within the housing of the associated electrical device. In another embodiment of the invention, at least two of the inventive optical to RF interface connectors are press fit into the housing of a fiber node or optical to RF media conversion unit, whereby one of the connectors retains a light transmitter for optically transmitting broadband signals back to the optical cable system of a cable television provider, whereas the other connector retains a light detecting device for the reception of broadband signals from the fiber optic cable as transmitted from the cable system provider. In yet another embodiment of the invention, the fiber node or bi-directional RF/optical converter includes means for electrically operating the light transmitting device to convert electrical signals to optical signals for transmission through the fiber optic cable connected to the optical to RF interface output connector, and means for operating the light detecting device to convert optical signals from a fiber optic cable connected to the optical to RF interface input connector into electrical signals, whereby a diplex filter is used to bi-directionally couple electrical output and input signals between a bi-directional RF connector of the converter, and the means for operating the light transmitting device, and means for operating the light detecting or receiving device, respectively.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Various embodiments of the present invention are described below with reference to the drawings, in which like items are identified by the same reference designation, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a front portion of an optical to RF interface connector for one embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a front elevational view of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a back elevational view of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a bottom plan view of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a top plan view of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a back portion of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, for a first embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a back portion of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, for a second embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a back portion of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, for a third embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a pictorial view looking toward the front of a known optical receiving or electrical transmitting device packaged in either one of the TO-18, TO-46, or TO-52 “top hat” packaging configuration;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8A</figref> shows a pictorial view looking toward the front or “top hat” end of TO-56 packaging configuration for a known optical transmitting or receiving device;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8B</figref> shows a bottom view (absent the electrical leads) of the packaging configuration of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8A</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows a longitudinal cross-sectional view taken along <b>9</b>-<b>9</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, for one embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> shows a top view of a fiber node or optical to RF media conversion device incorporating at least two of the connectors of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, for another embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows a pictorial view looking toward the back of the device of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, showing the mounting of the optical to RF interface connectors;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> shows a pictorial view looking toward the front of the device of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> shows a bottom plan view of the device of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> shows a block schematic diagram of the electronic circuitry for the device of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> shows a pictorial view looking toward a front portion of an optical to RF interface connector for a second embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a back portion of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a front portion of an optical to RF interface connector for a third embodiment of the invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a back portion of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> for the third embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a front portion of a female optical to RF interface connector for mating with a male ST fiber optical cable termination connector for an alternative embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 20</figref> is a pictorial view looking toward a rear portion of the connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a pictorial view looking toward the front left side of the present connector <b>2</b> is shown for a first embodiment of the invention. In this embodiment, the female connector is configured for receiving an ST style male connector, the latter being a male fiber optic cable connector that is known in the art. The protrusions <b>4</b> and an open slot <b>6</b> provide for the bayonet interlocking configuration with the male ST connector at the end of a fiber optic cable (not shown). The protrusions <b>4</b> and open slot <b>6</b> are formed in a frontmost cylindrical segment <b>8</b>, having a front face <b>3</b> with a beveled inside edge <b>5</b>, and a hole <b>18</b>, as shown. The inside diameter of hole <b>18</b> of the initial portion of the cylindrical segment <b>8</b> is dimensioned for snugly receiving the outermost portion of the male ST connector (not shown) to be received by the connector <b>2</b>. As will be described in greater detail below, a ferrule located at the frontmost portion of the standard ST male optical fiber connector is received in hole <b>18</b> of connector <b>2</b>. The hole <b>18</b> has a back face <b>10</b>, that has a centrally located hole <b>20</b>. The cylindrical segment <b>8</b> terminates to a back cylindrical segment <b>12</b> that includes a flat portion <b>14</b> for providing a D-configuration. In the preferred embodiment, segment <b>12</b>, is knurled on its cylindrical portion, as shown. The back cylindrical segment <b>12</b> has a larger outside diameter than a frontmost cylindrical segment <b>8</b> of connector <b>2</b>, as shown. The back circumferential edge <b>16</b> is beveled, with the back cylindrical segment <b>12</b> being otherwise configured for press fitting into a D-hole (not shown) of the housing of an electrical optical device. Use of the D-hole configuration, along with the flattened portion <b>14</b> of segment <b>12</b>, insures that the connector <b>2</b> is properly oriented when press fit into the housing, to insure that the leads of an electrical optical device retained in the segment <b>12</b> are optimally aligned to facilitate connection of the leads from the device (not shown) to a printed circuit board or other electrical termination within the housing (not shown) of the electro-optical device (not shown). This configuration will be discussed in greater detail below.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">A front elevational view of the present connector <b>2</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. As previously explained, the hole <b>18</b> in the frontmost segment <b>8</b> receives a portion of the male ST connector, and the hole <b>20</b> of the reduced inside diameter segment <b>10</b> is sized to receive the center ferrule of the male ST connector (not shown). Note that the front edge of the hole <b>20</b> includes a beveled surface <b>21</b> proximate its interface with the backwall <b>10</b> of hole <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a back elevational view of the connector <b>2</b> is shown. A beveled edge <b>22</b> is provided on a back portion or edge of the cylindrical segment <b>12</b>, as previously mentioned. Proceeding inward from the beveled edge <b>22</b>, a flat band like circular face or portion <b>24</b> is shown, followed by a hole <b>26</b>, followed by a flat ring-like portion <b>28</b> (back face of hole <b>26</b>), followed by countersunk hole <b>30</b> having a cylindrical sidewall <b>27</b> defining the sides thereof, and a backwall <b>29</b>, terminating to the center hole <b>20</b> which extends through to the reduced inside segment <b>10</b> in the frontmost portion or segment <b>8</b>. As will be shown in greater detail below, the countersunk hole <b>30</b>, and its backwall <b>28</b> are configured for receiving and press fitting therein an electro-optical device having a top-hat configuration, as will be described in greater detail below. Bottom and top plan views of the connector <b>2</b> are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">A pictorial view looking toward the back of the connector <b>2</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, for one embodiment of the invention. In another embodiment of the invention, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, a slotway <b>32</b> is included in a portion of a sidewall <b>23</b> of the countersunk hole <b>26</b> for insuring proper alignment of an optical device to be press fitted therein to, such as TO-18, TO-46, and TO-52 top-hat shells as known in the art. A pictorial view looking toward the front of such a top-hat electrical optical device <b>33</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The shell includes a tab <b>34</b> protruding from a collar-like portion <b>36</b>, and a frontmost cylindrical portion <b>38</b> extending from the top <b>36</b>. A circular window <b>40</b> is included at the top of a stub-like cylindrical portion <b>38</b>, for providing for the passage of a lightbeam either from the device in the case of a light transmitting device, or to the device in the case of a light receiving device, for example. Three electrical leads <b>42</b> are shown in this example protruding from the bottom of the device, which as previously explained, are typically electrically connected to a printed circuit board, or some other component within the housing of the electro-optical device to which the present connector <b>2</b> is press fit.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In another embodiment of the invention, as <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref>, three elongated semicircular protrusions <b>44</b> are axially aligned and spaced apart on the sidewall <b>23</b> of the hole <b>26</b> for ensuring proper alignment of an electro-optical receiving or transmitting device that is housed within a TO-56 shell. A pictorial view looking toward the front of a optical device <b>35</b> housed in TO-56 shell is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8A</figref> to include a pair of electrical leads <b>46</b>, a collar-like portion <b>48</b>, a cylindrical stud-like portion <b>50</b> extending from the collar <b>48</b>, the latter having an optical window <b>52</b> in the top center portion thereof for permitting the passage of light. The collar <b>48</b> includes three semicircular grooves <b>54</b> spaced apart about its circumference, as shown in the back view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8B</figref>. When the device <b>35</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8A and 8B</figref>, as housed in a TO-56 top-hat shell, in this example, is press fit into the connector <b>2</b>, the grooves <b>54</b> align with the semicircular protrusions <b>44</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref>), for ensuring that the associated optical device <b>35</b> is properly aligned, thereby ensuring that electrical leads <b>46</b> can be connected within the housing without interference with one another. The optical device alignment mechanisms shown in the embodiments of the invention of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6B and 6C</figref> are not meant to be limiting, and the back portion of the connector <b>2</b> can be configured for receiving optical electrical devices contained within other housing or shell configurations.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a partial cross-sectional view of the connector <b>2</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> taken along <b>9</b>-<b>9</b>. In this example, an optical device <b>56</b> having electrical leads <b>58</b> protruding from the bottom thereof is shown installed within the connector <b>2</b>, wherein the retention is via press fit in the preferred embodiment, as previously described. In other embodiments of the invention, the optical device <b>56</b> can be secured by other than press fitting, such as the use of appropriate epoxies, and other adhesive materials, for example. Note that in the example given, the connector <b>2</b> is press fit into a D-hole of the enclosure or housing <b>60</b> of the electro-optical apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">With further reference to the cross section of connector <b>2</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, various important dimensional features are shown. Dimension “A” determines the depth of an electro-optical transmitting or receiving device <b>56</b> that is predetermined for the top-hat shell thereof. The dimension “B” is predetermined for controlling the depth of the electro-optical device <b>56</b> within connector <b>2</b>. Dimension “C” is the inside diameter of the hole <b>30</b>, which is predetermined for permitting press fitting of the collar or flange portion <b>62</b> of device <b>56</b> into hole <b>30</b>. Dimension “D” represents the innermost and minimum diameter of the inward hole <b>26</b> of connector <b>2</b> for receiving the flange or collar portion <b>62</b> of electro-optical transmitting or receiving device <b>56</b>. Dimension “E” represents the length of the hole <b>20</b> necessary for receiving the optical fiber ferrule sleeve of the male ST connector (not shown) to be mated to the connector <b>2</b> of the present invention. Dimension “F” is the inside diameter of hole <b>20</b> necessary for snugly but slidingly receiving the ferrule of the mating ST male connector. Note that dimensions “A,” “B,” and “E” determine the distance required such that the receiving or transmitting end of the optical fiber within the ferrule sleeve of the mating male connector, and the light receiving or transmitting electro-optical device <b>56</b> are in physical contact.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The above-described embodiments of the invention are not meant to be limiting. The dimensions “A” through “F,” and the length and configuration of the frontmost cylindrical segment <b>8</b> of connector <b>2</b> can all be modified for accommodating different types of electro-optical transmitting and receiving devices <b>56</b>, and for mating with many other male terminating connectors at the ends of fiber optic cables, other than ST male connectors. As will be described below, other known optical cable terminating connectors that can be mated with by changing the configuration of a connector <b>2</b> include MT/RJ, SC, SC/APC, E-2000, O-C, FC, FC/APC, LC, and LC/APC all of which are known in the art. Note that the acronym “APC” stands for Angle-polished Physical Contact.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The present connector <b>2</b>, through the use of press fit into the housing of an electro-optical apparatus or device, is suitable for radio frequency interference (RFI) sealing of the housing, and moisture sealing, where the housing is used for an outdoor environment. The present inventors have developed an engineering prototype for a “fiber node” <b>64</b> (also known as an “optical to RF media conversion unit,” or “a bi-directional RF/optical converter”) that utilizes the present connectors <b>20</b> for facilitating the connection of fiber optic cables thereto. More specifically, the present inventors have designed a fiber node <b>64</b> to have many unique features, including the use of the subject inventive connectors <b>2</b> for eliminating the requirement of passing a fiber optic cable with its connector through a hole in the housing of the device <b>64</b> to mate with a female connector mounted upon a PC board, or otherwise within the employer of the housing <b>60</b> of the fiber node <b>64</b> apparatus. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, a top view of the fiber node <b>64</b> includes at one end a leftmost one of the present connectors <b>2</b> for providing a “REV Fiber Out” port <b>66</b> fiber interface with a laser transmitting device representing electro-optical device <b>56</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, for transmission of the optically modulated reverse CATV spectrum along a fiber optic cable connected to the associated connector <b>2</b>, as previously described. The rightmost connector <b>2</b> represents a fiber optic port “FWD Fiber In” port <b>68</b> for providing a fiber optic interface for the reception of the optically modulated forward CATV spectrum from a fiber optic cable terminated to the port <b>68</b> for coupling optical signals to a light receiving device representing electro-optical device <b>56</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>. Four F-type coaxial connectors are associated with ports <b>72</b>, <b>74</b>, <b>76</b>, and <b>78</b>, respectively. Port <b>72</b> provides a reverse spectrum test point (Rev TP). Port <b>74</b> provides a DC power termination, for in this example receiving 12 volts. Also in this example, the reverse spectrum frequency ranges from 5 to 42 MHZ. Port <b>76</b> provides a termination for a forward spectrum test point (Fwd TP) for a spectrum signal frequency range of 52-870 MHZ. Lastly, port <b>78</b> provides a “DC/RF” termination for both interfacing bi-directional RF signals to a user, and receiving DC power from a known adapter device that combines DC power and RF signals on a single coaxial cable. Also shown as provided on the top of the fiber node <b>64</b>, are a light emitting diode (LED) <b>80</b> that is activated to emit light to indicate that the light transmitting optical device <b>56</b> is active at port <b>66</b>, and another LED <b>82</b> activated to indicate that optical signals are being received at port <b>68</b> by an optical or light receiving device employed for the electro-optical device <b>56</b>. Test points <b>84</b>, <b>86</b>, and <b>88</b> are included in this example between LEDS <b>80</b> and <b>82</b>, as shown. One volt per milliwatt of optical power is provided at test point <b>84</b> for checking the power level of the signals being transmitted, which is proportional to the optical signal strength thereof. Test point <b>86</b> provides a common ground for the test points <b>84</b> and <b>88</b>. Test point <b>88</b> provides for a measure of the DC bias level, which is proportional to the optical signal strength of the optical signals being received at port <b>68</b>. Note also that the housing <b>60</b> includes left side and right side mounting flanges <b>90</b>, and <b>92</b>, respectively, each having open elevated slots <b>94</b>, <b>96</b>, respectively, for facilitating the positioning of the housing <b>60</b> on a flat mounting surface (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, a back view of the fiber node <b>64</b> is shown. Note that the housing is formed from appropriate metal material, in this example. A ground termination device <b>89</b> is provided along a side portion of the housing proximate port <b>72</b>, as shown in this example. A front view of the fiber node <b>64</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>. A bottom view thereof is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>. A bottom cover plate <b>98</b> is secured to the bottom of fiber node <b>64</b> in a manner hermetically sealing the components contained within the housing from the elements, via a known sealing technique such as using appropriate gasket material and adhesives or solder.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">A block schematic diagram is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> for the fiber node <b>64</b> in this embodiment of the invention. The fiber node <b>64</b> provides a bi-directional RF and optical converter device or apparatus that includes a printed circuit board <b>103</b> mounted within the fiber node housing <b>60</b>, in this example, via four grounding screws <b>120</b> located at each corner of the printed circuit board <b>103</b>, as shown and at other locations where grounding of the circuit to the housing is necessary. A laser diode <b>100</b> is secured within a connector <b>2</b> at port <b>66</b>, whereas a photodiode <b>102</b> is secured within the associated connector <b>2</b> at port <b>68</b>. The photodiode <b>102</b> converts optical input signals into electrical signals which are connected to input terminals of a receive control circuit <b>114</b>, and an amplifier <b>118</b>. The receive control circuit <b>114</b> provides power to LED <b>82</b> for indicating that signals are being received, and also delivers a voltage proportional to the optical power to the test point <b>88</b>. The output of amplifier <b>118</b> is connected to the input of a directional coupler <b>116</b>. The directional coupler couples electrical input signals to the forward receive test point port <b>76</b>, and also to a diplex filter <b>112</b>. Electrical signals are also bi-directionally coupled between the diplex filter <b>112</b> and port <b>78</b>, the latter providing bi-directional RF signal flow between a subscriber and the cable system provider. The diplex filter <b>112</b> also has an output connected to a directional coupler <b>106</b> for delivering electrical RF output signals from directional coupler <b>106</b> to port <b>72</b> providing a reverse transmit test point, and also to the input of a laser driver <b>104</b>. The laser driver <b>104</b> is connected to a transmit control circuit <b>108</b>, and also to laser diode <b>100</b>; in this example, for converting the reverse RF output signals to optical signals, for transmission to the cable provider. The transmit control <b>108</b> also provides an output to LED <b>80</b> for indicating times that reverse RF output signals are being transmitted. The transmit control <b>108</b> also delivers a voltage proportional to the transmitted optical power to test point <b>84</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 15 and 16</figref>, a second embodiment of the invention is for providing in this example a rectangular configured optical to RF interface connector <b>104</b> for mating with SC, LC E2000, MTRJ, and MU male fiber optic cable termination connectors. The frontmost segment of the connector <b>104</b> for this second embodiment of the invention is a substantially rectangular shell or enclosure <b>106</b> including an interface keyway or slot <b>108</b> cut through the shell from the open front face <b>110</b> toward the rear portion of the shell <b>106</b>, as shown. The shell <b>106</b> has a hollow cavity <b>112</b>, and a back wall <b>114</b> that has a cylindrical optical fiber ferrule guide <b>116</b> protruding therefrom into the interior of the cavity <b>112</b>, as shown. The through hole <b>118</b> of the optical ferrule guide <b>116</b>, similar to the hole <b>20</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> for the connector of the first embodiment of the invention, passes through to the back cylindrical segment <b>118</b> to permit light to travel between the electro-optical device <b>56</b> mounted within the back cylindrical segment <b>118</b>, in substantially the same manner as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> for the first embodiment of the invention. As in the previous embodiment, the flat portion <b>120</b> in the back cylindrical segment <b>118</b> serves as a press-fit orientation key. The remaining round outside portion of cylindrical segment of <b>118</b> is narrowed in the preferred embodiment of invention. An O-ring seal <b>122</b> is provided around the innermost portion of the back cylindrical segment <b>118</b>, as shown. Otherwise, the back cylindrical segment <b>118</b> of this alternative embodiment is substantially similar to the back cylindrical segment <b>12</b> of the first embodiment of the invention, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">A third embodiment of the invention is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 17 and 18</figref> for an optical to RF interface connector configured for mating with male FC, and SMA Optical fiber termination connectors. More particularly, the connector includes a threaded frontmost cylindrical segment <b>124</b> that is provided with a connector interface keyway <b>126</b> cut into its front edge, as shown. A cylindrical optical fiber ferrule guide <b>128</b> is centrally located within the cylindrical segment <b>124</b>, as shown, and serves the same purpose as the ferrule guide of the second embodiment of the invention (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>). A back cylindrical segment <b>130</b> is included as shown, with the rounded portion narrowed to provide better press-fit retention, and also configured with a flat portion <b>132</b> serving as a press-fit orientation key. The back cylindrical portion <b>130</b> has a greater outside diameter than the frontmost threaded cylindrical segment <b>124</b>, in this example. A circular flange <b>134</b> is located between the frontmost threaded cylindrical segment <b>124</b> and the back cylindrical portion <b>130</b>, as shown. The flange <b>134</b> has a greater outside diameter than the back cylindrical portion <b>130</b>. The configuration of the back portion <b>130</b> is substantially the same as that of the back portion <b>118</b> of the second embodiment of the invention shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>, which each include inner ring seal <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 19 and 20</figref>, an alternative embodiment of the invention for providing a female optical to RF interface connector for mating with a male ST fiber optical cable termination connector includes a frontmost cylindrical portion <b>8</b> that is configured in substantially the same manner as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 through 6A</figref>. The back cylindrical portion <b>130</b> is configured in substantially the same manner as that shown for the embodiments of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 17 and 18</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The various embodiments of the present invention provide a connector that relative to the prior art increases the interface reliability for the fiber optic cable connection, and reduces insertion loss by eliminating the necessity to loop a portion of fiber optic cable around the inside perimeter of the housing of a device, and by providing a direct electrical connection from the connector to the printed circuit board or other electrical components housed within the enclosure of the particular fiber optic device. Also, the alternative connector embodiments of the invention all permit the use of smaller enclosures or housings for the associated electro-optical devices, and further insure an RF seal to meet the requirements of Electromagnetic Interference suppression greater than 120 dB. Also particularly the press-fit connector embodiments insure a pressure tight seal between the connector and the housing of the associated device for preventing moisture migration into the interior of the housing. A yet further another advantage of the present invention in its various embodiments is that the alternative connector embodiments provide for optimum heat sinking of the active optical component mounted within the connector, whereby heat can pass from the optical component to the connector, and therefrom to the housing or enclosure of the associated device, thereby temperature stabilizing the optical component.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Although various embodiments of the invention have been shown and described, they are not meant to be limiting. Those of skill in the art may recognize certain modifications to these embodiments, which modifications are meant to be covered by the spirit of the appended claims. For example, the press fit configuration of connectors of the various embodiments of the invention can alternatively be screw-in type mounting by configuring the back portion to be externally threaded. Also, said connector embodiments can be made from any suitable metallic material such as nickel or tin plated brass, for example.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An optical to RF interface connector, comprising:
<claim-text>a front portion configured for receiving and securely retaining a male connector at one end of a fiber optic cable;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a back portion configured for mounting into a hole through a wall of a housing of an associated fiber optic/electrical device, wherein said back portion is configured for both press-fitting into the wall of said housing and providing alignment means for radially orienting the connector when press fit into a mounting hole of the housing of said fiber optic/electrical device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said back portion being further configured for receiving and retaining therein a light receiving or light transmitting electro-optical device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light pathway being provided between said front and back portions to permit the passage of light between said electro-optical device and the end of said fiber optic cable; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said back portion is further configured to include:
<claim-text>indexing means located on an inside wall for radially orienting said electro-optical device upon installation therein.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front and back portions are provided in a one piece shell of metallic material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front and back portions are provided in a one piece shell of nickel-plated brass material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion is configured for mating with an ST type fiber optic connector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion further includes a centrally located optical ferrule guide forming a portion of said light pathway.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion is configured for mating with either one of an SC, LC, E2000, MTRJ, and MU type fiber optic connector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion is configured for mating with either one of an FC and SMA type fiber-optic connector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion includes an outside threaded outer cylindrical wall having an open front face, with a longitudinal optical interface keyway cut into the front face.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion is configured for mating with a fiber optic connector selected from the group consisting of ST, SC, LC, E2000, MTRJ, MU, FC, and SMA types.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the alignment means comprises said back portion being further configured to include:
<claim-text>a cylindrical outer wall with a flat portion for radially orienting said connector when press fit into the mounting hole which is in the form of a corresponding D-hole.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion is further configured to include:
<claim-text>indexing means located on an inside wall for radially orienting said electro-optical device upon installation therein.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further including means for providing an O-ring seal between said back portion and said housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion is further configured to receive an electro-optical device having a TO-18 top-hat shell.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion is further configured to receive an electro-optical device having a TO-46 top-hat shell.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion is further configured to receive an electro-optical device having a TO-52 top-hat shell.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion is further configured to receive an electro-optical device having a TO-56 top-hat shell.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion is further configured to insure electrical leads from said electro-optical device protrude outward and away from a free end of said back portion, for facilitating mechanical and electrical connection to the electrical leads.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion is further configured for providing a female bayonet mechanical retention with a male bayonet connector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion includes:
<claim-text>a rectangular outer shell having an open front face, a back wall secured to said back portion, said rectangular outer shell defining a substantially rectangular cavity;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an optical connector interface keyway cut into a central portion of the front face; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cylindrical optical fiber ferrule guide secured to a central area of said back wall, said ferrule guide protruding into said substantially rectangular cavity, and forming a portion of said light pathway.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion has a knurled outside wall surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion further includes a centrally located optical ferrule guide forming a portion of said light pathway.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said front portion includes an outside threaded outer cylindrical wall having an open front face, with a longitudinal optical interface keyway cut into the front face.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. An optical to RF interface connector, comprising:
<claim-text>a front portion configured for receiving and securely retaining a male connector at one end of a fiber optic cable;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a back portion configured for mounting into a hole through a wall of a housing of an associated fiber optic/electrical device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said back portion being further configured for receiving and retaining therein a light receiving or light transmitting electro-optical device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light pathway being provided between said front and back portions to permit the passage of light between said electro-optical device and the end of said fiber optic cable;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said front portion includes:
<claim-text>a rectangular outer shell having an open front face, a back wall secured to said back portion, said rectangular outer shell defining a substantially rectangular cavity;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an optical connector interface keyway cut into a central portion of the front face; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a cylindrical optical fiber ferrule guide secured to a central area of said back wall, said ferrule guide protruding into said substantially rectangular cavity, and forming a portion of said light pathway.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion is further configured to include alignment means for radially orienting the connector when press fit into a mounting hole of the housing of said fiber optic/electrical device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00024">claim 24</claim-ref>, wherein the alignment means comprises said back portion being further configured to include:
<claim-text>a cylindrical outer wall with a flat portion for radially orienting said connector when press fit into the mounting hole which is in the form of a corresponding D-hole.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The connector of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref>, wherein said back portion is further configured to include:
<claim-text>indexing means located on an inside wall for radially orienting said electro-optical device upon installation therein.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
