<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297588-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297588</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11046079</doc-number>
<date>20050128</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>274</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>8238</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438229</main-classification>
<further-classification>438659</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E21637</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Electronic device comprising a gate electrode including a metal-containing layer having one or more impurities and a process for forming the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6444512</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Madhukar et al.</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438203</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6770521</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Visokay et al.</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6936508</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Visokay et al.</name>
<date>20050800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438199</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0065930</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lin et al.</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0132296</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lin et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0175910</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Pan et al.</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>Ha, et al., “Molybdenum Gate Work Function Engineering for Ultra-Thin-Body Silicon-on-Insulator (UTB SOI) MOSFETs,” Jpn. J. Appl. Phys. vol. 42 (2003), pp. 1979-1982, part 1, No. 4B the Japan Society of Applied Physics, Apr. 2003.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Polishchuk, et al., “Dual Work Function Metal Gate CMOS Transistors by Ni-Ti Interdiffusion,” vol. 23, No. 4, pp. 201-202, 2002 IEEE Electron Device Letters, Apr. 2002.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>Ranade, et al., “Work Function Engineering of Molybdenum Gate Electrodes by Nitrogen Implantation,” University of California at Berkeley, California, Electrochemical and Sold-State Letters, 2001 The Electrochemical Society, Inc., pp. G85-G87, May 30, 2001.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438229</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438230</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438658</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438659</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438918</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21623</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21637</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060172516</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060803</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Adetutu</last-name>
<first-name>Olubunmi O.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Austin</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gilmer</last-name>
<first-name>David C.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Austin</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tobin</last-name>
<first-name>Philip J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Austin</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Freescale Semiconductor, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Austin</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chaudhari</last-name>
<first-name>Chandra</first-name>
<department>2891</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">One or more impurities may be incorporated within a metal-containing layer of a metal-containing gate electrode to modify the work function of the metal-containing gate electrode of a transistor can affect the threshold voltage of the transistor. In one embodiment, the impurity can be used in a p-channel transistor to allow the work function of a metal-containing gate electrode to be closer to the valence band for silicon. In another embodiment, the impurity can be used in an n-channel transistor to allow the work function of a metal-containing gate electrode to be closer to the conduction band for silicon. In a particular embodiment, a boron-containing species is implanted into a metal-containing layer within the metal-containing gate electrode within a p-channel transistor, so that the metal-containing gate electrode has a work function closer to the valence band for silicon as compared to the metal-containing gate electrode without the boron-containing species.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="200.15mm" wi="144.86mm" file="US07297588-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="210.14mm" wi="145.54mm" file="US07297588-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="217.17mm" wi="148.17mm" file="US07297588-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Disclosure</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present disclosure relates to electronic devices and processes, and more particularly to an electronic device comprising a gate electrode including a metal-containing layer having one or more impurities and processes for forming the same.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">State-of-the-art semiconductor devices currently include transistors having a gate dielectric layer with one or more high dielectric constant (“high-k”) materials. These materials typically have a dielectric constant higher than the silicon nitride, which is approximately seven. Conventional transistors include N<sup>+</sup> or P<sup>+</sup> doped silicon gate electrodes. One or more problems can occur when a silicon layer contacts a high-k gate dielectric layer. A high-k gate dielectric layer can include a metal oxide, such as ZrO<sub>2</sub>. When ZrO<sub>2 </sub>contacts silicon at an elevated temperature, such as during a source/drain anneal, silicon (e.g., from the substrate or a subsequently-formed polysilicon gate electrode) can react with at least some of the zirconium to form ZrSi<sub>2</sub>, which is conductive. In addition, some of the dopant from the N<sup>+</sup> or P<sup>+</sup> silicon can migrate from the silicon into the gate dielectric layer or other parts of the transistor. The dopant concentration at the silicon-gate dielectric interface becomes depleted, thereby forming a more resistive portion, which electronically, reduces the electrically measured capacitance of the gate dielectric layer within the transistor, which is undesired.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">High-k dielectric materials, including HfO<sub>2</sub>, ZrO<sub>2</sub>, etc., when used as a gate dielectric layer typically have metal gate electrodes, due to the potential problems when high-k dielectric materials contact silicon and potential dopant migration into the gate dielectric layer. Exemplary materials for metal gate electrodes include TiN, TaC, TaSiN, and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">When a metal gate electrode is used, the portion of metal gate electrode closest to the gate dielectric layer establishes the work function for the gate electrode. An NMOS transistor may have TaSiN as the portion of its metal-containing gate electrode closest to the high-k gate dielectric layer, and a PMOS transistor may have TiN as the portion of its metal-containing gate electrode closest to the high-k gate dielectric layer. The work function for TaSiN is 4.3 eV, and the work function for TiN is 4.6 eV. As a basis for comparison, the work function for N<sup>+</sup> silicon and the energy level for the conduction band (“E<sub>c</sub>”) for silicon is 4.1 eV, and the work function for P<sup>+</sup> silicon and the energy level for the valence band (“E<sub>v</sub>”) for silicon is 5.2 eV. Therefore, the difference between E<sub>c </sub>and the work function for TaSiN is 0.2 eV, and the difference between E<sub>v </sub>and the work function for TiN is 0.6 eV. These differences can cause longer times to switch states (i.e., “on” and “off”) for the transistors, and therefore, result in a slower operating electronic device.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The invention is illustrated by way of example and not limitation in the accompanying figures.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> includes an illustration of cross-sectional views of portions of a semiconductor device substrate after forming a plurality of layers for part of a gate electrode stack.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> includes an illustration of cross-sectional views of the portions of the substrate in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> after removing a portion of a hard mask layer and a resist mask.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> includes an illustration of cross-sectional views of the portions of the substrate in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> after removing a portion of a first layer of a gate electrode and the remaining portion of the hard mask layer.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> includes an illustration of cross-sectional views of the portions of the substrate in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> during ion implantation.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> includes an illustration of cross-sectional views of the portions of the substrate in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> after forming the remaining layers of the gate electrode stacks in accordance with an embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> includes an illustration of cross-sectional views of the portions of the substrate in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> after forming gate electrodes and source/drain regions for transistors in accordance with an embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Skilled artisans appreciate that elements in the figures are illustrated for simplicity and clarity and have not necessarily been drawn to scale. For example, the dimensions of some of the elements in the figures may be exaggerated relative to other elements to help to improve understanding of embodiments of the invention.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">One or more impurities may be incorporated within a metal-containing layer of a metal-containing gate electrode to modify the work function of the metal-containing gate electrode of a transistor, which in turn, can affect the threshold voltage of the transistor. In one embodiment, the impurity can be used in a p-channel transistor to allow the work function of a metal-containing gate electrode to be closer to the valence band for silicon. In another embodiment, the impurity can be used in an n-channel transistor to allow the work function of a metal-containing gate electrode to be closer to the conduction band for silicon. In a particular embodiment, a boron-containing species is implanted into a metal-containing layer within the metal-containing gate electrode within a p-channel transistor, so that the metal-containing gate electrode has a work function closer to the valence band for silicon as compared to the metal-containing gate electrode without the boron-containing species.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In one aspect, a process for forming an electronic device includes forming a first layer of a first gate electrode over a substrate, wherein the first layer includes a first element that is a metallic element. The method also includes incorporating an impurity into the first layer after forming the first layer over the substrate. The impurity comprises a second element within Group 2 or 13 of the Periodic Table.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In one embodiment, the impurity includes a Group 13 element. In a particular embodiment, the impurity includes boron-containing species. In another embodiment, in incorporating the impurity includes implanting the impurity. In another particular embodiment, before implanting the impurity, the first layer includes another element other than silicon.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In still another embodiment, the substrate includes a first portion and a second portion, and the first layer overlies the first portion of the substrate. The process further includes forming a gate dielectric layer over the first and second portions of the substrate before forming the first layer, and forming a second layer over the gate dielectric layer within the second portion of the substrate, wherein a second gate electrode includes at least a portion of the second layer. In a particular embodiment, the process further includes removing the first layer from the second portion of the substrate before forming the second layer, or removing the second layer from the first portion of the substrate before forming the first layer. In another particular embodiment, a PMOS transistor is formed within the first portion of the substrate and includes the first gate electrode. The first layer lies closest to the gate dielectric layer compared to any other layer, if any, within the first gate electrode. An NMOS transistor is formed within the second portion of the substrate and includes the second gate electrode. The second layer lies closest to the gate dielectric layer compared to any other layer, if any, within the second gate electrode. The first gate electrode does not include the second layer, the second gate electrode does not include the first layer, or a combination thereof. In a more particular embodiment, the first gate electrode includes the first and second layers, or the second gate electrode includes the first and second layers.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In yet another embodiment, the process further includes forming a second layer over the first layer, wherein forming the second layer is performed before incorporating the impurity. In a particular embodiment, the second layer is mostly silicon.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In another aspect, an electronic device includes a first gate electrode that includes a first layer. The first layer includes a first element that is a transition metal element, and a second element that is an element within Group 2 or 13 of the Periodic Table.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In one embodiment, the second element includes a Group 13 element. In a particular embodiment, the second element is boron. In another embodiment, the first layer includes a third element other than silicon, wherein the third element is different from the first and second elements.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In still another embodiment, the electronic device further includes a substrate including a first portion and a second portion, a gate dielectric layer overlying the first and second portions of the substrate, and a second layer. The first layer overlies the first portion of the substrate and the gate dielectric layer. The second layer overlies the second portion of the substrate and the gate dielectric layer. In a particular embodiment, the electronic device includes a PMOS transistor within the first portion of the substrate, wherein the PMOS transistor includes the first gate electrode. The first layer lies closest to the gate dielectric layer compared to any other layer, if any, within the first gate electrode. The electronic device includes an NMOS transistor within the second portion of the substrate, wherein the NMOS transistor includes the second gate electrode. The second layer lies closest to the gate dielectric layer compared to any other layer, if any, within the second gate electrode. The first gate electrode does not include the second layer, the second gate electrode does not include the first layer, or a combination thereof. In a more particular embodiment, the first gate electrode includes the first and second layers, or the second gate electrode includes the first and second layers.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In yet another aspect, a process for forming an electronic device includes forming a first layer of a first gate electrode over a substrate, wherein the first layer includes a metallic element. The process also includes implanting a boron-containing species into the first layer.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In one embodiment, the boron-containing species includes B or BF<sub>2</sub>. In a particular embodiment, the first layer includes an elemental transition metal, a transition metal nitride, a transition metal silicon nitride, or any combination thereof. In another particular embodiment, the substrate includes a first portion and a second portion, and the first layer overlies the first portion of the substrate. The process further includes forming a gate dielectric layer over the first and second portions of the substrate before forming the first layer, and forming a second layer over the gate dielectric layer within the second portion of the substrate, wherein a second gate electrode includes at least a portion of the second layer. In a more particular embodiment, the process further includes removing the first layer from the second portion of the substrate before forming the second layer, or removing the second layer from the first portion of the substrate before forming the first layer.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In an even more particular embodiment, a PMOS transistor is formed within the first portion of the substrate and includes the first gate electrode. The first layer lies closest to the gate dielectric layer compared to any other layer, if any, within the first gate electrode. An NMOS transistor is formed within the second portion of the substrate and includes the second gate electrode. The second layer lies closest to the gate dielectric layer compared to any other layer, if any, within the second gate electrode. The first gate electrode does not include the second layer, the second gate electrode does not include the first layer, or a combination thereof. In a further particular embodiment, the first gate electrode includes the first and second layers, or the second gate electrode includes the first and second layers. In still another further particular embodiment, the process further includes forming a second layer over the first layer, wherein forming the second layer is performed before implanting the boron-containing species. In still a further particular embodiment, the second layer is mostly silicon.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Before addressing details of embodiments described below, some terms are defined or clarified. Group numbers corresponding to columns within the Periodic Table of the elements use the “New Notation” convention as seen in the <i>CRC Handbook of Chemistry and Physics, </i>81<sup>st </sup>Edition (2000).</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The term “metal” or any of its variants is intended to refer to a material that includes an element that is within any of Groups 1 to 12, within Groups 13 to 16, an element that is along and below a diagonal line defined by atomic numbers 13 (Al), 32 (Ge), 51 (Sb), and 84 (Po), or any combination thereof. Metal does not include Si. The tern “transition metal element” is intended to refer to an element that is within any of Groups 3 to 12.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The term “elemental transition metal” is intended to refer to a transition metal that is not part of a molecule that comprises at least two different elements. For example, Ti atoms that are not chemically bound to any other atoms are considered an elemental transition element; however Ti atoms within TiN are not considered to be an elemental transition metal.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As used herein, the terms “comprises,” “comprising,” “includes,” “including,” “has,” “having” or any other variation thereof, are intended to cover a non-exclusive inclusion. For example, a process, method, article, or apparatus that comprises a list of elements is not necessarily limited to only those elements but may include other elements not expressly listed or inherent to such process, method, article, or apparatus. Further, unless expressly stated to the contrary, “or” refers to an inclusive or and not to an exclusive or. For example, a condition A or B is satisfied by any one of the following: A is true (or present) and B is false (or not present), A is false (or not present) and B is true (or present), and both A and B are true (or present).</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Additionally, for clarity purposes and to give a general sense of the scope of the embodiments described herein, the use of the “a” or “an” are employed to describe one or more articles to which “a” or “an” refers. Therefore, the description should be read to include one or at least one whenever “a” or “an” is used, and the singular also includes the plural unless it is clear that the contrary is meant otherwise.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Unless otherwise defined, all technical and scientific terms used herein have the same meaning as commonly understood by one of ordinary skill in the art to which this invention belongs. All publications, patent applications, patents, and other references mentioned herein are incorporated by reference in their entirety. In case of conflict, the present specification, including definitions, will control. In addition, the materials, methods, and examples are illustrative only and not intended to be limiting.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Other features and advantages of the invention will be apparent from the following detailed description, and from the claims.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">To the extent not described herein, many details regarding specific materials, processing acts, and circuits are conventional and may be found in textbooks and other sources within the semiconductor and microelectronic arts.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> includes an illustration of a cross-sectional view of a substrate <b>10</b>, which includes a PMOS portion <b>11</b> and an NMOS portion <b>13</b>. The substrate <b>10</b> can include a monocrystalline semiconductor material, a semiconductor-on-insulator substrate, or nearly any other substrate used in forming semiconductor devices. Within the PMOS portion <b>11</b>, the substrate <b>10</b> may include an n-type dopant, and within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>, the substrate <b>10</b> may include a p-type dopant. In another embodiment, the conductivity types for the dopants may be reversed or may be the same.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Layers are sequentially formed over the substrate <b>10</b> within the PMOS and NMOS portions <b>11</b> and <b>13</b>. The layers include a gate dielectric layer <b>12</b>, a first layer <b>14</b>, which will the part of the gate electrode within PMOS portion <b>11</b>, and a hard mask layer <b>16</b>. The gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> has a thickness in a range of approximately 1 to 5 nm, the first layer has a thickness in a range of approximately 5 to 20 nm, and the hard mask layer <b>16</b> has a thickness in a range of approximately 10 to 100 nm. Although not illustrated, an interfacial layer of approximately 1 nm may be formed between the substrate <b>10</b> and the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> during or prior to the formation of the electronic device.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> can include one or more high-k materials, such as HfO<sub>2</sub>. In another embodiment, the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> can include HfO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>, HfSi<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub>, HfSi<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub>N<sub>z</sub>, HfZr<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub>N<sub>z</sub>, HfZr<sub>x</sub>Si<sub>y</sub>O<sub>z</sub>N<sub>q</sub>, HfZrO, ZrSi<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub>, ZrSi<sub>x</sub>O<sub>y</sub>N<sub>z</sub>, ZrO<sub>2</sub>, other Hf-containing or Zr-containing dielectric material, or any combination thereof. The first layer <b>14</b> is compatible with the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> (i.e., does not adversely interact with the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b>) and has a work function relatively closer to the E<sub>v </sub>as compared to other materials that could be used for a gate electrode with a high-k gate dielectric layer. In one embodiment, the first layer <b>14</b> includes a metallic element, such as a transition metal element. In a particular embodiment, the first layer <b>14</b> includes an elemental transition element (e.g., substantially only atoms of the transition metal). In another embodiment, the first layer <b>14</b> may include a second element that, in one embodiment, is any element other than silicon. The first layer may include a third element. The third element may include silicon. Therefore, the first layer <b>14</b> can include only one element that is a metallic element, can include only two elements, wherein both of the elements are not silicon, or can include three or more elements, of which, one of the elements may be silicon. The first layer <b>14</b> can include TiN, Mo<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>, MoSi<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>, RuO<sub>2</sub>, IrO<sub>2</sub>, Ru, Ir, MoSiO, MoSiON, MoHfO, MoHfON, other transition metal containing material, or any combination thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The hard mask layer <b>16</b> can include nearly any material that is relatively resistant to etching when portions of the first layer <b>14</b> are to be removed. Additionally, when the hard mask layer <b>16</b> is subsequently removed after patterning the first layer <b>14</b>, the hard mask layer <b>16</b> will be removed selectively to a remaining portion of the first layer <b>14</b>. The hard mask layer <b>16</b> can include SiO<sub>2</sub>, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>, or any combination thereof. In one embodiment, the hard mask layer <b>16</b> is formed by depositing an oxide layer using tetraethylorthosilicate (TEOS).</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The gate dielectric layer <b>12</b>, first layer <b>14</b>, hard mask layer <b>16</b>, or any combination thereof can be formed by depositing an appropriate material using atomic layer deposition, chemical vapor deposition, physical vapor deposition, or the like. In another embodiment, the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b>, first layer <b>14</b>, hard mask layer <b>16</b>, or any combination thereof can include one film or a plurality of films.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A resist layer is formed over the substrate <b>10</b> and is patterned to form a resist mask <b>18</b>, which overlies the hard mask layer <b>16</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b>. The resist mask <b>18</b> is not formed over the hard mask layer <b>16</b> within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>. In one embodiment, the resist mask <b>18</b> is formed by coating or otherwise depositing a photoresist material to form the resist layer, and using a lithographic process to pattern the resist layer to form the resist mask <b>18</b>. The resist layer may include a negative-acting or positive-acting photoresist material.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The exposed portion of the hard mask layer <b>16</b> is removed from the NMOS portion <b>13</b>, and the resist mask <b>18</b> is then subsequently removed, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The hard mask layer <b>16</b> may be removed by using a conventional etching process. The etching is performed such that the hard mask layer <b>16</b> is selectively removed as compared to the first layer <b>14</b>. In one embodiment, etching can be preformed as a wet etch using a dilute HF solution. In one embodiment, the dilute HF solution has at least 10 parts H<sub>2</sub>O for each part HF, and in a particular embodiment, the dilute HF solution has at least 100 parts H<sub>2</sub>O for each part HF. In another embodiment, etching can be performed as a dry etch. The resist mask <b>18</b> is removed using a conventional ashing technique.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">At this point in the process, a remaining portion of the hard mask layer <b>16</b> lies within the PMOS portion <b>11</b>, and a portion of the first layer <b>14</b> is exposed within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>. The exposed portion of the first layer <b>14</b> is removed from the NMOS portion <b>13</b>. The hard mask layer <b>16</b> protects the portion of the first layer <b>14</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b>, such that it is not removed. The first layer <b>14</b> may be removed by using a conventional etching process. The etching is performed such that the first layer <b>14</b> is selectively removed as compared to the hard mask layer <b>16</b>. In one embodiment, etching can be preformed as a wet etch using a dilute NH<sub>4</sub>OH solution. In one embodiment, the dilute NH<sub>4</sub>OH solution has at least 10 parts H<sub>2</sub>O and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>for each part NH<sub>4</sub>OH, and in a particular embodiment, the dilute NH<sub>4</sub>OH solution has at least 100 parts H<sub>2</sub>O and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>for each part NH<sub>4</sub>OH. In another embodiment, etching can be performed as a dry etch.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">After the exposed portion of the first layer <b>14</b> is removed, the remaining portion of the hard mask layer <b>16</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b> is removed, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The hard mask layer <b>16</b> may be removed by using a conventional etching process. The etching is performed such that the hard mask layer <b>16</b> is selectively removed as compared to the first layer <b>14</b> and the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b>. In one embodiment, etching can be preformed as a wet etch using a dilute HF solution. In one embodiment, the dilute HF solution has at least 10 parts H<sub>2</sub>O for each part HF, and in a particular embodiment, the dilute HF solution has at least 100 parts H<sub>2</sub>O for each part HF. In another embodiment, etching can be performed as a dry etch may be used</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">A dopant mask <b>42</b> is formed over the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The dopant mask <b>42</b> can be formed using any one or more conventional techniques for forming a resist mask. In one embodiment, the process is substantially the sane as described for the resist mask <b>18</b>. The thickness of the dopant mask <b>42</b> is sufficient to substantially prevent a significant amount of ions from reaching the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> within the NMOS portion <b>13</b> during a subsequent ion implanting act. In one embodiment, the dopant mask <b>42</b> includes a photoresist material and has a thickness in a range of approximately 100 to 1000 nm.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">An impurity is then introduced into the exposed portion of the first layer <b>14</b> by implanting ion as illustrated in with arrows <b>44</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. The impurity can include an element within Group 2 or 13 of the Periodic Table. The dose and energy used for the ion implantation may depend at least in part on the species to be implanted. In one embodiment, the impurity includes a Group 13 element. In one specific embodiment, B<sup>+</sup> is implanted to a dose in a range of 1E14 to 1E16 ions/cm<sup>2 </sup>and at an energy in a range of approximately 0.5 to 20 KeV. In another specific embodiment, BF<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> is implanted to a dose in a range of 1E14 to 1E16 ions/cm<sup>2 </sup>and at an energy in a range of approximately 1 to 30 KeV. In still another embodiment, the impurity can include Be<sup>+</sup>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In one embodiment, the range for the dose may be approximately the same as it is for the B<sup>+</sup> or BF<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> embodiment. The energy for implanting the other species can be chosen such that the projected range (R<sub>p</sub>)) and straggle (ΔR<sub>p</sub>) are about the same as they are for the boron-containing species. However, a different species may diffuse differently as compared to B<sup>+</sup> or BF<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup>. Therefore, in another embodiment, R<sub>p </sub>may need to be determined for each species due to a different diffusivity during subsequent thermal cycles. After reading this specification, skilled artisans will be able to consult ion implantation tables to choose the proper energy based on the species selected.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">After the impurity has been introduced, the dopant mask <b>42</b> is removed. If the dopant mask includes a resist material, the dopant mask <b>42</b> can be removed using a conventional ashing technique. If the dopant mask <b>42</b> includes a hard mask layer, it will be removed selective to the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> and the remaining portion of the first layer <b>14</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b>. If desired, an optional anneal may be performed to anneal damage caused by the ion implantation. The optional anneal can be performed using an inert gas (e.g., N<sub>2</sub>, a noble gas, or a combination thereof), at a temperature in a range of approximately 400 to 700° C. for a time in a range of approximately 0.5 to 2 minutes. In one embodiment, the concentration of the impurity within the first layer <b>14</b> can be less than 10 atomic %, and in a particular embodiment, less than 3 atomic %.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">A second layer <b>52</b> and a third layer <b>54</b> are then sequentially formed over the substrate <b>10</b> within the PMOS and NMOS portions <b>11</b> and <b>13</b>. The second layer <b>52</b> determines the work function for the gate electrode being formed within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>. In this embodiment, the second layer <b>52</b> includes a material having a work function relatively close to E<sub>c</sub>. For example, the second layer <b>52</b> can include TaC, TaSiN. TaN, TaSiC, HfC, NbC, TiC, NiSi, or any combination thereof. The third layer <b>54</b> includes one or more materials. In one embodiment, the third layer <b>54</b> includes heavily doped amorphous silicon or polycrystalline silicon, a metal silicide, or a combination thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The first, second, and third layers <b>14</b>, <b>52</b>, and <b>54</b> will be subjected to a temperature of 300° C. or higher during subsequent processing acts in forming the electronic device. One such act may include a source/drain anneal that may be performed at a temperature in a range of approximately 500-1100° C. In another embodiment, laser annealing may be performed at a temperature in a range of approximately 500 C to 1350° C. The actual materials selected for the first layer <b>14</b>, the second layer <b>52</b>, and the third layer <b>54</b> can depend on potential interactions that are to be avoided between layers that contact or are adjacent to each other, particularly at elevated temperatures (i.e., significantly above room temperature). After reading this specification, skilled artisans will be able to select proper materials for the layers <b>12</b>, <b>52</b>, and <b>54</b> from a wide array of materials and still be able to avoid interactions that are undesired.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The layers within the gate stacks are patterned to form a gate electrode <b>61</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b> and a gate electrode <b>63</b> within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>, as illustrated in FIG. <b>6</b>. The patterning is performed using a conventional technique. The gate electrode <b>61</b> includes portions of the first, second, and the third layers <b>12</b>, <b>52</b>, and <b>54</b>. The gate electrode <b>63</b> includes portions of the second and the third layers <b>52</b> and <b>54</b>. Ion implantation is performed to form P<sup>+</sup> source/drain regions <b>62</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b>, and N<sup>+</sup> source/drain regions <b>64</b> within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>. An anneal may be performed to activate the implanted dopants within the P<sup>+</sup> and N<sup>+</sup> source/drain regions <b>62</b> and <b>64</b>. Channel regions <b>66</b> and <b>68</b> lie within the substrate <b>10</b> between the P<sup>+</sup> and N<sup>+</sup> source/drain regions <b>62</b> and <b>64</b>. At this point in the process, a PMOS transistor and an NMOS transistor have been formed.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Although not illustrated, one or more insulating layers and one or more wiring layers are formed over the substrate <b>10</b>. A passivation layer and an optional alpha particle protection layer (e.g., polyimide) are deposited to form a substantially completed electronic device. Such layers and their processes for formation are conventional to skilled artisans. After processing of the electronic device is substantially completed, the concentration of the impurity that was introduced into the first layer <b>14</b> (in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) is greater than the concentration of the same impurity within the channel region <b>66</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Many modifications can be used to the embodiments described above. For example, the second layer <b>52</b> may be formed and patterned before forming the first layer <b>14</b>. In this embodiment, the hard mask layer <b>16</b> overlies the second layer <b>52</b> and is used during the removal of the second layer <b>52</b> from the PMOS portion <b>11</b> before the first layer <b>14</b> is formed. In this embodiment, the first layer may be formed over the second layer <b>52</b> before forming the third layer <b>54</b>. In another embodiment, a lithographic sequence can be performed to remove the portion of the first layer <b>14</b> from the NMOS portion <b>13</b> before the third layer <b>54</b> is formed. Along similar lines and referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the portion of the second layer <b>52</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b> call be removed before forming the third layer <b>54</b>. Therefore, the first layer <b>14</b> is not required within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>, and the second layer <b>52</b> is not required within the PMOS portion <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In another embodiment, implantation can be performed through at least part of a layer within the third conductive layer <b>54</b>. In this embodiment, the second conductive layer <b>52</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b> is removed before any portion of the third conductive layer <b>54</b> is formed. A relatively thinner layer that is part of the third conductive layer <b>54</b> is formed on the first layer <b>14</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b> before ion implantation is performed. The thickness of the thinner layer may be in a range of approximately 1 to 10 nm. The energy used for the ion implantation may the increased to account for this additional portion present during the ion implant. In one embodiment, the thinner layer includes amorphous silicon to reduce the effects of implant channeling. After the ion implantation and optional anneal, a relatively thicker layer that is part of the third layer <b>54</b> is then formed over the thinner layer. The thickness of the thicker layer is in a range of approximately 10 to 100 nm.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In still another embodiment, implantation can be performed through a sacrificial layer. For example, a sacrificial layer having a thickness of approximately 1 to 10 nm is deposited over the first layer <b>14</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. After forming the dopant mask <b>42</b> and performing the implantation, the sacrificial layer can be removed. In one embodiment the sacrificial layer includes SiO<sub>2</sub>, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In yet another embodiment, the impurity may be incorporated using one or more dopant gases. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a gas including B<sub>2</sub>H<sub>6</sub>, PH<sub>3</sub>, POCl<sub>3</sub>, AsH<sub>3</sub>, or the like may be exposed to the portion of the first layer <b>14</b> within the PMOS portion <b>11</b> and the dopant mask <b>42</b>. If the gas exposure is performed at a temperature of approximately 50° C. or higher, the dopant mask may include an inorganic material, such as SiO<sub>2</sub>, Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub>, SiO<sub>x</sub>N<sub>y</sub>, or the like. An optional anneal may be performed. The dopant mask <b>42</b> is removed using a conventional technique. Other processing activities are performed substantially the same as previously described.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In a further embodiment, an impurity can be introduced into the second layer <b>52</b> within the NMOS portion <b>13</b>. Any one of the impurities and introduction methods as previously described with respect to the impurity for the first layer <b>14</b> may be used.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Unexpectedly, the embodiments described herein have improved performance in that the impurity incorporated within the layer of the gate electrode closest to the gate dielectric layer <b>12</b> (first layer <b>14</b> for the PMOS portion <b>11</b>, and second layer <b>52</b> for the NMOS portion <b>13</b>) can be used to modify the work function of that layer to be closer to E<sub>v </sub>or E<sub>c</sub>. Many options are available for metal-containing gate electrode materials. For example, in one embodiment, the metal-containing gate electrode, without any impurity, may have a work function closer to E<sub>c </sub>and the impurity can be added to the metal-containing gate electrode to get the work function closer to E<sub>v</sub>, or vice versa. In another embodiment, a mid-band gap material may be used for the metal-containing gate electrode. One impurity can be used to get the work function closer to E<sub>v</sub>, and another impurity can be used to get the work function closer to E<sub>c</sub>. In this manner, the same material for the metal gate electrode can be deposited, and different impurities used to get the work function tailored more closely to E<sub>v </sub>for PMOS transistors and E<sub>c </sub>for NMOS transistors. A wider variety of materials can be used for gate electrodes with impurities used to more closely achieve desired work function(s) for the transistors within the electronic device.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">EXAMPLE</heading>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">The invention will be further described in the following example, which does not limit the scope of the invention described in the claims. The example below demonstrates that the work function of a gate electrode can be changed by incorporating an impurity into a metallic layer.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">PMOS transistors can be formed to include a HfO<sub>2 </sub>gate dielectric layer having a thickness in a range of approximately 1.5 to 10 nm. The gate electrodes for the PMOS transistors include a TiN layer having a thickness of approximately 10.0 nm. For different substrates, the TiN layer does not receive an implant, is implanted with B<sup>+</sup> (low or high energy implant), or is implanted with BF<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> (low or high energy). Table 1 below includes data regarding implant species, dose, and energy used for the example. After the implant, if any, a TaSiN layer having a thickness of approximately 10 nm and a polysilicon layer having a thickness of approximately 100 nm are sequentially deposited over the TiN layer. Source/drain regions are formed using a conventional technique.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="5">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="14pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="42pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="70pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="49pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="42pt" align="center"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" rowsep="1">TABLE 1</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Species</entry>
<entry>Dose (ions/cm<sup>2</sup>)</entry>
<entry>Energy (KeV)</entry>
<entry>Φ (eV)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>No implant</entry>
<entry>—</entry>
<entry>—</entry>
<entry>4.6</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>B<sup>+</sup></entry>
<entry>4E15</entry>
<entry>1.5 (low)</entry>
<entry>4.7</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>BF<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup></entry>
<entry>4E15</entry>
<entry>6.5 (low)</entry>
<entry>4.8</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>B<sup>+</sup></entry>
<entry>4E15</entry>
<entry> 3.5 (high)</entry>
<entry>5.2</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>BF<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup></entry>
<entry>4E15</entry>
<entry>15.0 (high)</entry>
<entry>5.1</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="4" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The flat band voltages are determined for a variety of equivalent oxide thicknesses (“EOTs”). The EOT is an electrical measurement of a thickness of an insulator, as opposed to a physical measurement of the thickness. The work functions of the gate electrodes of the PMOS transistors are determined from the flat band voltages and EOTs. Table 1 includes the calculated work functions. The data indicate that the boron-containing species within the TiN layer increase the work function, and the higher energy implants produce work functions closer to E<sub>v</sub>. The work function improves by 0.2 to 0.3 electron volts when implanting at relatively lower energies as compared to performing no implant. The work function improves by 0.5 to 0.6 electron volts when implanting at relatively higher energies as compared to performing no implant. The use of the impurity incorporation can change the work function more than just by merely switching metal-containing materials for the layer(s) that determine the work function for a gate electrode. Similar effects may be seen when impurities are added to the second layer <b>52</b> to get the work function closer to E<sub>c</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Note that not all of the activities described above in the general description or the examples are required, that a portion of a specific activity may not be required, and that one or more further activities may be performed in addition to those described. Still further, the order in which activities are listed are not necessarily the order in which they are performed. After reading this specification, skilled artisans will be capable of determining what activities can be used for their specific needs or desires.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">In the foregoing specification, the invention has been described with reference to specific embodiments. However, one of ordinary skill in the art appreciates that one or more modifications or one or more other changes can be made without departing from the scope of the invention as set forth in the claims below. Accordingly, the specification and figures are to be regarded in an illustrative rather than a restrictive sense and any and all such modifications and other changes are intended to be included within the scope of invention.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">Any one or more benefits, one or more other advantages, one or more solutions to one or more problems, or any combination thereof have been described above with regard to one or more specific embodiments. However, the benefit(s), advantage(s), solution(s) to problem(s), or any element(s) that may cause any benefit, advantage, or solution to occur or become more pronounced is not to be construed as a critical, required, or essential feature or element of any or all the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A process for forming an electronic device comprising:
<claim-text>forming a gate dielectric layer over a first portion and a second portion of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first layer of a gate stack over the gate dielectric layer, wherein the first layer comprises a first element that is a metallic element, and lies immediately adjacent to the gate dielectric layer over the first portion of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>incorporating an impurity into the first layer after forming the first layer over the gate dielectric layer, wherein the impurity comprises a second element within Group 2 or 13 of the Periodic Table;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second layer of the gate stack over gate dielectric layer, wherein the second layer lies immediately adjacent to the gate dielectric layer over the second portion of the substrate, and after forming the first layer and forming the second layer, the second layer overlies the first layer over the first portion of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a third layer of the gate stack over the first layer and the second layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>patterning the gate stack, wherein after patterning the gate stack, a first gate electrode overlies the first portion of the substrate, and a second gate electrode overlies the second portion of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first source/drain region over the first portion of the substrate, wherein after forming the first source/drain region, a first transistor lies over the first portion of the substrate and includes the first source/drain and the first gate electrode; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second source/drain region over the second portion of the substrate, wherein after forming the second source/drain region, a second transistor lies over the second portion of the substrate and includes the second source/drain and the second gate electrode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the impurity comprises boron-containing species.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein incorporating the impurity comprises implanting the impurity.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>removing the first layer from the second portion of the substrate before forming the second layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: the first transistor includes a PMOS transistor;
<claim-text>the first layer substantially determines the work function of the PMOS transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second transistor includes an NMOS transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second layer substantially determines the work function of the NMOS transistor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second gate electrode does not include the first layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>,
<claim-text>wherein forming the second layer is performed before incorporating the impurity.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A process for forming an electronic device comprising:
<claim-text>forming a gate dielectric layer over a first and a second portion of a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first layer of the gate stack over the gate dielectric layer, wherein the first layer includes a metallic element, and substantially determines a work function for the gate stack over the second portion of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second layer of a gate stack over the gate dielectric layer; wherein the second layer comprises a metallic element, and after forming the first layer and forming the second layer, the second layer overlies the first layer over the second portion of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>implanting a boron-containing species into the second layer wherein after implanting the boron-containing species, the second layer substantially determines a work function of the gate stack over the first portion of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a third layer of the gate stack after forming the first layer and the second layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>patterning the gate stack, wherein after patterning the gate stack a first gate electrode overlies the first portion of the substrate and a second gate electrode overlies the second portion of the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a first source/drain region over the first portion of the substrate, wherein after forming the first source/drain region, a first transistor lies over the first portion of the substrate and includes the first source/drain and the first gate electrode; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a second source/drain region over the second portion of the substrate, wherein after forming the second source/drain region, a second transistor lies over the second portion of the substrate and includes the second source/drain and the second gate electrode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the boron-containing species comprises B or BF<sub>2</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the second layer comprises an elemental transition metal, a transition metal nitride, a transition metal silicon nitride, or any combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising: removing the second layer from the first portion of the substrate before forming the first layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the first transistor is a PMOS transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first layer lies immediately adjacent to the gate dielectric layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second transistor is an NMOS transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second layer lies immediately adjacent to the gate dielectric layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first gate electrode does not include the first layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein forming the third layer is performed before implanting the boron-containing species.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the second layer over the first portion of the substrate and the second layer over the second portion of the substrate have substantially the same composition.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the PMOS transistor includes a metal-nitride material between the third layer and the gate stack and the gate dielectric layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the second layer comprises a third element that is a metallic element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein the first element is different from the third element.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the second layer over the first portion of the substrate and the second layer over the second portion of the substrate have substantially the same composition.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the NMOS transistor includes a metal-boride material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the metal boride material lies between the third layer and the gate dielectric layer of the NMOS transistor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The process of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the first layer and the second layer each comprise a different metallic element.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
