<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297438-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297438</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10785989</doc-number>
<date>20040226</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-065077</doc-number>
<date>20030311</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>666</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>M</subclass>
<main-group>10</main-group>
<subgroup>50</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>429120</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Cooling device for battery pack</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6709783</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Ogata et al.</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0211384</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hamada et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0004461</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hamada et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>07014616</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19950100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-76771</doc-number>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-167803</doc-number>
<date>20010600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-134177</doc-number>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Machine translation of JP 2001-076771 A.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>English Language Abstract of JP 2001-167803.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00010">
<othercit>English Language Abstract of JP 2001-76771.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>English Language Abstract of JP 2002-134177.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>429120</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>14</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040180257</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040916</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kimoto</last-name>
<first-name>Shinya</first-name>
<address>
<city>Toyohashi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Workman Nydegger</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Panasonic EV Energy Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Shizuoka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Cantelmo</last-name>
<first-name>Gregg</first-name>
<department>1745</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">In a battery pack including a plurality of rechargeable batteries arranged in parallel so as to interpose cooling medium paths therebetween, a cooling medium feeding device for feeding a cooling medium to the cooling medium paths is provided. One end of a heat pipe is thermally connected to the downstream side of the battery pack in the flow direction of the cooling medium, whereas the other end of the heat pipe is exposed in a portion having a lower temperature than the downstream side. In this structure, the battery pack is cooled by flow of the cooling medium, while a portion at the downstream side of the cooling medium is cooled with the heat pipe so as to uniformly cool the battery pack.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="152.99mm" wi="209.47mm" file="US07297438-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="186.77mm" wi="156.04mm" file="US07297438-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="212.01mm" wi="154.01mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297438-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="200.07mm" wi="145.20mm" file="US07297438-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="176.19mm" wi="156.89mm" file="US07297438-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="214.21mm" wi="158.41mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297438-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="167.13mm" wi="116.08mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297438-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="171.45mm" wi="156.04mm" file="US07297438-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="215.90mm" wi="161.21mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297438-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="191.35mm" wi="143.51mm" file="US07297438-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present disclosure relates to subject matter contained in priority Japanese Patent Application No. 2003-65077, filed on Mar. 11, 2003, the contents of which is herein expressly incorporated by reference in its entirety.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a cooling device for a battery pack composed of a plurality of rechargeable batteries arranged in parallel with a cooling medium path interposed therebetween.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">As a battery pack composed of a plurality of rechargeable batteries, the following type of battery pack is conventionally known so as to prevent a battery temperature from being increased due to heat emission caused by charge and discharge to decrease a battery output, a charge/discharge efficiency or a battery lifetime. A plurality of rechargeable batteries are arranged in parallel with a cooling medium path interposed therebetween. Then, a cooling medium feeding device for feeding a cooling medium to the cooling medium path is provided for the battery pack (for example, see Japanese Patent Laid-Open Publication No. 2001-167803).</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As such a type of battery pack, the following battery pack has also been conceived. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>, a rechargeable battery <b>22</b> is composed of a plurality of prismatic cells <b>23</b> by connecting their short side faces with each other. A plurality of thus constituted rechargeable batteries <b>22</b> are arranged in parallel so as to interpose cooling medium paths <b>24</b> for allowing a cooling medium to horizontally pass therethrough between the long side faces of the rechargeable batteries <b>22</b>, thereby constituting a battery pack <b>21</b>. A feeding hood <b>25</b> for feeding the cooling medium is connected to one end of the cooling medium path <b>24</b> of the battery pack <b>21</b>, whereas an exhaust hood <b>26</b> is connected to the other end of the cooling medium path <b>24</b>. In such a structure, the cooling medium is fed in a direction indicated with arrows on the cooling medium path <b>24</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In addition, the following type of battery pack is also known. In the battery pack, a container is provided so as to house a plurality of rechargeable batteries therein. The container is also thermally connected to circumferential wall surfaces of the rechargeable batteries so as to be in contact therewith. A heat pipe is provided for the container so as to externally dissipate heat transferred from the rechargeable batteries (for example, see Japanese Patent Laid-Open Publication Nos. 2001-76771 and 2002-134177).</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In the cooling device of the battery pack <b>21</b> having the structure as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>, if the cooling medium is allowed to pass through the cooling medium paths <b>24</b> between the rechargeable batteries <b>22</b> in the direction indicated with the arrows, a temperature of the cooling medium is elevated as the cooling medium passes through the cells <b>23</b> to cool them. When the cooling medium reaches the exhaust hood side, the cooling medium has lowered cooling performance. As a result, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10B</figref>, a temperature of the cell <b>23</b> on the downstream side of a flow direction of the cooling medium becomes higher than that of the cell <b>23</b> on the upstream side. Thus, a temperature variation ΔT between the cells <b>23</b> in the rechargeable battery <b>22</b> is increased. A variation in SOC between the cells <b>23</b> is also increased to elevate the maximum temperature Tmax of the cells <b>23</b> in the battery pack <b>21</b>, thereby adversely affecting the lifetime of the battery pack <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Moreover, in the structure of externally dissipating the heat generated by the rechargeable batteries housed in the container through the heat pipe as disclosed in Japanese Patent Laid-Open Publication Nos. 2001-76771 and 2002-134177, a large number of heat pipes or a large number of heat collector members are necessitated if cooling performance to efficiently cool all the rechargeable batteries is desired to be obtained. As a result, a space efficiency is disadvantageously lowered to increase the cost. Even though, it is difficult to uniformly cool each of the parts in the rechargeable battery.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In light of the above-mentioned conventional problems, the present invention has an object of providing a cooling device for a battery pack, which is capable of uniformly cooling each of the rechargeable batteries constituting the battery pack in a compact and inexpensive structure.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A cooling device for a battery pack according to the present invention includes a cooling medium feeding device for feeding a cooling medium to a cooling medium path in a battery pack composed of a plurality of rechargeable batteries arranged in parallel so as to interpose the cooling medium path therebetween, wherein an end of a heat pipe is thermally connected to a downstream side of the battery pack in a flow direction of the cooling medium, whereas the other end of the heat pipe is placed so as to be exposed in a portion of the battery pack having a lower temperature than the downstream side. The cooling medium is made to flow through the cooling medium path provided between the rechargeable batteries so as to cool each of the rechargeable batteries in a compact and inexpensive structure. In addition, the downstream side of the flow direction of the cooling medium where cooling performance may otherwise be lowered is cooled via the heat pipe. Consequently, the entire battery pack is uniformly cooled.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Moreover, the battery pack is configured such that the plurality of rechargeable batteries, each of which is a prismatic battery having rectangular long side faces and composed of a plurality of cells arranged along a longitudinal direction of the long side faces of the rechargeable battery, are arranged in parallel so as to interpose the cooling medium path between the long side faces of the rechargeable batteries. The battery pack is provided with the cooling medium feeding device for feeding the cooling medium along the longitudinal direction of the long side faces of the rechargeable batteries to the cooling medium path. In the thus constituted battery pack, the rechargeable batteries are cooled by flow of the cooling medium, and a temperature variation between the cells in each of the rechargeable batteries is reduced by cooling through the heat pipe. Accordingly, a variation in SOC between the cells is restrained to improve the lifetime of the rechargeable battery.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">While novel features of the invention are set forth in the preceding, the invention, both as to organization and content, can be further understood and appreciated, along with other objects and features thereof, from the following detailed description and examples when taken in conjunction with the attached drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref> are views showing a cooling device of a battery pack according to a first embodiment of the present invention, where <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> is a longitudinal sectional front view showing a schematic structure thereof, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> is a view showing a temperature profile over cells in a rechargeable battery;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded perspective view of the cooling device of the battery pack according to the first embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a partial sectional front view showing an external cooling medium path according to the first embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along the line IV-IV in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A and 5B</figref> are views showing a cooling device of a battery pack according to a second embodiment of the invention, where <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref> is a longitudinal sectional front view showing a schematic structure thereof, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref> is a view showing a temperature profile over cells in a rechargeable battery;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is an exploded perspective view of the cooling device of the battery pack according to the second embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along the line VII-VII in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8A and 8B</figref> are views showing a cooling device of a battery pack according to a third embodiment of the invention, where <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8A</figref> is a longitudinal sectional front view showing a schematic structure thereof, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8B</figref> is a view showing a temperature profile over cells in a rechargeable battery;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is an exploded perspective view of the cooling device of the battery pack according to the third embodiment; and</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10A and 10B</figref> are views showing a conventional cooling device of a battery pack, where <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref> is a longitudinal sectional front view showing a schematic structure thereof, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10B</figref> is a view showing a temperature profile over cells in a rechargeable battery.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Hereinafter, a cooling device of a battery pack according to a first embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A to 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A</figref>, <b>1</b>B, and <b>2</b>, a battery pack <b>1</b> serves as a driving power source for electric vehicles including a hybrid car. Ten to thirty rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> are arranged in parallel. A pair of end plates <b>3</b> are provided at both ends of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> in an aligning direction so as to interpose the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> therebetween. Then, the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> are integrally fixed by a binding member (not shown) to constitute the battery pack <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Each of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> is constituted as a battery module having the following structure. Each of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> has a flat and prismatic shape with long side faces whose horizontal length is larger than their height. A plurality of cells <b>4</b> (in the illustrated example, four cells) are arranged in a longitudinal direction of the long side faces of the rechargeable battery <b>2</b>. At the same time, the cells <b>4</b> are connected in series so as to be integrated, thereby constituting the rechargeable battery <b>2</b>. Each of the cells <b>4</b> is constituted by housing an electrode plate assembly and an electrolyte solution serving as a electric power generating element in a cell case made of a metal which provides high cooling performance.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The battery pack <b>1</b> generates a predetermined output voltage by serially connecting connection terminals (not shown) provided at both ends of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> through bus bars <b>5</b>. Moreover, cooling medium paths <b>6</b> are provided between the long side faces of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b>. A cooling medium feeding device <b>7</b> is provided so as to feed air, which is taken in from the interior of a vehicle as a cooling medium, from one end of the battery pack <b>1</b> in a horizontal direction in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> to the cooling medium paths <b>6</b>. The cooling medium feeding device <b>7</b> includes: a feeding hood <b>8</b> for feeding a cooling medium to each of the cooling medium paths <b>6</b>; and an exhaust duct <b>9</b> for exhausting the cooling medium flowing out of each of the cooling medium paths <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">On the outer face of one of the end plates <b>3</b>, a path formation member <b>10</b> made of a foamed heat insulating material and having a recessed portion <b>10</b><i>a </i>is attached as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 to 4</figref>. An external cooling medium path <b>11</b> is formed between the recessed portion <b>10</b><i>a </i>and the end plate <b>3</b>. An open end <b>11</b><i>a </i>of the external cooling medium path <b>11</b> is exposed in the feeding hood <b>8</b>, whereas the other open end <b>11</b><i>b </i>is externally exposed just before the exhaust duct <b>9</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">A frame-shaped thermally conductive member <b>14</b> including an insulating thermally conductive sheet <b>12</b> and a metal frame <b>13</b> is attached to an end face <b>1</b><i>a </i>of the battery pack <b>1</b> on the downstream side in a flow direction of the cooling medium. An end <b>15</b><i>a </i>of a heat pipe <b>15</b> is provided along a lower frame portion <b>13</b><i>a </i>of the metal frame <b>13</b> so as to be integrally attached and thermally connected thereto. The other end <b>15</b><i>b </i>of the heat pipe <b>15</b> is bent in an L-shape and is placed in the external cooling medium path <b>11</b> so as to be cooled by the cooling medium flowing therethrough. The end <b>15</b><i>a </i>serves as an endothermic portion, whereas the other end <b>15</b><i>b </i>serves as a heat dissipating portion. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the external cooling medium path <b>11</b> is constituted to have a reduced sectional area of the path at the end <b>15</b><i>b </i>of the heat pipe <b>15</b> so as to increase a flow rate of the cooling medium at the end <b>15</b><i>b</i>. With such a structure, a thermal conduction efficiency of the heat pipe <b>15</b> is improved. Furthermore, an angle of inclination of the end <b>15</b><i>b </i>is set so as to improve a thermal conduction efficiency with the cooling medium.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Examples of the insulating thermally conductive sheet <b>12</b> includes one including a base film carrying a silicone type or non-silicone type thermally conductive resin layer (for example, a “thermally conductive HT sheet” fabricated by Nitto Shinko Corporation), a sheet-type silicone gel containing a thermally conductive ceramic dispersed therein, and one including a base material made of fiber glass carrying such a sheet-type silicone gel.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">According to the above structure, the cooling medium feeding device <b>7</b> makes the cooling medium flow through the cooling medium paths <b>6</b> provided between the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b>, <b>2</b> so as to cool each of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b>. The entire battery pack <b>1</b> is efficiently cooled in a compact and inexpensive structure as compared with the case where the entire battery pack <b>1</b> is cooled by the heat pipe <b>15</b>. Furthermore, the downstream side in the flow direction of the cooling medium where the cooling performance may otherwise be lowered is cooled through the heat pipe <b>15</b>. Accordingly, the entire battery pack <b>1</b> is uniformly cooled.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In particular, each of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> is composed of a plurality of the cells <b>4</b> arranged in parallel in the longitudinal direction of the long side faces of the rechargeable battery <b>2</b>. In addition, the cooling medium paths <b>6</b> are formed between the long side faces of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> so that the cooling medium passes from one end of the rechargeable battery <b>2</b> in the longitudinal direction toward the other end. Accordingly, a height of the cross section of the battery pack <b>1</b> is approximately equal to a height of the rechargeable battery <b>2</b>, thereby achieving a compact structure.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Furthermore, the heat is conducted from the end face <b>1</b><i>a </i>of the battery pack <b>1</b> on the downstream side through the thermally conductive member <b>14</b> to the end <b>15</b><i>a </i>of the heat pipe <b>15</b> so that the heat is cooled at the end <b>15</b><i>b </i>of the heat pipe <b>15</b> by the cooling medium flowing through the external cooling medium path <b>11</b>. As a result, the end face <b>1</b><i>a </i>of the battery pack <b>1</b> is efficiently cooled. Moreover, since the external cooling medium path <b>11</b> is constituted by the path formation member <b>10</b> made of a foamed heat insulating material attached on the outer face of the end plate <b>3</b>. Thus, the end <b>15</b><i>b </i>of the heat pipe <b>15</b> is cooled in a lightweight and inexpensive structure.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Moreover, since the thermally conductive member <b>14</b> is composed of the insulating thermally conductive sheet <b>12</b> and the metal frame <b>13</b> to which the heat pipe <b>15</b> is attached, the thermally conductive member <b>14</b> can be applied to the rechargeable battery <b>2</b> which uses a metal battery case to enhance the cooling performance. Thus, extremely high cooling performance is obtained to improve an output characteristic and a lifetime characteristic. It is apparent that the insulating thermally conductive sheet <b>12</b> is not required if the outer faces of the battery cases of the rechargeable batteries <b>2</b> or those of the cells <b>4</b> are made of an insulating material.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As described above, a temperature of the cell <b>4</b> on the most downstream side in the flow direction of the cooling medium, which has the highest temperature, is effectively decreased as indicated in a solid line in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>, as compared with a temperature profile of the cell <b>4</b> without cooling with the heat pipe <b>15</b> as indicated with a broken line. Consequently, a temperature variation between the cells <b>4</b>, <b>4</b> in the rechargeable battery <b>2</b> is reduced from ΔT to Δt<b>1</b>. At the same time, the maximum temperature Tmax of the cell <b>4</b> in the battery pack <b>1</b> is decreased. In this manner, a variation in SOC between the cells <b>4</b>, <b>4</b> is restrained and the maximum temperature Tmax is decreased, whereby a lifetime of the battery pack <b>1</b> is improved.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">A second embodiment of a cooling device for a battery pack according to the present invention will now be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A to 7</figref>. The same components as those of the first embodiment are denoted by the same reference numerals, and the description thereof is herein omitted; only differences from the first embodiment will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In the second embodiment, the thermally conductive member <b>14</b> including the insulating thermally conductive sheet <b>12</b> and the metal plate <b>13</b> is attached to the downstream side of a side face <b>1</b><i>b </i>of the battery pack <b>1</b> (in the illustrated example, a lower face of the battery pack <b>1</b>) in the flow direction of the cooling medium. The side face <b>1</b><i>b </i>extends along the flow direction of the cooling medium in the battery pack <b>1</b> and is adjacent to the side faces on which the end faces <b>3</b> are provided. The one end <b>15</b><i>a </i>of the heat pipe <b>15</b> is integrally attached and thermally connected to the thermally conductive member <b>14</b>, whereas the other end <b>15</b><i>b </i>of the heat pipe <b>15</b> is placed in the external cooling medium path <b>11</b> formed between the end plate <b>3</b> and the path formation member <b>10</b> attached on the outer face of the end plate <b>3</b>. A heat insulating material <b>16</b> is attached to the upstream side of the lower face <b>1</b><i>b </i>of the battery pack <b>1</b> in the flow direction of the cooling medium.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In the illustrated example, the heat insulating material <b>16</b> is integrally formed with the path formation member <b>10</b>. In addition, the heat insulating material <b>16</b> covers the thermally conductive member <b>14</b>, the outer face of the end <b>15</b><i>a </i>of the heat pipe <b>15</b>, and the outer face of the end plate <b>3</b> provided on the opposite side of the end plate <b>3</b> to which the path formation member <b>10</b> is attached. The other open end <b>11</b><i>b </i>of the external cooling medium path <b>11</b> is exposed in the exhaust duct <b>9</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">According to the above-described structure, the heat dissipation from the cell <b>4</b> on the upstream side in the flow direction of the cooling medium is restrained by the heat insulating material <b>16</b>, while the heat is cooled by the cooling medium passing through the external cooling medium path <b>11</b> through the thermally conductive member <b>14</b> and the heat pipe <b>15</b> on the downstream side.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As a result, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>, a temperature variation between the cells <b>4</b>, <b>4</b> in the rechargeable battery <b>2</b> is reduced to Δt<b>2</b> that is smaller than Δt<b>1</b> obtained in the first embodiment. Accordingly, a variation in SOC between the cells <b>4</b>, <b>4</b> is restrained while the maximum temperature Tmax is lowered to improve a lifetime of the battery pack <b>1</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">Third Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">A third embodiment of a cooling device for a battery pack according to the present invention will now be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8A to 9</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In this third embodiment, the thermally conductive member <b>14</b> including the insulating thermally conductive sheet <b>12</b> and the metal plate <b>13</b> is attached to the nearly entire side face <b>1</b><i>b </i>of the battery pack <b>1</b> (in the illustrate example, a lower face of the battery pack <b>1</b>). The side face <b>1</b><i>b </i>extends along the flow direction of the cooling medium and is adjacent to the side faces on which the end plates <b>3</b> are provided. One or a plurality of heat pipes <b>15</b> are fixed to the metal plate <b>13</b> along the flow direction of the cooling medium.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">According to the above structure, the downstream side of the battery pack <b>1</b> in the flow direction of the cooling medium is also cooled by cooling derived from the upstream side, so that a temperature profile is made uniform between the upstream side and the downstream side in the flow direction of the cooling medium.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">As a result, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8B</figref>, a temperature variation between the cells <b>4</b>, <b>4</b> in the rechargeable battery <b>2</b> is reduced to Δt<b>3</b> that is smaller than Δt<b>1</b> obtained in the first embodiment and Δt<b>2</b> obtained in the second embodiment. Accordingly, a variation in SOC between the cells <b>4</b>, <b>4</b> is restrained. Moreover, since additional cooling by the cooling medium flowing through the external cooling medium path <b>11</b> by using the heat pipe <b>15</b> is not performed, a mean temperature of the entire battery pack <b>1</b> is decreased to a lesser extent in comparison with the first and second embodiments. However, since much more averaging effect is obtained, the maximum temperature Tmax is decreased to improve a lifetime of the battery pack <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">According to a cooling device for a battery pack of the present invention, the cooling medium is made to flow through the cooling medium paths between the rechargeable batteries in the battery pack so as to cool each of the rechargeable batteries. As a result, the battery pack is cooled in a compact and inexpensive structure. In addition, the downstream side in the flow direction of the cooling medium where cooling performance may otherwise be lowered is cooled through the heat pipe, so that the entire battery pack is uniformly cooled.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Although the present invention has been fully described in connection with the preferred embodiment thereof, it is to be noted that various changes and modifications apparent to those skilled in the art are to be understood as included within the scope of the present invention as defined by the appended claims unless they depart therefrom.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A cooling device for a battery pack including a plurality of rechargeable batteries arranged in parallel so as to interpose a cooling medium path therebetween, comprising:
<claim-text>a cooling medium feeding device for feeding a cooling medium to the cooling medium path in the battery pack;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat pipe having a first end that is thermally connected to a downstream side of the battery pack in a flow direction of the cooling medium and a second end; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an external cooling medium path formed outside the battery pack, wherein the second end of the heat pipe is exposed in the external cooling medium path.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the battery pack is configured such that the plurality of rechargeable batteries, each of which is a prismatic battery having rectangular long side faces and composed of a plurality of cells arranged along a longitudinal direction of the long side faces of the rechargeable battery, are arranged in parallel so as to interpose the cooling medium path between the long side faces of the rechargeable batteries, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the cooling medium feeding device feeds the cooling medium along the longitudinal direction of the long side faces of the rechargeable batteries to the cooling medium path.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>a thermally conductive member is attached to the downstream side of the battery pack in the flow direction of the cooling medium; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first end of the heat pipe is fixed to the thermally conductive member, whereas the second end of the heat pipe is exposed in a flow path of the cooling medium fed by the cooling medium feeding device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the thermally conductive member is attached to an end face of the battery pack on the downstream side in the flow direction of the cooling medium; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the external cooling medium path is formed outside one of end plates provided at both ends of the battery pack in a direction in which the rechargeable batteries are arranged.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the thermally conductive member is attached to the downstream side of a side face of the battery pack in the flow direction of the cooling medium, the side face extending along the flow direction of the cooling medium and being adjacent to side faces at both ends of the battery pack in a direction in which the rechargeable batteries are arranged;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat insulating material is attached to the upstream side of the side face in the flow direction of the cooling medium; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the external cooling medium path is formed outside one of end plates provided at both ends of the battery pack in the direction in which the rechargeable batteries are arranged.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>the external cooling medium path is made of a foamed heat insulating material attached to an outer face of one of the end plates.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>a thermally conductive member is attached to a nearly entire side face of the battery pack, the side face extending along the flow direction of the cooling medium and being adjacent to side faces at both ends of the battery pack in a direction in which the rechargeable batteries are arranged; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the heat pipe is fixed to the thermally conductive material along the flow direction of the cooling medium.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein
<claim-text>the thermally conductive member comprises: a metal plate to which the heat pipe is attached; and an insulating thermally conductive sheet interposed between the metal plate and the rechargeable batteries.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the external cooling medium path is made of a foamed heat insulating material attached to an outer face of one of the end plates.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The cooling device for a battery pack according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the thermally conductive member comprises: a metal plate to which the heat pipe is attached; and an insulating thermally conductive sheet interposed between the metal plate and the rechargeable batteries.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
