<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296666-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296666</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11174267</doc-number>
<date>20050629</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>239</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>45</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>192  328</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Heavy-duty cover for torque converter</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4785924</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jackel</name>
<date>19881100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192  329</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4821855</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jackel</name>
<date>19890400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192  329</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5407041</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fukunaga et al.</name>
<date>19950400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192  329</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5515955</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Victoria et al.</name>
<date>19960500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192  328</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0000682</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Yamamoto et al.</name>
<date>20060100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192  329</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>17</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>6</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>11</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Morin</last-name>
<first-name>Michael G.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Keene</city>
<state>NH</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Rey</last-name>
<first-name>Clifford F.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sonnax Industries, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Bellews Falls</city>
<state>VT</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Bonck</last-name>
<first-name>Rodney H.</first-name>
<department>3681</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A heavy-duty replacement torque converter cover for an automatic transmission designed to withstand the mechanical stresses generated during the torque converter lock-up cycle and other peak torque events in diesel engine pick-up trucks is disclosed. The present cover includes an internal spline that achieves up to a 70% increase in spline tooth engagement with a mating friction plate in the lock-up clutch in comparison to the original equipment cover providing increased torque capacity to the lock-up clutch. This is accomplished by machining a true internal spline within the cover on gear shaping equipment instead of utilizing the so-called Grob cold forming method, which provides only a simulated internal spline comprised of interlocking embossments having substantially less torque capacity than the present internal spline. The present cover also provides a thicker lock-up clutch surface, increased structural support for stud weldments, reduced stress cracking, improved heat dissipation, and increased service longevity.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="170.77mm" wi="104.73mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="219.03mm" wi="149.27mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="196.34mm" wi="150.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296666-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="241.13mm" wi="140.55mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="232.75mm" wi="135.21mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="210.90mm" wi="153.59mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="208.11mm" wi="149.35mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="223.60mm" wi="127.93mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="202.18mm" wi="167.39mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="230.04mm" wi="132.50mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="218.61mm" wi="128.10mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="196.68mm" wi="142.32mm" file="US07296666-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to automatic transmissions for land vehicles and, more particularly, to a heavy-duty torque converter cover for an automatic transmission of a land vehicle such as FORD E4OD and FORD 4R100 transmissions (hereinafter “FORD transmissions), and other similar automatic transmissions.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The torque converter of an automatic transmission replaces the clutch used in manual transmissions. It is the primary component for transmittal of power between the engine and the transmission in an automotive vehicle. The basic principle of torque converter operation can be observed by placing the blades of two electric fans opposite each other and turning on one of the fans. If one of the fans is turned on, the force of the air column produced will act upon the motionless blades of the other fan, which will begin turning and eventually reach a speed approaching the speed of the powered fan. The torque converter employs an analogous mechanism using automatic transmission fluid (hereinafter “ATF”) to provide a fluid coupling between the engine and the transmission of an automobile, which provides for a smooth conversion of torque from the engine to the mechanical components of the transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In the FORD transmissions a drum-shaped, torque converter cover (hereinafter “cover”) is connected by threaded studs to the engine flywheel at its forward end and is also welded to the converter pump (i.e. impeller) so that the impeller will rotate at engine speed. It is known in the industry that when the FORD transmissions, which were initially designed to operate behind a lower powered truck engine, are utilized in a higher horsepower vehicle such as behind a FORD F-250 or F-350 diesel engine or the FORD Titan V-10 truck engine, the structural strength of the original equipment manufacture (hereinafter “OEM”) torque converter cover is inadequate and as a result failure of the cover often occurs during converter lock-up and other peak torque events.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Further, in the automotive aftermarket engine tuning modules are marketed for such FORD trucks and SUVs, which deliver the most powerful, street-legal tuning available for towing the maximum loads allowed by the vehicle manufacturer. At such higher horsepower gains the OEM torque converter cover is overmatched and subject to mechanical stress and structural damage.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Thus, the present invention has been developed to resolve this problem and other shortcomings of the prior art.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF RELATED PRIOR ART</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">There are known prior art patents in the field and their discussion follows. One example of a lock-up device for a torque converter comprising a disk-shaped piston and a damper disk is disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 5,407,041 to Fukunaga et al. In this patent the piston <b>10</b> has in its radially outer end a spline part <b>10</b><i>a </i>engaged with a plurality of engaging projections <b>12</b> provided with circumferentially equal spacing and parallel to the rotational axis on a radially inner surface of the cylindrical projection <b>4</b><i>a </i>in the front cover <b>4</b>. However, such prior art torque converter covers are not adequate for the purposes of the present invention</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">U.S. Pat. Nos. 4,785,924 and 4,821,855 to Jackel disclose a lock-up clutch for a torque converter comprising a piston-like input element <b>15</b>, a first clutch disc <b>17</b> having radially inwardly extending torque transmitting portions, and a second disc <b>18</b> which is installed axially between the input element <b>15</b> and disc <b>17</b> and has radially outwardly extending torque transmitting portions <b>19</b><i>a</i>. The housing <b>10</b> includes a substantially cylindrical section <b>10</b><i>a </i>which surrounds the discs <b>17</b>, <b>18</b> and the input element <b>15</b> and whose internal surface is provided with torque transmitting portions <b>20</b><i>a</i>. Each torque transmitting portion <b>20</b><i>a </i>includes a radially inwardly extending prong <b>20</b><i>c </i>and the prongs <b>20</b><i>c </i>alternate with the torque transmitting portions <b>19</b><i>a </i>of the disc <b>18</b> in such a way that the disc <b>18</b> has freedom of axial movement relative to the cylindrical section <b>10</b><i>a</i>. The torque transmitting portions <b>20</b><i>a </i>jointly form a one-piece circular band at the inner side of the cylindrical section <b>10</b><i>a</i>. However, such a sheet metal band constructions (i.e. prongs <b>20</b><i>c</i>) spot welded to the inner surface of housing (i.e. cover) are not comparable to the structural features of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another example of a torque converter lock-up clutch including a torque converter cover having a simulated internal spline is disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 5,515,955 to Victoria et al. In the Victoria et al. patent a simulated internal spline comprised of interlocking embossments <b>74</b> is formed in the cover <b>14</b> using a cold forming method (i.e. the Grob process) to achieve the driving connection between the cover and a mating friction disc <b>60</b> carried in the lock-up clutch assembly. In this device mating teeth <b>72</b> formed about the periphery of the friction disc <b>60</b> engage the embossments <b>74</b> to permit torque transfer through the cover <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">However, it is known in the industry that such so-called Grob splines described hereinabove provide reduced spline tooth engagement (i.e. mating contact on tooth flank surfaces) and less torque capacity due to the inherent limitations of such cold forming processes. More particularly, such cold forming process can only be employed on lower grade steel alloys of a limited material thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In this respect the present invention substantially departs from the concepts and designs of the prior art, and in so doing provides a torque converter cover capable of withstanding the mechanical stresses generated within the torque converter lock-up clutch utilized in such FORD F-250 or F-350 diesel engines, FORD Titan V-10 engines, and other similar truck applications.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Accordingly, the present invention is a torque converter cover (hereinafter “cover”) for an automatic transmission such as FORD E4OD, FORD 4R100 transmission or other similar transmission, which is designed to withstand the mechanical stresses generated during the torque converter lock-up cycle and other peak torque events in the FORD transmissions utilized with FORD F-250 or F-350 diesel engines, FORD Titan V-10 engines and similar truck applications.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The present cover is fabricated from a high quality AISI 1026 steel forging and includes an internal spline manufactured in accordance with the American National Standards Institute (ANSI) B92.1-1996 Involute Splines standard. Manufactured to this standard the present internal spline provides up to a 70% increase in spline tooth engagement with the mating teeth of the OEM friction plate as compared to the tooth engagement achieved in the FORD OEM cover. This is accomplished by machining a true internal spline about the inner periphery of the present cover on conventional gear shaping equipment instead of utilizing the OEM cold forming method (i.e. so-called Grob method) that provides only a simulated internal spline comprised of interlocking embossments having substantially less torque capacity.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In addition, the present cover is constructed with a substantially thicker cross-section (i.e. axial length) at the converter clutch lock-up surface providing increased support for the threaded studs and eliminates the stud flanges, which attach the cover to the engine flywheel in the OEM version. The increased thickness at the lock-up surface also reduces stress concentration at the stud weldments and improves heat dissipation and service longevity.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">There has thus been outlined, rather broadly, the important features of the invention in order that the detailed description thereof that follows may be better understood, and in order that the present contribution to the art may be better appreciated. There are additional features of the invention that will be described hereinafter and which will form the subject matter of the claims appended hereto.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Other features and technical advantages of the present invention will become apparent from a study of the following description and the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The novel features of the present invention are set forth in the appended claims. The invention itself, however, as well as other features and advantages thereof will be best understood by reference to the following detailed description of an illustrative embodiment when read in conjunction with the accompanying figures, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a partial longitudinal cross-section of a torque converter assembly including an impeller assembly, a turbine assembly, and a torque converter cover and is labeled Prior Art;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded perspective view of the turbine, stator, and impeller assemblies of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrating the flow of automatic transmission fluid therein and is labeled Prior Art;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an enlarged partial longitudinal cross-section of the torque converter assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> showing further details thereof and is labeled Prior Art;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a partial longitudinal cross-section of a FORD E40D torque converter cover including a torque converter lock-up clutch wherein the present invention is utilized and is labeled Prior Art;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the FORD transmission lock-up clutch as seen from the section line <b>5</b>-<b>5</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and is labeled Prior Art;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a perspective view of a torque converter cover for the FORD E4OD transmission showing an array of embossments formed therein and is labeled Prior Art;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref> is a schematic representation of a cold rolling machine for producing a simulated internal spline in a hollow member and is labeled Prior Art;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref> is a schematic representation of a cold rolling machine using movable roller heads that are adapted to form simulated spline teeth on the periphery of a cylindrical member;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a perspective view of a heavy-duty torque converter cover of the present invention illustrating a true internal spline formed therein;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref> is a partial end view of the present torque converter cover illustrating an increased spline tooth engagement with the mating OEM friction plate;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref> is a partial end view of the FORD E4OD torque converter cover illustrating reduced spline tooth engagement with the mating OEM friction plate and is labeled Prior Art;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref> is a longitudinal cross-section of the present torque converter cover; and</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10B</figref> is an axial view of the present torque converter cover illustrating a true internal spline formed therein.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Prior to describing the present invention in detail, it may be beneficial to briefly review the structure and function of the torque converter and the torque converter clutch of an automatic transmission wherein the present invention is utilized. With further reference to the drawings there is shown therein a partial cross-sectional view of a torque converter assembly, indicated generally at <b>100</b> and illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, which is the primary component for transmittal of power between the engine and the automatic transmission or transaxle in an automotive vehicle. The torque converter assembly <b>100</b> provides for a smooth conversion of torque from the engine to the mechanical components of the transmission and also functions to multiply torque from the engine enabling the vehicle to achieve additional performance when necessary.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Torque converter assembly <b>100</b> is comprised of the following main sub-assemblies: (1) an impeller or converter pump assembly, indicated generally at <b>105</b>, which is the driving member; (2) a turbine assembly, indicated generally at <b>110</b>, which is the driven or output member; (3) a stator assembly, indicated generally at <b>115</b>, (4) a lock-up clutch, indicated generally at <b>120</b>, which is attached to the turbine assembly <b>110</b> to enable direct mechanical drive; and (5) a torque converter cover, indicated generally at <b>125</b>, which is typically welded at <b>121</b> to the impeller assembly <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Cover <b>125</b> is connected to the engine flywheel (not shown) by threaded studs <b>126</b> including stud flanges <b>126</b><i>a </i>so that it will rotate at engine speed. When the engine is running, the impeller assembly <b>105</b> acts as a centrifugal pump by picking up ATF at its center and discharging it at its rim between the impeller blades <b>103</b> as more clearly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> (see directional arrows <b>107</b>) establishing toroidal ATF out-flow passages <b>106</b> in fluid communication with toroidal ATF in-flow passages <b>108</b> defined by turbine blades <b>113</b>. The force of the ATF hits the turbine blades <b>108</b> and causes turbine assembly <b>110</b> to rotate as indicated (see directional arrows <b>109</b>). As the engine and impeller assembly <b>105</b> increase in speed, so does the turbine assembly <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As shown in further detail in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the prior art pressure plate <b>142</b> including peripheral teeth <b>143</b> engages inwardly extending projections or ribs <b>111</b> formed on the inner surface of cylindrical portion <b>125</b><i>a </i>of cover <b>125</b> and also attaches to the turbine hub <b>101</b> to provide a mechanical coupling of the engine to the transmission during the converter lock-up cycle. When the lock-up clutch <b>120</b> is applied, the slippage that occurs through the fluid coupling is eliminated thereby providing a direct mechanical drive for efficient transfer of engine torque to the drive wheels.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-2</figref>, the stator assembly <b>115</b> is located between the impeller assembly <b>105</b> and the turbine assembly <b>110</b> and is mounted on a stator carrier <b>114</b> that is connected to an inner race <b>119</b> through a one-way roller clutch <b>116</b>, which allows rotation in only one direction. The function of the stator assembly <b>115</b> is to redirect fluid returning from the turbine assembly <b>110</b> (see directional arrows <b>107</b>) to assist the engine in turning the impeller assembly <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The impeller assembly <b>105</b> is supported by an impeller hub <b>104</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), which extends from the impeller assembly <b>105</b> along its longitudinal axis and engages the hydraulic pump (not shown) in the transmission. The transmission input shaft <b>151</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) extends through the impeller hub <b>104</b> and delivers power to the transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">When the lock-up clutch <b>120</b> is installed within the torque converter cover <b>125</b> as most clearly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, a clutch release chamber <b>170</b> is formed between the cover <b>125</b> and the lock-up clutch <b>120</b>. When the fluid pressure behind the lock-up clutch <b>120</b> in the clutch apply chamber <b>180</b> exceeds the pressure in the release chamber <b>170</b>, the lock-up cycle is initiated and the clutch is energized establishing a mechanical torque flow path coupling the engine flywheel to the transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The latest versions (2000 to present date) of the FORD E4OD and 4R100 transmissions use a more modern system of converter lock-up that is used in virtually all transmissions being produced for automobiles today: the electronic/hydraulic converter clutch assembly. The lock-up cycle in the electronic converter clutch systems is controlled by the Powertrain Control Module (PCM) within the vehicle's onboard computer (not shown). The mechanical components of the FORD E4OD electronic/hydraulic converter clutch assembly are illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and indicated generally at <b>200</b>. In this embodiment the lock-up clutch assembly <b>200</b> includes a pressure plate <b>220</b>, a splined friction plate <b>224</b>, and a damper assembly, indicated generally at <b>240</b>, installed within the front cover <b>225</b> just forward of the turbine assembly as shown. Friction plate <b>224</b> includes friction material <b>222</b> on its aft surface, which contacts the adjacent forward surface of the pressure plate <b>220</b> during the converter lock-up cycle. Damper plate <b>244</b> also has friction material <b>222</b>′ on both its forward and aft surfaces, which engages a machined lock-up surface <b>245</b> formed on the outer periphery of the radial wall <b>224</b> of cover <b>225</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) during lock-up.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In a so-called multiplate lock-up clutch of the type shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the damper plate <b>244</b> includes springs <b>242</b> disposed within radially-spaced spring pockets <b>246</b> to absorb the impact of lock-up clutch engagement.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In operation when the vehicle is cruising and lock-up is appropriate, an electric solenoid is energized which opens the converter clutch control valve (not shown) increasing ATF pressure in the apply chamber <b>180</b>. This allows ATF pressure to act upon the pressure plate <b>220</b> to actuate the lock-up clutch. Friction plate <b>224</b> is guided forward in an axial direction by an array of teeth <b>247</b> formed about the periphery thereof as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. In the FORD transmissions teeth <b>247</b> on the friction plate <b>244</b> traverse an array of mating embossments <b>274</b> formed in the cover <b>225</b> by the so-called “Grob” method as hereinafter explained. Friction plate <b>224</b> together with pressure plate <b>220</b> act upon the damper assembly <b>240</b>, which, in turn, is forced against the lock-up surface <b>245</b> on the front cover. Pressure plate <b>220</b> is also connected to the transmission input shaft (not shown) via turbine hub <b>201</b> and, thus, a direct mechanical link between the engine and transmission is established.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">When converter lock-up is no longer required, a port opens that allows pressurized ATF to flow into the clutch release chamber <b>170</b> thereby releasing the lock-up clutch assembly <b>200</b>. ATF then flows out of the apply chamber <b>280</b> and the pressure plate <b>220</b> moves away from the lock-up surface <b>245</b> re-establishing the fluid coupling.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the FORD E4OD torque converter cover <b>225</b> is known in the industry as a “Grob cover” referring to Ernst Grob AG of Switzerland. Grob is the originator of a metal forming (i.e. cold forming) process utilized to form a simulated internal spline, indicated generally at <b>250</b>, comprised of an array of peripherally-spaced embossments <b>274</b> formed in cover <b>225</b>. A cold forming process suitable for fabricating the FORD E4OD cover <b>225</b> is referred to in the industry as the “Grob cold-rolling method” or “Grob method”. Tooling for cold forming workpieces of the kind described in this specification is manufactured by Ernst Grob AG of Switzerland, Kaltwalzmaschinen, Rohrgasse 9, 8708 Mannedorf, Switzerland.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The prior art Grob cover <b>225</b> is formed by a cold forming process using apparatus of the type schematically illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A and 7B</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref> shows a prior art device for cold forming embossments <b>176</b> on a hollow tubular member <b>178</b>. It involves placing the tubular member <b>178</b> over a forming die or mandrel <b>180</b> on which are formed external spline teeth. Rotary die heads <b>182</b>, <b>184</b> are rotated about their respective axes <b>186</b> and <b>188</b> being carried by stub shafts <b>190</b> and <b>192</b> respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">When the roller heads <b>182</b>, <b>184</b> follow the orbital motion pattern shown by directional arrows <b>194</b>, <b>196</b>, the roller heads impact the hollow member <b>178</b> thereby dynamically forging the material of the hollow member and forming embossments <b>176</b> whose geometry is determined by the geometry of the external teeth <b>180</b> of the central die. The same concept is used on an apparatus of the type shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref> where the roller heads are formed with spline tooth forming portions <b>198</b>, <b>199</b> formed on roller heads <b>102</b>, <b>104</b> respectively. The embossment forming portions <b>198</b>, <b>199</b> displace the metal into the spline tooth spaces of the mandrel <b>180</b>. At the same time metal flows in the axial direction causing the axial length of the workpiece to increase as the metal is displaced radially.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Although the apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A-7B</figref> is not directly adaptable in the form shown for forming embossments <b>274</b> in the cover <b>225</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>), the same principles are applied in its manufacture. The cylindrical portion <b>225</b><i>a </i>of the cover <b>225</b> can be mounted by specially designed holding fixtures (not shown), which correspond to the holding fixtures for the work pieces of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A-7B</figref>. Thus, roller heads <b>102</b>, <b>144</b> can be mounted for rotation about the Y axes illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref> such that the roller heads will impact the outer periphery of the cylindrical portion <b>225</b><i>a </i>of the cover <b>225</b> and displace metal inward to form the embossments <b>274</b> as the work piece is fed toward the roller heads in the direction of the Z axis illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref>. The cover <b>225</b> can be indexed in the direction indicated by the symbol “C” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref> such that the embossments <b>274</b> can be formed about the periphery of the cover as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Although the Grob cover <b>225</b> may fulfill the requirements of smaller truck drivetrains, the Grob process has inherent limitations which result in chronic torque converter malfunctions that typically occur when the FORD E4OD and 4R100 transmissions including the Grob cover are matched with a higher powered diesel engine, which is a popular option in FORD F-250 and F-350 pick-up trucks.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Initially, the Grob method must be utilized with relatively soft, ductile steel materials having a limited dimensional thickness (0.175 inches nominal) to facilitate cold forming of the simulated spline <b>250</b>. This results in a relatively low wall thickness at the cylindrical portion <b>225</b><i>a </i>of the Grob cover <b>225</b> in proximity to the embossments <b>274</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref>) as at <b>227</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Fabrication from such ductile sheet steel of a limited thickness results in a cover <b>225</b> that does not provide adequate structural support for the threaded studs <b>126</b> in diesel engine applications. It will be appreciated that studs <b>126</b> include perpendicular stud flanges <b>126</b><i>a </i>(<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>), which are attached to the outer surface of radial wall <b>224</b> of the cover <b>225</b> by weldment. The welding process hardens the area in proximity to the stud flanges <b>126</b><i>a </i>introducing a stress concentration in the surrounding material. As a result a common service complaint on the Grob cover <b>225</b> in FORD F-250 and F-350 diesel pick-up trucks is that the cover <b>225</b> often develops stress cracks adjacent the stud flanges <b>126</b><i>a</i>. Eventually stress cracks break through the cover <b>225</b> into the lock-up surface <b>245</b> as at <b>275</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) creating interruptions in the lock-up surface and causing disintegration of the friction material <b>222</b>′ on damper plate <b>244</b>, which results in malfunction of the lock-up clutch and failure of the torque converter.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In addition, the aforementioned limited material thickness results in a cover <b>225</b> wherein the lock-up surface <b>245</b> has insufficient mass to provide adequate heat dissipation within the lock-up surface. As a result the lock-up surface <b>245</b> is subject to overheating and distortion in diesel engine applications.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Thus, the present invention has been developed to resolve these problems and will now be described. The present invention is a heavy-duty torque converter cover, illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> and indicated generally at <b>325</b>, designed for direct replacement of the OEM cover <b>225</b> in FORD diesel pick-up trucks and other diesel engine applications.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Initially, cover <b>325</b> is machined from a high grade American Iron and Steel Institute (AISI 1026) steel forging in comparison to the lesser grade (AISI 1018 or comparable grade) ductile steel sheet typically utilized in the OEM cover <b>225</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Cover <b>325</b> comprises a drum-shaped body member <b>330</b> having a radial wall <b>324</b> extending in generally perpendicular relation to the longitudinal axis -A- (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10A</figref>). Radial wall <b>324</b> includes an outer peripheral portion defining a lock-up surface <b>345</b>. An integral cylindrical portion <b>324</b><i>a </i>of the cover <b>325</b> having an inner surface <b>324</b><i>c </i>extends axially from the radial wall <b>324</b> in concentric relation to axis -A-.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In the embodiment shown the present cover <b>325</b> includes a 54 tooth internal spline, indicated generally at <b>350</b>, which is manufactured in accordance with the American National Standards Institute (ANSI) B92.1-1996 Involute Splines and Inspection standard and the terms and definitions thereof, which are incorporated herein by reference. Of course, numerous other spline configurations manufactured in accordance with the ANSI B92.1-1996 standard are considered to be within the scope of the present invention and, thus, the embodiment shown herein is intended to be merely illustrative and not restrictive in any sense.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Internal spline <b>350</b> including spline teeth <b>374</b> is machined from inner surface <b>324</b><i>c </i>and dimensioned for mating engagement with teeth <b>247</b> formed on the OEM friction plate <b>224</b>. Critical to the present invention internal spline <b>350</b> provides up to a 70% increase in spline tooth engagement (i.e. tooth flank contact) with the mating teeth <b>247</b> formed on the OEM friction plate <b>224</b> in comparison to the tooth engagement achieved in the simulated spline <b>250</b> in the FORD E4OD cover <b>225</b> as produced by the Grob method. The increased spline tooth engagement is calculated based on spline data and dimensions and is achieved by machining spline <b>350</b> from solid stock with conventional gear shaping equipment, which provides more accurate spline dimensions, less variation in tooth form, and substantially increased mating tooth contact between the spline <b>350</b> and friction plate <b>224</b>. Spline tooth engagement achieved with the present internal spline <b>350</b> can range up to a 70% increase in comparison to the simulated OEM spline <b>250</b> depending on the blueprint tolerances specified for the spline dimensions.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">More particularly, it will be understood that the major diameter (D<sup>1</sup>) and minor diameter (D<sup>2</sup>) of the spline <b>350</b> are machined to a closer blueprint tolerance in the present spline <b>350</b> thereby increasing the actual length of tooth flank surfaces <b>374</b><i>a</i>, <b>374</b><i>b </i>(<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref>). This machining method provides increased tooth-to-tooth contact on the tooth flank surfaces <b>374</b><i>a</i>, <b>374</b><i>b </i>as shown in the comparison views of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A and 9B</figref>. The difference in spline tooth engagement between the present cover <b>325</b> with the mating friction ring <b>224</b> as compared to the OEM cover <b>225</b> with the mating friction ring <b>224</b> is most clearly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref> at the root and crest of each embossment <b>274</b> where substantial gaps as at <b>228</b>, <b>229</b> appear in the OEM version.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Thus, the present torque converter cover <b>325</b> provides up to a 70% increase in spline tooth engagement with the mating friction plate <b>224</b> of the lock-up clutch assembly resulting in increased torque capacity for the lock-up clutch, reduced wear on the tooth flank surfaces of the friction plate <b>224</b>, and improved service longevity for the torque converter.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10A and 10B</figref> it can be seen that the stud flanges <b>126</b><i>a </i>of the OEM cover <b>225</b> have been omitted in the present cover <b>325</b>, but the thickness (i.e. axial length A′) of the cover <b>325</b> at the lock-up surface <b>345</b> has been increased to a length equivalent to the sum of the axial stack-up dimensions (i.e. axial length A) of the OEM cover <b>225</b> (0.175 inches nominal) at the lock-up surface <b>245</b> plus the thickness (i.e. axial length F) of the stud flanges <b>126</b><i>a </i>(0.200 inches nominal) as previously shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Stated differently, A+F=A′, where A′ (0.375 inches nominal) or 0.365-0.385 inches is the axial length of the lock-up surface <b>345</b> in the present cover <b>325</b>. Thus, the critical working surfaces of OEM cover <b>225</b> (i.e. axial positions of lock-up surface <b>245</b> and mounting surface of flanges <b>126</b><i>a</i>) which abut the engine flywheel (not shown) are maintained in the present cover <b>325</b> (i.e. axial positions of lock-up surface <b>345</b> and mounting surface <b>324</b><i>b</i>) to ensure proper installation and function of the present replacement cover.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">The increased axial length A′ (i.e. thickness) of the lock-up surface <b>345</b> lends substantially more structural support and strength to studs <b>326</b>, which are welded directly to the exterior surface <b>324</b><i>b </i>of the present cover <b>325</b>. In the cover <b>325</b> the increased axial length A′ also eliminates the aforementioned stress cracking problem in proximity to OEM studs <b>126</b> caused by the stud weldments. In addition, heat dissipation within the lock-up surface <b>345</b> is substantially improved due to the increased thickness (i.e. axial length A′) of the lock-up surface.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Although not specifically illustrated in the drawings, it should be understood that additional equipment and structural components will be provided as necessary and that all of the components described above are arranged and supported in an appropriate fashion to form a complete and operative Heavy-Duty Torque Converter Cover incorporating features of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Moreover, although illustrative embodiments of the invention have been described, a latitude of modification, change, and substitution is intended in the foregoing disclosure, and in certain instances some features of the invention will be employed without a corresponding use of other features. Accordingly, it is appropriate that the appended claims be construed broadly and in a manner consistent with the scope of invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A replacement torque converter cover for replacement of an original equipment torque converter cover within an automatic transmission of a land vehicle, wherein said original equipment torque converter cover includes a drum-shaped member having a longitudinal axis, a radial wall perpendicular to said axis, wherein said radial wall further includes an original equipment lock-up surface having an axial length dimension, a plurality of threaded studs including integral stud flanges having an axial length dimension, wherein said stud flanges are mounted on an exterior surface of said radial wall for attachment of said cover to an engine of said vehicle, said drum-shaped member further including an integral cylindrical portion having an inner surface extending axially from said radial wall in concentric relation to said axis, wherein said inner surface includes an array of simulated spline embossments disposed at spaced intervals for mating engagement with at least one friction disc, wherein said at least one friction disc forms part of a lock-up clutch assembly installed within said cover, wherein said replacement torque converter cover comprises:
<claim-text>replacement drum-shaped member including a radial wall having an inner surface, wherein said inner surface comprises a modified lock-up surface having an increased axial length dimension equivalent to the sum of said axial length dimensions of said original equipment lock-up surface and said integral stud flanges; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a true internal spline machined on said inner surface of said cylindrical portion of said replacement drum-shaped member, wherein said true internal spline provides up to a 70% increase in spline tooth engagement with said mating friction disc in comparison to the spline tooth engagement achieved by said array of simulated spline embossments with said mating friction disc imparting increased torque capacity to said lock-up clutch assembly.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The replacement torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said true internal spline is comprised of fifty-four spline teeth.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The replacement torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said true internal spline is machined with conventional gear shaping equipment in accordance with ANSI B92.1-1996 Involute Splines and Inspection standard.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The replacement torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said axial length dimension of said modified lock-up surface measures in the range of 0.365-0.385 inches.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The replacement torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said replacement torque converter cover is manufactured from a steel forging in accordance with American Iron and Steel Institute (AISI 1026) specifications.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An improved torque converter cover for replacing an original equipment torque converter cover within an automatic transmission of a land vehicle, wherein said original equipment torque converter cover includes a drum-shaped member having a longitudinal axis, a radial wall including an outer peripheral portion defining an original equipment lock-up surface having an axial length dimension, a plurality of threaded studs including integral stud flanges having an axial length dimension, wherein said stud flanges are mounted on an exterior surface of said radial wall for attachment of said cover to an engine of said vehicle, said drum-shaped member further including an integral cylindrical portion having an inner surface extending axially from said radial wall, wherein said inner surface includes an array of simulated spline embossments disposed at spaced intervals for mating engagement with at least one friction disc, wherein said friction disc forms part of a lock-up clutch assembly installed within said cover, wherein the improvement comprises:
<claim-text>a replacement torque converter cover having a longitudinal axis, wherein said replacement torque converter cover includes a radial wall having an inner surface, wherein said inner surface comprises a modified lock-up surface having an axial length dimension equivalent to the sum of the axial length dimensions of said original equipment lock-up surface and said integral stud flanges.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The improved torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said replacement torque converter cover includes a true internal spline formed on said inner surface of said cylindrical portion of said cover, wherein said true internal spline provides up to a 70% increase in spline tooth engagement with said mating friction disc in comparison to the spline tooth engagement achieved by said array of simulated spline embossments with said mating friction disc imparting increased torque capacity to said lock-up clutch assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The improved torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said true internal spline is comprised of fifty-four spline teeth.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The improved torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said true internal spline is machined with conventional gear shaping equipment in accordance with ANSI B92.1-1996 Involute Splines and Inspection standard.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The improved torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said axial length dimension of said modified lock-up surface measures in the range of 0.365-0.385 inches.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The improved torque converter cover of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said replacement torque converter cover is manufactured from a steel forging in accordance with American Iron and Steel Institute (AISI 1026) specifications.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An improved torque converter for an automatic transmission of the type including an impeller assembly, a turbine assembly, a stator assembly, a lock-up clutch assembly, and an original equipment torque converter cover welded to said impeller assembly enclosing said turbine assembly, said stator assembly, and said lock-up clutch assembly therein, wherein said original equipment torque converter cover includes a drum-shaped member having a radial wall including an original equipment lock-up surface having an axial length dimension, a plurality of threaded studs including integral stud flanges having an axial length dimension, wherein said stud flanges are mounted on an exterior surface of said radial wall for attachment of said cover to an engine flywheel, said original equipment torque converter cover further including an integral cylindrical portion having an inner surface extending axially from said radial wall, wherein said inner surface includes an array of simulated spline embossments disposed at spaced intervals for mating engagement with a friction disc, wherein said friction disc forms a part of said lock-up clutch assembly installed in said cover, wherein the improvement comprises:
<claim-text>a replacement torque converter cover having a longitudinal axis, wherein said replacement torque converter cover includes a radial wall having an inner surface, wherein said inner surface comprises a modified lock-up surface having an increased axial length dimension equivalent to the sum of the axial length dimensions of said original equipment lock-up surface and said integral stud flanges.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The improved torque converter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein said replacement torque converter cover includes a true internal spline formed on said inner surface of said cylindrical portion of said replacement torque converter cover, wherein said true internal spline provides up to a 70% increase in spline tooth engagement with said mating friction disc in comparison to the spline tooth engagement achieved by said array of simulated spline embossments with said mating friction disc imparting increased torque capacity to said lock-up clutch assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The improved torque converter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said true internal spline is comprised of fifty-four spline teeth.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The improved torque converter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said true internal spline is machined with conventional gear shaping equipment in accordance with ANSI B92.1-1996 Involute Splines and Inspection standard.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The improved torque converter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein said axial length dimension of said modified lock-up surface measures in the range of 0.365-0.385 inches.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The improved torque converter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein said replacement torque converter cover is manufactured from a steel forging in accordance with American Iron and Steel Institute (AISI 1026) specifications.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
