<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296838-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296838</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11146446</doc-number>
<date>20050607</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>255</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>62</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>296 29</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Motor-driven vehicle with two vehicle bodies that are interconnected removably</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7028799</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lin</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180208</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0067151</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lin</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>280781</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0139410</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Fan</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180311</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0224275</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lin</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180311</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0283645</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lin et al</name>
<date>20061200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180208</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>296 29</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>29618701</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>296 351</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060273607</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061207</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lin</last-name>
<first-name>Ching-Yao</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chia Yi Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lin</last-name>
<first-name>Samuel</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chia Yi Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>McNees Wallace &amp; Nurick LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sunpex Technology Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Chia Yi</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Gutman</last-name>
<first-name>H</first-name>
<department>3612</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A motor-driven vehicle includes a first vehicle body with a fixed cantilever disposed at a front end thereof, and a second vehicle body with a fixed post disposed in front of the cantilever, and a connecting device interconnecting the first and second vehicle bodies removably. The connecting device includes a projection extending upwardly from a front end of the cantilever of the first vehicle body, and a spring-biased retaining block disposed movably on the post of the second vehicle body. The retaining block is biased to a position, where the projection is confined between the retaining block and the post so as to prevent relative movement of the first and second vehicle bodies.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="127.51mm" wi="163.66mm" file="US07296838-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="163.91mm" wi="144.36mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296838-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="218.69mm" wi="138.77mm" file="US07296838-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="160.27mm" wi="137.16mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296838-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="156.29mm" wi="142.58mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296838-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="164.25mm" wi="141.48mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296838-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to a motor-driven vehicle, and more particularly to a motor-driven vehicle that has two vehicle bodies, which are interconnected removably.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A conventional motor-driven vehicle includes front and rear vehicle bodies that are interconnected removably. When the front and rear vehicle bodies are removed from each other, it is convenient to transport and store the same. Such a vehicle, however, is typically hard to assemble and disassemble.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The object of this invention is to provide a motor-driven vehicle that includes two vehicle bodies, which can be interconnected and disconnected from each other with ease.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">According to this invention, a motor-driven vehicle includes a first vehicle body with a fixed cantilever disposed at a front end thereof, and a second vehicle body with a fixed post disposed in front of the cantilever, and a connecting device interconnecting the first and second vehicle bodies removably. The connecting device includes a projection extending upwardly from a front end of the cantilever of the first vehicle body, and a spring-biased retaining block disposed movably on the post of the second vehicle body. The retaining block is biased to a position, where the projection is confined between the retaining block and the post so as to prevent relative movement of the first and second vehicle bodies.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">These and other features and advantages of this invention will become apparent in the following detailed description of a preferred embodiment of this invention, with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a fragmentary, partly exploded perspective view of the preferred embodiment of a motor-driven vehicle according to this invention;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded perspective view of a retaining unit of the preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a fragmentary assembled perspective view of the preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a fragmentary, partly sectional side view of the preferred embodiment; and</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a fragmentary, partly sectional side view of the preferred embodiment, illustrating how an engagement rod of a second vehicle body is placed onto a horizontal supporting plate of a first vehicle body.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b>, <b>3</b> and <b>4</b>, the preferred embodiment of a motor-driven vehicle according to this invention includes a first vehicle body <b>1</b>, a second vehicle body <b>2</b> disposed in front of the first vehicle body <b>1</b>, and a connecting device <b>3</b> interconnecting the first and second vehicle bodies <b>1</b>, <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The first vehicle body <b>1</b> includes a hollow front end rod <b>11</b> having a square cross section, a projecting block <b>110</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) fixed on a middle portion of a top surface of the front end rod <b>11</b>, and a horizontal cantilever <b>12</b> fixed on the projecting block <b>110</b> and extending forwardly from a top end of the projecting block <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The second vehicle body <b>2</b> includes a mounting rod <b>21</b> parallel to the front end rod <b>11</b>, and a post <b>22</b> fixed on and extending upwardly from a middle portion of the mounting rod <b>21</b>. The post <b>22</b> is disposed in front of and aligned with the cantilever <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The connecting device <b>3</b> includes a horizontal supporting plate <b>31</b>, two vertical end plates <b>32</b>, two spaced-apart vertical side plates <b>33</b>, a horizontal engagement rod <b>34</b> connected fixedly to and spaced apart from the mounting rod <b>21</b>, a projection <b>35</b> extending upwardly from a front end of the cantilever <b>12</b>, and a retaining unit <b>36</b> disposed on a rear side of the post <b>22</b>. The supporting plate <b>31</b> has a rear side portion connected fixedly to a bottom end of the front end rod <b>11</b> of the first vehicle body <b>1</b>, and is disposed behind and below the projection <b>35</b>. The engagement rod <b>34</b> is disposed behind and parallel to the mounting rod <b>21</b>, and is superposed on the supporting plate <b>31</b>. The end plates <b>32</b> extend respectively, integrally, and upwardly from left and right ends of the supporting plate <b>31</b>. The engagement rod <b>34</b> is disposed between the end plates <b>32</b>. The end plates <b>32</b> are adjacent respectively to left and right ends of the engagement rod <b>34</b>. The side plates <b>33</b> extend integrally and upwardly from a front side of the supporting plate <b>31</b>, and are disposed in front of the engagement rod <b>34</b>. As such, the engagement rod <b>34</b> is confined between the front end rod <b>11</b> of the first vehicle body <b>1</b> and the side plates <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The projection <b>35</b> has a vertical rear side surface <b>351</b> and a forwardly and downwardly inclined top surface <b>352</b>. The retaining unit <b>36</b> includes a hollow housing <b>361</b> disposed fixedly on the post <b>22</b>, a retaining block <b>362</b> confined within the housing <b>361</b>, a pull rod <b>363</b> connected fixedly to the retaining block <b>362</b> and projecting outwardly from the housing <b>361</b>, and a resilient member <b>364</b> disposed within the housing <b>361</b> and biasing the retaining block <b>362</b> to project downwardly from the housing <b>361</b>. As a result, a lower end of the retaining block <b>362</b> abuts against the vertical rear side surface <b>351</b> of the projection <b>35</b> so as to confine the projection <b>35</b> between the retaining block <b>362</b> and the post <b>22</b>. This prevents relative movement of the first and second vehicle bodies <b>1</b>, <b>2</b>. The retaining block <b>362</b> is formed with a forwardly and downwardly inclined guiding surface <b>365</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The housing <b>361</b> consists of an L-shaped plate <b>366</b> and a U-shaped plate <b>367</b>. The resilient member <b>364</b> is configured as a coiled compression spring, and is sleeved on the pull rod <b>363</b> between the L-shaped plate <b>366</b> and the retaining block <b>362</b>. The housing <b>361</b> is formed with a slide slot <b>368</b> that has two closed ends. The retaining unit <b>36</b> further includes a limiting member <b>369</b> that is configured as a bolt. The limiting member <b>369</b> extends through the slide slot <b>368</b> in the housing <b>361</b>, and is connected fixedly to the retaining block <b>362</b>. As such, the retaining block <b>362</b> is movable within the housing <b>362</b> by a distance that is smaller than the length of the slide slot <b>368</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">During assembly of the first and second vehicle bodies <b>1</b>, <b>2</b>, the first vehicle body <b>1</b> is disposed behind the second vehicle body <b>2</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A front end of the first vehicle body <b>1</b> and a rear end of the second vehicle body <b>2</b> are slightly lifted, and are then moved toward each other so as to put the engagement rod <b>34</b> into a space defined among the supporting plate <b>31</b>, the end plates <b>32</b>, the side plates <b>33</b> and the front end rod <b>11</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. Subsequently, the front end of the first vehicle body <b>1</b> and the rear end of the second vehicle body <b>2</b> are released so that the first and second vehicle bodies <b>1</b>, <b>2</b> are leveled from their tilted positions, thereby resulting in the cantilever <b>12</b> moving forwardly toward the post <b>22</b>. Hence, the inclined top surface <b>352</b> of the projection <b>35</b> moves over the inclined guiding surface <b>365</b> of the retaining block <b>362</b> so as to push the retaining block <b>362</b> further into the housing <b>361</b>. When the projection <b>35</b> moves past the retaining block <b>362</b> to contact the post <b>22</b>, the resilient member <b>364</b> biases the retaining block <b>362</b> to move to the position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">When it is desired to remove the first and second vehicle bodies <b>1</b>, <b>2</b> from each other, the pull rod <b>363</b> is pulled upwardly. This results in separation of the retaining member <b>362</b> from the projection <b>35</b>, and therefore allows the engagement rod <b>34</b> to be removed from the first vehicle body <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">From the foregoing, it is evident that the first and second vehicle bodies <b>1</b>, <b>2</b> of the motor-driven vehicle of this invention can be interconnected and disconnected from each other with ease. The object of this invention is therefore achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">With this invention thus explained, it is apparent that numerous modifications and variations can be made without departing from the scope and spirit of this invention. It is therefore intended that this invention be limited only as indicated by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A motor-driven vehicle comprising:
<claim-text>a first vehicle body including a fixed cantilever disposed at a front end thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second vehicle body including a fixed post disposed in front of said cantilever; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a connecting device interconnecting said first and second vehicle bodies removably and including a projection extending upwardly from a front end of said cantilever of said first vehicle body, and a spring-biased retaining block disposed movably on said post of said second vehicle body and biased to a position, where said projection is confined between said retaining block and said post so as to prevent relative movement of said first and second vehicle bodies.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said projection has a vertical rear side surface, said connecting device further including a hollow housing, a pull rod and a resilient member, said housing being disposed fixedly on said post, said retaining block being disposed movably within said housing, said pull rod being connected fixedly to said retaining block and projecting outwardly from said housing, said resilient member being disposed within said housing and biasing said retaining block to project downwardly from said housing such that, during assembly of said first and second vehicle bodies, said cantilever of said first vehicle body is moved toward said post of said second vehicle body so that said projection pushes said retaining block to retract into said housing, after which said retaining block is biased by said resilient member to project downwardly from said housing so that a lower end of said retaining block abuts against said vertical rear side surface of said projection when said projection moves past said retaining block to contact said post, thereby confining said projection between said retaining block and said post.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said retaining block has a forwardly and downwardly inclined guiding surface, said projection further having a forwardly and downwardly inclined top surface that is movable over said guiding surface of said retaining block so as to retract said retaining block into said housing during assembly of said first and second vehicle bodies.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said housing is formed with a slide slot that has two closed ends, said connecting device further including a limiting member that extends through said slide slot in said housing and is connected fixedly to said retaining block so that said retaining block is movable within said housing by a distance that is smaller than a length of said slide slot.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said connecting device further includes a horizontal supporting plate that is connected fixedly to said first vehicle body and that is disposed behind and below said projection, and a horizontal engagement rod that is superposed on said supporting plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said support plate has opposite left and right ends, said connecting device further including two vertical end plates extending respectively, integrally, and upwardly from said left and right ends of said supporting plate, said engagement rod being disposed between said end plates.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein said first vehicle body includes a hollow front end rod extending parallel to said engagement rod, said supporting plate having a front side and a rear side portion that is connected fixedly to a bottom end of said front end rod, said connecting device further including two spaced-part vertical side plates extending integrally and upwardly from said front side of said supporting plate and disposed in front of said engagement rod so as to confine said engagement rod between said front end rod of said first vehicle body and said side plates.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said connecting device further includes a horizontal supporting plate that is connected fixedly to said first vehicle body and that is disposed behind and below said projection, and a horizontal engagement rod that is superposed on said supporting plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said support plate has opposite left and right ends, said connecting device further including two vertical end plates extending respectively, integrally, and upwardly from said left and right ends of said supporting plate, said engagement rod being disposed between said end plates.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The motor-driven vehicle as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said first vehicle body includes a hollow front end rod extending parallel to said engagement rod, said supporting plate having a front side and a rear side portion that is connected fixedly to a bottom end of said front end rod, said connecting device further including two spaced-part vertical side plates extending integrally and upwardly from said supporting plate and disposed in front of said engagement rod so as to confine said engagement rod between said front end rod of said first vehicle body and said side plates.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
