<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298872-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298872</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10920078</doc-number>
<date>20040817</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>248</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>19</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>382115</main-classification>
<further-classification>340  581</further-classification>
<further-classification>902  3</further-classification>
<further-classification>902  5</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Electronic identification system for form location, organization, and endorsment</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5857028</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Frieling</name>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>382116</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6976162</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ellison et al.</name>
<date>20051200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>713156</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0035485</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Mita et al.</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>705  2</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0003072</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Mathew et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>709223</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0006553</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>de Vries et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>707  1</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>16</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>20</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060064392</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060323</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Glisson</last-name>
<first-name>Shawn</first-name>
<address>
<street>805 Oxmoor Wood Pkwy.</street>
<city>Louisville</city>
<state>KY</state>
<postcode>40222</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Dinsmore &amp; Shohl LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Everett</last-name>
<first-name>Denise M.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Mehta</last-name>
<first-name>Bhavesh M</first-name>
<department>2624</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Kim</last-name>
<first-name>Charles</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Disclosed is a secure system of authentication including a means for retrieving information about an authenticated individual (i.e., citizens, customers, employees, patients, and subjects). More specifically, the system allows a person to execute forms (i.e., agreements, authorizations, contracts, records, and transactions) at any location across the world by submitting to a positive identification test. In turn, authorized personnel can receive all pertinent information associated with the authenticated individual. Importantly, the autonomy and the privacy of the individual with respect to his or her information are always maintained.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="159.51mm" wi="164.25mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="180.51mm" wi="174.33mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="209.63mm" wi="167.39mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="158.24mm" wi="176.02mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="153.67mm" wi="167.98mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="245.19mm" wi="196.85mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298872-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="227.84mm" wi="175.43mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="244.09mm" wi="195.33mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298872-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="242.65mm" wi="200.83mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298872-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="220.22mm" wi="181.86mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="201.51mm" wi="166.54mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="141.31mm" wi="181.19mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="135.13mm" wi="175.68mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00013" num="00013">
<img id="EMI-D00013" he="153.33mm" wi="188.13mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00013.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00014" num="00014">
<img id="EMI-D00014" he="148.93mm" wi="196.77mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00014.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00015" num="00015">
<img id="EMI-D00015" he="151.47mm" wi="199.56mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00015.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00016" num="00016">
<img id="EMI-D00016" he="215.98mm" wi="201.85mm" file="US07298872-20071120-D00016.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates to a system and method for positively identifying individuals (i.e., citizens, customers, employees, patients, and subjects) at particular points of interest in the areas of health care (e.g., hospitals or doctor's offices), security (e.g., banks, airports, etc.), and any other situations where an individual's identity must be confirmed. This invention further relates to a database that contains individual biometric data along with commonly accessed identifying information about the individual. The additional identifying information is contained in another category of databases that manage information about individuals including, but not limited to, health care information, security issue information, and any other private information which an individual wants to protect.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In today's society, it is becoming increasingly important for entities to accurately confirm the identity of individuals. This is made clear especially in three areas of challenge to current society: 1) the passage and maintenance of health care records; 2) the problem of identity theft to criminals and loss of control of identity in reference to other individuals or entities in society; and 3) security issues of national protection as required by certain functions (e.g., such as opening a bank account must now be monitored).</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In general, society currently relies on the confirmation of individuals through witnesses, identity cards, identity codes, and biometric identifiers. For example, a witness, (e.g., anyone from a casual acquaintance to a notary public) can confirm a person's identity. Also, identity cards and personal identification codes are utilized to authenticate an individual's identity. This system, however, is expensive and corruptible. Recognizing these deficiencies, attempts have been made to improve the situation.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">One example of a present identification system is a computer system that remotely records the arrival and departure times of field-based employees at various work sites through a telephone network. Specifically, the system detects an employee's automatic number identification data and further collects personal identification codes from the caller. The automatic number identification and personal identification code are used to identify the calling telephone. Once identified, the system can record the arrival and departure times of the employee.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">These systems have several disadvantages. First, automatic number identification (i.e. “Caller ID”) only indicates the telephone number of the particular telephone used to make the call. Automatic number identification information therefore does not affirmatively confirm the identity of an individual—only the location from which the individual is placing a telephone call. Similarly, personal identification codes are manually entered into a keypad by any individual and are therefore not reliable for confirming the identity of an individual. More specifically, mere receipt of a manually entered personal identification code does not assure that the person entering the personal identification code is the person assigned to the personal identification code.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Because these above systems are expensive, time consuming, or subject to misuse and abuse, biometric devices were created for use in identification and authorization. Generally, measurable and recordable body features (e.g., fingerprints, eye patterns, facial contours, or voice characteristics, etc.) are registered as biometric keys and, at the time of authentication, compared with the respective body features of a person to be authenticated.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A personal computer (“PC”) can be equipped with a device (e.g., a video camera) that makes it possible for the PC to record biometric information (e.g., facial features) and to reuse the information at a later time for authenticating an individual. The PC could grant access to a user only if it confirms the identity of the user by recognizing his or her facial features.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In any event, the above identification systems are currently used only on an ad hoc basis and are not connected to any national database. Furthermore, if a national database were implemented according to today's technology, the holder of the end data would not only have the individual's acquired data, but also the individual's unique identification information. Such systems do not protect the individual from fraud and abuse. Such systems cannot be currently regulated by US law to protect the identity of the individual from being passed to other entities. Over time the independence of the individual would be lost. In addition, they are also subject to fraud and abuse if implemented without a secured input device.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">There currently exists a need for a national or international system that would allow authentication of an individual at any given time and location while at the same time protecting the individual from loss of identity. On 27 Apr. 2004, President Bush called for the majority of Americans to have interoperable electronic health records within ten years. David J. Brailer, M.D., Ph.D., National Coordinator for Health Information Technology, released his report, “The Decade of Health Information Technology: Delivering Consumer-centric and Information-rich Health Care,” on 21 Jul. 2004. In the report he calls for four goals in the strategic framework: 1) Informed Clinical Practice; 2) Interconnected Clinicians; 3) Personalized Care; and 4) Improved Population Health.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">“The Uniting and Strengthening of America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Interrupt and Obstruct Terrorism” (USA Patriot Act) Act of 2001 (H.R. 3162-24 Oct. 2001) requires, among other things, the identification and verification by all financial institutions of accountholders and prospective accountholders (See, §326). Not only must an accountholder be identified and verified, records related to the accountholder, at a minimum name, address and other identifying information, must be maintained. In other words, a secure database is required.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Databases have been utilized for a number of years to store, sort and distribute information. Specifically, in the medical field, databases have been utilized to diagnose and treat patient diseases. David Bennahum illustrates the long known need for medical interconnectivity in an article entitled “Docs for Docs” in Wired Magazine in June 1995. He notes that doctors have been attempting to create a “virtual patient record” for years. Essentially, with the emergence of more efficient wireless networks, it was possible to link doctors, hospitals, insurance companies, and drug labs. As a result, doctors were able to record instructions, maintain medical information and receive general medical information from insurance companies and drug labs over a wireless network connecting several databases. Unfortunately, the system of interconnectivity has never occurred because the current system of authentication and security of the information electronically can not be secured in a timely, inexpensive manner that will not allow the possibility of identity loss.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">There exists a need for a system that positively authenticates an individual and that is connected to a database for immediate retrieval of an individual's medical information. More specifically, patients visiting such places as doctor's offices, dentist's offices and hospitals often need to complete forms they have completed in the past. A system that positively identifies an individual and that retrieves all pertinent information about the individual (e.g., name, insurance carrier, etc.) is greatly desired provided identity loss cannot occur.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">There exists a need for a secured system that allows an employee, client, patient, subject or citizen to interface with an organization, business, individual, or government agency when a positive identification for a form to be completed is required. Such form collections, authorizations, verifications and organization are increasingly costly and difficult to manage in a secure fashion. As more and more human abstract thought and information leaves the confines of the visible universe and enters the electronic “fifth dimension” in an ever growing world that occupies neither space nor time, where information about every individual can, as an electron around an atom, be every where and no where at the same time, it is important in the preservation of liberty that each individual's fifth dimension of abstract thought and information be protected and preserved as his or her own.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The present invention relates generally to a system of authentication and a means for retrieving information about the authenticated individual. More specifically, it allows a person to execute forms (e.g., consent forms) at any location across the world by submitting to a positive identification test. In turn, doctors and medical researchers can, for example, receive all pertinent information associated with the authenticated individual (e.g., medical history, allergies, consent forms, etc.).</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The present invention relates to an inexpensive and secure system that can positively authenticate an individual and retrieve pertinent information regarding that individual while leaving his or her fifth dimension of abstract knowledge and information secured. The present invention further allows an entity to interact with the general population to retrieve, process, and organize secured completed forms in a way that allow centralization of information while protecting the autonomy of the individual.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">An object of the present invention is to provide a system to allow an employee, client, patient, subject, or citizen to interface with an organization, business, individual, or government agency when a positive identification for a form to be completed is required. Another object of the present invention is to provide assured confirmation of an individual via a secure, tamper-proof system.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Yet another object of the present invention is to provide a system that can transmit its location when accessed to confirm the identity of the active user.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Yet another object of the present invention is to allow any entity (e.g., organization, business, individual, or government agency) that requires an individual to complete a form to ensure that the forms are properly signed and the identity of the signatory is verified.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Yet another object of the present invention is to allow any equipped entity (having the permission and verification of an individual) to access the individual's pertinent information, including all forms completed by the individual.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Another object of the present invention is to allow an individual to alter his or her pertinent information from a properly equipped personal computer.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Yet another object of the present invention is to allow an individual to fill out pertinent forms (i.e. agreements, authorizations, contracts, records, and transactions) at a convenient time and place.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Yet another object of the present invention is to allow communication of an individual's secured information from one Electronic Identification System's Biometrically Endorsed Repository Grid (“EISBERG”) to another, if he or she so chooses. If this decision is not made by the individual, then no communication may be made from an EISBERG with any other entity.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Other objects, features, and characteristics of the present invention, as well as the methods of operation and functions of the related elements of the structure, and the combination of parts and economies of manufacture, will become more apparent upon consideration of the following detailed description with reference to the accompanying drawings, all of which form a part of this specification.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">A further understanding of the present invention can be obtained by reference to a preferred embodiment set forth in the illustrations of the accompanying drawings. Although the illustrated embodiment is merely exemplary of systems for carrying out the present invention, both the organization and method of operation of the invention, in general, together with further objectives and advantages thereof, may be more easily understood by reference to the drawings and the following description. The drawings are not intended to limit the scope of this invention, which is set forth with particularity in the claims as appended or as subsequently amended, but merely to clarify and exemplify the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">For a more complete understanding of the present invention, reference is now made to the following drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> depicts an example of the Electronic Identification System for Form Location, Organization and Endorsement (“EISFLOE”) showing the flow of authentication and biometric parameter information between the components of the system.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> depicts an example of the Electronic Identification System's Comprehensive Authentication Process (“EISCAP”) that links an individual's biometric parameters with another piece of identification information in order to authenticate an individual in accordance with the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> depicts an example of the Electronic Identification System's Biometrically Endorsed Repository Grid (“EISBERG”) that allows an individual to complete specific forms (e.g., consent forms) by connecting to a secure database according to the preferred embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> depicts an example of an Electronic Identification System's Confirmed Unique Biometric Encounter (“EISCUBE”) for documenting the authentication of an individual according to the preferred embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> depicts a top view of the preferred embodiment of the Electronic Identification System Machine (“EIS Machine”) for interfacing between an individual and the system of the present invention, showing means for collecting information (including biometric information) from an individual for verification purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> depicts a front view of the interface of the preferred embodiment of the present invention, having a means for reading an identification card to authenticate the identity of an individual.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> depicts a rear view of the interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, showing electrical connection and outgoing data flow means for transferring collected information to the system.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref> depicts a side view of the interface shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, showing a locator device and a writing utensil for use in signature confirmation.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> depicts an example of internal components of the interface of the preferred embodiment of the present invention for securely retrieving and utilizing an individual's biometric information for authenticating an individual.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> depicts an example of internal components of the interface of an alternate embodiment of the present invention for securely retrieving and utilizing an individual's biometric information for authenticating an individual.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref> depicts a front view of the EIS Maker of the present invention, which is an alternative embodiment to the EIS Machine shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, without a digital camera, EIS Rink, or EIS Tray.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9B</figref> depicts a side view of the EIS Maker shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref>, showing a locator device and a power switch.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9C</figref> depicts a rear view of the EIS Maker shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9A</figref>, showing electrical connection and outgoing data flow means for transferring collected information to the system.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> depicts the ANI Network, which will exist for every individual that comes into the EISFLOE, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, comprising four complexes: Dianoian, Levavian, Nepheshian, and Meodian.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> depicts the Dianoian Complex shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, comprising three Systems: Educational, Intellectual, and Personality.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> depicts the Levavian Complex shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, comprising three Systems: Habitual, Charitable, and Preferential.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> depicts the Nepheshian Complex shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, comprising three Systems: Political, Philosophical, and Religious.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> depicts the Meodian Complex shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, comprising five Systems: Medical, Legal, Vocational, Financial, and Relational.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> depicts the Medical System (“Asklepios”) shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, comprising six Groups: Epione, Hygeia, Algla, Iasis, Akesis, and Panacea.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> depicts an example of a plexus of interaction between EISBERGs if an individual so authorizes. A Med-e-Plexus of ACB EISBERG in Asklepios is denoted. Arrows represent authorization points before personal data is transmitted.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As required, a detailed illustrative embodiment of the present invention is disclosed herein. However, techniques, systems and operating structures in accordance with the present invention may be embodied in a wide variety of forms and modes, some of which may be quite different from those in the disclosed embodiment. Consequently, the specific structural and functional details disclosed herein are merely representative, yet in that regard, they are deemed to afford the best embodiment for purposes of disclosure and to provide a basis for the claims herein, which define the scope of the present invention. The following presents a detailed description of a preferred embodiment (as well as some alternative embodiments) of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Referring first to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, an overview of the preferred embodiment of the present invention is depicted at the point of access by an individual. More specifically, the Electronic Identification System for Form Location, Organization and Endorsement (“EISFLOE”) <b>6</b> is shown, generally comprising three components: the point-of-access by a user of the system in EIS House <b>1</b>, Electronic Identification System's Comprehensive Authentication Process (“EISCAP”) <b>3</b>, and Electronic Identification System's Biometrically Endorsed Repository Grid (“EISBERG”) <b>5</b>, each of which will be described in more detail below.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">EIS House <b>1</b> serves as the site where the user elects to authenticate a form. The meaning of “form,” includes but is not limited to, agreements, authorizations, contracts, records, and transactions relating to all aspects of the Automated Numerical Identifier Network (“ANI Network”) (as defined below). A form may embody a physical document or alternatively an electronic document (e.g., a fillable internet webpage). Internet Access Device (“IAD”) <b>7</b> (e.g., a computer terminal) and EIS Machine <b>13</b> interact within EIS House <b>1</b>. Importantly, EIS Machine <b>13</b> receives no electronic data input. Through communication line <b>17</b>, EIS Machine <b>13</b> interfaces with IAD <b>7</b> when called upon by EISBERG <b>5</b>, requesting that the individual enter his or her electronic identity into EIS Machine <b>13</b>. Once the individual activates EIS Machine <b>13</b>, the electronic message is attached to a web page in IAD <b>7</b> and sent through communication line <b>9</b> to EISBERG <b>5</b>. Simultaneously EIS Machine <b>13</b> sends the electronic identity out of EIS House <b>1</b> to EISCAP <b>3</b> through communication line <b>15</b>, as noted below, which is discussed in greater detail below.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Generally, a user of the system of the present invention wishes to authorize a specific form (e.g., consent form, tissue donation authorization form, do not resuscitate form, etc.) and accesses the system of the present invention at EIS House <b>1</b>, via IAD <b>7</b>. The information regarding the specific form can be collected in any manner as described in greater detail below. Initially, IAD <b>7</b> transmits information regarding the requested form over communication line <b>9</b> to EISBERG <b>5</b>. In response, EISBERG <b>5</b> retrieves the requested form from an internal storage area (e.g., database) and transmits the corresponding form information over communication line <b>11</b> to IAD <b>7</b>. The user utilizes an interface device, such as a terminal, at EIS House <b>1</b> to supply the information required by the form and utilizes EIS Machine <b>13</b> to initiate authentication of the form. Generally, EIS Machine <b>13</b> transfers an electronic code along with the form from IAD <b>7</b> to EISBERG <b>5</b> while simultaneously transferring a coded signal containing a user's biometric and identification information over communication line <b>15</b> to EISCAP <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">As described above, in the preferred embodiment of the present invention an individual requests a form (e.g., a web page form) via IAD <b>7</b>. IAD <b>7</b> can comprise any computer means connected to EIS Machine <b>13</b> that is equipped with the proper identification peripherals as described in greater detail below.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Although all communication lines are depicted as physically connected communication means, it is contemplated that all communication within the system of the present invention can be completed by any method of information transfer, including but not limited to telephone trunk lines, T1 data lines, and wireless communication means.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Generally, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, EIS House <b>1</b> includes Internet Access Device (“IAD”) <b>7</b> and EIS Machine <b>13</b> and may be located anywhere in the world. EIS Machine <b>13</b> provides a secured means for an individual to interface with an organization, business, individual, or government agency when a positive identification for a form to be completed is required. Because EIS Machine <b>13</b> is tamper-proof and will transmit its location when accessed, the active participation of the person being identified (i.e., the user) can be assured.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">EIS Machine <b>13</b> is registered with EISFLOE system <b>6</b> and is assigned a unique identification code to confirm access when transmitting information to EISCAP <b>3</b> or EISBERG <b>5</b>. To access EISFLOE <b>6</b>, an individual who wishes to consider authorizing a form accesses IAD <b>7</b> by utilizing an interface (i.e., a terminal) in EIS House <b>1</b>. The user can enter information to indicate the desired form through any known means of collecting information, including, but not limited to, digital scan and keyboard means. EIS Machine <b>13</b> is capable of interfacing with IAD <b>7</b> in transmitting the response to a form that requires authentication over communication line <b>17</b> via IAD <b>7</b> to EISBERG <b>5</b> over communication line <b>9</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">EIS machine <b>13</b> also collects a user's identification information, which can be in the form of a number or other data. In the preferred embodiment, a user's identification information is the user's Social Security Number, but in alternative embodiments, a user's identification information may comprise a unique number assigned to the user or any other information that serves to uniquely identify the user (e.g., passport number, etc.). In addition, EIS machine <b>13</b> may collect a user's biometric information (e.g., digital picture, fingerprint, signature, DNA, etc.). Preferably, EIS Machine <b>13</b> is capable of transmitting a user's biometric information to EISCAP <b>3</b> over communication line <b>15</b>. In the preferred embodiment, EIS machine <b>13</b> is incapable of receiving any electronically transmitted information.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">While transferring the user's identification and biometric information to EISCAP <b>3</b>, EIS Machine <b>13</b> authorizes IAD <b>7</b> to transmit the completed form to EISBERG <b>5</b> via communication line <b>9</b>. EISBERG <b>5</b> then awaits authentication from EISCAP <b>3</b> via communication line <b>4</b>. Once EISCAP <b>3</b> verifies the identity of the user, it communicates back to EISBERG <b>5</b> via communication line <b>2</b>. The signal that the form has been successfully completed is then sent via communication line <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the system and method of authenticating the user via EISCAP <b>3</b> is shown. This is where the individual is judged to be authentic. Generally, EISCAP <b>3</b> is the system of connections between databases containing user identification numbers, biometric information, and other identifiers (both biometric and non-biometric). More specifically, EISCAP Server <b>21</b> receives the identification and biometric information from EIS Machine <b>13</b> via communication line <b>15</b>. Additional information, such as the location of EIS Machine <b>13</b> (sent by Global Positioning System (“GPS”) <b>23</b>) and the time of access (sent by atomic clock <b>25</b>) are recorded in EISCAP Server <b>21</b> with the biometric and identification information sent from EIS Machine <b>13</b>. This grouping of information serves to uniquely identify the transaction and is assigned tracking number <b>27</b>. The grouping of information (“EISCUBE” <b>29</b>) is sent to EISBERG Server <b>41</b> via communication line <b>31</b>, as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. In such a way, EISCAP <b>3</b> verifies the identity of the user of EIS Machine <b>13</b> in an accurate manner.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">In the preferred embodiment of the present invention, EISCAP <b>3</b> further comprises security monitoring system <b>33</b> that tracks the input of information over communication line <b>15</b>, GPS <b>23</b>, and atomic clock <b>25</b>. EISCAP <b>3</b> records the transfer of information between EIS Machine <b>13</b> and EISCAP <b>3</b> in EISCAP database <b>35</b>. Security monitoring system <b>33</b> further recognizes any irregular information and isolates any potential errors for review. By recording potential errors in EISCAP database <b>35</b>, security monitoring system <b>33</b> ensures that EISCAP <b>3</b> can provide accurate authentication information in a secure manner.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, EISBERG <b>5</b> performs the function of managing the forms that require authentication. For example, EISBERG <b>5</b> contains a plurality of forms (e.g., consent forms for treatment, do not resuscitate forms, etc.) that require an individual's consent for execution. Different EISBERGs can be connected to EISFLOE system <b>6</b> based on desired function. For example, different EISBERGs can include: (1) Tissue Donation/Consent for Cancer Research (or other medical illness research); (2) Medical Outcome Data Consent Form; (3) Medical Procedure Consent Form; (4) HIPAA compliance in medical offices, clinics, hospitals, etc.; (5) Insurance fraud prevention; (6) Sign-in system for employees/customers; (7) Verification for services rendered at a given time and place; and (8) Organ Donation for state non-profit organ donation organizations for organ procurement.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">As shown, in the preferred embodiment of the present invention, EISBERG <b>5</b> comprises EISBERG Server <b>41</b> for sending and receiving information via communication lines <b>2</b>, <b>4</b>, <b>9</b>, and <b>11</b>. Generally, as described in greater detail with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, EISBERG <b>5</b> receives information from IAD <b>7</b> corresponding to the form requested by the user and transmits the requested form to IAD <b>7</b> via communication line <b>11</b>. Once the user completes the form using the inputs at EIS Machine <b>13</b>, IAD <b>7</b> transmits the completed form to EISBERG Server <b>41</b> to await authentication. Authentication occurs when EISBERG Server <b>41</b> communicates with EISCAP Server <b>21</b> via communication line <b>4</b>. Then as also described in greater detail with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, EISBERG <b>5</b> receives information from EISCAP <b>3</b> (i.e., EISCUBE <b>29</b>) verifying the identity of the user.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">More specifically, EISBERG Server <b>41</b> receives and stores completed form information provided by IAD <b>7</b> over communication line <b>9</b>. EISBERG Server <b>41</b> further receives and stores EISCUBE <b>29</b> from EISCAP <b>3</b> over communication line <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">EISBERG Server <b>41</b> reviews EISCUBE <b>29</b> to ensure that the user has agreed to the content in the form transmitted to EISBERG <b>5</b> from IAD <b>7</b>. Once EISCUBE <b>29</b> is verified, EISBERG Server <b>41</b> matches EISCUBE <b>29</b> with the completed form sent to EISBERG <b>5</b> by IAD <b>7</b> and attaches EISCUBE <b>29</b> to the completed form to create a verified form. This verified form may then be retrieved at IAD <b>7</b> for internal use in EIS House <b>1</b> via communication line <b>11</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">It should be noted that signature information and photographic information can be collected-at EIS Machine <b>13</b> and utilized in the verification process in EISCAP <b>5</b>. Such signature and photographic information could be included in EISCUBE <b>29</b> and attached as part of the verified form in EISBERG <b>5</b>. All information received by EISBERG <b>5</b> (typically confidential or individual-sensitive information) remains within EISBERG Server <b>41</b> and can be used only in accordance with the agreement made with the individual. Such information is not transmitted to EISCAP <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">There is also a security program that runs at the EISCAP <b>3</b> for monitoring the system of EIS Machines and EISBERGs.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, shown is EISCUBE <b>29</b> utilized for authentication of the user at EIS Machine <b>13</b>. Specifically, EISCUBE <b>29</b> contains information such that the individual user can be positively authenticated. EISCUBE <b>29</b> is attached to a verified form to indicate that the form has been authenticated. Although EISCUBE <b>29</b> can comprise any number of personal identifiers, in the preferred embodiment depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, EISCUBE <b>29</b> comprises user name <b>51</b>, user signature <b>53</b>, tracking number code <b>27</b>, grid coordinates <b>55</b>, and date and time of transaction <b>57</b>. EISBERG <b>5</b> attaches EISCUBE <b>29</b> to the proper form as a symbol to the EISFLOW system that the user has been authenticated and verified the information contained in the form.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, one embodiment of EIS Machine <b>13</b> is depicted. Specifically, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows an example of the terminal associated with EIS Machine <b>13</b>, designed to receive identification and biometric information from the user. Shown is Liquid Crystal Display (“LCD”) <b>61</b> for display of requested information, EIS Keys <b>63</b> for entry of identification information, digital camera <b>65</b> for recording of biometric information such as facial features, EIS Crystal <b>67</b> for recording the user's fingerprint information, and EIS Rink <b>69</b> for entry of a user's signature. The inputted information is sent to EISCAP <b>3</b> as detailed above with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The cover of EIS Machine <b>13</b> is preferably fastened in such a way that it cannot be opened without deactivating the system.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, a front view of EIS Machine <b>13</b> is depicted. Specifically, in the preferred embodiment of the present invention, EIS Machine <b>13</b> is equipped with Digital Card Scan <b>71</b> having the ability to scan a user's identification card and transmit the individual's name to LCD <b>61</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, a rear view of EIS Machine <b>13</b> is depicted, including electrical plug <b>73</b> for supplying power to EIS Machine <b>13</b>. In addition, it is preferable to have communication lines connected from EIS Machine <b>13</b> to outgoing server port <b>75</b> (e.g., communication line <b>15</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) and to an IAD access port <b>77</b> (e.g., communication line <b>17</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). In the preferred embodiment, outgoing server port only handles outgoing data and the electrical plug is fixed in position. Alternate embodiments of the invention include portable EIS Machines powered by batteries, fuel cells or other available power source.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref>, shown is a side view of EIS Machine <b>13</b>, including GPS Antenna <b>79</b> for transmitting the location of EIS Machine <b>13</b> to EISCAP <b>3</b> during the authentication process. EIS Machine <b>13</b> also comprises EIS Pick <b>81</b>, a utensil to allow a user to sign his or her signature on EIS Rink <b>69</b>. In addition, the preferred embodiment of EIS Machine <b>13</b> contains On/Off Switch <b>83</b> to control whether the machine is accessible at any given time.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a cross section of the internal hardware of the preferred embodiment of EIS Machine <b>13</b> is depicted.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Specifically, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, hardware for LCD <b>61</b>, EIS Keys <b>63</b> digital camera <b>65</b>, EIS Crystal <b>67</b> and EIS Rink <b>69</b> (e.g., signature pad). In addition, hardware for digital card scan <b>71</b> is present within EIS Machine <b>13</b>. Memory <b>85</b> is located within EIS Machine <b>13</b> to store the information entered by the user. In the preferred embodiment of the present invention, memory <b>85</b> is flash memory and is erased entirely following each transaction. In this manner, no information is locally stored in EIS Machine <b>13</b> for any extended period of time, thereby eliminating any risk of user confidential information being stolen from EIS Machine <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Referring next to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, shown is the hardware configuration of the preferred embodiment of EIS Machine <b>13</b> of the present invention. As depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 7</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows LCD <b>61</b>, Camera <b>65</b> and Card Reader <b>71</b>. The preferred embodiment of EIS Machine <b>13</b> of the present invention further comprises circuit board <b>91</b> for connecting to the power source and the cover/screw entrance security system. Network Adapter <b>93</b> can comprise any standard network adapter for use with any high-speed data transfer connection, including wireless communication. Network adapter <b>93</b> is optimally configured to include encryption such that data is always forwarded across the network in a secure manner. GPS transmission device <b>95</b> can be activated for every data transmission to retrieve information to be sent to EISCAP <b>3</b>. GPS transmission device <b>95</b> can also be activated by EISCAP <b>3</b> in order to implement routine security checks.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9A-9C</figref> demonstrate a configuration of EIS Maker <b>8</b> which may in its present form accomplish similar tasks of EIS Machine <b>13</b> as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. For identification purposes it only contains the biometric device (e.g., EIS Crystal <b>67</b> in this representation) and EIS Keys <b>63</b> for identification number. It would be used when more complete forms of identification are not required such as with a repeat user.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">While the above description describes the preferred embodiment as it relates to obtaining authenticated consent forms, other embodiments of the present invention exist as well. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10-16</figref> generally depict several alternate embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> represents an ANI Network (Automated Numerical Identifier Network) and a conceivable connection of EISBERGs. An ANI Network may be unique to every individual and is composed of multiple EISBERGs. In the preferred embodiment, an ANI Network is composed of EISBERGs that are structured to form groups, which are then structured to form systems. Systems are structured to form complexes, which ultimately form an ANI Network. Each individual's ANI Network <b>101</b> may contain multiple complexes. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> depicts a preferred embodiment of a structure of complexes, namely the Dianoian Complex <b>103</b>, Levavian Complex <b>105</b>, Nepheshian Complex <b>107</b> and Meodian Complex <b>109</b>. A complex may be broken down into systems of EISBERGS, as clarified below with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11-14</figref>. In the preferred embodiment, the Dianoian Complex <b>103</b> refers to the complex of EISBERGs in the ANI Network that are contained in the individuals' educational system, intellectual system, and personality system. It is intended to cover all aspects of activities, business, and transactions primarily related to the individuals' “mind” and its development. The Levavian Complex <b>105</b> refers to the complex of EISBERGs in the ANI Network that are contained in the individuals' habitual system, charitable system, and preferential system. It is intended to cover all aspects of activities, business, and transactions primarily related to the individual's “emotion” and its development. The Nepheshian Complex <b>107</b> refers to the complex of EISBERGs in the ANI Network that are contained in the individuals' political system, philosophical system, and religious system. It is intended to cover all aspects of activities, business, and transactions primarily related to the individuals' “soul” and its development. The Meodian Complex <b>109</b> refers to the complex of EISBERGs in the ANI Network that are contained in the individuals' medical system, legal system, vocational system, financial system, and relational system. It is intended to cover all aspects of activities, business, and transactions primarily related to the individuals' “strength” and its development.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> depicts the structure of three systems of EISBERGs that comprise the Dianoian Complex <b>103</b>. The Educational System (“Minerva”) <b>111</b>, Intellectual System (“Athena”) <b>113</b> and Personality System (“Galen”) <b>115</b> are each composed of groups of EISBERGs. Together, the three systems form the Dianoian Complex <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> depicts the structure of three systems of EISBERGs that comprise the Levavian Complex <b>105</b>. The Habitual System (“Artemis”) <b>117</b>, Charitable System (“Hestia”) <b>119</b> and Preferential System (“Apollo”) <b>121</b> are each composed of groups of EISBERGs. Together, the three systems form the Levavian Complex <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> depicts the structure of three systems of EISBERGs that comprise the Nepheshian Complex <b>107</b>. The Political System (“Zeus”) <b>123</b>, Philosophical System (“Thales”) <b>125</b> and Religious System (“Enlil”) <b>127</b> are each composed of groups of EISBERGs. Together, the three systems form the Nepheshian Complex <b>107</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> depicts the structure of three systems of EISBERGs that comprise the Meodian Complex <b>109</b>. The Medical System (“Asklepios”) <b>129</b>, Legal System (“Hammurabi”) <b>131</b>, Vocational System (“Demeter”) <b>133</b>, Financial System (“Plutus”) <b>135</b> and Relational System (“Hera”) <b>137</b> are each composed of groups of EISBERGs. Together, the five systems form the Meodian Complex <b>109</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> represents the structure of Medical System <b>129</b>, a component of the Meodian Complex <b>109</b> as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>. Medical System <b>129</b> is comprised of Soothing Arts and Sciences Group (“Epione”) <b>139</b>, Health Maintenance Group (“Hygeia”) <b>141</b>, Physical Beauty Arts and Science Group (“Aigla”) <b>143</b>, Healing Treatment Centers Group (“Iasis”) <b>145</b>, Convalescence Arts and Sciences Group (“Akesis”) <b>147</b> and Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology, and Medical Equipment Group (“Panacea”) <b>149</b>. Each group is comprised of EISBERGs which represent the smallest entity that may store information. Each EISBERG is an independent unit capable of releasing information about an individual. Each individual may elect preferences as to how each EISBERG will release the individual's information. A plexus refers to the communication of various EISBERGs that an individual has linked together between and/or within groups, systems, or complexes that have been given authority by the individual to communicate information within the individual's ANI Network.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> represents a plexus formed in the Medical System <b>129</b> by the interaction of four groups of EISBERGs with independent organizations. Arrows represent authorization points before data is transmitted. Epione <b>138</b> and Hygeia <b>141</b> transmit information to Medical Research Organization <b>157</b>. Iasis <b>145</b> transmits information to Physician Clinics <b>151</b>, Hospital Companies <b>153</b> and American Cancer Biorepository Organization <b>155</b>. Physician Clinics <b>151</b> transmits information to Medical Research Organization <b>157</b>, Hospital Companies <b>153</b> and American Cancer Biorepository Organization <b>155</b>. State Cancer Registry Agency <b>159</b> receives information from American Cancer Biorepository Organization <b>155</b>, while Panacea <b>149</b> receives information from American Cancer Biorepository Organization <b>155</b> and Medical Research Organization <b>157</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">While the present invention has been described with reference to one or more preferred embodiments, such embodiments are merely exemplary and are not intended to be limiting or represent an exhaustive enumeration of all aspects of the invention. The scope of the invention, therefore, shall be defined solely by the following claims. Further, it will be apparent to those of skill in the art that numerous changes may be made in such details without departing from the spirit and the principles of the invention. It should be appreciated that the present invention is capable of being embodied in other forms without departing from its essential characteristics.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An apparatus for providing an individual's authorized consent forms comprising:
<claim-text>(a) a computer system comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>first input means for receiving said individual's identification information; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>second input means for receiving said individual's biometric information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) a database connection system comprising: a database comprising an individual's identification information and an individual's biometric information; at least one recording means for recording additional identification data indicating the time and/or location of receipt of the individual's identification information and biometric information; a database comprising the additional identification data; and verification means for authenticating the identity of said individual by verifying said individual's identification information and said individual's biometric information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) authorization means for recording said individual's consent on a consent form, wherein the authorization means is located remotely from the systems defined by (a) and (b) which are located remotely from each other; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(d) at least five communication lines: a first communication line for transmitting information from (a) to (b); a second communication line for transmitting information from (a) to (c); a third communication line for transmitting information from (c) to (a); a fourth communication line for transmitting information from (b) to (c); and a fifth communication line for transmitting information from (c) to (b).</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said identification information is a unique number.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said second input means is a fingerprint scanner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising at least one storage means for storing said authorized consent forms.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein location of receipt of the individual's identification information is determined by a global positioning system in communication with the database integration system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the database integration system further comprises a security apparatus to prevent fraudulent use of said apparatus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said first input means and said second input means are located remotely from said verification means and said authorization means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the computer system defined by (a) further comprises an internet access device (IAD) such that the first communication line transmits information from the IAD to (b), and the second communication line transmits information from (b) to the IAD.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An apparatus for providing authorized consent forms comprising:
<claim-text>a first computer device for receiving an individual's identification information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second computer device for authenticating the identity of said individual; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third computer device for recording authorized consent forms, wherein information flow between the first and second computer devices is unidirectional while information flow between the first and third computer devices and the second and third computer devices is bi-directional.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said first computer device receives said individual's biometric information.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said first computer device comprises a fingerprint scanner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said identification information is a unique number.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said third computer device comprises a database for storing consent forms.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein any of said first computer device, said second computer device, said third computer device are located in a composite unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said first computer device comprises an electronic identification system (EIS) machine and an internet access device (IAD), wherein the individual's identification information is transmitted from the EIS machine to the IAD and a consent form is requested at the IAD.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. An apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein the EIS machine is incapable of receiving any electronically transmitted information.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
