<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296590-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296590</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11060770</doc-number>
<date>20050218</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-050021</doc-number>
<date>20040225</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>207</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>18</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137399</main-classification>
<further-classification>137398</further-classification>
<further-classification>137588</further-classification>
<further-classification>2224644</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Liquid suction device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2656849</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Deatrick et al.</name>
<date>19531000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>137399</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2985423</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tischler et al.</name>
<date>19610500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>251210</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3217761</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Shapiro</name>
<date>19651100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4057174</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Trujillo et al.</name>
<date>19771100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4068681</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>McNair et al.</name>
<date>19780100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>137588</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4306670</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Oshikubo et al.</name>
<date>19811200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5769284</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Vargas et al.</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2224644</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6955185</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Rauworth et al.</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>137588</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>44-37 981</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19950400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>9-297146</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19971100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137398</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137399</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137588</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2224644</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2224646</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251210</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050183774</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050825</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kitagawa</last-name>
<first-name>Nobuhiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Akashi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Birch, Stewart, Kolasch &amp; Birch, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sysmex Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kobe-shi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Keasel</last-name>
<first-name>Eric</first-name>
<department>3753</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Price</last-name>
<first-name>Craig</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A liquid suction device for sucking liquid contained in a vessel is described herein. A liquid retention room having an inflow port and an exhaust port is inserted into the vessel via an opening at an upper part of the vessel and is dipped in the liquid. A suction tube connected to the exhaust port extends from the opening of the vessel. A float member provided in the liquid retention room is enabled to open and close the exhaust port. The liquid is retained in the liquid retention room when the retention room is dipped in the liquid and the float member is floated upward so as to open the exhaust port. The retained liquid is exhausted from the inflow port when the liquid is lessened to reach a predetermined volume or below, and the exhaust port is closed by the float member.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="195.33mm" wi="144.02mm" file="US07296590-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="212.94mm" wi="159.51mm" file="US07296590-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="239.44mm" wi="162.22mm" file="US07296590-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="244.26mm" wi="173.57mm" file="US07296590-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="225.38mm" wi="160.61mm" file="US07296590-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="213.95mm" wi="174.58mm" file="US07296590-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="218.78mm" wi="165.69mm" file="US07296590-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="218.86mm" wi="172.21mm" file="US07296590-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a liquid suction device for sucking liquid contained in a vessel, more particularly to a liquid suction device used such as a reagent suction device used for sucking a reagent for analysis from a vessel in which the reagent is contained and supplying a clinical testing device with the reagent through a supply tube.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In the field of a clinical test, there has been an advancement of automation in the pursuit of an improved measurement precision and also laborsaving. More specifically, clinical testing devices such as a dispensation device for dispensing a certain amount of liquid, a dilution device for diluting a test specimen to a certain ratio, and further, an automatic analyzer in which a process from quantifying the test specimen and dispensing a reagent to a measurement step is fully automated, have been so far developed.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In the foregoing clinical testing devices, a supply tube, such as a pliable tube, is connected to an opening portion of the vessel in which the reagent for analysis is contained, and the reagent sucked from the vessel is supplied to a predetermined spot through the supply tube.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Meanwhile, a suction tube to be inserted into the reagent for analysis is provided in the vessel, the reagent in the vessel is sucked through the suction tube and supplied to the clinical testing device through the supply tube.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">As the suction tube, a pliable tube, a hard pipe or a suction tube whose edge is connectively provided with a member having a certain weight and a suction hole for preventing the suction tube from floating onto a liquid surface in the reagent vessel is used.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">However, in using the pliable suction pipe or hard suction pipe, or suction tube whose edge is connectively provided with the member having the certain weight and the suction hole, in the case in which the reagent is sucked when a remaining volume of the reagent in the vessel is lessened, air as well as the reagent is inconveniently sucked into the tube, which generated air bubbles in the sucked reagent.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Of the generated air bubbles, those having a large size disappear within a relatively short length of time, while it takes a considerable amount of time before the small and fine air bubbles disappear. Further, when the air bubbles are once generated in the reagent including a surface active agent, it becomes even more difficult for the air bubbles to disappear.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In the foregoing situation, there was a resultant problem that the generated air bubbles were counted as particles in measuring the number of the particles in the measured test specimen by means of a particle counting device, for example, which made it not possible to obtain an accurate number of the particles included in the measured test specimen.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Further, in a device which is designed to obtain a concentration of a measurement object included in the test specimen through the measurement of an absorbance, the small and fine bubbles change the absorbance, which generated another problem that it was not possible to obtain the accurate concentration.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In order to solve the foregoing problems, a liquid suction device (see No. H09-297146 of the Publication of the Unexamined Japanese Patent Applications) comprising a suction pipe dipped in liquid contained in a liquid vessel and a float valve provided in the vicinity of an edge of the suction pipe for gradually closing an opening at the edge of the suction pipe in response to the lowering of a liquid level in the liquid vessel has been proposed.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">However, in the recited liquid suction device, the edge of the suction pipe is gradually closed in response to the liquid level, which generates a risk of the air incorporation immediately before the halt of the liquid suction. Therefore, the foregoing method may not be suitably applied to certain types of analyzers and testing devices.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Therefore, a main object of the present invention is to provide a liquid suction device having a simple constitution and capable of preventing the air incorporation in the liquid suction when the remaining volume of the liquid in the vessel is lessened to reach a certain value.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A liquid suction device for sucking liquid contained in a vessel of a first aspect of the present invention comprises: a liquid retention room inserted into the vessel via an opening at an upper part of the vessel and dipped in the liquid, the liquid retention room having an inflow port and an exhaust port; a suction tube connected to the exhaust port and extending from the opening of the vessel; and a float member provided in the liquid retention room, the float member opening and closing the exhaust port, wherein the liquid is retained in the liquid retention room when the retention room is dipped in the liquid, the float member is floated upward so as to open the exhaust port, the liquid in the vessel is sucked outward via the inflow port, the retention room, the exhaust port and the suction tube, the retained liquid is exhausted from the inflow port when the liquid in the vessel is lessened to reach a predetermined volume or below, and the exhaust port is closed by the float member.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A liquid suction device for sucking liquid contained in a vessel of a second aspect of the present invention comprises: a liquid retention room comprising a first room having an inflow port for inviting inflow of the liquid contained in the vessel and a second room communicated with the first room and having an exhaust port for exhausting the liquid inflow from the inflow port; a suction tube provided so as to communicate with the exhaust port, the suction tube for sucking the liquid contained in the vessel; and a float member housed in the second room.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a longitudinal sectional view of a liquid suction device before the liquid suction device is inserted into and fixed to a liquid vessel.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top view of a base-end member of the liquid suction device.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a sectional view taken along A-A line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a sectional view taken along B-B line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a sectional view taken along C-C line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a bottom view of a top-end member of the liquid suction device.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a sectional view taken along D-D line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is an illustration of an operation of the liquid suction device.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is an illustration of the operation of the liquid suction device.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is an illustration of the operation of the liquid suction device.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Hereinafter, the present invention is described in detail based on an embodiment shown in the drawings though the present invention is not limited to the embodiment.</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">Constitution of Liquid Suction Device</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a longitudinal sectional view of a liquid suction device and liquid vessel before the liquid suction device is inserted into and fixed to a liquid vessel.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">As shown in the drawing, a liquid suction device <b>1</b> comprises a top-end member <b>2</b> inserted into a liquid vessel <b>100</b> via an upper opening thereof and dipped in liquid <b>101</b>, a base-end member <b>3</b> mounted on the upper opening of the liquid vessel <b>100</b>, and a column-shaped member <b>4</b> whose one end is combined with the top-end member <b>2</b> by means of screws and another end is combined with the base-end member <b>3</b> by means of screws. The top-end member <b>2</b>, base-end member <b>3</b> and column-shaped member <b>4</b> are made of polyacetal resin having a chemical-resistant property.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The top-end member <b>2</b> comprises a retention room <b>7</b> for retaining the liquid <b>101</b>, an inflow port <b>5</b> for inviting the inflow of the liquid <b>101</b> into the retention room <b>7</b>, an exhaust port <b>6</b> for exhausting the liquid <b>101</b> from the retention room <b>7</b>, a flow channel <b>9</b> for opening the retention room <b>7</b> to the atmospheric air, a flow channel <b>8</b> for sucking the liquid from the inflow port <b>5</b> via the retention room <b>7</b> and the exhaust port <b>6</b>, a float member <b>10</b> of a spherical shape provided in the retention room <b>7</b> so as to move in vertical directions and having a specific gravity smaller than that of the liquid <b>101</b>, and an O ring <b>11</b> for closing the exhaust port <b>6</b> by means of the float member <b>10</b>. Nipples <b>8</b><i>a </i>and <b>9</b><i>a </i>are provided in respective end portions of the flow channels <b>8</b> and <b>9</b>. The float member <b>10</b> is made of a foaming member using ethylenepropylene rubber which is a material having a specific gravity smaller than that of the liquid. Further, the float member is a spherical body having an outer diameter larger than an opening diameter of the exhaust port so as to open and close the exhaust port.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The retention room <b>7</b> comprises a first room <b>31</b> comprising the inflow port <b>5</b> and a second room <b>32</b> comprising the exhaust port <b>6</b> communicatingly linked via communicating port <b>33</b> to the first room. The float member <b>10</b> is housed in the second room.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top view of the base-end member <b>3</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a sectional view taken along A-A line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the base-end member <b>3</b> comprises a main body member <b>12</b> and a cap member <b>13</b> mounted on the main body member <b>12</b> from an upper direction so as to slide in directions of arrows A and B. Junction flow channels <b>14</b> and <b>15</b> are vertically formed in the main body member <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Nipples <b>14</b><i>a </i>and <b>14</b><i>b </i>are connected to both ends of the junction flow channel <b>14</b>. A nipple <b>15</b><i>a </i>is connected to a lower end of the junction flow channel <b>15</b>. In the cap member <b>13</b>, an elastic member <b>16</b> is provided in a position thereof facing an upper end of the junction flow channel <b>15</b>, and the elastic member <b>16</b> is thereby adapted to close the upper end of the junction flow channel <b>15</b> when the cap member <b>13</b> moves in the direction of the arrow A.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The cap member <b>13</b> has an opening <b>17</b> in a position thereof facing the nipple <b>14</b><i>b</i>. The nipple <b>14</b><i>b </i>is constantly protruded from the cap member <b>13</b> via the opening <b>17</b>, and a suction tube (not shown) from an external device is connected to the nipple <b>14</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a sectional view taken along B-B line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. As shown in the drawing, the base-end member <b>3</b> comprises springs <b>18</b> for elastically drawing the cap member <b>13</b> from the main body member <b>12</b> in a direction of an arrow B and an adjustment bolt <b>19</b> for adjusting a distance by which the cap member <b>13</b> is drawn away from the main body member <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Further, the main body member <b>12</b> has a flow channel <b>20</b> for opening to the atmospheric air whose one end is open to an upper surface of the main body member <b>3</b> and another end is connected to the junction flow channel <b>14</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. In the cap member <b>13</b>, an elastic member <b>21</b> is disposed so as to face an opening end of the flow channel <b>20</b>, and the elastic member <b>21</b> is thereby adapted to close the opening end of the flow channel <b>20</b> when the cap member <b>13</b> moves in an direction of an arrow A.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a sectional view taken along C-C line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">As shown in the drawing, the main body member <b>12</b> has a vertical through hole <b>22</b>, the cap member <b>13</b> has an opening <b>23</b> coaxial with the through hole <b>22</b>, an internal part of the liquid vessel <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is constantly opened to the atmospheric air via the through hole <b>22</b> and the opening <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a bottom view of the base-end member <b>2</b> of the liquid suction device. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a sectional view taken along D-D line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As shown in the drawings, the inflow port <b>5</b> is formed in such manner as to have an opening area of at least ten times as large as an opening area of the exhaust port <b>6</b>. Therefore, as described later, the liquid <b>101</b> in the retention room <b>7</b> is instantly replaced by air via the inflow port <b>5</b> when the liquid <b>101</b> reaches a certain volume or below so that the float member <b>10</b> can immediately close the exhaust port <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the nipples <b>14</b><i>a </i>and <b>15</b><i>a </i>of the base-end member <b>3</b> are respectively connected to the nipples <b>8</b><i>a </i>and <b>9</b><i>a </i>of the top-end member <b>2</b> by means of pliable tubes <b>24</b> and <b>25</b>. Further, an engaging piece <b>26</b> having a flange shape is horizontally protruded from an outer peripheral surface of the main body member <b>12</b>. The engaging piece <b>26</b> is thereby adapted to engage the main body member <b>12</b> with an end portion of the opening when the main body member <b>12</b> is inserted into the upper opening of the liquid vessel <b>100</b>. The pliable tubes <b>24</b> and <b>25</b> are formed from a silicon tube having a chemical-resistant property.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">A cap <b>102</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is an accessory attached to the liquid vessel <b>100</b>, an upper part of which is opened and closed by means of screws. When the liquid suction device <b>1</b> according to the present invention is used, the cap <b>102</b> is previously provided with a processed insertion hole. A lower edge of the cap member <b>13</b> is provided with an engaging piece <b>27</b> protruding outward in a flange manner, which is engaged with an edge part of the hole provided in the cap <b>102</b> when the cap <b>102</b> is fastened so that the cap member <b>13</b> moves downward in the direction of the arrow A (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) in response to the fastening operation.</p>
<p id="h-0007" num="0000">Method of Use</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the foregoing constitution, the suction tube of the external device (for example, clinical testing device), which is not shown, is connected to the nipple <b>14</b><i>b </i>of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and the liquid suction device <b>1</b> is inserted into the liquid vessel <b>100</b> by a user through the hole of the cap <b>102</b> attached to the liquid vessel <b>100</b>. The liquid vessel <b>100</b> contains the liquid <b>101</b> of a liquid level L. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an edge of the top-end member <b>2</b> contacts a bottom surface of the liquid vessel <b>101</b>, and the base-end member <b>3</b> is accordingly held in the upper opening of the liquid vessel <b>100</b>. Thus, an edge of the top-end member <b>2</b> is formed so as to face the bottom surface of the liquid vessel, and the top-end member <b>2</b> is thereby held substantially vertical to the bottom surface. When the top-end member <b>2</b> is formed so as to face the bottom surface of the vessel, the inflow port <b>5</b> and the exhaust port <b>6</b> of the top-end member <b>2</b> are also disposed so as to face the bottom surface of the vessel. Further, a clearance for sucking the liquid is formed between the inflow port <b>5</b> and the bottom surface of the vessel because the edge of the top-end member <b>2</b> is protruded relative to a peripheral part of the inflow port <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">At this point, the cap <b>102</b> is not at all fastened with respect to the screws at the opening of the liquid vessel <b>100</b>, and the cap member <b>13</b> of the base-end member <b>3</b> is being lifted in the direction of the arrow B as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Therefore, the junction flow channel <b>14</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) is opened to the atmospheric air via the flow channel <b>20</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>), and further, the retention room <b>7</b> is opened to the atmospheric air via the flow channel <b>15</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). Accordingly, the liquid <b>101</b> flows into the retention room <b>7</b> from the inflow port <b>5</b> to fill the retention room <b>7</b> in accordance with a principle of a communicating tube. The float member <b>10</b> rises in response to a buoyancy of the liquid <b>101</b> in the retention room <b>7</b> and is thereby detached from the exhaust port <b>6</b>. The liquid <b>101</b> rises to a same height as the liquid level L of the liquid <b>101</b> in the pliable tubes <b>24</b> and <b>25</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Next, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, when the user fastens the screws to the cap <b>102</b>, the cap <b>102</b> is correspondingly engaged with the engaging piece <b>27</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 3</figref>) so that the cap member <b>13</b> is drawn downward. The opening end of the junction flow channel <b>15</b> and the opening end of the flow channel <b>20</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) are respectively closed by means of the elastic members <b>16</b> and <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Next, when a negative pressure is applied from the external device via the nipple <b>14</b><i>b</i>, the liquid <b>101</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, is sucked into the external device through the inflow port <b>5</b>, retention room <b>7</b>, exhaust port <b>6</b>, flow channel <b>8</b>, pliable tube <b>24</b>, junction flow channel <b>14</b> and nipple <b>14</b><i>b</i>, in response to which the liquid level L is gradually lowered. At this point, the liquid level of the liquid in the pliable tube <b>25</b> is maintained at the same height as the liquid level L of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> because the junction flow channel <b>15</b> is closed.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Then, when the liquid level L in the liquid vessel <b>100</b> becomes lower than the inflow port <b>5</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> to thereby invite the inflow of air, the liquid <b>101</b> retained in the pliable tube <b>25</b> and the retention room <b>7</b> is instantly replaced by the air and thereby escapes from the inflow port <b>5</b>. At the same time, the float member <b>10</b> drops and thereby closes the exhaust port <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Therefore, in the case in which the negative pressure from the external device is thereafter continuously applied, the negative pressure serves to make the float member <b>10</b> tightly contact the exhaust port <b>6</b>. Then, the liquid <b>101</b> continuously stays in the flow channel <b>8</b>, pliable tube <b>24</b> and junction flow channel <b>14</b>, which eliminates the possibility of the air being sucked into the external device.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In due course of time, the external device detects that the suction is no longer possible and halts the suction operation. When the user releases the screws of the cap <b>102</b> until the state shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> arrives, the junction flow channel <b>14</b> is opened to the atmospheric air. The liquid remaining in the junction flow channel <b>14</b>, pliable tube <b>24</b> and flow channel <b>8</b> is correspondingly exhausted into the vessel <b>100</b> via the inflow port <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The float member <b>10</b> in the tight contact with the exhaust port <b>6</b> is then released from the exhaust port <b>6</b>. The user extracts the liquid suction device <b>1</b> from the liquid vessel <b>100</b> with the external device remaining connected and install the device in a new liquid vessel as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The same suction operation as described so far can be thereby easily repeated.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">In the present embodiment, the top-end member is forcibly dipped in the liquid by means of the column-shaped member inserted from the opening of the vessel, however, may be formed from a material having a specific gravity larger than that of the liquid to be thereby dipped in the liquid as a result of its own weight.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In many cases, the liquid is a test specimen such as a hemolytic agent. Therefore, the top-end member is preferably formed from a material having a chemical-resistant property.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">An example of the material having a specific weight substantially larger than that of the liquid and chemical-resistant property usable for the top-end member, which can be dipped by its own weight, is preferably stainless steel (SUS316).</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In the present embodiment, the polyacetal resin is used as the top-end member, however, chloroethylene resin may be alternatively used.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In the present embodiment, the foaming member using ethylenepropylene rubber is used as the float member provided in the retention room and serving to open and close the exhaust port. However, a foaming member using silicon rubber may be alternatively used.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In the present embodiment, the silicon tube is used as the suction tube connected to the exhaust port and extending from the opening of the vessel. However, a pliable tube such as a urethane tube or a Teflon (registered trade mark) tube or a hard pipe such as a chloroethylene pipe or a stainless pipe may be alternatively used.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In the present embodiment, the pliable tube is used as the suction tube connected to the exhaust port and extending from the opening of the vessel. However, the suction tube may be provided in the column-shaped member.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A liquid suction device designed to for sucking liquid contained in a vessel and, comprising:
<claim-text>a liquid retention room inserted into the vessel via an opening at an upper part of the vessel and dipped in the liquid, the liquid retention room having an inflow port and an exhaust port;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a suction tube connected to the exhaust port and extending from the opening of the vessel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a float member provided in the liquid retention room, the float member opening and closing the exhaust port,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the liquid is retained in the liquid retention room when the retention room is dipped in the liquid, the float member is floated upward so as to open the exhaust port, the liquid in the vessel is sucked outward via the inflow port, the liquid retention room, the exhaust port and the suction tube, the retained liquid is exhausted from the inflow port when the liquid in the vessel is lessened to reach a predetermined volume or below, and the exhaust port is closed by means of the float member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base-end member having first and second openings to atmospheric air and mounted on the opening of the vessel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first opening and closing means and a second opening and closing means for respectively opening and closing the first and the second atmospheric-air openings.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the retention room comprises the inflow port at a position lower than a position of the exhaust port, the retained liquid is exhausted from the inflow port in response to inflow of air from the inflow port resulting from the lessened liquid in the vessel, and the exhaust port is closed by means of the float member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the retention room comprises a first room provided withhaving the inflow port and a second room communicatingly linked to with the first room and provided withhaving the exhaust port, and the float member is housed in the second room.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a first communicating portion for communicating the first atmospheric-air opening and the flow channel of the retention room;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second communicating portion for communicating the second atmospheric-air opening and the suction tube.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the first and the second atmospheric-air openings are opened by means of the first opening and closing means and the second opening and closing means when the retention room is dipped in the liquid and closed by means of the first opening and closing means and the second opening and closing means when the liquid in the vessel is sucked outward via the suction tube.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the float member is formed from a spherical body having an outer diameter larger than an opening diameter of the exhaust port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the float member is made of a material having a specific gravity smaller than a specific gravity of the liquid.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the float member is made of foaming ethylenepropylene rubber or foaming silicon rubber.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>an opening area of the inflow port is larger than an opening area of the exhaust port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the inflow port has an opening area at least ten times as large as an opening area of the exhaust port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A liquid suction device designed for sucking liquid contained in a vessel and, comprising:
<claim-text>a liquid retention room comprising a first room having an inflow port for inviting inflow of the liquid contained in the vessel and a second room communicatingly linked to with the first room and having an exhaust port for exhausting the liquid inflow from the inflow port;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a suction tube provided so as to communicate with the exhaust port, the suction tube for sucking the liquid contained in the vessel; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a float member housed in the second room,</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base-end member having first and second openings to atmospheric air and mounted on the opening of the vessel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first opening and closing means and a second opening and closing means for respectively opening and closing the first and the second atmospheric-air openings.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the float member is formed from a spherical body having an outer diameter larger than an opening diameter of the exhaust port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the float member is made of a material having a specific gravity smaller than a specific gravity of the liquid.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the float member is made of foaming ethylenepropylene rubber or foaming silicon rubber.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>an opening area of the inflow port is larger than an opening area of the exhaust port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the inflow port has an opening area at least ten times as large as an opening area of the exhaust port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the inflow port is disposed at a position lower than a position of the exhaust port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a partition wall for dividing the first room and the second room, the partition wall being provided with a communicating port communicatingly linked to with the first room and the second room at an upper part thereof.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the communicating port is disposed at a position higher than a position of the inflow port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A liquid suction device as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the exhaust port is disposed at a position higher than a position of the inflow port and a position lower than a position of the communicating port.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
