<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298629-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298629</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11341675</doc-number>
<date>20060130</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-024450</doc-number>
<date>20050131</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361808</main-classification>
<further-classification>439 67</further-classification>
<further-classification>174262</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Circuit board for mounting a semiconductor circuit with a surface mount package</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5207585</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Byrnes et al.</name>
<date>19930500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439 66</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5381307</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hertz et al.</name>
<date>19950100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361767</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5764485</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lebaschi</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361774</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5896037</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kudla et al.</name>
<date>19990400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324755</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6756663</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Shiraishi et al.</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257686</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7005586</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Duley</name>
<date>20060200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>174261</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7031170</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Daeche et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361813</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0043560</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Clarkson et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361782</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>03285338</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19911200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-078240</doc-number>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-309201</doc-number>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361808</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 67</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174255</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174262</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174266</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>12</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060172566</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060803</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nakajima</last-name>
<first-name>Yuji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Onoko</last-name>
<first-name>Kana</first-name>
<address>
<city>Oita</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Pillsbury Winthrop Shaw Pittman LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Kabushiki Kaisha Toshiba</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Zarroli</last-name>
<first-name>Michael C.</first-name>
<department>2839</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A circuit board has a plurality of pads arranged as a grid array in a quadrangle region. A surface mount type circuit component is connected to the circuit board through the pads. Each of pads arranged in the outermost side of the quadrangle region is formed in a substantially quadrangle shape in plan view.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="93.05mm" wi="81.96mm" file="US07298629-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="222.08mm" wi="89.15mm" file="US07298629-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="210.82mm" wi="62.31mm" file="US07298629-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="173.48mm" wi="89.83mm" file="US07298629-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="217.09mm" wi="92.88mm" file="US07298629-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="136.06mm" wi="95.08mm" file="US07298629-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is based upon and claims the benefit of priority from the prior Japanese Patent Application No. 2005-024450, filed on Jan. 31, 2005; the entire contents of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a circuit board for mounting a semiconductor circuit component having a surface mount type package. Particularly it relates to a circuit board for mounting a surface mount type circuit component which is formed so that electrodes formed in the bottom of a package are connected to pads of the board through metal bumps such as solder balls.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">As a wide variety of such packages serving as semiconductor circuit components to be mounted on circuit boards have advanced in recent years, surface mount type leadless packages which do not use any lead or pin for electric connection to the boards have been put into practical use broadly.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">For example, a BGA (Ball Grid Array) package, an LGA (Land Grid Array) package, etc., are used as such surface mount type leadless packages. In the BGA package, connection terminals are formed in such a manner that solder balls are attached to electrodes (pads) which are formed, for example, as a grid array, on the bottom of the package so as to be connected to an external circuit. In the LGA package, pads (lands) formed as a grid array on the bottom of the package are used directly as connection terminals.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">There is also known a CSP (Chip Size Package) having substantially the same size as that of a bare chip constituting a semiconductor. This CSP can be configured so that pads are provided on the bottom of the package so as to be connected to pads of a circuit board through solder balls or other metal bumps.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The BGA package is mounted on a circuit board by so-called reflow soldering which is performed in such a manner that soldering is performed by heating the solder balls while the solder balls are brought into contact with pads of the circuit board to be connected.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The LGA package is mounted on a circuit board through a socket provided with contactors being in contact with pads formed on the bottom of the package or the LGA package is mounted directly on a circuit board through solder balls attached to the pads.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The CSP can be also mounted on a circuit board substantially in the same manner as these circuit components.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">When the circuit board mounted thus with the surface mount type semiconductor having no lead is attached to the inside of a housing of an electronic apparatus to use the circuit board, the circuit board is incorporated as one of constituent members of circuits in the electronic apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In a process of executing the circuit board incorporating operation, stress may be sometimes applied on the circuit board in a direction crossing a board surface or shock may be applied on the circuit board because of falling, etc. As a result, the circuit board may be warped or distorted. This may affect junction portions between the circuit component and the board, so that there is a possibility that the pads of the board will be peeled or soldered portions will be broken. There is a problem that the circuit board cannot fulfill its original function.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">If the pads of the circuit board are peeled from the board body, the circuit board per se has to be exchanged for a new one. Accordingly, a considerably great deal of labor is required for assembling the electronic apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Particularly in recent years, there has been used the circuit board per se made of a thin material for reduction in size and thickness of the outer appearance of the electronic apparatus. In this case, the stiffness of the board is lowered so that the board is apt to be deformed by stress or shock applied externally. There is an increasing possibility that such an accident that peeling of the pads in the circuit board for mounting a surface mount type circuit component using no lead such as a BGA circuit component will occur.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">For example, JP-A-2003-78240 has heretofore disclosed a proposal to prevent lowering of peel strength of the pads in such a manner that the pads of the circuit board mounted with a BGA circuit component or a CSP circuit component are formed so that pads in outermost circumferential corner portions become larger in diameter than pads in the other portions. In this proposal, the space of the circuit board cannot be used effectively because the pads are circular. Moreover, when external stress is applied, the external stress is concentrated at one point of an outer edge of each pad. There is therefore a problem that the pads are apt to be peeled.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a plan view for explaining a circuit board according to an embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a plan view for explaining a state in which a solder resist is applied on the circuit board depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a view for explaining difference in junction area of a pad and a circuit board surface due to difference in shape of the pad;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A to 4C</figref> are views for explaining difference in peel strength due to difference in shape of the pad;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a view for explaining a state in which force to peel the pad is applied when the pad is rectangular;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a plan view for explaining a circuit board according another embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a plan view for explaining a state in which a solder resist is applied on the circuit board depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a plan view for explaining a circuit board according to still another embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a perspective view for explaining a general BGA circuit component; and</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a view for explaining a state of arrangement of solder balls on the BGA circuit component depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Embodiments of the invention will be described below in detail with reference to the drawings. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a perspective view for explaining a general BGA circuit component which is a surface mount type circuit component. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a bottom view of the general BGA circuit component.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the BGA circuit component <b>901</b> has a semiconductor chip not shown but provided in its inside. The semiconductor chip is sealed with a synthetic resin package material shaped like a cube. Electrodes electrically connected to external connection electrodes of the semiconductor chip are arranged, for example, as a grid array, on the bottom <b>902</b> of the package. Solder balls <b>903</b> are further attached to the electrodes respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a view of the BGA circuit component <b>901</b> depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, as seen from the bottom <b>902</b> side. The solder balls <b>903</b> are attached to the electrodes not shown but arranged as a grid array on the bottom <b>902</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a view for explaining a circuit board according to an embodiment of the invention. The circuit board <b>100</b> has a circuit component mount surface <b>101</b>, and pads <b>102</b> formed in correspondence to the arrangement of the solder balls of the BGA circuit component and provided for mounting the BGA circuit component.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Each of the pads <b>102</b> is shaped like a rectangle. The width W of each pad <b>102</b> along a short side of the rectangle is set to be larger by a predetermined size than the diameter of each of the solder balls of the BGA circuit component. In practice, each pad <b>102</b> is covered with a solder resist in the condition that the circular shape with a diameter substantially equal to the diameter of each of the solder balls of the BGA circuit component is left. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an example of the pads. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the solder resist <b>202</b> represented by the hatched region is applied on a surface of each pad in the condition that the circular shape <b>201</b> with a diameter substantially equal to the diameter of each of the solder balls of the BGA circuit component is left.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Next, the effect of the pads each shaped like a rectangle will be examined. The peel strength of each pad is proportional to the area of the pad. That is, in this specification, the term “peel strength” means the degree of force by which the pad is actually peeled when force acts on the pad to peel the pad from the circuit board body. That is, the fact that peel strength is high means the fact that the pad is hardly peeled. It can be said that the peel strength of the pad increases as the area of the pad increases.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">When the case where the pad is shaped like a circle with a diameter of 2r as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is compared with the case where the pad is shaped like a square 2r on a side, the area of the square is about 1.27 times as large as the area of the circle in accordance with A<b>2</b>/A<b>1</b>=4r<sup>2</sup>/Πr<sup>2</sup>=4/Πin which Πr<sup>2 </sup>is the area A<b>1</b> of the circular pad <b>301</b>, and 4r<sup>2 </sup>is the area A<b>2</b> of the square pad <b>302</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">When the pad is shaped like a rectangle, the peel strength of the pad can be made higher because the area of the rectangular pad is larger than the area of the square pad if the length of a short side of the rectangle is 2r.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">When each pad is formed to have the minimum area required for connecting the pad to the solder ball of the BGA circuit component in this manner, the total area of the square pad becomes larger than that of the circular pad so that the peel strength can be made higher.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Next, difference in peel strength due to difference in shape will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A to 4C</figref>. When the area of a circular pad is equal to the area of a square pad, the peel strength of the square pad is higher than that of the circular pad.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">When the pad is circular, force F to peel the pad <b>401</b> is applied on approximately one point <b>402</b> in the outer edge of the pad <b>401</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref>. It is conceived that the pad <b>401</b> is apt to be peeled because the force F is applied concentratedly on such a narrow place.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">On the other hand, when the pad is rectangular, high peel strength is obtained with respect to force F applied on a point <b>404</b> in an intermediate region of each side of the pad <b>403</b> and in a direction orthogonal to the side, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">It is supposed that this is because a phenomenon that the rectangular pad is hardly peeled unless larger force than the force required for peeling the circular pad is applied on the rectangular pad occurs as follows. According to simulation in the condition that a pressure sensitive adhesive tape <b>501</b> stuck on a certain surface is to be peeled as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, force F to peel the pressure sensitive adhesive tape <b>501</b> acts on the pressure sensitive adhesive tape <b>501</b> dispersively along the width L of the pressure sensitive adhesive tape <b>501</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As described above, in accordance with an embodiment of the invention, each pad is shaped like a square. Accordingly, a circuit board in which the peel strength of each pad is made high can be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">When the pad is square, high peel strength is obtained with respect to force applied on each side. When force F is applied on a corner portion <b>405</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>, it is however conceived that the pad is easily peeled like the circular pad because force is applied at one point. Therefore, when each corner portion of the square pad disposed in such an environment that force is applied on the corner portion <b>405</b> is cut linearly as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref>, the total peel strength of the pad can be made higher.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">When pads are formed on the circuit board body in correspondence with the positions of solder balls of the BGA circuit component, the pads are generally arranged as a grid array in a region, for example, formed of the edge shape of the bottom of the package of the BGA circuit component. In this case, the influence of force causing peeling on pads located in the outer side of the region is larger than the influence thereof on pads located in the inner side of the region, so that pads located in the outermost side are most intensively affected by the force. Moreover, when a region for provision of pads is square, pads located in corner portions of the region are more intensively affected by force causing peeling than pads located in the other portions. Accordingly, when each of pads in the outer side of the region for provision of pads is shaped like a rectangle while each of pads in corner portions is shaped like such a truncated rectangle that a rectangle is cut linearly at an angle on the corner portion side, peel strength can be made higher.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref> are views for explaining a circuit board according to another embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">That is, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the circuit board <b>600</b> has pads arranged as a grid array in a rectangular frame. Among the pads, each of pads <b>603</b> located in the outermost circumferential portion of the frame is shaped like a rectangle while each of pads <b>602</b> located in corner portions (inclusive of one-inner portions on diagonal lines) of the frame is shaped like such a truncated rectangle that the rectangle is cut obliquely linearly at an angle on the corner side.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Although <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows the case where each of the other pads <b>604</b> located in the inner side of the frame is shaped like a circle, it is a matter of course that each of the pads <b>604</b> can be shaped like a rectangle.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a state in which a solder resist <b>701</b> is applied on the respective pads <b>602</b>, <b>603</b> and <b>604</b> except portions to which solder balls are connected.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Incidentally, small circles <b>605</b> added into two pads <b>603</b> in the central portion of the uppermost line in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref> show through-holes.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">In the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 7</figref>, among the pads <b>602</b> to <b>604</b> arranged as a grid array in the rectangular frame, each of the pads <b>603</b> located in the outermost circumferential portion of the frame is shaped like a rectangle while each of four pads <b>602</b> located in each corner portion of the frame is shaped like such a truncated rectangular that the rectangle is cut obliquely linearly at an angle on the corner side.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As a result, the peel strength of the pads <b>603</b> located in the outermost circumferential portion and apt to be peeled can be made high. Moreover, because each of the four pads <b>602</b> located in each corner portion and apt to be peeled is shaped like such a truncated rectangle that the rectangle is cut linearly at an angle on the corner side, the phenomenon that force to peel the pad is applied concentratedly at one point on each corner of the pad can be avoided so that peel strength can be made higher.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Moreover, because the through-holes are provided, an excess of solder can be attached to the pads <b>603</b> provided with the through-holes so that peel strength of the pads can be made higher.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a plan view for explaining a circuit board according to a further embodiment of the invention. In the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the circuit board <b>800</b> has a circuit component mount surface <b>801</b>, and pads arranged on a region of the circuit component mount surface <b>801</b>. Among the pads, each of pads <b>802</b> to <b>806</b> arranged in corner portions of the region is cut linearly at an angle on the corner side so that the angle is set to be substantially equal to the angle of a line tangent to a concentric circle with the center of the region as its center. Incidentally, pads referred to by the same reference numeral are different in position of the cut corner portion but equal in angle.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">According to this configuration, peel strength adequate and delicate in accordance with the position of provision of each pad can be given to the pad.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">As described above, the circuit board according to the invention is configured so that square pads are arranged at least in portions where peeling is apt to occur. Accordingly, peel strength of the pads can be made high.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Among the pads arranged as a grid array in the rectangular frame, each of pads located in corner portions of the frame is cut obliquely linearly at a predetermined angle on the corner side. Accordingly, the phenomenon that each pad is peeled from the corner of the pad on the corner portion side can be retrained from occurring.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Moreover, when pads are provided with through-holes, the amount of deposited solder can increase so that peel strength can be made higher.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Incidentally, the circuit board according to the invention is not limited to the aforementioned embodiments and various modifications may be made without departing from the gist of the invention. For example, although the above description has shown the case where pads are connected to solder balls of a BGA circuit component, it is a matter of course that the invention can be also applied to the case where an LGA circuit component, not the BGA circuit component, is connected through metal bumps or the case where a CSP circuit component, not the BGA circuit component, is connected through metal bumps.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Although the above description has shown the case where pads are arranged in the whole of a rectangular frame, some BGA circuit component may be provided so that there is no electrode in the central portion of the bottom of the package but pads are arranged in several rows along the outer edge of the package. In this case, it is a matter of course that the circuit board according to the invention is formed to have pads in accordance with the arrangement of the electrodes.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A circuit board, comprising a plurality of pads arranged as a grid array in a quadrangle region;
<claim-text>wherein a surface mount type circuit component is connected to the circuit board through the pads; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>each of the pads located in a corner portion of the quadrangle region, is formed in a truncated rectangle shape in a plan view in such a form that a rectangle is cut linearly at an angle on a corner of the rectangle, wherein a position of the corner of the rectangle corresponds to a position of the corner portion of the quadrangled region with respect to the center of the quadrangle region.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The circuit board according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the rectangle is cut across by a straight line that is tangent to a concentric circle with an approximate center of the quadrangle region as its center.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The circuit board according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein at least one pad of the plurality of pads has a soldering region, to which a solder ball is soldered, and a through-hole.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
