<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296668-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296668</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11201482</doc-number>
<date>20050811</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>205</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>41</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>192 46</main-classification>
<further-classification>192 691</further-classification>
<further-classification>19211332</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Overrunning clutch having snap ring secured thrust plate</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2552166</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gardiner</name>
<date>19510500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>384425</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4757887</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ostrander et al.</name>
<date>19880700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192 451</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4913271</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kinoshita et al.</name>
<date>19900400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>19211332</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5769196</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Murata</name>
<date>19980600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>19211332</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5918715</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ruth et al.</name>
<date>19990700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6533461</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Gottlieb</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>384420</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6739440</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Dick</name>
<date>20040500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7100756</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kimes et al.</name>
<date>20060900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192 46</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7223198</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Kimes et al.</name>
<date>20070500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475331</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>17</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>192 691</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>19211332</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>384368</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>15</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070034470</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070215</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Fetting, Jr.</last-name>
<first-name>Robert D.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Caro</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Eisengruber</last-name>
<first-name>Gregory M.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Saginaw</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Brooks Kushman P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Means Industries, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Saginaw</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Bonck</last-name>
<first-name>Rodney H.</first-name>
<department>3681</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An overrunning clutch (<b>24</b>) has first and second clutch members (<b>30, 32</b>) having coupling faces (<b>34</b>) and (<b>36</b>) between which spring biased pivotal struts (<b>40</b>) and locking formations (<b>44</b>) cooperate to prevent relative rotation in only one direction. A snap ring (<b>48</b>) and thrust plate (<b>50</b>) cooperate to axially secure the clutch members (<b>30</b>) and (<b>32</b>) to each other and the thrust plate has a retainer (<b>52</b>) projecting therefrom to prevent rotation. The retainer (<b>52</b>) in certain embodiments is received between ends (<b>58</b>) of the snap ring (<b>48</b>) to prevent thrust plate rotation.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="73.49mm" wi="115.65mm" file="US07296668-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="247.57mm" wi="169.33mm" file="US07296668-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="239.44mm" wi="165.78mm" file="US07296668-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="242.32mm" wi="169.25mm" file="US07296668-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="240.71mm" wi="169.25mm" file="US07296668-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to an overrunning clutch having first and second annular clutch members that are selectively prevented from relative rotation in one direction and axially separated by an annular thrust plate that is secured by a snap ring.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Background Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Overrunning clutches conventionally include first and second annular clutch members that are supported for relative rotation with respect to each other about a common rotational axis. Opposed coupling faces of the first and second clutch members are provided with one coupling face having strut pockets that receive spring biased struts and with the other coupling face having locking formations so that the relative rotation of the members can be provided in one direction but not in the other direction. The coupling faces can be axially oriented as disclosed by U.S. Pat. No. 5,918,715 Ruth et al. or radially oriented as disclosed by U.S. Pat. No. 6,739,440 Dick. A snap ring is conventionally utilized to axially secure the first and second clutch members to each other such that there is necessarily rotational movement between the snap ring and one of the members.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">An object of the present invention is to provide an improved overrunning clutch.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In carrying out the above object, the overrunning clutch of the invention includes first and second annular clutch members that are supported with respect to each other for relative rotation about a common rotational axis, and the first and second clutch members have annular coupling faces that oppose each other. The coupling face of the first clutch member has pockets spaced about the rotational axis. Each pocket has a pivotal strut received thereby, and each pocket also includes a spring that pivotal biases its strut outwardly therefrom for locking. The coupling face of the second clutch member has locking formations that are engaged by the struts upon projecting outwardly from the pockets of the first clutch member to prevent relative rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in one direction while permitting relative rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in the opposite direction by pivoting of the struts into the pockets of the first clutch member. One of the clutch members has an annular groove that receives a generally round snap ring. An annular thrust plate is located axially along the rotational axis between the other clutch member and the snap ring. The thrust plate has a first axial face that contacts the snap ring and has a second axial face oriented in the opposite axial direction as the first axial face and contacting only the other clutch member without contacting the one clutch member, and the thrust plate has a retainer projecting therefrom to prevent rotation of the thrust plate.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The coupling faces can be oriented to face axially along the rotational axis or to face radially with respect to the rotational axis.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The thrust plate includes radially extending lubrication passages that are provided by radially extending portions of the thrust plate with reduced thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Different materials can be used to make the thrust plate. In certain embodiments, the thrust plate is a sheet metal stamping made from steel, brass, aluminum, or bronze. In another embodiment, the thrust plate is a synthetic resin molding.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Embodiments of the thrust plate have the retainer projecting axially therefrom along the rotational axis with the snap ring having opposite circumferential ends between which the thrust plate retainer is received to prevent thrust plate rotation. One of these embodiments is a sheet metal stamping from which the retainer extends axially along the rotational axis to between the opposite circumferential ends of the snap ring. More specifically, the thrust plate retainer of this embodiment extends axially at an oblique angle to the rotational axis. In another of these embodiments, the thrust plate is a synthetic resin molding defining the axially projecting retainer received between the circumferential ends of the snap ring.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In other embodiments, the one clutch member has a circumferential groove, and the retainer of the annular thrust plate extends radially into the circumferential groove of the one clutch member to prevent thrust plate rotation. One of these embodiments has the one clutch member provided with a plurality of the circumferential grooves spaced circumferentially from each other about the rotational axis, and the annular thrust plate includes a plurality of the radially extending retainers spaced circumferentially from each other about the rotational axis and respectively received by the circumferential grooves in the one clutch member to cooperate with each other to prevent thrust plate loading. Another of these embodiments has the thrust plate retainer extending to the circumferential groove between the opposite circumferential ends of the snap ring.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The objects, features and advantages of the present invention are readily apparent from the following detailed description of the preferred embodiments when taken in connection with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a partial sectional view taken through a portion of a transmission which includes an overrunning clutch constructed in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of one annular clutch member of the clutch.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view of another annular clutch member of the clutch.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an enlarged view of a portion of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrating a snap ring and annular thrust plate that are utilized to axially secure the clutch members shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> in their assembled condition of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a partial view illustrating flat axial coupling faces of the clutch members at which spring biased pivotal struts and locking formations cooperate to prevent relative rotation of the clutch members in one direction while permitting relative rotation in the opposite direction.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a view similar to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> but showing the clutch members with radial coupling faces at which spring biased pivotal struts and locking formations cooperate to prevent relative rotation in one direction while permitting relative rotation in the opposite direction.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is an axial view of the annular thrust plate.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a perspective view of a portion of the thrust plate showing a retainer that prevents thrust plate rotation.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a sectional view taken along the direction of line <b>9</b>-<b>9</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> to further illustrate the retainer.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a partial sectional view taken along the direction of line <b>10</b>-<b>10</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> to illustrate reduced thickness portions of the thrust plate for providing lubrication passages.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a partial perspective view showing the manner in which the thrust plate retainer is received between opposite circumferential ends of the snap ring.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a partial perspective view of another embodiment wherein the annular thrust plate is made from a synthetic resin and has an axially projecting retainer received between opposite circumferential ends of the snap ring.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a perspective view of another embodiment of the annular thrust plate which has circumferentially extending retainers.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a partial exploded perspective view illustrating the manner in which the circumferentially extending retainers of the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> thrust plate are aligned with circumferential grooves in one of the clutch members and received thereby to prevent thrust plate during rotation.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is a partial perspective view of another embodiment wherein the annular thrust plate extends axially between opposite circumferential ends of the snap ring and into a circumferential groove of one of the clutch members.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a transmission generally indicated by <b>20</b> includes a housing <b>22</b> which receives an overrunning clutch <b>24</b> that is constructed in accordance with the present invention and utilized with control clutches <b>26</b> and <b>28</b> to control torque transmission. The overrunning clutch <b>24</b> of the invention includes first and second annular clutch members <b>30</b> and <b>32</b> that are respectively shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> and are supported with respect to each other for relative rotation about a common rotational axis A. The first and second clutch members <b>30</b> and <b>32</b> have respective coupling faces <b>34</b> and <b>36</b> which are shown as facing axially along the rotational axis A as also shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. It should be appreciated that the coupling faces can also be oriented to face radially with respect to the rotational axis as shown by the embodiment of clutch <b>24</b><i>a </i>in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The coupling face <b>34</b> of the clutch member <b>30</b> has pockets <b>38</b>, six as shown, spaced circumferentially about the rotational axis A. Each pocket as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> includes a pivotal strut <b>40</b> received thereby, and each pocket also includes a spring <b>42</b> that pivotally biases its strut outwardly therefrom for locking, as shown by solid line representation, while permitting movement back into the pocket as partially shown by phantom line representation to permit relative rotation between the clutch members.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The coupling face <b>36</b> of the second clutch member <b>32</b> has locking formations <b>44</b> that are engaged by the struts upon projecting outwardly from the pocket <b>48</b> of the first clutch member <b>30</b> to prevent relative rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other while permitting relative rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in the opposite direction shown by the arrows, which is permitted by pivoting of the struts <b>40</b> into the pockets <b>38</b> against the bias of the associate spring <b>42</b>. It should be understood that the relative rotation can include rotation of both clutch members or rotation of only one of the clutch members while the other is held from rotation.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, clutch member <b>32</b> has an annular groove <b>46</b> that receives a snap ring <b>48</b> of a generally annular shape. An annular thrust plate <b>50</b> is located axially along the rotational axis between the clutch member <b>30</b> and the snap ring <b>48</b>. The thrust plate <b>50</b> has a first axial face that contacts the snap ring <b>48</b> and has a second axial face oriented in the opposite axial direction as the first axial face and contacting only the clutch member <b>30</b> without contacting the clutch member <b>32</b>. Furthermore, the thrust plate <b>50</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7-11</figref> has a retainer <b>52</b> projecting therefrom to prevent rotation of the thrust plate.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 and 10</figref>, the thrust plate <b>50</b> includes a plurality of circumferentially spaced lubrication passages <b>54</b> that extend radially and are provided as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> by portions <b>56</b> of reduced thickness of the thrust plate. These lubrication passages <b>54</b> as shown are provided on the opposite side of thrust plate from which the retainer <b>52</b> projects. Also, each of the other embodiments of the thrust plate as hereinafter more fully described also has radial lubrication passages provided by reduced thickness portions of the thrust plate.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The thrust plate embodiment <b>50</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7-11</figref> is a sheet metal stamping made from a metal such as steel, brass, aluminum or bronze. As is hereinafter described in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, it is also possible to make the thrust plate as a synthetic resin molding.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">As best illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, the snap ring <b>48</b> has opposite circumferential ends <b>58</b> that are spaced from each other and between which the thrust plate retainer <b>52</b> is received to prevent thrust plate rotation. More specifically, the sheet metal thrust plate is stamped to provide the retainer <b>52</b> which extends axially with respect to the rotational axis A at an oblique angle.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In another embodiment of the clutch <b>24</b><i>b </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, the thrust plate <b>50</b><i>b </i>is molded from a synthetic resin and has an axially projecting retainer <b>52</b><i>b </i>that is also received between the circumferential opposite ends <b>58</b> of the snap ring <b>48</b> so as to prevent thrust plate rotation.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In another embodiment illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 13 and 14</figref>, the clutch <b>24</b><i>c </i>the clutch member <b>32</b> has circumferential grooves <b>60</b>, and the annular thrust plate <b>50</b><i>c </i>as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> includes a plurality of the radially extending retainers <b>52</b><i>c </i>respectively received within associated grooves <b>60</b> of the clutch member <b>32</b>. These radially extending retainers <b>52</b><i>c </i>like the lubrication passages <b>54</b> are spaced circumferentially from each other about the central axis A.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>, another embodiment of the clutch <b>24</b><i>d </i>has its thrust plate <b>50</b><i>d </i>made from sheet metal with a stamped retainer <b>52</b><i>d </i>that extends between the snap ring ends <b>58</b> and is received by a circumferential groove <b>60</b> in the clutch member <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">While embodiments of the invention have been illustrated and described, it is not intended that these embodiments illustrate and describe all possible forms of the invention. Rather, the words used in the specification are words of description rather than limitation, and it is understood that various changes may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as defined by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An overrunning clutch comprising:
<claim-text>first and second annular clutch members that are supported with respect to each other for relative rotation about a common rotational axis, and the first and second clutch members having annular coupling faces that oppose each other;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the coupling face of the first clutch member having pockets spaced about the rotational axis, each pocket having a pivotal strut received thereby, and each pocket including a spring that pivotal biases its strut outwardly therefrom for locking;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the coupling face of the second clutch member having locking formations that are engaged by the struts upon projecting outwardly from the pockets of the first clutch member to prevent relative rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in one direction while permitting relative rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in the opposite direction by pivoting of the struts into the pockets of the first clutch member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>one of the clutch members having an annular groove;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a generally round snap ring that is received by the annular groove in the one clutch member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an annular thrust plate located axially along the rotational axis between the other clutch member and the snap ring, the thrust plate having a first axial face that contacts the snap ring and having a second axial face oriented in the opposite axial direction as the first axial face and contacting only the other clutch member without contacting the one clutch member, and the thrust plate having a retainer projecting therefrom to prevent rotation of the thrust plate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein coupling faces are oriented to face axially along the rotational axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the coupling faces are oriented to face radially with respect to the rotational axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the thrust plate includes radially extending lubrication passages.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the thrust plate includes radially extending portions of reduced thickness that define the radially extending lubrication passages.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the thrust plate is a sheet metal stamping.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the thrust plate is stamped from a metal selected from the group consisting of steel, brass, aluminum, and bronze.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the thrust plate is a synthetic resin molding.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the retainer of the thrust plate projects axially therefrom along the rotational axis, and the snap ring having opposite circumferential ends between which the thrust plate retainer is received to prevent thrust plate rotation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the thrust plate is a sheet metal stamping from which the retainer extends axially along the rotational axis to between the opposite circumferential ends of the snap ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the thrust plate retainer extends axially at an oblique angle to the rotational axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the thrust plate is a synthetic resin molding defining the axially projecting retainer received between the circumferential ends of the snap ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the one clutch member has a circumferential groove, the retainer of the annular thrust plate extending radially into the circumferential groove of the one clutch member to prevent thrust plate rotation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the one clutch member includes a plurality of the circumferential grooves spaced circumferentially from each other about the rotational axis, and the annular thrust plate including a plurality of the radially extending retainers spaced circumferentially from each other about the rotational axis and respectively received by the circumferential grooves in the one clutch member to cooperate with each other to prevent thrust plate rotation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. An overrunning clutch as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein the snap ring has opposite circumferential ends between which the thrust plate retainer is received to also prevent thrust plate rotation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. An overrunning clutch comprising:
<claim-text>first and second annular clutch members that are supported with respect to each other for relative rotation about a common rotational axis, and the first and second clutch members having annular coupling faces that axially oppose each other;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the coupling face of the first clutch member having pockets spaced about the rotational axis, each pocket having a pivotal strut received thereby, and each pocket including a spring that pivotal biases its strut outwardly therefrom for locking;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the coupling face of the second clutch member having locking formations that are engaged by the struts upon projecting outwardly from the pockets of the first clutch member to prevent relative rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in one direction while permitting rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in the opposite direction by pivoting of the struts into the pockets of the first clutch member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>one of the clutch members having an annular groove;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a generally round snap ring that is received by the annular groove in the one clutch member, and the snap ring having circumferentially spaced opposite ends; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an annular thrust plate located axially along the rotational axis between the other clutch member and the snap ring, and the thrust plate having an axially extending retainer projecting therefrom to between the circumferential spaced opposite ends of the snap ring to prevent rotation of the thrust plate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. An overrunning clutch comprising:
<claim-text>first and second annular clutch members that are supported with respect to each other for relative rotation about a common rotational axis, and the first and second clutch members having annular coupling faces that axially oppose each other;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the coupling face of the first clutch member having pockets spaced about the rotational axis, each pocket having a pivotal strut received thereby, and each pocket including a spring that pivotal biases its strut outwardly therefrom for locking;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the coupling face of the second clutch member having locking formations that are engaged by the struts upon projecting outwardly from the pockets of the first clutch member to prevent relative rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in one direction while permitting rotation of the clutch members with respect to each other in the opposite direction by pivoting of the struts into the pockets of the first clutch member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>one of the clutch members having an annular groove;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a generally round snap ring that is received by the annular groove in the one clutch member, and the snap ring having circumferentially spaced opposite ends; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an annular thrust plate that is stamped from sheet metal and located axially along the rotational axis between the other clutch member and the snap ring, and the sheet metal thrust plate having a stamped retainer extending axially to between the circumferential spaced opposite ends of the snap ring to prevent rotation of the thrust plate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
