<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297043-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297043</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11228156</doc-number>
<date>20050916</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>42</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>446211</main-classification>
<further-classification>446212</further-classification>
<further-classification>124 65</further-classification>
<further-classification>124 67</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Toy rocket launcher for multiple soft toy rockets</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2609811</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lawrence</name>
<date>19520900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>124 48</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3009453</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ayala</name>
<date>19611100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>124 27</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3726266</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Palmer</name>
<date>19730400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>124 59</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5186156</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Clayton</name>
<date>19930200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>124 59</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5267549</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Webber</name>
<date>19931200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>124 65</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5535729</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Griffin et al.</name>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>124 66</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6568985</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Binkley</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>446176</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>8</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>472 92</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>472 94</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>446176</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>446180</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>446211</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>446212</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>446429</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>124 65</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>124 67</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070077852</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070405</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lam</last-name>
<first-name>Ying Lung</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hong Kong</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CN</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CN</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Jensen &amp; Puntigam, P.S.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>D &amp; S Toys Company Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Fo Tan, Hong Kong</city>
<country>CN</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Kien T</first-name>
<department>3711</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The toy rocket launcher includes an elongated launch tube and a pusher assembly which slides inside the launch tube in an air-tight relationship. A launch head assembly is rotatably mounted on a forward end of the launch tube and has a plurality of launch ports for receiving toy rockets. The forward end of the launch tube assembly includes a small opening which mates with one of a plurality of air passageways in the launch head assembly. Each air passageway connects with a different launch port. As the head assembly is rotated by hand on the launch tube, a flow of air from the launch tube produced by user action on the pusher assembly is directed to successive launch ports, thereby launching successive toy rockets from the launch head assembly.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="84.92mm" wi="235.03mm" file="US07297043-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="247.40mm" wi="183.90mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297043-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="228.60mm" wi="153.16mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297043-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="224.87mm" wi="190.58mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297043-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="230.80mm" wi="149.69mm" file="US07297043-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="157.06mm" wi="170.26mm" file="US07297043-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates generally to the art of soft foam toy rockets. More specifically, it concerns an air pressure launcher for such toy rockets.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Launchers for soft foam toy rockets are known, as shown for instance in U.S. Pat. No. 6,568,985. Such launchers, however, can only launch one rocket at a time, i.e. after one rocket is launched, a new rocket must be positioned on the launcher by the user. This results in a significant time lag between successive rocket launchings. It would be desirable to be able to launch a plurality of rockets in quick succession, using a single air pressure launching system.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">DISCLOSURE OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Accordingly, the present invention is a toy rocket launching assembly, comprising: an elongated launch tube; a pusher assembly which fits moveably inside of the launch tube in an air-tight relationship therewith; a launch head assembly mounted on a forward end of the launch tube so as to be rotatable thereabout, the launch assembly including a plurality of launch ports at an upper end thereof for receiving a plurality of toy rockets, wherein the launch head assembly and an upper end of the launch tube are configured such that as the launch head assembly is rotated, an air pathway opens between the interior of the launch tube and successive launch ports in the launch head assembly; and a plurality of toy rockets adapted to be fitted onto the launch ports, wherein as the launch head assembly is rotated to successive launch port positions, movement of the pusher assembly into the launch tube produces sufficient air pressure at a selected launch port that a toy rocket mounted thereon is launched therefrom.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of the toy rocket launcher with the pusher assembly portion thereof extended from the launch tube.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of the toy rocket launcher with the pusher assembly fully inserted into the launch tube, showing a toy rocket flying off the launcher.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a close-up of a head portion of the toy rocket launcher.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an exploded view of a portion of the toy rocket launcher of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a bottom view of the head portion of the toy rocket launcher.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a partial lateral cross-sectional view of the head portion showing a portion of the arrangement receiving air flow into the head portion produced by action of the launch tube.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is an exploded view of the handle portion of the toy rocket launcher.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BEST MODE FOR CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A toy rocket launcher with multiple soft toy rockets mounted thereon is shown generally at <b>10</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>. The rocket launcher <b>10</b> includes a launch tube <b>12</b>, a pusher assembly <b>14</b> which fits into, and moves relative to, launch tube <b>12</b>, and a launch head assembly <b>16</b> which is positioned on a forward end of launch tube <b>12</b>. The launch head assembly is designed to support a plurality of soft toy rockets <b>18</b>-<b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In general operation, air is forced through an opening in the upper end of launch tube <b>12</b> by the action of pusher arm <b>14</b> being forced into launch tube <b>12</b> by a user's manual operation, with the forced air directed to a selected portion of the launch head assembly which is in fluid communication with one soft toy rocket <b>18</b>, producing a launch of the rocket away from the launch head assembly <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Now referring to the Figures in more detail, launch tube <b>12</b> is a hollow cylindrical member approximately <b>18</b> inches long by <b>2</b> inches in diameter and is made of a rigid plastic material. Pusher assembly <b>14</b> includes a hollow cylindrical tube <b>22</b> which fits into the interior of the launch tube <b>12</b> in a slideable but air-tight relationship. At the rear end of tube <b>22</b> is a handle member <b>24</b>, a forward surface section <b>25</b> which abuts against a rear end <b>28</b> of launch tube <b>12</b> when the pusher assembly <b>14</b> is fully inserted into the launch tube <b>12</b>. Handle member <b>24</b> includes a grip portion <b>26</b> which is slightly curved, for the user to grasp, and secures the handle <b>24</b> to the pusher assembly tube <b>22</b> and a forward cap member <b>29</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>) which fits into the end of pusher assembly tube <b>22</b>. The cap member <b>23</b> includes a lip <b>27</b> at a rear end thereof which fits into a circumferential slot <b>28</b> in the interior surface of the grip portion <b>24</b>. The upper end of the grip portion surrounds and contacts the lower end of the pusher assembly tube <b>22</b>. The surface section <b>25</b> gradually decreases in diameter between the circumferential slot <b>28</b> and the forward end of the handle.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">At the forward end of launch tube <b>12</b> is a plate <b>34</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) with an opening <b>19</b>, through which air moves when pusher assembly <b>14</b> is moved forcibly into launch tube <b>12</b>. Launch tube <b>12</b> also includes an arrow or other indicia <b>38</b> on its peripheral surface <b>39</b> near the forward end thereof, indicating the position of opening <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Extending from the center of plate <b>34</b> is an elongated centering rod <b>40</b> which centers and connects the launch head assembly <b>16</b> to the forward end of launch tube <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The launch head assembly <b>16</b> fits removably on the forward end of the launch tube <b>12</b> and is designed to rotate about launch tube <b>12</b> by action of the user. The launch head assembly <b>16</b> includes a lower portion <b>44</b> which rotatably mates with the launch tube and is configured to curve outwardly near its upper end to the lower end of an upper portion <b>46</b> thereof. Upper portion <b>46</b> includes four identical, spaced launch ports <b>48</b>, <b>50</b>, <b>52</b> and <b>54</b>. Each launch port (launch port <b>48</b> is exemplary) includes a short, thin-walled hollow cylinder portion <b>58</b> which extends upwardly from a shallow portion/cavity <b>59</b> in the upper surface <b>47</b> of upper portion <b>46</b>. Surrounding the thin-walled cylinder portion <b>58</b> is an open space, which defines cavity <b>59</b>. Cavity <b>59</b> accommodates one soft toy rocket <b>58</b> which has an internal plastic sleeve <b>66</b>, a lower end <b>67</b> of which is designed to fit tightly into the thin-walled cylinder portion <b>58</b>. In the embodiment shown, each thin-walled cylinder portion <b>58</b> is approximately ¾-inch high and angles slightly inwardly from its base end, which is connected to or part of upper portion <b>46</b>, to its upper, free end into which sleeve <b>66</b> of a toy rocket is fitted.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The toy rockets are, in the embodiment shown, approximately 10 inches long. Each toy rocket has, as indicated above, a hard plastic internal sleeve <b>66</b>, which is designed to fit into, in a tight relationship, its associated thin-walled cylinder portion <b>58</b> on the launch head assembly. Each toy rocket includes an elongated foam body section <b>68</b> and a foam nose section <b>70</b> which tapers to a soft point. The foam body section has an air-tight relationship with the plastic sleeve <b>66</b>. The internal sleeve <b>66</b> extends for most of the length of the rocket and extends below the lower edge of the body section <b>70</b> a sufficient distance that it can be tightly positioned into its associated thin-walled cylinder portion. At the lower end of body section <b>68</b> are three spaced stabilizing fins <b>72</b>-<b>72</b> which are made from a foam material, which stabilize the rocket in its flight.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5 and 6</figref> show the interior of the launch head assembly, including the structural arrangement for directing air which exits from launch tube opening <b>19</b> into one of the launch ports <b>48</b>, <b>50</b>, <b>52</b> or <b>54</b>, depending on the rotational position of the launch head assembly on the launch tube <b>12</b>. Looking into the interior of the head assembly, from the lower end thereof, in the center of the upper portion <b>46</b> of the launch head assembly is an opening <b>64</b> which receives centering rod <b>40</b> from launch tube <b>12</b>. Rod <b>40</b> acts as a guide in positioning launch head assembly <b>16</b> onto launch tube <b>12</b>. Surrounding opening <b>64</b> is a circular wall <b>78</b>, which is approximately ¼-inch high and has a diameter such that the top end of launch tube <b>12</b> fits snugly thereinto in an air-tight relationship. Between opening <b>64</b> and circular wall <b>78</b> are defined four spaced air chambers <b>82</b>, <b>83</b>, <b>84</b> and <b>85</b>. Each air chamber is identical, and has a fluid connection with one associated launch port <b>48</b>, <b>50</b>, <b>52</b> and <b>54</b> in the upper portion of the launch head assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Air chamber <b>82</b> is exemplary. Air chamber <b>82</b> is approximately ½-inch deep and extends from approximately a center area <b>81</b> of the upper portion <b>46</b> of the launch head assembly, passing under circular wall <b>78</b> and terminating at a circular portal area <b>86</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) which surrounds an entry portion <b>88</b> of its associated thin-walled cylinder, located beneath the surface of cavity portion <b>59</b> of the launch head assembly. The entry portion <b>88</b> includes four spaced, vertical slots <b>89</b> which provide air communication between entry portion <b>88</b> and the interior of the thin-walled cylinder <b>58</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">When the launch tube <b>12</b> is fully inserted into the head assembly, plate <b>34</b> at the upper end of the launch tube comes adjacent the upper edge <b>91</b> of each of the air chambers <b>82</b>-<b>85</b>, in an air-tight relationship. Opening <b>19</b> in plate <b>34</b> (indicated by indicia <b>38</b>) is in registry with the one air chamber and the one launch port which lines up with the indicia <b>38</b>. Hence, an air path for the flow of air under pressure produced by the action of a user on pusher <b>14</b> is defined between launch tube <b>12</b>, opening <b>19</b> in plate <b>34</b>, a selected air chamber, and the interior of a selected launch port, depending on the rotational position of the launch head assembly. That air path is air-tight, i.e. there is little or no leakage of air from that structural path to the outside or to another air chamber.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In operation, pusher assembly <b>14</b> is first pulled outwardly to its extended position by handle <b>24</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, with one or more soft toy rockets, respectively, positioned on launch ports <b>48</b>, <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>, and <b>54</b>. In the embodiment shown, as indicated above, a total of four rockets can be positioned on the launch head assembly at any one time, although this number could be varied, depending upon the particular configuration of the launch head assembly. The pusher assembly is rapidly moved into the launch tube, forcing air present in the launch tube <b>12</b> out opening <b>19</b> at a relatively high pressure. The air moves into the one air chamber in registry with opening <b>19</b> and then into the interior of the associated launch port and then further into the interior of the toy rocket. The buildup of air pressure is great enough that it forces the foam body section <b>68</b> of the rocket to be launched off its internal sleeve <b>66</b> from the launch port, at distances of 50-100 feet. The internal sleeve <b>66</b> remains behind, in the launch portion to which it was tightly fitted, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">After one rocket is launched, the launch head assembly is rotated by hand so that the indicia <b>38</b> on the exterior surface of the launch tube lines up with a second launch port. The above-described steps are then repeated and the second rocket is launched. This continues until all the rockets on the launch head assembly are launched. A plurality of soft toy rockets can thus be launched in a relatively fast sequence, without the necessity of having to place a new rocket on a single launch port after every launch. After a rocket lands, it can be retrieved and fitted back on the internal sleeve for a subsequent use, or the sleeve can be removed and fitted into the body section <b>68</b>, again for future use.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Although a preferred embodiment of the invention has been disclosed for purposes of illustration, it should be understood that various substitutions, modifications and changes can be accomplished without departing from the spirit of the invention which is defined by the claims as follows.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A toy rocket launching assembly, comprising:
<claim-text>an elongated launch tube;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pusher assembly which fits moveably inside of the launch tube in an airtight relationship therewith;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a launch head assembly mounted on a forward end of the launch tube so as to be rotatable thereabout and removable therefrom, the launch head assembly fitting onto the forward end of the launch tube in an air-tight relationship, the launch head assembly including a plurality of launch ports at an upper end thereof for receiving a plurality of toy rockets in a tightly fittable relationship, wherein the launch head assembly includes a plurality of spaced air passageways, each air passageway having an air entry opening, with airtight communication between each of said openings and an associated launch port, wherein the launch tube has an opening in the forward end thereof which is configured to be in air tight communication with successive air entry openings in the launch head assembly as the launch head assembly is rotated, such that successive air passageways open between the launch tube and successive launch ports in the launch head assembly; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of toy rockets adapted to be fitted onto the launch ports, wherein as the launch head assembly is rotated to successive launch port positions, movement of the pusher assembly into the launch tube produces sufficient air pressure at a selected launch port that a toy rocket mounted thereon is launched therefrom.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The rocket launching assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the pusher assembly includes a handle assembly which prevents the pusher assembly from being moved into the launch tube beyond a selected distance.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The rocket launching assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the handle portion is located at a lower end of the pusher assembly and includes a portion which prevents further movement of the pusher assembly into the launch tube.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The rocket launching assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein in operation the pusher assembly moves from an extended position relative to the launch tube to an operative position located substantially completely into the launch tube, resulting in air being moved vigorously through the air pathway to a launch port, forcing the rocket mounted thereon out away from the launch head assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The rocket launching assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, including four spaced launch ports in the launch head assembly, each launch port including a thin-walled cylinder protruding outwardly from a surface portion of the launch head assembly, on which cylinder a toy rocket can be mounted, each launch port further including an air entry portion in communication with an associated air passageway in the launch head assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The rocket launching assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the launch tube includes an indicia on an outer surface thereof indicating the position of the opening in the forward end thereof, so that a user can conveniently line up the opening in the forward end of the launch tube with a selected air passageway in the launch head assembly, wherein the opening in the forward end of the launch tube comes into registry with the air entry openings in the launch head assembly successively as the launch head assembly is rotated.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The rocket launching assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the launch head assembly includes a receiving portion which includes a circular wall which receives the upper end of the launch tube in an air-tight relationship and a central opening which receives a rod member extending from the upper end of the launch tube for centering of the launch head assembly on the launch tube.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The rocket launching assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the toy rockets include a rigid plastic inner sleeve, which is tightly fittable into a launch port, and a soft foam external body portion into which the inner sleeve fits, wherein the soft foam body portion flies off the inner sleeve during launch, leaving the inner sleeve in place on a launch port.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
