<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296842-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296842</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11149445</doc-number>
<date>20050610</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>6</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>60</class>
<subclass>P</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>29610001</main-classification>
<further-classification>29610004</further-classification>
<further-classification>29610005</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Lock mechanism for container covering apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3975047</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>McClellan</name>
<date>19760800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3977719</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Thurston</name>
<date>19760800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4505512</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schmeichel et al.</name>
<date>19850300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5882062</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chenowth</name>
<date>19990300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6234562</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Henning</name>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6338521</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Henning</name>
<date>20020100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6367862</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Henning</name>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0026076</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Henning</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>29610016</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0033615</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Henning</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>29610001</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>29610004</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>29610005</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>29610016</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>29610018</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60578409</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040610</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050280277</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051222</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Growcock</last-name>
<first-name>Steven Lewis</first-name>
<address>
<city>Stuart</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ahlstrom</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas Johan</first-name>
<address>
<city>Stuart</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Banner &amp; Witcoff</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>John Donovan Enterprises, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Stuart</city>
<state>FL</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lyjak</last-name>
<first-name>Lori L.</first-name>
<department>3612</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An apparatus for covering a top of an open container is provided that includes a cover, an arm assembly, and a lock mechanism. The arm assembly can move between a stowed position in which the container top is substantially open to an extended position in which the container top is substantially covered. The lock mechanism can easily and automatically lock the arm assembly in the extended position as part of the container covering operation. The lock mechanism may include a latch and a latch block that cooperate to automatically and mechanically engage and retain a hook mechanism. The lock mechanism may also include an actuator that, when energized, permits the latch to release the hook mechanism.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="141.99mm" wi="217.00mm" file="US07296842-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="218.52mm" wi="150.11mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296842-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="217.00mm" wi="152.06mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296842-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="155.87mm" wi="155.02mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296842-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="163.91mm" wi="166.37mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296842-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="142.83mm" wi="149.10mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296842-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="219.96mm" wi="155.87mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296842-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="176.28mm" wi="164.34mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296842-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="107.36mm" wi="153.92mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296842-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation in part of now abandoned, provisional U.S. patent application No. 60/578,409 filed Jun. 10, 2004 entitled “Locking Down Tarping Mechanism,” the contents of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates in general to covers for open topped cargo container and, more specifically, the invention pertains to a mechanism for restraining a flexible cargo cover over the cargo container.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Open topped cargo compartments, such as dump trucks, short vehicle trailers, storage bins and the like, are subject to having material stored therein fall or blow out. This can be particularly dangerous while the compartment is being transported. For instance, if portions of the load fall out onto a roadway (e.g., trucks or trailers hauling sand, gravel, dirt or similar materials), traffic accidents can occur, as well as damage to other vehicles and littering of the roadway. Wind effects can intensify the risk of inadvertent material loss. For instance, lightweight materials, such as plant clippings being taken to a landfill, mulch materials, or harvested plants like cotton, are liable to having gusty winds blow portions of the contents out of the vehicle or bin.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In many places, laws and regulations require the tops of such containers to be covered before they can be transported on public roadways to prevent material being blown out of the containers. Even where there are no laws regarding covering a load, it is beneficial for the driver to cover the load to reduce the possibility of damage to other property from escaping materials. Thus, tarpaulins are commonly used to cover the loads during transport. In addition, tarpaulins are often used to keep environmentally sensitive materials, such as asphalt, wheat, etc. dry and warm or cool during static storage as well as during transport.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Manually placing a tarp or cover on an open-top container is both time-consuming and expensive. As such, automated tarpaulin covering systems are commonly used. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a conventional automated tarpaulin covering system <b>10</b> for a cargo container <b>12</b>. The covering system <b>10</b> has a tarpaulin <b>14</b> connected at one end to a movable cross bar <b>16</b>. The cross bar joins parallel arms <b>18</b> and <b>20</b> that are pivotally mounted on opposite sides of the cargo compartment via pivot <b>22</b>. The parallel arms are spring biased rearward toward a covered position. The tarpaulin <b>14</b> is rolled on a roller bar <b>24</b>, from which it extends to connect with cross bar <b>16</b>. Roller bar <b>24</b> is mounted at the top of the cab shield <b>26</b> of the container. Roller bar <b>24</b> is driven via electric, hydraulic or manual mechanisms to roll and unroll the tarpaulin <b>14</b>. Due to their rearward spring bias, the parallel arms pull the tarpaulin toward the rear of the truck as it is unrolled, which covers the opening on top of the container.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The spring-driven force applied to the tarpaulin via parallel arms <b>18</b> and <b>20</b> decreases as the parallel arms rotate rearward to the covered position, because of the nature of the spring biasing that drives the parallel arms. The reduced spring force applied at the end of the tarp-covering stroke results in the parallel arms having reduced force to maintain tension in the tarpaulin in the covered position. Thus, the tension applied to the tarpaulin in conventional systems is often ineffective for counteracting movement of the stored materials against the inside of the tarpaulin, wind gusts applied to the tarpaulin, or other forces applied during static storage conditions.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">During transport of the container, the low tension applied to the tarpaulin is further exploited by higher wind shear and aeronautic effects. When traveling, trucks hauling these containers create turbulent airflow at their headend that undulates the tarpaulin as the turbulent air passes over it. In addition, low pressure on the open side of the container creates lift on the tarpaulin, which acts like an airfoil. The turbulent air and low pressure periodically lift the tarpaulin upwards when the vehicle is in motion. The reduced spring tension coupled with the undulating, upward motion of the tarpaulin often permits the tarpaulin to expose partially the open top container and, in some extreme cases, can catastrophically damage the arms, tarpaulin and other components of the automated tarpaulin system.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Manual and automatic hold down mechanisms are known that attempt to improve tension in the tarpaulin while in the closed configuration. The conventional automated systems rely upon complicated arrays of mechanical, electrical or hydraulic structures to apply a constant tension along the length of the tarp. In addition, the conventional systems typically must be activated by the user as a separate step subsequent to covering the container. Further, the conventional systems often require activation energy, such as electrical and hydraulic inputs, beyond movement used to move the cover.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The most common conventional system is a manual tie down system of cords attached to either the tarpaulin or the parallel arm structure of the automated tarpaulin system to improve tension in the tarpaulin and its retention of material within the container. The manual tie down system requires the vehicle operator to climb to the open top container and secure the cords after the cargo is loaded and the automated tarpaulin system has deployed. It also requires undoing the cords just before the tarpaulin is uncovered prior to unloading the cargo. This is very time consuming and potentially a hazardous process for the vehicle operator.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Another conventional hold down mechanism is shown in U.S. Pat. No. 6,234,562 issued May 22, 2001 to Henning (Henning), which discloses a lock mechanism that relies upon wind energy to activate it. The lock mechanism includes a pivotally mounted wind vane that rotates in response to sufficient air pressure being applied against the vane to activate the mechanism, such as would be provided at a certain rate of travel on a roadway. In addition, Henning teaches that the lock mechanism can be deployed by a human via activation of a cable system or of a mechanical linkage system using an electrically or hydraulically driven actuator. Thus, the Henning system requires sufficient air pressure to deploy the lock mechanism or it requires the user to activate another system to deploy it.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The principles of the present invention may be used advantageously to provide a lock mechanism and a container covering apparatus having a lock mechanism that can easily and automatically lock the covering apparatus as part of the container covering operation. In accordance with an aspect of the invention, an apparatus for covering an open container of a vehicle includes a cover movable between an extended position in which the cover overlies the container and a stowed position in which the container is open, an arm assembly coupled to the cover to move the cover between the extended and the stowed positions, and a lock mechanism that automatically locks the arm assembly in the extended position when the arm assembly moves to the extended position.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In accordance with another aspect of the invention, a lock mechanism for automatically locking a container covering apparatus in an extended position includes a latch and a latch block that cooperate to automatically, mechanically engage and retain a hook mechanism. In accordance with another aspect, a method for covering an open top container supported by a vehicle includes the steps of providing a cover attached to a pivoted arm structure, actuating a first actuator to drive the pivoted arm structure to an extended position, and, in response to the pivoted arm structure substantially reaching the extended position, automatically locking the pivoted arm in the extended position. These and additional features and advantages of the invention disclosed here will be further understood from the following detailed disclosure of certain embodiments.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is top perspective view of a vehicle with an open top container that is equipped with a conventional automated covering system.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top perspective view of a vehicle with an open top container that is equipped with an automated covering system and a lock mechanism according to embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view of the lock mechanism of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shown in a locked configuration when the covering system is in an extended position.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective view of the lock mechanism of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shown with the mechanism housing removed while the lock mechanism is in the locked configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a side view of the lock mechanism of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a side, close view of portions of the lock assembly of the lock mechanism of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a side view of the lock mechanism of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shown in an unlocked configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is perspective view of the hook assembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In the following description of the various embodiments, reference is made to the accompanying drawings, which form a part hereof, and in which is shown by way of illustration various embodiments in which the invention may be practiced. It is to be understood that other embodiments may be utilized and structural and functional modifications may be made without departing from the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-8</figref> show a truck <b>110</b>, or other vehicle, for use with illustrating various aspects of the invention that may be combined into a variety of embodiments of the invention. As shown, truck <b>110</b> has a container <b>112</b> thereon with an opening <b>114</b> at its top and a container covering apparatus <b>116</b> for covering the top. The container covering apparatus <b>116</b> includes a lock mechanism <b>118</b> that can lock the container covering apparatus in an extended position in which a flexible cover <b>120</b> at least partially covers opening <b>114</b>. The lock mechanism provides a restraining force against the flexible cover to counteract the effects of wind passing over the cover. While the illustrated embodiments are particularly adapted for use with hauling vehicles, the same principals can be applied to stationary open-topped containers utilizing flexible covers. In addition, the illustrated embodiments more specifically pertain to a dump truck hauling vehicle <b>110</b>. Nevertheless, the same principals can be applied to a variety of hauling vehicles having open-topped containers.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">As shown, covering apparatus <b>116</b> has a pair of arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> separated by a preselected lateral distance. Arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> are separated by a distance sufficient to clear container <b>112</b> as the arms move along their path of travel between front and rear portions of the container. Each arm <b>122</b>, <b>124</b> is rotatably mounted at a first end portion thereof to the container via a hinge mechanism <b>126</b>. In other embodiments, arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> may be mounted to the truck rather than to the container. As with the system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> are biased to rotate rearward about hinge mechanisms <b>126</b>. However, in other embodiments, arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> may also be driven rearward, such as via electrical or hydraulic drive mechanisms. In the spring biased configuration, hinge mechanisms <b>126</b> may include torsion springs (not shown) to bias the arms rearward. Other bias mechanisms may include a counter arm (not shown) coupled to the hinge mechanisms and loaded with a spring force in the rearward direction of rotation of the arms, or other rotational biasing mechanisms.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">A cross bar <b>128</b> extends between arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> at second end portions thereof opposite their first end portions. The cross bar is attached to a first end portion <b>130</b> of flexible cover <b>120</b>. Flexible cover <b>120</b> extends from the cross bar to a roller bar <b>132</b> mounted at the top of the cab shield <b>134</b> of the container. As with the prior art system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, roller bar <b>132</b> may be driven via electric, hydraulic or manual mechanisms to roll and unroll flexible cover <b>120</b> thereon. Due to the rearward biasing of the parallel arms, the parallel arms pull the cover toward the rear of the truck as it is unrolled to cover opening <b>114</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> and roller bar <b>134</b> may be tubular members; although, other configurations may be used. Cover <b>120</b> is wound about roller bar <b>132</b>, which includes a rod extending through a spool <b>136</b> on which the cover is rolled and support brackets attached to the rod. In other embodiments, a spool could be rotatably secured to truck <b>110</b> with the cover being pulled from the spool as it is deployed over container <b>112</b>, similar to the action of a window shade being pulled into its deployed condition. In further embodiments, a spool holding the rolled-up cover could be disposed on cross bar <b>128</b> and an end portion of the cover could be attached to roller bar <b>132</b> such that the remainder of the rolled-up cover would move as the arms move from a stowed position to an extended position.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Cover <b>120</b> may be formed of a flexible material such as polyester, polypropylene, vinyl, canvas, or another material suitable for retaining material within a container. Other suitable materials for cover <b>120</b> will become readily apparent to those skilled in the art, given the benefit of this disclosure. Spool <b>136</b> may also be spring loaded to cooperate with arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> to maintain the cover in tension while in the extended position.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In order to activate the automatic covering apparatus <b>116</b>, the operator initially actuates a release (not shown) to allow spool <b>136</b> to unroll the cover which permit arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> to rotate from a foreword position proximate roller bar <b>132</b> to a rearward position in which container opening <b>114</b> is substantially covered. The release may include a lock on spring-loaded spool <b>136</b> that prevents the spool from unwinding. In other configurations, the release may be mechanical, electrical and/or hydraulic controls for the roller bar <b>132</b> that control the rolling and unrolling of the cover via a powered spool. It could also be a mechanical, electrical and/or hydraulic release of a mechanism holding the arms in a stowed configuration. Further, the release could be a manual release of a retention mechanism (not shown) that holds arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> in the stowed configuration against the spring bias at hinge members <b>126</b>. The retention mechanism may simply be a hook or other type of latch that holds arms toward the forward portion of the container. Nonetheless, for the configuration shown and these alternatives, the operator can start the process of covering opening <b>114</b> by permitting the arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> to rotate in direction <b>141</b> from a stowed configuration to an extended configuration to cover opening <b>114</b>. Depending upon the particular configuration, the arms may have various extended and stowed configurations to accommodate different size containers and covering configurations. For example, the arms may be attached to the truck rather than to the container and they may be able to rotate in various arc sizes to accommodate larger or smaller containers.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">For the configuration illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, once the operator activates covering apparatus <b>116</b> to cover opening <b>114</b>, the system automatically proceeds to rotate arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b> to an extended configuration in which a hook assembly <b>142</b> of the lock assembly engages an actuator assembly <b>138</b> of the lock assembly. Upon engagement, the lock assembly automatically locks the arms in the extended configuration. In other words, the operator can simply activate the covering apparatus <b>116</b> to move the cover to an extended position, and that action can automatically result in the covering apparatus being locked by the lock mechanism <b>118</b> in the extended position without the operator needing to take further steps, such as a separate step to actuate the lock mechanism <b>118</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, lock mechanism <b>118</b> generally includes an actuator assembly <b>138</b> attached to a side of container <b>112</b> via an installation bracket <b>140</b> and a hook assembly <b>142</b>. Hook assembly <b>142</b> is mounted on parallel arm <b>122</b> and fixed in a desired position along the arm with a bolt, pin or other mechanical mechanism. As discussed later, hook assembly <b>142</b> is preferably slidably mounted on arm <b>122</b>, which permits it to be adjusted for different extended positions (e.g., less than fully covering the container) or, if the arms are attached to the truck for different container sizes. The hook assembly <b>142</b> may be formed from a tube slider <b>144</b> having a slightly larger internal shape than the exterior of parallel arm <b>122</b>. A hook <b>146</b> is attached to the slider, which may be formed from a generally U-shaped bolt <b>146</b>. A lower portion of U bolt <b>146</b> engages actuator assembly <b>138</b> to lock the automated covering apparatus <b>116</b> in an extended position.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, actuator assembly <b>138</b> and components of the hook assembly <b>142</b> are shown in the locked configuration when the covering apparatus is in an extended position. As shown, actuator assembly <b>138</b> has a housing <b>148</b> that may be fabricated out of rectangular shaped metallic tube. The housing <b>148</b> has a notch <b>150</b> that receives U bolt <b>146</b>, which may generally be V-shaped. The housing also includes holes through its side walls to accommodate bearing pins <b>154</b>, <b>155</b> and <b>156</b> extending therethrough. A rubber bumper <b>158</b> is attached to the top side of the assembly to provide a cushion between the parallel arm <b>122</b> and the actuator assembly while in the latched configuration. The actuator assembly <b>138</b> may be attached to the side of container <b>112</b> by means of an installation bracket <b>140</b>, which could be mechanically fastened or welded in place.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-6</figref> illustrate the internal components of the actuator assembly in the locked configuration with part of the housing removed to expose the internal components. Actuator assembly <b>138</b> generally consists of a housing <b>148</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>), a latch <b>160</b> and corresponding pin <b>156</b>, a latch block <b>162</b> and corresponding pin <b>155</b>, an actuator mount <b>166</b> and corresponding pin <b>164</b>, an actuator <b>165</b> and corresponding pin <b>164</b>, and a flexible linkage <b>174</b> and its attachment pins <b>170</b> and <b>172</b>. The latch <b>160</b> is generally crescent-shaped to form a concave opening <b>168</b> that may generally be V shaped. Latch <b>160</b> is pivotally mounted on its pin and can rotate to move V shaped opening <b>168</b> between a lock position, which may be substantially horizontal relative to a bottom wall <b>152</b> of the housing, to an open position upward from the bottom wall. The angle of rotation <b>169</b> between the lock position and the open position may be between about 30 and 120 degrees, and is preferably about 30-50 degrees. While V shaped notch <b>168</b> is in the lock position, U bolt <b>146</b> is retained within an intersection <b>171</b> between V shaped opening <b>168</b> and V notch <b>150</b> of the housing. The intersection of these two notches results in an end portion of the U bolt being enclosed within and securely retained by the actuator assembly <b>138</b>. When the V shaped notch <b>168</b> is permitted to rotate upward to the open position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, U bolt <b>146</b> is free to exit both V shaped notch <b>168</b> of the latch and V notch <b>150</b> of the housing.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Lock mechanism <b>118</b> can mechanically retain U bolt <b>146</b> in the locked configuration as a default state without receiving user input or without being activated manually, pneumatically, hydraulically or electrically. When an end portion of U bolt <b>146</b> is enclosed within intersection <b>171</b>, mechanical interactions between latch <b>160</b>, latch block <b>162</b>, and bottom wall <b>152</b> of the housing cooperate to maintain latch mechanism in the locked configuration. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, upward rotation of latch <b>160</b> in the direction <b>192</b> will cause a bottom prong <b>194</b> of the latch to make contact with a shoulder <b>196</b> of the latch block. This contact will apply upward force to shoulder <b>196</b>, which will cause it to rotate counterclockwise about pin <b>155</b> to drive foot <b>198</b> into bottom wall <b>152</b> of the housing and thereby halt rotation of the latch block. As such, the end portion of U bolt <b>146</b> remains trapped within the intersection <b>171</b> of V notches <b>150</b> and <b>168</b>. Of course, downward rotation of latch <b>160</b> will drive bottom prong <b>194</b> into bottom wall <b>152</b> to limit movement of the U bolt in the opposite direction.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In addition, lock mechanism <b>118</b> can operate in a mechanical manner to automatically engage and retain U bolt <b>146</b> in the locked configuration without requiring the user to take additional steps and without the lock mechanism being activated manually, pneumatically, hydraulically or electrically. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, in the unlocked configuration, V shaped opening <b>168</b> is angled upward to provide an entrance into intersection <b>171</b> through V notch <b>150</b>. As arm <b>122</b> rotates rearward, U bolt <b>146</b> moves in direction <b>181</b> into intersection <b>171</b>. As the U bolt engages bottom prong <b>194</b> and drives it downward, latch <b>160</b> rotates counterclockwise and pulls on linkage <b>174</b>. Linkage <b>174</b> connects a bottom portion of latch <b>160</b> to a bottom portion of latch block <b>162</b>. As such, counterclockwise rotation of latch <b>160</b> likewise causes latch block <b>162</b> to rotate counterclockwise about its pin <b>155</b>. In the absence of the actuator <b>165</b> being activated, latch block <b>162</b> is free to rotate with linkage <b>174</b> and to move into the latch position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4-6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Linkage <b>174</b> is preferably formed from one or more flexible linkages, such as a spring, that applies a tensile force along its length when stretched. A flexible linkage permits lock mechanism to release arm <b>122</b> without forcing it to move foreword out of intersection <b>171</b> until desired. Preferably, an extension type helical spring is used for linkage <b>174</b>, which can provide good biasing force in an opposite direction when stretched without applying excessive force when stretched. In order to release U bolt <b>146</b>, actuator <b>165</b> pulls on a bottom portion of latch block <b>162</b> to bias it forward rotation in a clockwise direction. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, clockwise rotation of latch block <b>162</b> from its locked configuration will move shoulder <b>196</b> out of interfering contact with bottom prong <b>194</b> of latch <b>160</b>. Thus, latch <b>160</b> is free to rotate clockwise and thereby free the end portion of U bolt <b>146</b> whenever arm <b>122</b> rotates foreword. Use of a flexible linkage <b>174</b>, rather than a rigid linkage, permits U bolt <b>146</b> to be released without prematurely forcing the U bolt out of the intersection <b>171</b>. Due to the flexible linkage <b>174</b> between the latch <b>160</b> and latch block <b>162</b>, their rotational movement is coordinated. Indeed, latch block <b>162</b> encourages latch <b>160</b> to rotate via flexible linkage <b>174</b> for releasing the U bolt and, similarly, latch <b>160</b> encourages latch block <b>162</b> to rotate into the locked configuration via linkage <b>174</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The actuator <b>165</b> provides a linear force to latch block <b>162</b> to cause rapid rotation thereof. The actuator could be energized by manual, pneumatic, hydraulic or electrical energy sources. Actuator <b>165</b> is attached to an actuator mount <b>166</b> that is pivotally mounted on its pin <b>164</b>. Preferably, an actuator arm <b>178</b> is attached to latch block <b>162</b> by means of a pin <b>176</b> to form a rotatable joint. The actuator arm <b>178</b> retracts when the actuator <b>165</b> is energized and it is free to slide between extended and contracted positions when there is no excitation energy on it.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a close view of hook assembly <b>144</b> is provided. Hook assembly <b>144</b> may be slidable with respect to parallel arm <b>122</b> to permit adjustability for locking the cover in various extension positions, such as to cover partially a load or to accommodate various container sizes for configurations in which the parallel arms are mounted to the truck and the container is removable. In general, hook assembly includes a jacket <b>184</b> that fits over parallel arm <b>122</b> and/or parallel arm <b>124</b>, a U bolt bracket <b>188</b>, a U bolt <b>146</b>, nuts <b>180</b> and washer <b>182</b> to attach the U bolt <b>146</b> on the U bolts bracket <b>188</b>. The U bolt bracket <b>188</b> is firmly attached to the jacket <b>184</b> via weldements or other mechanical mechanisms. The internal shape of the jacket <b>184</b> is slightly larger than the outer shape of the parallel arms <b>122</b> and <b>124</b>, which permits the hook assembly <b>144</b> to slide over the parallel arms. The hook assembly <b>144</b> can be fixed in a position along one of the parallel arms or crossbar <b>128</b> via a bolt or pin through the threaded or straight hole <b>186</b> on jacket <b>184</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">While the invention has been described with respect to specific examples including presently preferred modes of carrying out the invention, those skilled in the art will appreciate that there are numerous variations and permutations of the above-described systems and techniques that fall within the spirit and scope of the invention as set forth in the appended claims. In particular, many variations and permutations may be possible for the lock mechanism that fall within the scope of the present invention. In addition, the present invention may be applicable to a wide variety of automatic and manual cover systems. Further, although only one lock mechanism is shown in the drawings, lock mechanisms may exist on both sides of the container at an open portion of the container, and multiple mechanisms may be on one or both sides of the container to enhance latching effectiveness and/or to provide a variety of options and configurations.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An automated apparatus for covering a top of an open top container, the apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a flexible cover movable between an extended position in which the cover overlies the container top and a stowed position in which the container top is substantially open;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an arm assembly coupled to the cover to move the cover between the extended and the stowed positions; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lock mechanism coupled to the arm assembly to automatically lock the arm assembly in the extended position in response to the arm assembly substantially reaching the extended position while moving from the stowed position to the extended position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the lock mechanism includes a release for releasing the lock mechanism from the locked position and the lock mechanism retains the arm assembly in the extended position until the release is actuated.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. An automated apparatus for covering a top of an open top container, the apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a flexible cover movable between an extended position in which the cover overlies the container top and a stowed position in which the container top is substantially open;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an arm assembly coupled to the cover to move the cover between the extended and the stowed positions; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lock mechanism coupled to the arm assembly to automatically lock the arm assembly in the extended position in response to the arm assembly moving from the stowed position to the extended position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the lock mechanism includes a release for releasing the lock mechanism from the locked position and the lock mechanism retains the arm assembly in the extended position until the release is actuated and the release includes a powered actuator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the powered actuator is driven by one of electrical, pneumatic and hydraulic inputs.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An automated apparatus for covering a top of an open top container, the apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a flexible cover movable between an extended position in which the cover overlies the container top and a stowed position in which the container top is substantially open;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an arm assembly coupled to the cover to move the cover between the extended and the stowed positions; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lock mechanism coupled to the arm assembly to automatically lock the arm assembly in the extended position in response to the arm assembly moving from the stowed position to the extended position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the lock mechanism includes a release for releasing the lock mechanism from the locked position and the lock mechanism retains the arm assembly in the extended position until the release is actuated and the release includes a manual actuator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the lock mechanism includes a hook assembly mounted on one of the container and the arm assembly and a latch mechanism mounted on the other one of the container and the arm assembly, the hook assembly engaging the latch mechanism when the arm assembly is in the extended position, engagement of the latch mechanism by the hook assembly causing the lock mechanism to automatically and mechanically lock the arm assembly in the extended position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the latch mechanism includes an actuator and the latch mechanism releases the hook assembly from being mechanically locked therewith in response to the actuator being energized.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the actuator is energized by one of an electrical, hydraulic and pneumatic energy source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the actuator is energized by a manual mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the latch mechanism comprises a latch and a latch block, the latch retaining the hook assembly in a mechanically locked position and the latch block blocking the latch from moving out of the mechanically locked position when the actuator is not energized.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the actuator moves the latch block when energized to permit the latch to move from the mechanically locked position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the hook assembly is slideably attached to an arm of the arm assembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the latch mechanism includes a housing having a first notch formed therein, the first notch having an opening oriented to receive a hook of the hook assembly and to guide the hook into contact with a latch of the latch mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein the latch forms a second notch having an opening oriented to receive the hook entering the first notch while in an unlatched position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the first notch and the second notch intersect each other to form an enclosed space in a locked position for retaining a portion of the hook therein.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the lock mechanism further includes a resilient bumper disposed between the hook assembly and the latch mechanism while in a locked configuration.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the arm assembly comprises:
<claim-text>a first arm on a first side of the container;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second arm on a second side of the container opposite the first side;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first pivot on the first side of the container connected to a first end of the first arm;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second pivot on the second side of the container connected to a first end of the second arm; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bias mechanism biasing the first and second arms about their respective first and second pivots toward the extended position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method for covering a container having an open top, the method comprising:
<claim-text>providing a cover attached between ends of pivoted arm structures, one of the pivoted arm structures being provided to each side of the container;</claim-text>
<claim-text>driving the pivoted arm structures and the cover from a stowed position in which the top is substantially exposed to an extended position in which the cover substantially covers the top;</claim-text>
<claim-text>while being driven, when the pivoted arm structures substantially reach the extended position, automatically locking the pivoted arm structures in the extended position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the step of automatically locking includes manually locking the pivoted arm structures in the extended position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A method for covering a container having an open top, the method comprising:
<claim-text>providing a cover attached between ends of pivoted arm structures, one of the pivoted arm structures being provided to each side of the container;</claim-text>
<claim-text>driving the pivoted arm structures and the cover from a stowed position in which the top is substantially exposed to an extended position in which the cover substantially covers the top;</claim-text>
<claim-text>when the pivoted arm structures are substantially disposed at the extended position, automatically locking the pivoted arm structures in the extended position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the step of automatically locking includes manually locking the pivoted arm structures in the extended position and the step of automatically locking is performed via a lock mechanism, the method further comprising releasing the pivoted arm structures from the extended position in response to receiving activation energy at an actuator of a lock mechanism.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. An automated apparatus for covering a top of an open top container, the apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a flexible cover movable between an extended position in which the cover overlies the container top and a stowed position in which the container top is substantially open;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an arm assembly coupled to the cover to move the cover between the extended and the stowed positions;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bias mechanism biasing the first and second arms about their respective first and second pivots toward the extended position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lock mechanism coupled to the arm assembly to automatically and mechanically lock the arm assembly in the extended position in response to the arm assembly moving from the stowed position to the extended position, the lock mechanism comprising:
<claim-text>a hook assembly mounted to one of the container and the arm assembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a latch mechanism mounted on the other one of the container and the arm assembly, the latch mechanism including an actuator, the latch mechanism retaining the hook assembly in a locked position when the arm assembly is in the extended position and releasing the hook assembly from the locked position when the actuator is energized.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
