<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296466-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296466</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11047889</doc-number>
<date>20050131</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-088926</doc-number>
<date>20040325</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>97</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>10</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73437</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Underwater weighing container and apparatus for measuring specific gravity</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>1760658</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Pampe</name>
<date>19300500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73 32 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2045813</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Waterbury</name>
<date>19360600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>209239</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3747416</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wommack</name>
<date>19730700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73437</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3777892</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Thijssen et al.</name>
<date>19731200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>210178</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4243856</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gratzmuller</name>
<date>19810100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>200 815</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4372405</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Stuart</name>
<date>19830200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>177 2514</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4770041</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bearce</name>
<date>19880900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73437</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6098454</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ghorashi et al.</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73160</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6101874</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Shemoney</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73437</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6561025</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Ueno</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73437</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7194951</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Porter</name>
<date>20070300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>100116</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>CN</country>
<doc-number>1370986</doc-number>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-230885</doc-number>
<date>19990800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-243615</doc-number>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-307482</doc-number>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73433</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 73437</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>177207</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>209259</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050210975</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050929</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kusumoto</last-name>
<first-name>Tetsuro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Uji</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>J.C. Patents</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Shimadzu Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kyoto</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Williams</last-name>
<first-name>Hezron</first-name>
<department>2856</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Fitzgerald</last-name>
<first-name>John</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An underwater weighing container for measuring specific gravity, requiring relatively a small amount of reference liquids for measurement and offering wide space for mounting specimens to be measured are provided. The underwater weighing container includes a tubular body and a circular bottom plate. The tubular body has openings on both ends. One end has an introvert circular rim formed thereon and the other end has a plurality of stoppers attached to the internal surface thereof. The circular bottom plate has a mesh or a porous structure and is inserted between the circular rim and the stoppers. The underwater weighing container is immersed in a reference liquid, and a solid specimen is placed on or inserted underneath the bottom plate. The underwater weighing container is hung by means of a hanging member <b>13</b> to measure the weight of the solid specimen and determine the specific gravity.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="77.55mm" wi="137.33mm" file="US07296466-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="179.49mm" wi="140.46mm" file="US07296466-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="199.22mm" wi="64.26mm" file="US07296466-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="225.64mm" wi="87.55mm" file="US07296466-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="185.42mm" wi="142.83mm" file="US07296466-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="204.72mm" wi="85.85mm" file="US07296466-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the priority benefit of Japan application serial no. JP2004-088926, filed on Mar. 25, 2004.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to an underwater weighing container and an underwater weighing container unit for receiving a weight of a solid specimen immersed in a reference liquid and a buoyant force exerted thereon. The present invention also relates to an apparatus for measuring a specific gravity of the solid specimen.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Generally, the commonly employed method for determining a specific gravity of a solid specimen without knowledge of its volume is to weigh the solid specimen in air, measure a weight of the solid specimen immersed in a reference liquid or a buoyant force exerted thereon, and use the obtained values for calculating the relevant specific gravity based on the following equation (1):
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>Specific Gravity=Weight in Air/(Weight in Air−Weight in Liquid)=Weight in Air/Buoyant Force  Equation (1)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As will be exemplified hereinafter, methods of weighing a solid specimen both in air and in a reference liquid, or measuring a weight of the solid specimen in air and a buoyant force produced by the solid specimen, for calculation of the relevant specific gravity have been applied to a number of conventional apparatus for measuring specific gravity. One such example is a specific gravity measuring apparatus <b>5</b>A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, wherein a solid specimen <b>2</b> is first hung and suspended in air and then placed inside a liquid bath <b>3</b> to measure its weight by means of an electronic weighing scale <b>7</b>, for determining the specific gravity. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, another conventional specific gravity measuring apparatus <b>5</b>B has an underwater weighing container <b>1</b>A arranged on an electronic weighing scale <b>7</b>, allowing the underwater weighing container <b>1</b>A to mount a solid specimen <b>2</b> thereon in a liquid bath <b>3</b>B. With this configuration, after the underwater weighing container <b>1</b>A holding the solid specimen <b>2</b> is subjected to measurement, the corresponding tare weight is subtracted from the obtained weight to determine specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b>. The patent literatures pertaining to these apparatuses for measuring specific gravity are Unexamined Japanese Patent Application Publication Nos. H11-230885 and 2002-243615.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The aforementioned configurations are employed in the conventional specific gravity measuring apparatus and the underwater weighing containers. However, the method of hanging and suspending the solid specimen <b>2</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is troublesome, due to the need to replace and suspend the solid specimen <b>2</b> having different shapes. In the method of providing the underwater weighing container <b>1</b>A for measuring the weight of the solid specimen <b>2</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, the solid specimen <b>2</b>, if its specific gravity is lower than that of a reference liquid, will be floating. As representative measures to prevent the solid specimen <b>2</b> from floating, a sinker frame <b>8</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, or a lid (not illustrated) may be placed in a reference liquid L. If any such measure is to be implemented, users will be required to insert and remove the sinker frame <b>8</b> or to open and close the lid, whenever conducting weight measurement. This method, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, is inconvenient for users. Depending on whether the solid specimen <b>2</b> sinks or floats in the reference liquid L, users will be required to employ a different configuration of the underwater weighing container <b>1</b>A. This can increase users' work load for maintenance and management of the apparatus for measuring specific gravity. The amount of the reference liquid L used for the measurement process also increases.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In consideration of the situation presented heretofore, the present invention is provided. An object of the present invention is to provide an underwater weighing container and a specific gravity measuring apparatus using the same, which can be applied to a solid specimen that may be heavier or lighter than the reference liquid. In addition, the underwater weighing container and the specific gravity measuring apparatus are compact and require relatively a small amount of reference liquid used for the weight measurement.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In order to accomplish the aforementioned object, the present invention provides an underwater weighing container, equipped with a bottom plate movable both upwardly and downwardly within a given range. Furthermore, the bottom plate is designed to hold a solid specimen on the upper surface thereof and carry its weight thereon if the specific gravity of the solid specimen is higher than that of a reference liquid, or to place the solid specimen underneath the bottom plate for a buoyant force of the specimen to be exerted against the bottom plate if the specific gravity of the solid specimen is lower than that of the liquid.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In one embodiment of the present invention, the present invention further provides an underwater weighing container unit, comprises an underwater weighing container being arranged at a lower position, a bottom plate capable of moving both upward and downward in a given range, an aerial weighing container arranged at an upper position to carry the weight of a solid specimen in air, and coupling rods to couple with the underwater weighing container and the aerial weighing container.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Furthermore, apparatus for measuring specific gravity of the present invention comprises the underwater weighing container unit of the present invention, a frame supporting the underwater weighing container unit, and a weight measuring unit, the frame being placed on the weight measuring unit to determine the specific gravity of a solid specimen.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An underwater weighing container, an underwater weighing container unit and apparatus for measuring specific gravity according to the present invention have the aforementioned configurations, wherein a bottom plate of the underwater weighing container are movable so as to place and hold a solid specimen inside whenever the solid specimen is subjected to measurement in a reference liquid.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">For this reason, they occupy a relatively small space and enable users to effectively reduce the amount of reference liquid used for the measurement process.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In an underwater weighing container, an underwater weighing container unit and apparatus for measuring specific gravity according to the present invention, the underwater weighing container is equipped with a movable bottom plate. If a solid specimen is heavier than a reference liquid, the solid specimen is placed on the bottom plate and moved downward with the associated bottom plate by their gravity. If the solid specimen is lighter than the reference liquid, the solid specimen is inserted underneath the bottom plate and moved upward with the associated bottom plate by the specimen's buoyant force. Consequently the solid specimen remains inside the underwater weighing container in any case. Thus, it is possible to reduce the size of underwater weighing container, underwater weighing container unit, apparatus for measuring specific gravity, and a liquid bath used therein, and also to reduce the amount of reference liquids used for measurement.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref> show a configuration of an underwater weighing container <b>1</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> shows a front elevation view of the underwater weighing container <b>1</b>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> shows a cross-sectional side elevation thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> show cross-sectional front elevation views of the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> during use. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> shows a condition where a solid specimen to be measured is heavier than a reference liquid, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> shows the other condition where the solid specimen is lighter than the reference liquid.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> show a configuration of an underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> are a partial cross-sectional front elevation view and a plan view of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a partial cross-sectional front elevation view of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> during use.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a perspective view of a specimen mounting unit <b>6</b> associated with an example of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A and 6B</figref> show the partial cross-sectional front elevation views of the apparatus for measuring specific gravity during use. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>a</i>) shows a condition where a solid specimen to be measured is heavier than a reference liquid, while <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>b</i>) shows the other condition where the solid specimen is lighter than the reference liquid.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a block diagram of an electronic weighing scale associated with an example of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a partial cross-sectional front elevation view showing a configuration of a conventional apparatus for measuring specific gravity.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a partial cross-sectional front elevation view showing a configuration of another conventional apparatus for measuring specific gravity.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The present invention will be discussed hereinafter in detail in terms of the preferred configurations and functions of an underwater weighing container, an underwater weighing container unit and apparatus for measuring specific gravity according to the present invention with reference to the accompanying drawings. In the following description, numerous specific details are set forth in order to provide a thorough understanding of the present invention. It will be obvious, however, to those skilled in art that the present invention may be practiced without these specific details. In other instance, well-known configurations are not shown in detail in order to avoid unnecessary obscurity of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref> show a structure of an underwater weighing container <b>1</b> according to one embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> shows a front elevation view of the underwater weighing container <b>1</b>, while <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> shows a cross-sectional side elevation view thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The underwater weighing container <b>1</b> comprises a metallic tubular body <b>11</b> having openings on both ends, wherein one end of the openings has a circular rim <b>11</b><i>a </i>produced through such processes as bending and/or welding and the other end of the opening has four stoppers <b>11</b><i>b </i>on the internal surface, wherein the four stoppers are arranged with each fixed at 90 degrees from the central axis of the tubular body <b>11</b> . The underwater weighing container <b>1</b> further comprises a circular metallic bottom plate <b>12</b> having a mesh or a porous structure and being inserted between the circular rim <b>11</b><i>a </i>and the stoppers <b>11</b><i>b</i>; and a metallic hanging member <b>13</b> being attachable to the upper part of the tubular body <b>11</b> for hanging and suspending the tubular body <b>11</b>. The bottom plate <b>12</b> is basically configured in contact with the circular rim <b>11</b><i>a</i>. When a buoyant force that is greater than the weight of the bottom plate <b>12</b> is exerted to the bottom plate <b>12</b> from underneath, the bottom plate <b>12</b> can move upward until it reaches where the stoppers <b>11</b><i>b </i>are installed.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> show cross-sectional front elevation views of the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> holding a solid specimen <b>2</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> shows a condition that the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> is larger than that of a reference liquid L, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> shows the other condition where the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> is smaller than that of the reference liquid L. A method of measuring specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> by using the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> is described hereinafter with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">First, while the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> is submerged in a liquid bath <b>3</b>, a weighing apparatus (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>) such as a scale, together with a hanging member <b>13</b> is employed, to measure the weight (W<b>0</b>) of the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> per se. If the solid specimen <b>2</b> is heavier than the reference liquid L, the solid specimen <b>2</b> is placed on the bottom plate <b>12</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, and at which time the weight W<b>1</b> of the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> with the solid specimen <b>2</b> is measured. If the weight of the solid specimen <b>2</b> measured in air is Wa, the specific gravity S of the solid specimen <b>2</b> can be calculated based on the following equation (2).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>S=Wa</i>/(<i>Wa</i>−(<i>W</i>1−<i>W</i>0))  Equation (2)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">If the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> is smaller than that of the reference liquid L, the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> is lifted to insert the solid specimen <b>2</b> underneath the bottom plate <b>12</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>. Due to the buoyant force produced thereby, the solid specimen <b>2</b> is in contact with the bottom plate <b>12</b>, and moves upward together with the bottom plate <b>12</b> until the solid specimen <b>2</b> remain stationary and stable. Under this condition, the weight (W<b>2</b>) of the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> is determined. Accordingly, the specific gravity S of the solid specimen <b>2</b> can be calculated based on the following equation (3).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>S=Wa</i>/(<i>W</i>0−<i>W</i>2)  Equation (3)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> show a structure of an underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> according to another embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> shows a partial cross-sectional front elevation view of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> shows a plan view thereof. The underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> comprises the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> arranged in a lower position; an aerial weighing container <b>41</b> being a circular container made either of metal or resin, arranged in an upper position; coupling rods <b>42</b> coupling with the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> and the aerial weighing container <b>41</b>; and a hanging member <b>43</b> attached to the aerial weighing container <b>41</b>. Based on this configuration, a solid specimen can be solid received in the aerial weighing container <b>41</b> to measure its weight in air, and the solid specimen can be placed on or underneath the bottom plate <b>12</b>, so that the weight of the solid specimen immersed in a reference liquid or the buoyant force exerted thereon can be weighted.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a partially cross-sectional front elevation view of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b>, wherein solid specimens <b>2</b>A, <b>2</b>B and <b>2</b>C are received in the liquid bath <b>3</b>. The disposition of the solid specimen <b>2</b>A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> represents a position designated for measuring its weight in air. The disposition of the solid specimen <b>2</b>B represents a position designated for measuring its weight in the reference liquid L, wherein the solid specimen <b>2</b>B is placed on the bottom plate <b>12</b> and submerged in the reference liquid L if the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b>B is larger than that of the reference liquid L. The disposition of the solid specimen <b>2</b>C represents a position designated for measuring its buoyant force in the reference liquid L, wherein the solid specimen <b>2</b>C is inserted underneath the bottom plate <b>12</b> and submerged in the reference liquid L if the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b>C is smaller than that of the reference liquid L. A method of measuring the specific gravities of the solid specimens <b>2</b>A, <b>2</b>B and <b>2</b>C respectively by means of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> is described hereinafter with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">First, while only the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> is dipped and immersed in the liquid bath <b>3</b>, a weight measuring apparatus (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) such as a scale, together with a hanging member <b>43</b>, is employed to measure the weight W<b>0</b> of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> per se. The solid specimen <b>2</b>A is arranged on the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b>, at which time the weight W<b>1</b> of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> is measured. If the solid specimen is heavier than the reference liquid L, the solid specimen is placed in the designated position as shown by the solid specimen <b>2</b>B of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, and under this condition, the weight W<b>2</b> of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> with the solid specimen <b>2</b>B is measured. Hence, the specific gravity S of the solid specimen <b>2</b>B can be calculated based on the following equation (4).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>S</i>=(<i>W</i>1−<i>W</i>0)/(<i>W</i>1−<i>W</i>2)  Equation (4)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">If the solid specimen is lighter than the reference liquid L, the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> is lifted to insert the solid specimen underneath the bottom plate <b>12</b>, as indicated by the solid specimen <b>2</b>C in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. With the buoyant force produced thereby, the solid specimen <b>2</b>C floats, makes contact with the bottom plate <b>12</b>, moves upward together with the bottom plate <b>12</b> until reaching up to the locations of the stoppers <b>11</b><i>b</i>. The solid specimen <b>2</b>C then remains stationary and stable. Under this condition, the weight W<b>3</b> of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> with the solid specimen <b>2</b>C is measured. Therefore, the specific gravity S of the solid specimen <b>2</b>C can be calculated based on the following equation (5).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>S</i>=(<i>W</i>1−<i>W</i>0)/(<i>W</i>0−<i>W</i>3)  Equation (5)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a perspective view of a specimen mounting unit <b>6</b> used in specific gravity measuring apparatus <b>5</b> according to another embodiment of the present invention, which will be mentioned later. The specimen mounting unit <b>6</b> comprises the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b>; a frame <b>6</b>A supporting the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b>; a liquid bath <b>3</b> containing a reference liquid to hold the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> completely submerged therein; a liquid bath mounting platform <b>6</b>B to place the liquid bath <b>3</b> thereon while straddling a lower frame <b>62</b> of the frame <b>6</b>A.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The frame <b>6</b>A comprises an upper frame <b>61</b>; the lower frame <b>62</b> mounted and installed on a weighing pan <b>71</b> of an electronic weighing scale <b>7</b> to be described later; coupling rods <b>63</b> and <b>64</b> and setscrews <b>65</b> connecting the upper frame <b>61</b> with the lower frame <b>62</b> at a certain height. V-shaped notched-portions <b>66</b> that are able to hold or remove the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> are arranged on the upper frame <b>61</b> based on a gap between the coupling rods <b>63</b> and <b>64</b>. The underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> is supported by the frame <b>6</b>A, when the coupling rods <b>42</b> pass through the notched-portions <b>66</b>. The underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> can be removed from the frame <b>6</b>A by lifting the aerial weighing container <b>41</b> and drawing the coupling rods <b>42</b> out of the notched-portions <b>66</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref> show partially cross-sectional front elevation views of the specific gravity measuring apparatus <b>5</b>, wherein the specimen mounting unit <b>6</b> and the electronic weighing scale <b>7</b> are incorporated and the solid specimen <b>2</b> is held in position. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> shows a condition of mounting a solid specimen <b>2</b> wherein the specific gravity of which is larger than that of the reference liquid L. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> shows another condition of mounting a solid specimen <b>2</b> where the specific gravity of which is smaller than that of the reference liquid L. In these conditions, the lower frame <b>62</b> is placed on the weighing pan <b>71</b> of the electronic weighing scale <b>7</b>, and the liquid bath mounting platform <b>6</b>B is placed on a frame base <b>79</b> of the electronic weighing scale <b>7</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a block diagram of the electronic weighing scale <b>7</b>. The electronic weighing scale <b>7</b> uses a load sensor <b>72</b> to convert a weight load applied to the weighing pan <b>71</b> into electrical signals. After the electrical signals are amplified by an amplifier <b>73</b>, the amplified electrical signals are converted into digital signals by an A/D converter <b>74</b>. The digital signals are input into a CPU <b>75</b> constituting a microcomputer, and are subjected to calculations according to the aforementioned Equations (4) and (5) stored in a memory device <b>76</b>. Data of specific gravity values calculated are displayed on a display device <b>77</b>. The electronic weighing scale <b>7</b> is also equipped with operation buttons <b>78</b> providing instructions for differentiating the weights measured by the weighing pan <b>71</b> as well as for the start of the calculation process.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">A method of measuring the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> by means of the specific gravity measuring apparatus <b>5</b> is described hereinafter with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A</figref>, <b>6</b>B and <b>7</b>. First, the weight (W<b>0</b>) of the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> itself, i.e., the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> together with the frame <b>6</b>A are measured, and the operation buttons <b>78</b> is pressed to store the data of W<b>0</b> in the memory device <b>76</b>. Then, the weight (W<b>1</b>) of the aerial weighing container <b>41</b> holding the solid specimen <b>2</b> is measured, and the corresponding data is stored in the same manner. If the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> is larger than that of the reference liquid L, the solid specimen <b>2</b> is placed at the position as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> to measure the weight W<b>2</b>, and the relevant data is recorded in the same manner. The operation buttons <b>78</b> is pressed to allow the CPU <b>75</b> to start calculating the stored data based on the aforementioned Equation (4), and then the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> are calculated and displayed.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">If the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> is smaller than that of the reference liquid L, the solid specimen <b>2</b> is inserted in the position set forth in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> for measuring the weight W<b>3</b>. Subsequently, the operation buttons <b>78</b> is pressed to allows the CPU <b>75</b> to start calculating these stored data based on the aforementioned Equation (5), and then the specific gravity of the solid specimen <b>2</b> are calculated and displayed.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As described heretofore, and as shown by the underwater weighing container <b>1</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref> and the underwater weighing container unit <b>4</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the present invention is characterized in that a single and compact structure capable of weighing the solid specimen <b>2</b> immersed in the reference liquid L because the structure comprises the bottom plate <b>12</b> movable upwardly and downwardly in a given range within the tubular body <b>11</b>. Based on this configuration, the solid specimen <b>2</b> that will sink in the reference liquid L can be placed on the upper surface of the bottom plate <b>12</b> in the reference liquid L. While the solid specimen <b>2</b> that will float in the reference liquid L can be inserted underneath the bottom plate <b>12</b>. In this way, the weight of the solid specimen <b>2</b> can be measured in the reference liquid L. While several examples of the present invention are disclosed herein, the conceivable configurations according to the present invention are not limited to these embodiments. For example, the tubular body <b>11</b> can be provided with a guide that will help to prevent the bottom plate <b>12</b> from tilting during moving the bottom plate <b>12</b> upward or downward. By increasing the number of coupling rods <b>42</b>, it is possible to hang and hold the tubular body <b>11</b> more securely.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">While the present invention has been described with a preferred embodiment, this description is not intended to limit our invention. Various modifications of the embodiment will be apparent to those skilled in the art. It is therefore contemplated that the appended claims will cover any such modifications or embodiments as fall within the true scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for measuring specific gravity using an underwater weighing container the underwater weighing container comprising a body having a side wall defining a hollow space, an upper open end, and a bottom open and; and a bottom plate placed in the body which is movable both upwardly and downwardly along an axial direction of the body in a given range between the upper open end and the bottom open end for holding a solid specimen, wherein the underwater weighing container receives a weight or a buoyant force of the solid specimen immersed in a reference liquid, the method comprising:
<claim-text>weighing the solid specimen in air;</claim-text>
<claim-text>weighing the underwater weight container without the solid specimen while the underwater weight container is immersed in a reference liquid; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>weighing the underwater weight container and the solid specimen while the underweight container with the solid specimen is immersed in the reference liquid, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the solid specimen is placed on an upper surface of the bottom plate so that the weight of the solid specimen is applied to the bottom plate if a specific gravity of the solid specimen is greater than that of the reference liquid, or</claim-text>
<claim-text>the solid specimen is inserted underneath the bottom plate so that the buoyant force from the solid specimen is applied to the bottom plate if the specific gravity of the solid specimen is smaller than that of the reference liquid.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A method for measuring specific gravity using a specific gravity measuring apparatus, the specific gravity measuring apparatus comprising an underwater weighing container having a body with a side wall defining a hollow space, the body having an upper open end and a bottom open end, a bottom plate being placed in the body which is movable both upwardly and downwardly along an axial direction of the body in a given range between the upper open end and the bottom open end for holding a solid specimen, the underwater weighing container receiving a weight or a buoyant force of the solid specimen immersed in a reference liquid, the method comprising:
<claim-text>weighing the solid specimen in air;</claim-text>
<claim-text>weighing the underwater weight container without the solid specimen while the underwater weight container is immersed in a reference liquid; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>weighing the underwater weight container and the solid specimen while the underwater weight container with the solid specimen is immersed in the reference liquid, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the solid specimen is placed on an upper surface of the bottom plate so that the weight of the solid specimen is applied to the bottom plate if a specific gravity of the solid specimen is greater than that of the reference liquid, or</claim-text>
<claim-text>the solid specimen is inserted underneath the bottom plate so that the buoyant force from the solid specimen is applied to the bottom plate if the specific gravity of the solid specimen is smaller than that of the reference liquid.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. An underwater weighing container unit, comprising:
<claim-text>an underwater weighing container having a body with a side wall defining a hollow space, the body having an upper open end and a bottom open end, a bottom plate placed in the body which is movable both upwardly and downwardly along an axial direction of the body in a given range between the upper open end and the bottom open end for holding a solid specimen inside, the underwater weighing container receiving a weight or a buoyant force of a solid specimen immersed in a reference liquid;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an aerial weighing container to receive the weight of a solid specimen in air;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a frame supporting the underwater weighing container; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a weight measuring unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A method for measuring specific gravity using the underwater weighing container according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> comprising:
<claim-text>weighing the solid specimen on the underwater weight container in air by placing the solid specimen in the aerial weighing container;</claim-text>
<claim-text>weighing the underwater weight container without the solid specimen while the underwater weight container is immersed in the reference water; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>weighing the underwater weight container and the solid specimen while the underwater weight container with the solid specimen is immersed in the reference liquid, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the solid specimen is placed on an upper surface of the bottom plate so that the weight of the solid specimen is applied to the bottom plate if a specific gravity of the solid specimen is greater than that of the reference liquid, or</claim-text>
<claim-text>the solid specimen is inserted underneath the bottom plate so that the buoyant force from the solid specimen is applied to the bottom plate if the specific gravity of the solid specimen is smaller than that of the reference liquid.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An underwater weighing container comprising:
<claim-text>a body having a side wall defining a hollow space, an upper open end, and a bottom open end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bottom plate placed in the body which is movable both upwardly and downwardly along an axial direction of the body in a given range between the upper open end and the bottom open end for holding a solid specimen, wherein the underwater weighing container receives a weight or a buoyant force of the solid specimen immersed in a reference liquid;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an aerial weighing container to receive the weight of the solid specimen in air;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a frame supporting the underwater weighing container; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a weight measuring unit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A method for measuring specific gravity using the underwater weighing container according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> comprising:
<claim-text>weighing the solid specimen on the underwater weight container in air by placing the solid specimen in the aerial weight container;</claim-text>
<claim-text>weighing the underwater weight container without the solid specimen while the underwater weight container is immersed in the reference water; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>weighing the underwater weight container and the solid specimen while the underwater weight container with the solid specimen is immersed in the reference water, wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the solid specimen is placed on an upper surface of the bottom plate so that the weight of the solid specimen is applied to the bottom plate if a specific gravity of the solid specimen is greater than that of the reference liquid, or</claim-text>
<claim-text>the solid specimen is inserted underneath the bottom plate so that the buoyant force from the solid specimen is applied to the bottom plate if the specific gravity of the solid specimen is smaller than that of the reference liquid.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The underwater weighing container according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising a rim provided at the bottom end of the body for engaging with the bottom plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The underwater weighing container according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising a stopper provided on the side wall inside the hollow space of the body for engaging with the bottom plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The underwater weighing container according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the bottom plate has a mesh or porous structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
