<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296343-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296343</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10259783</doc-number>
<date>20020930</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-301258</doc-number>
<date>20010928</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>414</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>23</class>
<subclass>P</subclass>
<main-group>19</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29740</main-classification>
<further-classification> 29721</further-classification>
<further-classification> 29739</further-classification>
<further-classification> 29833</further-classification>
<further-classification> 29834</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Electronic component mounting apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5787577</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kent</name>
<date>19980800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 29833</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6128074</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hong et al.</name>
<date>20001000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>3562371</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6178626</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hada et al.</name>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 29833</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>0652699</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19950500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>63-249018</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19881000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>9-307292</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19971100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29833</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29721</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29834</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29739</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 29740</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20030093896</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20030522</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Usui</last-name>
<first-name>Yoshinao</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tatebayashi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kawai</last-name>
<first-name>Akihiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Isesaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Okamoto</last-name>
<first-name>Manabu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Isesaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Morrison &amp; Foerster LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sanyo Electric Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Osaka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sanyo High Technology Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Gunma</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chang</last-name>
<first-name>Rick K</first-name>
<department>3726</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electronic component mounting apparatus enables a reliable decision of abnormal suction of a component even when the difference between the width and the height of the component is small. When the difference between the thickness of the electronic component detected by a sensor and the data on the thickness stored in the RAM is within the tolerance, a CPU judges that the component is held by a suction nozzle in a normal posture and executes a normal processing control. Then an image of the electronic component is captured by a recognition camera, and a recognition processing is made by an image processing unit to measure the geometry of the component. The CPU, then, judges whether the size of the component is within tolerance or not. When both X-dimension and Y-dimension of the component measured by the image processing unit are within the tolerance, the Y-dimension measured by the image processing unit and the thickness detected by the sensor are compared and the component is judged normal when the Y-dimension is larger.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="218.44mm" wi="338.33mm" file="US07296343-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="190.67mm" wi="135.04mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296343-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="176.95mm" wi="144.78mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296343-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="187.62mm" wi="137.92mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296343-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="200.83mm" wi="141.48mm" file="US07296343-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="103.97mm" wi="142.41mm" file="US07296343-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="237.41mm" wi="163.91mm" file="US07296343-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="92.71mm" wi="115.06mm" file="US07296343-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="193.46mm" wi="175.09mm" file="US07296343-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="208.20mm" wi="137.50mm" file="US07296343-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to an electronic component mounting apparatus, specifically to an automatic electronic component mounting apparatus which takes out an electronic component from a component supply with a suction nozzle attached to a carrier head, recognizes the component to adjust the position of the component based on an image captured by a component recognition camera, and mounts the component on a printed circuit board.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">An electronic component mounting apparatus of prior art measures a level of a bottom surface of an electronic component picked up with a suction nozzle using a line sensor in order to detect an posture of the component held by the nozzle, compares the result with dimensional data of the component, and makes a decision of abnormal suction, in which the component is sucked in a wrong posture, when the result exceeds a certain level.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, the decision of the abnormal suction is difficult for a minute component, especially when difference between the width and height of the component is small.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">When the line sensor cannot make the decision, component recognition by capturing an image of the component with a component recognition camera is needed. Although the component recognition camera is higher in resolution and accuracy than the line sensor, and the decision by component recognition is reliable because the decision is made based on two dimensional information, there still is a possibility of the similar problem as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">This invention is directed to a mounting apparatus which enables a decision of abnormal suction of the component even when the difference between the width and height of the component is small.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">A first aspect of this invention is providing an electronic component mounting apparatus which takes out an electronic component from a component supply with a suction nozzle attached to a mounting head, captures an image of the component held by the suction nozzle with a component, recognition camera to recognize the component for recognition processing by a position recognition sensor, adjusts the position of the component based on the recognition processing, and mounts the component on a printed circuit board. The apparatus has a memory to memorize information on dimensions of each type of the electronic components, a CPU to detect thickness of the electronic component at the nozzle based on the output from a sensor set on the path of the mounting head, an image processing unit to measure the dimensions of the electronic component based on the image captured by the component recognition camera, and a CPU to make a decision whether the posture of the component at the nozzle is normal or abnormal based on the dimensions of the component measured by the image processing unit and thickness detected by the CPU to detect thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A second aspect of this invention is providing an electronic component mounting apparatus which takes out an electronic component from a component supply with a suction nozzle attached to a mounting head, captures an image of the component held by the suction nozzle with a component recognition camera to recognize the component for recognition processing by a position recognition sensor, adjusts the position of the component based on the recognition processing, and mounts the component on a printed circuit board. The apparatus has a memory to memorize information on dimensions of each type of the electronic components, a CPU to detect a bottom edge position of the electronic component at the nozzle based on the output from a sensor set on the path of the mounting head, a CPU to judge whether an posture of the electronic component held by the suction nozzle is normal or abnormal based on the bottom edge position detected by the CPU to detect the bottom edge position and the information on the dimensions of the component memorized in the memory, an image processing unit to measure the dimensions of the electronic component based on the image captured by the component recognition camera when the CPU judges the posture of the electronic component normal, and a CPU to judge whether the posture of the electronic component held by the suction nozzle is normal or abnormal based on the dimensions of the component and the bottom edge position detected by the CPU to detect the bottom edge position when the dimensions of the electronic component measured by the image processing unit is within the tolerance.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram showing control of an electronic component mounting apparatus of an embodiment of this invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top view of an automatic electronic component mounting apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side view with a partial cross-sectional view of the electronic component mounting apparatus of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a table showing data of a component used in the embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a table showing data of another component used in the embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a table showing data of another component used in the embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flow chart of posture judgement based on the bottom edge detection.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a side view showing a chip component held by a suction nozzle.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a flow chart of posture judgement based on the bottom edge detection and the dimensional measurement of a captured component image.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a side view of an integrated circuit used in the embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a side view of an electrolytic capacitor used in the embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">An embodiment of this invention will be described hereinafter.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> show a Y-table <b>1</b> which moves in Y-direction driven by a Y-axis motor <b>2</b>, an XY-table <b>3</b> which moves in X-direction driven by an X-axis motor <b>4</b> on the Y-table, therefore moves both in X and Y-directions, and a printed circuit board <b>6</b>, to which a chip electronic component <b>5</b> (hereafter referred to as a chip component or a component) is to be attached, mounted on the XY-table with a fixing means which is not shown in the figure.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">A multitude of component supply apparatuses <b>8</b> to supply the chip component <b>5</b> are disposed on a supply stage <b>7</b>. A supply stage drive motor <b>9</b> turns a ball screw <b>10</b> which fits into a nut <b>11</b> fixed to the supply stage <b>7</b> and makes the supply stage <b>7</b> move in X-direction guided by a linear guide <b>12</b>. Mounting heads <b>15</b> as carrier heads with six suction nozzles <b>14</b> for taking out nozzles are disposed on an outer edge of a rotary table <b>13</b>, which rotates intermittently, at regular intervals aligned with a pitch of the intermittence.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The mounting head <b>15</b> stops at a suction station, where the suction nozzle <b>14</b> sucks up the component <b>5</b> from the component supply apparatus <b>8</b>. A recognition camera <b>16</b> is disposed at a recognition station and captures an image of the electronic component <b>5</b> at the suction nozzle <b>14</b>. The image captured by the recognition camera <b>16</b> is processed by an image processing unit <b>18</b> to recognize a displacement of the electronic component <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">After the recognition station, the mounting head stops at an angle adjustment station, where the mounting head <b>15</b> is turned by a head rotation apparatus <b>17</b> in θ direction by an amount of angle that is an amount of angle to correct an angular displacement of the chip component <b>5</b> by a recognition result of the image processing unit <b>18</b> added to an amount of angle shown in a mounting data, which is not shown in the figure. A second stop position after the angle adjustment station is a mounting station where the electronic component <b>5</b> at the suction nozzle <b>14</b> is mounted on the substrate <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The mounting head <b>15</b> is attached to a bottom of a head up-and-down shaft <b>40</b> which penetrate the rotary table <b>13</b> at both inside and outside and movable upward and downward, and a top of the shaft <b>40</b> is fixed to an L-shaped roller mount <b>41</b>. An upper cam follower <b>42</b> and a lower cam follower <b>43</b> are held pivotable on and inward the mount <b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">A holding stage <b>44</b> is under the rotary table <b>13</b> and holds it pivotable horizontally. A cylindrical cam <b>45</b> is formed around the holding stage <b>44</b>. The mounting head <b>15</b> moves as the rotary table <b>13</b> rotates, while being held by the cylindrical cam <b>45</b> which is sandwiched between the upper cam follower <b>42</b> and the lower cam follower <b>43</b> through a spring (not shown in the figure).</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The cylindrical cam <b>45</b> is notched at the suction station and the mounting station. The mounting head <b>15</b> moves up and down in order to suck or mount the component, as up-and-down moving bodies <b>46</b> and <b>47</b> move upward and downward driven by a cam, which is not shown, while being sandwiched between the upper cam follower <b>42</b> and the lower cam follower <b>43</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">An up-and-down rod <b>20</b> rocks a rocking lever <b>21</b> of the component supply apparatus <b>8</b> to send the chip component <b>5</b> to a component suction position of the suction nozzle <b>14</b>, by advancing a component storage tape, which is not shown, storing the chip components <b>5</b> at predetermined intervals intermittently aligning with the intervals. A tape reel <b>22</b> reels the component storage tape which is not shown. At a second station from the suction station, a line sensor <b>27</b> is disposed to detect an posture of the chip component <b>5</b> held at the suction nozzle <b>14</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The line sensor <b>27</b> is composed of a transmitter <b>28</b> projecting a light beam horizontally and a receiver <b>29</b> consisting of a multitude of CCD elements aligned on a vertical line so that the light beam can be received. The transmitter <b>28</b> can use light from an LED and collect it with a condenser lens to transmit a collimated parallel beam, or use light from a laser in the same way. 1000 elements of CCDs aligned within a height of 10 mm is realized. Each of the CCD elements can detect amount of light received, and can be used as an ON/OFF sensor by setting a threshold for the amount of light received. A portion shielded by the component <b>5</b> or the suction nozzle <b>14</b> can be detected as vertical position data by the ON/OFF outputs.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The line sensor <b>27</b> is fixed so that the light beam from the transmitter <b>28</b> hits approximately the center of the suction nozzles <b>14</b> when the suction nozzle stops as the rotary table <b>13</b> stops the rotation.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Next, a control block of the automatic electronic component mounting apparatus of the embodiment will be described referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">A CPU <b>31</b> works as a central controller and controls various operations related to mounting the chip components <b>5</b> based on various data stored in RAM <b>32</b> and information from the line sensor <b>27</b> and so on, according to a program stored in ROM <b>33</b>. The line sensor <b>27</b> is connected to the CPU <b>31</b> through an interface <b>34</b>. An index motor <b>35</b> of the rotary table <b>13</b>, one of objects controlled by the CPU <b>31</b>, is connected to the CPU <b>31</b> through the interface <b>34</b> and a drive circuit <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The output of the line sensor <b>27</b> is given from each of the CCD elements. CPU <b>31</b> calculates a bottom edge position as a lowest edge peak value, that is a vertical position of a boundary between a lowest shielded portion and unshielded portion. The RAM <b>32</b> has a read-in memory <b>38</b> as a memory means for the bottom edge position on the move and a hold memory <b>39</b> as a memory means for the lowest bottom edge position. The read-in memory <b>38</b> reads the vertical position of the bottom edge of the component <b>5</b> calculated from the output of the line sensor <b>27</b> at a regular intervals, i.e., at every move of a certain distance the suction nozzle <b>14</b> makes. The hold memory <b>39</b> stores the larger value or lower position by comparing the data with the value in the read-in memory <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The RAM <b>32</b> also stores data regarding dimensions of each of the components as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> through <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, for example, such as thickness of a component and its tolerance to be referred in comparison with the lowest edge position stored in the hold memory <b>39</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Operations with the structure described above will be explained hereinafter.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">When the automatic operation of the automatic electronic component mounting apparatus is initiated by an operation on a operation unit which is not shown, the supply stage <b>7</b> moves and the component supply apparatus <b>8</b> stops at a suction position of the suction nozzle <b>14</b> at the suction station and the chip component <b>5</b> is taken out by a descend of the nozzle <b>14</b>, according to mounting data on the component <b>5</b> stored in the RAM <b>32</b> in the order to be mounted, which is not shown.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Next, the rotary table <b>13</b> rotates intermittently driven by an index motor <b>35</b> through an index mechanism, which is not shown, the head <b>15</b> moves to and stops at the next station and with the next rotation further moves to a station where the line sensor <b>27</b> is disposed. The CPU <b>31</b> detects timing to commence the detection just before the rotary table <b>13</b> stops moving, and makes operations shown in a flow chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. The timing is when the CPU detects that a sensor, which is not shown, is turned ON by detecting a predetermined amount of rotation of a camshaft that goes into a 360-degree roll while the rotary table <b>13</b> makes one intermittent rotation. A position of the head <b>15</b> at the timing is set to a fixed position so that the detection commences before a front edge of the chip component <b>5</b> at the suction nozzle <b>14</b> reaches a detection point, i.e., the light beam position taking a displacement in a direction of movement of the largest type of the chip component <b>5</b> into consideration. The transmitter <b>28</b> of the line sensor <b>27</b> always emits the light beam and the receiver <b>29</b> is always ready to receive the light beam and provide output. Instead, the transmitter can begin emitting the light beam and the line sensor <b>27</b> can begin outputting at the timing to commence the detection. Or the timing to commence the detection and the timing to terminate the detection can be set in a range that allows the detection of up to certain size of the component <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">At the timing to commence detection, firstly the read-in memory <b>38</b> and the hold memory <b>39</b> are cleared and the CPU <b>31</b> calculates the lowest position of transition from shielded to unshielded from the output of the line sensor <b>27</b> as a lowest edge peak value, and stores it in the read-in memory <b>38</b>. The origin for the value is set above the height of the bottom edge of the suction nozzle <b>14</b> and the value is set to increase downward.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The CPU compares the value with a value stored in the hold memory <b>38</b> and stores larger value in the hold memory <b>39</b>. It is zero at the beginning since there is no component. The nozzle <b>14</b> is moving during the operation, and the CPU repeats the operation because the timing is not a timing to terminate the detection. The CPU <b>31</b> reads the output of the line sensor <b>27</b> when a portion of the component <b>5</b>, for example, a portion indicated with the second dashed line from the left in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> comes to a position of the light beam from the transmitter <b>28</b> of the line sensor <b>27</b>. A bottom edge position indicated with a black round dot in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is calculated. A value for the position is stored in the read-in memory <b>38</b>, compared with the value in the hold memory <b>39</b>, and stored into the hold memory since the value in the read-in memory <b>38</b> is larger than the value in the hold memory <b>39</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Meantime the suction nozzle <b>14</b> moves on, and the output of the line sensor <b>27</b> for the third dashed line from left in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is read in at next reading time of the CPU <b>31</b>. This value is larger than the value in the hold memory <b>39</b>, thus the value in the hold memory <b>39</b> is superseded.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The bottom edge position is higher and the value gets smaller for the next read-in position. Therefore the value in the hold memory <b>39</b> remains intact. The output of the line sensor <b>27</b> is read at each position indicated with each of the dashed lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. The CPU <b>31</b> terminates the read-in when the timing to terminate the detection is detected by a sensor, which is not shown, attached to the camshaft and similar to one described before. When the component is a component described in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the value stored in the hold memory <b>39</b>, that is for example 5.8 mm, is compared with a sum 5.6 mm of thickness 0.6 mm and a nozzle level 5.0 mm, that is the bottom edge position of the suction nozzle <b>14</b>, stored in the RAM <b>32</b>. Since the difference 0.2 mm exceeds the tolerance (±0.1 mm) of the thickness, it is judged abnormal suction (abnormal posture) and followed by an abnormal processing control.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">As the abnormal processing, no operation related to component mounting is done when the suction nozzle stops at subsequent station, the chip component is not mounted at a mounting station and is ejected at an assigned ejection station.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Next, when the chip component is sucked in normal posture and carried to the station where the line sensor <b>27</b> is disposed, a vertical level of the bottom edge of the component <b>5</b> is calculated, read into the read-in memory <b>38</b> every time the CPU reads the output of the line sensor <b>27</b>, and the lowest edge position is stored in the hold memory <b>39</b>, in the same way as described before. The value stored in the hold memory <b>39</b>, that is for example 5.55 mm, is compared with the sum 5.6 mm of the thickness 0.6 mm and the nozzle level 5.0 mm that is a bottom edge position of the suction nozzle <b>14</b> stored in the RAM <b>32</b>. Since the difference 0.05 mm is within the tolerance (±0.1 mm) of the thickness, it is judged normal suction (normal posture) and followed by a normal processing control.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">After that, an image of the electronic component <b>5</b> at the suction nozzle <b>14</b> is captured by the recognition camera <b>16</b> at the recognition station and recognition processing is performed by the image processing unit <b>18</b>. That is, the image is captured (image capturing) by the image processing unit <b>18</b>, geometry of the component is measured, and the measured size of the component (in horizontal direction) is judged whether it is within the tolerance or not.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">When the size of the component measured by the image processing unit <b>18</b> is 1.7 mm for X-dimension and 0.65 mm for Y-dimension, both are judged within the tolerance as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, that is, the X-dimension is within 1.6 mm±0.1 mm and the Y-dimension is within 0.75±0.1 mm. Then the Y-dimension 0.65 mm measured by the image processing unit <b>18</b> and the thickness 0.55 mm by the result of the measurement based on the line sensor <b>27</b> are compared and the component is judged normal and undergoes normal processing, since the Y-dimension is larger than the thickness. Thus, the mounting head <b>15</b> is turned by a head rotation apparatus <b>17</b> to adjust the angle of the chip component <b>5</b> based on a recognition result of the image processing unit <b>18</b> and the chip component <b>5</b> is mounted on the printed circuit board <b>6</b> placed by the movement of the XY-table <b>3</b> at the mounting station. At that time, because the bottom edge position, i.e., the vertical position of the bottom edge of the component <b>5</b> is known, a downward stroke of the suction nozzle is adjusted accordingly to the bottom edge position to mount the component <b>5</b> on the printed circuit board <b>6</b> with an appropriate pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">But if the thickness by the result of the measurement based on the line sensor <b>27</b> is 0.7 mm and the Y-dimension is 0.65 mm, the component is judged abnormal and undergoes abnormal processing, since the Y-dimension is smaller than the thickness. Therefore the chip component <b>5</b> is not mounted on the printed circuit board and ejected at the assigned ejection station. This case is a so-called standing posture sucking and corresponds to a case the chip component <b>5</b> is sucked on a side surface rather than on its top surface.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Next case is for an integrated circuit component (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>) having component data shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The lowest edge position, for example 7.2 mm, stored in the hold memory <b>39</b> based on the output of the line sensor is compared with the sum 7.0 mm of the thickness 2.0 mm and the nozzle level 5.0 mm, that is a bottom edge position of the suction nozzle <b>14</b>, stored in the RAM <b>32</b>. Since the difference 0.2 mm is within the tolerance of the thickness (±0.2 mm), it is judged normal suction (normal posture) and the CPU <b>31</b> makes a normal processing control shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Thus an image of the electronic component <b>5</b> is captured with the recognition camera <b>16</b>, the recognition processing is done by the image processing unit <b>18</b> to measure geometry of the component and measured size of the component is judged whether it is within the tolerance or not. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, dashed lines represent geometry of leads conforming the specification, while solid lines show geometry of leads to be explained here. When X-dimension of the component size measured by the image processing unit <b>18</b> is 12.5 mm and Y-dimension is 5.6 mm with downward bent, Y-dimension is out of tolerance, i.e., the Y-dimension is out of 6.0 mm ±0.3 mm as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. If the thickness by the result of the measurement based on the line sensor <b>27</b> is 2.2 mm, although it is within the tolerance (±0.2 mm) of the thickness of the component and judged normal, the component is judged abnormal due to lead shape failure, and gets abnormal processing.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">And when the Y-dimension of the integrated circuit component measured by the recognition processing by the image processing unit <b>18</b> on the image of the electronic component <b>5</b> captured by the recognition camera <b>16</b> is 5.6 mm, if the thickness by the result of the measurement based on the line sensor <b>27</b> is 2.0 mm (no error), although the Y-dimension is out of the tolerance, the component is judged normal as it is within measurement tolerance of the lead edge, and gets normal processing.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">That is, for a component which shows large variation in the result of measurement of Y-dimension due to the recognition of geometry of lead, such as an integrated circuit component having a thin lead edge, the CPU <b>31</b> judges it normal (because the lead edge is thin), when the measurement result of the thickness of the component is exactly equal to the component data, even when the difference in the Y-dimension is large and there is a measurement error of the lead edge. On the contrary, the CPU <b>31</b> judges it abnormal due to the lead geometry failure (downward bent, etc.), when the difference in the measurement result of both the thickness of the component and the Y-dimension is large.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Next case is for an electrolytic capacitor (refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>) having component data shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The lowest edge position, for example 9.9 mm, stored in the hold memory <b>39</b> based on the output of the line sensor is compared with the sum 9.5 mm of the thickness 4.5 mm and the nozzle level 5.0 mm, that is a bottom edge position of the suction nozzle <b>14</b>, stored in the RAM <b>32</b>. Since the difference 0.4 mm is within the tolerance (±0.4 mm) of the thickness, it is judged normal suction (normal posture) in a routine shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, and the CPU <b>31</b> makes a normal processing control shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Thus an image of the electronic component <b>5</b> is captured by with the recognition camera <b>16</b>, the recognition processing is done by the image processing unit <b>18</b> to measure geometry of the component and measured size of the component is judged whether it is within the tolerance or not. When X-dimension and Y-dimension of the component size measured by the image processing unit <b>18</b> are within the tolerance but a lead length measured by the image processing unit is out of the tolerance, that is, if the lead length measures 1.7 mm with a downward bent of one of a pair of the leads as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, the component is judged abnormal component size because measured lead length is out of a range of 2.0 mm±0.2 mm. Therefore, although the thickness 4.9 mm by the result of the measurement based on the line sensor <b>27</b> is within the tolerance of the thickness, if a parallelism of a pair of the leads is +9 degree, the component is judged abnormal due to a twisted lead failure since the parallelism exceeds ±8 degree, although there is no parallelism as component data, according to the program stored in the ROM <b>33</b>, and undergoes abnormal processing.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">And when the X-dimension and the Y-dimension of the electrolytic capacitor measured by the recognition processing by the image processing unit <b>18</b> on the image of the electronic component <b>5</b> captured by the recognition camera <b>16</b> are within the tolerance, if the length of the lead is out of tolerance, the component is judged abnormal component size. If the thickness by the result of the measurement based on the line sensor <b>27</b> is 4.5 mm (no error), even if the parallelism of a pair of the leads is +9 degree (over ±8 degree), the component is judged normal as the thickness of the component is just as the specification and the parallelism is within processing tolerance of the lead, and undergoes normal processing.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">As described above, the posture of the component <b>5</b> is judged each time the component <b>5</b> moves to a stop station, and when necessary, not only position recognition but also posture judgement is performed and an appropriate procedure is taken. The CPU <b>31</b> reads-in the output of the line sensor <b>27</b> just after the processing such as calculating the bottom edge and comparing the read-in memory <b>38</b> and this hold memory <b>39</b> in the embodiment. However it is possible prolonging the read-in intervals to execute other processing during free time. It is also possible disposing another processing unit consisting of the read-in memory and the hold memory connected with the CPU of the automatic electronic component mounting apparatus through the interface and connected with the line sensor on the other hand, so that the CPU of the mounting apparatus gives the signals to commence and terminate the detection, and judges whether the component is normal or abnormal as described before, after the CPU of the mounting apparatus reads-in the content of the hold memory after completion of the detection.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The line sensor <b>27</b> is disposed at the station where the rotary table <b>13</b> stops and detects the bottom edge of the component <b>5</b> before and after the stopping in the embodiment. The line sensor <b>27</b> can be disposed between the stations and the detection can be done while the component <b>5</b> is moving. Or the line sensor can move horizontally while the component <b>5</b> is stopping at a station. Instead of the rotary table, the mounting head can be disposed on the XY-table which moves to and gets the component from the supply stage and mounts the component on the predetermined position on the printed circuit board, and the line sensor can be disposed on the path of the mounting head.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The bottom edge position is calculated by summing up the data for the thickness of the component and the noise level stored in the RAM <b>32</b> in the embodiment. Instead, the data for the bottom edge position can be stored in the RAM <b>32</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">As described above, this invention enables the decision of abnormal suction of a component even when the difference between the width and the height of the component is small.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">As described above, this invention enables a reliable decision of abnormal suction posture of an electronic component even when the difference between the width and the height of the component is small, and can reduce the occurrence of substrate failures.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The above is a detailed description of a particular embodiment of the invention which is not intended to limit the invention to the embodiment described. It is recognized that modifications within the scope of the invention will occur to a person skilled in the art. Such modifications and equivalents of the invention are intended for inclusion within the scope of this invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electronic component mounting apparatus picking up an electronic component with a suction nozzle, capturing an image of the electronic component held by the suction nozzle with a component recognition camera for a position recognition, adjusting a position of the electronic component held by the suction nozzle based on a result of the position recognition, and mounting the component on a printed circuit board, the apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a detecting device detecting a thickness of the electronic component held by the suction nozzle based on an output from a sensor disposed along a path of the suction nozzle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an image processing unit measuring at least a dimension of the electronic component based on the image captured by the component recognition camera; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a judging device judging whether a posture of the component held by the suction nozzle is normal or abnormal by comparing the dimension of the electronic component measured by the image processing unit with the thickness of the electronic component detected by the detecting device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The electronic component mounting apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the sensor comprises a plurality of light transmitters and a plurality of light receivers so configured that each of the light receivers receives light from a corresponding light transmitter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The electronic component mounting apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the dimension of the electronic component measured by the image processing unit is a lateral dimension of the electronic component.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
