<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298020-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298020</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10797081</doc-number>
<date>20040311</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-097248</doc-number>
<date>20030331</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257536</main-classification>
<further-classification>257537</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E27035</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Semiconductor device and method of manufacturing the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6194775</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Usami</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257536</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6441447</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Czagas et al.</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257379</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0053559</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Nagao et al.</name>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438 30</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0020879</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Shiiki et al.</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A-2001-118844</doc-number>
<date>20010400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A-2002-368100</doc-number>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257536-539</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E27035</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E27041</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21004</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257359</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257379</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257380</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257581</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E27047</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257904</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438760</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438330</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438210</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438384</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438238</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>19</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040188770</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040930</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Asano</last-name>
<first-name>Syuji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nukata-gun</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nakayama</last-name>
<first-name>Yoshiaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Okazaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Eguchi</last-name>
<first-name>Koji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kariya</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Posz Law Group, PLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>DENSO CORPORATION</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kariya</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Landau</last-name>
<first-name>Matthew C.</first-name>
<department>2815</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A wire (<b>12</b>) is formed on an insulating film (<b>10</b>) on a semiconductor substrate (<b>1</b>). The wire (<b>12</b>) is covered by silicon nitride film (<b>14</b>), inorganic SOG film (<b>20</b>) and TEOS film (<b>21</b>). A thin film resistance element (<b>30</b>) of chromium silicon (CrSi) is formed on the upper surface of the TEOS film (<b>21</b>). The acute angle (taper angle) at which a line connecting the local maximum and minimum points of a step on the upper surface of the TEOS film (<b>21</b>) beneath the area where the thin film resistance element (<b>30</b>) is formed intersects to the surface of the substrate (<b>1</b>) is set to 10° or less.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="79.59mm" wi="123.78mm" file="US07298020-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="228.85mm" wi="183.56mm" file="US07298020-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="233.68mm" wi="176.36mm" file="US07298020-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="255.69mm" wi="174.07mm" file="US07298020-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="238.59mm" wi="160.53mm" file="US07298020-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="211.24mm" wi="184.32mm" file="US07298020-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="165.86mm" wi="183.05mm" file="US07298020-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="216.83mm" wi="169.93mm" file="US07298020-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is based upon, claims the benefit of priority of, and incorporates by reference the contents of, Japanese Patent Application No. 2003-97248 filed on Mar. 31, 2003.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a semiconductor device having thin film resistance elements and a method of manufacturing the same.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In a process of manufacturing a semiconductor device having a semiconductor linear circuit which is a circuit using a bipolar transistor mainly, thin film resistance elements may be used for the purpose of fine adjustment, etc. of a circuit in the semiconductor device. That is, there is a case where at the final stage of the semiconductor device manufacturing process, thin film resistance elements having desired resistance values are formed in a manufactured circuit and used as a part of the circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> schematically shows an example of the semiconductor device having thin film resistance elements as described above. In this case, thin film resistance elements <b>130</b> are formed in a field area which is located above first and second interlayer insulating films <b>110</b>, <b>120</b> covering a semiconductor substrate <b>100</b> and in which any element such as a transistor or the like are not formed. In this field area, the upper surface of the second interlayer insulating film <b>120</b> is relatively flat, and thus the thin film resistance elements <b>130</b> can be formed in the field area so as to have a desired characteristic.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The formation of the thin film resistance elements <b>130</b> in the field area as described above causes an increase in the area of the semiconductor device.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In order to avoid the increase in the area of the semiconductor device, JP-A-2002-124639 (Patent Document <b>1</b>) has proposed that the thin film resistance elements <b>130</b> are formed above an area where elements and wires are formed as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">When the thin film resistance elements <b>130</b> are formed above the area where the elements and the wires are formed as described above, a step occurs on the upper surface of the second interlayer insulating film <b>120</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>. When the thin film resistance elements <b>130</b> are formed on the interlayer insulating film <b>120</b> having the step, dispersion in resistance value is increased to a non-negligible level.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention has been implemented in view of the foregoing situation, and has an object to provide a semiconductor device and a semiconductor device manufacturing method which can suitably suppress dispersion of the resistance values of thin film resistance elements even when the thin film resistance elements are formed above an area where elements and wires are formed.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In order to attain the above object, according to a semiconductor device of a first aspect of the present invention, an intersecting acute angle between the surface of a semiconductor substrate and a line connecting local maximum and minimum points of a step on the upper surface of an interlayer insulating film beneath an area where the thin film resistance elements are formed is set to 10° or less.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">As the step on the upper surface of the interlayer insulating film is larger, the dispersion of the resistance values of the thin film resistance elements is increased. Particularly, it has been confirmed by the inventors that when the scale of the step is defined by the intersecting acute angle between the line connecting the local maximum and minimum points of the step and the surface of the semiconductor substrate, the dispersion of the resistance value increases sharply at and after the stage that the intersecting acute angle exceeds “10°”.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to the above construction, the dispersion of the resistance values of the thin film resistance elements can be properly suppressed by setting the acute angle to “10°” or less.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A semiconductor device according to a second aspect of the present invention is equipped with an inorganic spin-on-glass film as the interlayer insulating film, the inorganic spin-on-glass film being formed so as to cover the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In the above construction, the inorganic spin-on-glass film is used. The inorganic spin-on-glass film has no methyl group, and thus it hardly pollutes a plug in a via hole as compared with an organic spin-on-glass film. Accordingly, when a via hole is formed in the inorganic spin-on-glass film, the upper and lower layers of the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be brought into contact with each other through the via hole and pollution in the via hole can be suppressed. Therefore, the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed can be covered by the inorganic spin-on-glass film. In this case, the upper surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be properly flattened by rotational coating.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In a semiconductor device according to a third aspect of the present invention, the interlayer insulating film comprises an inorganic spin-on-glass film and an insulating film of a lower layer of the inorganic spin-on-glass film. The insulating film of the lower layer is designed so that the upper surface of an area of the insulating film which is adjacent to an area of the insulating film above which the thin film resistance elements are formed (hereinafter referred to as “thin film resistance element formed area”) is higher than the upper surface of the thin film resistance element formed area of the insulating film.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In the above construction, when the inorganic spin-on-glass film is coated by rotational coating, the material of the inorganic spin-on-glass film flows to an area below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed. Accordingly, the upper surface of the interlayer insulating film beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed can be properly flattened by using the inorganic spin-on-glass film.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In addition, the inorganic spin-on-glass film has no methyl group, and thus it hardly pollutes a plug in a via hole as compared with an organic spin-on-glass film. Accordingly, when a via hole is formed in the inorganic spin-on-glass film, the upper and lower layers of the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be brought into contact with each other through the via hole. Therefore, the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed can be covered by the inorganic spin-on-glass film. In this case, the upper of the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be properly flattened by rotational coating.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In a semiconductor device according to a fourth aspect of the present invention, the thin film resistance elements are formed above an area where the wires are formed, and the interval of the wires is set to “1.7 μm” or more.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">As the interval of the wires formed below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed is narrower, the dispersion of the resistance values of the thin film resistance elements is liable to increase. Particularly, it has been confirmed by the inventors that when the interval of the wires is set to “1.7 μm” or more, the intersecting acute angle between the surface of the semiconductor substrate and the line connecting the local maximum and minimum points of the step on the upper surface of the interlay insulating film can be more easily set to “10°” or less.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Accordingly, in the above construction, the dispersion of the resistance value can be properly suppressed by setting the interval of the wires to “1.7 μm” or more.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In a semiconductor device according to a fifth aspect of the present invention, the thin film resistance elements are formed above the area where the wires are formed, and each thin film resistance element and each wire are disposed in parallel to each other so that the projections thereof are substantially overlapped with each other.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In the above construction, by forming the thin film resistance elements and the wires so that they are disposed in parallel to each other and the projections thereof are substantially overlapped with each other, occurrence of steps on the bottom surfaces of the thin film resistance elements in accordance with the presence or absence of the wires can be properly avoided.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Furthermore, in a semiconductor device according to a sixth aspect of the present invention, inorganic spin-on-glass film formed so as to cover the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed is equipped as the interlayer insulating film.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In the above construction, the inorganic spin-on-glass film is used. The inorganic spin-on-glass film has no methyl group, and thus it hardly pollutes a plug in a via hole as compared with an organic spin-on-glass film. Accordingly, when a via hole is formed in the inorganic spin-on-glass film, the upper and lower layers of the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be brought into contact with each other with suppressing pollution in the via hole. Therefore, the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be formed so as to cover the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed. In this case, the upper surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be properly flattened by rotational coating. In addition, the dispersion of the resistance values of the thin film resistance elements can be properly suppressed.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">A semiconductor device manufacturing method according to a seventh aspect of the present invention comprises a step of rotationally coating an inorganic spin-on-glass film to form the inorganic spin-on-glass film as an interlayer insulating film while flattening the upper surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film, and a step of forming any one of the thin film resistance element and the insulating film constituting the interlayer insulating film on the inorganic spin-on-glass film flattened by the rotational coating.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In the above manufacturing method, the inorganic spin-on-glass film is used. The inorganic spin-on-glass film has no methyl group, and thus it hardly pollutes a plug in a via hole as compared with an organic spin-on-glass film. Accordingly, when a via hole is formed in the inorganic spin-on-glass film, the upper and lower layers of the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be brought into contact with each other and pollution in the via hole can be suppressed.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Therefore, in the step of forming the inorganic spin-on-glass film, the inorganic spin-on-glass film can be formed so as to cover the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed. Any one of the thin film resistance element and the insulating film constituting the interlayer insulating film can be directly formed on the upper surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film flattened by the rotational coating without subjecting the upper surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film to a treatment such as etching or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Accordingly, according to the manufacturing method described above, the dispersion of the resistance values of the thin film resistance elements can be properly suppressed.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The above and other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent from the following detailed description made with reference to the accompanying drawings. In the drawings:</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a semiconductor device according to a first preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A to 2C</figref> are diagrams showing the relationship between the dispersion of “pairing performance” of thin film resistance elements and a step of an insulating film below the element;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A to 3D</figref> are diagrams showing the relationship between each of the dispersion of “pairing performance” of the thin film resistance elements and the step of the insulating film below the element and the interval of metal film formed below the thin film resistance elements;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a graph showing the comparison between characteristics of semiconductor devices when an inorganic SOG film and an organic SOG film are used as the interlayer insulating film;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A to 5E</figref> are cross-sectional views showing a manufacturing process according to an embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the semiconductor device according to a second preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a plan view of the semiconductor device according to a third preferred embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a modification of the third embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a related art semiconductor device; and</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a conventional semiconductor device.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Preferred embodiments according to the present invention will be described hereunder with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">First Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">A first embodiment of a semiconductor device and a method of manufacturing the semiconductor device according to the present invention will be described with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the semiconductor device according to a preferred embodiment. The device includes an insulating film <b>10</b> such as a silicon oxide film or the like formed on a semiconductor substrate <b>1</b> in which an element such as a bipolar transistor Tr or the like is formed. Wires <b>12</b> are formed on the insulating film <b>10</b>. The upper and side surfaces of the wires <b>12</b> are covered by a silicon nitride film <b>14</b> except for a contact site thereof which will be brought into electrical contact with the upper layer. The silicon oxide film <b>14</b> is provided to protect the wires <b>12</b>. Furthermore, an inorganic spin-on-glass film (inorganic SOG film) <b>20</b> is formed on the silicon nitride film <b>14</b>, and a TEOS (tetraethylorthosilicate) film <b>21</b> is formed on the inorganic spin-on-glass film <b>20</b>. The TEOS film <b>21</b> serves as a protection film for covering the surface of the inorganic SOG <b>20</b> because the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> has high hygroscopicity.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> formed of chromium silicon (CrSi) are formed on the upper surface of the TEOS film <b>21</b>, and an insulating film <b>40</b> such as a silicon nitride film or the like is formed so as to cover the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b>. Via holes <b>41</b> are formed in the insulating film <b>40</b>, and the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are brought into contact with wires <b>42</b> on the insulating film <b>40</b> through the via holes <b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In the semiconductor device of this embodiment in which a semiconductor linear circuit using a bipolar transistor mainly is mounted, the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are used to carry out fine adjustment, etc. on the semiconductor linear circuit. In this embodiment, the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed above an area where elements such as a bipolar transistor Tr, etc. and wires <b>12</b> are formed, thereby suppressing increase of the area of the semiconductor device concerned.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Here, with respect to a step occurring on the upper surface of the TEOS film <b>21</b>, the acute angle (taper angle) at which a line connecting the local maximum and minimum points of the step intersects to the surface of the semiconductor substrate <b>1</b> is set to “10°” or less. This will be described hereunder with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A to 2C</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a graph of experimental data showing the relationship between the dispersion of the resistance values of the thin film resistance elements and the taper angle for the step on the upper surface of the interlayer insulating film beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed. Each plot (o) in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> represents the average of plural measurement values for the dispersion of pairing performance, and the actual measurement values for each plot o are located over an area indicated by the line segment penetrating through the plot o. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> shows a pair of thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b> and L<b>2</b> which are formed to have the same shape and used for the above experiment. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along line IIC-IIC of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Here, the dispersion of the resistance values of the thin film resistance elements is defined as the dispersion in resistance value between the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b> and L<b>2</b> formed in the same shape (line width of “1 to 10 μm”, film thickness of “10 to 50 nm”) (dispersion of pairing performance). That is, when the resistance values measured for the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> are represented by R<b>1</b>, R<b>2</b> respectively, the dispersion of pairing performance is defined as follows:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>(<i>R</i><b>1</b>−<i>R</i><b>2</b>){(<i>R</i><b>1</b>+<i>R</i><b>2</b>)/<b>2</b>}×100<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>, the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> used in this experiment are formed in the same process including a film forming step based on sputtering and a patterning step based on a lithography technique. These thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> are formed through the interlayer insulating film <b>51</b> above the area where the wires <b>50</b> are formed so that they are substantially orthogonal to the wires <b>50</b>. The upper surfaces of the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> are covered by the interlayer insulating film <b>52</b>. The thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b> and L<b>2</b> are connected through barrier layers <b>53</b>, <b>54</b> and plugs <b>55</b> to the wires <b>56</b> on the interlayer insulating film <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The taper angle is defined as an acute angle θ at which a line Ld connecting the local minimum point Pmin and the local maximum point Pmax of a step on the upper surface of the interlayer insulating film <b>51</b> intersects to a plane S parallel to the semiconductor substrate. Here, the local maximum point Pmax and the local minimum point Pmin are defined as the local maximum and minimum points of a step caused by a member (in this case, a wire <b>50</b>) formed below the interlayer insulating film <b>51</b>. In the experiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, the taper angle is determined by achieving the local maximum point and the local minimum point from a photograph of the cross-section of a device as an experiment target.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">It is apparent from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> that the dispersion of pairing performance increases sharply at and after the stage that the taper angle exceeds “10°”. Therefore, in this embodiment, the taper angle for the step on the upper surface of the TEOS film <b>21</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is set to “10°” or less.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Next, a manner of equipping the member formed below the thin film resistance elements to implement the above setting will be described.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, in this case, plural metal films <b>60</b> of aluminum are equipped in parallel to one another below the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> for which the dispersion of pairing performance is to be measured so that the metal films <b>60</b> are disposed to be substantially orthogonal to the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b>. Then, these metal films <b>60</b> are covered by silicon nitride film <b>61</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> (which is a cross-sectional view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> along line IIIB-IIIB). Furthermore, an organic SOG film <b>62</b> is formed between the respective metal films <b>60</b> so as to compensate for the step between the respective metal films <b>60</b>. The upper side of the organic SOG films <b>62</b> and the silicon nitride film <b>61</b> are covered by an TEOS film <b>63</b> of 200 to 400 nm in film thickness. Thereafter, the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> are formed on the TEOS film <b>63</b>. The thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> are formed in the same process having the film formation step based on sputtering and the patterning step based on the lithography technique. Furthermore, the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> are covered by the interlayer insulating film <b>65</b>, and the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> and the electrodes <b>66</b> on the interlayer insulating film <b>65</b> are connected to one another through barrier layers <b>67</b>, <b>68</b> and plugs <b>69</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Under the condition described above, the dispersion of pairing performance when the interval of the metal films <b>60</b> (represented by W in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>) is varied in the range from 0.8 μm to 10 μm is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref>, as the interval of the metal films <b>60</b> is larger, the dispersion of pairing performance is reduced more greatly. A plot o in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref> represents the average value of plural measurement values for the dispersion of pairing performance, and the actual measurement values of each plot are located over the area indicated by a line segment penetrating through the plot (o).</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3D</figref> is a graph showing taper angles for steps in areas beneath the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> on the upper surface of the TEOS film <b>63</b> when the interval of the metal films <b>60</b> is varied in the range from 0.8 μm to 10 μm. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3D</figref>, as the interval of the metal films <b>60</b> is larger, the taper angle is reduced more greatly.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">From the foregoing description, it can be concluded that the dispersion of pairing performance is increased due to reduction of the interval of the metal films <b>60</b> because the reduction of the interval of the metal films <b>60</b> causes increase of the taper angle for the steps in the areas beneath the thin film resistance elements L<b>1</b>, L<b>2</b> on the upper surface of the TEOS film <b>63</b>. It can be estimated that this phenomenon occurs because when the interval of the metal films <b>60</b> is narrow, the patterning precision in the lithographing step and the subsequent etching step during the process of forming respective members on the metal films <b>60</b> is more greatly reduced as a patterning target is denser.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Accordingly, in order to reduce the dispersion of pair performance by reducing the taper angle, it is effective to increase the interval of the metal films <b>60</b>. Particularly, it is apparent from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3D</figref> that when the interval of the metal films <b>60</b> is set to 1.7 μm or more, the taper angle can be set to 10° or less.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Furthermore, according to the present invention, the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> is equipped as the interlayer insulating film formed between each wire <b>12</b> and each thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. This inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> has no methyl group, and thus it hardly pollutes the plug in the via hole as compared with the organic SOG film. Accordingly, when the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> is used, even when a via hole <b>23</b> through which the upper and lower layers thereof are brought into contact with each other is formed as indicated by a broken line of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the plug in the via hole <b>23</b> can be suitably avoided from being polluted.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Therefore, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> can be formed so as to cover the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed. Furthermore, in the area below the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed, the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> can be formed so that the upper surface thereof can be set to be higher than the upper surfaces of the wires <b>12</b> causing the steps on the upper surface of the TEOS film <b>21</b> even at the lowest position of the upper surface of the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b>. Accordingly, the flattening of the upper surface of the TEOS film <b>21</b> beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed can be promoted by using the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">On the other hand, if the organic SOG film has a methyl group, it might pollute the plug in the via hole if the organic SOG film comes into contact with the via hole. Therefore, when the organic SOG film is used to compensate for the steps of the elements and the wires, the organic SOG film is ordinarily formed on the side surfaces of the elements and the wires so that the organic SOG film does not come into contact with the via hole as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>. However, when the organic SOG film is formed in the above style, over-etching is carried out to surely avoid the contact between the organic SOG film and the via hole, and thus the flattening of the upper surface of the elements and the wires is not necessarily sufficiently performed.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the relationship between the interval of the metal films formed below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed, and the taper angle of the interlayer insulating film beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed. Plots o and Δ in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> show the average values of plural measurement values for the dispersion of pairing performance in the case of use of the inorganic SOG film and the organic SOG film, respectively. The actual measurement values are located over an area indicated by a line segment penetrating through each plot in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. In the case of use of the inorganic SOG film, the construction shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is used, and in the case of use of the organic SOG film, the construction shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is used.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the taper angle of the interlayer insulating film beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed can be more easily reduced in the case of the inorganic SOG film than in the case of the organic SOG film.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the taper angle is equal to “10°” or less irrespective of the metal film interval at all times in the case of use of the inorganic SOG film, however, this is satisfied in the case where the setting shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is carried out. That is, this is satisfied in the case where in the area below the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed, the upper surface of the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> is set to be higher than the upper surfaces of the wires <b>12</b> even at the lowest position of the upper surface of the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b>. Accordingly, in the case where the film thickness is extremely small, the taper angle is not necessarily equal to 10° or less even when the inorganic SOG film is used. Accordingly, even when the inorganic SOG film is used, it is favorable to properly consider the interval of the metal films and the laying direction of the metal films in order to set the taper angle to 10° or less.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Here, the manufacturing process of the semiconductor device according to this embodiment will be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5E</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">In this series of steps, wires <b>12</b> formed of aluminum or the like are first formed on the insulting film <b>10</b> in a step of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>. Thereafter, the wires <b>12</b> are covered by a silicon nitride film <b>14</b> in a subsequent step of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>. In a step of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>, the material of the inorganic SOG film is rotationally coated and then stepwise subjected to a baking treatment of 100 to 250° C. and a baking treatment of 300 to 350° to thereby form the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">As described above, by rotationally coating the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b>, the effect of the steps of the wires <b>12</b> is moderated on the upper surface of the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Furthermore, in a step of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5D</figref>, the TEOS film <b>21</b> is formed on the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> by a chemical vapor deposition method using plasma method (plasma CVD method). Thereafter, in a step of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5E</figref>, chromium silicon (CrSi) film is formed by sputtering and then subjected to patterning by using the lithography technique to form the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">According to the first embodiment described above, the following effects can be achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">(1) By setting the taper angle to 10° or less, the dispersion of the resistance value can be properly suppressed.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">(2) The inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> is used as the interlayer insulating film. The inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> can be formed so as to cover the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed, and thus the step occurring on the TEOS film <b>21</b> beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed can be properly suppressed.</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">Second Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Next, a second preferred embodiment will be described with reference to the accompanying drawings while concentrating on the different points from the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows the construction of a semiconductor device according to the second embodiment. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the same members as those of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> are represented by the same reference numerals for the sake of convenience.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, according to this embodiment, the upper surfaces of the silicon nitride film <b>14</b> serving as the insulating film and the insulating film <b>10</b> which are formed in the lower layer of the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> are set so that the upper surfaces of the insulating films <b>14</b> and <b>10</b> in an area adjacent to an area above which the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed is set to be higher than those in the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed. Therefore, when the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> is rotationally coated, the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> flows to the area below the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed. Accordingly, the flattening of the area beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed can be promoted by using the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">According to this embodiment, a field oxide film <b>2</b> and a polysilicon film <b>3</b> are used to set the upper surface of the silicon nitride film <b>14</b> in the above style. That is, in order to separate the elements on the semiconductor substrate <b>1</b>, the field oxide film <b>2</b> is formed by the LOCOS method, and then the polysilicon film <b>3</b> is formed on the field oxide film <b>2</b>, whereby the upper surfaces of the silicon nitride film <b>14</b> and insulating film <b>10</b> can be set to be higher than the upper surfaces of the wires <b>12</b> on the field oxide film <b>2</b> and the polysilicon film <b>3</b>. Accordingly, the upper surface of the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> can be formed-so as to be higher than the upper surfaces of the wires <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">According to the second embodiment described above, the following effect can be achieved in addition to the effects (1) and (2) of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">(3) The upper surfaces of the silicon nitride film <b>14</b> serving as the insulating film and the insulating film <b>10</b> which are formed in the lower layer of the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b> can be set to be higher in an area adjacent to an area above which the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed than in the area above which the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed. Accordingly, the flattening of the area beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed can be promoted by using the inorganic SOG film <b>20</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0009" level="1">Third Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a third preferred embodiment will be discussed by concentrating on the different points from the first embodiment. In this embodiment, the same members as those of the first embodiment are represented by the same reference numerals for the sake of convenience.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">In the first embodiment, each thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> and each wire <b>12</b> are laid so as to be substantially orthogonal to each other. On the other hand, in this embodiment, each thin film resistance element <b>30</b> and each wire <b>12</b> are formed so as to be disposed in parallel to each other and so that the projections thereof are substantially overlapped with each other. Specifically, the projections of the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are accommodated in the wires <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">Accordingly, occurrence of any step in the TEOS film <b>21</b> in accordance with the presence or absence of the wire <b>12</b> can be properly avoided in the area beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows a modification of the third embodiment of the present invention according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">In this modification, plural thin film resistance elements <b>200</b> are arranged on a metal wiring film <b>150</b> containing a power supply line, a ground line, etc. Furthermore, an interlayer insulating film formed of an insulating film such as TEOS, SOG or the like is interposed between the metal wiring film and each thin film resistance element. With this construction, the pairing performance of the thin film resistance elements can be secured.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">This modification is assumed to be applied to a circuit in which a power supply line and a GND line which have a relatively large wiring width are equipped in a chip. However, this modification may be also applied to an electrode of an MDS capacitor or metal capacitor which has a relatively large area.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">As described above, according to this embodiment, the following effect can be achieved in addition to the effects (1) and (2) of the first embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">(4) The thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> and the wires <b>12</b> are formed so that they are disposed in parallel to each other and the projections thereof are substantially overlapped with each other, whereby occurrence of any step on the TEOS film <b>21</b> due to the presence and absence of wires <b>12</b> can be properly avoided.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">The thin film resistance elements according to the present invention are suitably used as a resistance group needing pairing performance or unit performance like resistors for an input of an operational amplifier (for creating a reference voltage), for example.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">Furthermore, when the thin film resistance elements are disposed on a metal wire film or electrode like in the modification of the third embodiment, it is preferable that resistance elements used as a pair are equipped on a wire/electrode to which the same potential is applied. This is because even when these paired resistance elements suffer an effect of potential, the effects on these resistance elements are the same level, and thus these effects can be offset with each other.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">The above-described embodiments may be modified as follows.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">The material of the thin film resistance elements is not limited to chromium silicon (CrSi). For example, it may be formed of CrSiON, SnO<sub>2</sub>, CrSiN, NiCr, Ta, Cr, CrTi, Ti, TiAl, TiN, Re, β-FaSi, monocrystal silicon, polycrystal silicon, Wsi, W, TaN, Mo-Si, laminate film of Ti and TiN, laminate film of Ti and WN or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">The interlayer insulating film equipped between each wire and each thin film resistance element is not limited to the above embodiments. The interlayer insulating film is preferably to be equipped with inorganic SOG film.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">In the first and second embodiments, the wires are equipped through the interlayer insulating film in the area below the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed. In place of the wires, elements (devices) may be formed. That is, in the construction of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, elements such as bipolar transistors Tr or the like may be equipped below the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> in place of the wires <b>12</b>. In this case, there may occur dispersion in resistance values of the thin film resistance elements due to some step caused by the elements. Therefore, the setting of the interlayer insulating film like the first and second embodiments is effective.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">In the second embodiment described above, the formation area of the inorganic SOG film is not limited to only the area below the area where the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are formed as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, and it may be formed on the whole surface of the semiconductor substrate <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">In the second embodiment described above, the means of setting the height of the upper surface of the insulating film of the lower layer of the inorganic SOG film so that the upper surface of the insulating film in an area adjacent the area of the insulating film below the thin film resistance element formed area is higher than that in the thin film resistance element formed area is not limited to the embodiments of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. In short, with respect to the insulating film of the lower layer, in order to make the area adjacent to the area below the thin film resistance element formed area higher than the area below the thin film resistance element formed area, the adjacent area may be properly equipped with a step adjusting means.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">Even when no inorganic SOG film is used, the taper angle for the step on the upper surface of the interlayer insulting film beneath the area where the thin film resistance elements are formed can be set to 10° or less by the construction of the third embodiment or by sufficiently separating the metal films from each other as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">In the first and second embodiments, the wires <b>12</b> and the thin film resistance elements <b>30</b> are disposed so as to be substantially orthogonal to each other, however, the arrangement of these elements and wires is not limited to this embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">In the above-described embodiments, the present invention is applied to a semiconductor device having a semiconductor linear circuit which is a circuit using a bipolar transistor mainly. However, the present invention is not limited to this circuit, and it may be a semiconductor device having a CMOS circuit mounted therein.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A semiconductor device having a plurality of thin film resistance elements located above an interlayer insulating film above an area where at least one of an element and a wire is formed on a semiconductor substrate, wherein a taper angle at which a line connecting the local maximum and minimum points of a step on the upper surface of the interlayer insulating film beneath an area where the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed intersects to the surface of the semiconductor substrate is set to be within a range that is greater than 0° and less than or equal to 10°, wherein each of the plurality of thin film resistance elements has a similar shape, wherein the interlayer insulating film includes an inorganic spin-on-glass film and a tetraethylorthosilicate film covering a surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The semiconductor device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the inorganic spin-on-glass film is formed so as to cover the overall area below the area where the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The semiconductor device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed above an area where a plurality of wires is formed, and a wire interval is set to 1.7 μm or more.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The semiconductor device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed above the area where the wire is formed, and the plurality of thin film resistance elements and the wire are disposed in parallel to each other so that projections thereof are overlapped with each other.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The semiconductor device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of thin film resistance elements further comprises paired thin film resistance elements.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The semiconductor device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein each of the plurality of thin film resistance elements comprises chromium silicon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A semiconductor device having a plurality of thin film resistance elements located above an interlayer insulating film above an area where at least one of an element and a wire is formed on a semiconductor substrate, wherein a taper angle at which a line connecting the local maximum and minimum points of a step on the upper surface of the interlayer insulating film beneath an area where the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed intersects to the surface of the semiconductor substrate is set to be within a range that is greater than 0° and less than or equal to 10°, wherein each of the plurality of thin film resistance elements has a similar shape, wherein the interlayer insulating film includes an inorganic spin-on-glass film and a tetraethylorthosilicate film covering a surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film, wherein an upper surface of the interlayer insulating film has a higher area adjacent to an area where the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed than in the area where the plurality of thin film resistance elements is not formed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The semiconductor device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein each of the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed to have a width in a range between 1 and 10 μm, and a thickness in a range between 10 and 50 nm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A semiconductor device having a plurality of thin film resistance elements disposed above an interlayer insulating film above an area where at least one of an element and a plurality of wires is formed on a semiconductor substrate, wherein a taper angle at which a line connecting the local maximum and minimum points of a step on the upper surface of the interlayer insulating film beneath an area where the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed intersects to the surface of the semiconductor substrate is set to be greater than 0° and less than or equal to 10°, wherein the interlayer insulating film comprises an inorganic spin-on-glass film and a tetraethylorthosilicate film, wherein the inorganic spin-on-glass film is formed so as to cover the overall area below the area where the thin film resistance element is formed, wherein the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed on an area where the plurality of wires is formed, and a wire interval is set to 1.7 μm or more, wherein each of the plurality of thin film resistance elements has a similar shape, wherein the tetraethylorthosilicate film is formed to cover a surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The semiconductor device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein each of the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed to have a width in a range between 1 and 10 μm, and a thickness in a range between 10 and 50 nm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A semiconductor device having a plurality of thin film resistance elements disposed above an interlayer insulating film above an area where a plurality of wires is formed on a semiconductor substrate, wherein a taper angle at which a line connecting the local maximum and minimum points of a step on the upper surface of the interlayer insulating film beneath an area where the plurality of thin film resistance elements is formed intersects to the surface of the semiconductor substrate is set to be greater than 0° and less than or equal to 10°, wherein the interlayer insulating film comprises an inorganic spin-on-glass film and a tetraethylorthosilicate film covering a surface of the inorganic spin-on-glass film, wherein a wire interval is set to 1.7 μm or more, wherein each of the plurality of thin film resistance elements has a similar shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
