<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296543-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296543</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11399669</doc-number>
<date>20060406</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>P</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>10</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 4144</main-classification>
<further-classification>123 4147</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Engine coolant pump drive system and apparatus for a vehicle</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5619957</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Michels</name>
<date>19970400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>123 4144</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6318531</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Usoro</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>192 215</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6561141</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Stretch et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>123 4144</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6612815</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Pawellek</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>417366</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6668766</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Liederman et al.</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>123 4144</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0194459</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Namuduri</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 60435</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 4144</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 4147</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070234980</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20071011</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Namuduri</last-name>
<first-name>Chandra S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Troy</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Rule</last-name>
<first-name>David S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Waterford</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Murty</last-name>
<first-name>Balarama V.</first-name>
<address>
<city>West Bloomfield</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>GM Global Technology Operations, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Detroit</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Kamen</last-name>
<first-name>Noah P.</first-name>
<department>3747</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An engine coolant pump drive system for a vehicle having an engine, an engine coolant system, and at least one sensor for sensing at least one operational condition of the vehicle is disclosed. The pump drive system includes a magnetorheological fluid (MRF) clutch, and a coolant pump. The MRF clutch includes a torque input section coupled to a torque output section via a MRF, the torque input section being configured to receive a torque input from the engine. The coolant pump is configured for operable communication with the torque output section of the MRF clutch. In response to a signal from the at least one sensor, the MRF clutch is configured to provide a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section, thereby providing for variable coolant flow in the engine coolant system via the coolant pump capable of a continuously variable speed.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="147.66mm" wi="228.01mm" file="US07296543-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="228.60mm" wi="166.45mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296543-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="223.86mm" wi="175.34mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296543-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="257.64mm" wi="173.48mm" file="US07296543-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present disclosure relates generally to an engine coolant pump drive system and apparatus, and particularly to a variable speed engine coolant pump drive system and apparatus.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A typical engine cooling system employs an engine driven water pump, driven by a belt for example, for circulating coolant fluid, such as a water-glycol mixture for example, that is circulated through the engine block and the radiator. Since the pump is driven directly by the engine using a belt, its speed is determined by that of the engine, and it operates continuously as long as the engine is running, resulting in continuous losses due to constant operation and constant circulation of the coolant fluid through the cooling loop, whether the cooling action is needed or not. Also, the pump has to be designed to provide the required flow and pressure for the worst-case engine speed, which could be near idle or during high grade towing. This results in much higher pump flow at higher engine speeds than is necessary, further increasing the losses in the coolant system, which results ultimately in increased fuel consumption.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Other water pump systems have been introduced to decouple the coolant pump from the engine and provide an on-demand coolant flow using an electric motor-driven or electrically operated clutch driven pump. Both of these systems offer improvement to the vehicle fuel economy by providing an on-demand coolant flow and minimizing and/or eliminating the parasitic losses associated with the engine belt-driven coolant pump. However, the electric motor-driven coolant pump needs a high power electric motor, power electronics for controlling the speed of the motor, and a reliable electrical power supply, which includes the engine driven alternator and the battery. The overall power losses in a typical electric motor-driven coolant pump still involves significant losses through the engine alternator, power electronics, electric motor, and pump system. An electrically operated clutch driven coolant pump, employing an electromagnetic clutch for example, may be either on or off, with no continuous adjustment of the output speed being possible, resulting in significant shock loads on the engine.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Accordingly, there is a need in the art for an engine coolant pump drive system that overcomes these drawbacks.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">An embodiment of the invention includes an engine coolant pump drive system for a vehicle having an engine, an engine coolant system, and at least one sensor for sensing at least one operational condition of the vehicle. The pump drive system includes a magnetorheological fluid (MRF) clutch, and a coolant pump. The MRF clutch includes a torque input section coupled to a torque output section via a MRF, the torque input section being configured to receive a torque input from the engine. The coolant pump is configured for operable communication with the torque output section of the MRF clutch. In response to a signal from the at least one sensor, the MRF clutch is configured to provide a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section, thereby providing for variable coolant flow in the engine coolant system via the coolant pump capable of a continuously variable speed.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Another embodiment of the invention includes a magnetorheological fluid (MRF) clutch for coupling an engine coolant pump with an engine of a vehicle having at least one sensor productive of a signal representative of a temperature of the engine. The MRF clutch includes a torque input section coupled to a torque output section via a MRF, the torque input section being configured to receive a torque input from the engine. The torque input section includes first and second portions with a space therebetween, the first portion being radially outboard of the second portion, the first portion being configured to receive a torque input from the engine, the first and second portions being configured to rotate together about the same axis of rotation. The torque output section includes a rotor attached to a shaft, the rotor being disposed within the space between the first and second portions so as to form an annulus between the rotor and the first and second portions, the annulus containing a MRF, and the shaft being configured for operable communication with the coolant pump. The MRF clutch also includes a stationary magnetic field generator disposed radially inboard of the second portion. In response to a signal from the at least one sensor, the magnetic field generator is capable of generating a variable strength magnetic field that is in field communication with the first portion, the second portion, the rotor, and the MRF, thereby providing for a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Referring to the exemplary drawings wherein like elements are numbered alike in the accompanying Figures:</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> depicts in block diagram form an exemplary embodiment of an engine coolant system in accordance with an embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> depicts in cross-sectional view an exemplary embodiment of a pump drive system in accordance with an embodiment of the invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> depicts in cross-sectional view an exemplary embodiment of a magnetorheological clutch for use in an exemplary pump drive system in accordance with an embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">An embodiment of the invention provides a means to directly control the speed of an engine driven coolant pump by using a magnetorheological fluid (MRF) coupling (clutch) integrated between an accessory drive of the engine and the engine coolant pump. The MRF clutch provides for a continuously adjustable pump speed by controlling the torque transmitted from the engine drive shaft to that of the engine coolant pump. The MRF clutch may be part of the pump assembly or part of a pulley assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An electronic controller is used to interface engine sensors (engine rpm, throttle angle, manifold absolute pressure, coolant temperature, engine cylinder head temperature, for example) and vehicle sensors (speed, accelerator pedal position, brake pedal position, for example) with an electronic amplifier to generate a current signal to an excitation coil embedded in the MRF clutch, thereby enabling the speed of the pump to vary in a continuous manner. It is also envisioned that an integrated speed sensor within the pump and/or a pressure or flow sensor in the coolant lines may be used to provide additional control information to the electronic controller for adjusting the MRF clutch coil current.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">An embodiment of the invention provides an engine coolant pump drive system having the MRF clutch integrally arranged with the coolant pump. Another embodiment provides the MRF clutch external to the coolant pump. Both pump drive systems are configured for efficiently cooling the engine of a vehicle by providing for variable coolant flow via the coolant pump, which may be operated by continuously varying its speed according to the operating conditions of the vehicle. As such, an embodiment of the invention may be employed for the purpose of minimizing parasitic power losses present in a belt driven engine coolant pump by providing a variable speed direct drive or pulley drive.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> depicts in block diagram form an exemplary embodiment of an engine coolant system <b>100</b> having an engine coolant pump drive system <b>105</b>, a control system <b>110</b> responsive to one or more vehicle operating conditions and productive of a control signal to pump drive system <b>105</b>, a coolant loop <b>115</b>, such as a radiator and engine block with cooling channels (not specifically shown but known in the art), responsive to an output torque or speed from pump drive system <b>105</b>, an engine auxiliary drive shaft <b>120</b> for providing an input torque to pump drive system <b>105</b>, and a power source <b>125</b> for providing electrical power to control system <b>110</b>. Auxiliary drive shaft <b>120</b> is arranged in operable communication with the vehicle engine by any means suitable for providing an input torque to pump drive system <b>105</b> for the purposes disclosed herein.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In an embodiment, the control system <b>110</b> includes a set of sensors <b>130</b> disposed to receive signals representative of various operating conditions of the vehicle, a controller <b>135</b> in signal communication with the sensors <b>130</b>, and an electronic amplifier <b>140</b> in signal communication with the controller <b>135</b> and productive of a control signal <b>145</b> directed to the pump drive system <b>105</b>. The electronic amplifier may be of a Pulse Width Modulating (PWM) type, or a linear type, and are known in the art. Communication between sensors <b>130</b>, controller <b>135</b>, and electronic amplifier <b>140</b>, may be by a communication bus or a CAN (controller area network) communication link (represented generally by the arrowhead lines in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> between the respective devices). In an embodiment, the set of sensors <b>130</b> may include one or more of the following, in any combination: a temperature sensor productive of a signal representative of the temperature of the engine, an engine revolutions-per-minute (rpm) sensor, a vehicle throttle angle sensor, a vehicle MAP (manifold absolute pressure) sensor, an engine coolant system temperature sensor, an engine cylinder head temperature sensor, a vehicle speed sensor, a vehicle acceleration sensor, a vehicle acceleration pedal position sensor, a vehicle brake pedal position sensor, a coolant pump speed sensor, a coolant pump fluid pressure sensor, and a coolant pump fluid flow sensor. While a defined set of sensors have been herein described, it will be appreciated that the scope of the invention is not so limited, and that other sensors or switches may also be employed, such as an ambient temperature sensor, a heater control switch, or an air conditioner control switch, for example. In an embodiment, the controller <b>135</b> includes a processing circuit <b>150</b> and a storage medium <b>155</b>, readable by the processing circuit <b>150</b>, storing instructions for execution by the processing circuit <b>150</b> for receiving a signal from the set of sensors <b>130</b>, and for providing a signal to the electronic amplifier <b>140</b> for providing the control signal <b>145</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In an embodiment, the pump drive system <b>105</b> includes a MRF clutch <b>160</b> in operable communication with a coolant pump <b>165</b>, which may be integrally arranged with the MRF clutch <b>160</b> as will be described in more detail below.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, an exemplary embodiment of pump drive system <b>105</b> is depicted in cross-section view having MRF clutch <b>160</b> coupled to coolant pump <b>165</b>, which may be of a type known in the art, in a hub arrangement between the coolant pump <b>165</b> and the auxiliary drive shaft <b>120</b>. A pulley wheel arrangement will be discussed below with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In an embodiment, and with reference still to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the MRF clutch <b>160</b> includes a torque input section <b>170</b> coupled to a torque output section <b>175</b> via a MRF <b>180</b>, the torque input section <b>170</b> being configured to receive a torque input from the engine, such as via auxiliary drive shaft <b>120</b> for example. Torque input section <b>170</b> is disposed within a cavity <b>185</b> of a housing <b>190</b>, is generally circular in shape, is made of a ferrous material, and is fixed to the drive-shaft <b>120</b> by any suitable means. The torque output section <b>175</b> is also disposed within the cavity <b>185</b>, is also generally circular in shape, is made of ferrous material, and is fixed to an intermediate shaft <b>195</b> by any suitable means. The intermediate shaft <b>195</b> is operably connected to the coolant pump <b>165</b> by known means. MRF clutch <b>160</b> also includes an excitation coil <b>200</b> disposed within the cavity <b>185</b> and about the torque input section <b>170</b> and the torque output section <b>175</b>. The coil <b>200</b> is spaced a predetermined distance from the torque input section <b>170</b> and the torque output section <b>175</b>, and is connected by suitable means such as wires to the electronic amplifier <b>140</b>. Disposed within the cavity <b>185</b> is the MRF <b>180</b> between the torque input section <b>170</b> and the torque output section <b>175</b>. In an embodiment, MRF <b>180</b> contains magnetizable particles such as carbonyl iron spheroids of about one to fifty microns in diameter dispersed in a viscous fluid such as synthetic hydrocarbon oil that has a viscosity between about 10 and 10,000 cP (centi-Poise). However, it will be appreciated that MRF <b>180</b> may be of a type known in the art and may also contain surfactants, flow modifiers, lubricants, viscosity enhancers, and/or other additives.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In response to a signal from the set of sensors <b>130</b>, electronic amplifier <b>140</b> provides a control signal <b>145</b> to MRF clutch <b>160</b>, which energizes coil <b>200</b> in such a manner as to provide a magnetic field across torque input section <b>170</b>, MRF <b>180</b>, and torque output section <b>175</b>, thereby activating the MRF <b>180</b> to provide a torque transfer from the torque input section <b>170</b> to the torque output section <b>175</b>. In response to a continuously variable control signal <b>145</b>, a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section <b>170</b> to the torque output section <b>175</b> may be provided, thereby providing for variable coolant flow <b>205</b> directed to the engine block <b>210</b> via an impeller <b>215</b> in coolant pump <b>165</b>, which operates under a continuously variable speed.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, an exemplary embodiment of MRF clutch <b>160</b> for use in pump drive system <b>105</b> is depicted in cross-section view, where MRF clutch <b>160</b> is coupled to coolant pump <b>165</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, coolant pump <b>165</b> is not specifically illustrated, but may be of a type similar to that illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Here, the torque input section <b>170</b> includes a pulley wheel <b>220</b> having first <b>225</b> and second <b>230</b> portions with a space <b>235</b> therebetween. The first portion <b>225</b> is radially outboard of the second portion <b>230</b>. The first portion <b>225</b> is configured to receive a torque input from the engine, such as via a drive belt (not shown but known in the art) cooperating with a radial surface <b>240</b> of pulley wheel <b>220</b>. The first and second portions <b>225</b>, <b>230</b> are configured to rotate together about the same axis of rotation <b>245</b>. The torque output section <b>175</b> includes a rotor <b>250</b> attached to a shaft <b>255</b>. The rotor <b>250</b> is disposed within the space <b>235</b> between the first <b>225</b> and second <b>230</b> portions of the pulley wheel <b>220</b> so as to form an annulus <b>260</b> between the rotor <b>250</b> and the first and second portions <b>225</b>, <b>230</b>. The annulus <b>260</b> is sized to contain a MRF (not specifically illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, but similar to the MRF <b>180</b> discussed previously with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). The shaft <b>255</b> is configured for operable communication with the coolant pump <b>165</b> by any suitable means, such as a keyed axle arrangement for example. The rotor <b>250</b> and shaft <b>255</b> are configured to rotate together about axis <b>245</b>. The torque input and torque output sections <b>170</b>, <b>175</b> cooperate with each other via bearings <b>265</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">MRF clutch <b>160</b> also includes a magnetic field generator <b>270</b>, having coil <b>200</b> and a stator <b>275</b>, disposed radially inboard of the second portion <b>230</b> of the pulley wheel <b>220</b>. Similar to the previous discussion relating to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, in response to a signal from the set of sensors <b>130</b> and a control signal <b>145</b> from electronic amplifier <b>140</b>, the coil <b>200</b> of magnetic field generator <b>270</b> is capable of generating a variable strength magnetic field that is in field communication with the stator <b>275</b>, the first portion <b>225</b>, the second portion <b>230</b>, the rotor <b>250</b>, and the MRF <b>180</b> in annulus <b>260</b>, thereby providing for a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section <b>170</b> to the torque output section <b>175</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In general, the set of sensors <b>130</b> are configured to provide a variable signal representative of a variable temperature of the engine, and the MRF clutch <b>160</b> is responsive to a non-zero variable control signal <b>145</b> arising from at least one of the set of sensors <b>130</b>, thereby providing continuously variable speed control to the coolant pump <b>165</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In an embodiment, stator <b>275</b>, first portion <b>225</b>, second portion <b>230</b>, and rotor <b>250</b>, are constructed using magnetic and non-magnetic materials that serve to direct the magnetic field created by coil <b>200</b> in such a manner as to efficiently excite MRF <b>180</b> in annulus <b>260</b>, thereby resulting in efficient torque transfer to coolant pump <b>165</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">During cold engine operation, such as at start up or where the ambient temperature is extremely low, an embodiment of the invention may generate only a small control signal <b>145</b> to coil <b>200</b>, thereby resulting in low torque transfer from torque input section <b>170</b> to torque output section <b>175</b>, and a slow operational speed of pump <b>165</b>, thereby allowing the engine to get up to temperature quickly. During warm engine operation, such as when the engine is at a desired operating temperature, an embodiment of the invention may generate a large control signal <b>145</b> to coil <b>200</b>, thereby resulting in high torque transfer from torque input section <b>170</b> to torque output section <b>175</b>, and a fast operational speed of pump <b>165</b>, thereby allowing the high coolant flow through a radiator to maintain the desired engine operating temperature. During periods of high vehicle speed, such as on a highway for example, where increased air flow across the vehicle radiator would typically provide for a greater heat transfer of engine heat to ambient, an embodiment of the invention may generate only a moderate control signal <b>145</b> to coil <b>200</b>, thereby resulting in moderate torque transfer from torque input section <b>170</b> to torque output section <b>175</b>, and a moderate operational speed of pump <b>165</b>, thereby allowing for both effective and efficient cooling of the engine. As can be seen, strategically placed sensors <b>130</b> that sense a variety of vehicle operating characteristics, in combination with an appropriate algorithm in controller <b>135</b>, may be employed to generate a variety of characteristics for control signal <b>145</b>, depending on the cooling needs of a particular engine.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">While certain combinations of sensors <b>130</b> have been described herein, it will be appreciated that these certain combinations are for illustration purposes only and that any combination of any of sensors <b>130</b> may be employed in accordance with an embodiment of the invention. Any and all such combinations are contemplated herein and are considered within the scope of the invention disclosed.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">An embodiment of the invention may be embodied in the form of computer-implemented processes and apparatuses for practicing those processes. The present invention may also be embodied in the form of a computer program product having computer program code containing instructions embodied in tangible media, such as floppy diskettes, CD-ROMs, hard drives, USB (universal serial bus) drives, random access memory (RAM), read only memory (ROM), erasable programmable read only memory (EPROM), or any other computer readable storage medium, wherein, when the computer program code is loaded into and executed by a computer, the computer becomes an apparatus for practicing the invention. The present invention may also be embodied in the form of computer program code, for example, whether stored in a storage medium, loaded into and/or executed by a computer, or transmitted over some transmission medium, such as over electrical wiring or cabling, through fiber optics, or via electromagnetic radiation, wherein when the computer program code is loaded into and executed by a computer, the computer becomes an apparatus for practicing the invention. When implemented on a general-purpose microprocessor, the computer program code segments configure the microprocessor to create specific logic circuits. A technical effect of the executable instructions is to variably control the speed of an engine coolant pump.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">As disclosed, some embodiments of the invention may include some of the following advantages: improved fuel economy due to elimination of losses due to double energy conversion present in an electrically driven pump; less packaging issues with the MRF clutch integrated into the engine coolant pump pulley; reduced cost due to a simple low current controller replacing a costly high-current power electronics of an electric drive system; variable coolant flow by controlling the pump speed allowing faster engine warm-up and potentially reduced emissions; reduced mass due to elimination of electric motor and high-current power electronics of an electric drive system; and, improved reliability due to reduced number of components.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">While the invention has been described with reference to exemplary embodiments, it will be understood by those skilled in the art that various changes may be made and equivalents may be substituted for elements thereof without departing from the scope of the invention. In addition, many modifications may be made to adapt a particular situation or material to the teachings of the invention without departing from the essential scope thereof. Therefore, it is intended that the invention not be limited to the particular embodiment disclosed as the best or only mode contemplated for carrying out this invention, but that the invention will include all embodiments falling within the scope of the appended claims. Also, in the drawings and the description, there have been disclosed exemplary embodiments of the invention and, although specific terms may have been employed, they are unless otherwise stated used in a generic and descriptive sense only and not for purposes of limitation, the scope of the invention therefore not being so limited. Moreover, the use of the terms first, second, etc. do not denote any order or importance, but rather the terms first, second, etc. are used to distinguish one element from another. Furthermore, the use of the terms a, an, etc. do not denote a limitation of quantity, but rather denote the presence of at least one of the referenced item.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An engine coolant pump drive system for a vehicle having an engine, an engine coolant system, and at least one sensor for sensing at least one operational condition of the vehicle, the pump drive system comprising:
<claim-text>a magnetorheological fluid (MRF) clutch comprising a torque input section coupled to a torque output section via a MRF, the torque input section configured to receive a torque input from the engine; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coolant pump configured for operable communication with the torque output section of the MRF clutch;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the torque input section comprises first and second portions with a space therebetween, the first portion being radially outboard of the second portion, the first portion configured to receive a torque input from the engine, the first and second portions configured to rotate together about the same axis of rotation;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the torque output section comprises a rotor attached to a shaft, the rotor disposed within the space between the first and second portions so as to form an annulus between the rotor and the first and second portions, the annulus containing a MRF, the shaft configured for operable communication with the coolant pump; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein in response to a signal from the at least one sensor, the MRF clutch is configured to provide a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section, thereby providing for variable coolant flow in the engine coolant system via the coolant pump capable of a continuously variable speed.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the torque input section comprises a pulley wheel comprising first and second portions with a space therebetween, the first portion being radially outboard of the second portion, the first portion configured to receive a torque input from the engine, the first and second portions configured to rotate together about the same axis of rotation; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the torque output section comprises a rotor attached to a shaft, the rotor disposed within the space between the first and second portions of the pulley wheel so as to form an annulus between the rotor and the first and second portions, the annulus containing a MRF, the shaft configured for operable communication with the coolant pump.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a magnetic field generator disposed radially inboard of the second portion of the pulley wheel;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein in response to a signal from the at least one sensor, the magnetic field generator is capable of generating a variable strength magnetic field that is in field communication with the first portion, the second portion, the rotor, and the MRF, thereby providing for a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the pulley wheel is configured to be driven by a belt in operable communication with the engine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a magnetic field generator disposed radially inboard of the second portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein in response to a signal from the at least one sensor, the magnetic field generator is capable of generating a variable strength magnetic field that is in field communication with the first portion, the second portion, the rotor, and the MRF, thereby providing for a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the magnetic field generator comprises a stator and a coil, the coil configured to be responsive to a control signal arising from the at least one sensor, and to be productive of the variable strength magnetic field, which is in field communication with the stator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the control system comprises:
<claim-text>the at least one sensor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller in signal communication with the at least one sensor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electronic amplifier in signal communication with the controller, the electronic amplifier configured to provide the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the controller comprises:
<claim-text>a processing circuit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a storage medium, readable by the processing circuit, storing instructions for execution by the processing circuit for:</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving a signal from the at least one sensor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>providing a signal to the electronic amplifier for providing the control signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one sensor comprises:
<claim-text>a temperature sensor productive of a signal representative of the temperature of the engine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one sensor comprises:
<claim-text>an engine revolutions-per-minute sensor, a vehicle throttle angle sensor, a vehicle manifold absolute pressure (MAP) sensor, an engine coolant system temperature sensor, an engine cylinder head temperature sensor, a vehicle speed sensor, a vehicle acceleration sensor, a vehicle acceleration pedal position sensor, a vehicle brake pedal position sensor, a coolant pump speed sensor, a coolant pump fluid pressure sensor, a coolant pump fluid flow sensor, or any combination comprising at least one of the foregoing sensors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the at least one sensor is configured to provide a variable signal representative of a variable temperature of the engine; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the MRF clutch is responsive to a non-zero variable control signal from the control system thereby providing continuously variable speed control to the coolant pump.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a control system responsive to the at least one operational condition of the vehicle, and productive of a control signal to the MRF clutch for providing the continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The pump drive system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a control system responsive to a signal from the at least one sensor, and productive of at least a first control signal, a second control signal, and a third control signal, to the MRF clutch, the first control signal being productive of a first level of torque transfer across the MRF clutch, the second control signal being productive of a second level of torque transfer across the MRF clutch greater than the first level of torque transfer, and the third control signal being productive of a third level of torque transfer across the MRF clutch greater than the second level of torque transfer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A magnetorheological fluid (MRF) clutch for coupling an engine coolant pump with an engine of a vehicle having at least one sensor productive of a signal representative of a temperature of the engine, the MRF clutch comprising:
<claim-text>a torque input section coupled to a torque output section via a MRF, the torque input section configured to receive a torque input from the engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the torque input section comprising first and second portions with a space therebetween, the first portion being radially outboard of the second portion, the first portion configured to receive a torque input from the engine, the first and second portions configured to rotate together about the same axis of rotation;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the torque output section comprising a rotor attached to a shaft, the rotor disposed within the space between the first and second portions so as to form an annulus between the rotor and the first and second portions, the annulus containing a MRF, the shaft configured for operable communication with the coolant pump; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a stationary magnetic field generator disposed radially inboard of the second portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein in response to a signal from the at least one sensor, the magnetic field generator is capable of generating a variable strength magnetic field that is in field communication with the first portion, the second portion, the rotor, and the MRF, thereby providing for a continuously variable torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The MRF clutch of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the torque input section comprises a pulley wheel comprising the first and second portions, the pulley wheel being configured to be driven by a belt in operable communication with the engine.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The MRF clutch of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the vehicle further comprises a control system responsive to a signal from the at least one sensor, and productive of at least a first control signal, a second control signal, and a third control signal, to the MRF clutch, wherein:
<claim-text>in response to the first control signal, a first level of torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section results;</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to the second control signal, a second level of torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section results;</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to the third control signal, a third level of torque transfer from the torque input section to the torque output section results; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the second level of torque transfer is greater than the first level of torque transfer, and the third lever of torque transfer is greater than the second level of torque transfer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
