<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297067-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297067</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11007607</doc-number>
<date>20041208</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>238</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>027</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464182</main-classification>
<further-classification>464906</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Plug and method of retaining the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4008582</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Welschof</name>
<date>19770200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>464146</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4150553</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Aucktor</name>
<date>19790400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>464906</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4242888</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Komeiji et al.</name>
<date>19810100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>464111</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4507100</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dore et al.</name>
<date>19850300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>464111</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7097563</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Benson et al.</name>
<date>20060800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>464 17</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0127908</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lyon et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0235606</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Brossard</name>
<date>20041100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>GB</country>
<doc-number>2 086 534</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19820500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464 15</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464111</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464144</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464146</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464170</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464182</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464906</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>464 17</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>403 10</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>403 42</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2281121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2281145</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>138 89</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>285901</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Meyer</last-name>
<first-name>Erik Harry</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chesterfield Township</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Brumbaugh</last-name>
<first-name>Jennifer M</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nylander</last-name>
<first-name>Mick A.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>GKN Driveline North America, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Auburn Hills</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Binda</last-name>
<first-name>Greg</first-name>
<department>3679</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A shaft system for use in a vehicle is disclosed. The shaft system includes a tube. A constant velocity joint is secured to the tube. The shaft system also includes a plug arranged within the constant velocity joint wherein the plug is secured within the joint by a weld curl that is also used to secure the constant velocity joint to the tube.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="124.21mm" wi="155.96mm" file="US07297067-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="255.27mm" wi="172.30mm" file="US07297067-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention generally relates to constant velocity joints and propeller shafts and more particularly to a method and apparatus for attaching a plug to a constant velocity joint to create a seal that is positively retained in the joint.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Constant velocity joints (CV joints) are common components in automotive vehicles. Typically constant velocity joints are used where transmission of rotating motion at a constant velocity is desired. The common types of constant velocity joints are a plunging tripod, a fixed tripod, a plunging ball joint and a fixed ball joint. These types of joints are currently used in front wheel drive vehicles, rear-wheel drive vehicles and on propeller shafts found in rear-wheel drive, all-wheel drive and four-wheel drive vehicles. The constant velocity joints are generally lubricated and sealed by a sealing boot. The constant velocity joints are sealed in order to retain grease inside the joint and keep contaminates, such as dirt and water, out of the joint. To achieve this protection a constant velocity joint is usually enclosed at the open end of the outer race by a sealing boot made of a rubber, thermoplastic or silicone type material. The opposite end of the outer race generally is enclosed by a dome or cap, commonly known as a grease cap. A monoblock or integral stem and race design style joint is sealed by the internal geometry of the outer race. This sealing and protection of the constant velocity joint prevents contamination of the inner chamber of the constant velocity joint that may cause internal damage to the joint.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A main function of a constant velocity joint is the transmission of rotational torque at a constant velocity. Traditional constant velocity joint assemblies include a variety of bolted joint designs to assemble the joint to a propeller shaft or half shaft within an automotive vehicle. Other assemblies are welded or use other chemical or mechanical bonding methods to secure a constant velocity joint to a tube or other propeller shaft component.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Many of these traditional constant velocity joints use a plug that is pressed into place within the constant velocity joint outer race or tube. These traditional plugs are capable of being dislodged allowing disassembly and loss of sealing function of the constant velocity joint under certain pre-defined parameters. Furthermore, the integrity of sealing components and retaining rings used to create positive stops for varying types of CV joints, including fixed joints, plunging joints, or crashworthy joints, and to seal contaminates from entering the internal chamber of a constant velocity joint may decay with time and the harsh environments found in constant velocity joints. Therefore, costly repairs may be necessary to replace seals and/or to repair seals in the constant velocity joint environment. Furthermore, many of the plunging constant velocity joints typically have a monoblock design, which requires a heavier constant velocity joint thus increasing weight for the automotive manufacturing and requisite gas mileage for the vehicles.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Therefore, there is a need in the art for a constant velocity joint that has a plug installed into an outer race, tube or other component that will be used as a seal and as a positive stop for any known type of constant velocity joint. There also is a need in the art for a lighter weight constant velocity joint that is easier to manufacture and more cost effective than traditional constant velocity joints.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A shaft system for use in a vehicle wherein the system includes a tube and a constant velocity joint secured to the tube. The system also includes a plug arranged within the constant velocity joint. The plug is secured within the constant velocity joint by a weld curl that is also used to secure the constant velocity joint to the tube.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Many features of the present invention will become apparent from the subsequent description and appended claims, taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a cross-sectional view of a constant velocity joint having a welded plug according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a partial cross-sectional view of a portion of a constant velocity joint prior to the welding operation.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a cross-sectional view of the weld area of the present invention of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Referring to the drawings, a constant velocity joint <b>10</b> according to the present invention is shown. As illustrated, the constant velocity joint <b>10</b> is shown as a plunging ball joint, however, it should be noted that all types of joints such as, but not limited to, plunging tripods, fixed tripods, plunging ball joints, fixed ball joints, and the like, may be used with the present invention. Furthermore, any type of tube or other component to be sealed may also be used with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows an embodiment of the current invention. The constant velocity joint <b>10</b> is a plunging constant velocity ball joint that is generally used in a propeller shaft or half shaft of an all-wheel drive or four-wheel drive vehicle. The constant velocity joint <b>10</b> includes an outer race <b>14</b>. The outer race <b>14</b> has a lip <b>16</b> extending from one end thereof. Secured to the outer race <b>14</b> and/or lip <b>16</b> is a tube <b>18</b> or other component of a propeller shaft, half shaft or driveshaft of an automotive driveline system. An inner wall <b>19</b> of the outer race <b>14</b> generally defines a constant velocity joint chamber <b>20</b>. An inner race <b>22</b> is located and arranged within the outer race <b>14</b>. The inner race <b>22</b> is connected to a shaft <b>24</b>, of the driveline system. A plurality of rolling elements or balls <b>26</b> are located between an outer surface <b>23</b> of the inner race <b>22</b> and the inner surface <b>19</b> of the outer race <b>14</b>. The balls or rolling elements <b>26</b> are held in position between the outer race <b>14</b> and the inner race <b>22</b> by a cage <b>28</b>. The rotation of the outer race <b>14</b> rotates the inner race <b>22</b> at the same or constant speed thus allowing for rotational motion or torque to be transmitted at a constant velocity through the joint <b>10</b> between the tube <b>18</b> and the shaft <b>24</b>. The tube <b>18</b> and shaft <b>24</b> are positioned relative to each other at an angle up to a predetermined maximum angle. The constant velocity joint <b>10</b> allows the angle to change because the balls <b>26</b> rotate and compensate for any differences in the angle between the shaft <b>24</b> and the tube <b>18</b> by moving within tracks of the outer race <b>14</b> and inner race <b>22</b>. A ring retainer <b>30</b> or any other known fastener is arranged between the shaft <b>24</b> and the inner race <b>22</b> to connect the shaft <b>24</b> to the inner race <b>22</b>. The present invention also contemplates other types of connections between the shaft <b>24</b> and the inner race <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">A boot cover <b>32</b> is connected to an end of the outer race <b>14</b>. One end of the boot cover <b>32</b> has a boot member <b>34</b> engaged with it, which in an embodiment is made of a urethane. However, it should be noted that any other type of hard or soft plastic, rubber, composite, fabric and like material might also be used for the boot member <b>34</b>. The boot member <b>34</b> is secured to the boot cover <b>32</b> by any known fastener <b>36</b> using any type or known fastening technique. The opposite end of the boot member <b>34</b> engages the shaft <b>24</b> to create a seal on one end of the constant velocity joint <b>10</b> for the joint chamber <b>20</b>. The boot member <b>34</b> seals the one end of the constant velocity joint <b>10</b> from any outside contaminants, such as water, dirt, and road grime. The suppleness of the boot member <b>34</b> allows for the seal to be maintained at any angle of inclination and also for any axial plunge of the shaft <b>24</b> that may occur during normal roadway and off-road driving operations.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The constant velocity joint <b>10</b> includes a plug <b>12</b> that is arranged within a circumferential shoulder portion <b>15</b> of the outer race <b>14</b>. The shoulder portion <b>15</b> is defined by the intersection of the outer race <b>14</b> and the lip <b>16</b> of the outer race <b>14</b>. The plug <b>12</b> is in contact with the lip <b>16</b> of the outer race <b>14</b> and the shoulder portion <b>15</b> of the outer race <b>14</b>. Plug <b>12</b> may be made of a metal material. Any known shape for the plug <b>12</b> may be used. In the embodiment shown, the plug <b>12</b> generally has a disc-like shape with a circumferential flange <b>38</b> extending from an end thereof. The plug <b>12</b> generally has a U-shaped cross-section, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. It should be noted that any other shape of plug <b>12</b> might also be used for the present invention, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Further, as illustrated, the material thickness of the plug <b>12</b> is generally uniform. However, the material thickness may be varied in order to control the resulting performance of the plug <b>12</b> during a crash. The plug <b>12</b> is arranged within the outer race <b>14</b> such that the plug <b>12</b> engages the shoulder portion <b>15</b> of the outer race <b>14</b>. The plug <b>12</b> extends along the lip <b>16</b> of the outer race <b>14</b>. The plug <b>12</b> may be the same length as the outer race lip <b>16</b>, shorter than the outer race lip <b>16</b> or extend beyond the outer race lip <b>16</b> depending on the design requirements for the connecting methodology to be used.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Tube <b>18</b> is aligned with and connected to the outer race <b>14</b> via any known mechanical or chemical bonding technique. In one embodiment, welding is used to secure the tube <b>18</b> to the outer race <b>14</b>. Specifically, a typical friction weld operation is performed to secure the tube <b>18</b> to the outer race <b>14</b>. The friction weld operation creates a weld curl <b>40</b> to secure both the tube <b>18</b> and plug <b>12</b> to the outer race <b>14</b>. The weld curl <b>40</b> allows the plug <b>12</b> to be retained within the outer race <b>14</b> and to create a seal for the constant velocity joint <b>10</b> on one end. During the welding operation, in the present example, a friction welding operation, the outer race lip <b>16</b>, an end of tube <b>18</b>, and the plug <b>12</b> interact and fuse with each other from the heat of the friction welding operation to create a secure connection between the tube <b>18</b> and the outer race <b>14</b> and also between the outer race <b>14</b> and the plug <b>12</b>. The present invention creates a positive mechanical stop for the plug <b>12</b> by securing the plug <b>12</b> to the outer race <b>14</b> at a predetermined position with a predetermined force. The plug <b>12</b> acts as a mechanical stop for the plunging joint up to a predetermined axial force.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The welding operation, in the form of a weld curl <b>40</b>, also creates a positive seal without the use of additional gaskets, O rings, or sealants at one end of the constant velocity joint <b>10</b>. The present invention provides a positive seal that confines lubricant, specifically a grease or the like, within the constant velocity joint chamber <b>20</b> without any leakage to the outer environment. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> the weld curl <b>40</b> curls the outer race lip <b>16</b> around an end of the plug <b>12</b> thus creating a permanent and positive seal and permanent and positive mechanical stop for the constant velocity joint <b>10</b>. The use of the weld curl <b>40</b> allows for increased loads on the plug <b>12</b> before the plug <b>12</b> becomes dislodged from its position. Thus, plug retention is greater and the sealing effect of the constant velocity joint <b>10</b> is increased thus increasing overall durability of the constant velocity joint <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">It should be noted that the present invention can be used for any cylindrical member or tube needed to be sealed or positively capped. In the present invention the seal is used on the open end of a plunging constant velocity joint <b>10</b>. Generally, plunging joints are of a monoblock design, which have a closed geometry on one end thereof. The open joint design as shown in the present invention reduces the weight of the constant velocity joint. Further, the open joint design allows for broaching of tracks, which allows for greater dimensional contact throughout the constant velocity joint. Accordingly, there is a reduction of NVH and balancing concerns for the constant velocity joint <b>10</b> of the present invention. The weld curl <b>40</b> of the present invention creates a positive mechanical stop to prevent disassembly of the joint. The plug <b>12</b> of the present invention needs greater forces than traditionally attached plugs to dislodge thus making disassembly and loss of sealing function less likely with the present invention as compared to plugs that are simply pressed into the outer race and not secured via any known positive bond. Furthermore, the weld curl <b>40</b> retained plug <b>12</b> of the present invention creates a sealing barrier to prevent egress of grease, air or other liquids or lubricants and the like from the joint chamber <b>20</b> of the constant velocity joint <b>10</b>. Furthermore, plug <b>12</b> provides a barrier for entry of contaminants into the joint chamber <b>20</b> of the constant velocity joint <b>10</b>. The present invention also reduces the number of parts necessary for a constant velocity joint <b>10</b> by removing the need for a separate retaining ring or other fastener to attach a traditional plug to the outer race <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">A method of assembling a constant velocity joint <b>10</b> according to the present invention may be used as follows or in any other acceptable manner. The constant velocity joint <b>10</b> is assembled according to any well-known assembly method that will install all necessary components of the constant velocity joint within one another. Also, a plug <b>12</b> of any known shape is aligned and inserted into one end of the outer race <b>14</b> such that the plug <b>12</b> is seated on a shoulder portion <b>15</b> or other known portion of the outer race <b>14</b>. The plug <b>12</b> has a circumferential flange <b>38</b> that aligns with the end of the outer race lip <b>16</b>, aligns shorter than the end of the outer race lip <b>16</b>, or extends beyond the outer race lip <b>16</b> depending on the design requirements of the constant velocity joint <b>10</b>. Next, a tube <b>18</b> or other component is aligned and centered with respect to the outer circumference of the outer race <b>14</b> and in particular the outer race lip <b>16</b>. Then the assembly has any known connecting technique performed between the outer race <b>14</b> and the tube <b>18</b>. In one embodiment, the connecting method is a friction welding operation that results in a friction weld curl <b>40</b> between the tube <b>18</b>, the outer race lip <b>16</b>, and the end of the plug <b>12</b>. This welding operation creates a weld curl <b>40</b> that secures the tube <b>18</b> to the outer race <b>14</b> for transfer of rotational motion at a constant velocity through the constant velocity joint <b>10</b> and the shaft <b>24</b>. Further, the welding operation also creates a secure connection between the outer race <b>14</b> and the plug <b>12</b> thus creating a positive mechanical stop and a positive seal for the constant velocity joint <b>10</b> and the constant velocity joint chamber <b>20</b> on one end thereof. The weld <b>40</b> creates an interaction and fusion between the materials of the plug <b>12</b> and outer race <b>14</b> and outer race <b>14</b> and tube <b>18</b>. For example, an end of plug <b>12</b> may curl after a welding operation, interacting and fusing with outer race <b>14</b>. It should be noted that the plug <b>12</b>, outer race <b>14</b>, and tube <b>18</b>, all have the necessary preparation of their respective surfaces prior to the welding operation in order to create a proper welding and connecting environment. Furthermore, a proper cool down methodology and post welding technique is also contemplated to create a weld that is strong and performs at the high speeds and high torques found in constant velocity joint environments. It should be noted that any other known connecting method other than friction welding might also be used to connect the tube <b>18</b> to the outer race <b>14</b> and the outer race <b>14</b> to the plug <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an embodiment of the present invention using an alternate plug <b>12</b>′. The alternate plug <b>12</b>′ has a generally W-shaped design, including circumferential flange <b>38</b>′, as compared to the U-shaped design of plug <b>12</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> also shows the invention prior to the performance of the connecting or welding operation.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The present invention has been described in an illustrative manner. It is to be understood that the terminology that has been used is intended to be in the nature of words of description rather than of limitation.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Many modifications and variations of the present invention are possible in light of the above teachings. Therefore, within the scope of the appended claims, the present invention may be practiced otherwise than as specifically described.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A shaft system for use in a vehicle, said system including:
<claim-text>a hollow tube;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a constant velocity joint secured to said tube; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plug arranged within said constant velocity joint, said plug secured within said constant velocity joint by a weld curl, said weld curl used to secure said constant velocity joint to said tube.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said weld curl is provided by a friction welding operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said constant velocity joint including:
<claim-text>an outer race;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inner race arranged within said outer race; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of rolling elements arranged between said outer race and said inner race.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein said outer race having a lip extending from one end, said outer race having a shoulder, said plug in contact with said lip and said shoulder.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein said plug in part defines said weld curl.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said plug forms a seal for said constant velocity joint.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein said seal is a permanent and positive seal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said plug is a positive mechanical stop which prevents disassembly of said constant velocity joint.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein an end of said plug curls after a welding operation and interacts and fuses with said outer race.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said plug is made of a metal material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said plug has a generally uniform material thickness.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
