<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298150-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298150</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11699594</doc-number>
<date>20070129</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2006-025987</doc-number>
<date>20060202</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324522</main-classification>
<further-classification>324763</further-classification>
<further-classification>324765</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Test apparatus and test method</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5128618</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Yamada et al.</name>
<date>19920700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324501</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5392293</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hsue</name>
<date>19950200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324765</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324522</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324763</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324765</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070194794</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070823</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Amanuma</last-name>
<first-name>Seiji</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Osha Liang LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Advantest Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Benson</last-name>
<first-name>Walter</first-name>
<department>2858</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>He</last-name>
<first-name>Amy</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Change in power supply voltage supplied to a device under test is controlled. There is provided a test apparatus for testing a device under test, the test apparatus including: a reference voltage supply section for supplying a reference voltage; a field effect transistor provided between a positive side terminal and a negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, so that a drain terminal and a source terminal of the field effect transistor are in parallel connection with the device under test; an inductance that is connected between the positive side terminal and the negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, the inductance being in serial connection with the device under test between a positive-side power supply terminal and a negative-side power supply terminal of the device under test, and being in serial connection with the field effect transistor between the drain terminal and the source terminal of the field effect transistor; a control section for controlling a gate voltage of the field effect transistor, thereby changing a power supply voltage to be supplied to the device under test; and a judgment section for judging quality of the device under test, based on characteristic of the device under test in accordance with change in the power supply voltage.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="120.40mm" wi="197.27mm" file="US07298150-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="201.85mm" wi="127.00mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298150-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="102.02mm" wi="101.94mm" file="US07298150-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="153.25mm" wi="159.51mm" file="US07298150-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="174.84mm" wi="113.11mm" file="US07298150-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="197.95mm" wi="132.67mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298150-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application claims priority from a Japanese Patent Application No. 2006-025987 filed on Feb. 2, 2006, the contents of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Technical Field</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a test apparatus and a test method. In particular, the present invention relates to a test apparatus and a test method for testing characteristic of a device under test by changing a power supply voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Semiconductor devices having high withstand voltage (hereinafter high withstand voltage semiconductor devices) are known to be used for controlling motors of electric cars and for controlling alternate current fan motors, for example. In such a high withstand voltage semiconductor device, PN conjunction is separated by means of an insulating film of SiO<sub>2 </sub>for example, and so it is possible to incorporate circuits operating under low voltages and circuits operating under high voltages onto one chip.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Since insulating portions of high withstand voltage semiconductor devices contain capacitance, a defect may possibly occur attributable to a size of the gradient of the rising of a power supply voltage for example. In view of this, chances are that a defect may be detected when the gradient of the rising of the power supply voltage is larger than a predetermined value, while a defect may not be detected when the gradient is the predetermined value or smaller. Accordingly, a test apparatus is desired which is able to detect a defect attributable to a size of a gradient of the rising of a power supply voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">However, when testing a high withstand voltage semiconductor device, it is hard for a test apparatus to control the gradient of the rising of a power supply voltage to be supplied because the power supply voltage to be supplied is high.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In view of this, an advantage of the present invention is to provide a test apparatus and a test method that are able to solve the foregoing problems. This advantage is achieved by combinations of features described in the independent claims. The dependent claims define further advantageous and exemplary combinations of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">So as to solve the foregoing problems, according to the first aspect of the present invention, there is provided a test apparatus for testing a device under test, the test apparatus including: a reference voltage supply section for supplying a reference voltage; a field effect transistor provided between a positive side terminal and a negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, so that a drain terminal and a source terminal of the field effect transistor are in parallel connection with the device under test; an inductance that is connected between the positive side terminal and the negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, the inductance being in serial connection with the device under test between a positive-side power supply terminal and a negative-side power supply terminal of the device under test, and being in serial connection with the field effect transistor between the drain terminal and the source terminal of the field effect transistor; a control section for controlling a gate voltage of the field effect transistor, thereby changing a power supply voltage to be supplied to the device under test; and a judgment section for judging quality of the device under test, based on characteristic of the device under test in accordance with change in the power supply voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The judgment section may judge the quality of the device under test, based on a power supply current value consumed by the device under test when the power supply voltage is changed. The control section may decrease the gate voltage, thereby increasing the power supply voltage with a gradient designated in advance.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The control section conducts a first test in which the power supply voltage is raised from a first power supply voltage to a second power supply voltage while keeping the first reference voltage supplied from the reference voltage supply section, and on condition that no defect for the device under test is found in the first test, the control section conducts a second test in which the power supply voltage is raised from a voltage value substantially the same as a voltage value of the first power supply voltage to a third power supply voltage that is higher than the second power supply voltage, while keeping the second reference voltage supplied from the reference voltage supply section, the second reference voltage being higher than the first reference voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to the second aspect of the present invention, there is provided a test method for testing a device under test by means of a test apparatus, the test apparatus including: a reference voltage supply section for supplying a reference voltage; a field effect transistor provided between a positive side terminal and a negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, so that a drain terminal and a source terminal of the field effect transistor are in parallel connection with the device under test; and an inductance that is connected between the positive side terminal and the negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, the inductance being in serial connection with the device under test between a positive-side power supply terminal and a negative-side power supply terminal of the device under test, and being in serial connection with the field effect transistor between the drain terminal and the source terminal of the field effect transistor, the test method including: a control step for controlling a gate voltage of the field effect transistor, thereby changing a power supply voltage to be supplied to the device under test; and a judgment step for judging quality of the device under test, based on characteristic of the device under test in accordance with change in the power supply voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The summary of the invention does not necessarily describe all necessary features of the present invention. The present invention may also be a sub-combination of the features described above.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagram showing a test apparatus <b>10</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention, together with a device under test <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a relation between voltage and current of a field effect transistor <b>24</b>, a voltage generating section <b>26</b>, and an inductance <b>28</b>, which are included in the test apparatus <b>10</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> shows one example of a waveform of a gate voltage supplied to the field effect transistor <b>24</b>, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> shows one example of a waveform of a power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>in case where the voltage of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is supplied to the field effect transistor <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows one example of a test procedure performed by the test apparatus <b>10</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a diagram showing one example of a hardware configuration of a computer <b>1900</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF EXEMPLARY EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">As follows, the present invention is described based on some embodiments that do not intend to limit the scope of the present invention. All of the features and combinations thereof disclosed in the following are not necessarily essential to means provided by the aspects of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a test apparatus <b>10</b> according to the present embodiment, together with a device under test (hereinafter referred to as “DUT <b>100</b>”). The DUT <b>100</b> may include a low voltage side logic circuit <b>110</b> and a high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>, for example. The low voltage side logic circuit <b>110</b> and the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b> are insulated from each other, and are operated with different potentials as references respectively. For example, when the low voltage side logic circuit <b>110</b> is operated with 0V as a reference, the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b> may be operated with from some ten volts to some kilovolts as a reference. It should be noted that the reference potential for the low voltage side logic circuit <b>110</b> here is relatively low compared to that for the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>, i.e. the low voltage side logic circuit <b>110</b> may be operated at a reference potential that is the same as for a circuit which the test apparatus <b>10</b> is equipped with.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In addition, different power supply voltages are supplied respectively to the low voltage side logic circuit <b>110</b> and the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>. For example, the low voltage side logic circuit <b>110</b> is provided with a power supply voltage of from some volts to some ten volts, with 0 volt as a reference. On the other hand, the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b> is for example provided with a power supply voltage of from some volts to some ten volts, with 1 kilovolt as a reference.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The test apparatus <b>10</b> tests the DUT <b>100</b>. More specifically, the test apparatus <b>10</b> tests quality of the DUT <b>100</b> by detecting characteristic (e.g. power supply current value of the DUT <b>100</b>) of the DUT when the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> is changed. The DUT <b>100</b> is equipped with a reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>, a field effect transistor <b>24</b>, a voltage generating section <b>26</b>, an inductance <b>28</b>, a control section <b>30</b>, a floating power supply section <b>32</b>, a consumption current detection section <b>34</b>, a test signal generating section <b>36</b>, a driving section <b>38</b>, a comparison section <b>40</b>, and a judgment section <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The reference voltage supply section <b>22</b> supplies a reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>to the DUT <b>100</b>. The reference voltage supply section <b>22</b> has a positive side terminal <b>61</b> and a negative side terminal <b>62</b>, and generates the reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>between the positive side terminal <b>61</b> and the negative side terminal <b>62</b>. The reference voltage supply section <b>22</b> supplies, between a positive-side power supply terminal and a negative-side power supply terminal of the DUT <b>100</b>, the reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>having been generated between the positive side terminal <b>61</b> and the negative side terminal <b>62</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">As an example, the positive side terminal <b>61</b> may be connected to the positive-side power supply terminal of the DUT <b>100</b>, via the inductance <b>28</b>, and the negative side terminal <b>62</b> may be directly connected to the negative-side power supply terminal of the DUT <b>100</b>. Furthermore, when the DUT <b>100</b> has the low voltage side logic circuit <b>110</b> and the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>, the positive side terminal <b>61</b> may be connected to the power supply terminal of the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>, which functions as the positive-side power supply terminal of the DUT <b>100</b>, and the negative side terminal <b>62</b> may be connected to a ground terminal of the DUT <b>100</b>, which functions as the negative-side power supply terminal of the DUT <b>100</b>, as an example. According to this, the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b> may be operated with, as a reference, a potential higher than the ground potential of the DUT <b>100</b> by an amount of the reference voltage V<sub>R</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The field effect transistor <b>24</b> is provided between the positive side terminal <b>61</b> and the negative side terminal <b>62</b> of the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>, so that a drain terminal and a source terminal of the field effect transistor <b>24</b> are in parallel connection with the DUT <b>100</b>. As an example, the drain terminal of the field effect transistor <b>24</b> may be connected to the positive side terminal <b>61</b> via the inductance <b>28</b>, and the source terminal may be directly connected to the negative side terminal <b>62</b>. In addition, the field effect transistor <b>24</b> may be a MOS (Metal Oxide Semiconductor) type field effect transistor, as an example. In addition, the test apparatus <b>10</b> may be equipped with a plurality of field effect transistors <b>24</b> which connect the source terminal and the drain terminal in cascade connection for the purpose of raising the voltage resistance, instead of being equipped with only one field effect transistor <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The voltage generating section <b>26</b> generates a control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>to be supplied between the gate terminal and the source terminal of the field effect transistor <b>24</b>. The inductance <b>28</b> is connected between the positive side terminal <b>61</b> and the negative side terminal <b>62</b> of the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>, the inductance <b>28</b> being in serial connection with the DUT <b>100</b> between the positive-side power supply terminal and the negative-side power supply terminal of the DUT <b>100</b>, and being in serial connection with the field effect transistor <b>24</b> between the drain terminal and the source terminal of the field effect transistor <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The control section <b>30</b> controls the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>generated by the voltage generating section <b>26</b>. The control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>is supplied as a gate voltage of the field effect transistor <b>24</b>. Consequently, by controlling the control voltage V<sub>1</sub>, the control section <b>30</b> is able to control switching of the field effect transistor <b>24</b>. Furthermore, because the source terminal and the drain terminal of the field effect transistor <b>24</b> are in parallel connection with the DUT <b>100</b> between the positive-side power supply terminal and the negative-side power supply terminal of the DUT <b>100</b>, the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> is changed by switching by the field effect transistor <b>24</b>. In this way, by controlling the voltage generating section <b>26</b> so as to control the gate voltage of the field effect transistor <b>24</b>, the control section <b>30</b> changes the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>to be supplied to the DUT <b>100</b>. Moreover, the control section <b>30</b> may control the reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>generated by the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>, in addition to the above.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The floating power supply section <b>32</b> generates a power supply voltage whose objective is to drive the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b> within the DUT <b>100</b>, with a potential of the positive side terminal <b>61</b> of the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b> as a reference. As one example, if the positive side terminal <b>61</b> of the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b> is brought to be connected to a sink side power supply terminal V<sub>s </sub>of the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>, the floating power supply section <b>32</b> generates a voltage (e.g. +15 volts or the like) whose reference is the sink side power supply terminal V<sub>s </sub>to be supplied to the source side power supply terminal V<sub>b </sub>of the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The consumption current detection section <b>34</b> detects a power supply current value consumed by the DUT <b>100</b>. The test signal generating section <b>36</b> outputs a test signal to be supplied to the DUT <b>100</b>. The driving section <b>38</b> supplies, to the DUT <b>100</b>, the test signal outputted from the test signal generating section <b>36</b>. As an example, when the test signal is to be supplied to the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>, the driving section <b>38</b> converts the test signal to a signal whose reference voltage corresponds to the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b> by insulating between the input and the output, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The comparison section <b>40</b> obtains an output signal that the DUT <b>100</b> outputs in accordance with the test signal, and compares the obtained output signal with an expected value. As an example, when the output signal is obtained from the high voltage side logic circuit <b>120</b>, the comparison section <b>40</b> converts the output signal into a signal whose reference voltage corresponds to the test apparatus <b>10</b> by insulating between the input and the output, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The judgment section <b>42</b> judges the quality of the DUT <b>100</b> based on a comparison result by the comparison section <b>40</b> or a consumption current value of the DUT <b>100</b> having been detected by the consumption current detection section <b>34</b>, and the like. More specifically, the judgment section <b>42</b> judges the quality of the DUT <b>100</b>, based on the characteristic of the DUT <b>100</b> in accordance with the change in the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>when the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> is changed. As one example, the judgment section <b>42</b> may judge the quality of the DTU <b>100</b>, based on the power supply current value consumed by the DUT <b>100</b> when the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>is changed.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows voltage and current of the field effect transistor <b>24</b>, the voltage generating section <b>26</b>, and the inductance <b>28</b>, which are included in the test apparatus <b>10</b> according to the present embodiment. It should be noted that <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows one example in which the negative side terminal <b>62</b> of the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b> and the negative-side power supply terminal of the DUT <b>100</b> are both connected to the ground potential (0 volt).</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> changes according to the switching state of the field effect transistor <b>24</b>. More specifically, when the field effect transistor <b>24</b> is brought OFF in the normal state, the resistance value of the inductance <b>28</b> becomes substantially 0, and so the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> becomes the reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>generated by the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>. On the contrary, when the field effect transistor <b>24</b> is brought ON in the normal state, the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> becomes the ground potential (0 volt).</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In addition, in the transition state in which the field effect transistor <b>24</b> changes from ON to OFF, or from OFF to ON, the inductance <b>28</b> generates an induction voltage. In such a case, if the voltage between terminals in the inductance <b>28</b> is represented as V<sub>L</sub>, the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> is represented as V<sub>R</sub>-V<sub>L</sub>. Accordingly, in the transition state in which the field effect transistor <b>24</b> changes from ON to OFF, or from OFF to ON, the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>changes in accordance with V<sub>L</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Here, suppose the inductance <b>28</b> is L, and the current that runs through the inductance <b>28</b> is i. In addition, suppose that the drain current of the field effect transistor <b>24</b> is i<sub>D</sub>, and the gate voltage of the field effect transistor <b>24</b> is V<sub>GS</sub>. In this case, the impedance for the power-supply input terminal of the DUT <b>100</b> is extremely high, and so the current i that runs through the inductance <b>28</b> and the drain current i<sub>D </sub>become substantially the same as each other, and so the following equation (1) holds true:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>i≈i<sub>D</sub>  (1)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In addition, the direct current voltage characteristic at the time of saturation of the MOS type field effect transistor is represented by the following equation (2).
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>i</i><sub>D</sub>=β×(<i>V</i><sub>GS</sub><i>−V</i><sub>t</sub>)<sup>2</sup>/2  (2)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">When the gate voltage V<sub>GS </sub>is sufficiently higher than the threshold voltage Vt of the MOS type field effect transistor, the equation (2) can be modified into the following equation (3) that indicates that the drain current i<sub>D </sub>is proportional to the gate voltage V<sub>GS </sub>squared.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>i<sub>D</sub>∝(V<sub>GS</sub>)<sup>2</sup>  (3)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Furthermore, since V<sub>GS</sub>=V<sub>1</sub>, the equation (3) can be modified into the following equation (3)′ that indicates that the drain current i<sub>D </sub>is proportional to the control voltage V<sub>i </sub>squared.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>i<sub>D</sub>∝(V<sub>1</sub>)<sup>2</sup>  (3)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">On the other hand, as far as the inductance <b>28</b> is concerned, the voltage V<sub>L </sub>is a value obtained by multiplying, by the inductance, a differential value of the running current i squared. Consequently, the following equation (4) holds true.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>V</i><sub>L</sub><i>=L</i>(<i>di</i><sup>2</sup><i>/dt</i>)  (4)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Based on the equation (1), the equation (3)′, and the equation (4), it becomes possible to derive the following equation (5) indicating that the voltage V<sub>L </sub>is a value obtained by multiplying, by the inductance, a differential value of the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>squared.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>V<sub>L</sub>∝L(dV<sub>1</sub><sup>2</sup>/dt)  (5)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Then by solving the differential equation of the equation (5), the following equation (6) can be derived.
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>V<sub>L</sub>∝LV<sub>1</sub>  (6)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The equation (6) means that when the inductance <b>28</b> has caused an induced electromotive force, the voltage between terminals V<sub>L </sub>in the inductance <b>28</b> is proportional to L and the control voltage V<sub>1</sub>. As a consequence, since the power supply voltage V<sub>A</sub>=V<sub>R</sub>−V<sub>L </sub>during the transition state in which the field effect transistor <b>24</b> changes from ON to OFF or from OFF to ON, the control section <b>30</b> is able to control the gradient of the change in the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>by means of the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>(i.e. gate voltage V<sub>GS </sub>of the field effect transistor <b>24</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> shows one example of a waveform of a gate voltage supplied to the field effect transistor <b>24</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> shows one example of a waveform of the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>in case where the voltage of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is supplied to the field effect transistor <b>24</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, when the field effect transistor <b>24</b> is changed from ON to OFF, the control section <b>30</b> decreases the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>with a predetermined gradient (ΔV<sub>1</sub>/Δt). In this case, the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>is proportional to the control voltage V<sub>1</sub>, and so the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>will increase with the gradient that is in accordance with the gradient of the control voltage V<sub>1</sub>, i.e. (ΔV<sub>A</sub>/Δt), as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. In addition, when the control section <b>30</b> changes the size of the gradient of the control voltage V<sub>1</sub>, the gradient of the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>changes accordingly.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Accordingly, in case of raising the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>to be supplied to the DUT <b>100</b>, from the first reference voltage (e.g. 0 volt) to the second reference voltage (e.g. V<sub>R</sub>) by changing the field effect transistor <b>24</b> from ON to OFF, the control section <b>30</b> is able to increase the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>with a gradient designated in advance, by gradually decreasing the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>thereby decreasing a gate voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In addition, in case of changing the field effect transistor <b>24</b> from OFF to ON as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, the control section <b>30</b> may increase the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>with a gradient designated in advance. In this case too, the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>is proportional to the control voltage V<sub>1</sub>, and so the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>decreases with a gradient that is in accordance with the gradient for the control voltage V<sub>1</sub>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>. In addition, when the control section <b>30</b> changes the size of the gradient for the control voltage V<sub>1</sub>, the gradient of the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>changes accordingly.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Accordingly, in case of lowering the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>to be supplied to the DUT <b>100</b>, from the second reference voltage (e.g. V<sub>R</sub>) to the first reference voltage (e.g. 0 volt) by changing the field effect transistor <b>24</b> from OFF to ON, the control section <b>30</b> is able to decrease the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>with a gradient designated in advance, by gradually increasing the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>thereby increasing the gate voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The test apparatus <b>10</b> controls the gradient for the change in the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>in the above way, thereby enabling the characteristic of the DUT <b>100</b> to be detected. Consequently, the test apparatus <b>10</b> becomes able to detect a defect attributable to a size of the gradient of the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>to be supplied to the DUT <b>100</b>, with high reproducibility. In addition, when changing the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>with a predetermined gradient (ΔV<sub>1</sub>/Δt), the test apparatus <b>10</b> may perform control by designating a peak value of the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>and a period between 0 and the peak value.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">For example, when the insulating section of the DUT <b>100</b> that corresponds to high voltage has a large capacity above a certain level, and when the gradient of the rising of the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>becomes a predetermined value or above, a large consumption current runs therethrough and so the DUT <b>100</b> is detected as a defect. The test apparatus <b>10</b> is able to set a gradient designated in advance as a gradient for the change in the power supply voltage V<sub>A</sub>, and so reproducibility for the defect detection is improved in case of detecting a defect attributable to the gradient of the power supply voltage V<sub>A</sub>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows one example of a test procedure performed by the test apparatus <b>10</b> according to the present embodiment. First, the control section <b>30</b> sets, as a first reference voltage, a reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>generated by the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b> (Step S<b>11</b>). Next, while keeping the first reference voltage supplied from the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>, the control section <b>30</b> gradually decreases the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>and conducts the first test in which the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>to be supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> is raised from the first power supply voltage to the second power supply voltage (Step S<b>12</b>). During the first test, the consumption current detection section <b>34</b> may detect a consumption current value of the DUT <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Next, during the first test, the judgment section <b>42</b> judges whether the DUT <b>100</b> is a non-defective item, based on the consumption current value detected by the consumption current detection section <b>34</b> for example (Step S<b>13</b>). When the DUT <b>100</b> is judged not to be a non-defective item, i.e. when a defect has been detected (Step S<b>13</b>: NG), the judgment section <b>42</b> ends the processing. When the DUT <b>100</b> is judged to be a non-defective item, i.e. when a defect has not been detected (Step S<b>13</b>: OK), the judgment section <b>42</b> proceeds to Step S<b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Next, on condition that the DUT <b>100</b> has not been detected as a defective item as a result of the first test, the control section <b>30</b> sets the reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>generated by the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>, to the second reference voltage that is higher than the first reference voltage (Step S<b>14</b>). Next, while keeping the second reference voltage supplied from the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>, the control section <b>30</b> gradually decreases the control voltage V<sub>1 </sub>and conducts the second test in which the power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>to be supplied to the DUT <b>100</b> is raised from the voltage value substantially the same as that of the first power supply voltage to the third power supply voltage that is higher than the second power supply voltage (Step S<b>15</b>). During the second test, the consumption current detection section <b>34</b> may detect a consumption current value of the DUT <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Next, during the second test, the judgment section <b>42</b> judges whether the DUT <b>100</b> is a non-defective item, based on the consumption current value detected by the consumption current detection section <b>34</b> for example (Step S<b>16</b>). When the DUT <b>100</b> is judged not to be a non-defective item (Step S<b>16</b>: NG), the judgment section <b>42</b> ends the processing. When the DUT <b>100</b> is judged to be a non-defective item (Step S<b>16</b>: OK), the judgment section <b>42</b> proceeds to a next different test, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">As described above, the test apparatus <b>10</b> first conducts a test while keeping a relatively low reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>supplied from the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>, and then conducts a second test while keeping a high reference voltage V<sub>R </sub>supplied from the reference voltage supply section <b>22</b>. Consequently, it becomes possible to exclude defective DUT <b>100</b> prior to application of a power supply voltage V<sub>A </sub>that is of a high voltage. Accordingly, it becomes possible to prevent application of large current and the like to defective DUT <b>100</b> due to application of high voltage thereto, thereby lessening the burden on the test apparatus <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a diagram showing one example of a hardware configuration of a computer <b>1900</b> according to the present embodiment. The computer <b>1900</b> according to the present embodiment is equipped with a CPU periphery that includes a CPU <b>2000</b>, a RAM <b>2020</b>, a graphics controller <b>2075</b>, and a display apparatus <b>2080</b> which are mutually connected by a host controller <b>2082</b>. The computer <b>1900</b> is also equipped with an input/output unit having a communication interface <b>2030</b>, a hard disk drive <b>2040</b>, and a CD-ROM drive <b>2060</b> which are connected to the host controller <b>2082</b> via an input/output controller <b>2084</b>, and a legacy input/output unit having a ROM <b>2010</b>, a flexible disk drive <b>2050</b>, and an input/output chip <b>2070</b> which are connected to the input/output controller <b>2084</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The host controller <b>2082</b> connects the RAM <b>2020</b> with the CPU <b>2000</b> and the graphics controller <b>2075</b> which access the RAM <b>2020</b> at a high transfer rate. The CPU <b>2000</b> operates according to programs stored in the ROM <b>2010</b> and the RAM <b>2020</b>, thereby controlling each unit. The graphics controller <b>2075</b> obtains image data generated by the CPU <b>2000</b> or the like on a frame buffer provided in the RAM <b>2020</b>, and causes the image data to be displayed on the display apparatus <b>2080</b>. Alternatively, the graphics controller <b>2075</b> may contain therein a frame buffer for storing image data generated by the CPU <b>2000</b> or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The input/output controller <b>2084</b> connects the host controller <b>2082</b> with the communication interface <b>2030</b>, the hard disk drive <b>2040</b>, and the CD-ROM drive <b>2060</b>, which are relatively high-speed input/output apparatuses. The communication interface <b>2030</b> communicates with other apparatuses via a network. The hard disk drive <b>2040</b> stores a program and data used by the CPU <b>2000</b> within the computer <b>1900</b>. The CD-ROM drive <b>2060</b> reads the program or the data from the CD-ROM <b>2095</b>, and provides the hard disk drive <b>2040</b> with the program or the data via the RAM <b>2020</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">The ROM <b>2010</b>, and the flexible disk drive <b>2050</b> and the input/output chip <b>2070</b> which are relatively low-speed input/output apparatuses are connected to the input/output controller <b>2084</b>. The ROM <b>2010</b> stores therein a boot program executed by the computer <b>1900</b> at the time of activation, a program depending on the hardware of the computer <b>1900</b>, or the like. The flexible disk drive <b>2050</b> reads the programs or data from a flexible disk <b>2090</b>, and provides the hard disk drive <b>2040</b> with the programs or data via the RAM <b>2020</b>. The input/output chip <b>2070</b> connects various input/output apparatuses via the flexible disk drive <b>2050</b>, and a parallel port, a serial port, a keyboard port, a mouse port, and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">A program to be provided for the hard disk drive <b>2040</b> via the RAM <b>2020</b> is provided by a user by being stored in such a recording medium as the flexible disk <b>2090</b>, the CD-ROM <b>2095</b>, and an IC card. The program is read from the recording medium, installed into the hard disk drive <b>2040</b> within the computer <b>1900</b> via the RAM <b>2020</b>, and executed in the CPU <b>2000</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">A program that is installed in the computer <b>1900</b> and causes the computer <b>1900</b> to function as a control apparatus of the test apparatus <b>10</b> has a control section module and a judgment section module. These program or modules act on the CPU <b>2000</b> and so on, to cause the computer <b>1900</b> to function as the control section <b>30</b> and the judgment section <b>42</b> respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The programs or modules described above may be stored in an external recording medium. The recording medium may be, besides the flexible disk <b>2090</b> and the CD-ROM <b>2095</b>, an optical recording medium such as a DVD and a CD, a magneto-optical recording medium such as an MO, a tape medium, a semiconductor memory such as an IC card. In addition, it is also possible to use, as the recording medium, a recording apparatus such as a hard disk or a RAM provided in a server system connected to a dedicated communication network or the Internet, for the purpose of providing a program to the computer <b>1900</b> via the network.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">In the above, the present invention has been described by way of an exemplary embodiment. However, it is needless to say that the technical scope of the present invention should not be limited by the above-described embodiment. It should be understood that those skilled in the art might make many changes and substitutions without departing from the spirit and the scope of the present invention. It is obvious from the appended claims that embodiments with such modifications also belong to the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">According to the present invention, it becomes possible to test a device under test, by controlling a change in power supply voltage to be supplied to the device under test.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A test apparatus for testing a device under test, the test apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a reference voltage supply section for supplying a reference voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a field effect transistor provided between a positive side terminal and a negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section so that a drain terminal and a source terminal of the field effect transistor are in parallel connection with the device under test;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inductance that is connected between the positive side terminal and the negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, the inductance being in serial connection with the device under test between a positive-side power supply terminal and a negative-side power supply terminal of the device under test, and being in serial connection with the field effect transistor between the drain terminal and the source terminal of the field effect transistor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control section for controlling a gate voltage of the field effect transistor, thereby changing a power supply voltage to be supplied to the device under test; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a judgment section for judging quality of the device under test, based on characteristic of the device under test in accordance with change in the power supply voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The test apparatus as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the judgment section judges the quality of the device under test, based on a power supply current value consumed by the device under test when the power supply voltage is changed.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The test apparatus as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the control section, by decreasing the gate voltage, increases the power supply voltage with a gradient designated in advance.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The test apparatus as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the control section conducts a first test in which the power supply voltage is raised from a first power supply voltage to a second power supply voltage while keeping the first reference voltage supplied from the reference voltage supply section, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>on condition that no defect for the device under test is found in the first test, the control section conducts a second test in which the power supply voltage is raised from a voltage value substantially the same as a voltage value of the first power supply voltage to a third power supply voltage that is higher than the second power supply voltage, while keeping the second reference voltage supplied from the reference voltage supply section, the second reference voltage being higher than the first reference voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A test method for testing a device under test by means of a test apparatus, the test apparatus including:
<claim-text>a reference voltage supply section for supplying a reference voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a field effect transistor provided between a positive side terminal and a negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, so that a drain terminal and a source terminal of the field effect transistor are in parallel connection with the device under test; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an inductance that is connected between the positive side terminal and the negative side terminal of the reference voltage supply section, the inductance being in serial connection with the device under test between a positive-side power supply terminal and a negative-side power supply terminal of the device under test, and being in serial connection with the field effect transistor between the drain terminal and the source terminal of the field effect transistor,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the test method comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control step for controlling a gate voltage of the field effect transistor, thereby changing a power supply voltage to be supplied to the device under test; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a judgment step for judging quality of the device under test, based on characteristic of the device under test in accordance with change in the power supply voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
