<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297088-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297088</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11109045</doc-number>
<date>20050419</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-124641</doc-number>
<date>20040420</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>194</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>63</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>22</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>482  3</main-classification>
<further-classification>482  8</further-classification>
<further-classification>482900</further-classification>
<further-classification>377 242</further-classification>
<further-classification>702160</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Electronic pedometer</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4855942</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Bianco</name>
<date>19890800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>702160</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6254513</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Takenaka et al.</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>482  3</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>56086309</doc-number>
<date>19810700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>63262784</doc-number>
<date>19881000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2697911</doc-number>
<date>19970900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>3017529</doc-number>
<date>19991200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>18</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>482  1-  9</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>482 54</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>482900-902</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>235105</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34235706</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 36132</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 36136</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>377 24</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>377 242</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>702160</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050238132</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051027</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tsuji</last-name>
<first-name>Tomoharu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chiba</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Adams &amp; Wilks</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Seiko Instruments Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Richman</last-name>
<first-name>Glenn E.</first-name>
<department>3764</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">To enhance precision in measurement of the number of steps even when a walk cycle changes. An acceleration detecting portion outputs a walk signal corresponding to a walk of a user detected by a walk sensor. A step number counting portion of a counting portion counts each signal which is judged to be beyond a first reference cycle range by a walk cycle comparing portion among signals from the acceleration detecting portion as the number of steps for one step, and when an extra-regulation step number processing portion judges that a predetermined number of signals each within a second reference cycle range among the signals each beyond the first reference cycle range is continuously outputted, counts the predetermined number of signals as the predetermined number of steps.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="190.25mm" wi="180.51mm" file="US07297088-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="257.73mm" wi="182.20mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297088-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="267.97mm" wi="194.82mm" file="US07297088-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="214.88mm" wi="113.88mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297088-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an electronic pedometer which is used by being mounted on a human body in order to electronically count the number of steps by a person having the electronic pedometer mounted thereon.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Heretofore, an electronic pedometer has been developed which is used by being mounted on a human body in order to count the number of steps by a user through an electronic processing.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In general, for counting of the number of steps, an acceleration caused by vertical movement of a user's body during walking is detected to count how many times the accelerations occur as the number of steps.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">However, a problem arises in that various noises due to motions of daily life other than a walk are detected, and hence the number of steps cannot be precisely measured as has been pointed out formerly.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In order to solve this problem, there have been proposed a method in which after an acceleration is detected once, a predetermined dead zone time period is set to avoid misdetection due to noises (refer to Patent Document 1 for example), a method in which detection signals are counted as the number of steps only when it is detected that the detection signs are continuously outputted by the predetermined number of times (refer to Patent Document 2 and Patent Document 3 for example), and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, the acceleration is not only caused by a walk, but also caused by motions in daily life. Thus, it is impossible to distinguish the acceleration by a walk from the acceleration (caused by an office work for example) which regularly continues to enter the walk.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In order to improve this problem, a method is proposed in which a cycle in a walk is detected, and the number of steps is calculated from the cycle and a walk time period (refer to Patent Document 4 for example).</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">However, even if such measures are taken, a walk cycle is not usually maintained in a fixed state. A pace may be changed or a detection signal may be mixed with a noise. Hence, it is actually difficult in many cases to detect precisely a cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of a pedometer described in Patent Document 1 described above. The pedometer includes: an acceleration detecting portion <b>301</b>, which is used by being mounted on the body of a user, for detecting an acceleration caused by a walk of the user to output a signal (walk signal) corresponding to the walk; a filter portion <b>302</b> for outputting a signal having a predetermined cycle corresponding to a walk cycle from the output signal from the acceleration detecting portion <b>301</b>; a walk cycle calculating portion <b>306</b> for calculating a walk cycle as a reference by averaging a predetermined number of signals of the signals outputted from the filter portion <b>302</b>; a walk cycle comparing portion <b>303</b> for comparing a cycle of each signal outputted from the filter portion <b>302</b> with the walk cycle as the reference calculated in the walk cycle calculating portion <b>306</b> to output a signal having a cycle similar to the walk cycle as the above reference of the signals outputted from the filter portion <b>302</b>; a step number counting portion <b>304</b> for counting signals from the walk cycle comparing portion <b>303</b>; and a display portion <b>305</b> for displaying thereon a count value obtained through the counting in the step number counting portion <b>304</b>. It should be noted that the filter portion <b>302</b>, the walk cycle comparing portion <b>303</b>, the step number counting portion <b>304</b>, and the walk cycle calculating portion <b>306</b> can be configured with a central processing unit (CPU), and a storage portion for storing therein a program to be executed by the CPU.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The acceleration detecting portion <b>301</b> detects an acceleration caused by a walk of a walker to output a signal corresponding to the walk. The filter portion <b>302</b> outputs a signal having a predetermined cycle corresponding to a walk cycle from the output signal of the acceleration detecting portion <b>301</b>. The walk cycle calculating portion <b>306</b> calculates a walk cycle as a reference by averaging a predetermined number of signals of the signals outputted from the filter portion <b>302</b>. The walk cycle comparing portion <b>303</b> compares a cycle of each signal outputted from the filter portion <b>302</b> with the walk cycle as the reference calculated in the walk cycle calculating portion <b>306</b> to output a signal having a cycle similar to the walk cycle as the above reference of the signals outputted from the filter portion <b>302</b>. The step number counting portion <b>304</b> counts signals from the walk cycle comparing portion <b>303</b> as signals corresponding to the walk. The display portion <b>305</b> displays thereon data on the number of steps as a count value obtained through the counting in the step number counting portion <b>304</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In such a manner, the electric pedometer is configured such that the walk cycle comparing portion <b>303</b> outputs the signals which are generated with a cycle similar to the walk cycle as the reference. Thus, a predetermined dead zone is provided so as not to detect any of the signals which are generated for time periods other than the time period similar to the time period having the walk cycle. As a result, it becomes possible to avoid that the noise is detected as the signal caused by the walk by mistake.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">However, a walk cycle is not usually maintained in a fixed state. A pace may be changed or a detection signal may be mixed with a noise. Hence, it is actually difficult in many cases to detect precisely a cycle. Moreover, even if a dead zone time period is provided, precision in measurement of the number of steps is low. This is a problem.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">&lt;patent document 1&gt; JP laid-open disclosure public patent bulletin 56-86309</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">&lt;patent document 2&gt; JP laid-open disclosure public patent bulletin 63-262784</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">&lt;patent document 3&gt; JP patent number 3017529</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">&lt;patent document 4&gt; JP patent number 2697911</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">It is an object of the present invention to enhance precision in measurement of the number of steps even when a walk cycle changes.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">According to the present invention, there is provided an electronic pedometer having: walk detecting means, having a walk sensor, for outputting a walk signal corresponding to a walk of a user detected by the walk sensor; and counting means for counting the number of steps based on the walk signal from the walk detecting means, the walk sensor being used at least by being mounted on a body of the user, in which the counting means counts each signal within a first reference cycle range of signals from the walk detecting means as the number of steps for one step, and when a predetermined number of signals each within a second reference cycle range of the signals each beyond the first reference cycle range are continuously outputted from the walk detecting means, the counting means counts the predetermined number of signals as a predetermined number of steps.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The counting means counts each signal within a first reference cycle range of signals from the walk detecting means as the number of steps for one step, and when a predetermined number of signals each within a second reference cycle range of signals each beyond the first reference cycle range are continuously outputted from the walk detecting means, the counting means counts the predetermined number of steps as the predetermined number of steps.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Here, the counting means may include: first cycle judging means for judging whether or not each signal from the walk detecting means is a signal within the first reference cycle range; second cycle judging means for judging whether or not each signal judged to be beyond the first reference cycle by the first cycle judging means among the signals from the walk detecting means is a signal within the second reference cycle range; and step number counting means for counting each signal judged to be a signal within the first reference cycle range by the first reference cycle judging means among the signals from the walk detecting means as the number of steps for one step, and for, when the second reference cycle judging means judges that a predetermined number of signals each within the second reference cycle range are continuously outputted from the walk detecting means, counting the predetermined number of signals thus continuously outputted as the predetermined number of steps.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In addition, the second cycle judging means may include first cycle storing means for successively storing data on cycles of the predetermined number of signals each judged to be a signal within the second reference cycle range, and when the signal judged to be beyond the first reference cycle range by the first cycle judging means is a signal within a predetermined cycle range with a cycle of a newest signal data on which is stored in the first cycle storing means as a reference, judge that the signal thus judged is a signal within the second reference cycle range and stores the signal thus judged in the first cycle storing means. The first cycle storing means may be configured such that when storing therein data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals, the predetermined number of signals are outputted as the predetermined number of steps. The counting means may count the predetermined number of steps.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In addition, the counting means includes reference cycle calculating means for movement-averaging cycles of a predetermined number of signals from the walk detecting means; and the first cycle judging means judges whether or not a signal from the walk detecting means is a signal within the first reference cycle range using as the first reference cycle range a predetermined range having as a reference the moving average calculated by the reference cycle calculating means.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In addition, the reference cycle calculating means may include second cycle storing means for successively storing therein data on cycles of a predetermined number of newest signals each judged to be within the first reference cycle range by the first cycle judging means, and obtain a moving average of the cycles of the predetermined number of signals the data on which is stored in the second cycle storing means.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In addition, the reference cycle calculating means may be configured such that when receiving data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals from the first cycle storing means, the reference cycle calculating means stores the data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals in the second cycle storing means, and obtains a moving average using the cycles of the signals the data on which is stored in the second cycle storing means.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In addition, the walk sensor may be used by being mounted on an arm of a user.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In addition, an electronic pedometer may be configured to have a timing function.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">A preferred form of the present invention is illustrated in the accompanying drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of an electronic pedometer according to an embodiment mode of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram showing the details of an extra-regulation step number holding portion used in the embodiment mode of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flow chart for explaining processings in the embodiment mode of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block diagram of a conventional electronic pedometer.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">An electronic pedometer according to an embodiment mode of the present invention will hereinafter be described with reference to the drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of an electronic pedometer according to an embodiment mode of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the electronic pedometer includes: an acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> which has a walk sensor <b>100</b> constituted by an acceleration sensor and which serves to detect a walk (including running) of a user by the walk sensor <b>100</b> to output a signal (walk signal) corresponding to the walk; a counting portion <b>102</b> for counting the number of steps of the user based on the walk signal from the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b>; a display portion <b>103</b> which is constituted by a liquid crystal display device and which serves to display thereon data on the number of steps of the user counted by the counting portion <b>102</b>; and a switch <b>104</b> as manipulation means for carrying out manipulations such as a counting start manipulation and a counting end manipulation for the counting portion <b>102</b>, and a manipulation for resetting the count value.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The counting portion <b>102</b> may be constructed of a central processing unit (CPU) and a storage portion for storing therein a program to be executed by the CPU.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a functional block diagram in which the counting portion <b>102</b> is functionally illustrated. The counting portion <b>102</b> includes: a filter portion <b>105</b> for outputting a signal having a cycle within an allowable change range among signals outputted from the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b>; a walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> for calculating a reference walk cycle by obtaining a moving average Ta of cycles of a predetermined number of newest signals (four signals in this embodiment mode) among signals each of which is judged to be a walk signal in a walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>; the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> for comparing a cycle of a signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> with a first reference cycle range (Ta ±10% in this embodiment mode) based on the reference walk cycle to output a signal having a cycle within the first reference cycle range among signals outputted from the filter portion <b>105</b> as the number of steps for one step to a step number counting portion <b>107</b> and to output a signal beyond the first reference cycle range among signals from the filter portion <b>105</b> to an extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b>; the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> for comparing a cycle of a signal from the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> with a second reference cycle range (a cycle of the newest signal among the cycles of the signals data on which is stored in an extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> in this embodiment mode) to store a signal having a cycle within the second reference cycle range among the signals from the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>, and for, when the number of cycles of signals data on which is stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> becomes a predetermined number (four in this embodiment mode), outputting the data of the number of cycles of signals stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> to the step number counting portion <b>107</b> and resetting and erasing the data stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b>; and a step number counting portion <b>107</b> for counting the current number of steps by adding the numbers of steps obtained from the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> and the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> to a step number count value.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, has a predetermined number (four in this embodiment mode) of storage areas <b>201</b> to <b>204</b>. The extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> is configured so as to successively store data on cycles of signals from the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> in the storage areas <b>201</b> to <b>204</b>. The extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> is a shift register having an FIFO configuration. Data on a cycle of the newest signal is stored in the storage area <b>201</b>, . . . , data on a cycle of the oldest signal is stored in the storage area <b>204</b>. Thus, at the same time when data on a cycle of a new signal is stored in the storage area <b>201</b>, data on cycles of signals stored in the storage areas <b>201</b>, <b>202</b>, and <b>203</b>, respectively, are successively shifted, and the data on the cycle of the oldest signal stored in the storage area <b>204</b> is discharged to be erased.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> has storage means <b>112</b> in its inside. The storage means <b>112</b> has areas, in which data on cycles of a predetermined number (four in this embodiment mode) of signals is to be stored, similarly to the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b>. The walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> successively stores data on cycles of a predetermined number of newest signals of signals each of which is judged to be a walk signal by the walk cycle comparing portion in the storage means <b>112</b>, and calculates the reference walk cycle by obtaining a moving average Ta of the cycles of the predetermined number of signals to output data on the reference walk cycle to the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>. Note that while, in this embodiment mode, a storage capacity of the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> and a storage capacity of the storage means <b>112</b> are made identical to each other, those storage capacities are not necessarily made identical to each other.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In addition, when the walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> receives data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> from the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b>, the walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> rewrites the storage contents within the storage means <b>112</b> to the data on the cycle of the predetermined number of signals received from the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b>, and calculates the moving average Ta using the data on the cycle of the predetermined number of signals obtained through the rewriting to output the resultant moving average Ta to the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>. Hereinafter, the walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> successively stores data on cycles of signals from the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> in the storage means <b>112</b>, and calculates the moving average Ta using data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals thus stored to output the resultant moving average Ta to the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The filter portion <b>105</b> has an allowable cycle range storing means <b>111</b> for storing therein data on an allowable cycle range. Data on an allowable range for a cycle with which a signal from the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> is recognized as a walk signal, i.e., data on a fluctuation range (allowable cycle range) for a cycle when a user normally walks is stored in the allowable cycle range storing means <b>111</b> in advance. In this embodiment mode, the allowable cycle range is set in a range of 333 msec (180 rpm) to 1,000 msec. The setting of the allowable cycle range in the allowable cycle range storing means <b>111</b> is carried out by manipulating the switch <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In addition, while not illustrated, the counting portion <b>102</b> has a timing function, and carries out the switching and display of data on the number of steps and time through the manipulation of the switch <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">It should be noted that the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b>, the counting portion <b>102</b>, the display portion <b>103</b>, the switch <b>104</b>, the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>, the step number counting portion <b>107</b>, the work cycle calculating portion <b>108</b>, processing portion <b>109</b>, the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b>, and the storage means <b>112</b> constitute walk detecting means, counting means, display means, manipulation means, first cycle judging means, step number counting means, reference cycle calculating means, second cycle judging means, first cycle storing means, and second cycle storing means, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flow chart showing processings executed in the counting portion <b>102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">An operation of the electronic pedometer according to this embodiment mode will hereinafter be described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 to 3</figref>, and with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> as may be necessary.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">First of all, a user wears the electronic pedometer on his/her body as preparation for measurement of the number of steps. At this time, the acceleration sensor provided in the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> is mounted on an arm of the user. In this state, the user causes the electronic pedometer to start an operation for measuring the number of steps by manipulating the switch <b>104</b>, and starts to walk.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> detects a walk (including running) of the user to output a signal (walk signal) corresponding to the walk. The filter portion <b>105</b> judges whether or not a cycle T of the output signal from the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> is a value within a predetermined reference cycle range (the third reference cycle range) for a walk (Step S<b>201</b>). That is, the filter portion <b>105</b> judges whether or not the cycle T of the output signal from the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> falls within the third reference cycle range the data on which is stored in the allowable cycle range storing means <b>111</b> in advance. In this embodiment mode, the filter portion <b>105</b> judges whether or not the cycle T of the output signal meets a condition of 333 msec (180 rpm)&lt;T&lt;1,000 msec.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">When the filter portion <b>105</b> judges in Step S<b>201</b> that the cycle T is beyond the third reference cycle range, the filter portion <b>105</b> judges that the output signal is a noise, and outputs no signal (Step S<b>210</b>). When the filter portion <b>105</b> judges in Step S<b>201</b> that the cycle T falls within the third reference cycle range, the filter portion <b>105</b> judges that the signal from the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> is the walk signal, and outputs that signal.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Next, the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> compares the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> with the first reference cycle range based on a reference walk cycle calculated by the walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b>, thereby judging whether or not the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is similar to the reference walk cycle (Step S<b>202</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Here, the judgment reference related to whether or not the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is similar to the reference walk cycle means a reference with which the frequency of occurrence of a counting error due to noises is small and the walk signal can be counted with less leakage. In this embodiment mode, Ta±10% (Ta is a moving average value of the cycles of a newest predetermined number of signals during a walk outputted from the filter portion <b>105</b>) is set as the above first reference cycle range. Then, when the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is within the first reference cycle range, the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> judges that the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is similar to the reference walk cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">When the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> judges in Step S<b>202</b> that the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is within the first reference cycle range, the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> judges that the signal from the filter <b>105</b> is the walk signal, and outputs the data on the cycles of the signal to the walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b>. The step number counting portion <b>107</b> counts the walk signal from the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> and adds 1 count to the step number count value until now to output the resultant value to the display portion <b>103</b> (Step S<b>203</b>). The count value which is obtained by adding 1 count to the count value displayed until now is displayed as an accumulated number of steps on the display portion <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> successively stores data on cycles of a predetermined number of newest signals each of which is judged to be a walk signal by the walk cycle comparing means <b>106</b> in the storage means <b>112</b>, and calculates the reference walk cycle by obtaining the moving average Ta of the cycles of the predetermined number of signals data on which is stored in the storage means <b>112</b> to output the resultant moving average Ta to the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> executes the above processing using data on the reference walk cycle.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">On the other hand, when the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> judges in Step S<b>202</b> that the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is beyond the first reference cycle range, the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> outputs the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> to the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges whether or not a cycle of a signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is similar to a cycle of a signal data on which is stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> the last time by the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>, i.e., judges whether or not a cycle of a signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is within a predetermined range (second reference cycle range) which takes the cycle of the walk signal the data of which is stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> the last time as a reference (Step S<b>204</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">When the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges in Step S<b>204</b> that the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> judged to be beyond the first reference cycle range by the extra-regulation step number portion <b>109</b> is similar to the cycle of the signal the data on which is stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> the last time, i.e., judges in Step S<b>204</b> that the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is within the second reference cycle range, the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges that the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is a walk signal, and stores data on the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> (Step S<b>205</b>). Then, the operation proceeds to Step S<b>206</b>. Note that the judgment in Step S<b>204</b> shows that the storage contents in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> are empty, the operation proceeds unconditionally to Step S<b>205</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">When the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges in Step S<b>204</b> that the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> judged to be beyond the first reference cycle range by the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> is not similar to the cycle of the signal the data on which is stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> the last time, i.e., judges in Step S<b>204</b> that the cycle of the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is beyond the second reference cycle range, the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges that the signal from the filter portion <b>105</b> is not a walk signal, and clears all the storage contents in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> (Step S<b>209</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Next, the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges whether or not the signals outputted from the filter portion <b>105</b> through the step cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> are signals each within the second reference cycle range and are continuously outputted from the filter portion <b>105</b> by the predetermined number of times (four times in this embodiment mode) (Step S<b>206</b>). When the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges that the signals are continuously outputted from the filter portion <b>105</b> by the predetermined number of times, the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges that after a cycle of a walk of a user changes, the cycle in the walk of the user becomes stable. Then, the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> outputs the predetermined number of signals as the predetermined number of steps to the step number counting portion <b>107</b>, and outputs the data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> to the walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> (Step S<b>207</b>). The step number counting portion <b>107</b> counts the number of steps as the predetermined number of steps, and data on the accumulated number of steps is displayed on the display portion <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">When the walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> receives the data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> from the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b>, the walk cycle calculating portion <b>108</b> rewrites the storage contents within the storage means <b>112</b> to data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals received from the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion <b>110</b> to store the resultant data in the storage means <b>112</b>, and newly calculates the moving average Ta of a walk cycle using the data of the cycles of the predetermined number of signals thus stored (Step S<b>208</b>) to output the resultant moving average Ta to the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b>. The walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> calculates a first reference cycle range using the moving average Ta of the walk cycles, and executes the above processing based on the resultant first reference cycle range.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">When the extra-regulation step number processing portion <b>109</b> judges in Step S<b>206</b> that the signals outputted from the filter portion <b>105</b> through the walk cycle comparing portion <b>106</b> are signals each within the second reference cycle range and are not continuously outputted from the filter portion <b>105</b> by the predetermined number of times, the processings are completed.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">By repeating the above operation, the counting portion <b>102</b> executes the processing for counting the number of steps based on the walk signal detected by the acceleration detecting portion, and data on the accumulated number of steps is displayed on the display portion <b>103</b> at any time.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">When the user intends to complete the step number measurement, the user can stop the counting operation in the counting portion <b>102</b> by manipulating the switch <b>104</b>. In addition, the displayed contents on the display portion <b>103</b> can also be reset by manipulating the switch <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">As described above, the electronic pedometer according to this embodiment mode having: the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> having the walk sensor <b>100</b> for outputting a walk signal corresponding to a walk of a user detected by the walk sensor <b>100</b>; and the counting portion <b>102</b> for counting the number of steps based on the walk signal from the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b>, the walk sensor <b>100</b> being used at least by being mounted on the body of the user is characterized in that the counting portion <b>102</b> counts each signal within a first reference cycle range of the signals from the acceleration detecting portion <b>101</b> as one step, and counts as the predetermined number of steps the predetermined number of signals in the case where signals within a second reference cycle range, among the signals each beyond the first reference cycle range are continuously outputted.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Consequently, even when the detection signal is mixed with a noise caused by a factor other than a walk, or the walk cycle changes, a change in walk cycle can be discriminated to detect the number of steps. Hence, it becomes possible to enhance the precision in measurement of the number of steps.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The present invention can also be applied to an electronic pedometer which is configured such that all constituent elements of the pedometer are mounted on a user for use, or to an electronic pedometer which is configured such that: a part (including at least sensors) of constituent elements is mounted on a user; other constituent elements transmit/receive signals in a wireless manner to/from the part of the constituent elements; and the other constituent elements are provided in a place distant from the user. In addition, the present invention can also be applied to an electronic pedometer in which the walk sensor is mounted on a part of the body other than an arm.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">According to the present invention, even when a detection signal is mixed with a noise caused by a factor other than a walk, or a walk cycle changes, it becomes possible to enhance precision in measurement of the number of steps.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electronic pedometer comprising:
<claim-text>walk detecting means having a walk sensor mountable on a user's body for outputting a walk signal corresponding to a walk of a user detected by the walk sensor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>counting means for counting the number of steps based on the walk signal from the walk detecting means by counting each signal within a first reference cycle range of signals from the walk detecting means as the number of steps for one step, and counting a predetermined number of signals as a predetermined number of steps when the predetermined number of signals each within a second reference cycle range of the signals each beyond the first reference cycle range are continuously outputted from the walk detecting means, the counting means comprising first cycle judging means for judging whether or not each signal from the walk detecting means is a signal within the first reference cycle range, second cycle judging means for judging whether or not each signal judged to be beyond the first reference cycle by the first cycle judging means among the signals from the walk detecting means is a signal within the second reference cycle range, and step number counting means for counting each signal judged to be a signal within the first reference cycle range by the first reference cycle judging means among the signals from the walk detecting means as the number of steps for one step, and for, when the second reference cycle judging means judges that a predetermined number of signals each within the second reference cycle range are continuously outputted from the walk detecting means, counting the predetermined number of signals thus continuously outputted as the predetermined number of steps.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>; wherein the second cycle judging means includes first cycle storing means for successively storing data on cycles of the predetermined number of signals each judged to be a signal within the second reference cycle range; wherein when the signal judged to be beyond the first reference cycle range by the first cycle judging means is a signal within a predetermined cycle range with a cycle of a newest signal data on which is stored in the first cycle storing means as a reference, the second cycle judging means judges that the signal thus judged is a signal within the second reference cycle range and stores the signal thus judged in the first cycle storing means; wherein when the first cycle storing means stores therein data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals, the predetermined number of signals are outputted as the predetermined number of steps; and wherein the counting means counts the predetermined number of steps.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>; wherein the counting means comprises reference cycle calculating means for movement-averaging cycles of a predetermined number of newest signals each judged to be within the first reference cycle range by the first cycle judging means among signals from the walk detecting means; and wherein the first cycle judging means judges whether or not a signal from the walk detecting means is a signal within the first reference cycle range using as the first reference cycle range a predetermined range having as a reference the moving average calculated by the reference cycle calculating means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>; wherein the reference cycle calculating means includes second cycle storing means for successively storing therein data on cycles of a predetermined number of newest signals each judged to be within the first reference cycle range by the first cycle judging means; and wherein the reference cycle calculating means obtains a moving average of the cycles of the predetermined number of signals using the data stored in the second cycle storing means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>; wherein when the reference cycle calculating means receives data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals from the first cycle storing means, the reference cycle calculating means stores the data on the cycles of the predetermined number of signals in the second cycle storing means and obtains a moving average using the cycles of the signals stored in the second cycle storing means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>; wherein the walk sensor is used by being mounted on an arm of a the user.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>; wherein the counting means performs a timing function.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>; further comprising a display portion for displaying data corresponding to the number of steps counted by the counting means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>; wherein the display portion comprises a liquid crystal display device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>; further comprising means for starting a counting operation of the counting means, stopping the counting operation, and resetting a count value of the counting operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An electronic pedometer comprising:
<claim-text>a walk sensor that detects a walk of a user;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an acceleration detection portion that outputs a walk signal corresponding to a walk of the user detected by the walk sensor; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a counting portion that counts the number of steps of the user in accordance with the walk signal from the acceleration detection portion, the counting portion comprising a filter portion that outputs a signal having a cycle within an allowable change range among signals outputted from the acceleration detecting portion, a walk cycle calculating portion that calculates a reference walk cycle, a walk cycle comparing portion that compares a cycle of a signal from the filter portion with a first reference cycle range in accordance with the reference walk cycle to output a signal having a cycle within the first reference cycle range among signals outputted from the filter portion as the number of steps for one step and to output a signal beyond the first reference cycle range among signals from the filter portion, an extraregulation step number temporarily holding portion that stores cycles of signal data, an extraregulation step number processing portion that compares a cycle of a signal from the walk cycle comparing portion with a second reference cycle range corresponding to a cycle of a newest signal among the cycles of signal data stored in an extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion to store a signal having a cycle within the second reference cycle range among the signals from the walk cycle comparing portion and that outputs the data of the number of cycles of signals stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion and resets and erases the signal data stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion when the number of cycles of signal data stored in the extra-regulation step number temporarily holding portion becomes a predetermined number, and a step number counting portion for counting the current number of steps by adding the number of steps obtained from the walk cycle comparing portion and the extraregulation step number processing portion to a step number count value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>; wherein the walk sensor is mountable on the user's body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>; wherein the walk sensor is used by being mounted on an arm of the user.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>; wherein the counting portion performs a timing function.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>; further comprising a display portion for displaying data corresponding to the number of steps counted by the counting portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>; wherein the display portion comprises a liquid crystal display device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>; further comprising a switch that is adapted for manipulation to start a counting operation of the counting portion, stop the counting operation, and reset a count value of the counting operation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. An electronic pedometer according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>; wherein the walk sensor is mountable on the user's body; and wherein at least one of the acceleration detection portion and the counting portion is not mountable on the user's body and communicates with the walk sensor by wireless communication.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
