<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298162-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298162</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11331815</doc-number>
<date>20060113</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-298259</doc-number>
<date>20041012</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>157</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324769</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Test apparatus and test method</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4712058</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Branson et al.</name>
<date>19871200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324763</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5065091</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tobita</name>
<date>19911100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5157627</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gheewala</name>
<date>19921000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>36518901</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5834967</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kuroda et al.</name>
<date>19981100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5942922</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dinteman et al.</name>
<date>19990800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>327108</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>5-72287</doc-number>
<date>19930300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>PCT Office Action dated Jan. 10, 2006 (3 pages).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Patent Abstracts of Japan; Publication No. 05-072287 dated Mar. 23, 1993 (2 pages).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>3</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324763</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324765</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324769</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3241581</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>368110</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>368118</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>368120</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714718</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714721</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714725</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10992988</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20041119</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7023233</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11331815</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060114015</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060601</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Furukawa</last-name>
<first-name>Yasuo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Osha Liang LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Advantest Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Ha Tran</first-name>
<department>2829</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Tung X.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A test apparatus for testing switching speed of a circuit, which includes a pre-stage logic element outputting a first or second level voltage and a post-stage logic element to which the output signal of the pre-stage logic element is input, is provided, wherein the post-stage logic element includes the post-stage FET, a gate terminal of which the output signal is input to, for outputting a different level of voltage according to the case that the output signal voltage is higher or lower than a predetermined threshold voltage, and the test apparatus includes a threshold voltage setting unit for setting a threshold voltage of a post-stage field effect transistor (FET) to be different from that in a normal operation by setting a substrate voltage of the post-stage FET to have a value different from that in the normal operation of the circuit; a delay time measuring unit for measuring a delay time of the circuit to which the threshold voltage different from that in the normal operation is set; and an error detecting unit for detecting an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the delay time.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="151.47mm" wi="240.71mm" file="US07298162-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="239.95mm" wi="165.44mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298162-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="244.94mm" wi="129.88mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298162-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="189.40mm" wi="132.50mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298162-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="224.54mm" wi="136.14mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298162-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="142.92mm" wi="108.37mm" file="US07298162-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="241.64mm" wi="161.12mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298162-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="153.42mm" wi="109.90mm" file="US07298162-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="238.42mm" wi="119.55mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298162-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This patent application is a divisional application of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 10/992,988 filed on Nov. 19, 2004 now U.S. Pat. No. 7,023,233, which claims priority from Japanese patent application No. 2004-298259 filed on Oct. 12, 2004, the contents of which are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to a test apparatus and a test method. More particularly, the present invention relates to a test apparatus and a test method for detecting a delay failure of a circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In connection with miniaturization of LSI in recent years, miniaturization of logical elements in the LSI is progressing. Accordingly, driving performance of the logic element decreases, and thus a delay failure of the logic element becomes a major cause for a failure of the LSI.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The following documents relate to a scan test for detecting this kind of delay failure and discloses a scan method which switches a test pattern of a cycle to a test pattern of its next cycle at a high speed (cf. J. P. Hurst, N. Kanopoulos, “Flip-Flop Sharing in Standard Scan Path to Enhance Delay Fault Testing of Sequential Circuits,” Asian Test Symposium 1995, IEEE, Nov. 23, 1995, p. 346-352; K. Hatayama, M. Ikeda, M. Takakura, S. Uchiyama, Y. Sakamoto, “Application of a Design for Delay Testability Approach to High Speed Logic LSIs,” Asian Test Symposium 1997, IEEE, Nov. 17, 1997, p. 112-115; N. A. Touba, E. J. McCluskey, “Applying Two-Pattern Tests Using Scan-Mapping,” IEEE VLSI Test Symposium 1996, IEEE, Apr. 28, 1996, p. 393-397; Eric MacDonald, N. A. Touba, “Delay Testing of SOI Circuits: Challenges with the History Effect,” International Test Conference 1999, IEEE, Sep. 27, 1999, p. 269-275. According to the documents, it is possible to detect whether or not a circuit operates within a predetermined delay time by controlling clock intervals of adjacent clocks (double clocks) and testing whether or not the circuit correctly operates</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">According to the above tests using the double clocks, the absolute value of a delay time of a circuit is measured and acceptability of an LSI is determined based on the measured absolute value. Therefore, it is impossible to determine whether the measured delay is caused by the variance of a process or by a delay failure of a logic element.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Therefore, it is an object of the present invention to provide a test apparatus and a test method, which are capable of overcoming the above drawbacks. The above and other objects can be achieved by combinations described in the independent claims. The dependent claims define further advantageous and exemplary combinations of the present invention.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">According to the first aspect of the present invention, there is provided a test apparatus for testing switching speed of a circuit, which includes a pre-stage logic element outputting a first or second level voltage and a post-stage logic element to which the output signal of the pre-stage logic element is input, is provided, wherein the post-stage logic element includes the post-stage FET, a gate terminal of which the output signal is input to, for outputting a different level of voltage according to the case that the output signal voltage is higher or lower than a predetermined threshold voltage. The test apparatus includes a threshold voltage setting unit for setting a threshold voltage of a post-stage field effect transistor (FET) to be different from that in a normal operation by setting a substrate voltage of the post-stage FET to have a value different from that in the normal operation of the circuit; a delay time measuring unit for measuring a delay time of the circuit to which the threshold voltage different from that in the normal operation is set; and an error detecting unit for detecting an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the delay time.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The threshold voltage setting unit may include a first substrate voltage setting unit for setting the threshold voltage to the post-stage FET by setting the substrate voltage to a first substrate voltage; and a second substrate voltage setting unit for setting the threshold voltage to the post-stage FET by setting the substrate voltage to a second substrate voltage. The delay time measuring unit may include a first delay time measuring unit for measuring a first delay time of the circuit when the substrate voltage is set to the first substrate voltage; and a second delay time measuring unit for measuring a second delay time of the circuit when the substrate voltage is set to the second substrate voltage. The error detecting unit detects the error in switching speed of the circuit in case of the difference between the first and the second delay times being larger than a predetermined reference value.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The first substrate voltage setting unit may set the substrate voltage to the first substrate voltage used in the normal operation of the circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The pre-stage logic element may include a pre-stage P-channel FET including a source terminal coupled to a voltage source with respect to the output signal and a drain terminal coupled to the side of the output signal with respect to the source terminal; and a pre-stage N-channel FET including a source terminal coupled to a ground with respect to the output signal and a drain terminal coupled to the side of the output signal with respect to the source terminal. The post-stage logic element may include a post-stage P-channel FET including a source terminal coupled to a voltage source with respect to the output of the post-stage logic element and a drain terminal coupled to the output side with respect to the source terminal; and a pre-stage N-channel FET including a source terminal coupled to a ground with respect to the output and a drain terminal coupled to the output side with respect to the source terminal. The first substrate voltage setting unit may set the substrate voltage of the post-stage N-channel FET to the first substrate voltage. The first delay time measuring unit measures the first delay time when the substrate voltage of the post-stage N-channel FET is set to the first substrate voltage. The second substrate voltage setting unit may set the substrate voltage of the post-stage N-channel FET to the second substrate voltage. The second delay time measuring unit may measure the second delay time when the substrate voltage is set to the second substrate voltage. The error detecting unit may detect an error in the pre-stage P-channel FET in case of the difference between the first and second delay times being larger than the reference value.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The pre-stage logic element may include a pre-stage P-channel FET including a source terminal coupled to a voltage source with respect to the output signal and a drain terminal coupled to the side of the output signal with respect to the source terminal; and a pre-stage N-channel FET including a source terminal coupled to a ground with respect to the output signal and a drain terminal coupled to the side of the output signal with respect to the source terminal. The post-stage logic element may includes a post-stage P-channel FET including a source terminal coupled to a voltage source with respect to the output of the post-stage logic element and a drain terminal coupled to the output side with respect to the source terminal; and a pre-stage N-channel FET including a source terminal coupled to a ground with respect to the output and a drain terminal coupled to the output side with respect to the source terminal. The first substrate voltage setting unit may set the substrate voltage of the post-stage P-channel FET to the first substrate voltage. The first delay time measuring unit may measure the first delay time when the substrate voltage of the post-stage P-channel FET is set to the first substrate voltage. The second substrate voltage setting unit may set the substrate voltage of the post-stage P-channel FET to the second substrate voltage. The second delay time measuring unit measures the second delay time when the substrate voltage is set to the second substrate voltage. The error detecting unit may detect an error in the pre-stage N-channel FET in case of the difference between the first and second delay times being larger than the reference value.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to the second aspect of the present invention, there is provided a test apparatus for testing switching speed of a combination circuit, where a level voltage based on a signal input from a first flip-flop (FF) is input to a second FF, including a pre-stage logic element outputting a first or second level voltage and a post-stage logic element to which the output signal of the pre-stage logic element is input, is provided, wherein the test apparatus includes a clock setting unit for setting a clock interval from the time when a clock signal is provided to the first FF to the time when a clock signal is provided to the second FF; a threshold voltage setting unit for setting a threshold voltage of a post-stage field effect transistor (FET) to be different from that in a normal operation by setting a substrate voltage of the post-stage FET to have a value different from that in the normal operation of the circuit; a first boundary value measuring unit for measuring a first boundary value of the substrate voltage for a normal operation of the circuit by changing the substrate voltage by the threshold voltage setting unit while the clock interval is set to the first clock interval; and an error detecting unit for detecting an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the first boundary value, wherein the post-stage logic element includes the post-stage FET, a gate terminal of which the output signal is input to, for outputting a different level of voltage according to the case that the output signal voltage is higher or lower than a predetermined threshold voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The test apparatus may further include a second boundary value measuring unit for measuring a second boundary value of the substrate voltage for a normal operation of the circuit by changing the substrate voltage by the threshold voltage setting unit with the clock interval set to the second clock interval, wherein the error detecting unit may detect an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the first and second boundary values.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">According to the third aspect of the present invention, there is provided a test method for testing switching speed of a circuit, which includes a pre-stage logic element outputting a first or second level voltage and a post-stage logic element to which the output signal of the pre-stage logic element is input, includes a threshold voltage setting step of setting a threshold voltage of a post-stage field effect transistor (FET) to be different from that in a normal operation by setting a substrate voltage of the post-stage FET to have a value different from that in the normal operation of the circuit; a delay time measuring step of measuring a delay time of the circuit to which the threshold voltage different from that in the normal operation is set; and an error detecting step of detecting an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the delay time, wherein the post-stage logic element includes the post-stage FET, a gate terminal of which the output signal is input to, for outputting a different level of voltage according to the case that the output signal voltage is higher or lower than a predetermined threshold voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">According to the fourth aspect of the present invention, there is provided a test method for testing switching speed of a combination circuit, where a level voltage based on a signal input from a first flip-flop (FF) is input to a second FF, including a pre-stage logic element outputting a first or second level voltage and a post-stage logic element to which the output signal of the pre-stage logic element is input, wherein the post-stage logic element includes a post-stage field effect transistor (FET), the output signal being input to a gate terminal of the post-stage FET, for outputting a different level of voltage according to the case that the output signal voltage is higher or lower than a predetermined threshold voltage, the test method includes: a clock setting step of setting a clock interval from the time when a clock signal is provided to the first FF to the time when a clock signal is provided to the second FF; a threshold voltage setting step of setting a threshold voltage of the post-stage FET to be different from that in a normal operation by setting a substrate voltage of the post-stage FET to have a value different from that in the normal operation of the circuit; a first boundary value measuring step of measuring a first boundary value of the substrate voltage for a normal operation of the circuit by changing the substrate voltage in the threshold voltage setting step while the clock interval is set to the first clock interval; and an error detecting step of detecting an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the first boundary value.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The summary of the invention does not necessarily describe all necessary features of the present invention. The present invention may also be a sub-combination of the features described above. The above and other features and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent from the following description of the embodiments taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows an example of the configuration of a test apparatus <b>10</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an example of the configuration of a DUT <b>100</b> according to the embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a normal operation of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows an abnormal operation of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a flow of an operation of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows an example of the configuration of the test apparatus <b>10</b> according to an alternative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a flow of an operation of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the alternative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows another example of the configuration of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The invention will now be described based on the preferred embodiments, which do not intend to limit the scope of the present invention, but exemplify the invention. All of the features and the combinations thereof described in the embodiment are not necessarily essential to the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows an example of the configuration of a test apparatus <b>10</b> and a DUT <b>100</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention. The test apparatus <b>10</b> detects an error by testing switching speed of a circuit of the DUT <b>100</b>. The test apparatus <b>10</b> includes a clock setting unit <b>110</b>, a threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b>, a setting vector generating unit <b>130</b>, a scan pattern generating unit <b>140</b>, a delay time measuring unit <b>150</b>, and an error detecting unit <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The clock setting unit <b>110</b> sets a clock interval provided to the circuit of the DUT <b>100</b>. The threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> sets a threshold of a FET (Field Effect Transistor) provided in a logic element in the DUT <b>10</b> by setting a substrate voltage of the FET. The threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> includes a first substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>a </i>for setting a first threshold voltage of the FET by setting the substrate voltage of the FET in the DUT to a first substrate voltage and a second substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>b </i>for setting a second threshold voltage of the FET by setting the substrate voltage to a second substrate voltage. The first substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>a </i>according to the present embodiment sets the substrate voltage of the FET to the first substrate voltage in a normal operation of the circuit. The second substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>b </i>sets the FET to have a threshold voltage of which value is different from that of the normal operation by setting the substrate voltage of the FET to a value different from the value of the substrate voltage in the normal operation of the circuit. Instead, the first and the second substrate voltages may be different from the voltage in the normal operation of the circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The setting vector generating unit <b>130</b> generates a setting vector which is a test pattern used to test a path to be tested out of paths in the DUT and provides a signal terminal with the setting vector. Thus, the setting vector generating unit <b>130</b> sets the DUT to be in a state capable of testing the path to be tested. The scan pattern generating unit <b>140</b> generates a scan pattern used for a test of a delay failure and provides a scan terminal of the DUT <b>100</b> with the scan pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The delay time measuring unit <b>150</b> measures a delay time of the circuit of the DUT <b>100</b> in case of being provided with the first substrate voltage and a delay time of the circuit of the DUT <b>100</b> in case of being provided with the second substrate voltage. The delay time measuring unit <b>150</b> includes a first delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>a </i>for measuring a delay time of the circuit in a state of the substrate voltage's being set to the first substrate voltage (a first delay time) and a second delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>b </i>for measuring a delay time of the circuit in a state of the substrate voltage's being set to the second substrate voltage (a second delay time). The first delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>a </i>according to the present embodiment measures a delay time of the circuit set to the first threshold voltage, which is substantially the same as that in the normal operation, in a state of the FET's being provided with the first substrate voltage. The second delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>b </i>measures a delay time of the circuit set to a threshold different from that of the normal operation.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The error detecting unit <b>160</b> detects an error in switching speed of the circuit of the DUT <b>100</b> based on the delay time measured by the delay time measuring unit <b>150</b>. The error detecting unit <b>160</b> according to the present embodiment detects an error in the switching speed of the circuit in case of the difference between the first delay time and the second delay time being larger than a predetermined reference value.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an example of the configuration of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the present embodiment. The DUT <b>100</b> includes a plurality of flip-flops (FF <b>200</b>, FF <b>210</b>, etc.) and a plurality of combination circuits provided between a pre-stage FET and a post-stage FET. According to the present embodiment, a test of a logic path including FF <b>200</b>, FF <b>210</b>, and a circuit <b>220</b> provided between the FF <b>200</b> and the FF <b>210</b> will be explained as a representative of a plurality of logic paths in the DUT <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The FF <b>200</b> is an example of a first FF according to the present invention, receives a level voltage of an input Di at a rising timing of a clock signal CLK<b>1</b>, and outputs it as an output Do. The FF <b>210</b> is an example of a second FF according to the present invention, receives a level voltage of an input Di at a rising timing of a clock signal CLK<b>2</b>, and outputs it as an output Do.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The circuit <b>220</b> is a combination circuit which inputs the level voltage based on the signal Do input from the FF <b>200</b> to an input terminal Di of the FF <b>210</b>. More specifically, the circuit <b>220</b> performs a predetermined logic operation based on the signal input from the FF <b>200</b> and inputs a level voltage showing a logic value resulting from the logic operation to the FF <b>210</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The circuit <b>220</b> has a structure in which the logic elements such as AND, NAND, OR, NOR, EXOR, and NOT are cascade-connected. According to the example of the present figure, the circuit <b>220</b> includes a pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> for outputting a first level voltage (for example, a voltage showing a logic value H) or a second level voltage (for example, a voltage showing a logic value L) onto a logic path from the FF <b>200</b> to the FF <b>210</b> and a post-stage logic element <b>240</b> coupled to the rear part of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> to which the output signal of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> is input.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> includes a pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> and a pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>. The pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> is a MOSFET of which source is coupled to a voltage source side with respect to the output signal, and drain is coupled to an output signal side with respect to the source. The pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> is a MOSFET of which source is coupled to a ground side with respect to the output signal, and drain is coupled to an output signal side with respect to the source. The pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> according to the present embodiment functions as an inverter. The pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> may further include one or a plurality of P-channel FET(s) coupled between the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> and the voltage source or between the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> and the output signal in series. In addition, the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> may further include one or a plurality of N-channel FET(s) coupled between the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> and the ground or between the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> and the output signal in series. In this case, the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> functions as a logic element such as AND, NAND, NOR, OR, or EXOR.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The post-stage logic element <b>240</b> includes a post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> and a post-stage P-channel FET <b>280</b> for inputting the output signal of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> to a gate terminal and outputting a different level of voltage in case of the output signal voltage being higher and lower than a threshold voltage. Since the post-stage logic element <b>240</b> has a configuration similar to that of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b>, the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> corresponds to the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b>, and the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> corresponds to the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b>, explanation on the same parts is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a normal operation of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the present embodiment. In case of a voltage Va input to the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> being a voltage VL showing a level L, the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> becomes ON and the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> becomes OFF. Therefore, a voltage Vb of the output signal of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> becomes a voltage VH showing a level H. Further, the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> becomes OFF, the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b> becomes ON, and a voltage Vc output from the post-stage logic element <b>240</b> becomes the voltage VL.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Then, in case of the voltage Va being changed from VL to VH, if the voltage Va is higher than a threshold voltage Vth (L) of the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>, the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> is switched from OFF to ON (time t<b>1</b>). As a result, the voltage Vb of the output signal of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> begins to change from VH to VL. Then, if the voltage Va is higher than a threshold voltage Vth (H) of the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b>, the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> is switched from ON to OFF and the voltage Vb of the output signal becomes VL.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Then, if the voltage Vb becomes lower than a threshold voltage Vth (H) of the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b>, the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> is switched from OFF to ON (time t<b>2</b>). As a result, the voltage Vc of the output signal of the post-stage logic element <b>240</b> begins to change from VH to VL. Then, if the voltage Vb is lower than a threshold voltage Vth (L) of the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b>, the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b> is switched from ON to OFF and the voltage Vc becomes VH.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">According to the above operations, in case of the voltage Va being the voltage VH, the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> becomes OFF, the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> becomes ON, the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> becomes ON, and the post-stage N-channel FET <b>270</b> becomes OFF.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In the mean time, in case of the voltage Va being changed from VH to VL, if the voltage Va is lower than the threshold voltage Vth (H) of the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b>, the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> is switched from OFF to ON (time t<b>3</b>). As a result, the voltage Vb of the output signal of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> begins to change from VL to VH. Then, if the voltage Va is lower than the threshold voltage Vth (L) of the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>, the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> is switched from ON to OFF and the voltage Vb of the output signal becomes VH.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Then, if the voltage Vb becomes higher than a threshold voltage Vth (L) of the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b>, the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b> is switched from OFF to ON (time t<b>4</b>). As a result, the voltage Vc of the output signal of the post-stage logic element <b>240</b> begins to change from VH to VL. Then, if the voltage Vb is higher than the threshold voltage Vth (H) of the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b>, the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> is switched from ON to OFF and the voltage Vc becomes VL.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows an abnormal operation of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the present embodiment. In a case where there is a delay failure in the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b>, the fall of the voltage Vb becomes slow even if the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> is switched to ON at the time t<b>1</b>. As a result, the time from t<b>1</b> to t<b>2</b> at which the voltage Vb becomes lower than the threshold voltage Vth (H) of the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> becomes longer than that in a normal state. Since the voltage Vc begins to change from VL to VH at the time t<b>2</b>, a delay time of the circuit <b>220</b> becomes longer as a result of the time (t<b>2</b>−t<b>1</b>) becomes larger caused by the delay failure.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In a case where there is a delay failure in the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b>, the rising of the voltage Vb becomes slow even if the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> is switched to ON at the time t<b>3</b>. As a result, the time from t<b>3</b> to t<b>4</b> at which the voltage Vb becomes higher than the threshold voltage Vth (L) of the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b> becomes longer than that in a normal state. Since the voltage Vc begins to change from VH to VL at the time t<b>4</b>, the delay time of the circuit <b>220</b> becomes longer as a result of the time (t<b>4</b>−t<b>3</b>) becomes larger caused by the delay failure.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a flow of an operation of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the present embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In case of detecting a delay failure of the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>, the first substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>a </i>sets the P-channel side substrate voltage VBBp provided to the DUT <b>100</b> to the substrate voltage VBBp<b>1</b> of the side of a first P-channel (S<b>500</b>). Thus, the threshold voltage of each of the pre-stage P-channel type <b>250</b> and the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> is set to a voltage Vth<b>1</b> (H).</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Then, the first delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>a</i>measures a first P-channel side delay time Tp<b>1</b> when the substrate voltage of the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> is set to the first substrate voltage VBBp<b>1</b> (S<b>510</b>). A method for measuring the delay time Tp<b>1</b> is described in the following, for example. The clock setting unit <b>110</b> sets a clock interval from the time when a clock signal is provided to the FF <b>200</b> to the time when a clock signal is provided to the FF <b>210</b> based on an instruction of the first delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>a</i>. The setting vector generating unit <b>130</b> generates a setting vector for testing the logic path including the FF <b>200</b>, the circuit <b>220</b>, and the FF <b>210</b> and provides a signal terminal of the DUT <b>100</b> with it. Then, the scan pattern generating unit <b>140</b> generates a scan pattern used for a test for a delay failure of the logic path, and provides a scan terminal of the DUT <b>100</b> with it to make the DUT <b>100</b> operate. The first delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>a </i>acquires a result of the operation of the DUT <b>100</b> from the DUT <b>100</b> and compares the result with an expectation value generated by the scan pattern generating unit <b>140</b>. In case of the result of the operation of the DUT <b>100</b> being the same as the expectation value, the clock interval is reduced and then the above steps are repeated. According to the above process, the test apparatus <b>10</b> can acquire a minimum clock interval at which the logic path in the DUT <b>100</b> operates properly and use it as the delay time Tp<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Then the second substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>b </i>sets the P-channel side substrate voltage VBBp to the second P-channel side substrate voltage VBBp<b>2</b> (S<b>520</b>). Thus, the threshold voltage of each of the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> and the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> is set to a voltage Vth<b>2</b> (H). Here, the threshold voltage depends on the substrate voltage as disclosed in Hiroyuki Mizuno, “Increase of Leak Current Accompanying Low voltage and High-Speed of CMOS LSI and a Technique for Reducing the Leak Current,” Collection of Learned Papers of Electronic Information Communication Society, Electronic Information Communication Society, Vol. J83-C, No. 10, October of 2000, p. 926-935). Therefore, the test apparatus <b>10</b> can set the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> to a second threshold voltage Vth<b>2</b> (H) different from the first threshold voltage Vth<b>1</b> (H) by setting the second substrate voltage VBBp<b>2</b> different from the first substrate voltage VBBp<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Then, in a similar way to S<b>510</b>, the second delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>b </i>measures a second P-channel side delay time Tp<b>2</b> when the substrate voltage of the post-stage P-channel FET <b>270</b> is set to the second substrate voltage VBBp<b>2</b> (S<b>530</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The error detecting unit <b>160</b> detects an error in the switching speed of the circuit <b>220</b> caused by a defect of the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> based on the first and second delay times Tp<b>1</b> and Tp<b>2</b> (S<b>540</b>). More specifically, letting the absolute value of the difference between the substrate voltages VBBp<b>1</b> and VBBp<b>2</b> be ΔVBB, the absolute value of the difference between the delay times Tp<b>1</b> and Tp<b>2</b> be ΔTd, and a=ΔTd/ΔVBB. In this case, the index a shows a variation in the delay time with respect to the variation of the substrate voltage. Further, the index a is larger In a case where there is a delay failure in one N-channel side FET or there are delay failures in a plurality of N-channel side FET's provided on the logic path, than that in a normal state.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Here, in case of testing the DUT <b>100</b> with the constant ΔVBB, the error detecting unit <b>160</b> can detect an error in the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> if ΔTd which is the difference between the first delay time Tp<b>1</b> and the second delay time Tp<b>2</b> is larger than a predetermined reference value. In other words, the test apparatus <b>10</b> can acquire ΔTd which is an increase in the delay time caused by a delay failure of the pre-stage logic element <b>230</b> by the above process and find out a delay failure of the switching by the N-channel FET based on ΔTd. Further, it is preferable that the reference value is set so that it has a value larger than a variation width of ΔTd caused by a variance of the process in order to distinguish the delay failure from the variance of the process.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In the mean time, in case of detecting a delay error in the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b>, the first substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>a </i>sets the N-channel side substrate voltage VBBn provided to the DUT <b>100</b> to the first N-channel side substrate voltage VBBn<b>1</b> (S<b>500</b>). Thus, the threshold of each of the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> and the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b> is set to the voltage Vth<b>1</b> (L).</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">Then, in a similar way to the case of detecting the delay time of the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>, the first delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>a </i>measures a first N-channel side delay time Tn<b>1</b> when the substrate voltage of the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b> is set to the first substrate voltage VBBn<b>1</b> (S<b>510</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The second substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>b </i>sets the substrate voltage of the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b> to the second substrate voltage VBBn<b>2</b> (S<b>520</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">In a similar way to S<b>510</b>, the second delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>b </i>measures the second delay time Tn<b>2</b> when the substrate voltage of the post-stage N-channel FET <b>280</b> is set to the second substrate voltage VBBn<b>2</b> (S<b>530</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Then, in a similar way to the case of detecting the delay error in the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>, the error detecting unit <b>160</b> detects an error in the switching speed of the circuit <b>220</b> caused by a defect of the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> based on the first and second delay times Tn<b>1</b> and Tn<b>2</b> (S<b>540</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">As described above, according to the test apparatus <b>10</b>, it is possible to detect delay errors in the N-channel FET and the P-channel FET in the DUT <b>100</b> based on the increases of the delay times in case of changing the substrate voltages provided to the P-channel FET and the N-channel FET in the DUT <b>100</b>, respectively. Thus, the test apparatus <b>10</b> can detect properly an error in the switching speed of the circuit <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Further, the substrate voltage setting units <b>122</b><i>a </i>and <b>122</b><i>b </i>may detect an error or errors in the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b> and the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> in single test by setting the P-channel side and the N-channel side substrate voltages VBBp<b>1</b> and VBBn<b>1</b> at the same time and setting the P-channel side and the N-channel side substrate voltages VBBp<b>2</b> and VBBn<b>2</b> at the same time.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows an example of the configuration of the test apparatus <b>10</b> according to an alternative embodiment of the present invention. The test apparatus <b>10</b> according to the present embodiment acquires a boundary value of the substrate voltage in case of setting a predetermined clock interval to the clock interval from the time when a clock signal is provided to the FF <b>200</b> to the time when a clock signal is provided to the FF <b>210</b> and detects an error in the switching speed of the DUT <b>100</b> based on the boundary value. Since the elements indicated by the same reference numerals as those of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> have the same functions and configurations as those of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, explanation on the elements with the exception of differences is omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">The delay time measuring unit <b>650</b> includes a first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>and a second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b</i>. The first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>sets the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to Tp<b>1</b> using the clock setting unit <b>110</b>. Then, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>changes the substrate voltage VBBP by the threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> and measures a boundary value VBBp<b>1</b> of the substrate voltage at which the circuit <b>220</b> properly operates, when the clock interval is set to Tp<b>1</b>. Similarly, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>sets the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to Tn<b>1</b> using the clock setting unit <b>110</b>. Then, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>changes the substrate voltage VBBn by the threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> and measures a boundary value VBBn<b>1</b> of the substrate voltage at which the circuit <b>220</b> properly operates when the clock interval is set to Tn<b>1</b>. Here, in case of using a value T<b>1</b> as the clock interval Tp<b>1</b> and Tn<b>1</b>, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>may change the substrate voltages VBBp and VBBn by the threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> and measure the boundary values VBBn<b>1</b> and VBBn<b>1</b> of the substrate voltage when the clock interval is set to T<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">In a similar way to the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a</i>, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b </i>sets the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to Tp<b>2</b> using the clock setting unit <b>110</b>. Then, in a similar way to the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a</i>, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b </i>changes the substrate voltage VBBp and/or VBBn by the threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> and measures a boundary value VBBp<b>2</b> and/or VBBn<b>2</b> of the substrate voltage at which the circuit <b>220</b> properly operates, when the clock interval is set to Tp<b>2</b> and/or Tn<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The error detecting unit <b>160</b> detects an error in the switching speed of the circuit <b>220</b> based on the first boundary value of the substrate voltage VBBp and/or VBBn when the clock interval is set to Tp<b>1</b> and/or Tn<b>1</b> and the second boundary value of the substrate voltage VBBp and/or VBBn when the clock interval is set to Tp<b>2</b> and/or Tn<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a flow of an operation of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the alternative embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">In case of detecting a delay error in the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>first instructs the clock setting unit <b>110</b> to set the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to the first clock interval Tp<b>1</b>. In response, the clock setting unit <b>110</b> sets the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to Tp<b>1</b> (S<b>700</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Then, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>changes the substrate voltage VBBp by the threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> while the clock interval is set to Tp<b>1</b>. Then, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>625</b><i>a </i>performs a test on a logic path including the FF <b>220</b>, the circuit <b>220</b> and the FF <b>210</b> for each time when the substrate voltage VBBp is changed. By this, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>measures the first boundary value VBBp<b>1</b> of the substrate voltage for the normal operation of the circuit <b>220</b> (S<b>710</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Then, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b </i>instructs the clock setting unit <b>110</b> to set the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to the second clock interval Tp<b>2</b>. In response, the clock setting unit <b>110</b> sets the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to Tp<b>2</b> (S<b>720</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Then, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b </i>changes the substrate voltage VBBp by the threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> while the clock interval is set to Tp<b>2</b>. Then, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>625</b><i>b </i>performs a test on a logic path including the FF <b>220</b>, the circuit <b>220</b> and the FF <b>210</b> for each time when the substrate voltage VBBp is changed. By this, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b </i>measures the second boundary value VBBp<b>2</b> of the substrate voltage for the normal operation of the circuit <b>220</b> (S<b>730</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Then, the error detecting unit <b>160</b> detects an error in the switching speed of the circuit <b>220</b> caused by an error in the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> based on the first and second boundary values VBBp<b>1</b> and VBBp<b>2</b> (S<b>740</b>). In more detail, in case of testing the DUT <b>100</b> with ΔTd made constant, it is possible to detect an error in the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b> when the difference ΔVBB between the first and second boundary values VBBp<b>1</b> and VBBp<b>2</b> is smaller than a predetermined reference value.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">On the other hand, in case of detecting a delay error in the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>250</b>, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>first instructs the clock setting unit <b>110</b> to set the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to the first clock interval Tn<b>1</b>. In response, the clock setting unit <b>110</b> sets the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to Tn<b>1</b> (S<b>700</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Then, as in case of detecting the delay error of the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>changes the substrate voltage VBBn by the threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> while the clock interval is set to Tn<b>1</b>, and performs a test. Then, the first boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>a </i>measures the first boundary value VBBn<b>1</b> of the substrate voltage for the normal operation of the circuit <b>220</b> (S<b>710</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">Then, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b </i>instructs the clock setting unit <b>110</b> to set the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to the second clock interval Tn<b>2</b>. In response, the clock setting unit <b>110</b> sets the clock interval of the DUT <b>100</b> to Tn<b>2</b> (S<b>720</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">Then, like the case of detecting the delay error of the pre-stage N-channel FET <b>260</b>, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b </i>changes the substrate voltage VBBn by the threshold voltage setting unit <b>120</b> while the clock interval is set to Tn<b>2</b>, and performs a test. Then, the second boundary value measuring unit <b>652</b><i>b </i>measures the second boundary value VBBn<b>2</b> of the substrate voltage for the normal operation of the circuit <b>220</b> (S<b>730</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Then, the error detecting unit <b>160</b> detects an error in the switching speed of the circuit <b>220</b> caused by an error in the pre-stage P-channel FET <b>260</b> based on the first and second boundary values VBBp<b>1</b> and VBBp<b>2</b> (S<b>740</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">As described above, according to the test apparatus <b>10</b> of the present alternative embodiment, it is possible to detect a delay failure of the N-channel FET in the DUT <b>100</b> based on the boundary value of the substrate voltage provided to the P-channel FET in the DUT <b>100</b>, and a delay failure of the P-channel FET in the DUT <b>100</b> based on the boundary value of the substrate voltage provided to the N-channel FET in the DUT <b>100</b>. By this, the test apparatus <b>10</b> can detect an error in the switching speed of the circuit <b>220</b> properly.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">Further, the first and second boundary value measuring units <b>652</b><i>a </i>and <b>652</b><i>b </i>may detect an error or errors in the pre-stage P-channel and N-channel FET's <b>250</b> and <b>260</b> through the same test by setting the substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>a </i>to the P-channel side substrate voltage VBBp<b>1</b> and the N-channel side substrate voltage VBBn<b>1</b> at the same time and setting the substrate voltage setting unit <b>122</b><i>b </i>to the P-channel side substrate voltage VBBp<b>2</b> and the N-channel side substrate voltage at the same time.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows another example of the configuration of the DUT <b>100</b> according to the present embodiment. According to the present embodiment, the DUT <b>100</b> includes the FF's <b>200</b> and <b>210</b>, a circuit <b>220</b> to which a plurality of logic elements <b>800</b> are coupled and provided between the FF's <b>200</b> and <b>210</b>, a connection switching unit <b>810</b>, and a loop counting unit <b>820</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">The connection switching unit <b>810</b> includes switching units <b>812</b><i>a </i>and <b>812</b><i>b</i>, and forms an oscillating circuit including the circuit <b>220</b> by connecting the circuit <b>220</b> in a loop shape based on the instruction of the scan pattern generating unit <b>140</b> in case of the test apparatus <b>10</b> measuring the delay time of the circuit <b>220</b>. The loop counting unit <b>820</b> counts the number of repeated transmission of a signal input to the circuit <b>220</b> in the looped manner.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">For measuring the delay time, the setting vector generating unit <b>130</b> generates a setting vector for testing the circuit <b>220</b> and provides the signal terminal of the DUT <b>100</b> with the setting vector. Then, the scan pattern generating unit <b>140</b> generates the scan pattern used for a test for a delay failure of the circuit <b>220</b>, and provides the scan terminal of the DUT <b>100</b> with the scan pattern. When this scan pattern is input, the circuit <b>220</b> is coupled in looped manner by the connection switching unit <b>810</b> and a counting value of the loop counting unit <b>820</b> is initialized. Therefore, operation of the circuit <b>220</b> in the DUT <b>100</b> starts. As a result, the signal, which makes the circuit <b>220</b> operate, is input to the circuit <b>220</b>, and the circuit <b>220</b> transmits the signal in the looped manner and repeats the switching operation. The loop counting unit <b>820</b> measures the number of circulation of the signal in the circuit <b>220</b> by counting the number of the change of the output of the circuit <b>220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">Then, the first delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>a </i>stops counting of the loop counting unit <b>820</b> after a predetermined time from the start of the operation of the circuit <b>220</b>. Therefore, the first delay time measuring unit <b>152</b><i>a </i>acquires the delay time Tp<b>1</b> of the circuit <b>220</b> by dividing the predetermined time by the counting value of the loop counting unit <b>820</b>. Further, it is possible to acquire the delay time(s) Tn<b>1</b>, Tp<b>2</b> and/or Tn<b>2</b> by the same or similar method.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">According to the present embodiment, it is possible to acquire a delay time accurately without changing the clock interval for the logic path provided with a loop function.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">Although the present invention has been described by way of exemplary embodiments, it should be understood that those skilled in the art might make many changes and substitutions without departing from the spirit and the scope of the present invention which is defined only by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A test apparatus for testing switching speed of a combination circuit, where a level voltage based on a signal input from a first flip-flop (FF) is input to a second FF, comprising a pre-stage logic element outputting a first or second level voltage and a post-stage logic element to which the output signal of the pre-stage logic element is input, comprising:
<claim-text>a clock setting unit for setting a clock interval from the time when a clock signal is provided to the first FF to the time when a clock signal is provided to the second FF;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a threshold voltage setting unit for setting a threshold voltage of a post-stage field effect transistor (FET) to be different from that in a normal operation by setting a substrate voltage of the post-stage FET to have a value different from that in the normal operation of the circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first boundary value measuring unit for measuring a first boundary value of the substrate voltage for a normal operation of the circuit by changing the substrate voltage by said threshold voltage setting unit while the clock interval is set to the first clock interval; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an error detecting unit for detecting an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the first boundary value,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the post-stage logic element comprises the post-stage FET, a gate terminal of which the output signal is input to, for outputting a different level of voltage according to the case that the output signal voltage is higher or lower than a predetermined threshold voltage.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A test apparatus as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a second boundary value measuring unit for measuring a second boundary value of the substrate voltage for a normal operation of the circuit by changing the substrate voltage by said threshold voltage setting unit with the clock interval set to the second clock interval, wherein
<claim-text>said error detecting unit detects an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the first and second boundary values.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A test method for testing switching speed of a combination circuit, where a level voltage based on a signal input from a first flip-flop (FF) is input to a second FF, comprising a pre-stage logic element outputting a first or second level voltage and a post-stage logic element to which the output signal of the pre-stage logic element is input, wherein
<claim-text>said post-stage logic element comprises a post-stage field effect transistor (FET), the output signal being input to a gate terminal of said post-stage FET, for outputting a different level of voltage according to the case that the output signal voltage is higher or lower than a predetermined threshold voltage, the test method comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a clock setting step of setting a clock interval from the time when a clock signal is provided to the first FF to the time when a clock signal is provided to the second FF;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a threshold voltage setting step of setting a threshold voltage of said post-stage FET to be different from that in a normal operation by setting a substrate voltage of the post-stage FET to have a value different from that in the normal operation of the circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first boundary value measuring step of measuring a first boundary value of the substrate voltage for a normal operation of the circuit by changing the substrate voltage in said threshold voltage setting step while the clock interval is set to the first clock interval; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an error detecting step of detecting an error in switching speed of the circuit based on the first boundary value.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
