<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296661-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296661</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11165228</doc-number>
<date>20050624</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>66</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>187266</main-classification>
<further-classification>187256</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Elevator levelling</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>610256</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Brown</name>
<date>18980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>187350</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2861449</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cohan</name>
<date>19581100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73 1201</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2891636</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Krieger et al.</name>
<date>19590600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>187253</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5018925</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ganser</name>
<date>19910500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>414240</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5119906</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kondratuk</name>
<date>19920600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>187253</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5533595</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Narumi et al.</name>
<date>19960700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>187266</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6193016</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hollowell et al.</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>187250</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6345695</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Fargo et al.</name>
<date>20020200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>187277</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6742628</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Bauer</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>187254</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>187256</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>187266</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Petricio Yaksic</last-name>
<first-name>Davor</first-name>
<address>
<street>La Colpa 681, Sector la Chimba, Casilla 902</street>
<city>Antofagasta</city>
<country>CL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>CL</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>CL</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wray</last-name>
<first-name>James Creighton</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hyra</last-name>
<first-name>Clifford D.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Cuomo</last-name>
<first-name>Peter M.</first-name>
<department>3654</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Pico</last-name>
<first-name>Eric E.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Elevators are maintained in level condition by four fixed ropes or cables passing diagonally across an elevator in angularly related opposite directions. The ropes extend from opposite corners of the elevator to fixed upper and lower ends. Moving the elevator causes equal and opposite changes in lengths of the portions of the ropes extending upward and downward from the pulleys on the elevator, keeping the elevator level.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="201.34mm" wi="131.23mm" file="US07296661-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="155.28mm" wi="180.76mm" file="US07296661-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="195.83mm" wi="141.39mm" file="US07296661-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="218.27mm" wi="178.82mm" file="US07296661-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="215.90mm" wi="134.54mm" file="US07296661-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Elevators are raised and lowered in guideways using cables which are called ropes. Rollers on the elevators move along the guideways, keeping the elevators centered.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Uneven loads in elevators tend to tip the elevators. Undesirable tipping is controlled by simple or complex mechanisms. Occasionally when riding an unevenly loaded elevator a passenger is aware of sounds related to roller and guideway contact, particularly when starting. The problem of controlling tipping is particularly acute with large room-sized elevators.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Needs exist to maintain elevators level with simple and easy-to-install equipment.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Elevators are maintained in level condition by four fixed ropes or cables passing diagonally across an elevator in angularly related opposite directions. The ropes extend from opposite corners of the elevator to fixed upper and lower ends. Moving the elevator causes equal and opposite changes in lengths of the portions of the ropes extending upward and downward from the pulleys on the elevator, keeping the elevator level.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">A preferred elevator levelling apparatus includes first and second rigidly connected cross beams extending at angles across an elevator. Eight pulleys on the beams include four pulleys on each beam. Paired pulleys are positioned on axles at opposite ends of each beam for freely rotating on the axles. four fixed ropes extend oppositely across the beams and upward and downward from opposite ends of the beams. Each beam has two oppositely extending ropes. Each rope extends downward from a fixed position near a top of an elevator guide around a first pulley, across the beam, around a second pulley and downward to a fixed position near a bottom of the elevator. Raising and lowering an elevator with the crossed beams, pulleys and ropes constrains the ends of the beams and the elevator for equal movement along the ropes and maintains the beams and elevator in constant relation with respect to horizontal.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A preferred elevator levelling apparatus uses an elevator having a rectangular planform. Pairs of pulleys are mounted near corners of the elevator. Ropes have upper ends fixed above the corners near an upper end of a guide and have lower ends fixed below diagonally opposite corners near a bottom of the guide. Each rope extends downward from its fixed upper end, passes around a pulley in one pair, extends diagonally across the elevator, passes around a pulley near a diagonally opposite corner of the elevator, and extends downward to its fixed lower end. Pairs of the ropes extend diagonally in opposite directions across the elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Preferably four ropes are used. Each of the four ropes is connected above a different corner of the elevator and extends downward and corner to corner across the elevator and around the pulleys and downward to its fixed position under a diagonally opposite corner of the bottom of the elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Stabilizing elevators for level operation fixes upper ends of ropes to diagonally opposite spaced positions above corners of an elevator. The ropes extend downward, and pass under and over pulleys at diagonally opposite corners of the elevator. Lower ends of the ropes are fixed to diagonally opposite and spaced anchor positions.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In one embodiment a vertical guideway has a rectangular cross-section, and each rope is connected to the anchor positions and to diagonally opposite upper frame positions.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Preferably an elevator has a rectangular planform. Four ropes extend downward to four corners of the elevator, across the elevator and to diagonally opposite anchors.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Eight pulleys and provided, two at each corner of the rectangular planform elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Brakes connected to the elevator and to the ropes or the pulleys retard or stop the elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Preferably the brakes are regenerative electric brakes.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In some embodiments, motors connected to the pulleys move the elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Preferably, rigidly connected rigid cross-beams are connected across the elevator and extend from corner to corner of the elevator, and the pulleys are mounted in pairs at ends of the rigid cross beams.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">These and further and other objects and features of the invention are apparent in the disclosure, which includes the above and ongoing written specification, with the claims and the drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic detail of a beam with four pulleys and two fixed ropes which constrain the beam to level up and down movements.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic detail of four fixed ropes and two rigidly interconnected crossed rigid beams for attaching to an elevator and constraining the elevator to level raisings and lowerings.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a prior art roller construction for rolling along a fixed channel or I-beam and resisting tipping of an elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic detail of an elevator moving in a guideway.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic detail of one embodiment of the invention showing a guide I-beam and a guide attached to an elevator with four fixed ropes passing diagonally across the elevator around pulleys at diagonal and spaced positions on the elevator.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic detail of a beam with four pulleys and two fixed ropes which constrain the beam to level up and down movements.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a beam <b>1</b> and two ropes <b>2</b> and <b>3</b> extending around pulleys <b>5</b>, <b>6</b> and <b>4</b>, <b>7</b> respectively on the beam. The rope extremities are held fixed.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Ropes <b>2</b> and <b>3</b> are fixed at opposite ends <b>9</b>, <b>10</b> and <b>8</b>, <b>11</b> respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The ropes and pulleys ensure that as beam <b>1</b> is raised or lowered, both ends of the beam must move equally. For example, moving the beam upward lengthens the portion <b>21</b> of rope <b>2</b> between fixed end <b>9</b> and pulley <b>5</b>, and shortens portion <b>33</b> of rope <b>3</b> between fixed end <b>8</b> and pulley <b>43</b>. Concurrently the lengthening of portion <b>21</b> shortens portion <b>23</b> of rope <b>2</b> between pulley <b>6</b> and fixed end <b>10</b>. At the same time, and by the same amount, portion <b>31</b> of rope <b>3</b> between pulley <b>7</b> and fixed end <b>11</b> is lengthened. All lengthenings and all shortenings of portions of the ropes are equal. The portions have equal changes or deltas, although changes to the upper portions <b>33</b>, <b>23</b> have opposite signs or directions than the equal but opposite changes to the lower portions <b>21</b>, <b>31</b>. The beam <b>1</b> is rigid.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Regenerative electric brakes <b>95</b> connected to the elevator and to the pulleys <b>4</b> and <b>6</b> retard or stop the elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> a second rigid beam <b>41</b> is diagonally rigidly attached to the first beam <b>1</b> by a rigid interconnection <b>35</b> and bolts <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Pulleys <b>44</b> and <b>45</b> at end <b>58</b> of beam <b>41</b> are similar to and function similarly to pulleys <b>4</b> and <b>5</b> at end <b>38</b> of beam <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Pulleys <b>46</b> and <b>47</b> at end <b>59</b> of beam <b>41</b> are similar to and function similarly to pulleys <b>6</b> and <b>7</b> at end <b>39</b> of beam <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Ropes <b>42</b> and <b>43</b> which pass around the pulleys on beams <b>41</b> are similar to and function similarly to ropes <b>2</b> and <b>3</b> which pass around the pulleys on beam <b>1</b>. Rope <b>42</b> is fixed at its upper end <b>50</b>, descends and passes around pulley <b>46</b>, extends across beam <b>41</b>, passes around pulley <b>45</b>, descends and is anchored and fixed at end <b>49</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">When the cross beams <b>41</b> and <b>1</b> are connected to an elevator, the elevator may be raised and lowered by cables attached to the central rigid interconnection <b>35</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Rope <b>43</b> is fixed at upper end <b>48</b> and passes around pulley <b>44</b>, across beam <b>41</b>, and around pulley <b>47</b>. End <b>51</b> is anchored.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Moving any part of the rigidly connected frame upward or downward causes the frame to move in a level condition.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a prior art roller construction for rolling along a fixed channel or I-beam and resisting tipping of an elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a prior art elevator guide system that uses two or more guide channels <b>61</b> or I-beams to guide rollers <b>63</b>, <b>64</b>, <b>67</b>, <b>68</b>, which rotate on a mount <b>62</b> on connectors <b>65</b> extending outward from an elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic detail of an elevator moving in a guideway.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> schematically shows a guideway <b>70</b> with beams <b>71</b>, <b>72</b> in which elevator <b>73</b> rides when hauled upward or lowered by cables <b>76</b>. The elevator is rigidified with rigid cross beams <b>74</b> between the floor <b>77</b> and ceiling <b>78</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic detail of one embodiment of the invention showing a guide I-beam and a guide attached to an elevator with four fixed ropes passing diagonally across the elevator around pulleys at diagonal and spaced positions on the elevator.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows an elevator <b>81</b> guided by a vertical I-beam guide <b>91</b> and a guide follower <b>92</b>. The elevator has a rigid upper frame forming a rectangular ceiling <b>83</b>, side walls <b>85</b> and floor <b>87</b>. Paired pulleys are mounted near upper corners of the rigid elevator box or roof or on crossed beams in, under or on the roof. The function of the ropes and pulleys is similar to that described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The elevator roof or base has fixed rigidly interconnected beams <b>1</b> and <b>41</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Pulleys <b>44</b> and <b>45</b> at end <b>58</b> of beam <b>41</b> are similar to and function similarly to pulleys <b>4</b> and <b>5</b> at end <b>38</b> of beam <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Pulleys <b>46</b> and <b>47</b> at end <b>59</b> of beam <b>41</b> are similar to and function similarly to pulleys <b>6</b> and <b>7</b> at end <b>39</b> of beam <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Ropes <b>42</b> and <b>43</b> which pass around the pulleys on beams <b>41</b> are similar to and function similarly to ropes <b>2</b> and <b>3</b> which pass around the pulleys on beam <b>1</b>. Rope <b>42</b> is fixed at its upper end <b>50</b>, descends and passes around pulley <b>46</b>, extends across beam <b>41</b>, passes around pulley <b>45</b>, descends and is anchored and fixed at end <b>49</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">When the cross beams <b>41</b> and <b>1</b> are connected to an elevator, the elevator may be raised and lowered by cables attached to the central rigid interconnection <b>35</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Rope <b>43</b> is fixed at upper end <b>48</b> and passes around pulley <b>44</b>, across beam <b>41</b>, and around pulley <b>47</b>. End <b>51</b> is anchored.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Moving any part of the rigidly connected frame upward or downward causes the frame to move in a level condition.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The elevator is raised or lowered by a series of cables <b>93</b> attached centrally to the elevator, or riding in cable guides along sides or corners, if the guideway is formed in a reinforced rectangular cross-section.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The pulleys may be driven by electric motors or brakes regeneratively or mechanically to control elevator movement.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">While the invention has been described with reference to specific embodiments, modifications and variations of the invention may be constructed without departing from the scope of the invention, which is defined in the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. Elevator levelling apparatus, comprising an elevator, first and second rigidly connected cross beams extending at angles across the elevator, eight pulleys on the beams, including four pulleys on each beam, the pulleys further comprising paired pulleys positioned on axles at opposite ends of each beam for freely rotating on the axles, four fixed ropes extending oppositely across the beams upward and downward from opposite ends of the beams, each beam having two oppositely extending ropes, each rope extending downward from a fixed position near a top of an elevator guide around a first pulley, across the beam, around a second pulley and downward to a fixed position near a bottom of the elevator, whereby raising and lowering an elevator with the crossed beams, pulleys and ropes constrains the ends of the beams and the elevator for equal movement along the ropes and maintains the beams and elevator in constant relation with respect to horizontal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. Elevator levelling apparatus, comprising an elevator having a rectangular planform, pairs of pulleys mounted near corners of the elevator, an elevator guide, ropes having upper ends fixed above the corners near an upper end of the guide and having lower ends fixedly secured below diagonally opposite corners near a bottom of the guide, each rope extending downward from its fixed upper end, passing around a pulley in one pair, extending diagonally across the elevator, passing around a pulley near a diagonally opposite corner of the elevator, and extending downward to its fixed lower end, pairs of the ropes extending diagonally in opposite directions across the elevator, further comprising a pair of rigidly connected rigid cross beams being connected diagonally across the elevator and extending from corner to corner across the elevator, and wherein the pulleys are mounted in pairs at the ends of the rigid cross beams.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the ropes comprise four ropes and the guide comprises a rectangular guideway with four corners at the top and the bottom of the guideway, wherein each of the four ropes is connected near a different corner of the top and extends downward, corner to corner across the elevator and around the pulleys and downward to its fixed position near a diagonally opposite corner of the bottom of the guideway.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of stabilizing elevators for level operation, comprising providing an elevator, fixing upper ends of ropes to diagonally opposite spaced positions above corners of an elevator, extending the ropes downward, passing the ropes under first pulleys at diagonally opposite corners of an elevator, extending the ropes in diagonally opposite spaced directions across the elevator, passing the ropes around second pulleys at diagonally opposite spaced corners of the elevator, extending the ropes downward, and fixedly securing lower ends of the ropes to diagonally opposite and spaced anchor positions, further comprising providing a pair of rigidly connected rigid cross beams being connected diagonally across the elevator and extending from corner to corner across the elevator, and wherein the pulleys are mounted in pairs at the ends of the rigid cross beams.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising providing a vertical guideway having a rectangular cross-section, and connecting the anchor positions and the upper frame to the guideway.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the providing the elevator comprises providing an elevator with a rectangular planform, wherein the providing of the ropes further comprises providing four ropes, and wherein the extending the ropes downward comprises extending the ropes downward to four corners of the elevator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising providing eight pulleys, two at each corner of the rectangular planform elevator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising providing brakes connected to the elevator and to the ropes or the pulleys for retarding or stopping the elevator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the brakes are regenerative electric brakes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, further comprising providing motors connected to the pulleys for moving the elevator.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
