<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298562-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298562</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11273005</doc-number>
<date>20051114</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-255040</doc-number>
<date>20050902</date>
</priority-claim>
<priority-claim sequence="02" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2005-314565</doc-number>
<date>20051028</date>
</priority-claim>
<priority-claim sequence="03" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2006-078343</doc-number>
<date>20060322</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359819</main-classification>
<further-classification>359822</further-classification>
<further-classification>359823</further-classification>
<further-classification>359824</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e97">Lens drive unit</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0012090</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kawano</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>369 4416</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>11</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359819</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359811</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359813</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359818</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359815</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359822</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359824</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359826</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359821</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359823</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359 4415</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359 4411</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>359 4414</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>35944316</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4415</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4411</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4414</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>369 4416</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>15</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070053082</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070308</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sue</last-name>
<first-name>Takeshi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nagano</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ootsuki</last-name>
<first-name>Noboru</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nagano</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Reed Smith LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nidec Sankyo Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Nagano</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Mack</last-name>
<first-name>Ricky</first-name>
<department>2873</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Thomas</last-name>
<first-name>Brandi</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Lens drive unit is provided with a moving lenticular body (sleeve <b>15</b>, etc.) equipped with a lens, a driving mechanism to move the moving lenticular body in the optical axis direction of the lens and a fixed body (yoke <b>16</b>, etc.) that supports the moving lenticular body so as to make it movable in the optical axis direction of the lens. The driving mechanism is provided with magnet <b>17</b> magnetized in the direction perpendicular to the optical axis direction of the lens, and multiple coils (first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14′</b>) arranged so that the magnet is present in the optical axis direction of the lens. Either one of the magnet and the multiple coils is installed in the moving lenticular body, and the other in the fixed body. The driving mechanism is provided with a controlling element (flat spring <b>13, 13′</b>) to control the movement of the moving lenticular body caused by the electromagnetic force when a current is supplied to the multiple coils to generate the electromagnetic force, and magnetic member <b>30</b> is attracted to magnet <b>17</b> and is arranged on the opposite side of magnetic member <b>30</b> so as to sandwich one of the multiple coils between magnetic member <b>30</b> and magnet <b>17. </b></p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="112.18mm" wi="292.78mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="229.45mm" wi="177.80mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="249.68mm" wi="142.75mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="237.66mm" wi="164.59mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="231.39mm" wi="140.04mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="240.37mm" wi="161.46mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="216.41mm" wi="123.78mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="240.37mm" wi="146.30mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="234.53mm" wi="140.46mm" file="US07298562-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a lens drive unit which displaces and drives the lens in the optical axis direction to form the image of a subject.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">In recent years, as camera-attached cell phones to which cameras are mounted became widespread, photographing various subjects with the cell phones has been done with increasing frequency. For example, pictures of subjects separated from the camera lens at a certain degree, such as friends or landscapes, may be taken (regular photographing), or pictures of subjects positioned closely at the camera lens, such as bus schedules or petals, may be taken (tight close-up photographing).</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In the case of tight close-up photographing (macro photographing), the camera lens must be placed at a position slightly closer to the subject side than the position of the lens during the ordinary photographing. Consequently, this type of photographing lens is equipped with a driving mechanism to displace and drive the lens in the optical axis direction, and this driving mechanism is driven by changing the switch so that the lens can be moved in the optical axis direction.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The lens drive unit disclosed in Japanese Kokai Patent 2005-37865 comprises a moving body equipped with a lens, and a fixed body which moves this moving body in the optical axis direction of the lens and, at the time, holds the moving body; a drive magnet is installed in the moving body and a drive coil and two yokes are installed in the fixed body. And, when energization of the drive coil is stopped, the magnetic adsorption between the drive magnet and the yoke is utilized to hold the moving body at a position close to any of the above-mentioned two yokes. Hence, this lens drive unit has such advantages as a simple construction, few parts and suitability for miniaturization.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The lens drive unit disclosed in Japanese Patent Application Publication 2005-128392 moves a lens support body along the optical axis direction of the lens by electromagnetic force generated by supplying a current to coils. And in the absence of an electric current supplied to coils, two springs energizes (presses) the lens support body against the base. Under this condition, when the camera is not in use, the lens support body is unlikely to experience shaking or loosening.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">On the other hand, the lens drive unit disclosed in Japanese Patent Application Publication 2005-165058 moves a lens holder along the optical axis direction of the lens caused by means of the electromagnetic force when a current is supplied to coils. It comprises a holder contact section to control the motion of lens holder and a holder spring to energize the lens holder. The holder contact section controls the range within which the lens holder can move excluding the neutral position where the holder spring is in the neutral state. In this way, the holder spring constantly applies its force to the lens holder, thereby improving shock resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">However, since the lens drive unit disclosed in Japanese Patent Application Publication 2005-128392 and Japanese Patent Application Publication 2005-165058 holds the lens unit (the lens support component or the lens holder mentioned above) by relying on the energizing force of the spring as described above, unstabilizing alignment accuracy becomes unstable; this is a problem.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">That is, generally strains or burrs occur in springs made by press processing, and variations in spring constants result in unstable alignment accuracy. On the contrary, springs made by etching can reduce variations in spring constants to a certain degree; however, this type provides poor productivity, thus increasing manufacturing costs.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The present invention was made in view of the above problems, and its objective is to provide a lens drive unit which can stabilize stationary position accuracy of the lens unit.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In order to solve the above problems, the present invention provides the following.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A lens drive unit characterized by the fact that it comprises a moving lenticular body equipped with a lens, a driving mechanism to move said moving lenticular body in the optical axis direction of the lens and a fixed body that supports said moving lenticular body so as to make it movable in the optical axis direction of the lens; said driving mechanism is provided with a magnet and multiple coils arranged so that said magnet is present in the optical axis direction of the lens; either one of said magnet and said multiple coils is installed in said moving lenticular body, and the other in said fixed body; wherein said driving mechanism also comprises a controlling means to control the movement of said moving lenticular body caused by the electromagnetic force when a current is supplied to said multiple coils to generate said electromagnetic force, and a magnetic member arranged on the opposite side of said magnet to be attracted to said magnet while sandwiching one of said multiple coils between said magnetic member and said magnet.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to the present invention, the lens drive unit comprises a moving lenticular body equipped with a lens, a driving mechanism to move the moving lenticular body with a magnet and multiple coils, and a fixed body that supports the moving lenticular body. Either one of the magnet and the multiple coils is installed in the moving lenticular body; the other in the fixed body. The driving mechanism also comprises a controlling means to control the movement of the moving lenticular body caused by the electromagnetic force, and a magnetic member arranged on the opposite side of the magnet to be attracted to the magnet while sandwiching one of the multiple coils. Thus, the magnetic attraction acts between the magnetic member and the magnet via coils.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">As a result, during macro photographing, for example, the moving lenticular body is held at an appropriate position by the balance between the electromagnetic force generated by multiple coils and the controlling force caused by the controlling means. On the other hand, during normal photographing (or a camera is not in use), for example, the moving lenticular body can be held by the magnetic attraction acting between a magnetic member and a magnet. Unlike the conventional lens drive unit mentioned above, the present invention in particular holds a moving lenticular body without relying on the energizing force of a spring but by relying on the highly stable magnetic attraction. In this way, the stationary position accuracy of a moving lenticular body varies less and stabilized. In addition, since there is no need for manufacturing the spring for holding a moving lenticular body; this contributes a reduction in manufacturing costs.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Here, the meaning of “control means” used in the present invention is a means to generate a force in the direction opposite to the direction of the moving lenticular body movement; it is preferable that the force vary in accordance with the amount of the moving lenticular body movement. For example, it may be a flat spring, coil spring, magnet spring or an elastic member such as rubber or the like. Moreover, it may be a substance in which a magnet of the N pole (S pole) is set up in the fixed body, a magnet of the N pole (S pole) is set up in the moving lenticular body, and both magnetic repulsive forces are utilized. It does not matter what the type is.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Moreover, the “magnetic member” as defined in the present invention may be any member that generates some degree of magnetic attraction in the presence of a magnet. For example, even if a member is generally known for its non-magnetic characteristic, it may be included in the “magnetic member” as long as a small degree of magnetic attraction occurs in the presence of a magnet. Moreover, there is no restriction with respect to the shape, type, and size of the “magnetic member”.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The lens drive unit as set forth in characterized by the fact that said magnetic member has a circular shape and is arranged along the same axis as the optical axis of the lens.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">According to the present invention, since the magnetic component mentioned above is formed in a circular shape and arranged along the same axis as the optical axis of the lens, the magnetic attraction can be generated between the magnetic member and the magnet stably, thus stabilizing the stationary position accuracy of the moving lenticular body.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In other words, for example, in the case in which small pieces of magnetic members are spread along the circumferential direction of a coil, a certain spacing arrangement causes magnetic attractions acting between magnetic members and the magnet to vary; this affects stabilization of stationary position accuracy of the moving lenticular body. However, according to the present invention, circular magnetic members are arranged along the same axis as the optical axis of the lens in the present invention; as a result, the magnetic attractions do not vary between the magnetic members and a magnet. Hence, it is possible to generate magnetic attraction stably at all points along the circumferential direction of the coil, thereby stabilizing the stationary position accuracy of a moving lenticular body.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The lens drive unit can also be provided with a magnetic member that is arranged on the opposite side of said magnet in such a manner that, among said multiple coils, the coil on the subject side is sandwiched between said magnetic member and said magnet.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">According to the present invention, the above mentioned magnetic member is arranged on the opposite side of the magnet while sandwiching one of the multiple coils on the subject side (Namely, this is the coil on the side toward which the moving lenticular body moves during macro photographing) between the magnetic member and the magnet. As a result, during normal photographing (or when the camera is not in use), the moving lenticular body can be held by the magnetic attraction acting between the magnetic member and the magnet, thereby stabilizing stationary position accuracy of the moving lenticular body.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">A lens drive unit characterized by the fact that it comprises a moving lenticular body equipped with a lens, a driving mechanism to move said moving lenticular body in the optical axis direction of the lens and a fixed body that supports said moving lenticular body so as to make it movable in the optical axis direction of the lens; said driving mechanism is provided with a magnet and multiple coils arranged so that said magnet is present in the optical axis direction of the lens; either one of said magnet and said multiple coils is installed in said moving lenticular body, and the other in said fixed body; and said driving mechanism is provided with a controlling means to control the movement of said moving lenticular body caused by the electromagnetic force when a current is supplied to said multiple coils to generate said electromagnetic force and, at the same time, said controlling means is a member to be magnetically attracted to said magnet.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">According to the present invention, the lens drive unit comprises a moving lenticular body equipped with a lens, a driving mechanism to move the moving lenticular body with a magnet and multiple coils, and a fixed body that supports the moving lenticular body so as to make it movable in the optical axis direction of the lens. either one of the magnet and the multiple coils is installed in the moving lenticular body, and the other in the fixed body; and the driving mechanism is provided with a controlling means to control the movement of the moving lenticular body caused by the electromagnetic force and is attracted to the magnet. As a result, magnetic attractions act between the controlling means and the magnet via coils.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Accordingly, during normal photographing (or when the camera is not in use), for example, a moving lenticular body can be held without relying on the energizing force of a spring but by relying on the highly stable magnetic attraction. As a result, the stationary position accuracy of a moving lenticular body varies less, and what is more, it can be stabilized.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">(5) The lens drive unit as set forth in (4) characterized by that said controlling means comprises a first elastic member to energize said moving lenticular body in one of the optical axis directions, a second elastic member to energize in the opposite direction of said first direction wherein either said first elastic member or said second elastic member is the member to be electromagnetically attracted to the magnet.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">According to the present invention, the above-mentioned controlling means comprises a first elastic member to energize the moving lenticular body in one of the optical axis directions of the lens and a second elastic member to energize the moving lenticular body in the direction opposite to the above such that one of the elastic members can be magnetically attracted to a magnet. As a result, the magnetic attraction acts, for example, between the first elastic member and the magnet.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Therefore, between the first elastic member and the second elastic member (for example, the first elastic member), by making the elastic member on the subject side attracted to the magnet, the moving lenticular body can be held by relying on the highly stable magnetic attraction during normal photographing (or when the camera is not in use). As a result, the stationary position accuracy of the moving lenticular body varies less, and what is more, it can be stabilized.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">According to the lens drive unit associated with the present invention, for example, during normal photographing (or the camera is not in use), the moving lenticular body can be held by relying on the highly stable magnetic attraction. As a result, the stationary position accuracy of the moving lenticular body varies less, and what is more, it can be stabilized.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a cross section of the lens drive unit of one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a three-dimensional view of the assembly of the lens drive unit in one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates the state in which a sleeve is held in a lens drive unit;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates an outline of an alternative lens drive unit of another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows an outline of the lens drive unit of the another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is illustrates an outline of the lens drive unit of a third embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows an outline of the lens drive unit of a fourth embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a across sectional drawing to illustrate the machine construction of lens drive unit <b>10</b> of the first mode of embodiment of the present invention. To be more specific, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>a</i>) is a cross sectional drawing of lens drive unit <b>10</b> that is cut in the direction of optical axis X of the lens. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>b</i>) is a plane cross sectional drawing when lens drive unit <b>10</b> as illustrated in the cross sectional drawing of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>a</i>) is cut along A–A′ alternate long and short dash line. Moreover, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>a</i>), for convenience of description the top is the front side close to the subject.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, lens drive unit <b>10</b> is mainly composed of cover holder <b>1</b> corresponding to a part of the fixed body and sleeve <b>15</b> corresponding to a part of the moving lenticular body. Attached to the inside of sleeve <b>15</b> is roughly cylindrical lens barrel <b>12</b> wherein optical axis X is positioned in the center (Not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). The inside of lens barrel <b>12</b> is equipped with lens <b>12</b> <i>a </i>(See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Moreover, lens <b>12</b> <i>a </i>is generally composed of a combination of multiple lenses.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Cover holder <b>11</b> can be fitted in holder receiver <b>19</b> (See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Thus, fixed is cylindrical yoke <b>16</b>. Ring-shaped magnet <b>17</b> is fastened to the inner periphery of this yoke <b>16</b>. Namely, magnet <b>17</b> is fastened to yoke <b>16</b> so as to protrude to the inside from the inner periphery of yoke <b>16</b> (See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), and magnetized in the direction perpendicular to the optical axis X direction. Moreover, yoke <b>16</b> is composed of a ferromagnetic material such as a steel plate or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Ring-shaped first coil <b>14</b> is fastened to the front side of the outer periphery of sleeve <b>15</b>, and ring-shaped second coil <b>14</b>′ is fastened to the rear side. Namely, in the outer periphery of sleeve <b>15</b>, first coil <b>14</b> is arranged on the front side from magnet <b>17</b> so as to face this magnet <b>17</b>, and second oil <b>14</b>′ is arranged so that magnet <b>17</b> is present in the direction of optical axis X due to the relationship with this first coil <b>14</b>. As a result, the rear end of first coil <b>14</b> faces the front and of magnet <b>17</b>, and the front end of second coil <b>14</b>′ faces the rear end of magnet <b>17</b>. Moreover, first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ which are fastened to sleeve <b>15</b> are able to perform a relative displacement in the direction of optical axis X with respect to yoke <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The magnetic flux from the N pole of magnet <b>17</b> passes through sleeve <b>15</b>, first coil <b>14</b> and yoke <b>16</b> to return to magnet <b>17</b> again. Moreover, the magnetic flux from the N pole of magnet <b>17</b> passes through sleeve <b>15</b>, second coil <b>14</b>′ and yoke <b>16</b>, for example, to return to magnet <b>17</b> again. Therefore, a magnetic circuit (magnetic path) is formed by the members comprising first coil <b>14</b>, second coil <b>14</b>′, yoke <b>16</b> and sleeve <b>15</b>. In this case, a magnetic material is preferably employed for the material of sleeve <b>15</b>. Moreover, sleeve <b>15</b> can also be removed from the material that makes up the magnetic circuit (magnetic path).</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The distance between the opposed surfaces of first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ is greater than the thickness of magnet <b>17</b> in the direction of optical axis X. There is a gap between magnet <b>17</b> and first coil <b>14</b> (or second coil <b>14</b>′), and sleeve <b>15</b> integrated with first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ can be moved in the direction of optical axis X within the range of this gap. The length of yoke <b>16</b> in the direction of optical axis X is made greater than the distance between the opposed surfaces of first coil and second coil <b>14</b>′. By doing so, the leakage flux leaked out from the magnetic path between magnet <b>17</b> and first coil <b>14</b> (or second coil <b>14</b>′) can be reduced, and the linearity between the movement amount of sleeve <b>15</b> and the current supplied to first coil <b>14</b> (and second coil <b>14</b>′) can be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Installed in the center of the front side of cover holder <b>11</b> is circular entrance window <b>18</b> which is for taking in the reflected light from the subject to lens <b>12</b> <i>a </i>(See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>).</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Lens drive unit <b>10</b> is provided with the flat spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′ to control the movement of sleeve <b>15</b>. Here, flat spring <b>13</b>′ is described in detail with reference to as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>a</i>). In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>b</i>), flat spring <b>13</b>′ attached to holder receiver <b>19</b> is engaged with antirotation groove <b>19</b><i>a</i>, thereby preventing flat spring <b>13</b>′ from rotating.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Flat spring <b>13</b>′ is a metal-made spring to supply a current, and the rear end of sleeve <b>15</b> is mounted to innermost circumferential part <b>13</b>′ a. In addition, terminal <b>13</b>′ b for energizing second coil <b>14</b>′ is formed in three places in circumferential part <b>13</b>′ a (See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>b</i>)) and a current can be supplied to second coil <b>14</b>′ via terminal <b>13</b>′ b.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Moreover, while the detailed description is omitted here, a terminal for energizing first coil <b>14</b> is also formed in flat spring <b>13</b> in the same way as flat spring <b>13</b>, and a current can be supplied to first coil <b>14</b> through its terminal. Thus, flat spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′ can be allowed to function as the wiring for energizing first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′. By extension, the circuit construction (circuit wiring) of lens drive unit <b>10</b> can be made easy, and miniaturization of whole lens drive unit can be undertaken.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In the present embodiment, wiring <b>20</b> for energizing first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ is installed in sleeve <b>15</b> (See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>a</i>)) thereby enabling the current supplied to first coil <b>14</b> to become equal to the current supplied to second coil <b>14</b>′, and controlling the current becomes easy.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">By the use of lens drive unit composed of such a construction, the elastic force due to flat spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′ can be utilized to stop sleeve <b>15</b> (to which first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ are fastened) at a desired position. This stopping operation is described in detail in “stopping operation” that is described later.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Now, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>a</i>), in the lens drive unit <b>10</b>, circular magnetic member <b>30</b> is arranged on the opposite side of magnet <b>17</b> sandwiching first coil <b>14</b> between circular magnetic member <b>30</b> and magnet <b>17</b>. Moreover, magnetic component <b>30</b> is arranged along the same axis as the optical axis X. This enables sleeve <b>15</b> to be held by the magnetic attraction acting between magnetic member <b>30</b> and magnet <b>17</b>. This holding operation is described in detail in the in the [Holding Operation] section described later. Next, a method for assembling lens drive unit <b>10</b> is described.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a disassembled three-dimensional view for explaining the assembly method for the lens drive unit of the present invention. The same assembly method can also be adopted for lens drive unit <b>10</b> A of another embodiment of the present invention which is described later. Moreover, first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ should be fastened to the outside of sleeve <b>15</b> in advance and, at the same, lens barrel <b>12</b> having lens <b>12</b> <i>a </i>should be preinstalled inside sleeve <b>15</b>. In addition, magnet <b>17</b> should be fastened in advance to the inner periphery of yoke <b>16</b>. Moreover, a crevice is present in the direction of optical axis X in magnet <b>17</b> and yoke <b>16</b>, and they become dividable into two pieces.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, first, flat spring <b>13</b>′ is attached to holder receiver <b>19</b> so as to be engaged with antirotation groove <b>19</b> <i>a </i>formed in holder receiver <b>19</b>. Then, circular magnetic member <b>30</b> can be fastened to the upper edge (or top) of first coil <b>14</b>. At this stage, magnetic member <b>30</b> may be fastened to the upper edge sleeve <b>15</b>. Next, magnet <b>17</b> and yoke <b>16</b> are divided into two pieces, and magnet <b>17</b> and yoke <b>16</b> are integrated (fastening) again so that magnet <b>17</b> is present between second coil <b>14</b>′ and first coil <b>14</b> fastened to the outer periphery of sleeve <b>15</b>. Then yoke <b>16</b> inside which sleeve <b>15</b> is incorporated is fastened to holder receiver <b>19</b>. At this time, the rear end of sleeve <b>15</b> is mounted to the innermost side of circumferential part <b>13</b>′ of flat sprint <b>13</b>′ a. Finally, flat spring <b>13</b> is mounted so that its innermost circumferential part abuts on the front end of sleeve <b>15</b>. Thereafter, cover holder <b>11</b> is engaged with holder receiver <b>19</b>. Thus, lens drive unit <b>10</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>a</i>) can be assembled. Moreover, in flat spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′, a tongue is formed on the outside in the radial direction; this becomes the feeding part to the coil.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a drawing to describe the state of holding sleeve <b>15</b> at a desired position in lens drive unit <b>10</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>a</i>) and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>b</i>) shows the machine construction when the right half is viewed from optical axis X in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> (<i>a</i>). Magnet <b>17</b> is magnetized so that the inward radial direction becomes the N pole and the outward radial direction becomes the S pole.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>a</i>), the magnetic flux from the N pole of magnet <b>17</b> passes through in the sequence of sleeve <b>15</b>→first coil <b>14</b>→yoke <b>15</b> (See arrows of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>b</i>)). On the other hand, the magnetic flux from the N pole of magnet <b>17</b> passes through in the sequence of sleeve <b>15</b>→second coil <b>14</b>′→yoke <b>16</b>. In such a state, a current of the same direction is supplied to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′. In the present embodiment mode, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>c</i>), a current is supplied “frontward” from the “back” of the paper. Then, each of first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ which are placed in a magnetic field and are under energization is subjected to upward (front side) magnetic force FH (See arrows of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>c</i>)). Therefore, a magnetic circuit (magnetic path) is formed by the members comprising first coil <b>14</b>, second coil <b>14</b>′, yoke <b>16</b> and sleeve <b>15</b>. Thus, sleeve <b>15</b> fastened to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ begins to move forward.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Moreover, in the present embodiment mode, as mentioned above, wiring <b>20</b> for energization is installed in sleeve <b>15</b> and the current supplied to first coil <b>14</b> is made equal to the current supplied to second coil <b>14</b>′. As a result, approximately equal electromotive force FH is applied to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′. Moreover, since the size of lens drive unit <b>10</b> is very small (for instance, outer diameter about 10 mm×height about 5 mm), the magnetic flux passing through first coil <b>14</b> is considered roughly equal to the magnetic flux passing through second coil <b>14</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">At this time, a force to control the movement of sleeve <b>15</b> (elastic force FS<b>1</b>, elastic force FS<b>2</b>) is generated between flat spring <b>13</b> and the front end of sleeve <b>15</b>, and between flat spring <b>13</b>′ and the rear end of sleeve <b>15</b> (See arrows of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>d</i>)). Therefore, when electromagnetic fore FH+FH to move sleeve <b>15</b> forward and elastic force FS<b>1</b>+FS<b>2</b> to control the movement of sleeve <b>15</b> are in balance, sleeve <b>15</b> stops. Thus, sleeve <b>15</b> can be stopped at a desired position by adjusting the current amount to be supplied to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ and elastic force applied on sleeve <b>15</b> by first spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Furthermore, in the present embodiment mode, since flat spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′ in which a linear relationship between the elastic force (stress) and displacement amount (strain) is established are used, the linearity between the movement amount of sleeve <b>15</b> and the current supplied to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ can be improved. Moreover, since two elastic members comprising flat spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′ are used, when sleeve <b>15</b> stops a great force of balance is applied in the optical axis X direction and, even if other forces such as a centrifugal force and the like are applied in the optical axis X direction, sleeve <b>15</b> can be stopped more stably. Furthermore, in lens drive unit <b>10</b>, stoppage of sleeve <b>15</b> is not done by collision with a collision material (cushioning material); it is done by utilizing the balance between the electromagnetic force and elastic force. Hence generation of the collision sound can also be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">When the mode switches from macro photographing to the normal photographing (when the camera is not in use), lens drive unit <b>10</b> moves from the state shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>a</i>) to the state shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>b</i>). More concretely, when a current does not flow to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′, the previously described electromagnetic force FH does not act on first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′, so sleeve <b>15</b> returns to the original position due to the elastic forces FS<b>1</b> and FS<b>2</b> of flat spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′ respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">At this time, sleeve <b>15</b> is held by the magnetic forces Fm<b>1</b> and Fm<b>2</b> acting between magnetic member <b>30</b> and magnet <b>17</b> through first coil <b>14</b>. This prevents sleeve <b>15</b> from shaking and loosening. What is more, it suppresses variations of stationary position accuracy of lens <b>12</b><i>a</i>, lens barrel <b>12</b>, and the like during normal photographing (when the camera is not in use).</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Particularly, according to lens drive unit <b>10</b> associated with this embodiment, since magnetic member <b>30</b> has a circular shape and is arranged along the same axis as the optical axis X, magnetic attractions caused between magnetic member <b>30</b> and magnet <b>17</b> do not vary; as a result, magnetic attractions can be generated stably at all points in the circumferential direction of first coil <b>14</b>. Therefore, the stationary position accuracy of the moving lenticular body of lens <b>12</b><i>a</i>, lens barrel <b>12</b>, and the like can be better stabilized. In addition, the thickness of magnetic member <b>30</b> in the direction of the optical-axis X can be changed to various thicknesses in order to adjust the magnitude of magnetic attraction.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Moreover, in lens drive unit <b>10</b> associated with this embodiment, the outer diameter of magnetic component <b>30</b> is about the middle value between the inner diameter and the outer diameter of first coil <b>14</b> (See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> or <b>2</b>). In this way, the radial magnetic attraction between magnetic component <b>30</b> and a yoke <b>16</b> can be reduced, and what is more, it prevents the moving lenticular body such as lens <b>12</b><i>a </i>or lens barrel <b>12</b> from becoming off-centered from the optical axis X. In addition, in view of this, it can be said that it is desirable that the outer diameter of magnetic member <b>30</b> is smaller than the middle value mentioned above.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a drawing to illustrate an outline of the machine construction of lens drive unit <b>10</b> A of another embodiment mode of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, unlike lens drive unit <b>10</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> (<i>b</i>), in lens drive unit <b>10</b>A, the magnetic component <b>30</b> is eliminated, and flat spring <b>13</b> is used as the magnetic member magnetically attracted to magnet <b>17</b>. In this way, sleeve <b>15</b> is held by the magnetic attractions Fm<b>1</b> and Fm<b>2</b> that act between flat spring <b>13</b> and magnet <b>17</b> through first coil <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Thus, lens drive unit <b>10</b>A can prevent sleeve <b>15</b> from shaking and loosening, and what is more, it can suppress variations in the stationary position accuracy of lens <b>12</b><i>a</i>, lens barrel <b>12</b>, and the like during normal photographing (when the camera is not in use).</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">In addition, as described above, in view of the fact that flat spring <b>13</b> works as a terminal such that a current is supplied to first coil, it is desirable that its material is, for example, stainless steel of the copper type or phosphorous type.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a drawing to illustrate an outline of lens drive unit <b>10</b> A of one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, lens drive unit <b>10</b> A adopts coil spring <b>21</b> and coil spring <b>21</b>′, which is shorter than coil spring <b>21</b>, to control the movement of sleeve <b>15</b>. Thus even when flat spring <b>13</b> and flat spring <b>13</b>′ in lens drive unit <b>10</b> adjustment of the current amount supplied to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ can generate an appropriate elastic force to control and stop lens <b>12</b> <i>a </i>attached to sleeve <b>15</b> at a desired position. Moreover, it is also possible to use coil spring <b>21</b> and coil spring <b>21</b>′ for the wiring for energization. Moreover, although the length of coil spring <b>21</b>′ is made shorter than that of coil spring <b>21</b> in the present embodiment mode, it is because of the fact that the standard position of sleeve <b>15</b> is on the rear side. For instance, when the standard position of sleeve <b>15</b> is on the front side, coil spring <b>21</b> becomes shorter. Naturally, when the standard position of sleeve <b>15</b> is at the center both have the length.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a drawing to illustrate an outline of the machine construction of lens drive unit <b>10</b> B of yet another embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> (<i>a</i>), for lens drive unit <b>10</b> B, cylindrical case <b>22</b> is fixed with cover holder <b>11</b> and holder receiver <b>19</b>. Magnet <b>17</b> is fastened so as to protrude inward from the inner periphery of this case <b>22</b> and, at the time, yoke <b>16</b> is fastened to this magnet <b>17</b>. Thus the position of yoke <b>16</b> may be arranged inward in the radial direction from first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> (<i>b</i>), case <b>22</b> may be replaced with yoke <b>16</b> and yoke <b>16</b> may be arranged on both the outside in the radial direction and the inside in the radial direction with respect to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′. By doing so, the leakage flux leaked out from the magnetic path between first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ can be reduced, and the linearity between the movement amount of sleeve <b>15</b> and the current supplied to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ can be improved.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Moreover, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> (<i>b</i>), the length of yoke <b>16</b> (fastened to the N pole of magnet <b>17</b>) in the inside in the radial direction becomes shorter than that of yoke <b>16</b> (fastened to the S pole of magnet <b>17</b>) on the outside in the radial direction. The present invention, however, is not limited to this; for instance, the length of yoke <b>16</b> (fastened to the N pole of magnet <b>17</b>) in the inside in the radial direction may be made longer. Naturally, they may also have the length. However, as mentioned above, if the leakage flux is taken into consideration, it is desirable that they be formed so as to be at least longer than the distance between the opposed surfaces of first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Furthermore, in lens drive units <b>10</b>, both magnet <b>17</b> and yoke <b>16</b> are installed in either one of the moving lenticular body such as sleeve <b>15</b> or the like and the fixed body such as cover holder <b>11</b> or the like. Consequently, even if the moving lenticular body undergoes relative displacement with respect to the fixed body, the relative position relationship between magnet <b>17</b> and yoke remains unchanged, and the adverse influence caused by an attraction applied between magnet <b>17</b> and yoke <b>16</b> can be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">On the other hand, the present invention is not limited only to the case that the relative position relationship between magnet <b>17</b> and yoke <b>16</b> is non-changing. For example, it is also possible to consider lens drive unit <b>10</b> C shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a drawing to illustrate an outline of the machine construction of lens drive unit <b>10</b> of the fourth embodiment mode of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> (<i>a</i>), magnet <b>17</b> is fastened to sleeve <b>15</b> and, at the time, first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ are fastened to yoke <b>16</b> which is fixed with cover holder <b>11</b> and holder receiver <b>19</b>. As mentioned above, if the moving lenticular body to which magnet <b>17</b> is fastened moves in the optical axis direction X with respect to the fixed body to which yoke <b>16</b> is fastened, it is subjected to the adverse influence caused by attractions in the radial direction which is applied between magnet <b>17</b> and yoke <b>16</b>. On the other hand, since first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ are fastened to the fixed body instead of the moving lenticular body, there is an advantage that the wiring for energization does not become complicated. Additionally, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> (<i>a</i>), although yoke <b>16</b> is installed only on the outside in the radial direction with respect to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′, naturally it may also be arranged on both the outside in the radial direction and the inside in the radial direction (See <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> (<i>b</i>)). Moreover, as first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ are fastened to yoke <b>16</b> in lens drive unit <b>10</b> C, a force of reaction to the electromagnetic force applied to first coil <b>14</b> and second coil <b>14</b>′ acts on sleeve <b>15</b> and can move sleeve <b>15</b> in the optical axis X direction.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Lens drive units <b>10</b> as described above can be attached to various electronic instruments in addition to camera-attached cell phones. For instance, they are PHS, PDA, bar code readers, thin digital cameras, monitor cameras, cameras for confirming the rear side, doors having an optical certification function and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">While this invention has been described in conjunction with the specific embodiments outlined above, it is evident that many alternatives, modifications and variations will be apparent to those skilled in the art. Accordingly, the preferred embodiments of the invention as set forth above are intended to be illustrative, not limiting. Various changes may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as defined in the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A lens drive unit comprising:
<claim-text>a moving lenticular body equipped with a lens;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driving mechanism to move said moving lenticular body in the optical axis direction of the lens; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixed body that supports said moving lenticular body so as to make it movable in the optical axis direction of the lens;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein:
<claim-text>said driving mechanism is provided with a magnet magnetized in the direction perpendicular to the optical axis direction of the lens, and multiple coils arranged so that at least one coil of said multiple coils is arranged on one side in the optical axis direction with respect to said magnet and at least another one coil of said multiple coils is arranged on the other side in the optical axis direction with respect to said magnet, and said magnet is relatively moved so as to move towards and away from said one coil or said another one coil in the optical axis direction;</claim-text>
<claim-text>either one of said magnet and said multiple coils is installed in said moving lenticular body, and the other in said fixed body; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said driving mechanism is provided with a controlling means to control the movement of said moving lenticular body caused by the electromagnetic force when a current is supplied to said multiple coils to generate said electromagnetic force.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The lens drive unit as described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said controlling means is an elastic member energizing said moving lenticular body in the optical axis direction of the lens.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The lens drive unit as described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said elastic member comprises a first elastic member energizing said moving lenticular body in one direction of the optical axis directions of the lens, and a second elastic member energizing in the direction opposite to said one direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The lens drive unit as described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said first elastic member and said second elastic member are metal-made elastic members which allow said multiple coils to be energized.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The lens drive unit as described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said lens drive unit is further equipped with a yoke which changes the direction of the magnetic flux from said magnet;
<claim-text>and said yoke is formed in such a manner that its length in the optical axis direction of the lens becomes greater than the distance between two opposed surfaces of said multiple coils and, it is installed in said moving lenticular body and/or said fixed body.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The lens drive unit as described in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said magnet and said yoke are installed either in said moving lenticular body or in said fixed body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A lens drive unit comprising:
<claim-text>a moving lenticular body equipped with a lens;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driving mechanism to move said moving lenticular body in an optical axis direction of the lens; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixed body that supports said moving lenticular body so as to make it movable in the optical axis direction of the lens;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said driving mechanism is provided with a magnet and multiple coils arranged so that at least one coil of said multiple coils is arranged on one side in the optical axis direction with respect to said magnet and at least another one coil of said multiple coils is arranged on the other side in the optical axis direction with respect to said magnet, and said magnet is relatively moved so as to move towards and away from said one coil or said another one coil in the optical axis direction, and either one of said magnet and said multiple coils is installed in said moving lenticular body, and the other in said fixed body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said driving mechanism also comprises a controlling means to control the movement of said moving lenticular body caused by the electromagnetic force when a current is supplied to said multiple coils to generate said electromagnetic force, and a magnetic member arranged on the opposite side of said magnet so as to be attracted to said magnet and so as to sandwich one of said multiple coils between said magnetic member and said magnet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The lens drive unit as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein said magnetic member is formed in a circular shape and arranged along the axis as the optical axis of said lens.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The lens drive unit as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein, said magnetic member is arranged on the opposite side of said magnet in such a manner that, among said multiple coils, the coil on the subject side is sandwiched between said magnetic member and said magnet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A lens drive unit comprising:
<claim-text>a moving lenticular body equipped with a lens;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driving mechanism to move said moving lenticular body in the optical axis direction of the lens; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixed body that supports said moving lenticular body so as to make it movable in the optical axis direction of the lens;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said driving mechanism is provided with a magnet and multiple coils arranged so that at least one coil of said multiple coils is arranged on one side in the optical axis direction with respect to said magnet and at least another one coil of said multiple coils is arranged on the other side in the optical axis direction with respect to said magnet, and said magnet is relatively moved so as to move towards and away from said one coil or said another one coil in the optical axis direction, and either one of said magnet and said multiple coils is installed in said moving lenticular body, and the other in said fixed body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said driving mechanism is provided with a controlling means to control the movement of said moving lenticular body caused by the electromagnetic force when a current is supplied to said multiple coils to generate said electromagnetic force and, at the same time, said controlling means is a member to be magnetically attracted to said magnet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The lens drive unit as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein said controlling means comprises a first elastic member to energize said moving lenticular body in one of the optical axis directions, a second elastic member to energize in the opposite direction of said first direction wherein either said first elastic member or said second elastic member is the member to be magnetically attracted to said magnet.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
