<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296898-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296898</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11187481</doc-number>
<date>20050722</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>93130524 A</doc-number>
<date>20041008</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>88</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>18</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 52</main-classification>
<further-classification>353 57</further-classification>
<further-classification>353 30</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Image projector having a LED light source</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7156522</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Plut</name>
<date>20070100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>353 31</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0176054</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Mihalakis</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>353 31</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0046808</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Shiraishi et al.</name>
<date>20050300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>353 98</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0061733</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kuhlmann et al.</name>
<date>20060300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>353 30</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 52</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 57</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 59</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 60</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 61</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>353 30</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349161</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060077353</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060413</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wu</last-name>
<first-name>Chao Hsien</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Premier Image Technology Corp.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Diane</first-name>
<department>2851</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Kong</last-name>
<first-name>Andrew</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An image projector having a LED light source comprises: an optical engine using the LED as the light source, a PCB module, a heat sink module and a main frame. The printed circuit board (PCB) module further comprises: a first circuit board, a second circuit board, at least one I/O interface for connecting an external device, at least one card reader for connecting an external memory card, and a control unit for processing the image data received from the I/O interface or card reader and projecting the image by using the optical engine. The first circuit board and second circuit board are furnished in an overlap and parallel manner to decrease the space consumption. The heat sink module comprises a fan, an air inlet and an air outlet, which substantially forms a heat dissipating passage from the air inlet through the fan toward the air outlet. The LED and control unit are located in the heat dissipating passage for increasing better heat dissipation effect.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="158.16mm" wi="331.47mm" file="US07296898-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="180.85mm" wi="145.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296898-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="177.04mm" wi="143.51mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296898-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="174.24mm" wi="147.32mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296898-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="173.06mm" wi="127.59mm" file="US07296898-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="167.64mm" wi="117.01mm" file="US07296898-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="148.08mm" wi="146.73mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296898-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="190.58mm" wi="165.61mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296898-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="206.42mm" wi="126.24mm" file="US07296898-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention is related to an image projector; in particular, is related to an image projector having a LED as the light source.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The conventional image projector has reached the threshold in effectively sizing down due to the limitation in the design of the optical engine, the PCB module and the heat-dissipating route. On one hand, the complexity of the optical elements and the design of the light path prevented smaller space usage in designing the image projector; on the other hand, the complexity and the numerous electronic elements used prevented the minimization of the printed circuit board (PCB). Moreover, the large quantity of heat generated by the illuminator of the optical engine and the microprocessor of the PCB module has to be effectively dissipated by using two or more units of bigger-size high power fan combined with a wide, smooth heat-dissipating route in the image projector produced. In conclusion, the space taken up by the heat dissipating route and the fan prevented the effective minimization of the size of the image projector produced by custom technology.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is therefore one of the objectives of the claimed invention to provide an image projector that utilizes a light emitting diode (LED) as its illuminator. The image projector could dramatically decrease its size without affecting the efficiency and function thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">It is therefore one of the objectives of the claimed invention to provide an image projector that utilizes a light emitting diode (LED) as illuminator that includes two horizontally overlapping PCBs as its PCB module to reduce the space usage of itself. This design, as a result, enhances the reduction in size of this image projector.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It is therefore one of the objectives of the claimed invention to provide an image projector that utilizes a light emitting diode (LED) as its illuminator, with the special design for its heat dissipating module which separately places the heat generating light emitting diode and the PCB control unit, the former, near the vicinity of the entrance airway and the later, near the fan of the heat sink module, to enhance the effect of heat dissipation. Therefore, the image projection device in this invention can utilize a single and yet smaller heat dissipating fan which has smaller power, combined with a narrower heat dissipating route to effectively dissipate the heat generated by the device. This design further reduced the size of the image projector.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is therefore one of the objectives of the claimed invention to provide an image projector that utilizes a light emitting diode as its illuminator so that the heat generation is effectively reduced, and favors the minimization of the size of the heat-dissipating module. Furthermore, the size of the image projector can be further diminished due to the special design of the optical elements and illumination pathway that reduces the dimensions of the optical engine.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">It is therefore one of the objectives of the claimed invention to provide an image projector that utilizes a light emitting diode as illuminator, which contains a card reader that can be connected to a memory card. This device can directly retrieve the image data that is stored in the memory card and project it through the optical engine.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In accordance with these aspects of the present invention, an optical engine having a LED is provided, which comprises: an optical engine using the LED as the light source, a PCB module, a heat sink module and a main frame. The printed circuit board (PCB) module further comprises: a first circuit board, a second circuit board, at least one I/O interface for connecting an external device, at least one card reader for connecting an external memory card, and a control unit for processing the image data received from the I/O interface or card reader and projecting the image by using the optical engine. The first circuit board and second circuit board are furnished in an overlap and parallel manner to decrease the space consumption. The heat sink module comprises a fan, an air inlet and an air outlet, which substantially forms a heat dissipating passage from the air inlet through the fan toward the air outlet. The LED and control unit are located in the heat dissipating passage for increasing better heat dissipation effect.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The details of the present invention will be more readily understood from a detailed description of the preferred embodiments taken in conjunction with the following Figures.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates the frontal stereoscopic view of the exterior appearance of the image projector that utilizes a light emitting diode as illuminator;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates the posterior stereoscopic view of the exterior appearance of the image projector as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a perspective view of such image projector as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> from a different angle;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a composite drawing of the internal optical engine, PCB module and the lower frame of the main frame of the image projector as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates the composite drawing of the heat dissipating module, operation interface module and the upper frame of the main frame of the image projector as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a diagram of the heat-dissipating pathway of the heat flow of the image projector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illustrates the three-dimensional diagram of the optical engine of the image projector according to the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> illustrates the three-dimensional diagram of the illumination module of the image projector according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. The figures describe a preferred embodiment of the image projector that utilizes a light emitting diode (LED) as its illuminator according to the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates the frontal stereoscopic view of the exterior appearance of the image projector that utilizes a light emitting diode as illuminator. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates the posterior stereoscopic view of the exterior appearance of the image projector as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a perspective view of such image projector as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> from a different angle. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a composite drawing of the internal optical engine, PCB module and the lower frame of the main frame of the image projector as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates the composite drawing of the heat sink module, operation interface module and the upper frame of the main frame of the image projector as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b> and <b>5</b>, the image projector <b>1</b> of this invention that utilizes a light emitting diode (LED) as illuminator includes: an optical engine <b>10</b>, a PCB module <b>20</b>, a heat sink module <b>30</b>, a operation interface module <b>40</b>, a main frame and a casing <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The optical engine <b>10</b> is used for projecting an image. There is a light emitting diode (LED) <b>111</b> (as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>) in the optical engine <b>10</b> that produces the light needed for the projection of an image.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The printed circuit board (PCB) module <b>20</b> is connected to the optical engine <b>10</b> in order to control the projection of the optical engine. The PCB module <b>20</b> includes: a first PCB <b>22</b> and a second PCB <b>23</b> that are set-up in parallel to each other; at least one connecting interface <b>21</b> (such as USB interface or AV terminal) for connecting an external device (such as computer or DVD player); at least one card reader <b>24</b> (such as flash memorycard reader) for connecting an external memory card (such as CF Card or SmartMedia Card or MMC or SD or MS Card); and a control unit <b>25</b> to process the image data received from the connecting interface <b>21</b> or card reader <b>24</b> and then project the image through the optical engine <b>10</b>. In a preferred embodiment, the first PCB <b>22</b> and the second PCB <b>23</b> are horizontally overlaped with each other. The dimension of the first PCB <b>22</b> is smaller than the second PCB <b>23</b>. This provides an area on the second PCB <b>23</b> that will not overlap with the first PCB <b>22</b>. In the design, the card reader <b>24</b> is set up on the first PCB <b>22</b>. The heat-dissipating fan <b>31</b> is set up on the supporting plate <b>26</b> on the second PCB <b>23</b> that does not overlap with the first PCB <b>22</b>. The control unit <b>25</b> is positioned on the second PCB <b>23</b> and does not overlap with a heat-dissipating fan <b>31</b>. The design of this invention, which includes a PCB module <b>20</b> including two overlapping PCB <b>22</b>,<b>23</b> and the heat dissipating fan <b>31</b> being positioned on the area on the second PCB <b>23</b> that does not overlap with the first PCB <b>22</b>, enables a more economical use of space which significantly reduces the dimensions of the image projector <b>1</b> of this invention. Also, this design enables higher heat dissipating efficiency due to the reason that the heat-dissipating fan can be placed closer to the heat generating electronic elements such as the microprocessor.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The heat sink module <b>30</b> is used for dissipating the heat generated by the optical engine <b>10</b> and the PCB module <b>20</b>. The heat sink module <b>30</b> comprises at least a heat dissipating fan <b>31</b>, an entrance airway <b>33</b> and an exit airway <b>32</b>, which in fact build into a heat dissipating route that starts from the entrance airway <b>33</b> then passes through the heat dissipating fan <b>31</b> and then ends at the exit airway <b>32</b> (The arrow in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows the direction of the heat flow in the heat dissipating pathway). Also, the light emitting diode <b>111</b> and the control unit <b>25</b> are positioned on the heat-dissipating route. In this preferred embodiment, the exit airway <b>32</b> of the heat sink module <b>30</b> is at one of the front flank of the lower frame <b>61</b> of the supporting frame. The heat-dissipating fan <b>31</b> is placed at the vicinity of the exit airway <b>32</b> and close to the control unit <b>25</b>. The entrance airway <b>33</b> is positioned at the posterior flank of the lower frame <b>61</b> of the supporting frame, which is close by the illumination PCB <b>114</b> that contains the light emitting diode <b>111</b>. Therefore, better heat dissipating effect is achieved due to the reason that the light emitting diode <b>111</b> receives the cool air that enters through the entrance airway <b>33</b>, while the control unit <b>25</b> dissipates the heat faster by the concentrated airflow that passes through the close-by heat-dissipating fan <b>31</b>. This designed heat sink module <b>30</b> enables the image projector <b>1</b> of this invention to eliminate the need of two or more fans or fan with big size of higher power to achieve excellent heat-dissipating effect. It also has the benefit of cutting down the space usage and electricity consumption. Thus, the image projector <b>1</b> of this invention needs only one heat-dissipating fan <b>31</b> of low power and size together with a heat-dissipating route of less width than usual to achieve efficient heat-dissipating effect, and therefore enables the minimization of the size of the image projector <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The operation interface module <b>40</b> is connected to the PCB module <b>20</b> for the operations of the image projector <b>1</b> according to this invention. The operation interface module <b>40</b> includes but not limits a power switch of the image projector <b>1</b>, video signal converter, the adjustment of projection proportion and focus, projection angle or brightness. In a preferred embodiment, the operation interface module <b>40</b> includes several keys <b>41</b>, a keyboard <b>42</b> and a keyboard PCB <b>43</b>. The keyboard PCB <b>43</b> is connected to the upper frame <b>62</b>, while the keyboard <b>42</b> and keys <b>41</b> are sequentially assembled on the keyboard PCB <b>43</b>. The abovementioned components are only a preferred embodiment of the invention and not for giving any limitation to the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The supporting frame is used to contain and position the optical engine <b>10</b>, the PCB module <b>20</b>, the heat sink module <b>30</b> and the operation interface module <b>40</b>, which were described previously. In this preferred embodiment, the supporting frame includes a lower frame <b>61</b> and an upper frame <b>62</b>. There are several screw holes and sockets at the predetermined area of the lower frame <b>61</b> and upper frame <b>62</b> so that the optical engine <b>10</b>, the PCB module <b>20</b>, the heat sink module <b>30</b> and the operation interface module <b>40</b> can be screwed on to the predetermined area and the elements such as connection interface <b>21</b> and keys <b>41</b> can be exposed external of the casing <b>50</b>. Through this assembly, the upper and lower frames <b>62</b>,<b>61</b> of the supporting frame can integrate the optical engine <b>10</b>, PCB module <b>20</b>, heat sink module <b>30</b> and operation interface module <b>40</b> into the image projector <b>1</b>. Thus, the designer of the image projector <b>1</b> of this invention only needs to overlay different designs for the casing <b>50</b> on only one unit of the supporting frame that includes all the elements for the image projector <b>1</b>, for the diversification of the product. The designer does not have to design different supporting frame for each of the different outer casing. This invention provides for the effect of design-modularization.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. These figures illustrate the preferred embodiments of the optical engine <b>10</b> of the image projector <b>1</b> according to this invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> illuminates the three-dimensional diagram of the optical engine <b>10</b> of the image projector <b>1</b> of this invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> shows the three-dimensional diagram of the illumination module <b>11</b> of the image projector <b>1</b> of this invention.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the optical engine <b>10</b> of this invention includes: an illuminator module <b>11</b>, a concave mirror <b>12</b>, a condenser <b>13</b>, a prism module <b>14</b>, a Digital Micromirror Device (DMD) <b>15</b> and a projection lens set <b>16</b> put together by several lenses <b>161</b> and an aperture <b>162</b>. The formation of the image at an external surface is by the following process: firstly, the dispersed rays of the light emitted by the light-emitting diode <b>111</b> of the illumination module <b>11</b> is concentrated by the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> of the illumination module <b>11</b>. A concave mirror <b>12</b> then collects and refracts the concentrated rays to the converging lens <b>13</b>, which collects the rays and pass it towards the prism module <b>14</b> that refracts the rays towards the DMD <b>15</b>. The DMD <b>15</b> reflexes the rays and produces images that is again refracted by the prism module <b>14</b> towards the projection lens set <b>16</b>, focuses the image and then forms image at the external projection surface.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">To precisely orient all the elements described previously, the optical engine <b>10</b> of this invention has a special orientation mechanism. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the optical engine further includes a base <b>17</b> and an upper lid <b>18</b>. In this embodiment, it is better to produce the base <b>17</b> and the upper lid <b>18</b> by plastic injection molding. On the base <b>17</b>, a right cover <b>171</b> and a lower lid <b>172</b> are also included. The right cover <b>171</b> forms a first space <b>173</b> to contain the DMD <b>15</b>. The lower lid <b>172</b> on the other hand, forms a v-shape lower concave base <b>174</b>, which adjoins with a below-prism shading piece <b>175</b> at the right cover <b>171</b>. It also forms a below-concave groove <b>176</b> in between the v-shape lower concave base <b>174</b> and the below-prism shading piece <b>175</b>. The upper lid <b>18</b> can be connected to the lower lid <b>172</b> on the base <b>17</b>. Moreover, there is a v-shape upper concave base <b>181</b>, an above-prism shading piece <b>182</b> and an above concave groove (not shown in the FIG.) on the upper lid <b>18</b>. The position of the upper concave base <b>181</b>, the above-prism shading piece <b>182</b> and the above concave groove each respectively corresponds to the v-shape lower concave base <b>174</b>, the below-prism shading piece <b>175</b> and the below-concave groove <b>176</b>. When the upper lid <b>18</b> shuts with the lower lid <b>172</b>, a containing space is formed between the two lids. When assembling the optical engine <b>10</b> of this invention, the prism module <b>14</b> is contained between the above-prism shading piece <b>182</b> and the below-prism shading piece <b>175</b>. The converging lens <b>13</b> is contained between the above-concave groove and the below-concave groove <b>176</b>. The concave mirror <b>12</b> is contained between the v-shape upper concave base <b>181</b> and the bended area of the v-shape lower concave base <b>174</b>. Also, the pyramidal pole <b>112</b>, the fixing stand <b>115</b> and the spring clip <b>116</b> are contained between the v-shape upper concave base <b>181</b> and the end of the v-shape lower concave base <b>174</b>. In addition, under the lower surface of the prism module <b>14</b>, there is a prism supporting board <b>143</b> and a spring <b>144</b> that is used for orienting and micro-adjusting the relative position of the prism module <b>14</b>. As a result, using the specially designed structure of the base <b>17</b> and the upper lid <b>18</b>, one can rapidly, easily and precisely assemble each element at its predetermined angle, relative position and distance.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The DMD <b>15</b> further includes: a DMD chip <b>151</b>, a DMD socket <b>152</b> for the DMD chip <b>151</b> to plug in, a DMD PCB <b>153</b> to connect to the DMD socket <b>152</b>, and a DMD power connector <b>154</b> to connect to the DMD PCB <b>153</b>. When DMD <b>15</b> is assembled to the right lid <b>171</b> of the base <b>17</b>, the DMD chip <b>151</b> would be exposed at a window located at the center of the first space <b>173</b>. This enables the DMD chip to receive light from the prism module <b>14</b>. The projection lens set <b>16</b> is located at an opening in between the above-prism shading piece <b>182</b> and the below-prism shading piece <b>175</b>. The projection lens set <b>16</b> also includes a rubber <b>163</b> and a fastening ring <b>164</b>. The rubber <b>163</b> can be put around the exterior of the projection lens set <b>16</b>, and the contour of the rubber <b>163</b> can seal the space between the above-prism shading piece <b>182</b> and the below-prism shading piece <b>175</b> to prevent disturbance due to light leakage. The fastening ring <b>164</b> locks the projection lens set <b>16</b> on the extension frame <b>177</b> of the right lid <b>171</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In this preferred embodiment, the prism module <b>14</b> is of the reversed total internal reflection (RTIR) design. It includes: a first prism <b>141</b>, a second prism <b>142</b> and a prism supporting board <b>143</b>. The first prism <b>141</b> is placed closer to converging lens <b>13</b> while the second prism is placed closer to the DMD <b>15</b>. Both first and second prisms <b>141</b>,<b>142</b> are made from transparent material that has a predetermined reflective index. The first prism <b>141</b> is a wedge prism. The cross section in which the direction of the light beam passes is conical in shape. The second prism <b>142</b> is a right angle prism. The cross section in which the direction of the light beam passes is a right triangle. Also the first prism <b>141</b> is attached to hypotenuse surface of the right triangle of the cross section of the second prism <b>142</b>. The DMD <b>15</b> and the projection lens <b>16</b> are respectively placed on the two perpendicular surfaces of the right triangle of the cross section of the second prism <b>142</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the illuminator module <b>11</b> includes: a light emitting diode <b>111</b>, a pyramidal pole <b>112</b>, a light reflective measure, a PCB <b>114</b>, a fixing stand <b>115</b> and a spring clip <b>116</b>. A heat-dissipating element <b>117</b> is combined to the illuminator module to enhance heat-dissipation.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The light emitting diode <b>111</b> is used for emitting light at a predetermined beam axis. In this invention, one end of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> is closer to the light emitting diode <b>111</b>. The pyramidal pole <b>112</b> has several numbers of narrow and long surfaces <b>1121</b> that extends in the direction of the beam axis. In this preferred embodiment, the cross section of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> that is perpendicular to the beam axis has a square contour. Each narrow and long surfaces <b>1121</b> respectively has two opposite long edges that follows the direction of the beam axis <b>1122</b>, <b>1123</b> and two opposite short edges that is perpendicular to the beam axis <b>1124</b>,<b>1125</b>. Also, the short edge <b>1125</b> on the narrow and long surface <b>1121</b> closer to the light emitting diode <b>111</b> is shorter compared to the short edge <b>1124</b> that is further away from the light emitting diode <b>111</b>. In this case, the cross section of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> in essence, increases in size as furthering away from the light emitting diode <b>111</b>. The concave mirror <b>12</b> is located at the end of biggest cross section of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">This reflective measure that was utilized in each narrow and long surfaces <b>1121</b> of the pyramidal pole let the narrow and long surfaces <b>1121</b> reflex the light beam emitted by the light emitting diode <b>111</b>, which guides the light beam to move along the beam axis. In the preferred embodiment in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> is a hollow conical structure that is better made of transparent materials. However, glass, plastic crystals and quartz can also be used. The reflective measure is such that the inner surface of each narrow and long surfaces <b>1121</b> of the hollow pyramidal pole <b>112</b> are coated with reflective material (such as silver, etc), which enables the total reflex of the light in the hollow pyramidal pole <b>112</b> and passing of the light beam from the smaller cross section towards the larger cross section of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b>. In this case, the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> in this invention could achieve the purpose of generally directing the light beam to move along the beam axis.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The PCB <b>114</b> is used to support the light emitting diode <b>111</b>. There are also several electronic elements (not numbered) to drive the light emitting diode <b>111</b> and a connector <b>1142</b>. The fixing stand <b>115</b> is connected to the PCB <b>114</b>. On the fixing stand <b>115</b>, there is an approximately square shape hollow sink <b>1151</b> in which the smaller cross section end of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> can fit in. Also, the position of the light emitting diode <b>111</b> respectively fits in with the smaller cross section end of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b>. Moreover, the fixing stand <b>115</b> has two stands <b>1152</b>,<b>1153</b> and a sliding route <b>1154</b> positioned between the two stands. The dimensions of the sliding route <b>1154</b> matches the dimensions of the PCB <b>114</b>, so that the PCB <b>114</b> can slide into the sliding route <b>1154</b> to connect with the fixing stand <b>115</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The spring clip <b>116</b> clips and secures the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> on the fixing stand <b>115</b>. In this preferred embodiment, the spring clip <b>116</b> further includes several clips <b>1161</b>, at least one buttoning clip <b>1162</b> on one of the clips <b>1161</b>, and holes <b>1163</b> located in between each clips <b>1161</b>. The dimensions of the holes are bigger than that of the largest cross section of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b>. When the holes <b>1163</b> of the spring clip <b>116</b> slip onto the pyramidal pole <b>112</b>, and at least one of the clips <b>1161</b> clips on to the edge of the fixing stand <b>115</b>, the pyramidal pole <b>112</b> can be connected and fixed on the fixing stand <b>115</b>. In this preferred embodiment, a bump <b>1126</b> can be set up on at least one narrow and long surface <b>1121</b> of the pyramidal pole <b>112</b>, so that when the hole <b>1163</b> of the spring clip <b>116</b> slips onto the pyramidal pole <b>112</b>, the bump <b>1126</b> can exactly sustain the spring clip <b>116</b> and the fixing stand <b>115</b> to prevent shifting.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The heat-dissipating element <b>117</b> contains a heat dissipating contact surface <b>1171</b> and multiple heat-dissipating fins <b>1172</b> that extended from the heat dissipating contact surface <b>1171</b>. On the heat dissipating contact surface <b>1171</b> there is also a convex surface <b>1173</b> of predetermined shape. The fixing stand <b>115</b> and the PCB <b>114</b> make connections on the heat dissipating contact surface <b>1171</b>, and the bump <b>1173</b> is exactly located at the space formed by the two stands <b>1152</b>,<b>1153</b>. This enables the location on the PCB <b>114</b> that supports the light emitting diode <b>111</b> to directly contact the bump <b>1173</b> on the heat dissipating contact surface <b>1171</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Those skilled in the art will readily observe that numerous modifications and alterations of the device may be made while retaining the teachings of the invention. Accordingly, that above disclosure should be construed as limited only by the metes and bounds of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An image projector having a light emitting diode (LED) light source, the image projector comprising:
<claim-text>an optical engine for projecting an image, the optical engine having a LED for producing the light needed for the projection of the image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a printed circuit board (PCB) module coupled to the optical engine to control the projection of the optical engine, the PCB module comprising:
<claim-text>a first PCB;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second PCB which is set-up in parallel to the first PCB;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one connecting interface for connecting an exterior device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control unit, coupled to the at least one connecting interface, for processing image data received from the at least one connecting interface and transferring the processed image data to the optical engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat sink module for dissipating the heat generated by the optical engine and the PCB module, the heat sink module comprising a heat dissipating fan, an entrance airway, and an exit airway, which build into a heat dissipating route that starts from the entrance airway then passes through the heat dissipating fan and then ends at the exit airway, and the LED and the control unit are positioned on the heat-dissipating route;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a operation interface module, coupled to the PCB module, for controlling the operation of the image projector; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a supporting frame utilized to contain and position the optical engine, PCB module, heat-dissipating module and operation interface module;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first PCB and the second PCB horizontally overlaps each other, the size of the first PCB is smaller than that of the second PCB, the heat dissipating fan is located on the area on the second PCB that does not overlap with the first PCB.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the PCB module further comprises at least one memory-card connecting module for connecting an external memory card, wherein the control unit processes image data from the external memory card and transfers the processed image data to the optical engine, the at least one memory-card connecting module is located at the first PCB.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the control unit is located on the area of the second PCB and does not overlap with the heat-dissipating fan.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the supporting frame includes a lower frame and an upper frame, and there are several screw holes and sockets at the predetermined position of the lower frame and upper frame so that optical engine, the PCB module, the heat sink module, and the operation interface module be screwed on to the predetermined position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the exit airway of the heat sink module is at one of the front flank of the lower frame of the supporting frame, wherein the heat-dissipating fan is placed at the vicinity of the exterior airway and close to the control unit, wherein the entrance airway is positioned at the posterior flank of the lower frame of the supporting frame such that better heat dissipating effect is achieved due to the reason that the LED receives the cool air that enters through the entrance airway, while the control unit dissipates the heat faster by the concentrated airflow that passes through the close-by heat-dissipating fan.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the operation interface module further comprises a plurality of keys, a keyboard, and a keyboard PCB which is connected to the upper frame, wherein the keyboard and the keys are sequentially assembled on the keyboard PCB.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the optical engine comprises:
<claim-text>a Digital Micromirror Device (DMD) for receiving the light from the optical engine, and refracting the image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a projection lens set for focusing the image and forming on an external projection surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pyramidal pole having one end being closer to the LED, and a plurality of narrow and long surfaces that extends in the direction of the beam axis, wherein the cross section of the pyramidal pole that is perpendicular to the beam axis has a square contour, and the cross section of the pyramidal pole increases in size as furthering away from the LED; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a reflecting piece which is implemented to the narrow and long surfaces to reflect the light from the LED and guides it toward the direction of the light axis.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the pyramidal pole is a hollow cone made of transparent material, and the light reflecting pieces is the interior surfaces of the narrow and long surfaces.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the optical engine comprises:
<claim-text>a light source printed circuit board (PCB) for supporting the LED;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a fixing stand, connected to the light source PCB, having a hollow sink, wherein the hollow sink is used for installing the end with the smaller cross-sectional area of the pyramidal pole and the location of the LED corresponds exactly to the end with the smaller cross-sectional area of the pyramidal pole; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a spring clip for clipping the pyramidal pole to the fixing stand.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the fixing stand comprises a first stand, a second stand and a sliding route which is between the first stand and the second stand, wherein the size of the sliding route matches exactly with the size of the light source PCB so that the light source PCB slides into the sliding route to attach with the fixing stand, wherein the optical engine further comprises:
<claim-text>a heat sink module comprising a heat dissipating surface and a plurality of heat dissipating fins extended from the heat dissipating surface, the heat dissipating surface comprising a convex surface with predetermined shape, wherein the fixing stand and the light source PCB are connected to the heat dissipating surface, and the location of the convex surface forms exactly a space with the first and the second stands so that the light source on the light source PCB is contacted to the convex surface of the heat dissipating surface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the spring clip comprises a plurality of clips, at least one buttoning clip on one of the clips and a plurality of holes corresponding to the clips, the size of the hole is greater than the larger cross-sectional area end of the pyramidal pole, the pyramidal pole is fixed to the fixing stand with the hole of the spring clip encases upon the pyramidal pole and with the help of at least a clip to clip onto the edge of fixing stand; wherein a bump is set up on at least one narrow and long surface of the pyramidal pole, so that when the hole of the spring clip slips onto the pyramidal pole, the bump exactly sustains the spring clip and the fixing stand to prevent shifting.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the optical engine further comprises:
<claim-text>a concave mirror, which is located at the end of the cross-sectional area of the pyramidal pole, for refracting and converging the light which is guided toward the direction of a light axis;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light condenser for receiving and converging the light from the concave mirror; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a reversed total internal reflection (RTIR) for receiving and refracting the light from the light condenser, the reversed total internal reflection (RTIR) comprising:
<claim-text>a first prism which is located near the light condenser; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second prism, which is located near the Digital Micromirror Device (DMD) and the projection lens set;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first prism is a wedge prism which presents itself in on the cross-sectional surface of the light as a pyramidal shape, the second prism presents itself on the cross-sectional surface of the traveling light as a right triangle, the first prism leans against the surface drawn from an edge of the right triangle along the cross-sectional surface formed by the second prism.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the optical engine further comprises:
<claim-text>a base comprising:
<claim-text>a right cover for forming a first space to contain the Digital Micromirror Device (DMD); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lower lid for forming a v-shaped lower concave base and a below-prism shading piece connected in adjacent to the right cover, wherein a lower concave groove is located between the v-shaped lower concave base and the below-prism shading piece; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a upper lid for connecting the lower lid of base, the upper lid comprising a v-shaped upper concave base, an above-prism shading piece and an upper groove whose locations correspond to the v-shaped lower concave base, the below-prism shading piece and a lower concave groove, respectively, wherein a space is formed when the upper lid covers up with lower lid;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the reversed total internal reflection (RTIR) is located in between the above-prism shading piece and the below-prism shading piece, the light condenser is located in between the upper concave groove and the lower concave groove, the concave mirror is located in the corner formed by the v-shaped upper concave base and the v-shaped lower concave base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the end of the v-shaped upper concave base and the v-shaped lower concave base contain the pyramidal pole and the fixing stand.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. An image projector having a light emitting diode (LED) light source, comprising:
<claim-text>an optical engine comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light emitting diode (LED) for producing the light;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a Digital Micromirror Device (DMD) for receiving the light from the optical engine, and refracting the image; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a projection lens set, for focusing the image and forming on an external projection surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a printed circuit board (PCB) module connected to the optical engine to control the projection of the optical engine, the PCB module comprising:
<claim-text>a first PCB;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second PCB which is set-up in parallel to the first PCB;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one connecting interface for connecting an exterior device; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control unit, coupled to the at least one connecting interface, for processing image data received from the at least one connecting interface and transferring the processed image data to the optical engine;
<claim-text>a heat sink module for dissipating the heat generated by the optical engine and the PCB module, the heat sink module comprising a heat dissipating fan, an entrance airway, and an exit airway, which build into a heat dissipating route that starts from the entrance airway then passes through the heat dissipating fan and then ends at the exit airway;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a operation interface module, coupled to the PCB module, for controlling the operation of the image projector; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a supporting frame utilized to contain and position the optical engine, PCB module, heat-dissipating module and operation interface module;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first PCB and the second PCB horizontally overlaps each other, the size of the first PCB is smaller than that of the second PCB, the heat dissipating fan is located on the area on the second PCB that does not overlap with the first PCB.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the control unit is located on the area of the second PCB and does not overlap with the heat-dissipating fan.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the exit airway of the heat sink module is at one of the front flank of the lower frame of the supporting frame, wherein the heat-dissipating fan is placed at the vicinity of the exterior airway and close to the control unit, wherein the entrance airway is positioned at the posterior flank of the lower frame of the supporting frame such that better heat dissipating effect is achieved due to the reason that the LED receives the cool air that enters through the entrance airway, while the control unit dissipates the heat faster by the concentrated airflow that passes through the close-by heat-dissipating fan.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. An image projector having a light emitting diode (LED) light source, the image projector comprising:
<claim-text>an optical engine for projecting an image;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a printed circuit board (PCB) module, coupled to the optical engine, for controlling an operation of the optical engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a heat sink module, coupled to the optical engine and the PCB module, for dissipating a heat generated by the optical engine and the PCB module;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a operation interface module, coupled to the PCB module, for controlling an operation of the image projector; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a supporting frame utilized to contain and position the optical engine, PCB module, heat-dissipating module and operation interface module;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the PCB module comprises:
<claim-text>a first PCB;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second PCB which is set-up in parallel to the first PCB;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one connecting interface for connecting an exterior device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control unit, coupled to the at least one connecting interface, for processing image data received from the at least one connecting interface and transferring the processed image data to the optical engine;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the heat sink module comprises a heat dissipating fan, an entrance airway, and an exit airway, which build into a heat dissipating route that starts from the entrance airway then passes through the heat dissipating fan and then ends at the exit airway;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first PCB and the second PCB horizontally overlaps each other, the size of the first PCB is smaller than that of the second PCB, the heat dissipating fan is located on the area on the second PCB that does not overlap with the first PCB.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein the control unit is located on the area of the second PCB and does not overlap with the heat-dissipating fan.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The image projector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein the heat-dissipating fan is placed at the vicinity of the exterior airway and close to the control unit, wherein the entrance airway is positioned at the posterior flank of the lower frame of the supporting frame such that better heat dissipating effect is achieved due to the reason that the LED receives the cool air that enters through the entrance airway, while the control unit dissipates the heat faster by the concentrated airflow that passes through the close-by heat-dissipating fan.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
