<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298732-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298732</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10354978</doc-number>
<date>20030131</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>2002-8716</doc-number>
<date>20020219</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>1026</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>12</main-group>
<subgroup>66</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370352</main-classification>
<further-classification>370356</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Method for initializing internet protocol phone in internet protocol telephony system</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6400950</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Patel et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4554351</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6427170</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Sitaraman et al.</name>
<date>20020700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6661785</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Zhang et al.</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370352</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6791970</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ng et al.</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370352</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7023838</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Hahn et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370352</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7031279</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lee et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370331</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7046659</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Woundy</name>
<date>20060500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>370352</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0046263</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Camerini et al.</name>
<date>20020400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO 01/95063</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO 02/082794</doc-number>
<kind>A2</kind>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00011">
<othercit>“Search Report under Section 17” issued by U.K. Patent Office dated on May 22, 2003.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370352</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>370356</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>379900</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20030156579</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20030821</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cho</last-name>
<first-name>Jun-Woo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Songnam-shi</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bushnell, Esq.</last-name>
<first-name>Robert E.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung Electronics Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si, Gyeonggi-do</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Matar</last-name>
<first-name>Ahmad F.</first-name>
<department>2614</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Haq</last-name>
<first-name>Aamir</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method for initializing an IP phone in an IP telephony system. The IP (Internet Protocol) telephony system includes an IP network; at least one gatekeeper connected to the IP network, having a DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) server and a TFTP (Trivial File Transfer Protocol) server; an IP phone connected to the gatekeeper for voice communication service; and an AAA (Authentication, Authorization and Account) server. The method allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address, and allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone; allocating subscriber information having a phone number and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone to allow the IP phone to access the gatekeeper and transmit a registration request signal to the gatekeeper; the gatekeeper informing the AAA server of subscriber information of the IP phone.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="121.84mm" wi="188.21mm" file="US07298732-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="190.75mm" wi="124.63mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298732-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="233.76mm" wi="185.76mm" file="US07298732-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="244.01mm" wi="178.73mm" file="US07298732-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="246.72mm" wi="179.83mm" file="US07298732-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CLAIM OF PRIORITY</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application makes reference to, incorporates the same herein, and claims all benefits accruing under 35 U.S.C §119 from an application entitled METHOD FOR INITIALIZING INTERNET PROTOCOL PHONE IN INTERNET PROTOCOL TELEPHONY SYSTEM earlier filed in the Korean Industrial Property Office on 19 Feb. 2002, and there duly assigned Serial No. 2002-8716 by that Office.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates to an Internet protocol (IP) telephony system, and more particularly to a method for initializing an Internet protocol (IP) terminal.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Firstly, prior to the explanation of the preferred embodiment of the present invention, the abbreviations and technical terms are defined as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="3">
<colspec colname="offset" colwidth="14pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="49pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="154pt" align="left"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>G/K:</entry>
<entry>Gatekeeper</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>IP:</entry>
<entry>Internet Protocol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>VoIP:</entry>
<entry>Voice over IP</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TFTP:</entry>
<entry>Trivial File Transfer Protocol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>DHCP:</entry>
<entry>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>AAA:</entry>
<entry>Authentication, Authorization and Account</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MCU:</entry>
<entry>Multi-point Control Unit</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>RRG:</entry>
<entry>Registration Request</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>RCF:</entry>
<entry>Registration Confirmation</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>RAS:</entry>
<entry>Registration/Admission/Status</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry>(Registration and Admission Control Signaling)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>RRJ:</entry>
<entry>Registration Rejection</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry namest="offset" nameend="2" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In recent times, following the current trend of rapidly growing Internet technology, an IP-based network or a packet-based network (hereinafter referred to as “IP network”) is developing rapidly not only in the Internet performance aspect but also in the Internet service aspect. For instance, the IP network is typically implemented in consideration of data transmission, but currently needs to be implemented in consideration of voice transmission as well as the data transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">According to demand for data and voice transmission at the same time, the IP network has been developed in the form of a multimedia service by which not only voice transmission, like a typical network, but also video and data transmission are possible. The IP network is called “VoIP (Voice over IP) system” or “Internet Protocol Telephony System” in that it makes it possible to perform voice communication between many subscribers by transmitting voice signals to them. Likewise, besides the data transmission, the voice transmission over the IP network is very important in the IP network. Under this condition, many developers are intensively conducting research into a voice transmission method in the IP network.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">For example, a multimedia communication standard H.323 protocol recommended by ITU-T (International Telecommunication Union—Telecommunication) provides fundamental principles for voice, video, and data communications over the IP network including the Internet. One of the H.323 entities defined in the H.323 protocol is a gatekeeper. The gatekeeper binds H.323 endpoints present in a packet-based network (i.e., an IP-based network) in one control zone defined as a “Zone”, and then controls/manages the bound H.323 endpoints. For instance, there are a variety of H.323 endpoints such as a gateway, a terminal, and a MCU (Multi-point Control Unit). One gatekeeper is present in the zone, and is composed of at least one H.323 endpoint. A plurality of gatekeepers are collected to form a multi-zone, and other gatekeepers for controlling the multi-zone may exist.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The gatekeeper has various kinds of principal functions such as an address translation function, a call admission function, a bandwidth control function, a call control function, and a maintenance function. The address translation function translates an alias name or a destination number into a network address (i.e., an IP address). The call admission function means a function by a RAS (Registration/Admission/Status) protocol generically naming protocols related to a gatekeeper in the H.323 standards. The bandwidth control function distributes a limited bandwidth of a network into a plurality of endpoints, and performs a blocking function by checking whether the bandwidth reaches a threshold value or not. The call control function makes a call connection/disconnection between endpoints through the medium of a gatekeeper. The maintenance function means a supplementary function such as accounting or statistics.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">One of the basic signaling protocols of the gatekeeper is the RAS. The RAS is a protocol for implementing a basic interface between endpoints (e.g., a terminal, gateway, and MCU, etc.) and a gatekeeper. In the RAS, the gatekeeper is a server, and the endpoints are clients. Namely, the RAS is a basic protocol necessary for the gatekeeper functioning as the server to manage/control/monitor the endpoints functioning as clients, in such a way that the gatekeeper can reflect the RAS results in its own operation and control procedure. The registration mode in the RAS means that the endpoint (client) registers its own presence to the gatekeeper (server).</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">An admission mode in the RAS determines whether the endpoint follows the rules of H.323 and a corresponding zone in the gatekeeper, and permits access to a VoIP network upon receiving the result signal. Herein, the rule of H.323 determines whether an alias name being a registration ID (Identification) of the endpoint is equal to that of another endpoint. The rule of the corresponding zone determines whether a corresponding endpoint is registered to the gatekeeper.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In the status mode of the RAS, the endpoint periodically informs the gatekeeper of its own information and current status in such a way that the gatekeeper acquires information needed to operate/control the endpoint, thereby making a periodic link test between a server and a client.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">As stated above, a communication interface between an IP terminal (i.e., IP-phone) and a gatekeeper in the VoIP system or the IP telephony system is performed according to the RAS protocol functioning as a H.323 protocol being one of ITU-T standards. However, the communication interface between the IP phone and the gatekeeper according to the RAS protocol has the following problems, resulting in user's inconvenience in operation.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Firstly, a user must manually input initialization information (e.g., a server IP address, and H.323 ID, etc.) in initializing the IP phone and the gatekeeper.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Secondly, a signal mismatch occurs in performing a link restart between the IP phone and the gatekeeper, resulting in user's inconvenience in operation.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Therefore, the present invention has been made in view of the above problems, and it is an object of the present invention to provide a method for controlling an IP phone by a gatekeeper in case of initializing an IP phone and a gatekeeper in a VoIP system.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">It is another object of the present invention to provide a method for matching an IP phone with a gatekeeper in case of restarting the IP phone in a VoIP system.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">It is yet another object of the present invention to provide a method for matching an IP phone with a gatekeeper in case of restarting the gatekeeper in a VoIP system.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">It is yet another object of the present invention to provide a method for simplifying information input procedures of a user in case of initializing an IP phone and a gatekeeper in a VoIP system.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In accordance with one aspect of the present invention, the above and other objects can be accomplished by the provision of an IP (Internet Protocol) telephony system including an IP network; at least one gatekeeper connected to the IP network, having a DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) server and a TFTP (Trivial File Transfer Protocol) server; an IP phone connected to the gatekeeper for voice communication service; and an AAA (Authentication, Authorization and Account) server for performing an authentication, authorization, and accounting of the IP phone, wherein a method for initializing the IP phone comprises the steps of a) allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts, and allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone; b) allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, and allocating subscriber information having a phone number and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone; c) allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, and transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper; and d) allowing the gatekeeper to inform the AAA server of subscriber information of the IP phone.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In accordance with another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a method for initializing an IP phone, comprising the steps of a) allowing a gatekeeper to transmit a restart message to the IP phone when the gatekeeper restarts; b) allowing the IP phone to access a DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user upon receiving the restart message, and allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone; c) allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, and allocating subscriber information having a phone number and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone; d) allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, and transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper; and e) allowing the gatekeeper to inform the. AAA server of subscriber information of the IP phone.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In accordance with yet another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a method for initializing an IP phone, comprising the steps of a) allowing the IP phone to access a DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user, and allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone; b) allowing the IP phone to access a TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, and allocating subscriber information having a phone number and an IP address of a gatekeeper to the IP phone; c) allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, and transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper; d) determining whether initialization of the gatekeeper is completed in case of transmitting the registration request signal to the gatekeeper; e) if the initialization of the gatekeeper is not completed, repeatedly performing the steps (a) to (d); and f) if the initialization of the gatekeeper is completed, allowing the gatekeeper to inform the AAA server of subscriber information of the IP phone.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The foregoing embodiments of the present invention are briefly disclosed to be readily understood by those skilled in the art. Although the present invention has been described with respect to specific embodiments, various changes and modifications will be apparent to those skilled in the art. The following embodiments are given by way of example. The present invention is not limited to these embodiments, but encompasses all variants falling within the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">A more complete appreciation of the present invention, and many of the attendant advantages thereof, will become readily apparent as the same becomes better understood by reference to the following detailed description when considered in conjunction with the accompanying drawings in which like reference symbols indicate the same or similar components, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a view illustrating a block diagram of an IP (Internet protocol) telephony system in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a view illustrating a signal flow among internal components shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in case of initializing an IP phone in accordance with a preferred embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a view illustrating a signal flow among internal components shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in case of initializing an IP phone in accordance with another preferred embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view illustrating a signal flow among internal components shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in case of initializing an IP phone in accordance with yet another preferred embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Now, preferred embodiments of the present invention will be described in detail with reference to the annexed drawings. In the drawings, the same or similar elements are denoted by the same reference numerals even though they are depicted in different drawings. In the following description, a detailed description of known functions and configurations incorporated herein will be omitted when it may make the subject matter of the present invention rather unclear.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a view illustrating a block diagram of an IP telephony system in accordance with the present invention. The IP telephony system shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a VoIP system for performing voice transmission over an IP network. As well known in the art, a VoIP system generally comprises a plurality of gatekeepers. The VoIP system according to the present invention, however, is composed only of a gatekeeper positioned in a predetermined service zone and IP phones connected to the gatekeeper.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the IP telephony system includes a gatekeeper (G/K) <b>10</b>, a plurality of IP phones (i.e., IP terminals) <b>22</b> and <b>24</b>, and an AAA (Authentication, Authorization and Account) server <b>30</b>. These components are connected to an IP network.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The gatekeeper <b>10</b> includes a G/K (gatekeeper) core <b>12</b>, a TFTP (Trivial File Transfer Protocol) server <b>14</b>, a DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) server <b>16</b> and a storage unit <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> are connected to the gatekeeper <b>10</b> to perform a voice communication service over the IP network. The IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> are connected to the DHCP server <b>16</b> of the gatekeeper <b>10</b>, and are assigned their own IP addresses and a TFTP server IP address from the DHCP server. Also, the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> are connected to the TFTP server <b>14</b>, and are assigned a phone number (H.323 ID (Tel #)) being subscriber information and a gatekeeper IP address from the TFTP server <b>14</b>. Further, the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> receive software version information regarding their own execution files (i.e., .exe files). In the case where the received software version information is different from prior software version information concerning the execution files of the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b>, the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> download a new execution file from the gatekeeper <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The G/K core <b>12</b> controls an overall operation accompanied by the gatekeeper <b>10</b>. The storage unit <b>18</b> includes a database (DB) for storing information of a plurality of IP phones generating registration request (RRQ) signals, and also stores a package file therein. As for the package file, the gatekeeper <b>10</b> downloads the package file along with subscriber information of the terminals (IP-phones) from the AAA server <b>30</b>. In this case, the subscriber information indicates information stored in the DB of the storage unit <b>18</b> and is, for example, a phone number (H.323 ID (Tel #)) and an IP address.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In case of using the DHCP server <b>16</b>, the IP address is useless. There are software version information and execution files of IP phones in the package file. The DHCP server <b>16</b> allocates an IP address and an IP address of the TFTP server <b>14</b> to an IP phone accessed thereto.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The TFTP server <b>14</b> allocates a phone number (H.323 ID (Tel #)) being subscriber information and a gatekeeper IP address to an IP phone accessed thereto. In the case where software version information concerning an execution file of an IP phone is different from another software version information concerning an execution file stored in the storage unit <b>18</b>, a corresponding IP phone transmits a request signal to the TFTP server <b>14</b>, and the TFTP server <b>14</b> provides the corresponding IP phone with an execution file stored in the storage unit <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The G/K core <b>12</b>, TFTP server <b>14</b>, DHCP server <b>16</b>, and storage unit <b>18</b> contained in the gatekeeper <b>10</b> are interconnected to make an IPC (Inter-Processor Communication) possible. The AAA server <b>30</b> authenticates the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b>, authorize that the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> to allow the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> to gain access to the IP network, and performs an accounting operation after the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>25</b> access the IP network.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As previously described, the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> access the gatekeeper <b>10</b> according to a RAS (Remote Access Service (dial-up network access)) protocol and are then initialized, thereby the registration, admission and status modes contained in the RAS protocol are performed.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">During the initialization operation, users of the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> manually input only an IP address of the DHCP server <b>16</b> without any other manipulation, increasing the user's convenience. For reference, in case of a typical initialization step using the RAS protocol of H.323 standards, the user always has to manually input all information needed for the initialization of an IP phone, resulting in a user's inconvenience. But, the present invention obviates this problem in that it requires just one IP address input process.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">If the gatekeeper <b>10</b> or one of the IP phones <b>22</b> and <b>24</b> restarts, an initialization operation is performed again. Likewise, in the case where either the gatekeeper <b>10</b> or the IP phone performs such restarting operation, a signal mismatch occurs between the gatekeeper <b>10</b> and the IP phone <b>22</b> or <b>24</b>. This mismatch part can be removed by the following operations shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In the following description, an initialization operation between the gatekeeper <b>10</b> and the IP phone <b>22</b> will be described by way of example. But, it should be noted that an initialization operation between the gatekeeper <b>10</b> and the IP phone <b>24</b> is the same.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a view illustrating a signal flow among internal components shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> when initializing an IP phone in accordance with a first preferred embodiment of the present invention. The signal flow shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is followed in the case where the IP phone <b>22</b> and the gatekeeper <b>10</b> simultaneously restart or only IP phone <b>22</b> restarts.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the IP phone <b>22</b> determines at step <b>101</b> whether its own IP and phone number (H.323 ID) are detected. If the IP phone <b>22</b> does not detect its own IP and phone number (H.323 ID) at step <b>102</b>, it gains access to the DHCP server <b>16</b> at step <b>103</b> and then broadcasts a DHCP server request message to the DHCP server <b>16</b>. When connecting the IP phone <b>22</b> to the DHCP server <b>16</b> over an IP network, an IP address of the DHCP server <b>16</b> is directly input by a user.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Upon receiving the DHCP server request message, the DHCP server <b>16</b> performs an IP address allocation of the IP phone <b>22</b>, an IP address allocation of a TFTP server <b>14</b>, and a file name allocation at step <b>104</b>, and then transmits the allocated results to the IP phone <b>22</b>. Herein, the file name indicates a name of a software file to be transmitted from the TFTP server <b>14</b> to the IP phone <b>22</b>. Then, the IP phone <b>22</b> is connected to the TFTP server <b>14</b> via the allocated IP address of the TFTP server <b>14</b> at step <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">If the TFTP server <b>14</b> is connected to the IP phone <b>22</b> at step <b>105</b>, then TFTP server <b>14</b> transmits a script file to the IP phone <b>22</b> at step <b>106</b>. Herein, the script file includes script file contents, a gatekeeper (G/K) IP address, a phone number (H.323 ID (Tel #)), and a software version (S/W VER.) of an execution file of the IP phone <b>22</b>. At this time, in the case where a software version of an execution file of the IP phone <b>22</b> is different from a software version of a gatekeeper <b>110</b>, corresponding software (S/W), that is, a corresponding execution file is downloaded from the TFTP server <b>14</b> to the IP phone <b>22</b> at step <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The determination of the software version difference is provided after software version information is transmitted to the IP phone <b>22</b>. In other words, after the software version information transmitted to the IP phone <b>22</b> at step <b>106</b>, the IP phone <b>22</b> determines whether the received software version information is equal to a software version of a gatekeeper <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Thereafter, the IP phone <b>22</b> requests corresponding software from the TFTP server <b>14</b>, and then downloads the corresponding software from the TFTP server <b>14</b> responsive to the request signal. Note that the aforementioned operations after step <b>105</b> are all contained in the step <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In order to allocate the phone number (H.323 ID (Tel #)) and the gatekeeper (G/K) IP at step <b>106</b>, the TFTP server <b>14</b> has a function for receiving the phone number (H.323 ID (Tel #)) and the gatekeeper (G/K) IP to be allocated from a database (DB) of the storage unit <b>18</b>. Also, the TFTP server <b>14</b> has another function of preventing the phone number (H.323 ID (Tel #)) from overlapping with another phone number during the allocation step at step <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Then, at step <b>107</b>, the IP phone <b>22</b> receives the script file provided at step <b>106</b>, is connected to gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> by adapting the allocated gatekeeper (G/K) IP, and transmits a RRQ (Registration Request) message to the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> so as to request registration in the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">At this time, the IP phone <b>22</b> uses its own allocated H.323 ID and IP. Upon receiving the RRQ message, the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> transmits a RCF (Registration Confirmation) message used for authorizing a registration to the IP phone <b>22</b> at step <b>108</b>. Thereafter, at step <b>109</b>, the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> stores information (i.e., subscriber information) concerning the IP phone <b>22</b> in the DB of storage unit <b>18</b>, and informs the AAA server <b>30</b> of the aforesaid storage status in such a way that synchronization between the gatekeeper <b>10</b> and the AAA server <b>30</b> in association with subscriber information of the IP phone <b>22</b> can be maintained.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In the meantime, a user of the IP phone <b>22</b> may want to use another phone number other than the initial allocated phone number H.323 ID. In this case, the user needs to change only a current phone number to a desired phone number on his or her IP phone. But, under this condition, if the desired phone number is in use by someone else, then the gatekeeper <b>10</b> generates an alarm signal indicating occupancy of the desired phone number, and transmits the alarm signal to a corresponding terminal. In this case, a system manager (or operator) needs to directly change a current phone number to another phone number in the AAA server <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a view illustrating a signal flow among internal components shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> when initializing an IP phone in accordance with a second preferred embodiment of the present invention. The signal flow shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is made in the case where a phone number of an IP phone <b>22</b> is changed to another phone number or a gatekeeper <b>10</b> restarts.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, an AAA server <b>30</b> transmits subscriber information (H.323 ID and IP) to gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> at step <b>111</b>. As previously stated, this operation at step <b>111</b> is performed in the case where a phone number of the IP phone <b>22</b> is changed to another phone number or the gatekeeper <b>10</b> restarts. Upon receiving the subscriber information from the AAA server <b>30</b>, the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> transmits an “IP-Phone Restart” message functioning as a restart message to the IP phone <b>22</b> at step <b>112</b>. Transmitting the “IP-Phone Restart” message prevents a service from being delayed.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The reason for the service delay is that the IP phone <b>22</b> cannot transmit a registration request signal to the gatekeeper <b>10</b> or transmits the registration request signal to the gatekeeper <b>10</b> late under the condition that only the gatekeeper <b>10</b> restarts or a phone number of the IP phone <b>22</b> is changed to another phone number. Therefore, in case of restarting the gatekeeper <b>10</b> or changing the IP phone <b>22</b>'s phone number functioning as a key value for a system operation, it is necessary for the gatekeeper <b>10</b> to directly restart a corresponding IP phone <b>22</b> to achieve a registration.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">After the steps <b>111</b> and <b>112</b>, the aforesaid steps <b>101</b>˜<b>110</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> are performed. That is, besides steps <b>111</b> and <b>112</b>, a signal flow shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is identical with that in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view illustrating a signal flow among internal components shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, when initializing an IP phone in accordance with a third preferred embodiment of the present invention. The signal flow shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is followed in the case where a registration request signal of an IP phone <b>22</b> is rejected by a gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> after the IP phone <b>22</b> transmits the registration request signal to the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b>. For example, in the case where subscriber information downloading from an AAA server <b>30</b> to the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> is not completed or the gatekeeper <b>10</b>'s initialization is not completed even though the IP phone <b>22</b> transmits the registration request signal to the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b>, the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> rejects the registration request signal of the IP phone <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, steps <b>101</b>˜<b>107</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> are identical with steps <b>101</b>˜<b>107</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Accordingly, the IP phone <b>22</b> transmits a registration request signal to the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> at step <b>107</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> rejects the registration request signal at step <b>121</b>. In this case, if subscriber information downloading from an AAA server <b>30</b> to the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> is not completed, the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> provides the IP phone <b>22</b> with a RRJ (Registration Rejection) message at step <b>121</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">After step <b>121</b>, if subscriber information downloading from the AAA server <b>30</b> to the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> is completed at step <b>131</b>, the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> transmits an “IP-Phone Restart” message to the IP phone <b>22</b> at step <b>132</b>. Following step <b>132</b>, steps <b>133</b>˜<b>137</b>, identical with the aforesaid steps <b>103</b>˜<b>107</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, are performed.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The steps <b>133</b>˜<b>137</b>, are repeatedly performed in the case where the initialization of the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> is not completed, because the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> provides the IP phone <b>22</b> with a RRJ (Registration Rejection) message in response to the RRQ message until the initialization of the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> is not completed, not shown. On the contrary, in the case where the initialization of the gatekeeper (G/K) core <b>12</b> is completed, as shown, subscriber information registration procedures such as steps <b>138</b>˜<b>140</b> are performed.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">As apparent from the above description, the present invention effectively controls an IP phone by a gatekeeper in a VoIP system (i.e., IP telephony system). The present invention has an advantage in that it removes a user's inconvenience by adapting a play&amp;plug method in initializing the IP-phone and the gatekeeper. Therefore, a user needs not manually input all of the initialization information (e.g., a server IP address or a H.323 ID, etc.) in initializing the IP-phone and the gatekeeper. In brief, a user needs to designate only a DHCP server IP on his or her IP-phone in initializing the IP-phone and the gatekeeper. Furthermore, the present invention removes a signal mismatch part (e.g., subscriber information) occurring in performing a link restart between the IP phone and the gatekeeper, thereby maintaining accurate synchronization between a server and a client.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">Although the preferred embodiments of the present invention have been disclosed for illustrative purposes, those skilled in the art will appreciate that various modifications, additions and substitutions are possible, without departing from the scope and spirit of the invention as disclosed in the accompanying claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for initializing an IP (Internet Protocol) phone in an IP telephony system including an IP network; at least one gatekeeper connected to the IP network, the gatekeeper having a DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) server and a TFTP (Trivial File Transfer Protocol) server; the IP phone connected to the gatekeeper for voice conmmunication service; and an AAA (Authentication, Authorization and Account) server for performing an authentication, authorization, and accounting of the IP phone, the method for initializing the IP phone comprising steps of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to inform the AAA server of the subscriber information of the IP phone.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a step of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone connected to the TFTP server to receive software version information concerning an execution file of the IP phone from the TFTP server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising a step of:
<claim-text>if the received software version information concerning said execution file of the IP phone is different from stored software version information concerning said execution file of the IP phone stored in the gatekeeper, downloading to the IP phone a new execution file, corresponding to the stored software version information, from the TFTP server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a step of:
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit a restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone when the gatekeeper restarts.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting subscriber information from the AAA server to the gatekeeper when the telephone number of the IP phone is changed; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit a restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting subscriber information from the AAA server to the gatekeeper when the gatekeeper restarts; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit a restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting a registration rejection signal from the gatekeeper to the IP phone in response to the registration request signal when it is determined that subscriber information is not completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
<claim-text>repeating, until it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper, said steps of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit a restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone when it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting a registration rejection signal from the gatekeeper to the IP phone in response to the registration request signal when it is determined that said subscriber information is not completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
<claim-text>repeating, until it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper, said steps of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit said restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone when it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting a registration rejection signal from the gatekeeper to the IP phone in response to the registration request signal when it is determined that said subscriber information is not completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
<claim-text>repeating, until it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper, said steps of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit said restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone when it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method for initializing an IP (Internet Protocol) phone in an IP telephony system including an IP network; at least one gatekeeper connected to the IP network, the gatekeeper having a DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) server and a TFTP (Trivial File Transfer Protocol) server; the IP phone connected to the gatekeeper for voice communication service; and an AAA (Authentication, Authorization and Account) server for performing an authentication, authorization, and accounting of the IP phone, the method for initializing the IP phone comprising steps of:
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit a restart message to the IP phone when the gatekeeper restarts;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to inform the AAA server of the subscriber information of the IP phone.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising a step of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone connected to the TFTP server to receive software version information concerning an execution file of the IP phone from the TFTP server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, further comprising a step of:
<claim-text>if the received software version information concerning said execution file of the IP phone is different from stored software version information concerning said execution file of the IP phone stored in the gatekeeper, downloading to the IP phone a new execution file, corresponding to the stored software version information, from the TFTP server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting a registration rejection signal from the gatekeeper to the IP phone in response to the registration request signal when it is determined that subscriber information is not completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
<claim-text>repeating, until it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper, said steps of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit a restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone when it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method for initializing an IP (Internet Protocol) phone in an IP telephony system including an IP network; at least one gatekeeper connected to the IP network, the gatekeeper having a DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) server and a TFTP (Trivial File Transfer Protocol) server; the IP phone connected to the gatekeeper for voice communication service; and an AAA (Authentication, Authorization and Account) server for performing an authentication, authorization, and accounting of the IP phone, the method for initializing the IP phone comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting subscriber information from the AAA server to the gatekeeper when the telephone number of the IP phone is changed and allowing the gatekeeper to transmit a restart message to the IP phone</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to inform the AAA server of the subscriber information of the IP phone.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising a step of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone connected to the TFTP server to receive software version information concerning an execution file of the IP phone from the TFTP server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, further comprising a step of:
<claim-text>if the received software version information concerning said execution file of the IP phone is different from stored software version information concerning said execution file of the IP phone stored in the gatekeeper, downloading to the IP phone a new execution file, corresponding to the stored software version information, from the TFTP server.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting a registration rejection signal from the gatekeeper to the IP phone in response to the registration request signal when it is determined that said subscriber information is not completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
<claim-text>repeating, until it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper, said steps of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit said restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone when it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method as set forth in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, further comprising steps of:
<claim-text>transmitting a registration rejection signal from the gatekeeper to the IP phone in response to the registration request signal when it is determined that said subscriber information is not completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
<claim-text>repeating, until it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper, said steps of:
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the DHCP server via a DHCP server IP address received from a user when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number, the DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the TFTP server via the TFTP server IP address, the TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the IP phone to access the gatekeeper via the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the gatekeeper to transmit said restart message to the IP phone to restart the IP phone when it is determined that subscriber information is completely downloaded from the AAA server to the gatekeeper.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. An IP (Internet Protocol) telephony system comprising
<claim-text>an IP network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one gatekeeper connected to the IP network, the gatekeeper having a DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) server and a TFTP (Trivial File Transfer Protocol) server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an IP phone connected to the gatekeeper for voice communication service; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an AAA (Authentication, Authorization and Account) server for performing an authentication, authorization, and accounting of the IP phone;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said IP phone accessing the DHCP server in response to a DHCP server IP address input by a user of the IP phone when the IP phone restarts and the IP phone does not detect its own terminal IP address and phone number;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said DHCP server allocating a terminal IP address and a TFTP server IP address to the IP phone when said IP phone accesses the DHCP server in response to the DHCP server IP address input by the user;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said IP phone accessing the TFTP server in response to the TFTP server IP address;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said TFTP server allocating subscriber information having a phone number of the IP phone and an IP address of the gatekeeper to the IP phone when said IP phone accesses the TFTP server;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said IP phone accessing the gatekeeper in response to the IP address of the gatekeeper, the IP phone transmitting a registration request signal to the gatekeeper; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said gatekeeper informing the AAA server of the subscriber information of the IP phone.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The IP (Internet Protocol) telephony system as set in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, said gatekeeper comprising:
<claim-text>a gatekeeper core controlling overall operation of the gatekeeper; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a storage unit including a database storing information of a plurality of IP (Internet Protocol) phones generating registration request signals and storing package files containing subscriber information of the plurality of IP phones.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
