<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298171-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298171</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11177563</doc-number>
<date>20050708</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>183</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>50</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>19</main-group>
<subgroup>21</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326 55</main-classification>
<further-classification>326112</further-classification>
<further-classification>326 96</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Layout area efficient, high speed, dynamic multi-input exclusive or (XOR) and exclusive NOR (XNOR) logic gate circuit designs for integrated circuit devices</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4570084</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Griffin et al.</name>
<date>19860200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4645954</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Schuster</name>
<date>19870200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>326 73</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4749886</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hedayati</name>
<date>19880600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4888499</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sanwo et al.</name>
<date>19891200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5134616</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Barth, Jr. et al.</name>
<date>19920700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5399921</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dobbelaere</name>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>326113</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5859548</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kong</name>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>326113</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5936427</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tsujihashi</name>
<date>19990800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>61-264820</doc-number>
<date>19861100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>03-262317</doc-number>
<date>19911100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>08-123665</doc-number>
<date>19960500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>Chu, Kan M. and Pulfrey, David I., Design Procedures for Differential Cascode Voltage Switch Circuits, IEEE Journal of Solid-State Circuits, vol. SC-21, No. 6, Dec. 1986, pgs. 1082-1087.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>26</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326 52</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326 54</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326 55</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070008014</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070111</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Parris</last-name>
<first-name>Michael C.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Colorado Springs</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kubida</last-name>
<first-name>William J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Meza</last-name>
<first-name>Peter J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hogan &amp; Hartson LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>United Memories, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Colorado Springs</city>
<state>CO</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sony Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Cho</last-name>
<first-name>James H.</first-name>
<department>2819</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Hammond</last-name>
<first-name>Crystal L</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A layout area efficient, high speed, dynamic multi-input exclusive OR (XOR) and exclusive NOR (XNOR) logic gate circuit design of especial utility with respect to integrated circuit devices. The logic gate design disclosed herein utilizes fewer transistors than traditional static designs and, therefore, requires a smaller amount of integrated circuit layout area while nevertheless affording higher speed operating performance than that exhibited in existing conventional circuits.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="164.93mm" wi="211.67mm" file="US07298171-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="181.61mm" wi="126.58mm" file="US07298171-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="208.11mm" wi="140.97mm" file="US07298171-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="152.74mm" wi="91.95mm" file="US07298171-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="177.46mm" wi="162.31mm" file="US07298171-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="213.95mm" wi="170.94mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298171-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="213.87mm" wi="197.10mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298171-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates, in general, to the field of integrated circuit logic circuits and devices. More particularly, the present invention relates to layout area efficient, high speed, dynamic multi-input exclusive OR (XOR) and exclusive NOR (XNOR) logic gate circuit designs of especial utility with respect to integrated circuit devices.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Error correction circuitry (ECC) and other types of logic functions that make use of parity require XOR and the XNOR logic gate functions. These XOR and XNOR gates are more difficult to implement with complementary metal oxide semiconductor (CMOS) technology than standard NAND and NOR logic gates, particularly when considering multi-input gates having more than two inputs. Conventional static three-input XOR circuits are generally slow and require many transistors. Representative implementations of various XOR logic gates are shown, for example, in U.S. Pat. No. 4,749,886 issued Jun. 7, 1988 for “Reduced Parallel Exclusive OR and Exclusive NOR Gate”, U.S. Pat. No. 4,888,499 issued Dec. 19, 1989 for “Three Input Exclusive OR-NOR Gate Circuit' and U.S. Pat. No. 5,936,427 issued Aug. 10, 1999 for “Three-Input Exclusive NOR Circuit”. Examples of conventional four-input XOR circuits are shown, for example, in U.S. Pat. No. 4,570,084 issued Feb. 11, 1986 for “Clocked Differential Cascode Voltage Switch Logic Systems” and U.S. Pat. No. 5,134,616 issued Jul. 28, 1996 for “Dynamic RAM with On-Chip ECC and Optimized Bit and Word Redundancy”. The larger number input XOR gates are important in order to reduce stages in wide-word ECC circuit blocks.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Disclosed herein is a dynamic, multi-input XOR and XNOR logic gate circuit design (as exemplified by representative three and four-input embodiments) utilizing fewer transistors than traditional static designs and, therefore, requiring a smaller amount of integrated circuit layout area while nevertheless affording higher speed operating performance than that exhibited by existing conventional circuits.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Particularly disclosed herein is a logic gate comprising a clocked latch circuit selectively couplable between a supply voltage source and a reference voltage source in response to a first clock signal. The latch circuit has first and second nodes thereof respectively coupled to first and second complementary logic gate outputs. First and second clocked strings of N number of series coupled transistors are selectively couplable between the supply voltage source and the reference voltage source in response to a second clock signal with a selected terminal of each of the N transistors defining first through Nth intermediate nodes therebetween. The logic circuit further comprises N additional transistors with each of the N additional transistors being coupled between one of the intermediate nodes of the first and second clocked strings and a next higher number intermediate node on an opposite one of the first and second clocked strings. The Nth intermediate node of the first and second clocked strings are also selectively couplable to the first and second nodes of said clocked latch circuit in response to the second clock signal and the control terminals of each of the first and second clocked strings of N series coupled transistors and the N additional transistors define logic inputs to the logic gate.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Also particularly disclosed herein is an XOR/XNOR logic gate which comprises a plurality of logic signal inputs and first and second complementary logic signal outputs together with a clocked latch circuit having first and second nodes thereof coupled to the first and second complementary logic signal outputs. The clocked latch circuit is clocked by a first clock signal. The logic gate further comprises a plurality of transistors, with each transistor coupled to receive one of the plurality of logic signal inputs at a control terminal thereof. The plurality of transistors are coupled to first and second intermediate nodes of the logic gate and selectively couplable to the first and second nodes of the clocked latch circuit in response to a second clock signal having an opposite phase with respect to the first clock signal.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The aforementioned and other features and objects of the present invention and the manner of attaining them will become more apparent and the invention itself will be best understood by reference to the following description of a preferred embodiment taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref> are, respectively, a conventional representation of a two-input XOR gate and a truth table indicative of its functionality;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A through 2D</figref> are schematic, device level illustrations of various implementations of conventional static two-input XOR gates;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> are, respectively, a conventional representation of a three-input XOR gate and a truth table indicative of its functionality;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a conceptual representation of a static three-input XOR gate implemented in a manner analogous to the two-input XOR gate of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> utilizing conventional design techniques;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic diagram of a dynamic three-input XOR/XNOR gate in accordance with a particular implementation of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a schematic diagram of a dynamic four-input XOR/XNOR gate in accordance with a further implementation of the present invention and illustrative of how the concepts disclosed herein can be utilized to implement an N-input XOR/XNOR gate.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF A REPRESENTATIVE EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">With reference now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref>, a conventional representation of a two-input XOR gate <b>100</b> is shown together with a truth table indicative of its functionality and the output “Q” provided for the various permutations of the two inputs signals on leads “A” and “B”.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">With reference additionally now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A through 2D</figref>, schematic, device level illustrations of various implementations of conventional two-input XOR gates are shown. None of the designs illustrated lend themselves particularly well to more than two-input XOR devices.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">With particular reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, the two-input XOR gate <b>200</b> comprises two series connected strings of transistors coupled between a supply voltage source (e.g. VCC) and a reference voltage source (e.g. VSS or circuit ground). A first string of series connected P-channel transistors <b>202</b> and <b>204</b> is connected in series with N-channel transistors <b>206</b> and <b>208</b> between VCC and circuit ground. In like manner, a second string of series connected P-channel transistors <b>210</b> and <b>212</b> is also connected in series with N-channel transistors <b>214</b> and <b>216</b> between VCC and circuit ground. The “A” input is coupled to the gate of transistor <b>202</b> and the gate of transistor <b>206</b> while the “B” input is coupled to the gate of transistor <b>208</b> and the gate of transistor <b>212</b>. The complementary signal /A (or “A bar”) is coupled through an inverter to the gate of transistor <b>210</b> and also supplied to the gate of transistors <b>214</b>. Similarly, the complementary signal /B (or “B bar”) is coupled through an inverter <b>220</b> to the gate of transistor <b>216</b> and also applied to the gate of transistor <b>204</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">With particular reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, the two-input XOR gate <b>230</b> comprises a pair of inverters <b>232</b> and <b>234</b> having their input respectively coupled to the “A” and “B” inputs. The output of the inverter <b>232</b> is coupled to the output “Q” through a CMOS pass gate <b>236</b> while the “A” input itself is coupled to the “Q” output through another CMOS pass gate <b>238</b>. The “B” input controls the operation of the pass gates <b>236</b> and <b>238</b> both directly and through the inversion of its signal by means of inverter <b>234</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">With particular reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>, the two-input XOR gate <b>240</b> comprises a series connected P-channel transistor <b>242</b> and N-channel transistor <b>244</b> in association with an inverter <b>246</b> and a CMOS pass gate <b>248</b>. The “A” input is coupled to the source terminal of transistor <b>242</b> as well as to one control terminal of the CMOS pass gate <b>248</b> and the input of the inverter <b>246</b>. The “B” input is coupled to the common connected gate terminals of the transistors <b>242</b> and <b>244</b> as well as to the output of the CMOS pass gate <b>248</b>. The “Q” output is coupled to the input of the CMOS pass gate <b>248</b> and the common connected drain terminals of the transistors <b>242</b> and <b>244</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">With particular reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>, the two input XOR gate <b>250</b> comprises a number of N-channel transistors <b>252</b>, <b>254</b>, <b>256</b> and <b>258</b> as shown. The “A” input is coupled to one terminal of transistors <b>254</b> and <b>256</b> as well as to one terminal of transistor <b>258</b> as signal /A through inverter <b>262</b>, which signal is also supplied to one terminal of transistor <b>252</b>. The “B” input of XOR gate <b>259</b> is supplied to the gate terminals of transistors <b>254</b> and <b>258</b> while its complement, /B is supplied through inverter <b>260</b> to the gate terminals of transistors <b>252</b> and <b>256</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">P-channel transistor <b>264</b> is coupled between VCC and the common connected outputs of transistors <b>252</b> and <b>254</b>, which is also coupled to the gate terminal of another P-channel transistor <b>268</b>. Similarly, P-channel transistor <b>268</b> is coupled between VCC and the common connected outputs of transistors <b>256</b> and <b>258</b>, which is also coupled to the gate terminal of the P-channel transistor <b>264</b>. The common connected outputs of transistors <b>252</b> and <b>254</b> is provided through an inverter <b>266</b> as the “Q” output while the common connected outputs of transistors <b>256</b> and <b>258</b> is provided through another inverter <b>270</b> as the “/Q”, or XNOR output.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">With reference additionally now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> a conventional representation of a three-input XOR gate <b>300</b> is shown together with a truth table indicative of its functionality and the output “Q” provided for the various permutations of the three inputs signals on leads “A”, “B” and “C”.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">With reference additionally now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a conceptual representation of a static three-input XOR gate <b>400</b> is shown as implemented in a manner analogous to the two-input XOR gate <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> utilizing conventional design techniques. The XOR gate <b>400</b> comprises four series connected strings of transistors, as shown. A first string comprises series connected P-channel transistors <b>402</b>, <b>404</b> and <b>406</b> with series connected N-channel transistors <b>408</b>, <b>410</b> and <b>412</b> all connected together in series between VCC and circuit ground. In like manner, a second string comprises series connected P-channel transistors <b>414</b>, <b>416</b> and <b>418</b> with series connected N-channel transistors <b>420</b>, <b>422</b> and <b>424</b> also connected together in series between VCC and circuit ground. Similarly, a third string comprises series connected P-channel transistors <b>426</b>, <b>428</b> and <b>430</b> with series connected N-channel transistors <b>432</b>, <b>434</b> and <b>436</b> connected together in series between VCC and circuit ground. Finally, a fourth string comprises series connected P-channel transistors <b>438</b>, <b>440</b> and <b>442</b> with series connected N-channel transistors <b>444</b>, <b>446</b> and <b>448</b> again connected together in series between VCC and circuit ground.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The “Q” output is taken at the common drain terminals of transistors <b>406</b>, <b>418</b>, <b>430</b>, <b>442</b>, <b>408</b>, <b>420</b>, <b>432</b> and <b>444</b>. The “A” input is supplied to the gate terminals of transistors <b>408</b>, <b>414</b>, <b>420</b> and <b>426</b> and its complement, “/A”, is supplied to the gate terminals of transistors <b>402</b>, <b>432</b>, <b>438</b> and <b>444</b>. The “B” input is supplied to the gate terminals of transistors <b>404</b>, <b>410</b>, <b>428</b> and <b>434</b> while the complementary “/B” signal is supplied to the gate terminals of transistors <b>416</b>, <b>422</b>, <b>440</b> and <b>446</b>. The “C” input is supplied to the gate terminals of transistors <b>406</b>, <b>418</b>, <b>424</b> and <b>436</b> while the complementary “/C” signal is supplied to the gate terminals of transistors <b>412</b>, <b>430</b>, <b>442</b> and <b>448</b>. A representative number of inverters for furnishing the “/A”, “/B” and “/C” input signals are also illustrated. As is apparent, the number of transistors required to provide a conventional three-input XOR gate <b>400</b> soon grows to be unreasonably large, and possibly prohibitively so for conventional static designs of four or more inputs.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">With reference additionally now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a schematic diagram of a dynamic three-input XOR/XNOR logic gate <b>500</b> in accordance with a particular implementation of the present invention is shown. The logic gate comprises, in pertinent part, a clocked latch circuit <b>502</b> comprising a pair of cross-coupled CMOS inverters <b>504</b> and <b>506</b> coupled to VCC and selectively couplable to circuit ground by an N-channel transistor <b>508</b>. First and second nodes of the latch circuit <b>502</b> provide respective “Q” (XOR) and complementary “QB” (XNOR) outputs on lines <b>518</b> and <b>518</b>B. Inputs to the logic gate <b>500</b> comprise “A” input <b>510</b>, “B” input <b>512</b> and “C” input <b>514</b> as well as their complements, “AB” input <b>510</b>B, “BB” input <b>512</b>B and “CB” input <b>514</b>B.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The logic gate <b>500</b> is clocked by means of a clock (CLK) signal coupled to line <b>520</b> and its complement “CLKB” derived, for example, at the output of a CMOS inverter <b>522</b> on line <b>520</b>B. The CLKB signal is supplied to the gate terminal of transistor <b>508</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The logic gate <b>500</b> comprises first and second strings of series coupled N-channel transistors, with the first string including transistors <b>526</b>AB, <b>530</b>BBL and <b>534</b>CBL while the second string comprises transistors <b>526</b>A, <b>530</b>BBR and <b>534</b>CBR. The first string is selectively couplable to VCC through the enabling of P-channel transistor <b>524</b>UL and to circuit ground through N-channel transistor <b>524</b>LL, both of which receive the CLK signal at their gate terminal. Similarly, the second string is selectively couplable to VCC through the enabling of P-channel transistor <b>524</b>UR and to circuit ground through N-channel transistor <b>524</b>LR, both of which also receive the CLK signal at their gate terminal.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">An N-channel transistor <b>540</b>BL has its source terminal coupled to a first intermediate node <b>528</b>R at the drain of transistor <b>526</b>A and its drain terminal coupled to a second intermediate node <b>532</b>L at the drain of transistor <b>530</b>BBL. In like manner, another N-channel transistor <b>540</b>BR has its source terminal coupled to a first intermediate node <b>528</b>L at the drain of transistor <b>526</b>AB and its drain terminal coupled to a second intermediate node <b>532</b>R at the drain of transistor <b>530</b>BBR. Further, an N-channel transistor <b>542</b>CL has its source terminal coupled to the second intermediate node <b>532</b>R at the drain of transistor <b>530</b>BBR and its drain terminal coupled to a third intermediate node <b>536</b>L (“QP”) at the drain of transistor <b>534</b>CBL. In like manner, another N-channel transistor <b>542</b>CR has its source terminal coupled to the second intermediate node <b>532</b>L at the drain of transistor <b>530</b>BBL and its drain terminal coupled to a third intermediate node <b>536</b>R (“QPB”) at the drain of transistor <b>534</b>CBR. The first and second nodes of the latch circuit <b>502</b> are selectively couplable to the QP and QPB nodes <b>536</b>L and <b>536</b>R through N-channel transistors <b>538</b>L and <b>538</b>R respectively, which receive the CLK signal at their gate terminals.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">As illustrated the gate of transistor <b>526</b>A receives the “A” input signal on line <b>510</b>, the gate terminals of transistors <b>540</b>BL and <b>540</b>BR receive the “B” input signal on line <b>512</b>, while the gate terminals of transistors <b>542</b>CL and <b>542</b>CR receive the “C” input signal on line <b>514</b>. The complementary “AB” signal is supplied to the gate of transistor <b>526</b>AB on line <b>510</b>B, the complementary “BB” signal is supplied to the gate of transistors <b>530</b>BBL and <b>530</b>BBR on line <b>512</b>B while the complementary “CB” signal is supplied to the gate of transistors <b>534</b>CBL and <b>534</b>CBR on line <b>514</b>B.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Functionally, when the CLK signal is “low”, the “QP” <b>536</b>L and “QPB” <b>536</b>R nodes are precharged “high”, while outputs “Q” <b>518</b> and “QB” <b>518</b>B are disconnected and allowed to remain latched at their previous levels. When the CLK signal transitions to a logic level “high”, inputs “A” <b>510</b>, “B” <b>512</b>, “C” <b>514</b>, “AB” <b>510</b>B, “BB” <b>512</b>B and “CB” <b>514</b>B are evaluated and either node “QP” <b>536</b>L or “QPB” <b>536</b>R will go “low”. Since pass gate transistors <b>538</b>L and <b>538</b>R are now “on” and coupled to nodes <b>536</b>L and <b>536</b>R, this information is transferred to the “Q” <b>518</b> and “QB” <b>518</b>B nodes when the CLK transitions to logic level “low” again, that is, when the complementary CLKB signal goes “high”. The output “Q” and “QB” levels are sensed and amplified through the latch circuit <b>502</b> devices.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As previously described, at this time node “QP” <b>536</b>L and “QPB” <b>536</b>R are precharged and disconnected from the outputs “Q” <b>518</b> and “QB” <b>518</b>B. The series coupled N-channel transistors <b>534</b>CBL, <b>540</b>BL, <b>530</b>BBL, <b>526</b>AB, <b>542</b>CR, <b>530</b>BBR, <b>540</b>BR, <b>534</b>CBR, <b>526</b>A and <b>542</b>CL are configured to pull down node “QP” <b>536</b>L or “QPB” <b>536</b>R when the CLK signal is “high” according to the three input XOR truth table shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>. It should be noted that the logic gate <b>500</b> performs both an XOR and XNOR function on the three inputs “A” <b>510</b>, “B” <b>512</b> and “C” <b>514</b> since both the “Q” <b>518</b> and “QB” <b>518</b>B outputs are made available.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">With reference additionally now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a schematic diagram of a dynamic four-input XOR/XNOR logic gate <b>600</b> in accordance with a further implementation of the present invention is shown. In this illustration, like structure to that previously described with respect to the three-input XOR/XNOR gate <b>500</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is like numbered and the foregoing description thereof shall suffice herefor.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Utilizing the principles of the present invention, a four-input XOR/XNOR logic gate <b>600</b> can be readily provided through the addition of a “D” input <b>602</b> at the gate of additional N-channel transistors <b>608</b>DL and <b>608</b>DR and a complementary “DB” input <b>602</b>B at the gate of additional N-channel transistors <b>606</b>DBL and <b>606</b>DBR added to the first and second transistor strings as shown. The transistor <b>608</b>DR is coupled to an intermediate node <b>604</b>L at the drain of transistor <b>534</b>CBL and the “QPQ” node <b>536</b>R. Similarly, the transistor <b>608</b>DL is coupled to node <b>604</b>R at the drain of transistor <b>534</b>CBR and the “QP” node <b>536</b>L. Transistor <b>606</b>DBL is placed in series between transistors <b>524</b>UL and transistor <b>534</b>CBL while transistor <b>606</b>DBR is placed in series between transistors <b>523</b>UR and <b>534</b>CBR. The four-input XOR/XNOR logic gate <b>600</b> shown operates in a manner analogous to the three-input XOR/XNOR logic gate <b>500</b> previously described.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">It should be further noted that, while a representative three-input XOR/XNOR logic gate <b>500</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) and a four-input XOR/XNOR logic gate <b>600</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) have been illustrated, the principles of the present invention are likewise applicable to five-input (and more) multi-input XOR/XNOR gates. For example, the four-input XOR/XNOR logic gate <b>600</b> can be readily expanded to a five-input gate by breaking the connections between the drain terminals of transistors <b>606</b>DBL and <b>608</b>DL with node “QP” <b>536</b>L and the connections between the drain terminals of transistors <b>606</b>DBR and <b>608</b>DR with node “QPB” <b>536</b>R. An additional N-channel transistor can then be placed in series between the drain terminal of transistor <b>606</b>DBL with node “QP” <b>536</b>L while a similar device is placed in series between the drain terminal of transistor <b>606</b>DBR and node “QPB” <b>536</b>R. The signal “FB” would then be input to the gate terminals of these devices. Another N-channel transistor would then be placed in series between the drain of transistor <b>608</b>DR and node “QP” <b>536</b>L while a similar device is place in series between the drain of transistor <b>608</b>DL and node “QPB” <b>536</b>R. The signal “F” would then be input to the gate terminals of these devices. Multi-input XOR/XNOR gates having even more inputs can be readily provided in the same manner.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">While there have been described above the principles of the present invention in conjunction with specific circuit implementations, it is to be clearly understood that the foregoing description is made only by way of example and not as a limitation to the scope of the invention. Particularly, it is recognized that the teachings of the foregoing disclosure will suggest other modifications to those persons skilled in the relevant art. Such modifications may involve other features which are already known per se and which may be used instead of or in addition to features already described herein. Although claims have been formulated in this application to particular combinations of features, it should be understood that the scope of the disclosure herein also includes any novel feature or any novel combination of features disclosed either explicitly or implicitly or any generalization or modification thereof which would be apparent to persons skilled in the relevant art, whether or not such relates to the same invention as presently claimed in any claim and whether or not it mitigates any or all of the same technical problems as confronted by the present invention. The applicants hereby reserve the right to formulate new claims to such features and/or combinations of such features during the prosecution of the present application or of any further application derived therefrom.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A logic gate comprising:
<claim-text>a clocked latch circuit selectively couplable between a supply voltage source and a reference voltage source in response to a first clock signal, said latch circuit having first and second nodes thereof respectively coupled to first and second complementary logic gate outputs;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first and second clocked strings of N number of series coupled transistors selectively couplable between said supply voltage source and said reference voltage source in response to a second clock signal, a selected terminal of each of said N transistors defining first through Nth intermediate nodes therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>N additional transistors, each of said N additional transistors being coupled between one of said intermediate nodes of said first and second clocked strings and a next higher number intermediate node on an opposite one of said first and second clocked strings, said Nth intermediate node of said first and second clocked strings also being selectively couplable to said first and second nodes of said clocked latch circuit in response to said second clock signal and wherein control terminals of each of said first and second clocked strings of N series coupled transistors and said N additional transistors define logic inputs to said logic gate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first and second clocked strings of N number of series coupled transistors are selectively couplable to said supply voltage source in response to a signal supplied to a control terminal of a transistor coupled in series with each of said first and second clocked strings and said supply voltage source.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said clocked latch circuit comprises cross-coupled inverters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein said cross-coupled inverters comprise CMOS inverters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said first and second clock signals are complementary clock signals.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said clocked latch circuit is selectively couplable between said supply voltage source and said reference voltage source in response to a signal supplied to a control terminal of a transistor coupled in series with said clocked latch circuit and said reference voltage source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein said transistor coupled in series with said clocked latch circuit and said reference voltage source comprises an N-channel device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said transistor coupled in series with each of said first and second clocked strings and said supply voltage source comprises a P-channel device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said first and second clocked strings of N number of series coupled transistors are selectively couplable to said reference voltage source in response to a signal supplied to a control terminal of a transistor coupled in series with each of said first and second clocked strings and said reference voltage source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein said transistor coupled in series with each of said first and second clocked strings and said reference voltage source comprises an N-channel device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said Nth intermediate nodes of said first and second clocked strings are selectively couplable to said first and second nodes of said clocked latch circuit in response to a signal supplied to a control terminal of a transistor coupled between said Nth intermediate node of said first clocked string and said first logic gate output and a signal supplied to a control terminal of another transistor coupled between said Nth intermediate node of said second clocked string and said second logic gate output.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein said transistor coupled between said Nth intermediate node of said first clocked string and said first node of said clocked latch circuit and said another transistor coupled between said Nth intermediate node of said second clocked string and said second node of said clocked latch circuit comprise N-channel devices.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said first and second complementary logic gate outputs represent XOR and XNOR outputs of said logic inputs to said logic gate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein N is greater than two.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A logic gate comprising:
<claim-text>a clocked latch circuit selectively couplable between a supply voltage source and a reference voltage source in response to a first clock signal, said latch circuit having first and second nodes thereof respectively coupled to first and second complementary logic gate outputs;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first and second clocked strings of N number of series coupled transistors selectively couplable between said supply voltage source and said reference voltage source in response to a second clock signal, a selected terminal of each of said N transistors defining first through Nth intermediate nodes therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>N additional transistors, each of said N additional transistors being coupled between one of said intermediate nodes of said first and second clocked strings and a next higher number intermediate node on an opposite one of said first and second clocked strings, said Nth intermediate node of said first and second clocked strings also being selectively couplable to said first and second nodes of said clocked latch circuit in response to said second clock signal and wherein control terminals of each of said first and second clocked strings of N series coupled transistors and said N additional transistors define logic inputs to said logic gate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said Nth intermediate nodes of said first and second clocked strings are selectively couplable to said first and second nodes of said clocked latch circuit in response to a signal supplied to a control terminal of a transistor coupled between said Nth intermediate node of said first clocked string and said first logic gate output and a signal supplied to a control terminal of another transistor coupled between said Nth intermediate node of said second clocked string and said second logic gate output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said clocked latch circuit comprises cross-coupled inverters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein said cross-coupled inverters comprise CMOS inverters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said first and second clock signals are complementary clock signals.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said clocked latch circuit is selectively couplable between said supply voltage source and said reference voltage source in response to a signal supplied to a control terminal of a transistor coupled in series with said clocked latch circuit and said reference voltage source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein said transistor coupled in series with said clocked latch circuit and said reference voltage source comprises an N-channel device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said first and second clocked strings of N number of series coupled transistors are selectively couplable to said supply voltage source in response to a signal supplied to a control terminal of a transistor coupled in series with each of said first and second clocked strings and said supply voltage source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref> wherein said transistor coupled in series with each of said first and second clocked strings and said supply voltage source comprises a P-channel device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said first and second clocked strings of N number of series coupled transistors are selectively couplable to said reference voltage source in response to a signal supplied to a control terminal of a transistor coupled in series with each of said first and second clocked strings and said reference voltage source.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00022">claim 22</claim-ref> wherein said transistor coupled in series with each of said first and second clocked strings and said reference voltage source comprises an N-channel device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said transistor coupled between said Nth intermediate node of said first clocked string and said first node of said clocked latch circuit and said another transistor coupled between said Nth intermediate node of said second clocked string and said second node of said clocked latch circuit comprise N-channel devices.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein said first and second complementary logic gate outputs represent XOR and XNOR outputs of said logic inputs to said logic gate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. The logic gate of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref> wherein N is greater than two.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
