<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298176-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298176</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11204401</doc-number>
<date>20050816</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>133</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>19</main-group>
<subgroup>20</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326119</main-classification>
<further-classification>326 93</further-classification>
<further-classification>326 27</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Dual-gate dynamic logic circuit with pre-charge keeper</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6204696</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Krishnamurthy et al.</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>326 98</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6429684</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Houston</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>326 83</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6600340</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Krishnamurthy et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>326 98</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00004">
<othercit>Keunwoo, et. al., “Double-Gate CMOS: Symmetrical-Versus Asymmetrical-Gate Devices,” <i>IEEE Transaction on Electron Devices</i>, vol. 48, No. 2, Feb. 2001, pp. 294-299.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00005">
<othercit>Chiang, et. al., “Novel High-Density Low-Power High-Performance Double-Gate Logic Techniques,” <i>2004 IEE International SOI Conference, Charleston, SC</i>, Oct. 4-7, 2004, pp. 122, 123.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>“Taurus-MEDICI, Industry-Standard Device Simulation Tool,” Mountain View, CA, <i>Synopsis, Inc</i>., 2003, pp. 1-7, no month.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326 80</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326 81</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326 93- 98</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326112</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326119</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>326121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070040584</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070222</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ngo</last-name>
<first-name>Hung C.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Austin</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chuang</last-name>
<first-name>Ching-Te</first-name>
<address>
<city>South Salem</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kim</last-name>
<first-name>Keunwoo</first-name>
<address>
<city>Somers</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kuang</last-name>
<first-name>Jente B.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Austin</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Nowka</last-name>
<first-name>Kevin J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Georgetown</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Winstead PC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>International Business Machines Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Armonk</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Le</last-name>
<first-name>Don</first-name>
<department>2819</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A dynamic logic gate has an asymmetrical dual-gate PFET device for charging a dynamic node during a pre-charge phase of a clock. A logic tree evaluates the dynamic node during an evaluate phase of the clock. The front gate of the asymmetrical dual-gate PFET device is coupled to the clock signal and the back gate is coupled to the ground potential of the power supply. When the clock is a logic zero both the front gate and the back gate are biased ON and the dynamic node charges with maximum current. The clock signal transitions to a logic one during the evaluation phase of the clock turning OFF the front gate. The back gate remains ON and the asymmetrical dual-gate PFET device operates as a keeper device with a current level sufficient to counter leakage on the dynamic node.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="108.20mm" wi="149.69mm" file="US07298176-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="152.32mm" wi="138.09mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298176-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="162.90mm" wi="148.34mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298176-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="161.04mm" wi="136.99mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298176-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="163.66mm" wi="141.05mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298176-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="212.17mm" wi="183.47mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298176-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?GOVINT description="Government Interest" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">GOVERNMENT RIGHTS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention was made with Government support under PERCS II, NBCH3039004, BGR W0132280. THE GOVERNMENT HAS CERTAIN RIGHTS IN THIS INVENTION.</p>
<?GOVINT description="Government Interest" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to dynamic logic circuits, and in particular, to dynamic logic circuits using a keeper for holding the state of the dynamic node.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND INFORMATION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Modern data processing systems may perform Boolean operations on a set of signals using dynamic logic circuits. Dynamic logic circuits are clocked. During the precharge phase of the clock, the circuit is preconditioned, typically by precharging an internal node (dynamic node) of the circuit by coupling to a power supply rail. During an evaluate phase of the clock, the Boolean function being implemented by the logic circuit is evaluated in response to the set of input signal values appearing on the inputs during the evaluate phase. (For the purposes herein, it suffices to assume that the input signals have settled to their “steady-state” values for the current clock cycle, recognizing that the input value may change from clock cycle to clock cycle.) Such dynamic logic may have advantages in both speed and the area consumed on the chip over static logic. However, the switching of the output node with the toggling of the phase of the clock, each cycle may consume power even when the logical value of the output is otherwise unchanged.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">This may be appreciated by referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrating an exemplary three-input OR dynamic logic gate. Dynamic logic <b>100</b> includes three inputs A, B and C coupled to a corresponding gate of N channel field effect transistors (NFETs) <b>101</b>-<b>103</b>. During an evaluate phase (logic one) of clock <b>104</b>, NFET <b>106</b> is turned ON, and if any of inputs A, B or C are a logic one, dynamic node <b>108</b> is pulled low (logic zero), and OUT transitions to a logic one via inverter <b>110</b>. During the precharge phase (logic zero) of Clk <b>104</b>, dynamic node <b>108</b> is precharged to a logic one via P channel field effect transistor (PFET) <b>112</b>. Half-latch PFET <b>114</b> maintains the charge on dynamic node <b>108</b> through the evaluate phase unless one or more of inputs A, B or C is turned ON. Consequently, dynamic node <b>108</b> undergoes two discharge-precharge cycles. OUT similarly undergoes two discharge-precharge cycles, albeit with opposite phase. Because OUT is discharged during the precharge phase of dynamic node <b>108</b>, even though the Boolean value of the logical function is “true”, the dynamic logic gate dissipates power even when the input signal states are unchanged.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Dynamic logic may use a footer NFET <b>106</b> or not. In the case the footer NFET <b>106</b> is not used, the inputs A, B, and C must be timed to be valid during the evaluate phase of Clk <b>104</b>. Regardless, dynamic circuits rely on the ability to precharge the dynamic node to a logic one state in advance of having valid logic inputs valid. In logic circuitry with a wide input fan-in, there are many parallel paths in the form of one or more intermediate nodes that may be coupled to the dynamic node by one or more select devices. When a select device connects the intermediate nodes to the dynamic node, leakage current may make it difficult to hold the logic state on the dynamic node until the start of the evaluation cycle. This is especially true as device size decreases.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The sharp increase of leakage currents in scaled technologies severely limits the robustness of dynamic circuits, especially for high fan in wide dynamic gates, commonly employed in the performance critical units of high-performance microprocessors. A strong keeper is necessary in the pre-charged state or after the completion of evaluation to compensate for the larger leakage current and to hold the right state at the dynamic node. However, the use of a strong (large) keeper results in severe contention during the evaluation phase causing significant degradation of the performance. Recently, a “conditional keeper” technique has been proposed in the art where only a small fraction of the keeper is turned ON at the onset of the evaluation phase while a large fraction of the keeper is only turned ON after a delay time and only if the dynamic output remains at a logic one. This scheme reduces the contention during evaluation and thus improves the performance of the dynamic logic gate. Furthermore, the strong keeper improves the noise margin and robustness of the dynamic logic gate. Alternatively, a programmable keeper has been proposed where the effective width of the keeper is optimally programmed based on die leakage to compensate for variations in die-to-die leakage. While effective, both of these techniques result in increased area of the dynamic logic gate and added capacitance to the dynamic node which increase cost and reduce performance.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Therefore, there is a need for a dynamic logic gate with a keeper circuit that operates as a keeper during the evaluation cycle and a pre-charge device during the evaluation cycle that reduces the circuit area.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">A dynamic logic gate has an asymmetrical dual-gate PFET device that operates as a pre-charge device during the pre-charge cycle and a keeper device during the evaluation cycle. The asymmetrical dual-gate PFET has its front gate coupled to the normal clock input and its back gate coupled to a voltage potential. During the pre-charge cycle of the clock, both the front and back gate are ON and the dynamic node is charged with maximum current as the back gate operates to modulate the front gate current. During the evaluation cycle, the back gate holds the dynamic node with a current level that is one tenth to one twentieth the pre-charge current. The NFET evaluation devices sink the keeper current if the dynamic node evaluates to a logic zero. If the dynamic node evaluates to a logic one, the back gate current keeps leakage current from discharging the dynamic node. During testing the clock is high and the dynamic gate operates as a pseudo-NMOS circuitry.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The foregoing has outlined rather broadly the features and technical advantages of the present invention in order that the detailed description of the invention that follows may be better understood. Additional features and advantages of the invention will be described hereinafter which form the subject of the claims of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">For a more complete understanding of the present invention, and the advantages thereof, reference is now made to the following descriptions taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a circuit diagram of a dynamic logic gate configuration with conventional single gate FET devices and a half-latch keeper circuit;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a circuit diagram of a dynamic logic gate configuration with an un-gated keeper device using a single gate FET device;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a circuit schematic of the dynamic logic gate of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> implemented with dual-gate FET devices according to one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is a circuit schematic of the dynamic logic gate of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> implemented with dual-gate FET devices according to another embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a high level block diagram of selected operational blocks within a central processing unit (CPU) suitable for practicing principles of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In the following description, numerous specific details are set forth to provide a thorough understanding of the present invention. For example, specific logic functions and the circuitry for generating them may be described; however, it would be recognized by those of ordinary skill in the art that the present invention may be practiced without such specific details. In other instances, well-known circuits have been shown in block diagram form in order not to obscure the present invention in unnecessary detail. Refer now to the drawings wherein depicted elements are not necessarily shown to scale and wherein like or similar elements are designated by the same reference numeral by the several views.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Refer now to the drawings wherein depicted elements are not necessarily shown to scale and wherein like or similar elements are designated by the same reference numeral through the several views.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Dual or double gate FET devices have been described in the literature. Two references are included in the following which explain differing architectures of dual-gated FET devices including symmetrical and asymmetrical structures. These references explain details of these devices and the size and thus capacitance reduction that results from using a dual-gated FET device in place of two single gate FET devices in appropriate applications. The reader is referred to “Double-Gate CMOS: Symmetrical-Gate Versus Asymmetrical-Gate Devices” IEEE Transactions on Electron Devices, Vol. 48, NO. 2, February 2001 and “Novel High-Density Low-Power High-Performance Double-Gate Logic Techniques”, IEEE International SOI Conference, 2004.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The separate, independent biasing of the front and back gate in double gate devices has been exploited to reduce the number of transistors required for implementing logic functions to improve the performance, power and area of the circuits. Prior art, however, is limited to the “logic” transistors, and not the “keeper” or intermediate node pre-charged device in the dynamic gate.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a circuit diagram illustrating a dynamic logic gate <b>200</b> powered by power supply voltage Vdd <b>216</b> and suitable for practicing principles of the present invention. Clk <b>209</b> has an pre-charge cycle and a evaluation cycle. When Clk <b>209</b> is a logic zero, PFET <b>201</b> turns ON and pre-charges dynamic node <b>208</b> to a logic one. Footer NFET <b>204</b> is turned OFF preventing a logic one state on input <b>212</b> from discharging dynamic node <b>208</b>. During the evaluation cycle Clk <b>209</b> is a logic one and PFET <b>201</b> is turned OFF and NFET <b>204</b> is turned ON. Depending on the logic state of input <b>212</b>, dynamic node <b>208</b> evaluates to either a logic zero or a logic one. If dynamic node <b>208</b> evaluates to a logic one, then keeper PFET <b>202</b> holds the pre-charge state during the evaluation cycle preventing leakage current from discharging the dynamic node <b>208</b>. PFET <b>205</b> and NFET <b>206</b> form a static inverter that isolates the dynamic node and generates Output <b>210</b>. Keeper PFET <b>202</b> is biased ON all the time by ground connection <b>211</b>. If the dynamic node <b>208</b> evaluates to a logic zero, then NFETs <b>203</b> and <b>204</b> must sink the ON state current of PFET <b>202</b> during the evaluation cycle. PFET <b>202</b> is normally sized as a small device as it only has to overcome leakage current. PFET <b>212</b> is sized according to the number of parallel devices coupled to dynamic node <b>208</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a dynamic logic gate <b>300</b> powered by Vdd <b>316</b> and configured using dual-gated FET devices according to embodiments of the present invention, in particular, using pre-charge dual-gated PFET <b>301</b>. Asymmetrical dual-gate PFET <b>301</b> has two functions, it operates as the pre-charge device during the pre-charge cycle of Clk <b>309</b> and operates as the keeper device during the evaluation cycle of Clk <b>309</b> when the logic state of Data <b>312</b> is asserted on dynamic node <b>308</b>. If dual-gate PFET <b>301</b> is an asymmetrical device, back gate <b>326</b> provides a weaker channel than front gate <b>325</b>. However, the channel conduction produced by the front gate <b>325</b> is strongly influenced by the back gate <b>326</b>. When the front gate <b>325</b> is ON and the back gate <b>326</b> is OFF the channel conduction is much lower than if both gates are ON. The conduction of the channel between the source and drain is modulated by the back gate <b>326</b> and the current when both front gate <b>325</b> and back gate <b>326</b> are ON is approximately twice the current when only front gate <b>325</b> is ON.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">During the pre-charge cycle, Clk <b>309</b> is a logic zero and both front gate <b>325</b> and back gate <b>326</b> are a logic zero causing the channel of dual-gate PFET <b>301</b> to have the highest conduction and thus the highest current for pre-charging dynamic node <b>308</b>. During the evaluation cycle, Clk <b>309</b> is a logic one and front gate <b>325</b> is a logic one and back gate <b>326</b> remains a logic zero by virtue of ground connection <b>311</b>. In this case, the conduction current of dual-gate PFET <b>301</b> drops by at least an order of magnitude thus providing holding current to prevent the discharge of dynamic node <b>308</b> by leakage paths from the logic tree (e.g., NFET <b>313</b>) coupled to the dynamic node. Since dual-gate PFET <b>301</b> is much smaller that two single gated PFETs (e.g., PFET <b>301</b> and <b>302</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) with the same function, logic gate <b>300</b> is smaller than logic gate <b>200</b> which has the same functionality. In fact, all of the FET devices in logic gate <b>300</b> are implemented as dual-gate FET devices to reap the benefits of reduced leakages afforded by the asymmetrical dual-gate FET structure.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The dynamic node <b>308</b> is isolated with a static inverter comprising NFET <b>306</b> with back/front gate connection <b>315</b> and PFET <b>305</b> with back/front gate connection <b>316</b>. The output <b>310</b> is generated by the static inverting circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is a logic gate <b>350</b> which is the same as the dynamic logic gate <b>300</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> with the exception that it is modified by coupling the gate of asymmetrical dual-gate NFET <b>304</b> to the positive power supply potential Vdd <b>316</b>. As in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, asymmetrical dual-gate PFET <b>301</b> has two functions, it operates as the pre-charge device during the pre-charge cycle of Clk <b>309</b> and operates as the keeper device during the evaluation cycle of Clk <b>309</b> when the logic state of Data <b>312</b> is asserted on dynamic node <b>308</b>. If dual-gate PFET <b>301</b> is an asymmetrical device, back gate <b>326</b> provides a weaker channel than front gate <b>325</b>. However, the channel conduction produced by the front gate <b>325</b> is strongly influenced by the back gate <b>326</b>. When the front gate <b>325</b> is ON and the back gate <b>326</b> is OFF the channel conduction is much lower than if both gates are ON. The conduction of the channel between the source and drain is modulated by the back gate <b>326</b> and the current when both front gate <b>325</b> and back gate <b>326</b> are ON is approximately twice the current when only front gate <b>325</b> is ON.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">During the pre-charge cycle, Clk <b>309</b> is a logic zero and both front gate <b>325</b> and back gate <b>326</b> are a logic zero causing the channel of dual-gate PFET <b>301</b> to have the highest conduction and thus the highest current for pre-charging dynamic node <b>308</b>. In this circuit configuration, the back gate <b>314</b> of NFET <b>304</b> is coupled to Vdd <b>316</b> to reduce the clock loading by one-half. However, when Clk <b>309</b> is a logic zero, NFET <b>304</b> will conduct the leakage current resulting from the back gate being biased ON with Vdd <b>316</b>. It is important to note that the signals from a preceding stage (e.g., Data <b>312</b>) are a logic zero during their pre-charge cycle. The dynamic node in each preceding dynamic stage, pre-charges to a logic one which the output static inverter converts to a logic zero. Therefore the NFET devices (e.g., NFET <b>313</b>) in the logic tree are not conducting during the time NFET <b>304</b> would have leakage due to back gate <b>314</b> being tied to Vdd <b>316</b>. The evaluation cycle and static inverter output stage of logic gate <b>350</b> is the same as described relative to logic gate <b>300</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a high level functional block diagram of selected operational blocks that may be included in a central processing unit (CPU) <b>400</b>. In the illustrated embodiment, CPU <b>400</b> includes internal instruction cache (I-cache) <b>440</b> and data cache (D-cache) <b>442</b> which are accessible to memory (not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) through bus <b>412</b>, bus interface unit <b>444</b>, memory subsystem <b>438</b>, load/store unit <b>446</b> and corresponding memory management units: data MMU <b>430</b> and instruction MMU <b>432</b>. In the depicted architecture, CPU <b>400</b> operates on data in response to instructions retrieved from I-cache <b>440</b> through instruction dispatch unit <b>448</b>. Dispatch unit <b>448</b> may be included in instruction unit <b>434</b> which may also incorporate fetch unit <b>436</b> and branch processing unit <b>438</b> which controls instruction branching. An instruction queue <b>460</b> may interface fetch unit <b>436</b> and dispatch unit <b>448</b>. In response to dispatched instructions, data retrieved from D-cache <b>442</b> by load/store unit <b>446</b> can be operated upon by one of fixed point unit (FXU) <b>460</b>, FXU <b>462</b> or floating point execution unit (FPU) <b>464</b>. Additionally, CPU <b>400</b> provides for parallel processing of multiple data items via vector execution unit (VXU) <b>466</b>. VXU <b>466</b> includes vector permute unit <b>468</b> which performs permutation operations on vector operands, and vector arithmetic logic unit (VALU) <b>470</b> which performs vector arithmetic operations, which may include both fixed-point and floating-point operations on vector operands. VALU <b>470</b> may be implemented using a dynamic logic gate <b>300</b> or <b>350</b> in accordance with the present inventive principles. Other units may also employ dynamic logic gates configured like dynamic logic gate <b>300</b> or <b>350</b> according to embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Although the present invention and its advantages have been described in detail, it should be understood that various changes, substitutions and alterations can be made herein without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as defined by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A dynamic logic circuit receiving a clock signal and a plurality of logic inputs comprising:
<claim-text>a dynamic node pre-charged in response to a pre-charge phase of a clock signal and a first voltage potential;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a multi-gate field effect transistor (FET) device having a power terminal coupled to a second voltage potential greater than the first voltage potential, a front gate coupled to the clock signal, a back gate coupled to the first voltage potential, and a pre-charge terminal coupled to the dynamic node; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a logic tree for evaluating the dynamic node in response to a Boolean combination of logic signals coupled to the plurality of logic inputs and an evaluation phase of the clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a static logic circuit having an input coupled to the dynamic node and an output generating the logic output of the dynamic logic gate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the multi-gate FET device couples the dynamic node to the second voltage potential with a first conductivity in response to the pre-charge phase of the clock signal and the first voltage potential and couples the dynamic node to the second voltage potential with a second conductivity in response to the evaluate phase of the clock signal and the first voltage potential.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the multi-gate FET device is a dual-gate PFET having a source coupled to the second voltage potential, a drain coupled to the dynamic node, the front gate coupled to the clock signal and the back gate coupled to the first voltage potential.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the static logic circuit is a logic inverter having an input coupled to the dynamic node and generating a logic output of the dynamic logic circuit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the a multi-gate FET device operates as a keeper circuit holding a logic one pre-charge state of the dynamic node when the dynamic node evaluates to a logic one during the evaluation phase of the clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the dual-gate PFET is an asymmetrical dual-gate PFET and a combination of the back gate and the front gate turns ON the dual-gate PFET with the first conductivity, the back gate turns ON the dual-gate PFET with the second conductivity and the first conductivity is greater than the second conductivity.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the dual-gate PFET has P+ polysilicon for the front gate and N+ polysilicon for the back gate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a multi-gate NFET as a footer device for coupling the logic tree to a voltage potential equal to less than the first voltage potential in response to the evaluation phase of the clock signal and the second voltage potential.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The dynamic logic circuit of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the multi-gate NFET is an asymmetrical dual-gate NFET with an N+ polysilicon back gate coupled to the second voltage potential and a P+ polysilicon front gate coupled to the clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A data processing system comprising:
<claim-text>a central processing unit (CPU); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a memory operable for communicating instructions and operand data to the CPU, wherein the CPU includes one or more dynamic logic circuits receiving a clock signal and a plurality of logic inputs and having a dynamic node pre-charged in response to a pre-charge phase of a clock signal and a first voltage potential, a multi-gate field effect transistor (FET) device having a power terminal coupled to a second voltage potential greater than the first voltage potential, a front gate coupled to the clock signal, a back gate coupled to the first voltage potential, and a pre-charge terminal coupled to the dynamic node, and a logic tree for evaluating the dynamic node in response to a Boolean combination of logic signals coupled to the plurality of logic inputs and an evaluation phase of the clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> further comprising a static logic circuit having an input coupled to the dynamic node and generating a logic output of the dynamic logic gate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the multi-gate FET device couples the dynamic node to the second voltage potential with a first conductivity in response to the pre-charge phase of the clock signal and the first voltage potential and couples the dynamic node to the second voltage potential with a second conductivity in response to the evaluate phase of the clock signal and the first voltage potential.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein the multi-gate FET device is a dual-gate PFET having a source coupled to the second voltage potential, a drain coupled to the dynamic node, the front gate coupled to the clock signal and the back gate coupled to the first voltage potential.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the static logic circuit is a logic inverter having an input coupled to the dynamic node and an output generating the logic output of the dynamic logic circuit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the a multi-gate FET device operates as a keeper circuit holding a logic one pre-charge state of the dynamic node when the dynamic node evaluates to a logic one during the evaluation phase of the clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the dual-gate PFET is an asymmetrical dual-gate PFET and a combination of the back gate and the front gate turns ON the dual-gate PFET with the first conductivity, the back gate turns ON the dual-gate PFET with the second conductivity and the first conductivity is greater than the second conductivity.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the dual-gate PFET has P+ polysilicon for the front gate and N+ polysilicon for the back gate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> further comprising a multi-gate NFET as a footer device for coupling the logic tree to a voltage potential equal to less than the first voltage potential in response to the evaluation phase of the clock signal and the second voltage potential.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The data processing system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the multi-gate NFET is an asymmetrical dual-gate NFET with an N+ polysilicon back gate coupled to the second voltage potential and a P+ polysilicon front gate coupled to the clock signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
