<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296606-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296606</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11092924</doc-number>
<date>20050330</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>94201744 U</doc-number>
<date>20050131</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>317</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>E</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>303</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>160115</main-classification>
<further-classification>1601681 R</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Venetian blind slat control mechanism</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2117953</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Grau</name>
<date>19380500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>160114</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3100013</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Randmark</name>
<date>19630800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>1601681 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4377194</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tsuhako</name>
<date>19830300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>1601681 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6648048</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Lai</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>160115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7100664</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hsu</name>
<date>20060900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>160115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7159636</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Liang</name>
<date>20070100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>160115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>160115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>160114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1601661 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1601681 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>160173 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1601761 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>160177 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1601781 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>1601782</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060169420</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060803</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Liang</last-name>
<first-name>Wen Ying</first-name>
<address>
<street>No. 276, Minzu Rd.</street>
<city>Lugang Town, Changhua County</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Chan Law Group LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Purol</last-name>
<first-name>David</first-name>
<department>3634</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A Venetian blind slat control mechanism comprises a set of first string ladders suspended between a head rail and a bottom rail of a Venetian blind for holding a plurality of equally spaced slats thereon before respectively fixed onto a pair of adjusting seats that, having an adjusting shaft mounted thereon, are accommodated at both ends of the head rail therein to tilt the slats into different angles thereby. A lift cord is applied to sequentially thread through cord passages of each slat before wound and suspended from a first pulley seat adapted at one end of the head rail to raise or lower the slats thereby. Between the adjusting seats inside the head rail is situated a positioning seat with a set of guide sliding members accommodated at both sides thereof in linking movement with a linkage actuating plate controlled by an operational cord that is wound and suspended from a second pulley seat adapted at the other end of the head rail. A set of second string ladders whose upper ends are respectively fixed to the guide sliding members thereof are mounted to extend downwards in a U-shaped form to cross the bottom rail, and multiple positioning steps of the second string ladder are applied to hold in place every even/odd-numbered slats thereby. Therefore, the operational cord is simply drawn to trigger the linkage mechanism and synchronically lift the second string ladders so as to alternatively collect and arrange the slats in pairs, facilitating an easier and speedier operation thereof to achieve the best using status.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="135.38mm" wi="262.97mm" file="US07296606-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="261.37mm" wi="191.09mm" file="US07296606-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="242.99mm" wi="180.09mm" file="US07296606-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="255.10mm" wi="169.25mm" file="US07296606-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="257.64mm" wi="184.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296606-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="229.87mm" wi="135.72mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296606-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="265.01mm" wi="155.19mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296606-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="254.17mm" wi="190.33mm" file="US07296606-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention is related to a Venetian blind slat control mechanism, comprising a set of first string ladders suspended between a head rail and a bottom rail of a Venetian blind for holding a plurality of equally spaced slats thereon, and a set of second string ladders whose upper ends are attached to a pair of guide sliding members connected to a linkage actuating plate and controlled by an operational cord attached to the linkage actuating plate thereof; whereby the operational cord is simply drawn to trigger the linkage mechanism thereof and synchronically lift the second string ladders so as to alternatively collect the slats in pairs in an easy and speedy manner without tilting the slats due to uneven pulling force applied thereto. Besides, the operational cord is mounted to one end of the head rail opposite to a lift cord so as to avoid confusing both cords in operation and achieve the best using status thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A conventional Venetian blind slat control mechanism is made up of a Venetian blind <b>10</b> having a first string ladder <b>11</b> and a second string ladder <b>12</b> sequentially mounted to a plurality of slats <b>13</b> and respectively crossing the length of a lower rail <b>14</b> into U-shaped forms. Positioning slide posts <b>151</b> and a first and second pulley seats <b>152</b>, <b>153</b> are respectively disposed at both ends of a head rail <b>15</b> for both ends of the first and second string ladders to respectively wind there-through and extend downwards there-from. When the first string ladder <b>11</b> is pulled downwards, the slats <b>13</b> of odd or even numbers will be actuated to raise upwards, each overlapping with the slat <b>13</b> above in pairs to augment the light-passable space as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. When the second string ladder <b>12</b> is pulled downwards, the slats <b>13</b> will keep gathering up from bottom to top in a sequence. A mounting seat with an adjustment member is adapted inside the head rail <b>15</b> for retaining a ladder tape (without shown in the diagram) to tilt the slats <b>13</b> into different angles thereby.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">There are some drawbacks to such conventional Venetian blind slat control mechanism. First, the first and the second string ladders <b>11</b>, <b>12</b> are suspended downwards from the same side of the head rail <b>15</b>. In practical use, it's easy to confuse the two string ladders <b>11</b>, <b>12</b> and require a repetition of the operation thereof. Besides, in case pulling force is unevenly applied onto both ends of the first or the second string ladders <b>11</b>, <b>12</b>, the slats <b>13</b> can easily get tilted and result in an inconvenient operation thereof. Second, the first string ladder <b>11</b> is wound across the length of the bottom rail <b>14</b> thereof. In case of a great pulling force applied thereto, the first string ladder <b>11</b> tends to raise upwards the bottom rail <b>14</b> and sequentially gather up each slat <b>13</b> from bottom to top, losing the function to pile up the slats <b>13</b> in pairs. Thus, the conventional Venetian blind slats mechanism is more difficult to manipulate in operation thereof. Third, the first string ladder <b>11</b>, winding across the length at the inner side of the bottom rail <b>14</b>, must first actuate the bottom rail <b>14</b> before extending through the first pulley seat <b>152</b> to suspend downwards there-from, which can waste quite a lot of efforts and pains in the operation thereof.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">It is, therefore, the primary purpose of the present invention to provide a Venetian blind slat control mechanism wherein, via guide sliding members with upper ends of second string ladders fixed thereto, and a linkage actuating plate connected with the guide sliding members and controlled by an operational cord attached thereto, the operational cord is simply drawn to trigger the linkage movement of the guide sliding members and synchronically lift the second string ladders in an easy and speedy manner without tilting slats of a Venetian blind due to uneven pulling force applied thereto. Besides, the operational cord is individually mounted to one end of a head rail opposite to a lift cord at the other end thereof as to as to avoid confusing both thereof in operation and achieve the best using status thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is, therefore, the second purpose of the present invention to provide a Venetian blind slat control mechanism wherein the operational cord is simply drawn to move the linkage actuating plate along with the guide sliding members and synchronically lift the second string ladders so as to alternatively collect the slats so as to alternatively collect and arrange the slats in pairs, facilitating an easier and speedier operation thereof to achieve the best using status.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a sectional view of a conventional blind slat control mechanism.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a diagram showing the conventional blind slat control mechanism in practical use.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an exploded perspective view of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional assembled view of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a partially enlarged and cross sectional assembled view of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a diagram showing an operational cord of the present invention drawn downwards in practical use thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a diagram showing slats of the present invention alternatively collected into pairs and positioned in the status thereof.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The present invention is related to a Venetian blind slat control mechanism, including a positioning seat <b>20</b>, guide sliding members <b>30</b>, and a linkage actuating plate <b>40</b>. The positioning seat <b>20</b> is made up of a guide cavity <b>21</b> internally cut downwards from the top with a lateral opening disposed at one side thereof, a pivotal retaining groove <b>22</b> concaved at the other lateral side wall opposite to the lateral opening of the guide cavity <b>21</b> thereof, and a right-angle recessed slot <b>23</b> properly cut at the lateral side wall under the pivotal retaining groove <b>22</b> thereof to form a guide board <b>24</b> at the bottom side of the guide cavity <b>21</b> thereof. A slide rod <b>25</b> is pivotally mounted at a predetermined position at one side of the recessed slot <b>23</b> thereof, and a plurality of coupling blocks <b>26</b> are disposed protruding downwards at the bottom surface of the guide board <b>24</b> to be engaged with an assembly hole <b>511</b> disposed at the interior of a head rail <b>51</b> of a Venetian blind <b>50</b> for secure abutting location of the positioning seat <b>20</b> thereon. The guide sliding member <b>30</b> is equipped with a hooked inserting block <b>31</b> protruding upwards in the middle section thereof, a pair of protrusive coupling posts <b>32</b> with indented retaining grooves <b>33</b> symmetrically disposed at both sides of the hooked inserting block <b>31</b> thereof, and a pivoting tube <b>35</b> with an inner guide thru-hole <b>34</b> defined therein symmetrically extending right beneath the hooked inserting block <b>31</b> in vertical alignment therewith. The linkage actuating plate <b>40</b> is made of a flexible plate body having an inserting slot <b>41</b> aligned side by side with a plurality of symmetrical inserting holes <b>42</b> properly disposed at the surface of both lateral sides thereon respectively to mate precisely with the hooked inserting block <b>31</b> and the coupling posts <b>32</b> of the guide sliding member <b>30</b> thereof, and a positioning cord hole <b>43</b> disposed at a predetermined position thereon.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 to 5</figref> inclusive. In assembly as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a set of first string ladders <b>53</b> are suspended between the head rail <b>51</b> and a bottom rail <b>52</b> of the Venetian blind <b>50</b> for holding a plurality of equally spaced slats <b>64</b> in abutting location thereon. A lift cord <b>55</b>, sequentially led through each slat <b>54</b> thereof and fixedly attached to the bottom rail <b>52</b> at the bottom end thereof, is guided across the interior of the head rail <b>51</b> to wind through a first pulley seat <b>512</b> adapted at one end of the head rail <b>51</b> therein and extend downwards there-from. The upper ends of each first string ladder <b>53</b> are wound and fixed to an adjusting seat <b>56</b> that, having an adjusting shaft <b>561</b> mounted thereto, is accommodated at each lateral end of the head rail <b>51</b> so as to tilt the slats <b>54</b> into different angles thereby. The positioning seat <b>20</b> is then placed into the head rail <b>51</b> till the coupling blocks <b>26</b> thereof are securely fixed to the assembly hole <b>511</b> thereof, permitting the lift cord <b>55</b> extending at the outermost side of the first pulley seat <b>512</b> thereof to sequentially pass through the recessed slot <b>23</b> of the positioning seat <b>20</b> and extend along the guide board <b>24</b> thereof till reaching an adjusting seat <b>56</b> to wind around the first pulley seat <b>512</b> and suspend downwards there-from. A guide sliding member <b>30</b> is then applied with the pivoting tube <b>35</b> thereof mounted onto the retaining groove <b>22</b> from the side of the guide cavity <b>21</b> thereof before another guide sliding member <b>30</b> is accommodated from the other side to situate at an appropriate position between the retaining groove <b>22</b> of the positioning seat <b>20</b> and the adjusting seat <b>56</b> thereof, permitting the adjusting shaft <b>561</b> thereof to pivotally thread through the guide thru-holes <b>34</b> of both guide sliding members <b>30</b> thereof. At the corresponding sides of each first string ladder <b>63</b> is mounted a second string ladder <b>63</b>′ suspended downwards in a U-shaped form to cross the bottom rail <b>52</b> thereof and provided with a plurality of positioning steps <b>531</b>′ to hold in place alternatively every even/odd-numbered slats <b>54</b> thereby. Both ends of the second string ladder <b>53</b>′ are respectively led upwards through a cord passage hole <b>562</b> of the adjusting seat <b>56</b> thereof and correspondingly guided towards the adjacent guide sliding member <b>30</b> till fixed onto the retaining grooves <b>323</b> thereof respectively. One of the second string ladder <b>53</b>′ is first wound around the slide post <b>25</b> of the positioning seat <b>20</b> (referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) so as to form a guide sliding effect thereby. Then, the inserting slots <b>41</b> and the inserting holes <b>42</b> disposed at both lateral end surface of the linkage actuating plate <b>40</b> are mounted from top to bottom to engage with the hooked inserting block <b>31</b> and the coupling posts <b>32</b> of both guide sliding members <b>30</b> respectively, permitting the linkage actuating plate <b>40</b> to precisely locate on the top side of the positioning seat <b>31</b> thereof so as to actuate both guide sliding members <b>30</b> in a linkage movement thereby. An operational cord <b>60</b> is applied to thread through and fixedly attach to the positioning cord hole <b>43</b> of the linkage actuating plate <b>40</b> before guided along the upper edge of the linkage actuating plate <b>40</b> inside the head rail <b>51</b> to wind around a second pulley seat <b>61</b> disposed at the other end of the head rail <b>51</b> and suspend downward there-from to complete the assembly of the present invention thereof. Therefore, the lift cord <b>55</b> thereof is drawn downwards or released to collect or expand the slats <b>54</b> thereby.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. To increase the light-passable space of the slats <b>54</b> thereof, the operational cord <b>60</b> is pulled downwards to trigger the movement of the linkage actuating plate <b>40</b> that in turn will actuate the guide sliding members <b>30</b> to synchronically slide along the guide cavity <b>21</b> of the positioning seat <b>20</b> towards the second pulley seat <b>61</b> thereof. Along with the sliding movement of the guide sliding members <b>32</b> thereof, the second string ladder <b>53</b>′ with both ends securely fixed at the retaining grooves <b>33</b> therein is actuated to lift upwards therewith, synchronically raising the even/odd-numbered slats <b>54</b> held in place by the positioning steps <b>531</b>′ of the second string ladder <b>63</b>′ thereof to abut against the immediate upper slat <b>54</b> thereof respectively and piled up in pairs. Then, the pulling force is removed to securely clamp the operational cord <b>60</b> via the second pulley seat <b>61</b> and precisely relocate the second string ladders <b>63</b>′ at the lift position thereof. Thus, the slats <b>54</b> of the Venetian blind <b>50</b> can be alternatively collected and arranged in pairs with the light-passable space accurately increased so as to adjust the light coming indoors as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. Via the guide sliding members <b>30</b> with the second string ladders <b>53</b>′ and the linkage actuating plate <b>40</b> connected thereto in a linkage mechanism, the operational cord <b>60</b> is simply pulled to actuate the guide sliding members <b>30</b> and synchronically lift upwards the second string ladders <b>53</b>′ therewith, efficiently refraining from the risk of tilting the slats <b>54</b> due to uneven pulling force applied thereto in operation to achieve the best using status thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">To expand the Venetian blind <b>50</b> downwards again, the operational cord <b>60</b> is drawn to one side to detach from the clamping location of the second pulley seat <b>61</b> thereof before the pulling force thereof is properly removed there-from, permitting the second string ladders <b>53</b>′ affected by the gravity of the slats <b>54</b>′ to generate a down-pulling force thereby. The guide sliding members <b>30</b> along with the second string ladders <b>53</b>′ actuated by the descending gravity of the slats <b>54</b> thereof will drag along the linkage actuating plate <b>40</b> connected therewith, permitting both guide sliding members <b>30</b> to respectively slide back to their former positions in abutting location by the positioning seat <b>20</b> thereof, and the second string ladders <b>53</b>′ to synchronically descend therewith so as to release the collected slats <b>54</b> in the expanding operation thereof.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A Venetian blind slat control mechanism, wherein a set of first string ladders are suspended between a head rail and a bottom rail of a Venetian blind for holding a plurality of equally spaced slats in abutting location thereon, and at both ends inside the head rail thereof is respectively disposed an adjusting seat with an adjusting shaft mounted thereon to tilt the slats into different angles thereby; a lift cord is configured to be sequentially threaded through cord passages of each slat and wound through a first pulley seat adapted at one end of the head rail therein and suspended downwards there-from so as to raise or lower the slats thereby in the collecting or expanding operation thereof; a positioning seat is mounted between the adjusting seats thereof inside the head rail, and a set of guide sliding members is situated at both sides of the positioning seat wherein the upper edge of each guide sliding member is securely engaged with a linkage actuating plate controlled by an operational cord; a set of second string ladders whose upper ends are respectively fixed to the guide sliding members thereof are mounted to extend downwards in a U-shaped form to cross the bottom rail, and multiple positioning steps of the second string ladder are configured to hold in place alternately every even/odd-numbered slats thereby; the operational cord fixedly attached to a positioning cord hole of the linkage actuating plate is guided along from one end of the head rail to wind around a second pulley seat disposed at the other end of the head rail and suspend downward there-from; the operational cord drawn to trigger the movement of the linkage actuating plate and synchronically actuate both guide sliding members that lift upwards the second string ladders with each odd/even-numbered slat raised therewith to abut against the immediate upper slat respectively in pairs; wherein the lift cord and the operational cord are separately mounted at both opposite ends of the head rail respectively.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The Venetian blind slat control mechanism as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the positioning seat is made up of a guide cavity internally cut downwards from the top with a lateral opening disposed at one side thereof; a pivotal retaining groove concaved at the other lateral side wall opposite to the lateral opening of the guide cavity thereof; a right-angle recessed slot disposed at the lateral side wall under the retaining groove thereof to form a guide board at the bottom side of the guide cavity thereof; and a slide rod pivotally mounted at a predetermined position at one side of the recessed slot thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The Venetian blind slat control mechanism as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the guide sliding member is configured with a hooked inserting block protruding upwards in the middle section thereof, a pair of protrusive coupling posts with indented retaining grooves symmetrically disposed at both sides of the hooked inserting block thereof, and a pivoting tube with an inner guide thru-hole defined therein symmetrically extending right beneath the hooked inserting block in vertical alignment therewith.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The Venetian blind slat control mechanism as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the linkage actuating plate has an inserting slot aligned side by side with a plurality of symmetrical inserting holes disposed at the surface of both lateral sides thereon respectively, and a positioning cord hole disposed at a predetermined position thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The Venetian blind slat control mechanism as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the linkage actuating plate is fabricated from a flexible plate body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The Venetian blind slat control mechanism as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the positioning seat has a plurality of coupling blocks protruding downwards at the bottom surface of the guide board thereof to be engaged with an assembly hole disposed at the interior of the head rail for secure abutting location of the positioning seat thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A window blind system comprising:
<claim-text>a head rail having a first securing device and a second securing device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a bottom rail, wherein the bottom rail is suspended from the head rail;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first plurality of slats and a second plurality of slats horizontally disposed between the head rail and the bottom rail, wherein each of the first plurality of slats is positioned between each of the second plurality of slats;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a set of first string ladders connected between the head rail and the bottom rail for supporting each of the first plurality of slats and each of the second plurality of slats, wherein each string ladder further comprises a first string, a second string, and a first plurality of steps connected horizontally therebetween;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of lift cords, each lift cord having a first end and a second end, wherein each of the second ends of each lift cord is connected to the bottom rail and wherein each of the lift cords is adjustably secured by the first securing means to position the bottom rail at an adjustable location below the head rail;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an adjusting shaft for tilting the first plurality of slats and the second plurality of slats; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a linkage actuating plate located in the head rail for raising and lowering the second plurality of slats, wherein the linkage actuating plate slides between a first operational position and a second operational position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The window blind system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the adjusting shaft differentially adjusts the length of the first and the length of the second string of each set of the first string ladders thereby angling the first set of steps relative to the horizontal position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The window blind system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>a set of second string ladders connected between the head rail and the bottom rail for supporting each of the second plurality of slats and an operational cord connected to the linkage actuating plate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each string ladder set of second string ladders further comprises a third string, a fourth string, and a second plurality of steps connected horizontally therebetween for supporting the each of the second plurality of slats;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each third string and each fourth string of the set of second string ladders is connected to the linkage actuating plate such that when the linkage actuating plate is in the first operational position, each of the second plurality of steps is in a first lowered position below the head rail, and when the linkage actuating plate is in the second operational position, each of the second plurality of steps is in a second lowered position below the head rail; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the operational cord is connected to the linkage actuating plate for sliding the linkage actuating plate between the first operational position and the second operational position, and the operational cord is adjustably secured to the second securing means to secure the linkage actuating plate in any intermediate position between the first operational position and the second operational positions.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A Venetian blind slat control apparatus for a window blind having a head rail, a bottom rail, a first plurality of horizontal slats, and a second plurality of horizontal slats, the slat control apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a linkage actuating plate slideably located in the head rail;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an operational cord connected to the linkage actuating plate for sliding the linkage actuating plate between a first operational position and a second operational position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a connecting means for connecting each of the second plurality of slats to the linkage actuating plate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a securing device connected to the operational cord for adjustably securing the linkage actuating plate to any position between the first operational and the second operational positions,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the bottom rail is suspended beneath the head rail, wherein the each of the first plurality of slats is alternately disposed between each of the second plurality of slats, and wherein each of the first plurality and second plurality of slats is suspended horizontally between the head rail and the bottom rail; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the second plurality of slats is in a first lowered position when the linkage actuating plate is in the first operational position, and each of the second plurality of slats is in a second lowered position when the linkage actuating plate is in the second operational position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The Venetian blind slat control apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein each of the slats of the second plurality of slats abuts the adjacent slat of the first plurality of slats when each of the slats of the second position is in the second lowered position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A Venetian blind slat control apparatus for a window blind having a head rail, a bottom rail, a first plurality of horizontal slats, and a second plurality of horizontal slats, wherein the bottom rail is suspended beneath the head rail, wherein the each of the first plurality of slats is alternately disposed between each of the second plurality of slats, and wherein each of the first plurality and second plurality of slats is suspended horizontally between the head rail and the bottom rail, the slat control apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a means for moving each of the second plurality of slats from a first lowered position to a second lowered position, wherein each of the slats of the second plurality of slats abuts the adjacent slat of the first plurality of slats when each of the slats of the second position is in the second lowered position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the means for moving each of the second plurality of slats further comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>a linkage actuating plate slidably located in the head rail;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a means for connecting each of the second plurality of slats to the linkage actuating plate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a means for sliding the linkage actuating plate between a first operational position and a second operational position, and for adjustable securing the linkage actuating plate in any intermediate position, wherein each of the second plurality of slats is in the first lowered position when the linkage actuating plate is in the first operational position and is in the second lowered position when the linkage actuating plate is in the second operational position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
