<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296892-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296892</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11015417</doc-number>
<date>20041220</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-425965</doc-number>
<date>20031222</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>401</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>61</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351200</main-classification>
<further-classification>351202</further-classification>
<further-classification>351209</further-classification>
<further-classification>351210</further-classification>
<further-classification>351246</further-classification>
<further-classification>351211</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Ocular accommodative function examination apparatus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5463430</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Isogai et al.</name>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351208</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6120461</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Smyth</name>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>600558</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6361168</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Fujieda</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>351208</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003070740</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>A 2003-070740</doc-number>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>Suzuki et al., “Evaluation of Accommodative Function by High Frequency Component of Accomodative Microfluctuation,” <i>Jpn. J. Vis. Sci.</i>, vol. 22, No. 3, pp. 93-97 (Nov. 8, 2001).</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>351200-247</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050174536</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050811</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hanaki</last-name>
<first-name>Miwako</first-name>
<address>
<city>Gamagori</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Isogai</last-name>
<first-name>Naoki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Nishio</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hayashi</last-name>
<first-name>Akihiro</first-name>
<address>
<city>Toyokawa</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Oliff &amp; Berridge, PLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nidek Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Gamagori</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Sugarman</last-name>
<first-name>Scott J.</first-name>
<department>2873</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Greece</last-name>
<first-name>James R</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An ocular accommodative function examination apparatus for examining an accommodative function of an examinee's eye, comprises: a fixation target presenting optical system which presents a fixation target at a presenting position to the eye, the presenting position being changeable in a direction of a visual axis of the eye; a refractive power measuring optical system which measures refractive power of the eye and includes a light projecting optical system which includes a light source and projects examination light to a fundus of the eye and a light receiving optical system which includes a light receiving element and receives the examination light reflected from the fundus; an analysis part which acquires variation in the refractive power of the eye gazing at the fixation target at a certain presenting position within a predetermined time based on output of the light receiving element, and determines the accommodative function including a range of accommodation and HFC (a frequency of occurrence of a high frequency component of accommodative microfluctuation) of the eye based on an acquired result; and an output part which outputs a result determined by the analysis part, wherein the analysis part determines presence/absence of accommodative constriction and presence/absence of accommodative spasm based on the determined range of accommodation and HFC.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="151.98mm" wi="228.77mm" file="US07296892-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="231.90mm" wi="163.66mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296892-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="220.30mm" wi="173.14mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296892-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="168.66mm" wi="154.18mm" file="US07296892-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="179.58mm" wi="151.81mm" file="US07296892-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="234.78mm" wi="154.60mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296892-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="261.03mm" wi="180.00mm" file="US07296892-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an ocular accommodative function examination apparatus for examining an accommodative function of an examinee's eye.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">When refractive power of an eye of an examinee who gazes at a target is objectively observed with time, the refractive power exhibits fluctuation like a sine wave, called accommodative microfluctuation. This accommodative microfluctuation is separated into a high frequency component (1.0 Hz-2.3 Hz) and a low frequency component (less than 0.6 Hz). In recent years, attention has been given to that the “a frequency of occurrence of the high frequency component” (hereinafter, HFC) of the accommodative microfluctuation has certain correlation with the degree of accommodative constriction (inertia of accommodation); e.g., the HFC increases as a burden (constriction) on the ciliary muscle becomes larger. Based on this point of view, there has been proposed a method for examining the degree of the accommodative constriction by examining the HFC (see “Evaluation of accommodative function by HFC of accommodative microfluctuation”, Visual Science, Vol. 22 No. 3). Because it is thought that accommodation abnormal is one of causes of asthenopia, knowing the degree of the accommodative constriction is meaningful.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The present invention has been made in view of the above circumstances and has an object to provide an ocular accommodative function examination apparatus capable of efficiently and precisely examining an accommodative function of an eye.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Additional objects and advantages of the invention will be set forth in part in the description which follows and in part will be obvious from the description, or may be learned by practice of the invention. The objects and advantages of the invention may be realized and attained by means of the instrumentalities and combinations particularly pointed out in the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">To solve the above problems, according to the invention, there is provided an ocular accommodative function examination apparatus for examining an accommodative function of an examinee's eye, comprising: a fixation target presenting optical system which presents a fixation target at a presenting position to the eye, the presenting position being changeable in a direction of a visual axis of the eye; a refractive power measuring optical system which measures refractive power of the eye and includes a light projecting optical system which includes a light source and projects examination light to a fundus of the eye and a light receiving optical system which includes a light receiving element and receives the examination light reflected from the fundus; an analysis part which acquires variation in the refractive power of the eye gazing at the fixation target at a certain presenting position within a predetermined time based on output of the light receiving element, and determines the accommodative function including a range of accommodation and HFC (a frequency of occurrence of a high frequency component of accommodative microfluctuation) of the eye based on an acquired result; and an output part which outputs a result determined by the analysis part, wherein the analysis part determines presence/absence of accommodative constriction and presence/absence of accommodative spasm based on the determined range of accommodation and HFC.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The accompanying drawings, which are incorporated in and constitute a part of this specification illustrate an embodiment of the invention and, together with the description, serve to explain the objects, advantages and principles of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In the drawings,</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic structural view of an ocular accommodative function examination apparatus;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic structural diagram of optical systems disposed in a right-eye examination unit;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic block diagram of a control system of the examination apparatus;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view explaining rotation of right and left movable mirrors according to convergence amounts of right and left eyes;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an example of a display showing results of analysis of an accommodative function; and</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a flowchart explaining automatic determination on symptoms of the accommodative function.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">A detailed description of a preferred embodiment of the present invention will now be given referring to the accompanying drawings. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic structural view of an ocular accommodative function examination apparatus in the embodiment of the invention. This apparatus is capable of simultaneously examining (measuring) both eyes.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The apparatus is provided with a right-eye examination unit <b>10</b>R in which an optical system for examining a right eye ER of an examinee is disposed and a left-eye examination unit <b>10</b>L in which an optical system for examining a left eye EL of the examinee is disposed. The examination unit <b>10</b>R is mounted on a fixed base <b>2</b> so that it is movable in three dimensional directions; a right-and-left direction (X-direction), an up-and-down direction (Y-direction), and a back-and-forth direction (Z-direction) with respect to the eye ER. The examination unit <b>10</b>L is mounted to be movable in three dimensional directions with respect to the eye EL. A moving part <b>11</b>R moves the examination unit <b>10</b>R in the three dimensional directions, while a moving part <b>11</b>L moves the examination unit <b>10</b>L in the three dimensional directions. Each of the moving parts <b>11</b>R and <b>11</b>L is constructed of a sliding mechanism, a motor, and others for movement in each direction. The examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L may be arranged to be movable in the three dimensional directions in a suspended state from an arm or the like. A position detecting part <b>12</b>R detects the position of the examination unit <b>10</b>R in the three dimensional directions, while a position detecting part <b>12</b>L detects the position of the examination unit <b>10</b>L in the three dimensional directions. Detected positional information is utilized for detection of a pupillary distance between the eyes ER and EL, and others.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In the examination unit <b>10</b>R, an eye refractive power measuring optical system <b>20</b>R, an alignment target projecting optical system <b>45</b>R, an observation optical system <b>50</b>R which is also used for alignment target detection, a fixation target presenting optical system <b>55</b>R, and a movable mirror <b>15</b>R are disposed. In the examination unit <b>10</b>L, an eye refractive power measuring optical system <b>20</b>L, an alignment target projecting optical system <b>45</b>L, an observation optical system <b>50</b>L which is also used for alignment target detection, a fixation target presenting optical system <b>55</b>L, and a movable mirror <b>15</b>L are disposed.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic structural view of optical systems disposed in the examination unit <b>10</b>R. The measuring optical system <b>20</b>R includes a light projecting optical system which projects spot-shaped examination (measurement) light to a fundus through the center portion of the pupil of the eye ER and a light receiving optical system which receives the examination light reflected from the fundus through the peripheral portion of the pupil.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The light projecting optical system includes an infrared point light source <b>21</b>R such as LED, SLD, or the like, a relay lens <b>22</b>R, a hole mirror <b>23</b>R, and an objective lens <b>24</b>R for examination (measurement), which are disposed on an optical axis L<b>1</b>. The light source <b>21</b>R is in an optically and substantially conjugate positional relation with the fundus of the emmetropic eye ER. A hole portion of the mirror <b>23</b>R is in an optically and substantially conjugate positional relation with the pupil of the eye ER. The mirror <b>15</b>R is placed in front of the eye ER. A dichroic mirror (or a half mirror) <b>19</b>R is disposed between the mirror <b>15</b>R and the lens <b>24</b>R. The mirror <b>19</b>R has the property of reflecting visible light and near-infrared light while allowing infrared light to pass therethrough, thereby guiding near-infrared reflection light from an anterior segment of the eye ER to the observation optical system <b>50</b>R by reflection, guiding visible fixation target light from the fixation target presenting optical system <b>55</b>R (a light source <b>59</b>R) to the eye ER by reflection, and guiding infrared examination light from the light projecting optical system (the light source <b>21</b>R) to the eye ER by transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The light receiving optical system uses the lens <b>24</b>R and the mirror <b>23</b>R in common with the light projecting optical system and includes a relay lens <b>25</b>R and a reflection mirror <b>26</b>R, which are disposed on the optical axis L<b>1</b> in a reflecting direction of the mirror <b>23</b>R, a light receiving diaphragm <b>27</b>R, a collimator lens <b>28</b>R, a ring lens <b>29</b>R, and an image pick-up element <b>30</b>R which is a two-dimensional light-receiving element such as a CCD or the like, which are disposed on the optical axis L<b>1</b> in a reflecting direction of the mirror <b>26</b>R. The diaphragm <b>27</b>R and the image pick-up element <b>30</b>R are in an optically and substantially conjugate positional relation with the fundus of the eye ER.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The ring lens <b>29</b>R is constructed of a lens part having a cylindrical lens formed in a ring shape on one side of a transparent flat plate and a shielding part formed of shielding coating applied to the one side other than the ring shaped cylindrical lens part. With this construction, the lens <b>29</b>R is formed with a ring-shaped aperture. The ring-shaped aperture of the lens <b>29</b>R is in an optically and substantially conjugate positional relation with the pupil of the eye ER. On this account, the examination light reflected from the fundus is taken out, through the peripheral portion of the pupil, in a ring shape by the lens <b>29</b>R (the ring-shaped aperture). When parallel light enters in the lens <b>29</b>R, a ring image of the same size with the ring-shaped aperture is formed on the image pick-up element <b>30</b>R disposed in a focal position of the lens <b>29</b>R. The lens part and the shielding part of the lens <b>29</b>R may be constructed of separate members.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The light source <b>21</b>R of the light projecting optical system and the diaphragm <b>27</b>R, lens <b>28</b>R, lens <b>29</b>R, and image pick-up element <b>30</b>R of the light receiving optical system are integrally movable as a movable unit <b>31</b>R along the optical axis L<b>1</b>. This movable unit <b>31</b>R is moved according to a spherical refractive error (a spherical refractive power) of the eye ER to correct the spherical refractive error, so that the light source <b>21</b>R, diaphragm <b>27</b>R, and image pick-up element <b>30</b>R are brought in an optically and substantially conjugate positional relation with respect to the fundus. The movement position of the movable unit <b>31</b>R is detected by a potentiometer. The mirror <b>23</b>R and the lens <b>29</b>R are disposed to establish an optically and substantially conjugate positional relation with the pupil at a fixed magnification, independently of the movement amount of the movable unit <b>31</b>R.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The alignment target projecting optical system <b>45</b>R includes two first projecting optical systems disposed symmetrically with respect to the optical axis L<b>1</b> and two second projecting optical systems disposed symmetrically with respect to the optical axis L<b>1</b> at a smaller angle than the first projecting optical systems. The first projecting optical systems have near-infrared point light sources <b>46</b><i>a</i>R and <b>46</b><i>b</i>R such as an LED or the like and collimator lenses <b>47</b><i>a</i>R and <b>47</b><i>b</i>R and project an infinite alignment target to the eye ER by substantially parallel light. On the other hand, the second projecting optical systems have near-infrared point light sources <b>46</b><i>c</i>R and <b>46</b><i>d</i>R such as an LED or the like and project a finite alignment target to the eye ER by divergent light.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The observation optical system <b>50</b>R includes an objective lens <b>51</b>R for observation, a dichroic mirror (or a half mirror) <b>52</b>R having the property of reflecting near-infrared light while allowing visible light to pass therethrough, a photographing lens <b>53</b>R, and an image pick-up element <b>54</b>R such as a CCD or the like, which are disposed on an optical axis L<b>2</b> made coaxial with the optical axis L<b>1</b> by the mirror <b>19</b>R. An image of the anterior segment of the eye ER formed by near-infrared light source not shown for illumination of the anterior segment is formed on an image pick-up surface of the image pick-up element <b>54</b>R via the mirror <b>15</b>R through the lens <b>53</b>R and then displayed as an observation image on a monitor <b>7</b> mentioned later. The observation optical system <b>50</b>R is also used as an optical system for detecting an alignment target image formed on the cornea of the eye ER.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The fixation target presenting optical system <b>55</b>R uses the lens <b>51</b>R and the mirror <b>52</b> in common with the observation optical system <b>50</b>R and includes a visible light source <b>59</b>R, a fixation target plate <b>58</b>R, a light-projection lens <b>57</b>R, and a reflection mirror <b>56</b>R, which are disposed on the optical axis L<b>2</b> in a transmitting direction of the mirror <b>52</b>R. The light source <b>59</b>R and the fixation target plate <b>58</b>R are moved along the optical axis L<b>2</b> to optically change a presenting position (a presenting distance) of a fixation target along the visual axis of the eye ER. At the time of measurement of eye refractive power, fogging is applied for removing accommodation of the eye ER. Fixation target light provided by illumination of a fixation target (a stimulating target) of the fixation target plate <b>58</b>R by the light source <b>59</b>R is projected to the eye ER via the lens <b>57</b>R through the mirror <b>15</b>R. Thus, the eye ER can perform fixation. Instead of moving the light source <b>59</b>R and the fixation target plate <b>58</b>R, the lens disposed on the optical axis L<b>2</b> may be moved along the optical axis L<b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The mirror <b>15</b>R is rotated by a motor <b>16</b> according to convergence of the eye ER for near view, thereby changing a direction of light to be projected to the eye ER and light reflected from the eye ER.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Since the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L are basically symmetrical, the construction of the optical systems disposed in the examination unit <b>10</b>L corresponds to that in the examination unit <b>10</b>R by changing the reference numerals of optical members and others from “R” to “L” and therefore its explanation is omitted. The fixation target plate <b>58</b>R of the examination unit <b>10</b>R and the fixation target plate <b>58</b>L of the examination unit <b>10</b>L have identical fixation targets. Consequently, even in a simultaneous binocular examination (measurement), an examinee can view the simultaneously presented fixation targets as a single fixation target by fusion.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic block diagram of a control system of the apparatus. An output signal (an image signal) from the image pick-up element <b>54</b>R is inputted to an analysis and control part <b>70</b> through an image processing part <b>71</b>R. An output signal (an image signal) from the image pick-up element <b>54</b>L is inputted to the analysis and control part <b>70</b> through an image processing part <b>71</b>L. The analysis and control part <b>70</b> detects an alignment state (positional information) of the examination unit <b>10</b>R with respect to the eye ER based on an alignment target image detected and processed in the image processing part <b>71</b>R and detects an alignment state (position information) of the examination unit <b>10</b>L with respect to the eye EL based on an alignment target image detected and processed in the image processing part <b>71</b>L. On the monitor <b>7</b>, the anterior segment images of the eyes ER and EL picked up by the image pick-up elements <b>54</b>R and <b>54</b>L are displayed selectively or in two screens. An output signal (an image signal) from the image pick-up element <b>30</b>R is inputted to the analysis and control part <b>70</b> through an image processing part <b>72</b>R. An output signal (an image signal) from the image pick-up element <b>30</b>L is inputted to the analysis and control part <b>70</b> through an image processing part <b>72</b>L. The analysis and control part <b>70</b> obtains refractive power of the eye ER based on a ring image detected and processed in the image processing part <b>72</b>R and obtains refractive power of the eye EL based on a ring image detected and processed in the image processing part <b>72</b>L. Further, the analysis and control part <b>70</b> is connected to a moving part <b>60</b>R which moves the light source <b>59</b>R and the fixation target plate <b>58</b>R along the optical axis L<b>2</b>, a moving part <b>60</b>L which moves the light source <b>59</b>L and the fixation target plate <b>58</b>L along the optical axis L<b>2</b>, a motor <b>16</b>R which rotates the mirror <b>15</b>R, a motor <b>16</b>L which rotates the mirror <b>15</b>L, the moving parts <b>11</b>R and <b>11</b>L, the position detecting parts <b>12</b>R and <b>12</b>L, a switch part <b>80</b> including various input switches, a joystick <b>81</b> serving as operating means for moving the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L in the X- and Z-directions, a rotary knob <b>82</b> serving as operating means for moving the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L in the Y-direction, a memory <b>84</b>, and others.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The examination of an accommodative function using the apparatus constructed as above is explained. The examinee rests his head on a head support unit not shown. After that, the examination unit <b>10</b>R is aligned to the eye ER and the examination unit <b>10</b>L is aligned to the eye EL, respectively. This embodiment exemplifies the case where an automatic alignment mode and an automatic tracking mode are selected.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Firstly, regular measurement for distance refractive power is executed. While observing images of the anterior segments of the eyes ER and EL both displayed on the monitor <b>7</b>, an examiner operates the joystick <b>81</b> and the rotary knob <b>82</b> to move the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L in the X-, Y-, and Z-directions by the moving parts <b>11</b>R and <b>11</b>L for rough alignment. The examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L are arranged to be simultaneously or separately moved. For separate movement, a separate movement mode is set by the switch on the switch part <b>8</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">When four alignment target images formed by the alignment target projecting optical system <b>45</b>R are picked up by the image pick-up element <b>54</b>R, the automatic alignment and the automatic tracking of the examination unit <b>10</b>R with respect to the eye ER are performed. The analysis and control part <b>70</b> determines whether an alignment state of the examination unit <b>10</b>R with respect to the eye ER in the X- and Y-directions is proper based on a result of the detection of each target image. The determination of the alignment state in the X- and Y-directions is conducted by a comparison between the center position of two infinite target images formed by the first projecting optical systems and the position of the optical axis L<b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The determination of the alignment state in the Z-direction is executed by a comparison between an image distance of two infinite target images formed by the first projecting optical systems and an image distance of two finite target images formed by the second projecting optical systems. In the case of projection of a target at infinite, an image distance (image height) remains unchanged even when a working distance (a distance in the Z-direction) is changed. In the case of projection of a target at finite, on the other hand, an image distance (image height) changes according to changes in working distance. This characteristics may be utilized to determine an alignment state in the Z-direction (see U.S. Pat. No. 5,463,430 corresponding to Japanese unexamined patent publication No. H6(1994)-46999).</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Likewise, when four alignment target images formed by the alignment target projecting optical system <b>45</b>L are picked up by the image pick-up element <b>54</b>L, the automatic alignment and the automatic tracking of the examination unit <b>10</b>L with respect to the eye EL are performed. The analysis and control part <b>70</b> determines whether an alignment state of the examination unit <b>10</b>L with respect to the eye EL in the X-, Y-, and Z-directions is proper based on a result of the detection of each target image.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In the above alignment, by the fixation target presenting optical systems <b>55</b>R and <b>55</b>L, the fixation target of the fixation target plate <b>58</b>R is presented to the right eye ER and simultaneously the fixation target of the fixation target plate <b>58</b>L is presented to the left eye EL. In the distance refractive power measurement, the mirrors <b>15</b>R and <b>15</b>L are not rotated, so that the visual axes of the eyes ER and EL are guided forward in parallel.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The analysis and control part <b>70</b> drivingly controls the moving parts <b>11</b>R and <b>11</b>L based on results of the determination of the alignment states in the X-, Y-, and Z-directions to move the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L in respective directions. When all of the alignment states in the above directions fall within a predetermined allowable range (proper range), the analysis and control part <b>70</b> automatically generates a trigger signal to start measurement (the examiner may input the trigger signal by pressing a measurement start switch not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The examination light from the light source <b>21</b>R is projected to the fundus of the eye ER via the lens <b>22</b>R through the mirror <b>15</b>R, and forms a spot image of the point light source on the fundus. The light of the point light source image formed on the fundus is reflected and scattered to exit from the eye ER and is reflected by the mirror <b>15</b>R. After that, the light is condensed by the lens <b>24</b>R and, via the mirror <b>23</b>R through the mirror <b>26</b>R, condensed again on an aperture of the diaphragm <b>27</b>R, made into substantially parallel light by the lens <b>28</b>R, made into ring-shaped light by the lens <b>29</b>R, and received by the image pick-up element <b>30</b>R. The picked ring image is inputted in the image processing part <b>72</b>R.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The analysis and control part <b>70</b> determines the refractive power based on the ring image picked up in preliminary measurement. Further, based on the refractive power, the analysis and control part <b>70</b> moves the light source <b>59</b>R and the fixation target plate <b>58</b>R along the optical axis L<b>2</b>, bringing the fundus and the fixation target plate <b>58</b>R in substantially conjugate relation, and then applies a fogging to the eye ER by moving to a far position by an appropriate diopter and determines distance refractive power based on the ring image picked up in this state. Specifically, each value of the eye ER; S (spherical power), C (cylindrical power), and A (astigmatic axis angle) is determined based on the size and shape of the ring image and the positional information of the movable unit <b>31</b>R and is stored in the memory <b>84</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In the examination unit <b>10</b>L, similarly, each value of the eye EL; S, C, and A is determined and stored in the memory <b>84</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">After the distance refractive power measurement, continuously, the examination of an accommodative function is conducted. On the basis of the position of an S value (which can be regarded as a far point of the eyes ER and EL) of each distance refractive power of the eyes ER and EL, a presenting position of a fixation target is changed (moved) to a far position by +0.5D. Variations in refractive power within a predetermined time T (e.g., 20 seconds) at this presenting position are acquired. Thereafter, the presenting position of each fixation target is simultaneously changed (moved) in steps of 0.5D in turn to eight positions toward a near potion; +0.5D, 0.0D, −0.5D, −1.0D, −1.5D, −2.0D, −2.5D, and −3.0D. Variations in refractive power within the time T at each presenting position are acquired. The acquired variations in each refractive power are stored in the memory <b>84</b> in one-to-one correspondence with the presenting positions.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Herein, in association with the change (movement) of the presenting position of each fixation target to the near position, the mirrors <b>15</b>R and <b>15</b>L are rotated by an amount corresponding to the convergence amount of the eyes ER and EL at each presenting position.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view explaining the rotation of the mirrors <b>15</b>R and <b>15</b>L according to each convergence amount of the eyes ER and EL. Assuming that the distance from a cycloduction point O to a corneal apex Cp of the eye ER (EL) is “a”, the distance from the corneal apex Cp to the presenting position of a fixation target is “b”, and the pupillary distance between the eyes ER and EL for far vision is “d”, the deflection angle α (half of the convergence angle θ) of the visual axis of the eye ER (EL) is:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>α=tan<sup>−1</sup>(<i>d</i>/(2<i>a</i>+2<i>b</i>)).<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
Assuming that the incident angle of the optical axes L<b>1</b> and L<b>2</b> to the mirror <b>15</b>R (<b>15</b>L) at this time is “β”, the following expression is given:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?>β=(90°−α)/2.<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
The pupillary distance d is obtained based on the detected positional information by the position detecting parts <b>12</b>R and <b>12</b>L at the time of completion of alignment of the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L in the distance refractive power measurement. Alternatively, a value obtained by a pupillary distance measurement device may be inputted by use of the switch of the switch part <b>80</b>.
</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The analysis and control part <b>70</b> obtains the rotation amount of the mirrors <b>15</b>R and <b>15</b>L for the above respective fixation target presenting positions and causes the motors <b>16</b>R and <b>16</b>L to rotate the mirrors <b>15</b>R and <b>15</b>L so that each visual axis of the eyes ER and EL is brought in a convergence state according to the presenting position (the presenting distance) of the fixation target, changing the incident angle of the optical axes L<b>1</b> and L<b>2</b> to the eyes ER and EL, thereby converging each visual axis of the eyes ER and EL looking the fixation target. In association with this rotation of the mirrors <b>15</b>R and <b>15</b>L, the alignment state of the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L is adjusted. The adjustment of the alignment state of the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L is conducted based on the alignment target images picked up by the image pick-up elements <b>54</b>R and <b>54</b>L in the same manner as above.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">By changing (moving) the presenting position of the fixation target, variations in refractive power within the time T for each position are acquired. At the same time, variations in pupil size and changes in eye position are acquired (detected) based on each anterior segment image of the eyes ER and EL picked up by the image pick-up elements <b>54</b>R and <b>54</b>L. The changes in eye position can be acquired (detected) from changes in center position of the pupil and besides from changes in center position of two infinite target images by the first projecting optical systems. Each acquired (detected) result is stored in the memory <b>84</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">For determining the frequency of occurrence of the high frequency component (HFC) from the variations in refractive power, it is necessary to acquire variations in refractive power at period time shorter than 0.1 second. If it takes long time to analyze the whole ring image, partial information of the ring image may be used for acquisition of the variations. For instance, two coordinates in only a specified meridian direction, e.g., the horizontal meridian direction with reference to the center of the ring image, are detected and the refractive power in that direction is obtained based on the interval between the two coordinates. In case of the eye having astigmatism, it is preferably to correct the refractive power by an amount corresponding to the astigmatism based on the astigmatism information obtained in the distance refractive power measurement.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">When the variations in refractive power acquired at each fixation target presenting position and others are stored in the memory <b>84</b>, the analysis and control part <b>70</b> starts the analysis of an accommodative function.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The analysis of the accommodative function is briefly explained. Since refractive power data may be widely different in case the eye blinked, this is removed. Data loss and irregularity due to the blinking are corrected by cubic spline. Then, a frequency analysis is performed by means of a fast Fourier transform (FFT) to calculate a power spectrum. This calculation of a power spectrum is conducted at each of intervals set within the time T (e.g. 20 seconds). Within the time T, the intervals are set to lag behind preceding ones by a predetermined time (e.g., 1 second) and have an equal duration (e.g., 8 seconds). The calculated power spectrum is converted to common logarithms and analyzed. Based on this power spectrum, a mean power spectrum (in dB) in the intervals for high frequency components of 1.0 to 2.3 Hz is determined and evaluated as the “frequency of occurrence of high frequency component” (HFC) of accommodative microfluctuation.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an example of a analysis result displayed on the monitor <b>7</b>. This is a display example of the analysis result of one eye. The analysis results of both eyes may be displayed simultaneously on the monitor <b>7</b>. These analysis results are displayed in terms of three parameters; fixation target presenting position (distance), amount of accommodation response, and HFC, in the form of a three dimensional graph with color cord maps. In this graph, the vertical axis indicates the amount of accommodation response (in D) and the horizontal axis indicates the fixation target presenting position, where variations in the amount of accommodation response corresponding to elapsed times within the time T at each presenting position are graphed in a bar graph. The HFC is color-coded in for example seven levels. For example, an HFC less than 50 is displayed in green, an HFC not less than 70 is displayed in red, and other HFC therebetween is displayed with gradations in color between green through yellow to red. In this figure, a single line FS indicates an S value obtained in the distance refractive power measurement and is shown in association with the amount of accommodation response at each presenting position. A dotted line Fi indicates refractive power obtained by conversion of each presenting position to refractive power.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Next, the automatic determination of symptoms of the accommodative function is explained (see a flowchart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>). This determination is divided roughly into the determination based on the range of accommodation and the determination based on the HFC. The alphabetic signs used in the following explanation mean as follows;
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0050">HomeS: Refractive power (S value) acquired in the distance refractive power measurement;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0051">MaxRef: Refractive power on the farthest point side;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0003" num="0052">MinRef: Refractive power on the nearest point side;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0004" num="0053">Hfc<b>1</b>: Average HFC in a range from MaxRef to MaxRef−0.75D;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0005" num="0054">Hfc<b>2</b>: Average HFC in a range from MaxRef−1.0D to MaxRef−3.0;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0006" num="0055">Hfc<b>1</b>SD: HFC Standard deviation in a range from MaxRef to MaxRef−0.75D.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0056">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, MaxRef is shown in the lowest portion of the accommodative response amount graph, it is +0.25D in this example. MinRef is shown in the highest portion of the accommodative response amount graph, it is −2.50D. In this example, Hfc<b>1</b> is an average HFC in a range of +0.25D to −0.25D and Hfc<b>2</b> is an average HFC in a range of −0.75D to −2.75D.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0057">The reason for separating Hfc<b>1</b> and Hfc<b>2</b> in the determination based on the HFC is as follows. The resting state of accommodation (a state where ciliary muscle is not working) of a human eye is in −0.75D to about −1.0D from refractive power for a far point. Ciliary muscle works to thin a crystalline lens for the far point side than the accommodation resting state, whereas ciliary muscle works to thicken the crystalline lens for the near point side than the accommodation resting state. Accordingly, Hfc<b>1</b> is an index for judging a state of the ciliary muscle working to thin the crystalline lens and Hfc<b>2</b> is an index for judging a state of the ciliary muscle working to thicken the crystalline lens.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0058">A flow of the automatic determination is explained. Firstly, it is determined whether or not a value obtained by subtracting MaxRef from HomeS is smaller (a negative side) than −0.3D (whether or not a difference between HomeS and MaxRef is larger than 0.3D) (step S<b>1</b>). If YES, it is determined that “there is a high possibility that the eye accommodated in the distance refractive power measurement” (step S<b>2</b>). In general, there is an error of the order of 0.25D when the distance refractive power of a human eye is measured. Considering the error, a difference of 0.3D is set as a determination condition (a reference value). If NO in step S<b>1</b>, it is determined whether or not a value (a variation range of refractive power) obtained by subtracting MinRef from MaxRef is smaller than 1.0D (whether or not a difference between MaxRef and MinRef is smaller than 1.0D) (step S<b>3</b>). If YES, which shows that the variation in accommodation response amount is small even when the presenting position of the fixation target is changed to the near position, it is determined that “the range of accommodation is low or there is a high possibility that accommodative effort was insufficient” (step S<b>4</b>). This corresponds to the case of a presbyopic eye. If No in step S<b>3</b>, found is an absolute value of a value obtained by subtracting an average refractive power (range of accommodation) of an i+1 step from an average refractive power (range of accommodation) of a certain i step of the presenting position of the fixation target changed (moved) in steps of 0.5D. The absolute value is a difference between the average refractive power of the i step and the average refractive power of the i+1 step. It is determined whether or not the number N of the absolute value that exceeds 1.0D is at least one or more (step S<b>5</b>). This 1.0D as the determination condition (the reference value) is set as a larger value than 0.5D which is a step for changing (moving) the presenting position of the fixation target. If NO in step S<b>5</b>, which shows accommodative spasm may have occurred, the flow advances to steps S<b>7</b> and S<b>8</b> for determining the presence/absence of accommodative spasm based on the HFC. In the present embodiment, the changing (moving) step i of the presenting position of the fixation target used for the determination in step S<b>5</b> is set at 1 to 5 steps on the far point side. The further steps on the near point side are excluded. This is made to remove the case where, when the presenting position of the fixation target comes to a near position to some degree, a person who has a small accommodative range cannot clearly see the fixation target and likely abandons, causing the range of accommodation to lower. If YES in step S<b>5</b>, it is determined that the range of accommodation is normal (step S<b>6</b>). Each determination condition is not limited to these values.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0059">After the determination based on the range of accommodation, the determination based on the HFC follows. If NO in step S<b>5</b>, the presence/absence of accommodative spasm is determined based on the HFC (step S<b>7</b>). Firstly, it is determined whether or not Hfc<b>2</b> is a higher value than an HFC value 70 (dB). If YES, it is further determined whether or not Hfc<b>1</b> is a higher value than the HFC value 70 (dB) (step S<b>8</b>). If YES in step S<b>8</b>, it is determined that the HFC is a higher value with respect to the presenting position of the fixation target other than a visual distance regarded as an accommodation resting state and “there is a tendency of accommodative spasm” (step S<b>9</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0060">If YES in any one of steps S<b>1</b>, S<b>3</b>, and S<b>5</b> or if NO in step S<b>7</b> or S<b>8</b>, the presence/absence of accommodation constriction is determined based on the HFC. It is first determined whether or not Hfc<b>2</b> is a higher value than the HFC value 70 (dB) (step S<b>10</b>). If NO, it is further determined whether or not Hfc<b>1</b> is a higher value than the HFC value 60 (dB) (step S<b>11</b>). If NO in step S<b>11</b>, it is further determined whether or not a value obtained by adding Hfc<b>1</b> and Hfc<b>1</b>SD/2 is a higher value than an HFC value 62 (step S<b>12</b>). If YES in any one of steps S<b>10</b>, S<b>11</b>, and S<b>12</b>, it is determined that “there is a possibility of accommodative constriction” (step S<b>13</b>). In step S<b>12</b>, even when the average HFC in a range from MaxRef to MaxRef−0.75D does not show a high value, it is determined that “there is a possibility of accommodative constriction” if a certain high value is given in consideration of a standard deviation. If NO in step S<b>12</b>, the HFC is determined as being normal (step S<b>14</b>). It is then determined in the following step S<b>15</b> whether or not the range of accommodation was also normal. If YES, it is determined that “the accommodative function is considered as normal” (step S<b>16</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0061">Each determination result in the above steps S<b>2</b>, S<b>4</b>, S<b>6</b>, S<b>9</b>, S<b>13</b>, and S<b>16</b> is displayed on the monitor <b>7</b> as a message or the like in addition to the graphical display in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> to inform the examiner thereof. Such display of the determination results, the examiner can accurately grasp the symptom of accommodative function and easily diagnose. Further, differences in reading among examiners are eliminated, and determination errors, a failure to notice of symptoms, and so on can be reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0062">Not only determining the presence/absence of accommodative constriction and the presence/absence of accommodative spasm but also determining respective degrees in steps make it possible to further facilitate diagnosis. For instance, the degree of accommodative constriction is determined in three steps; severe accommodotonia, accommodotonia, accommodotonia tendency, according to the values such as Hfc<b>1</b> and Hfc<b>2</b> (in the order of higher values of the HFC) in the above steps S<b>10</b>, S<b>11</b>, and S<b>12</b>. The degree of accommodative spasm is determined in three steps according to the number N in step S<b>5</b>; severe accommodative spasm if the number N is five or more, moderate accommodative spasm if the number N is three or four, and slight accommodative spasm if the number N is one or two.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0063">In the present apparatus, in addition to the determination of the symptoms of accommodative function, determination is conducted based on the pupil size, eye position, and convergence state. These are explained below.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0064">In the accommodative function examination, at the time of acquiring variations in refractive power at each presenting position of the fixation target, changes in pupil size and changes in eye position are acquired (detected) based on the picked-up anterior segment image. When an amount of change and a speed of change are larger than a permissible range determined from an acquired (detected) result about a normal eye, it is determined that the eye may have some abnormalities or be fatigable. A message to that effect is displayed on the monitor <b>7</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0065">The changes in eye position can be utilized for the determination of presence/absence of nystagmus and others. The changes in pupil size can be utilized for the determination of stability of fixation.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0066">Since the changes in positions of both eyes can be acquired (detected) at the same time, the changes in convergence amount can also be acquired (detected). The changes in convergence amount are acquired (detected) based on the positional information of the examination units <b>10</b>R and <b>10</b>L in the X-, Y-, and Z-directions and the rotational information of the mirrors <b>15</b>R and <b>15</b>L. Whether the optical axes L<b>1</b> and L<b>2</b> coincide with the visual axis is detected based on the positional relation between the alignment target image and the pupil. Each examination unit <b>10</b>R, <b>10</b>L is moved in the X-, Y-, Z-directions and also the mirrors <b>15</b>R and <b>15</b>L are rotated so that the center position of the alignment target image comes to the center position of the pupil. Alternatively, the changes in convergence amount is acquired (detected) based on a difference between a normal convergence amount calculated according to the presenting position (the presenting distance) of the fixation target as mentioned above and an actual convergence amount. Further, in the same manner as above, when the change amount and change speed of the convergence amount vary largely than a permissible range (which can be determined based on the acquired (detected) result about the normal eye), it is determined that the eye has convergence function errors such as convergence spasm, convergence response disorder, and others. A message to that effect is displayed on the monitor <b>7</b>. Furthermore, the convergence normally changes according to the changes in the presenting position of the fixation target. However, if the convergence follows with a large delay or without stability, there may be convergence function errors. The movements of right and left eyes can be not only merely obtained as the convergence amount but also separately acquired (detected). Thus, it is possible for example to determine a difference in converging motion between the right and left eyes when the fixation target comes to the near position. Moreover, convergent accommodation can also be acquired (detected), which facilitates more appropriate diagnosis.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0067">In the above explanation, the values used in the determination of symptoms of accommodative function (e.g., the values for a range such as Hfc<b>1</b>, Hfc<b>2</b>, and others, the values for determination of the presence/absence of accommodative constriction and accommodative spasm, and others) are merely examples and not limited to them.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0068">The eye refractive measuring optical system is not limited to the above one but may be selected from various well known types. Similarly, the fixation target presenting optical system is not limited to the above one but may be selected from various well known types.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0069">While the presently preferred embodiment of the present invention has been shown and described, it is to be understood that this disclosure is for the purpose of illustration and that various changes and modifications may be made without departing from the scope of the invention as set forth in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An ocular accommodative function examination apparatus for examining an accommodative function of an examinee's eye, comprising:
<claim-text>a fixation target presenting optical system which presents a fixation target at a presenting position to the eye, the presenting position being changeable in a direction of a visual axis of the eye;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a refractive power measuring optical system which measures refractive power of the eye and includes a light projecting optical system which includes a light source and projects examination light to a fundus of the eye and a light receiving optical system which includes a light receiving element and receives the examination light reflected from the fundus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an analysis part which acquires variation in the refractive power of the eye gazing at the fixation target at a certain presenting position within a predetermined time based on output of the light receiving element, and determines the accommodative function including a range of accommodation and HFC (a frequency of occurrence of a high frequency component of accommodative microfluctuation) of the eye based on an acquired result; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output part which outputs a result determined by the analysis part,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the analysis part determines presence/absence of accommodative constriction and presence/absence of accommodative spasm based on the determined range of accommodation and HFC.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the analysis part determines the presence/absence of the accommodative constriction and the presence/absence of the accommodative spasm based on the number of times N that a difference between the ranges of accommodation at two presenting positions exceeds a reference value.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the analysis part determines the presence/absence of the accommodative constriction and the presence/absence of the accommodative spasm based on the HFC in a first presenting position range on a far point side and the HFC in a second presenting position range on a near point side.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the analysis part determines a degree of the accommodative constriction in steps based on the HFC and determines a degree of the accommodative spasm in steps based on the number of times N.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a pupil size detecting part which detects pupil size of the eye,
<claim-text>wherein the analysis part acquires change in the pupil size based on a result of the detection of the pupil size and, based on a result thereof, determines presence/absence of abnormality of the eye.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a position detecting part which detects a position of the eye,
<claim-text>wherein the analysis part acquires change in the position of the eye based on a result of the detection of the position and, based on a result thereof, determines presence/absence of abnormality of the eye.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising a convergent state detecting part which detects a convergent state of the eye,
<claim-text>wherein the analysis part acquires change in the convergent state based on a result of detection of the convergent state and, based on a result thereof, determines presence/absence of abnormality of the eye.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An ocular accommodative function examination apparatus for examining an accommodative function of an examinee's eye, comprising:
<claim-text>a fixation target presenting optical system which presents a fixation target at a presenting position to the eye, the presenting position being changeable in a direction of a visual axis of the eye;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a refractive power measuring optical system which measures refractive power of the eye and includes a light projecting optical system which includes a light source and projects examination light to a fundus of the eye and a light receiving optical system which includes a light receiving element and receives the examination light reflected from the fundus;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a right eye examination unit and a left eye examination unit in each of which the fixation target presenting optical system and the refractive power measuring optical system are disposed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a moving part which moves each examination unit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a position detecting part which detects each position of a right eye and a left eye;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control part which controls the moving part based on the detected positions;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an analysis part which acquires variation in the refractive power of the eye gazing at the fixation target at a certain presenting position within a predetermined time based on output of the light receiving element, and determines the accommodative function including a range of accommodation and HFC (a frequency of occurrence of a high frequency component of accommodative microfluctuation) of the eye based on an acquired result; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output part which outputs a result determined by the analysis part.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> further comprising a pupillary distance acquiring part which acquires a pupillary distance between the right eye and the left eye,
<claim-text>wherein the control part controls the moving part based on the acquired pupillary distance.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> further comprising converging means which changes an incident angle of an optical axis of the fixation target presenting optical system for the right eye with respect to the right eye and changes an incident angle of an optical axis of the fixation target presenting optical system for the left eye with respect to the left eye so that each visual axis of the right and left eyes is brought in a convergence state according to the presenting position of the fixation target.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the control part controls the moving part based on change of each incident angle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the converging means includes a movable mirror disposed in each of the examination units.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the position detecting part includes a projecting optical system which projects an alignment target to the eye and a detecting optical system which detects the projected alignment target, the position detecting part is disposed in each of the examination unit to detect a relative position of the right eye with respect to the right eye examination unit and detects a relative position of the left eye with respect to the left eye examination unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The ocular accommodative function examination apparatus according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the analysis part determines presence/absence of accommodative constriction and presence/absence of accommodative spasm based on the determined range of accommodation and HFC.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
