<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298217-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298217</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11292847</doc-number>
<date>20051201</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>97</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>331 12</main-classification>
<further-classification>331 77</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Phased array radar systems and subassemblies thereof</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5568098</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Horie et al.</name>
<date>19961000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>331 16</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>FR</country>
<doc-number>2 542 930</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>19840900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00003">
<othercit>Behzad Razavi, A Study of Injection Locking and Pulling in Oscillators. 2004, pp. 1415-1424, Department of Electrical Engineering, University of California, Los Angeles, CA 90095.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00004">
<othercit>A.S. Daryoush, M. Francisco, R. Saedi, D. Polifko, R. Kunath, Phase Control of Optically Injection Locked Oscillators for Phased Arrays, 1990, pp. 1247-1250, Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA 19104.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00005">
<othercit>Xiangdong Zhang, Afshin S. Daryoush, Full 360 Phase Shifting of Injection-Locked Oscillators, 1993, pp. 14-16, vol. 3, No. 1, Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA 19104.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00006">
<othercit>Hossein Hashemi, Xiang Guan, Abbas Komijani, Ali Hajimiri, A 24-GHZ SiGe Phased-Array Receiver-LO Phase-Shifting Approach, 2005, pp. 614-626, vol. 53, No. 2, Department of Electrical Enginering, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00007">
<othercit>PCT Search Report and Written Opinion of the ISA for PCT/US 2006/043485 dated Apr. 5, 2007.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00008">
<othercit>Hall, P. S. et al,; “Beamforming in quasi-optic active arrays using subharmonic locking”; IEE Colloquium ON Novel Techniques For Antenna Beam Control, (Digest No. 1995/003), 1995, pp. 4/1-4/3, IEE, London, UK.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00009">
<othercit>Hall, P. S. et al,; “Microstrip Active Patch Array With Beam Scanning”; Electronics Letters, IEE Stevenage, GB, vol. 28, No. 22, Oct. 22, 1992, pp. 2056-2057.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>8</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>331 12</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>331 77</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070129040</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070607</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Adlerstein</last-name>
<first-name>Michael G</first-name>
<address>
<city>Wellesley</city>
<state>MA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kaper</last-name>
<first-name>Valery S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Winchester</city>
<state>MA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Daly, Crowley, Mofford &amp; Durkee, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Raytheon Company</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Waltham</city>
<state>MA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chang</last-name>
<first-name>Joseph</first-name>
<department>2817</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A phase shifter is fed an input signal having a frequency f. A coupler is included fed by the input signal. The coupler has a pair of output terminals for providing a pair of signals having the frequency f and having a relative phase shift difference of mπ/2 radians, where m is an integer. A switch is included having a pair of inputs, each one of the pair of inputs being coupled to a corresponding one of the pair of output terminals of the coupler. The switch has an output, one of the pair of inputs of the switch being coupled to the output of the switch selectively in accordance with a first control signal fed to the switch. An oscillator is included having a tunable resonant circuit coupled to the output of the switch, such tunable resonant circuit has a nominal resonant frequency which is an integer multiple of the frequency f, the frequency of the resonant circuit being detuned from the nominal resonant frequency in response to a second control signal fed to the tunable resonant circuit to shift the nominal resonant frequency relative to the a harmonic of the signal at the output of the switch.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="166.29mm" wi="248.92mm" file="US07298217-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="250.19mm" wi="172.21mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298217-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="227.16mm" wi="141.22mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298217-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="202.78mm" wi="99.57mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298217-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates generally to phased array radar system and subassemblies therefor and more particularly to beam forming transmit and receive elements used therein and adapted for integrated circuit fabrication</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">As is known in the art, microwave phased array elements which incorporate electronic phase shifters have a wide variety of applications. One such application is in phased array systems. More particularly, beam forming apparatus is used to form beams of electromagnetic radiation. The shape of the beam is related to the phase and amplitude distributions provided to signals received or transmitted across an aperture of the apparatus. For example, in a phased array antenna, the aperture includes a plurality of antenna elements. Each one of the antenna elements is coupled to a feed structure through a corresponding one of a plurality of variable phase shifter-variable gain modules. The feed structure may be a corporate feed or may be through illuminations as in a space fed phased array system. In any event, the modules are controlled by signals from a beam steering computer to provide a collimated and directed beam of radiation. For example, for a broadside (i.e., boresight) beam the phase shift of the signals emanating from each antenna element is zero relative to some arbitrary reference. If the phase shift from element to element differs by a fixed amount from zero, the direction of the main radiation lobe is shifted from broadside accordingly.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">When used to transmit radar energy, transmitted pulses have a carrier frequency, f<sub>c </sub>and each module operates at this same frequency, f<sub>c</sub>. Thus, for proper operation of the array, there must be a common reference frequency brought to each element through the feed structure.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">As is also known in the art, it is desirable to have modules adapted for integrated circuit fabrication. Today, the amplifier sections of the modules are constrained for many applications to be constructed with III-V technology (e.g. GaAs, GaN, InP) materials. The phase shifter portions of the modules are most often monolithically constructed using discrete, switched phase shifters operating at the microwave frequency to be radiated. Recent advances in silicon CMOS technology have enabled implementation of phase shifting functions in an analog manner. Advantages include greater flexibility and lower cost for the phase shifting and frequency control of the array element. One technique suggested is described in an article entitled “Full 360° Phase Shifting of Injection-Locked Oscillators” by Xiangdong Zhang, published in “IEEE MICROWAVE AND GUIDED WAVE LETTERS, VOL. 3, NO. 1, JANUARY 1993. A shortcoming of this technique is the potential for unwanted frequency shift concurrent with beam steering. A further shortcoming is the omission of an efficient and flexible receive path as needed for radar application</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In accordance with the invention, a phase shifter is provided. The phase shifter is fed an input signal having a frequency f. A coupler is included fed by the input signal. The coupler has a pair of output terminals for providing a pair of signals having the frequency f and having a relative phase difference of mπ/2 radians, where m is an integer. A switch is included having a pair of inputs, each one of the pair of inputs being coupled to a corresponding one of the pair of output terminals of the coupler. The switch has an output, one of the pair of inputs of the switch being coupled to the output of the switch selectively in accordance with a first control signal fed to the switch. Coupled to the output of the switch is a tunable resonant circuit. The tunable resonant circuit has a nominal resonant frequency which is an integer multiple of the frequency f, the frequency of the resonant circuit being detuned from the nominal resonant frequency in response to a second control signal fed to the tunable resonant circuit to shift the nominal resonant frequency relative to the a harmonic of the signal at the output of the switch.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In one embodiment, a frequency multiplier is included for multiplying the frequency, f/M, of a second signal by a factor M, where M is an integer, to produce the input signal having the frequency f.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In one embodiment, the frequency multiplier includes a phase locked loop, having: a phase detector having a first input fed by the second signal to the frequency multiplier; and an oscillator controlled by the phase detector for producing the input signal. The phase detector has a second input fed by a portion of the signal produced by the oscillator.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">In one embodiment, the phase locked loop includes a frequency divider fed by a portion of the signal produced by the oscillator. The output of the frequency divider is fed to the second input of the phase detector. The frequency divider divides the frequency of the signal produced by the oscillator by the factor M.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In one embodiment, a transmit/receive module is provided. The module includes: (A) a transmit path having the phase shifter, and (B) a receive path having a mixer fed by power coupled from the transmit signal path.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In one embodiment, a phase shifter is provided having a frequency multiplier for converting the frequency, f/(2M), of an input signal, where M is an integer greater than one, to produce a first output signal having a frequency f/2; and a tunable resonant circuit coupled to the frequency multiplier for producing a second output signal having a nominal frequency nf/2, where n is an integer greater or equal to 1, the phase of the second output signal being detuned from its nominal phase in response to a control signal fed to the tunable resonant circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In one embodiment, the phase shifter includes a hybrid junction having a pair of outputs for providing at one output a signal having a fixed 90 degree phase shift relative to a signal at the other one of the outputs, such hybrid junction having an input coupled to the frequency multiplier; and a switch for coupling one of the pair of outputs to the tunable resonant circuit selectively in accordance with a switch control signal.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">With such an arrangement, i.e., using the frequency multiplier followed by the tunable resonant circuit, such as an injection locked oscillator or an amplifier, a phase shifter is provided that ensures that the frequency is held constant. The arrangement provides flexibility in choosing the up-conversion ratio by changing M and n—modulus of the frequency divider in the frequency multiplier. In the case where n=2, using a 90 degree hybrid and the switch in conjunction with the tunable resonant circuit provides a ±180 degrees of the phase shifting range as needed by a fully scannable phased array antenna application.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The invention provides the aforesaid architecture for a transmit phased array element which allows digital control of the beam direction without the need for a microwave beam forming network operating at the transmit frequency Much of the circuit can be implemented in CMOS circuitry since the functions are implemented at subharmonics of frequencies rationally related to the radiated frequency. The design allows for frequency control and multiplexing control with reference data.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In one embodiment, a receive path for a return signal uses one or more local oscillator signals derived from the transmit path having the same desired phase shift during both transmit and receive. The system thereby allows the option of single conversion to base band where analog to digital conversion can be implemented. Alternatively, double conversion can be implemented allowing for other detection schemes including in-phase (I) and quadrature (Q) phase processing. This embodiment allows for retention of the transmit beam pattern in the receive mode without the need to separately set the phases in the receive path.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The details of one or more embodiments of the invention are set forth in the accompanying drawings and the description below. Other features, objects, and advantages of the invention will be apparent from the description and drawings, and from the claims.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a radar system according to the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of a transmit portion of an exemplary one of a plurality of identical variable transmit/receive phase shifting and amplitude adjusting elements used in the radar system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> according to the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram of an exemplary one of a plurality of identical variable transmit/receive phase shifting and amplitude adjusting modules used in the radar system of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> implemented with a plurality of integrated circuit chips.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Like reference symbols in the various drawings indicate like elements.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> a phased array radar system <b>10</b> is shown having an array of antenna elements <b>12</b><i>a</i>-<b>12</b><i>n </i>coupled to a radar system processor <b>14</b> through a beam forming network. The beam forming network includes interfaces to a plurality of identical variable transmit/receive phase shifting and amplitude adjusting modules <b>16</b><i>a</i>-<b>16</b><i>n. </i></p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Each variable transmit/receive phase shifting and amplitude adjusting module <b>16</b><i>a</i>-<b>16</b><i>n </i>includes a phase lock loop (PLL) <b>19</b> fed by a common reference frequency signal produced by the radar system processor <b>14</b> on line <b>18</b>. The frequency of the signal on line <b>18</b> is represented as f<sub>s</sub>=f<sub>ant</sub>/(2M), where M is an integer greater than one, typically a power of 2. Here, in this example, M=16 and f<sub>ant </sub>is 10 GHz. Thus, the reference signal on line <b>18</b> is 625 MHz. It should be noted that because of this relatively low frequency, the usual beam forming network can be replaced with conventional UHF transmission media (e.g. coax, printed traces or demodulated optical signals).</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The PLL <b>19</b> includes a phase detector (PD) <b>20</b> fed by the reference signal on line <b>18</b> as well as a feedback signal derived from a master oscillator <b>22</b> to be described. The output of the phase detector <b>20</b> is fed to a low pass filter <b>24</b>. The output of the low pass filter <b>24</b> is a DC signal used to control a voltage controlled oscillator <b>22</b>. The output of the voltage controlled oscillator <b>22</b> has a nominal frequency of f<sub>ant</sub>/2 (i.e., the nominal frequency f<sub>ant</sub>/2 is produced when the level of the DC signal produced by the low pass filter <b>24</b> is zero). A portion of the output signal produced by the voltage controlled oscillator <b>22</b> is fed back to the phase detector <b>20</b> through a coupler <b>26</b> and a frequency divider <b>28</b>. The frequency divider <b>28</b> divides the frequency, f<sub>ant</sub>/2 of the feed back signal from the coupler <b>26</b> by the factor M producing a signal having the frequency f<sub>ant</sub>/(2M), where M is an integer. Thus, the PLL <b>19</b> provides a frequency multiplier for multiplying the frequency, f<sub>s</sub>, of the reference signal on line <b>18</b> by a factor M, where M is an integer, to produce at the output <b>30</b> of the PLL <b>19</b> a signal having a frequency f<sub>s</sub>/2.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The major portion of the output of the PLL <b>19</b> is fed to a buffer amplifier <b>32</b>. The output of the buffer amplifier <b>32</b> is fed to a 90-degree hybrid junction <b>34</b>. The hybrid junction <b>34</b> produces a pair of output signals as terminal 0° and 90°, such output signals are equal in amplitude and have a ninety degree phase difference therebetween.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The outputs of the hybrid junction <b>34</b> are fed to a switch <b>36</b>. The switch <b>36</b> operates in response to a control signal produced by the radar system processor <b>14</b> on line <b>39</b>. The control signal on line <b>39</b> has two DC states; in one state the control signal on line <b>39</b> operates the switch <b>36</b> to couple the signal at the terminal 0° to the input of an injection locked oscillator <b>38</b> to obtain phase variations from 0 degrees to 180 degrees while in the other state the control signal on line <b>39</b> operates the switch <b>36</b> to couple the signal at the terminal 90° to the input of an injection locked oscillator (ILO) <b>38</b> to obtain phase shift variations from 180 degrees to 360 degrees, for reasons to be explained below.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The injection locked (i.e., slave) oscillator <b>38</b> is voltage controlled by a signal produced by the radar system processor <b>14</b> on line <b>42</b>. More particularly, the oscillator <b>38</b> includes an amplifier <b>37</b> having a tunable resonator circuit <b>41</b> (i.e., a capacitor, here variable capacitor (C)-inductor (L) resonant circuit) connected around it in a feedback relationship, as shown. It should be understood that tunable resonant circuit may take other forms such parallel resonant circuit, for example. The resonance of the tunable resonant circuit <b>41</b> is here controlled by a voltage on line <b>42</b> changing the capacitance of the variable capacitor C. The output of the injection locked oscillator <b>38</b> is fed to a variable gain amplifier <b>44</b> or attenuator, which gain, or attention, as the case may be, is controlled by a control signal (usually DC) produced by the radar system processor <b>14</b> on line <b>46</b>. The output of the variable gain/attention device <b>44</b> is fed to a high power amplifier <b>50</b> though a coupler <b>52</b>. The output of the amplifier has a frequency f<sub>ant</sub>, and is, during transmit, fed through a transmit/receive switch <b>56</b> to the antenna element <b>12</b><i>a </i>in the case of module <b>16</b><i>a</i>, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">It is noted that the frequency produced by injection locked oscillator <b>38</b>, sometimes herein referred to as a slave oscillator with oscillator <b>22</b> sometimes being referred to as a master oscillator) is twice that of the frequency produced by master oscillator <b>22</b>. Therefore, the phase of slave oscillator <b>38</b> is referenced to the second harmonic of the master oscillator <b>22</b>; this harmonic being produced by the inherent non-linearity of the slave oscillator <b>38</b>. The phase of the slave oscillator <b>38</b> can be varied by +/−90 degrees relative to the reference phase (i.e., the second harmonic of the master oscillator <b>22</b>). In one state, the reference phase is obtained with the switch <b>36</b> set to 0 degrees. In a vector representation, the output of the phase of the slave oscillator <b>38</b> output may be represented as a 180 degree semicircle. However, for operation of any phased array element, it is necessary that the phase be variable over a range of +/−180 degrees. The required adjoining semicircle to form a complete 360 circle is achieved by setting the switch <b>36</b> to the 90 degree polarity. This results in a 180 degree phase shift of the phase reference signal within the slave oscillator <b>38</b>. Thus, every phase state available within the slave oscillator <b>38</b> has a counterpart of opposite polarity. The output phasor then covers the desired 360 degree range. To put it another way, when the signal at the terminal 0° is coupled to the input of an injection locked oscillator, slave, <b>38</b>, phase shift variations from −90 degrees to +90 degrees are obtained at the output of slave oscillator <b>38</b> whereas when switch <b>36</b> couples the signal at the terminal 90° to the input of an injection locked oscillator (ILO), slave, <b>38</b> the phase shift variations increases from +90 degrees to +270 degrees at the output of slave oscillator <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">It is noted that the T/R switch <b>56</b> is operated by a control signal produced by the radar system processor <b>14</b> on line <b>47</b>. It is also noted that pulses of RF energy for transmission are generated by pulse modulation of the high power amplifier <b>50</b> responding to the XMT command signals from the radar system processor <b>14</b>, for example.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">A minor portion of the signal produced by the variable gain/attention device <b>44</b> is fed to a mixer <b>60</b> through the coupler <b>52</b>. This signal acts as a local oscillator whose phase is controlled by the signal produced by the processor <b>14</b> control lines <b>39</b> and <b>42</b>. Thus, during the receive mode, energy received by the antenna elements <b>12</b><i>a</i>-<b>12</b><i>n </i>are fed to the mixer <b>60</b> in the corresponding module <b>16</b><i>a</i>-<b>16</b> via an amplifier <b>62</b>. The output of the mixer <b>60</b> is fed via low pass filter <b>64</b> back to the radar system processor <b>14</b> via an analog to digital converter <b>66</b>, as indicated. Other detection schemes can be employed in base band including those involving quadrature detection (i.e., in-phase (I) and quadrature (Q) channels).</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The shape of the beam provided by the antenna elements <b>12</b><i>a</i>-<b>12</b><i>n </i>is related to the relative phase and amplitude distributions provided to input signal by the plurality of identical variable transmit/receive phase shifting and amplitude adjusting modules <b>16</b><i>a</i>-<b>16</b><i>n</i>. It is noted that the reference signal on line <b>18</b> is used with a pair of voltage-controlled oscillators <b>22</b>, <b>38</b>, referred to as “master” and “slave”, respectively. The reference signal on line <b>18</b> is fed to the phase detector <b>20</b> that is part of the master oscillator phase locked loop (PLL) circuit <b>19</b>. The frequency divider and low pass filter (LPF) portion of the PLL serve to phase lock the master oscillator <b>22</b> in a conventional manner. This phase locking is accomplished by a loop input to a DC varactor, not shown, included in a resonant tank circuit, not shown of the oscillator <b>22</b> or any other means of injection locked oscillator phase control in the master oscillator tank circuit, not shown. The free running frequency of the master oscillator <b>22</b> is, in this example, f<sub>o</sub>/2, here f<sub>o</sub>/2 is 5 GHZ. The buffer amplifier <b>32</b> following the oscillator <b>22</b> provides power gain as well as a constant load for oscillator <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The combination of components comprising the master oscillator <b>22</b> is designed to maintain low phase noise and provide input to the compact quadrature hybrid coupler <b>34</b>. As noted above, the two output terminals of the hybrid coupler <b>34</b> are equal in amplitude and 90 degrees different in phase. The switch <b>36</b> passes a signal at f<sub>ant</sub>/2 to select the sense of the phase that is input to the slave oscillator <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">It is noted that for a free running oscillator, the frequency of oscillation is determined such that the phase of the output signal results in optimal positive feedback to the input of the gain element. That phase is determined by the resonator present in the oscillator as well as the feedback path. If the resonator is tunable, as would be a varactor in combination with an inductor, the frequency varies in order to maintain the desired feedback phase. In an injection locked oscillator, a signal, here the signal from switch <b>36</b>, is injected into the feedback path, i.e., the tunable resonate circuit <b>41</b>, as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Suppose that the injected signal is at the free running frequency. Then the oscillator phase will adjust such that the vector sum of the injected signal and the output signal will provide the desired feedback phase to sustain oscillation, as described in an article entitled “A study of locking phenomena in oscillators” by R. Adler, Proceeding of IRE vol. 34, pp. 351-357). Suppose further that the resonant frequency of the oscillator is changed by varying the varactor. Then, in order to sustain oscillation, the phase of the output signal will have to readjust to accommodate the phase shift through the retuned resonator <b>41</b>. If the injected signal is strong enough, oscillator dynamics will prevent the frequency from shifting.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">It can be shown that the phase shifting produced in this way is limited to +/−90 degrees while +/−180 degrees is required for beam steering. This problem is solved, as noted above, by providing the hybrid coupler <b>34</b> and switch <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">According to the invention, the output of the switch <b>36</b> is a signal having a frequency f<sub>ant/</sub>2 and is injected directly into the slave oscillator <b>38</b>. The oscillator <b>38</b> is itself a highly nonlinear device and thus generates a second harmonic signal internally which acts like an injected signal at the free running frequency. The injected signal results in subharmonic frequency locking to f<sub>ant </sub>of the slave oscillator <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Relative to the phase of the harmonic of the injected signal, the classical effect described above will allow a +/−90 degree phase shift. For any of these phase settings, an abrupt 90 degree phase shift of the reference signal corresponds to a 180 degree phase shift of the second harmonic. This will result in a 180 degree phase shift in the output signal from oscillator <b>38</b>. This phase would not be accessible by simply varying the varactor tuner, i.e., the resonant <b>41</b>. The abrupt 90 degree shift in the reference is due to switch selection of the opposite hybrid branch.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The voltage sensitivity of output variation will depend on the ratio of the injected input power from the master oscillator <b>22</b> to the output power from the slave oscillator <b>38</b>. The Q of the resonator <b>41</b> in the slave oscillator <b>38</b> also plays a role in the voltage sensitivity of phase shift. Thus, there is also a trade-off between injected power, Q and phase noise.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The phase control voltage provided to the slave oscillator <b>38</b> on line <b>42</b> as well as the voltage used to operate the switch <b>36</b> on line <b>39</b> is provided by the radar system processor <b>14</b>. One scheme is to use D/A conversion of data that is multiplexed onto the reference UHF signal on line <b>18</b>. This data can control not only the phase of the rf signals (and hence the beam direction) but also can induce a frequency change. This would be accomplished by using various combinations of divider settings (i.e. the choice of M) in the phase locked loop, and sub harmonic number, n for frequency locking the slave oscillator <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In accordance with the above invention, the phase shifting operation is provided by the frequency multiplier, here the PLL <b>19</b>, having the master oscillator <b>22</b>, for converting the frequency, f<sub>ant</sub>/(2M), of the reference signal, where M is an integer greater than one (usually a power of 2), to a first output signal having a frequency f<sub>ant</sub>/2. The slave oscillator <b>38</b> is coupled to the frequency multiplier and produces an output signal having a nominal frequency nf<sub>ant</sub>/2, where n is an integer greater than one, here n is two, the phase of the output signal being detuned from its nominal phase in response to a control signal fed to the slave oscillator <b>38</b> via line <b>42</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In the phased array what is important is the ability to steer the beam at the frequency of f<sub>ant</sub>, meaning to be possible to introduce relative phase shift between the array antenna elements <b>12</b><i>a</i>-<b>12</b><i>n </i>relative to a zero phase of a certain antenna element. For example, consider that antenna element <b>12</b><i>a </i>transmits at some phase define as the reference phase. The next antenna element <b>12</b><i>b</i>, not shown, is at the frequency of f<sub>ant </sub>and has its phase adjusted by the module <b>12</b><i>b</i>, not shown (injection-lock oscillator ILO <b>42</b> with the switch <b>36</b> and the hybrid <b>36</b>) to have a phase X relative to that of the antenna element <b>12</b><i>a</i>. The next antenna element <b>12</b><i>c</i>, not shown has a phase shift is 2X again relative to the antenna element <b>12</b><i>a </i>phase. And so on so that antenna element <b>12</b><i>n </i>has a phase shift nX relative to the antenna element <b>12</b><i>a</i>. The signal on line <b>18</b> of frequency f<sub>ant</sub>/(2M) serves as a common reference signal. In this arrangement, it is important to understand the magnitude of the instantaneous phase uncertainty between the antenna elements <b>12</b><i>a</i>-<b>12</b><i>n </i>in the array at f<sub>ant</sub>. Due to the upconversion process in the PLL <b>19</b> and ILO <b>38</b>, this uncertainty (or phase error) is 2M*delta phi common, where delta phi common is the phase error between inputs to the antenna elements <b>12</b><i>a</i>-<b>12</b><i>n </i>at the frequency of f<sub>ant</sub>/(2M). The system uses an initial calibration of the array to account for such systematic errors.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Considering now the receive operation, in the receive mode, the T/R switch <b>56</b> connects the antenna elements <b>12</b><i>a</i>-<b>12</b><i>n </i>in modules <b>16</b><i>a</i>-<b>16</b><i>n </i>to the corresponding receive path in such module <b>16</b><i>a</i>-<b>16</b><i>n</i>. The slave oscillator <b>38</b> in the transmit chain acts as a local oscillator (LO) for a direct conversion mixer <b>60</b> in the receive path. The antenna element-to-antenna element phase relations of the received signal are preserved in the conversion. Hence the direction of the antennal lobe is the same as the transmit lobe direction since the LO phases are derived from the same phase shifting module <b>16</b><i>a</i>-<b>16</b><i>n </i>as during transmit. The mixer <b>60</b> is designed to provide isolation between the LO and RF ports in both directions. A very good output match for the low noise amplifier <b>62</b> supplements this isolation.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Another requirement of the up-conversion in the receive chain is that the LO phases into the mixer <b>60</b> be coherent, antenna element-to-antenna element. This requirement is addressed by the same mechanism at work in the transmit mode as described above. If the mixers introduce any element-to-element phase shift, the phase of the slave oscillator <b>38</b> can be readjusted upon transition from the transmit mode to the receive mode in order to preserve the beam direction.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the transmit section of the module shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is. shown in a two-chip implementation: one chip <b>92</b> is silicon suitable for CMOS fabrication, and the other chip <b>90</b> uses a III-V material optimized for RF performance. Thus, such an arrangement allows digital control of the beam direction, eliminates the need for a microwave beam former, and much of the circuit can be implemented in CMOS circuitry since the functions are implemented at subharmonics of the radiated frequency. The design allows for frequency control and multiplexing control through radar system commands.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, another embodiment of a variable transmit/receive phase shifting and amplitude adjusting modules, here module <b>16</b>′<i>a</i>. is shown. Here, the output of low pass filter <b>64</b> is fed to a mixer <b>70</b>. Here, the frequency divider <b>28</b>, FIH. <b>1</b>, in the module <b>16</b><i>a </i>is replaced with a pair of dividers, <b>28</b><i>a </i>and <b>28</b><i>b</i>. The frequency divider <b>28</b><i>a </i>produces a signal having a frequency f<sub>ant</sub>/(M/2) which is fed to a second input of mixer <b>70</b> via coupler <b>72</b>. The frequency divider <b>28</b><i>b </i>produces a signal having a frequency f<sub>ant</sub>/2 which is fed to the phase detector <b>20</b>. The output of mixer <b>70</b> thus is thereby upconverted to a frequency f<sub>ant</sub>/M for processing by the radar system processor <b>14</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) on line <b>74</b>. Thus, the frequency produced by the receiver channel to the radar system processor <b>14</b> is different from the signal from the radar system processor <b>14</b> to the module <b>16</b>′, i.e., distinct from the transmit frequency reference of f<sub>ant</sub>/(2M).</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The resulting up-conversion allows potential reuse of the UHF system/element interface which caries the original reference signal f<sub>ant</sub>/2 to the array elements. To avoid phase pulling, care must be taken to provide isolation between the receive and the transmit UHF paths. There are a number of alternative approaches to achieving this isolation:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0045">1. Good UHF directional couplers must be used to route the input signal on line <b>18</b> and the output signal from the mixer <b>70</b>.</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0046">2. A separate receive path UHF transmission line <b>74</b> can run in parallel to the transmit reference lines <b>18</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0003" num="0047">3. The local oscillator frequency from the feedback signal in the PLL used in the receive chain up-converter (i.e., mixer <b>70</b>) can be derived from any intermediate divider stage in the master oscillator PLL, as shown. For example, taking the LO prior to the last divide-by-two stage will yield a local oscillator frequency of f<sub>ant</sub>/M. This is distinct from the transmit frequency reference of f<sub>ant</sub>/(2M).</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0004" num="0048">4. The baseband output of the direct conversion mixer in the receive chain can be digitized and multiplexed with the signals from other elements.</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0005" num="0049">5. Modulation of light on optical fiber can be used to carry UHF signals to and from the array element.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0050">A number of embodiments of the invention have been described. Nevertheless, it will be understood that various modifications may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention. Accordingly, other embodiments are within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A phase shifter, comprising:
<claim-text>an input signal source having a frequency f;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coupler fed by the input signal, such coupler having a pair of output terminals for providing a pair of signals having the frequency f and having a relative phase difference of mπ/2 radians, where m is an integer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch having a pair of inputs, each one of the pair of inputs being coupled to a corresponding one of the pair of output terminals of the coupler, such switch having an output, one of the pair of inputs of the switch being coupled to the output of the switch selectively in accordance with a first control signal fed to the switch;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tunable resonant circuit coupled to the output of the switch, such tunable resonant circuit having a nominal resonant frequency which is an integer multiple of the frequency f, the frequency of the resonant circuit being detuned from the nominal resonant frequency in response to a second control signal fed to the tunable resonant circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The phase shifter recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> including a frequency multiplier for multiplying the frequency, f/M, of a second signal by a factor M, where M is an integer, to produce the input signal having the frequency f.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The phase shifter recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the frequency multiplier includes a phase locked loop, comprising:
<claim-text>a phase detector having a first input fed by the second signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an oscillator controlled by the phase detector for producing the input signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the phase detector has a second input fed by a portion of the signal produced by the oscillator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The phase shifter recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the phase locked loop includes a frequency divider fed by the portion of the signal produced by the oscillator, such frequency divider being fed to the second input of the phase detector, such frequency divider dividing the frequency of the signal produced by the oscillator by the factor M.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A transmit/receive module, comprising:
<claim-text>(A) a transmit path having:
<claim-text>a phase shifter, comprising:
<claim-text>an input signal having a frequency f;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coupler fed by the input signal, such coupler having a pair of output terminals for providing a pair of signals having the frequency f and having a relative phase difference of mπ/2 radians, where m is an integer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch having a pair of inputs, each one of the pair of inputs being coupled to a corresponding one of the pair of output terminals of the coupler, such switch having an output, one of the pair of inputs of the switch being coupled to the output of the switch selectively in accordance with a first control signal fed to the switch;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tunable resonant circuit coupled to the output of the switch, such tunable resonant circuit having a nominal resonant frequency which is an integer multiple of the frequency f, the frequency of the resonant circuit being detuned from the nominal resonant frequency in response to a second control signal fed to the tunable resonant circuit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a transmit signal is derived from the signal produced by the tunable resonant circuit; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>(B) a receive path, comprising;
<claim-text>a mixer fed by reflections of the transmit signal and a portion of the signal produced by the tunable resonant circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A transmit/receive module, comprising:
<claim-text>(A) a transmit path having:
<claim-text>a phase shifter, comprising:
<claim-text>an input signal having a frequency f;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coupler fed by the input signal, such coupler having a pair of output terminals for providing a pair of signals having the frequency f and having a relative phase difference of mπ/2 radians, where m is an integer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch having a pair of inputs, each one of the pair of inputs being coupled to a corresponding one of the pair of output terminals of the coupler, such switch having an output, one of the pair of inputs of the switch being coupled to the output of the switch selectively in accordance with a first control signal fed to the switch;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tunable resonant circuit coupled to the output of the switch, such tunable resonant circuit having a nominal resonant frequency which is an integer multiple of the frequency f, the frequency of the resonant circuit being detuned from the nominal resonant frequency in response to a second control signal fed to the tunable resonant circuit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a transmit signal is derived from the signal produced by the tunable resonant circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a frequency multiplier for multiplying the frequency, f/M, of a second signal by a factor M, where M is an integer, to produce the input signal having the frequency f; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>(B) a receive path, comprising;
<claim-text>a mixer fed by reflections of the transmit signal and signal derived from the frequency multiplier.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The transmit/receive module of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claims 6</claim-ref> wherein the frequency multiplier includes a phase locked loop, comprising:
<claim-text>a phase detector having a first input fed by the second signal;
<claim-text>an oscillator controlled by the phase detector for producing the input signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the phase detector has a second input fed by a portion of the signal produced by the oscillator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A phase shifter, comprising:
<claim-text>a frequency multiplier for converting the frequency, f/(2M), of an input signal where M is an integer greater than one, to produce a first output signal having a frequency f/2;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an resonant circuit coupled to the frequency multiplier for producing a second output signal having a nominal frequency nf/2, where n is an integer, the phase of the second output signal being changed from a nominal phase in response to a control signal fed to the resonant circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a coupler having a pair of outputs for providing at one output a signal having a fixed 90 degree phase difference relative to a signal at the other one of the outputs, such hybrid junction having an input coupled to the frequency multiplier;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a switch for coupling one of the pair of outputs of the coupler to the resonant circuit selectively in accordance with a switch control signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
