<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298965-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298965</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11013062</doc-number>
<date>20041214</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>25</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>225</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386117</main-classification>
<further-classification>386 46</further-classification>
<further-classification>386 94</further-classification>
<further-classification>380201</further-classification>
<further-classification>380202</further-classification>
<further-classification>380203</further-classification>
<further-classification>352 47</further-classification>
<further-classification>352 97</further-classification>
<further-classification>352135</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Interfering with illicit recording activity</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5023709</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kita et al.</name>
<date>19910600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5907350</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nemirofsky</name>
<date>19990500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5959717</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chaum</name>
<date>19990900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6542618</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Rhoads</name>
<date>20030400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0124171</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Rhoads</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001313006</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>15</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386 46</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386 94</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>386117</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>380201</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>380202</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>380203</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>352 47</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>352 97</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>352135</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>09957810</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20010920</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6868229</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11013062</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050219112</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051006</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Balogh</last-name>
<first-name>Stephen P.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Hillsboro</city>
<state>OR</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Blakely, Sokoloff, Taylor &amp; Zafman LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Intel Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Santa Clara</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Miller</last-name>
<first-name>John</first-name>
<department>2621</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Fletcher</last-name>
<first-name>James A.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Often, during an event, such as a movie, play, concert, opera, etc., viewers of the event attempt to illicitly record the event. Such illicit recording attempts may be interfered with by using emitters that emit radiation that interferes with recording and/or operation of the recording devices. For example, infrared emitters may be used to saturate an event viewing area. The infrared, while non-visible to human viewers, is received and recorded by recorders using charge-coupled devices (CCDs), such as conventional digital cameras, movie cameras, television cameras, telescopes, etc. Other radiation can be emitted based on the type of recorder with which one desires to interfere. Alternatively, or in addition thereto, emitters may also be used to send commands to recorders, such as stop, rewind, eject, etc., to interfere with operation of the recorders.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="217.93mm" wi="171.28mm" file="US07298965-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="212.60mm" wi="182.88mm" file="US07298965-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="230.80mm" wi="172.55mm" file="US07298965-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="168.57mm" wi="167.81mm" file="US07298965-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="233.43mm" wi="172.64mm" file="US07298965-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This U.S. patent application is a continuation of U.S. patent application Ser. No. 09/957,810 filed Sep. 20, 2001 now U.S. Pat. No. 6,868,229.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The invention generally relates to preventing illicit recording of events, and more particularly to emitting non-visible radiation, such as infrared, so as to interfere with recording devices.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In recent years, charge-coupled devices (CCDs) have been used within recording devices such as still-shot cameras, movie cameras, television cameras, telescopes, and other recording devices.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A charge-coupled device (CCD) is an instrument comprising an array of light sensitive elements, such as capacitors, that are charged by incoming light and the generated current is recorded. CCDs are advantageous in recording devices since CCDs are highly sensitive to light, and due to their inherent digital nature, easily incorporated into electronic machines. For example, in telescopes for recording celestial images, CCDs record a higher percentage of light reaching the CCD than does conventional film-based telescopes.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In addition to visible light, CCDs are also sensitive to non-visible radiation.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The features and advantages of the present invention will become apparent from the following detailed description of the present invention in which:</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an environment according to one embodiment of the invention for using projectors of non-visible radiation to interfere with illicit attempts to record an event with a recorder sensitive to the non-visible radiation.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates an alternate configuration for the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> projectors of non-visible radiation.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a flowchart according to one embodiment of the invention for controlling the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> projectors.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a suitable computing environment in which certain aspects of the invention may be implemented.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an environment according to one embodiment of the invention. Illustrated is a focus region <b>100</b>, such as a movie theater screen, television screen, computer monitor, stage, outdoor area, or other area in which viewer attention is focused. In the illustrated embodiment, it is assumed the focus region is a screen, and projectors <b>102</b>, illustrated with dashed lines and not drawn to scale, are behind the focus region <b>100</b> with an opening or openings in screen through which projections occur. In another embodiments, the projectors may be mounted within the focus region, e.g., for a stage, the projectors may be mounted on the surface of props.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Also illustrated are viewing positions <b>104</b>, which may be theater seats or the like. In the illustrated embodiment, one of the viewing positions <b>106</b> represents someone attempting within the viewing positions that is attempting to illicitly record an event, such a pre-recorded event, such as a movie, or live presentation, e.g., a play, concert, opera, etc. Projectors <b>102</b> are used to confound this illicit activity. In particular, advantageous usage may be made of known sensitivity of CCDs to certain non-visible radiation, such as infrared that can not be seen by people. When a CCD based recorder receives infrared input, the input is recorded as visible light. Typically, infrared input is recorded as white light at varying intensities, e.g., it is recorded as a gray-scale image. The non-visible infrared input can be used to interfere with illicit recording attempts of an event, or to introduce an infrared watermark or copyright notice on a recording, without affecting viewing of the event by people.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The illustrated projectors <b>102</b> have one or more emitters <b>108</b> that emit infrared and/or other non-visible light that is subsequently received and recorded by recording devices such a CCD based video cameras, digital cameras, etc. It will be appreciated that other recording media sensitive to non-visible light may also be similarly manipulated. For example, if an alternate light sensitive technology, such as complementary metal-oxide-semiconductor (CMOS) Active Pixel Sensors (APS) replaces conventional use of CCDs in recording devices, then the projectors may be configured to emit non-visible radiation that affects the alternate light sensitive technology in a manner similar to the effect of infrared on CCDs.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In one embodiment, the projectors are configured to blanket the viewing area <b>104</b> with infrared light, causing the illicit recorder <b>106</b> to record a washed out image. Or, assuming a sufficient number of projectors, in another embodiment, the projectors are configured to project a pattern forming words, such as a Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) warning, copyright information, purchase information to allow an illicit recorder opportunity to purchase a legitimate copy of the event, an arbitrary image, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In one embodiment, the projectors <b>102</b> may be configured to emit known infrared commands designed to stop or interfere with an illicit recording. Most recording devices provide an infrared interface for controlling the recording device. Thus, for example, along with projecting a pattern to recording devices, the projectors could also emit all known stop, rewind, eject, etc. commands for recording devices. Thus, to an unsophisticated thief, the recording device would appear to malfunction. Assuming multiple emitters <b>108</b> within a projector, a single projector may simultaneously interfere with image recording while also emitting control commands.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In one embodiment, the projectors <b>102</b> emit the above described interference continually throughout the event. In another embodiment, the interference is emitted randomly. In a still further embodiment, the interference emissions are queued to particular moments of the event. For example, certain moments of high interest in an event may be interfered with so as to allow an illicit recorder to believe a recording was successful. That is, when the illicit recording is played back, after successful viewing for some period of time, at an important moment during the event, e.g., a key scene in a movie or play, the quality of the recording is substantially degraded due to the emitted interference.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates an alternate environment according to one embodiment of the invention, in which .</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Illustrated is a focus region <b>100</b> as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, but in this embodiment the projectors <b>200</b> are disposed about the focus region, instead of on or behind the focus region as with the projectors <b>102</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. As with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the projectors are not drawn to scale. As discussed above, the projectors may be used to emit interference for an illicit recording device. In one embodiment, the illustrated projectors may be configured to direct their emissions in certain directions or patterns, e.g., to move like a search light or laser show light. In one embodiment, the projectors are moved so as to spell out words or patterns on receiving recorders.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In another embodiment, rather than projecting towards an illicit recorder <b>106</b>, instead the focus region <b>100</b> is coated in a material that is highly reflective to the radiation emitted from the projectors <b>200</b>. That is, assuming infrared based projectors, and the focus region is a screen, then the screen is coated with a material that absorbs and reflects the projected infrared. In this embodiment, the projectors are directed towards the screen, and as discussed above, the projectors are directed to draw words and/or patterns on the screen that are not visible to intended audience viewers, but that nonetheless ruin an illicit recording. It will be appreciated that the techniques of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> may be employed simultaneously. It will be further appreciated that emitting towards the illicit recorder or towards the focus region may be configured to operate in conjunction with movement through space so as to give the appearance of a large image or message displayed by the moving emitters.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In one embodiment, since more and more devices are being configured with short range communication technology, such as Blue Tooth, wireless plug and play, and other wireless technology, a transceiver (not illustrated) is used to query for the identity of recorders within range of the transceiver. In such fashion, commercial recording devices may be able to announce the identify of the recorder owner, or at least to place management of an event on notice that an illicit recording may be occurring.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a flowchart according to one embodiment for initializing and/or actively managing projectors <b>102</b>, <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The projectors may be stationary, e.g. having non-moving emitters, or they may be directed or moved about to blanket an area with a desired radiation, e.g., infrared or other emission. Initialization and/or management of projectors may be controlled by a machine such as is described with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">A first illustrated operation is the determination <b>300</b> that an event has started. Such determination may occur by way of a signal received at the start of an event, such as from a signal embedded within a movie, by monitoring an environment for a change, such as dimming lighting, by manual human indication, or by other indication. Different emission techniques may be applied to interfere with illicit recordings, e.g., as discussed above, emissions may be designed to interfere with recorded images, while other emissions are designed to interfere with operation of recording devices.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In the illustrated embodiment, a test <b>302</b> may be performed to determine whether continuous emissions, such as blanketing a presentation environment with infrared, will be used. If so, then the projectors <b>102</b>, <b>200</b> are configured and/or actively directed to continuously emit <b>304</b> a desired radiation as desired. In one embodiment, a projector controller, e.g., a machine such as in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, assigns a particular task to a projector, e.g., engage in continuous emission. In one embodiment, once assigned a task, projector performs the task without further direction from the projector controller until a new task is assigned. In another embodiment, the controller remains in intermittent or continuous communication with the projectors to control their activity.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">If <b>302</b> continuous emission is not desired, a test <b>306</b> may be performed to determine whether random emissions will be used. For example, to minimize wear on emitters, or reduce electricity consumption, the projectors may be utilized at random intervals during the event. If so, then the projectors <b>102</b>, <b>200</b> are configured and/or actively directed to randomly emit <b>308</b> a desired radiation as desired.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">If <b>306</b> random emission is not desired, a test <b>306</b> may be performed to determine whether targeted emissions will be used. For example, rather than interfering with an entire event, instead, certain portions of the event that are deemed of interest, such as an emotional moment within an event, are flagged for interference. During these moments of interest, illicit recording devices are interfered with. This embodiment allows one to partially illicitly record an event before receiving interference. As discussed above, emissions may be configured to display messages on recorders, and such messages may include instructions for obtaining a legitimate copy of the event. Thus, if targeting is to be used, then the projectors <b>102</b>, <b>200</b> are configured and/or actively directed to randomly emit <b>312</b> a desired radiation as desired.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">If no emissions are desired, or when emissions are completed, such as at the end of the event, then processing ends <b>314</b>. Ending processing may include a determination (not illustrated) of the end of the event, such as, for a movie, due to an end signal embedded within the event, or based on some other signal or cue.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> and the following discussion are intended to provide a brief, general description of a suitable computing environment in which certain aspects of the illustrated invention may be implemented.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">An exemplary machine <b>400</b>, e.g., a computer or other device, for controlling the projectors <b>102</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), <b>200</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) includes a system bus <b>402</b>. Typically, attached to the bus are processors <b>404</b>, a memory <b>406</b> (e.g., RAM, ROM), storage devices <b>408</b>, a video interface <b>410</b>, and input/output interface ports <b>412</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The system may also include embedded controllers, such as Generic or Programmable Logic Devices or Arrays, Application Specific Integrated Circuits, single-chip computers, smart cards, or the like, and the system is expected to operate in a networked environment using physical and/or logical connections to one or more remote machines <b>414</b>, <b>416</b> through a network interface <b>418</b>, modem <b>420</b>, or other data pathway. Systems may be interconnected by way of a wired or wireless network <b>422</b>, such as an intranet, the Internet, local area networks, wide area networks, cellular, cable, laser, satellite, microwave, short range wireless networks such as “BlueTooth” type networks, optical, infrared, or other short range or long range wired or wireless carrier.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The invention may be described by reference to or in conjunction with program modules, including functions, procedures, data structures, application programs, etc. for performing tasks, or defining abstract data types or low-level hardware contexts. Program modules may be stored in memory <b>406</b> and/or storage devices <b>408</b> and associated storage media, e.g., hard-drives, floppy-disks, optical storage, magnetic cassettes, tapes, flash memory cards, memory sticks, digital video disks, biological storage. Program modules may be delivered over transmission environments, including network <b>422</b>, in the form of packets, serial data, parallel data, propagated signals, etc. Program modules may be used in a compressed or encrypted format, and may be used in a distributed environment and stored in local and/or remote memory, for access by single and multi-processor machines, portable computers, handheld devices, e.g., Personal Digital Assistants (PDAs), cellular telephones, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Thus, for example, with respect to the illustrated embodiments, assuming machine <b>400</b> operates to control the projectors <b>102</b>, <b>200</b>, then remote machines <b>414</b>, <b>416</b> may respectively be the projectors <b>102</b>, <b>200</b>, and a transceiver-based system for detecting illicit recorders. It will be appreciated that remote machines <b>414</b>, <b>416</b> may be configured like machine <b>400</b>, and therefore include many or all of the elements discussed for machine. It should also be appreciated that machines <b>400</b>, <b>414</b>, <b>416</b> may be embodied within a single device, or separate communicatively-coupled components.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Having described and illustrated the principles of the invention with reference to illustrated embodiments, it will be recognized that the illustrated embodiments can be modified in arrangement and detail without departing from such principles. And, though the foregoing discussion has focused on particular embodiments, other configurations are contemplated. In particular, even though expressions such as “in one embodiment,” “in another embodiment,” or the like are used herein, these phrases are meant to generally reference embodiment possibilities, and are not intended to limit the invention to particular embodiment configurations. As used herein, these terms may reference the same or different embodiments that are combinable into other embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Consequently, in view of the wide variety of permutations to the embodiments described herein, this detailed description is intended to be illustrative only, and should not be taken as limiting the scope of the invention. What is claimed as the invention, therefore, is all such modifications as may come within the scope and spirit of the following claims and equivalents thereto.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for interfering with illicit attempts to record an event with a recording device, comprising:
<claim-text>initializing an emitter to emit a control command to the recording device according to a time pattern, the control command to interfere with the recording device's ability to record; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>emitting the control command to the recording device in accordance with the time pattern.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said emitting comprises emitting human imperceptible radiation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the human imperceptible radiation comprises infrared.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>checking whether the recording device has an authorization to record the event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>determining receipt of a payment associated with the recording device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the recording device to record the event based at least in part on the payment.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the time pattern is one of random emission during the event, continuous emission during at least a portion of the event, or emission at selected times during the event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A program module on a machine-accessible medium having associated data for interfering with illicit attempts to record an event with a recording device, wherein the data, when accessed, results in a machine performing:
<claim-text>initializing an emitter to emit a control command to the recording device according to a time pattern, the control command to interfere with the recording device's ability to record; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>emitting the control command to the recording device in accordance with the time pattern.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The program module of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the associated data further includes data, which when accessed, results in the machine emitting human imperceptible radiation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The program module of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein the human imperceptible radiation comprises infrared.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The program module of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the associated data further includes data, which when accessed, results in the machine checking whether the recording device has an authorization to record the event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The program module of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the associated data farther includes data, which when accessed, results in the machine performing:
<claim-text>determining receipt of a payment associated with the recording device; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the recording device to record the event based at least in part on the payment.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The medium of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the time pattern is one of random emission during the event, continuous emission during at least a portion of the event, or emission at selected times during the event.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method for interfering with illicit attempts to record an event, comprising:
<claim-text>identifying a starting point for projecting interference during an event; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>emitting a radiation that is not human perceptible during the event that will interfere with recording devices used during the event;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the emitting the radiation comprises emitting control instructions to affect operation of recording devices used during the event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein the control instructions comprise selected ones of the following operation commands:
<claim-text>stop, rewind, fast forward, power off, power on, erase recording media, identify the recording device, and sound theft alarm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A program module on a machine-accessible media having associated data for interfering with illicit attempts to record an event, wherein the data, when accessed, results in a machine performing:
<claim-text>identifying a starting point for projecting interference during an event; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>emitting a radiation that is not human perceptible during the event that will interfere with recording devices used during the event;</claim-text>
<claim-text>emitting control instructions to affect operation of recording devices used during the event.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
