<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297239-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297239</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10921666</doc-number>
<date>20040818</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>608</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>25</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>17</main-group>
<subgroup>14</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>25</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>23</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>23</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>22</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>204224M</main-classification>
<further-classification>204224 R</further-classification>
<further-classification>204279</further-classification>
<further-classification>204284</further-classification>
<further-classification>2042881</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Method and apparatus for the electrochemical deposition and planarization of a material on a workpiece surface</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6802955</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Emesh et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>205662</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7025860</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chadda</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>204224 M</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7201828</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Emesh</name>
<date>20070400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>204199</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0035354</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Ashjaee et al.</name>
<date>20011100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>205103</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0132120</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Emesh et al.</name>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>205117</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0163950</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Emesh</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>20429706</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0211662</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chadda</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>204242</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0016681</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Emesh et al.</name>
<date>20050100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>15634512</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>25</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10044514</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20020111</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6802955</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10921666</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050016681</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050127</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Emesh</last-name>
<first-name>Ismail</first-name>
<address>
<city>Gilbert</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Gopalan</last-name>
<first-name>Periya</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chandler</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Rayer, II</last-name>
<first-name>Phillip M.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chandler</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Palmer</last-name>
<first-name>Bentley J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chandler</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ingrassia Fisher &amp; Lorenz, P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Novellus Systems, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>San Jose</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Wilkins, III</last-name>
<first-name>Harry D</first-name>
<department>1753</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electrochemical apparatus is provided which deposits material onto or removes material from the surface of a workpiece. The apparatus comprises a polishing pad and a platen which is in turn comprised of a first conductive layer in contact with the polishing pad and coupled to a first potential, a second conductive layer coupled to a second potential, and a first insulating layer disposed between the first and second conductive layers. At least one electrical contact is positioned within the polishing pad and is electrically coupled to the second conductive layer. A reservoir is provided which places an electrolyte solution in contact with the polishing pad and the workpiece. A carrier positions and/or presses the workpiece against the polishing pad.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="125.05mm" wi="284.65mm" file="US07297239-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="235.46mm" wi="163.41mm" file="US07297239-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="209.72mm" wi="122.77mm" file="US07297239-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="211.41mm" wi="126.66mm" file="US07297239-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="207.69mm" wi="137.75mm" file="US07297239-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="224.96mm" wi="160.19mm" file="US07297239-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="211.33mm" wi="164.59mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297239-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a divisional of application Ser. No. 10/044,514, filed Jan. 11, 2002 now U.S. Pat. No. 6,802,955.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates generally to techniques for depositing conductive material and/or for removing conductive material from a workpiece such as a semiconductor wafer. More particularly, this invention relates to an apparatus, a system, and a method for electrolytically depositing and/or planarizing a conductive material on a workpiece surface and polishing the surface of the workpiece to remove a portion of the conductive material. Still more particularly, this invention relates to the deposition and/or planarization of copper on a workpiece surface.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Chemical mechanical polishing (CMP) is a technique which has been conventionally used for the planarization of semiconductor wafers. For example, see U.S. Pat. No. 5,099,614, issued in March in 1992 to Riarai et al; U.S. Pat. No. 5,329,732 issued July 1994 to Karlsrud et al, and U.S. Pat. No. 5,498,199 issued March 1966 to Karlsrud et al. Furthermore, chemical mechanical polishing is often used in the formation of microelectriconic devices to provide a substantially smooth, planar surface suitable for subsequent fabrication processes such as photoresist coating and pattern definition. A typical chemical mechanical polishing apparatus suitable for planarizing a semiconductor surface generally includes a wafer carrier configured to support, guide, and apply pressure to a wafer during the polishing process, a polishing compound such as a slurry to assist in the removal of material from the surface of the wafer, and a polishing surface such as a polishing pad. In addition, the polishing apparatus may include an integrated wafer cleaning system and/or an automated load/unload station to facilitate automatic processing of the wafers.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A wafer surface is generally polished by moving the surface of the wafer to be polished relative to the polishing surface in the presence of a polishing compound. In particular, the wafer is placed in a carrier such that the surface to be polished is placed in contact with the polishing surface, and the polishing surface and the wafer are moved relative to each other while slurry is supplied to the polishing surface.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Chemical mechanical polishing may also be used to form microelectronic features. For example, a conductive feature such as a metal line, conductive plug, or the like may be formed on a surface of a wafer by forming trenches and vias on the wafer surface, depositing conductive material over the wafer surface and into the trenches and vias, and removing the conductive material on the surface of the wafer using chemical mechanical polishing, leaving the vias and trenches filled with conductive material. The conductive features often include a barrier material to reduce unwanted diffusion of the conductive material and to promote adhesion between the conductive material and any adjacent layer of the circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Aluminum is often used to form conductive features because its characteristics are compatible with conventional deposition (e.g. chemical vapor deposition) and etch (e.g., reactive ion etch) techniques. While the use of aluminum to form conductive features is adequate in some cases, the use of aluminum in the formation of conductive features becomes increasingly problematic as the size of the conductive feature decreases. In particular, as the size of the conductive feature decreases, the current density through the feature generally increases, and thus the feature becomes increasingly susceptible to electromigrations; i.e., the mass transport of metal due to the flow of current. Electromigration may cause short circuits where the metal accumulates, open circuits where the metal has been depleted, and/or other circuit failures. Similarly, increased conductive feature resistance may cause unwanted device problems such as access power consumption and heat generation.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Recently, techniques have been developed which utilize copper to form conductive features because copper is less susceptible to electromigration and exhibits a lower resistivity than aluminum. Since copper does not readily form volatile or soluble compounds, the copper conductive features are often formed using damascene. More particularly, the copper conductive features are formed by creating a via within an insulating material, depositing a barrier layer onto the surface of the insulating material and into the via, depositing a seed layer of copper into the barrier layer, electrodepositing a copper layer onto the seed layer to fill the via, and removing any excess barrier metal and copper from the surface of the insulating material using chemical and mechanical polishing. During the electrodeposition process, additives such as leveling agents may be added to the plating bath to reduce the formation of voids within the conductive features.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Forming copper conductive features according to the method described above can be relatively expensive, in part because each material deposition and removal step is typically carried out using dedicated equipment. U.S. Pat. No. 6,176,922, issued to Talieh on Jan. 23, 2001, discloses an apparatus for both electroplating and polishing copper. The apparatus disclosed includes a wafer carrier having a cathode electrode contact that contacts the surface of the wafer to be polished. Unfortunately, the apparatus shown in Taleih is problematic is several ways. In particular, a film deposited using the apparatus of Taleih may be undesirably non-uniform because the cathode electrode contacts the wafer in a limited number of fixed locations about the perimeter of the wafer. Such a cathode contact configuration may lead to increased deposition about the perimeter of the wafer, i.e., in the areas proximate to the cathode contact, and thus lead to non-uniform deposition of the conduct film. Furthermore, wafer areas in contact with the cathode generally cannot include active devices.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">As stated previously, the CMP machine typically includes a wafer carrier configured to hold, rotate, and transport a wafer during the process of polishing or planarizing the wafer. During the planarizing operation, a pressure applying element (e.g., a rigid plate, a bladder assembly, or the like) that may be an integral part of the wafer carrier, applies pressure such that the wafer engages a polishing surface with a desired amount of force. The carrier and the polishing surface are rotated, typically at different rotational velocities, to cause relative lateral motion between the polishing surface and the wafer and to promote uniformed planarization. The polishing surface generally comprises a horizontal polishing pad that may be formed of various materials such as blown polyurethane and are available commercially from, for example, Rodel Inc. located in Phoenix, Ariz. The hardness and density of the polishing pad depend on the material that is being polished, and an abrasive slurry may also be applied to the polishing surface which acts to chemically weaken the molecular bonds at the wafer surface so that the mechanical action of the polishing pad and slurry abrasive can remove the undesirable material from the wafer surface.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Unfortunately, the CMP process tends to leave stresses in the worked workpiece leading to subsequent cracking and shorting between metal layers. Furthermore, the CMP process may result in sheering or crushing of fragile layers. This process also has a tendency to cause dishing in the center of wide metal features, such as trenches and vias, oxide erosion between metal features, and dielectric oxide loss. Electrochemical planarization is an attractive alternative to CMP because it does not impart significant mechanical stresses to the workpiece, and consequently does not significantly reduce the integrity of the devices. Furthermore, electrochemical planarization is less likely to cause dishing, oxide erosion, and oxide loss of the dielectric layer.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Electrochemical planarization is based on electroetching and electrochemical machining; that is, the removal of a thin layer of metal from a substrate through the action of an electrical solution and electricity. For example, if two electrodes, an anode and a cathode, are emerged in a liquid electrolyte and are wired so as to permit a potential difference between the electrodes, metal atoms in the anode are ionized by the electricity and go into the solution as ions. Depending on the chemistry of the metals and salt, the metal ions from the anode either plate the cathodes, fall out as precipitate, or remain in solution. Unfortunately, using conventional electrochemical planarization techniques, etching selectivity is reduced in areas of large dimension, high and low topography on the wafer, and uniform planarization is not achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In view of the foregoing, it should be appreciated that it would be desirable to provide improved methods and apparatus for the electrochemical deposition and/or planarization of a metal on a workpiece such as a semiconductor wafer.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In accordance with an aspect of the invention, there is provided an apparatus for performing an electrochemical process on the surface of a workpiece. The apparatus includes a polishing pad and a platen which includes a first conductive layer in contact with the polishing pad and coupled to a first potential, a second conductive layer coupled to a second potential, and a first insulating layer disposed therebetween. At least one electrical contact is positioned within the polishing pad and is electrically coupled to the second conductive layer. A reservoir is utilized to provide electrolyte solution and place it in contact with the polishing pad and the workpiece. Finally, a carrier is configured to carry the workpiece and press it against the polishing pad.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In accordance with a further aspect of the invention, there is provided a platen for use in an electrochemical process. The platen comprises a first insulating layer having a first surface and a second surface. The first insulating layer contains at least a first aperture and a second aperture therethrough. At least a first insulating island protrudes from the first surface and is disposed around the first aperture. Similarly, at least a second insulating island protrudes from the second surface and is disposed around the second aperture. A first conductive layer on the first surface surrounds the first insulating island, and a second conductive layer on the second surface surrounds the second insulating island. Finally, a conductive element resides in the first aperture and is electrically coupled to the second conductive layer.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">According to a still further aspect of the invention, there is provided a method for depositing material onto or removing material from a surface of a workpiece which comprises the steps of providing a polishing pad, providing a platen comprising a first conductive layer, a second conductive layer, and a first insulating layer therebetween. A first potential is applied to the first conductive layer, a second potential is applied to the second conductive layer, and an electrolyte solution is placed in contact with the polishing pad and the workpiece. The workpiece is pressed against the polishing pad, and relative motion is imparted between the workpiece and the polishing surface.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The following drawings are illustrative of particular embodiments of the invention and therefore do not limit the scope of the invention, but are presented to assist in providing a proper understanding of the invention. The drawings are not to scale (unless so stated) and are intended for use in conjunction with the explanations in the following detailed description. The present invention will hereinafter be described in conjunction with the appended drawing figures, wherein like numerals and like elements, and:</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a top cutaway view of a polishing system in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a top cutaway view of a portion of an electrochemical polishing apparatus in accordance with another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a bottom cutaway view of a carousel for use with the apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a top plan view of a typical workpiece carrier for use in conjunction with the inventive electrochemical deposition apparatus;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a top cutaway view of a portion of an electrochemical polishing apparatus in accordance with still another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a portion of a platen/polishing pad stack for use in conjunction with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross-sectional view illustrating the details of the plastic layer shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is an isometric view of the upper surface of the plastic insulator shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a portion of an electrochemical deposition apparatus in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is an isometric view illustrating the upper surface of the polishing pad employed in the apparatus shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a cross-sectional view of an apparatus for producing orbital motion.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF EXEMPLARY EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The following description is exemplary in nature and is not intended to limit the scope, applicability, or configuration of the invention in any way. Rather, the following description provides a convenient illustration for implementing exemplary embodiments of the invention. Various changes to the described embodiments may be made in the function and arrangement of the elements described herein without departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a top cutaway view of the polishing apparatus <b>100</b>, suitable for electrochemically depositing or planarizing conductive material on or from the surface of a workpiece in accordance with the present invention. Apparatus <b>100</b> includes a multi-station polishing system <b>102</b>, a clean system <b>104</b>, and a wafer load/unload station <b>106</b>. In addition, apparatus <b>100</b> includes a cover (not shown) that surrounds apparatus <b>100</b> to isolate apparatus <b>100</b> from the surrounding environment. In accordance with a preferred embodiment in the present invention, machine <b>100</b> is a Momentum machine available from SpeedFan-IPEC Corporation of Chandler, Ariz. However, machine <b>100</b> may be any machine capable of removing or depositing material from or onto a workpiece surface.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Although the present invention may be used to remove material or deposit material on the surface of a variety of workpieces such as magnetic disks, optical disks, and the like, the invention is conveniently described below in connection with removing and depositing material on the surface of a wafer. In the context of the present invention, the term “wafer” shall mean semiconductor substrates, which may include layers of insulating, semiconductor, and conducting layers or features formed thereon and used to manufacture microelectronic devices.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Exemplary polishing station <b>102</b> includes four polishing stations, <b>108</b>, <b>110</b>, <b>112</b>, and <b>114</b>, that each operate independently; a buff station <b>116</b>; a stage <b>118</b>; a robot <b>120</b>; and optionally, a metrology station <b>122</b>. Polishing stations <b>108</b>-<b>114</b> may be configured as desired to perform specific functions. In accordance with the present invention, at least one of the stations <b>108</b>-<b>114</b> includes an electrochemical deposition and polishing apparatus as described herein. Another one of the stations <b>108</b>-<b>114</b> includes electrochemical planarization apparatus as described herein, and the remaining stations may be configured for traditional chemical mechanical polishing or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Polishing system <b>102</b> also includes polishing surface conditioners <b>140</b> and <b>142</b>. The configuration of conditioners <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> generally depend on the type of polishing surface to be conditioned. For example, when the polishing surface comprises a polyurethane polishing pad, conditioners <b>140</b> and <b>142</b> may include a rigid substrate coated with diamond material. Various other surface conditioners may also be used in accordance with the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Clean system <b>104</b> is generally configured to remove debris such as slurry residue and material from the wafer surface during polishing. In accordance with the illustrated embodiment, system <b>104</b> includes clean stations <b>124</b> and <b>126</b>, a spin rinse dryer <b>128</b>, and a robot <b>130</b> configured to transport the wafer between clean stations <b>124</b> and <b>126</b> and spin rinse dryer <b>128</b>. Alternatively, clean station <b>104</b> may be separate from the remainder of the electrochemical deposition and planarization apparatus. In this case, load station <b>106</b> is configured to receive dry wafers for processing, but the wafers may remain in a wet (e.g., deionized water) environment until the wafers are transferred to the clean station. In operation, cassettes <b>132</b>, including one or more wafers, are loaded onto apparatus <b>100</b> at station <b>106</b>. The wafers are then individually transported to a stage <b>134</b> using a dry robot <b>136</b>. A wet robot <b>138</b> retrieves a wafer at stage <b>132</b> and transports the wafer to metrology station <b>122</b> for film characterization or to stage <b>118</b> within polishing system <b>102</b>. Robot <b>120</b> picks up the wafer from metrology station <b>122</b> or stage <b>118</b> and transports the wafer to one of polishing stations <b>108</b>-<b>114</b> for electrochemical deposition or planarization of a conductive material. After a desired amount of material has been deposited or removed, the wafer may be transported to another polishing station. Alternatively, as will be more fully discussed below, a polishing environment within one of the stations may be changed from an environment suitable for the electrochemical deposition to an environment suitable for electrochemical planarization; e.g., by changing the solution and the bias applied to the wafer. In this case, a single polishing station may be used to both deposit material and remove material from the wafer.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">After conductive material has been either deposited or removed from the wafer surface, the wafer is transferred to buff station <b>116</b> to further polish the surface of the wafer. After the polishing and/or buff process, the wafer is transferred to stage <b>118</b> which is configured to maintain one or more wafers in a wet (e.g. deionized water) environment.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">After the wafer is placed in stage <b>118</b>, robot <b>138</b> picks up the wafer and transports it to clean system <b>104</b>. In particular, robot <b>138</b> transports the wafer to robot <b>130</b>, which in turn places the wafer in one of the clean stations <b>124</b> or <b>126</b>. The wafer is cleaned using one or more stations <b>124</b> and <b>126</b> and then is transported to spin rinse dryer <b>128</b> to rinse and dry the wafer prior to transporting it to load/unload station <b>106</b> using robot <b>136</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a top cut away view of another exemplary polishing apparatus <b>200</b>, configured to electrochemically planarize, electrochemically deposit material onto a wafer, and polish the surface of a wafer to remove a portion of the deposited material. Apparatus <b>200</b> is suitably coupled to carousel <b>300</b> illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> to form an automated electrochemical deposition, planarization, and polishing system. The system in accordance with this embodiment may also include a removable cover (not shown) overlying apparatus <b>200</b> and <b>300</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Apparatus <b>200</b> includes three polishing stations, <b>202</b>, <b>204</b>, and <b>206</b>, a wafer transfer station <b>208</b>, a center rotational post <b>210</b> that is coupled to carousel <b>300</b> and which operatively engages carousel <b>300</b> to cause carousel <b>300</b> to rotate, a load and unload station <b>212</b>, and a robot <b>214</b> configured to transport wafers between stations <b>212</b> and <b>208</b>. Furthermore, apparatus <b>200</b> may include one or more rinse washing stations <b>216</b> to rinse and/or wash a surface of a wafer before or after a polishing, electrodeposition, or electroplanarization. Although illustrated with three polishing stations, apparatus <b>200</b> may include any desired number of polishing stations, and one or more such polishing stations may be used to buff a surface of a wafer. Furthermore, apparatus <b>200</b> may include an integrated wafer clean and dry system similar to system <b>104</b> described above. Wafer station <b>208</b> is generally configured to stage wafers before or between polishing and/or buff operations and may be further configured to wash and/or maintain the wafers in a wet environment.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Carousel apparatus <b>300</b> includes polishing heads, or carriers, <b>302</b>, <b>304</b>, <b>306</b>, and <b>308</b>, each configured to hold a single wafer and urge the wafer against the polishing surface (e.g., a polishing surface associated with one of stations <b>202</b>-<b>206</b>). Each carrier <b>302</b>-<b>308</b> is suitably spaced from post <b>210</b> such that each carrier aligns with a polishing station or station <b>208</b>. In accordance with one embodiment of the invention, each carrier <b>302</b>-<b>308</b> is attached to a rotatable drive mechanism using a Gimble system (not illustrated) which allows carriers <b>302</b>-<b>308</b> to cause a wafer to rotate (e.g., during a polishing process). In addition, the carriers may be attached to a carrier motor assembly that is configured to cause the carriers to translate as, for example, along tracks <b>310</b>. Furthermore, each carrier <b>302</b>-<b>308</b> may rotate and translate independently of the other carriers.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In operation, wafers are processed using apparatus <b>200</b> and <b>300</b> by loading a wafer onto station <b>208</b> from station <b>212</b> using robot <b>214</b>. When a desired number of wafers are loaded onto the carriers, at least one of the wafers is placed in contact with the polishing surface. The wafer may be positioned by lowering a carrier to place the wafer surface in contact with the polishing surface, or a portion of the carrier (e.g., a wafer holding surface) may be lowered to position the wafer in contact with the polishing surface. After polishing is complete, one or more conditioners <b>218</b> may be employed to condition the polishing surfaces.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">During a polishing process, a wafer may be held in place by a carrier <b>400</b>, illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>. Carrier <b>400</b> comprises a retaining ring <b>406</b> and a receiving plate <b>402</b> including one or more apertures <b>404</b>. Apertures <b>404</b> are designed to assist retention of a wafer by carrier <b>400</b> by, for example, allowing a vacuum pressure to be applied to the backside of the wafer or by creating enough surface tension to retain the wafer. Retaining ring <b>406</b> limits the movement of the wafer during the polishing process.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates another polishing system <b>500</b> in accordance with the present invention. It is suitably configured to receive a wafer from a cassette <b>502</b> and return the wafer to the same or to a predetermined different location within the cassette in a clean common dry state. System <b>500</b> includes polishing stations <b>504</b> and <b>506</b>, a buff station <b>508</b>, a head loading station <b>510</b>, a transfer station <b>512</b>, a wet robot <b>514</b>, a dry robot <b>516</b>, a rotatable index table <b>518</b>, and a clean station <b>520</b>. Dry robot <b>516</b> unloads a wafer from cassette <b>502</b> and places the wafer on transfer station <b>512</b>. The wafer then travels to polishing stations <b>504</b>-<b>508</b> for polishing and returns to station <b>510</b> for unloading by robot <b>514</b> and station <b>512</b>. The wafer is then transferred to clean system <b>520</b> to clean, rinse, and dry the wafer before the wafer is returned to load and unload station <b>502</b> using dry robot <b>516</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a portion of a platen/polishing pad stack <b>600</b> which may be utilized to perform electrochemical deposition, planarization, and polishing (e.g., a portion of one of stations <b>108</b>-<b>114</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> or stations <b>202</b>-<b>206</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). Stack <b>600</b> includes a platen support member <b>602</b> constructed of a suitable material (e.g. titanium, stainless steel), a first electrically conductive layer <b>606</b> (e.g. copper), an insulating layer <b>604</b> (e.g. plastic) electrically isolating layer <b>606</b> from support member <b>602</b> for reasons which will become apparent, a second insulating layer <b>608</b> (e.g. a ceramic or a non-electrically conductive polymer such as plastic), and a second electrically conductive layer <b>610</b> (e.g. copper having a thickness of between 0.1 cm and 3 cm; preferably 1 cm) having a polishing pad <b>612</b> disposed thereon. Polishing pad <b>612</b> is suitably formed of an insulating material such as a polymeric material, a polymeric/inorganic composite material, or a ceramic insulation material. The hardness and density of the polishing surface are selected based on the type of material to be polished or removed. Polyurethane polishing pads are available from Rodel Inc. of Phoenix, Ariz. and may be advantageously used to polish a wafer although it should be appreciated that any suitable polishing surface could be used.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a cross-sectional view illustrating insulating layer <b>608</b> in more detail. Layer <b>608</b> includes an upper surface <b>722</b>, a lower surface <b>724</b>, and a plurality of openings therethrough. For example, apertures <b>708</b> are provided through which electrolyte (e.g., a copper sulfate electrolyte known as EC2001 and additives available from Shipley) may flow from a reservoir (not shown). Layer <b>608</b> also includes a plurality of apertures <b>710</b> which receive conductive pins therethrough for making electrical contact to copper layer <b>606</b>. As can be seen, apertures <b>710</b> include a region <b>712</b> of reduced dimension (e.g. diameter) for receiving the stem of a conductive pin (e.g. copper) and a region <b>714</b> of an increased dimension for receiving the head of the copper pin which ultimately makes electrical contact with a wafer to be polished or on which copper is to be deposited as will be described hereinbelow. The upper surface of layer <b>608</b> has a plurality of insulating islands <b>716</b> formed thereon which insulate the conductive pins from a layer of copper which will be formed on surface <b>722</b> in recessed regions <b>718</b> between adjacent insulating islands <b>716</b> as will be described more fully below. Similarly, a plurality of insulating wells <b>720</b> are provided around apertures <b>710</b> creating recessed regions <b>726</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Insulating islands <b>716</b> are shown more clearly in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> which is a perspective view of the upper portion of layer <b>608</b>. As can be seen, layer <b>608</b> is provided with a plurality of insulating wells <b>716</b> protruding above surface <b>722</b>. Apertures <b>708</b> are also visible in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> and, as explained earlier, are provided to enable delivery of an electrolyte solution from a reservoir to a wafer. Eventually, copper layer <b>610</b> will be disposed on surface <b>722</b> and surround insulating wells <b>716</b>. The upper surface of copper layer <b>610</b> will be coplanar with the upper surface of insulating wells <b>716</b>. In a similar fashion, copper layer <b>606</b> will be deposited in regions <b>726</b> on lower surface <b>724</b> between insulating wells <b>720</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In accordance with one embodiment of the invention, apparatus <b>900</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is configured to perform electrochemical deposition, electrochemical planarization, and/or polishing, utilizing the platen/polishing pad stack shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. Apparatus <b>900</b> includes stack <b>600</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a wafer carrier assembly <b>902</b>, a wafer <b>904</b>, a source of potential <b>908</b>, a source of temperature controlled electrolytic solution <b>910</b>, and drive controller <b>914</b>. In general, apparatus <b>900</b> is configured to electrochemically deposit onto or remove material from surface <b>912</b> of semiconductor wafer <b>904</b> retained by carrier assembly <b>902</b>. Apparatus <b>900</b> is further configured to polish surface <b>912</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Copper layer <b>610</b> is disposed on the upper surface of insulating layer <b>608</b>. The upper surface of copper layer <b>610</b> resides between insulating wells <b>716</b> and is coplanar with the upper surface thereof so as to present a planar surface to surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b>. In the case of a deposition process, copper layer <b>610</b> is coupled to the anode of a source of supply voltage <b>908</b>, and the second copper layer <b>606</b> disposed between insulating wells <b>720</b> is coupled to the cathode of supply voltage <b>908</b>. By reversing the polarity, the process becomes an electro-polishing process. Finally, insulating layer <b>604</b> is provided beneath copper layer <b>606</b>. It is to be noted that support member <b>602</b>, insulating layer <b>604</b>, copper layer <b>610</b>, and polishing pad <b>612</b> likewise have openings therethrough which align with openings <b>708</b> to enable delivery of the electrolyte solution from reservoir <b>910</b> to the interface between the upper surface of polishing pad <b>612</b> and surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b>. It should be also noted that polishing pad <b>612</b> is provided with a plurality of conductive regions <b>903</b> (e.g., made from a conductive polymer epoxy and of a hardness substantially equal of that of polishing pad <b>612</b>) which provide electrical conductivity between copper pins <b>906</b> in apertures <b>710</b> and wafer <b>904</b>. Polishing pad <b>612</b> is also provided with a plurality of channels or grooves <b>909</b> which are configured to effect transportation of the electrolyte solution on the surface of polishing pad <b>612</b> and into holes <b>905</b> for providing electrical coupling between conductive layer <b>610</b> and surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b>. Holes or apertures <b>905</b> preferably have a cumulative cross-sectional area substantially equal to fifty percent of the surface area of surface <b>912</b>. Furthermore, hoes <b>905</b> may be of different sizes or diameters as is shown at <b>911</b> and <b>913</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> to provide a measure of distribution control.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">Channels <b>909</b>, slurry apertures <b>708</b>, and conductive pads <b>903</b> are shown more clearly in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> which is a perspective view illustrating the top surface of polishing pad <b>612</b>. As can be seen, channels <b>909</b> form a rectangular grid forming islands <b>912</b> which alternately contain conductive pads <b>903</b> and slurry openings <b>708</b>. It should be clear, however, that the pattern of slurry openings, pads, and channels shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is given by way of example only. The pads, openings, and channels may be patterned in any manner suitable to achieve the intended purpose.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">As stated previously, electrochemical deposition results when the required potential difference is applied between surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b> and copper layer <b>610</b>. The cathode of voltage source <b>908</b> is electrically coupled to copper layer <b>606</b>. Copper layer <b>606</b> is electrically coupled through copper pins <b>906</b> to conductive pads <b>903</b> in polishing pad <b>612</b>. The anode of power supply <b>908</b> is coupled to copper layer <b>610</b>. Thus, a potential difference has been provided between surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b> and layer <b>610</b>. Since the electrolyte solution is being provided by reservoir <b>910</b> through channels <b>708</b> to the region between polishing pad <b>612</b> and surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b>, copper is electrochemically deposited on surface <b>912</b>. Of course, it should be understood that a thin seed layer of copper must first be deposited on wafer <b>612</b>. This may be accomplished by forming a seed layer of copper on the surface of wafer <b>904</b> as, for example, by sputtering, chemical vapor deposition, or any other suitable deposition methods. In particular, power supply <b>908</b> applies a relative positive charge to conductive layer <b>610</b> and a relative negative charge to copper layer <b>606</b>. This relative negative charge is transmitted to the surface of wafer <b>904</b> by means of copper pins <b>906</b> and conductive pads <b>903</b> in polishing pad <b>612</b>. Positioning the heads of pins <b>906</b> adjacent pads <b>903</b> provides a significant amount of electrical contact area between pads <b>903</b> and surface <b>912</b> of the wafer <b>904</b>. This facilitates the creation of a uniform electric potential gradient across the surface of the wafer reducing the likelihood that edge effects and the like may result. Since the cathode electrodes are not attached directly to the surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b>, a greater amount of surface area of wafer <b>904</b> is available for device formation.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The platen assembly having polishing pad <b>612</b> disposed thereon is generally configured to move relative to carrier <b>902</b> and wafer <b>904</b> so as to facilitate polishing of wafer <b>904</b> and promote a uniform deposition of material onto surface <b>912</b>. The platen assembly may be connected to a drive motor assembly <b>914</b> that is operative to rotate the platen and polishing surface about a vertical axis. It will be appreciated, however, that the drive or motor assembly may be operative to move the platen assembly and polishing surface in an orbital, linear, rotational, or oscillatory pattern or any combination thereof. For example, U.S. Pat. No. 5,582,534 (Sheldon et al) and U.S. Pat. No. 5,938,884 (Hoshizaki et al) disclose several mechanisms for creating an orbital motion.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a cross-sectional view of an exemplary apparatus that may be used to generate an orbital motion for a platen <b>1102</b> of the type described above. The supporting base is generally disclosed in U.S. Pat. No. 5,554,064 Breivogel et al. and is hereby incorporated by reference. The supporting base may have a rigid frame <b>1104</b> that can be fixedly secured. Stationary frame <b>1104</b> is used to provide support and balance. Outside ring <b>1106</b> of a lower bearing <b>1105</b> is rigidly fixed by clamps to stationary frame <b>1104</b>. Stationary frame <b>1104</b> prevents outside ring <b>1106</b> of lower bearing <b>1108</b> from rotating. Wave generator <b>1110</b> formed of a circular, hollow rigid stainless steel body is clamped to the inside ring <b>1112</b> of lower bearing <b>1108</b>. Wave generator <b>1110</b> is also clamped to outside ring <b>1114</b> of an upper bearing <b>1116</b>. Wave generator <b>1110</b> positions upper bearing <b>1116</b> parallel to lower bearing <b>1108</b>. Wave generator <b>1110</b> offsets the center axis <b>1117</b> of upper bearing <b>1116</b> from the center axis <b>1119</b> of lower bearing <b>1108</b>. A circular platen <b>1102</b> is symmetrically positioned and securely fastened to the inner rings of <b>1121</b> of upper bearing <b>1116</b>. A polishing pad or pad assembly can be securely fastened to ridge <b>1127</b> formed around the outside edge of the upper surface of platen <b>1102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">A universal joint <b>1120</b>, having two pivot points <b>1122</b><i>a </i>and <b>1122</b><i>b, </i>is securely fastened to stationary frame <b>1104</b> and to the bottom surface of platen <b>1102</b>. The lower portion of wave generator <b>1110</b> is rigidly connected to a hollow and cylindrical drive spool <b>1124</b> that in turn is connected to a hollow and cylindrical drive pulley <b>1125</b>. Drive pulley <b>1125</b> is coupled by a belt <b>1126</b> to a motor <b>1128</b>. Motor <b>1128</b> may be a variable speed, three phase, two horsepower AC motor.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The orbital motion of platen <b>1102</b> is generated by spinning wave generator <b>1110</b>. Wave generator <b>1110</b> is rotated by variable speed motor <b>1128</b>. As wave generator <b>1110</b> rotates, the center axis <b>1117</b> of upper bearing <b>1116</b> orbits about the center axis <b>1119</b> of lower bearing <b>1108</b>. The radius of the orbit of the upper bearing <b>1119</b> is equal to the offset (R) <b>1128</b> between the center axis <b>1117</b> of upper bearing <b>1116</b> and the center axis <b>1119</b> of the lower bearing <b>1108</b>. Upper bearing <b>1116</b> orbits about the center axis <b>1119</b> of lower bearing <b>1108</b> at a rate equal to the rotation of wave generator <b>1110</b>. It is to be noted that the outer ring <b>1114</b> of upper bearing <b>1116</b> not only orbits but also rotates (spins) as wave generator <b>1110</b> rotates. The function of universal joint <b>1120</b> is to prevent torque from rotating or spinning platen <b>1102</b>. The dual pivot points <b>1122</b><i>a </i>and <b>1122</b><i>b </i>of universal joint <b>1120</b> allow the platen <b>1102</b> to move in all directions except a rotational direction. By connecting platen <b>1102</b> to the inner ring <b>1121</b> of upper bearing <b>1116</b> and by connecting universal joint <b>1120</b> to platen <b>1102</b> and stationary frame <b>1104</b> the rotational movement of inner ring <b>1121</b> and platen <b>1102</b> is prevented and platen <b>1102</b> only orbits as desired. The orbit rate of platen <b>1102</b> is equal to the rotation rate of wave generator <b>1110</b> and the orbit radius of platen <b>1102</b> is equal to the offset of the center <b>1117</b> of upper bearing <b>1116</b> from the center <b>1117</b> of lower bearing <b>1108</b>. It is to be appreciated that a variety of other well-known means may be employed to facilitate the orbital motion of the polishing pad. While a particular method for producing an orbital motion has been given in detail, the present invention may be practiced using a variety of techniques for orbiting the polishing pad on the platen <b>1102</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The electrolytic solution contained in reservoir <b>910</b> includes the suitable precursors to the material being deposited onto the surface of wafer <b>904</b> (in this case, copper). Such solutions are generally known in the art and typically include dissolved copper such as copper sulfate, leveling agents, suppressants, and accelerators.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The apparatus of the present invention may include a temperature control mechanism for controlling the temperature of the electrolytic solution since the temperature of the surface of wafer <b>904</b> may have a significant effect on the uniformity of the deposited conductive film, the quality of the deposited film, and the rate of deposition or planarization of the film. If, for example, the temperature is too high in a given area, the deposition rate may increase in that area causing non-uniform film deposition on the surface of the wafer. To counteract the generation of localized hot spots, the electrolytic solution in reservoir in <b>910</b> may be cooled using any one of a number of known techniques for this purpose. For example, the electro-solution may be subject to a cooler or chiller before being delivered to surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">A method of simultaneously electrically chemically depositing material onto a surface of a wafer <b>904</b> and polishing the surface <b>812</b> thereof will now be described. Although the illustrated method includes substantially simultaneously polishing the wafer surface and depositing the material onto the wafer surface, alternate embodiments of the invention include intermittently depositing material onto the surface and polishing the wafer surface.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, wafer carrier assembly <b>902</b> urges wafer <b>904</b> against the polishing surface of pad <b>912</b> at a desired temperature. Preferably, the wafer carrier <b>902</b> applies a uniform and constant pressure of 3 PSI or less, although it will be appreciated that any suitable pressure which promotes polishing without interfering with the concurrent electrochemical deposition process may be used. Alternatively, to further control the rate of material removal and/or deposition, the wafer carrier may press the wafer against the polishing pad for a predetermined amount of time, subsequently withdraw the wafer from the polishing pad for a predetermined amount of time, and then repeat the pressing/withdrawing pattern for a desired number of times.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">During the polishing process, an electrolyte solution is delivered to the surface of polishing pad <b>612</b> through channels <b>708</b>. An electric potential is also applied to create a complete circuit between the platen and surface <b>912</b> of wafer <b>904</b>. Power supply <b>908</b> may be configured to (1) apply a constant voltage or constant current, (2) apply different currents or voltages at predetermined times in the process or (3) modulate between a predetermined current or voltage and no current or no voltage at all. Wafer carrier assembly <b>902</b> and wafer <b>904</b> may rotate about an axis while the platen assembly and polishing surface move in a rotational, orbital, or linear pattern. In addition, wafer carrier assembly <b>902</b> and wafer <b>904</b> may oscillate relative to the polishing surface. Adjusting the various conditions of the electrochemical deposition process, such as the electric potential, distance between the electric conductors and the wafer surface, conductivity of the electrolyte solution, temperature, and the like, permits suitable control of the uniformity and rate of deposition or planarization of conductive material onto or from the wafer surface.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> shows the anode of power supply <b>908</b> coupled to copper layer <b>610</b> and the cathode coupled to copper layer <b>606</b> (and therefore to polishing pad <b>612</b> via copper pins <b>906</b>) to effectuate an electrochemical deposition process. It should be clear, however, that by reversing the polarity of power supply <b>908</b> (i.e., electrically conductive layer <b>610</b> to the cathode and electrically conductive layer <b>606</b> to the anode) the process becomes a planarization process. That is, material will be removed from the surface of wafer <b>904</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Thus, there has been provided an improved method and apparatus for electrochemically depositing, planarizing, and/or polishing a conductive material on a workpiece surface. A potential difference is applied across a platen and a surface of a wafer through the use of upper and lower copper layers and conductive pins through the platen to complete the circuit. This potential difference in the presence of an electrolytic material such as a copper sulfate causes copper to be deposited on or removed from the surface of a semiconductor wafer depending on the polarity of the potential difference. A reservoir is provided for supplying a non-abrasive electrolyte into the region between a polishing pad and the wafer surface. Since the platen and polishing pad are only slightly larger in diameter than the wafer, electrolyte and/or slurry is introduced only under the wafer thus avoiding unwanted distribution of the slurry. The result is a more reliable and easier to manufacturer apparatus and method of depositing and/or planarizing a semiconductor wafer.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">In the foregoing specification, the invention has been described with reference to specific embodiments. However, it may be appreciated that various modifications and changes can be made without departing from the scope of the invention as set forth in the appended claims. Accordingly, the specification and figures are to be regarded as illustrative rather than as restrictive, and all such modifications are intended to be included within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A platen for use in an electrochemical process, the platen comprising:
<claim-text>a first insulating layer having a first surface and a second surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least a first aperture in said first insulating layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least a second aperture in said first insulating layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least a first insulating island protruding from said first surface and disposed around said first aperture;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least a second insulating island protruding from said second surface and disposed around said second aperture;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first conductive layer on said first surface around said first insulating island;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second conductive layer on said second surface and around said second insulating island; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least a first conductive element residing in said at least a first aperture and electrically coupled to said second conductive layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein said at least a first aperture comprises a first array of apertures.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein said first conductive layer is disposed onto said first surface in regions between each of said first array of apertures.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein said at least a second aperture comprises a second array of apertures.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein said second layer is disposed on said second surface in regions between each of said second array apertures.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein a surface of said first conducting layer is coplanar with the protruding end of each of said first array of insulating islands to form a first substantially flat surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein a surface of said second insulating layer is coplanar with a protruding end of each of said second array of insulating islands to form a second substantially flat surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein said at least a first conductive element comprises a plurality of conductive elements each residing in one of said first array of apertures and each electrically coupled to said second layer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> where each of said plurality of conductive elements comprises a conductive pin having a stem portion of a first dimension coupled to a head portion of a second dimension.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein said stem portion is electrically coupled to said second layer and said head portion has an upper surface coplanar with said protruding end of each of said first array of insulating islands.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein each of said plurality of conductive elements is copper.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref> wherein said first conductive layer is copper.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein said second conductive layer is copper.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> wherein said first insulating layer, said first array of insulating islands, and the second array of insulating islands are contiguously formed of from a non-electrically conducting polymer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising a second insulating layer disposed on said second substantially flat surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref> wherein said second insulating layer contains a third array of apertures which align with said second array of apertures.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> further comprising a support plate disposed proximate said second insulating layer, said support plate containing a fourth array of apertures which align with said third array of apertures.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref> wherein said support plate is metallic.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref> wherein said support plate is titanium.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising a polishing pad disposed on said first substantially flat surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00020">claim 20</claim-ref> wherein said polishing pad contains an array of contact pads therein which align with and electrically contact said conductive elements.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref> wherein each of said array of contact pads is formed of a conductively enhanced polymer material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref> wherein said polishing pad is formed of an insulating material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein said insulating material is polyurethane.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. A platen according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00023">claim 23</claim-ref> wherein said contact pads and said polishing pad are of substantially the same hardness.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
