<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296780-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296780</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11176366</doc-number>
<date>20050708</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>47</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251121</main-classification>
<further-classification>251331</further-classification>
<further-classification>239526</further-classification>
<further-classification>239570</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Control valve assembly structure for spray guns</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3763881</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jones</name>
<date>19731000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>137414</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6352212</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wang</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>239390</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6796515</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Heren et al.</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>239526</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251331</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>251 45</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239526</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239570</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239574</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239525</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>239527</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137846</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137849</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>137244</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Hung</last-name>
<first-name>Shih Yuan</first-name>
<address>
<city>Changhua Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Troxell Law Office, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ruey Ryh Enterprise Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Cnanghua Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Yu</last-name>
<first-name>Justine R.</first-name>
<department>3751</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Rost</last-name>
<first-name>Andrew J</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A control valve assembly structure for spray guns comprises a pistol body made up of water inlet and outlet conduits in fluid communication with a valve chamber having a control valve assembly mounted therein wherein the water inlet and outlet conduits and the valve chamber are respectively equipped with a first aperture, a second aperture, and a third aperture having a narrowed opening to form a stop seat for the abutting location of an end cover. The end cover has a receiving section and an actuating groove disposed therein for the accommodation of a valve seat and a spring element respectively, permitting a valve sleeve and a plunger flexibly pushed by the spring element to abut tight against a flexible valve whose water-sealing portion is stretched to tightly seal off the third aperture thereby, facilitating an even application of force thereon as well as an easier and economical processing thereof.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="210.65mm" wi="145.03mm" file="US07296780-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="186.52mm" wi="173.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296780-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="188.47mm" wi="173.99mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296780-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="227.41mm" wi="144.44mm" file="US07296780-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="266.02mm" wi="180.76mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296780-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="180.26mm" wi="178.73mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296780-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="193.12mm" wi="177.04mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296780-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention is related to a control valve assembly structure for spray guns, comprising a pistol body made up of water inlet and outlet conduits in fluid communication with a valve chamber having a control valve assembly mounted therein wherein a pressing guide surface of a plunger is closely abutted tight against a water-sealing portion of a flexible valve, and flexibly pushed and supported by a spring element so that force can be evenly applied onto the water-sealing portion thereof, facilitating an accurate and smooth operation thereof. Besides, the flexible valve is simplified in structure to provide an easier processing and save the cost in the making of mould for the economical efficiency thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b>. A conventional spray gun structure as disclosed in the U.S. Pat. No. 6,796,515B2 includes a spray gun 10 wherein a pistol body 11 is equipped with a valve chamber 111 and a valve shaft 12 mounted to a flexible diaphragm 13 at the valve chamber 111 therein. The control diaphragm 13 is clamped and located by an end cover 14 and a valve seat 15 to form a water seal-off state. When the valve shaft 12 is pushed, the flexible diaphragm 13 affected by the fluid pressure generated inside the pistol body 11 will be expanded to detach from the valve seat 15 thereof, permitting the fluid flow accommodated in an inlet conduit 16 to come into the valve seat 15 before sprayed outwards via an outlet conduit 17. However, the flexible diaphragm 13 simply makes use of the tension to control the shutoff or discharge of fluid flow, which is complicatedly structured and may increase the cost in the making of mold thereof. Besides, the flexible diaphragm 13 is fixedly located by the end cover 14 and the valve seat 15 and can only depend on the tension produced by the interior pressure of the pistol body 11 to control the operation thereof, which can easily cause flexible fatigue of the diaphragm 13 under the repeated expansion and contraction thereof and lead to awkward and jamming operation thereof.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">It is, therefore, the primary purpose of the present invention to provide a control valve assembly structure for spray guns, comprising a pistol body made up of water inlet and outlet conduits in fluid communication with a valve chamber having a control valve assembly mounted therein wherein a pressing guide surface of a plunger is closely abutted tight against a water-sealing portion of a flexible valve, and flexibly pushed and supported by a spring element so that force can be evenly applied onto the water-sealing portion thereof, facilitating an accurate and smooth operation thereof. Besides, the flexible valve is simplified in structure to provide an easier processing and save the cost in the making of mold for the economical efficiency thereof.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a conventional spray gun structure as disclosed in the U.S. Pat. No. 6,796,515B2 in a water-shutoff state.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is the conventional spray gun structure as disclosed in the U.S. Pat. No. 6,796,515B2 in a state of water discharge.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an assembled cross sectional view of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an exploded perspective view of a control valve assembly of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a partially assembled and cross sectional view of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a diagram showing a pressing operation of the present invention in a state of water discharge.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> showing an assembled cross sectional view of the present invention (accompanied by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref>, <b>5</b>). The present invention is related to a control valve assembly structure for spray guns, comprising a pistol body <b>20</b> having a water inlet conduit <b>21</b> and a water outlet conduit <b>22</b> in fluid communication with a valve chamber <b>23</b> disposed at the interior thereof to form a first aperture <b>211</b>, a second aperture <b>221</b>, and a third aperture <b>231</b> therein respectively wherein the third aperture <b>231</b> is shaped with a narrowed opening so as to provide a stop seat <b>232</b> defining the outer periphery of the third aperture <b>231</b> thereon. Into the valve chamber <b>23</b> thereof is accommodated a control valve assembly made up of an end cover <b>30</b>, a sleeve valve <b>40</b>, a plunger <b>50</b>, a valve seat <b>60</b>, and a flexible valve <b>70</b>. The end cover <b>30</b> with one contact edge abutted against the stop seat <b>232</b> of the valve chamber <b>23</b> is equipped with a positioning seat <b>31</b> having a sealing ring <b>311</b> mounted thereon to precisely abut tight against the opening end of the valve chamber <b>23</b> thereby, and a screw hole <b>32</b> disposed at the other contact end thereof to reciprocally lock with an adjusting cap <b>24</b> so as to adjustably rotate the end cover <b>30</b> thereby. At the interior of end cover <b>30</b> is disposed a receiving section <b>33</b> for the accommodation of the valve seat <b>60</b> therein, and an actuating chamber <b>34</b> with a plurality of stop rings <b>35</b> formed at the inner wall thereon, permitting the end edge of the valve seat <b>60</b> and a positioning ring <b>61</b> protruding at the outer periphery thereon to respectively abut against the stop rings <b>35</b> for location thereby. At the bottom of the actuating chamber <b>34</b> thereof is disposed a protrusive rod <b>341</b> for the mounting of a spring element <b>36</b> thereon. The interior of the valve seat <b>60</b> is shaped in stepwise having a first chamber <b>62</b> and a second chamber <b>63</b> respectively formed therein to provide a set of first and second locating seats <b>621</b>, <b>631</b> for the abutting location of the sleeve valve <b>40</b> and the plunger <b>50</b> thereby. The inner wall of the first and second chambers <b>62</b>, <b>63</b> is respectively defined by a plurality of first/second guide grooves <b>622</b>, <b>632</b> to be reciprocally matched with a plurality of first/second guide blocks <b>41</b>, <b>51</b> respectively protruding at the outer periphery of the sleeve valve <b>40</b> and the plunger <b>50</b> thereon. The sleeve valve <b>40</b> also includes a sleeve hole <b>42</b> with a limiting seat <b>421</b> defining thereon to be mounted to the other end of the spring element <b>36</b> thereof, permitting the sleeve valve <b>40</b> and the plunger <b>50</b> accurately in flexible support by the spring element <b>36</b> to respectively abut tight and close against the first and the second locating seats <b>621</b>, <b>631</b> thereon, and the plunger <b>50</b> to extend outwards from the valve seat <b>60</b> thereof. The sleeve valve <b>40</b> has serrated toothed surface <b>43</b> defining one end edge thereon to precisely mesh with a matching toothed end <b>52</b> of the plunger <b>50</b> disposed at the corresponding contact side thereof. Besides, the plunger <b>50</b> has a conically tapered pressing guide surface <b>53</b> disposed at the other end thereon, and a valve shaft <b>54</b> extending from the center of the pressing guide surface <b>53</b> to be actuated by the pushing operation of a control button <b>25</b> thereby. The flexible valve <b>70</b> has a central thru-hole <b>71</b> disposed thereon for the extending there-through of the valve shaft <b>54</b> of the plunger <b>50</b>, permitting the flexible valve <b>70</b> to accommodate into an indented cavity <b>64</b> defining one end surface of the valve seat <b>60</b> thereof. A conic water-sealing portion <b>72</b> is provided protruding at one side of the flexible valve <b>70</b> to be closely abutted tight by the pressing guide surface <b>53</b> thereof, and an inserting rib <b>73</b> is annularly disposed at the outer periphery of the conic water-sealing portion <b>72</b> thereof to be reciprocally mounted into an insert recess <b>741</b> defining one end surface of a support collar <b>74</b>, permitting the outer periphery and the one end surface of the support collar <b>74</b> thereof to precisely abut against the indented cavity <b>64</b> thereby. Multiple support blocks <b>742</b> are provided protruding at the other end surface of the support collar <b>74</b> to abut against the stop seat <b>232</b> of the valve chamber <b>23</b>, permitting a plurality of water inlet spaces <b>743</b> to form between the stop seat <b>232</b> and the support blocks <b>742</b> thereby. A limiting hole <b>744</b> is formed at the center of the support collar <b>74</b> for the extending there-through of the water-sealing portion <b>72</b> of the flexible valve <b>70</b> that is flexibly pushed and stretched by the pressing guide surface <b>53</b> of the plunger <b>50</b> to abut closely against the third aperture <b>231</b> so as to securely separate the first aperture <b>211</b> from the second aperture <b>221</b> to achieve a water sealing-off state thereby. Besides, the end cover <b>30</b> also has a passage <b>37</b> disposed at one side corresponding to the first aperture <b>211</b> of the water inlet conduit <b>21</b>, and the adjusting cap <b>24</b> is adjustably rotated to change the position of the passage <b>37</b> so as to control the amount of water discharge thereby.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Please refer to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> showing a press operation of the present invention in a state of water discharge. The control button <b>25</b> is pushed to press against the valve shaft <b>54</b> and allow the guide blocks <b>51</b>, <b>41</b> of the plunger <b>50</b> and the sleeve valve <b>40</b> thereof to respectively slide along the guide grooves <b>622</b>, <b>632</b> of the first and second chambers <b>62</b>, <b>63</b> thereof and compress against the spring element <b>36</b> thereby. Meanwhile, the pressing guide surface <b>53</b> of the plunger <b>50</b> will stop abutting against the flexible valve <b>70</b>, releasing the water-sealing portion <b>72</b> thereof from the pushing force of the spring element <b>36</b>, the sleeve valve <b>40</b> and the plunger <b>50</b> thereof to flexibly bounce inwards so as to fluidly communicate the third aperture <b>231</b> with the first and second apertures <b>211</b>, <b>221</b> in an opening-up state thereby. Therefore, fluid flow accommodated in the water inlet conduit <b>21</b> will sequentially flow from the first aperture <b>211</b> and the passage <b>37</b> of the end cover <b>30</b> to go through the water inlet spaces <b>743</b> of the support collar <b>74</b> and then the third and second apertures <b>231</b>, <b>221</b> till entering the water outlet conduit <b>22</b> to be discharged there-from. In case the control button <b>25</b> is released to stop the pressing operation of the valve shaft <b>54</b>, the compressed spring element <b>36</b> will flexibly rebound and again press against the sleeve valve <b>40</b> and the plunger <b>50</b> to recover their former positions respectively. As a result, the water-sealing portion <b>74</b> of the flexible valve <b>70</b> will be synchronically pushed and stretched by the pressing guide surface <b>53</b> of the plunger <b>50</b> to closely abut tight against the third aperture <b>231</b> and seal off the water discharge thereby. Therefore, via the pressing guide surface <b>53</b> of the plunger <b>50</b> in close abutting contact with the water-sealing portion <b>74</b> of the flexible valve <b>70</b> and flexibly pushed and supported by the spring element <b>36</b> thereof, force can be evenly applied onto the water-sealing portion <b>74</b> thereof to facilitate more accurate and smooth operation thereof. Besides, the flexible valve <b>70</b> is simplified in structure to provide an easier processing as well as to save the cost in the opening of mold for the economical efficiency thereof.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A control valve assembly structure for spray guns, comprising a pistol body having a water inlet conduit and a water outlet conduit in fluid communication with a valve chamber into which is accommodated a control valve assembly made up of an end cover, a sleeve valve, a plunger, a valve seat, and a flexible valve; the control valve assembly structure for a spray gun further comprising:
<claim-text>the water outlet conduit, the water inlet conduit, and the valve chamber of the pistol body thereof being respectively equipped with a second aperture, a first aperture, and a third aperture shaped with a narrowed opening to provide a stop seat defining the outer periphery thereon;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the end cover of the control valve assembly having one contact edge abutted against a stop seat of the valve chamber, a positioning seat with a sealing ring mounted thereon to precisely abut tight against the opening end of the valve chamber thereby, and an adjusting cap locked at the other contact end thereon so as to adjustably rotate the end cover thereby; at the interior of end cover being disposed a receiving section for the accommodation of the valve seat therein, and an actuating chamber for the abutting location of the valve seat and a spring element thereby;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the valve seat having a first chamber and a second chamber respectively formed at the interior therein to provide a set of first and second locating seats for the abutting location of the sleeve valve and the plunger thereby;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the sleeve valve having a sleeve hole with a limiting seat defining thereon to be mounted to the other end of the spring element thereof, permitting the plunger flexibly supported by the spring element to extend outwards from the valve seat thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the plunger having a pressing guide surface disposed at one end thereon, and a valve shaft extending from the center of the pressing guide surface thereof to be actuated by the pushing operation of a control button thereby;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the flexible valve having a central thru-hole for the extending there-through of the valve shaft of the plunger, permitting the flexible valve to accommodate into an indented cavity defining one end surface of the valve seat thereby; the flexible valve also including a water-sealing portion disposed at one side thereon to be pushed and abutted tight by the pressing guide surface of the plunger thereby, and an inserting rib annularly disposed at the outer periphery of the water-sealing portion to be reciprocally mounted to an insert recess of a support collar thereby, permitting the support collar to precisely abut against the valve seat thereby;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the support collar having multiple support blocks protruding at the other end surface thereon to abut against the stop seat of the valve chamber, permitting a plurality of water inlet spaces to be formed between the stop seat and the support blocks thereof, and a limiting hole being disposed at the center of the support collar for the extending there-through of the water-sealing portion of the flexible valve that is flexibly pushed and stretched by the pressing guide surface of the plunger to abut closely against the third aperture so as to securely separate the first aperture from the second aperture and achieve a water sealing-off state thereby;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the end cover also having a passage disposed at one side corresponding to the first aperture of the water inlet conduit, and the adjusting cap being adjustably rotated to change the position of the passage so as to control the amount of water discharge thereby.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The control valve assembly structure for spray guns as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the end cover is equipped with a screw hole disposed at one end edge thereon to be reciprocally locked to the adjusting cap thereby.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The control valve assembly structure for spray guns as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the receiving section and the actuating chamber of the end cover is provided with a plurality of stop rings formed at the inner wall thereon, permitting the end edge of the valve seat and a positioning ring protruding at the outer periphery thereon to respectively abut against the stop rings for location thereby.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The control valve assembly structure for spray guns as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the first and second chambers of the valve seat is respectively provided with a plurality of first/second guide grooves to be matched to a plurality of first/second guide blocks respectively protruding at the outer periphery of the sleeve valve and the plunger thereon for reciprocal engagement therewith.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The control valve assembly structure for spray guns as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the sleeve valve has serrated toothed surface defining one end edge thereon to precisely mesh with a matching toothed end of the plunger disposed at the corresponding contact side thereon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The control valve assembly structure for spray guns as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the pressing guide surface of the plunger is made in a conically tapered shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The control valve assembly structure for spray guns as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the water-sealing portion of the flexible valve is made in a conic shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
