<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297870-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297870</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11135304</doc-number>
<date>20050523</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>02</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174 50</main-classification>
<further-classification>174 63</further-classification>
<further-classification>362148</further-classification>
<further-classification>248 57</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Unitized fixture frame and junction box and method of forming same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4274615</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chan et al.</name>
<date>19810600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4336575</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gilman</name>
<date>19820600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362147</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4408262</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kusmer</name>
<date>19831000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5662414</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Jennings et al.</name>
<date>19970900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5857766</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sieczkowski</name>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6461016</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Jamison et al.</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6691968</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Tseng</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7118254</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Czech</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362365</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0231954</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Czech</name>
<date>20051000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362263</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174 50</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174 63</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174 65 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248 57</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248343</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>200297</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362148</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Sartini</last-name>
<first-name>Gene</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fall River</city>
<state>MA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cole</last-name>
<first-name>James E.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Middleton Reutlinger</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Genlyte Thomas Group, LLC</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Louisville</city>
<state>KY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Patel</last-name>
<first-name>Dhiru R.</first-name>
<department>2831</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A fixture frame having a junction box formed from a blank and an integrally connected frame arm connected to the junction box and formed from the blank. The frame arm is formable in a plurality of configurations for receiving a corresponding plurality of ring aperture sizes.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="134.03mm" wi="140.63mm" file="US07297870-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="211.33mm" wi="158.83mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="148.67mm" wi="145.88mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="226.23mm" wi="114.64mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="180.09mm" wi="147.24mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="184.32mm" wi="155.62mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="192.87mm" wi="157.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="149.61mm" wi="143.00mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="160.10mm" wi="147.07mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="178.39mm" wi="148.51mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297870-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCES TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">None.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR DEVELOPMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">None.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">REFERENCE TO SEQUENTIAL LISTING, ETC.</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">None.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The present invention relates to a recessed downlight mounting fixture frame. More specifically, the present invention relates to recessed downlight mounting fixture frame which may be utilized with a plurality of recessed lighting sizes but is formed from a single blank and therefore improves manufacturing efficiency.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Recessed downlights have become increasingly popular for use in both commercial and residential constructions and as a result, competition has increased dramatically in this lighting area. One reason for the increased popularity is that the recessed downlight fixtures meet a wide range of interior lighting requirements while also being aesthetically pleasing. The recessed lighting fixtures come in various sizes and therefore can be used in multiple arrangements depending on room size, ceiling height and desired brightness. Further these recessed downlight fixtures may be installed in new constructions as well as existing ceilings and therefore installers like using them. Typically, ceiling-mounted recessed downlight fixtures comprise a frame or frame-in kit with a fixture frame connection means for retaining the fixture frame between structural supports of the ceiling.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Fixture frames are an integral component of the recessed downlight and hold the fixture, reflector, reflector trim, lamp and other parts in place. As previously described, the recessed downlights come in various sizes and therefore require fixture frames to be formed in corresponding various sizes to retain the fixtures. Since distinct frames must be formed for each size light fixture, manufacturing efficiency is decreased. Specifically, forming separate fixture frames for each lighting size is difficult because it raises tooling and manufacturing costs while decreasing production output.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Given the foregoing deficiencies, it will be appreciated that a recessed downlight mounting fixture frame is needed which is formed from a single blank which therefore increases manufacturing efficiency and maybe utilized with various fixture sizes.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">With regard to the foregoing, the present invention eliminates the oversights, difficulties, and disadvantages of the prior art by providing a recessed downlight mounting fixture frame.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to one embodiment, a fixture frame comprises a frame arm having a first end and a second end, the frame arm further comprising a first elbow and a second elbow between the first end and the second end. A junction box is integrally connected to the frame arm between the first elbow and the second elbow, the frame arm has multiple bend positions defining the first and second elbows. The fixture frame is formed from a single blank and includes mounting means. The fixture frame can receive aperture rings of multiple diameters at two opposed locations.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to a second embodiment, a fixture frame comprises a junction box integrally formed with a frame arm, the frame arm has first and second ends, the junction box is disposed between the first and second ends. The frame arm has multiple bend positions defining first and second elbows. The junction box and the frame arm are formed from a single blank and capable of receiving multiple aperture ring sizes.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to yet another embodiment, a fixture frame comprises a junction box formed from a blank and an integrally connected frame arm connected to said junction box and formed from said blank. The frame arm is formable to a plurality of configurations for receiving a corresponding plurality of ring aperture sizes.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">According to still another embodiment, a fixture frame comprises a junction box and a frame arm formed from a single metal blank, the frame arm has a first arm portion, a second arm portion and a third arm portion defining a substantially U-shape. The junction box is integrally connected to the first arm portion and the frame arm has elbows disposed between the first arm portion and the second arm portion as well as the first arm portion and the third arm portion. The elbows being formable in various positions to vary a preselected distance between the second arm portion and the third arm portion. A method of forming fixture frame, comprising:</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">A final embodiment of forming the fixture frame has a junction box and an integral frame arm wherein the fixture frame is formed from a single blank of material and receives multiple aperture ring sizes, comprises the steps of forming one of the junction box and the frame arm from the single blank, forming the other of the junction box and the frame arm from the single blank, and forming the frame arm to receive one of the multiple aperture ring sizes.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">A method of forming fixture frame having a junction box and an integral frame arm wherein the fixture frame is formed from a single blank of material and can receive multiple aperture ring sizes comprises the steps of forming one of the junction box and the frame arm from said single blank in a progressive die, forming the other of the junction box and the frame arm from the single blank in a progressive die; forming the frame arm to receive one of the multiple aperture ring sizes in a secondary tooling.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Several benefits and advantages are derived from the broad method and/or the embodiment of the invention. The instant invention provides a single blank which may be manufactured and formed into a junction box and integral frame arm. The frame arm may be formed into a plurality of shapes during manufacture in order to receive a corresponding plurality of aperture ring sizes.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a fixture frame-in kit including a unitized frame and junction box of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of the unitized frame and junction box of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a top view of the unitized frame and junction box of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> laid out on a sheet of material which defines a blank;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a top view of the unitized frame and junction box of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a side view of the unitized frame and junction box of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a perspective view of a first alternative embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a perspective view of a second alternative embodiment;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a perspective view of a third alternative embodiment; and,</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a perspective view of a fourth alternative embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">It shall be understood that the invention is not limited in its application to the details of construction and the arrangement of components set forth in the following description or illustrated in the drawings. The invention is capable of other embodiments and of being practiced or of being carried out in various ways. Also, it shall be understood that the phraseology and terminology used herein is for the purpose of description and should not be regarded as limiting. The use of “including,” “comprising,” or “having” and variations thereof herein is meant to encompass the items listed thereafter and equivalents thereof as well as additional items. Unless limited otherwise, the terms “connected,” “coupled,” and “mounted,” and variations thereof herein are used broadly and encompass direct and indirect connections, couplings, and mountings. In addition, the terms “connected” and “coupled” and variations thereof are not restricted to physical or mechanical connections or couplings. Furthermore, and as described in subsequent paragraphs, the specific mechanical configurations illustrated in the drawings are intended to exemplify embodiments of the invention and that other alternative mechanical configurations are possible.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Referring now in detail to the drawings, wherein like numerals indicate like elements throughout the several views, there are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 through 9</figref> various aspects of a recessed downlight fixture frame both before and after manufacture. The fixture frame is formed from a single sheet of material or blank form utilizing a progressive die in order to improve manufacturing efficiency, reduce waste, and reduce cost of materials utilized in manufacturing the mounting fixture. Further, a single fixture frame blank may be utilized to form a fixture frame for use with light fixtures and reflectors of various sizes.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Referring initially to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a perspective view of a recessed downlight mounting or frame-in kit <b>10</b> is depicted. The frame-in kit <b>10</b> is typically positioned above an interior ceiling to provide useable downlight as well as reduce glare seen by those utilizing the room, or within an over-hanging eve on the exterior of a building. The frame-in kit <b>10</b> is preferably formed of a formable metallic material, such as steel, aluminum or other such lightweight metal. The frame-in kit of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> comprises a plurality of hanger bars <b>12</b> which extend between joists or suspended ceiling members (not shown). An exemplary embodiment of the hanger bars <b>12</b> is described in U.S. patent application Ser. No. 11/117,680, which is incorporated by reference herein. The hanger bars <b>12</b> are connected to the frame-in kit <b>10</b> by a clip mechanism <b>14</b> which retains the slidable relationship between adjacent hanger bars <b>12</b> and also provides adjustability in a vertical dimension. When the hanger bars <b>12</b> are connected to ceiling members. The frame-in kit <b>10</b> remains suspended therebetween and above ceiling level.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The frame-in kit <b>10</b> further comprises an aperture ring <b>16</b> which is disposed along inside surfaces of a fixture frame <b>30</b>. The aperture ring <b>16</b> functions to retain a housing or “can” (not shown) wherein various lighting components are located, including but not limited to, the lamp socket, the lamp, the reflector and trim. The aperture ring <b>16</b> is substantially cylindrical in shape with a flat upper surface <b>18</b> connected to the clip mechanism <b>14</b>. As described further herein, a single fixture frame <b>30</b> can receive multiple ring sizes and therefore multiple housing or “can” sizes. This</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, a fixture frame <b>30</b> comprises a frame arm <b>32</b> and an integral junction box <b>50</b>. First, the junction box <b>50</b> comprises a top wall <b>52</b>, a bottom wall opposite the top wall <b>52</b> and opposed side walls <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> extending between the top wall <b>52</b> and bottom wall <b>58</b>. The junction box <b>50</b> defines a position where wire splices may be located providing electrical communication between a ballast (not shown) and a light source or lamp, such as a high intensity discharge (HID) lamp (not shown). The junction box top wall <b>152</b>, bottom wall <b>158</b> and side walls <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> further define front and rear openings which are substantially rectangular or square in shape. Junction box doors (not shown) are disposed over the openings in order to close the junction box <b>50</b> per applicable electrical codes. The junction box doors (not shown) are connected to the junction box by door apertures <b>59</b> located in the bottom wall <b>58</b> of the junction box <b>50</b> as well as an arm or spring <b>53</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) extending across the top wall <b>52</b>. Otherwise stated, the junction box doors have tabs extending into the apertures <b>59</b> to retain a bottom edge of each door while the top edge of each door is retained against the junction box top wall <b>52</b> by an arm (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 6</figref>) extending across the junction box top wall <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The junction box side walls <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> and the top wall <b>52</b> each comprise a plurality of knockouts <b>55</b>. The knockouts <b>55</b> provide a plurality of wire paths for electrical wires and conduit to move from the ballast (not shown) to within the junction box <b>50</b> and from within the junction box <b>50</b> to the lamp (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The fixture frame <b>30</b> further comprises a frame arm <b>32</b> integrally connected to the junction box <b>50</b> having a first end <b>31</b><i>a </i>and second end <b>31</b><i>b </i>each comprising a mounting bracket <b>60</b> along an inside edge of the bottom wall <b>58</b>. The mounting means <b>60</b> are utilized for connection of the aperture ring <b>16</b>. More specifically, the frame arm <b>32</b> comprises a first arm portion <b>34</b>, integrally connected to the junction box <b>50</b>, and having first and second distal ends. The frame arm <b>32</b> further comprises a second arm portion <b>36</b> and a third arm portion <b>38</b>. At a first end of the first arm portion <b>34</b> is a first elbow <b>40</b> and at a second end of the first arm portion <b>34</b> is a second elbow <b>42</b>. The first and second elbows <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> connect the first arm portion <b>34</b> to the second arm portion <b>36</b> and third arm portion <b>38</b>, respectively. Thus, the frame arm <b>32</b> is defined by the first arm portion <b>34</b>, second arm portion <b>36</b> and third arm portion <b>38</b>. At distal ends of the second and third arm portions <b>36</b>, <b>38</b> are opposed mounting brackets <b>60</b> which connect the clip mechanism <b>14</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). As will be discussed further, the frame arm <b>32</b> is manufactured from a single blank into various configurations to allow the fixture frame <b>30</b> to receive various aperture ring sizes.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The elbows <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> are formed at ends of the first arm portion <b>34</b> to partially define a pre-selected spacing between the second arm portion <b>36</b> and the third arm portion <b>38</b> as well as between the mounting brackets <b>60</b>. As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the spacing between the second and third arm portions <b>36</b>, <b>38</b> and the opposed mounting brackets <b>60</b> is provided to receive the aperture ring <b>16</b> wherein a reflector and lamp may be located. The elbows <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> may be disposed at various positions and in various orientations in order to change the configuration of the blank so that a single blank may be utilized to form a fixture frame which may be used in combination with various light fixture sizes. Thus, although the first, second and third arm portions are described as part of the frame arm <b>32</b>, the elbows are the structural feature which distinguish these portions from one another.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">One advantage of the instant invention is that a single frame <b>30</b> may be utilized to receive multiple aperture ring sizes. Accordingly, various size reflectors may be utilized with the frame <b>30</b>. A further advantage of the present invention is that the frame <b>30</b> may be formed from a single blank and may be manufactured to receive various reflector sizes, as described herein.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-6</figref>, the fixture frame <b>30</b> is shown in various views from the starting point of a blank piece of metal through various tooling processes to form the fixture frame <b>30</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The fixture frame <b>30</b> is depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> as a blank prior to any folding processes by tooling equipment during manufacturing. The blank layout of the fixture frame <b>30</b> is depicted with solid lines representing the edges of the cut blank while fold lines generally shown as broken lines along the blank and is formed in a progressive die. As previously described, the fixture frame <b>30</b> has a junction box <b>50</b> comprising a bottom wall <b>58</b>, opposed side walls <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> and two surfaces which are folded to generally form the top wall <b>52</b>. Integrally connected to the junction box is the frame arm <b>32</b>, which is defined by the first arm portion <b>34</b>, the second arm portion <b>36</b> and the third arm portion <b>38</b>, the latter portions <b>36</b>, <b>38</b> disposed at the opposed ends of the first arm portion. The blank also reveals the elbows <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> generally distinguishing the first arm portion <b>34</b> from the second and third arm portions <b>36</b>, <b>38</b> as will be described further herein.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the fixture frame <b>30</b> is shown in a perspective view. The junction box <b>50</b> is formed in the progressive die and is shown partially formed by folding the side walls <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> at opposed edges of the bottom wall <b>58</b>. As the side walls <b>54</b>,<b>56</b> are folded upwardly the two sections defining the top wall <b>52</b> are also folded such that the junction box is partially formed. Preferably, the junction box <b>50</b> is fully formed in the progressive die but is depicted in the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3-6</figref> to show the progression of bends made to form the junction box <b>50</b>. The frame arm <b>32</b> is still depicted in its flattened position so that the elbows are not distinguishing the first arm portion <b>34</b> from the second and third arm portions <b>36</b>, <b>38</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the junction box <b>50</b> is again shown in its partially completed position. The frame arm <b>32</b> is folded at a substantially perpendicular angle to the junction box <b>50</b>, which may be performed in the progressive die or a secondary tooling. Further, the frame arm <b>32</b> is shown with elbows <b>40</b> and <b>42</b> distinguishing the first arm portion <b>34</b> from the second and third arm portions <b>36</b>, <b>38</b>. The frame arm <b>32</b> is bent in a secondary tooling to begin forming the elbows <b>40</b>,<b>42</b>. The elbows <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> are not fully formed since the first and second arm portions <b>36</b>, <b>38</b> are not fully disposed in a parallel configuration, as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Depending on the size/embodiment of the fixture frame <b>30</b> being formed, as discussed further herein, different secondary toolings may be utilized.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the junction box <b>50</b> is fully folded so that the two upper surfaces defining the top wall are properly oriented and aligned to receive a junction box door retaining arm or spring <b>53</b> and fastener, such as a rivet or screw. Further, the frame arm <b>32</b> is fully folded in a secondary tooling to its substantially U-shaped configuration so that the elbows <b>40</b>, <b>42</b> are fully formed. As a result, the second and third arm portions <b>36</b>, <b>38</b> are parallel to one another and substantially perpendicular to the first arm portion <b>34</b>. Further, in this position, the mounting brackets <b>60</b>, are also parallel to properly receive an aperture ring of a pre-selected specific size.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a first alternative embodiment of a fixture frame <b>130</b> is depicted comprising elbows <b>140</b>, <b>142</b> which are formed during manufacture of the product in order to receive the aperture ring of a smaller size than that of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. The elbows <b>140</b>, <b>142</b> are bent in a manner which is different from the ninety degree (90°) bend shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. According to the second embodiment, elbows <b>140</b>, <b>142</b> each comprise a first bend <b>143</b> and a second bend <b>145</b>. The first bend <b>143</b> extends from the first arm portion <b>134</b> toward the junction box <b>50</b>. The second bend <b>145</b> is greater than 90 degrees and turns toward a distal end of the second and third arm portions, away from the junction box <b>50</b>. Accordingly, the first bend defines a first obtuse angle and the second bend defines an acute angle to provide a pre-selected distance between the second and third arm portions <b>136</b>, <b>138</b>. With this first alternative embodiment, the elbows <b>140</b>,<b>142</b> design effectively shortens the frame arm length <b>32</b> so that the preselected distance between the second frame arm portion and the third frame arm portion is decreased, as compared to the first embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. With this design, the frame arm <b>132</b> is sized to receive a ring aperture of a smaller diameter than the ring aperture <b>16</b> of Figure with fixture frame <b>30</b>. Further, the frame <b>130</b> may be formed of the same material and the same blank as used to form the fixture frame <b>30</b>. By merely changing the elbow bending step during manufacturing, the blank may be shaped to form a ring aperture of a larger or smaller size.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, a second alternative fixture frame <b>230</b> is depicted. The fixture frame <b>230</b> comprises a junction box as well as a frame arm <b>232</b> defined by a first arm portion <b>234</b> having first and second ends integrally connected to the junction box <b>50</b>. The frame arm <b>234</b> further comprises second and third arm portions <b>236</b>,<b>238</b> connected by elbows <b>240</b>,<b>242</b> to first and second ends of the first arm portion <b>234</b>. The frame arm <b>232</b> defines a substantially U-shaped structure as shown in the fixture frame <b>30</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> such that the second and third arm portions <b>236</b>,<b>238</b> are parallel. However, the second and third arm portions <b>236</b>,<b>238</b> are spaced apart a preselected distance further than the fixture frame <b>30</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) or fixture frame <b>130</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>) so as to receive an aperture ring having a larger diameter than the fixture frame <b>30</b> or the fixture frame <b>130</b>. Accordingly, the first arm portion <b>234</b> is longer than that of the first arm portion <b>34</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) or the first arm portion <b>134</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>). Elbows <b>240</b>, <b>242</b> extend between the first arm portion and the second and third arm portions, respectively. By lengthening the first arm portion <b>234</b> and locating ninety-degree (90°) elbows <b>240</b>,<b>242</b> at first and second ends of the first arm portion <b>234</b> the preselected distance between the first arm portion <b>236</b> and the third arm portion <b>238</b> and mounting brackets <b>60</b> is widened to receive an aperture ring of a larger diameter than the fixture frame <b>30</b> and first alternative fixture frame <b>130</b>. Otherwise stated, the exemplary embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> moves the elbows <b>240</b>,<b>242</b> laterally along the first arm portion <b>234</b> and away from the junction box <b>50</b> in order to widen the distance between the second arm portion <b>236</b> and third arm portion <b>238</b>. However, this embodiment is formed from the same blank as the fixture frames <b>30</b> and <b>130</b> but can accept different sized aperture rings by merely changing the elbow <b>240</b>,<b>242</b> configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, a third alternative embodiment is depicted. A fixture frame <b>330</b> comprises a junction box <b>50</b> and a substantially U-shaped arm <b>332</b>. The arm <b>332</b> comprises a first portion <b>334</b> and opposed second and third arm portions <b>336</b>, <b>338</b> respectively. The second and third arm portions <b>336</b>, <b>338</b> are disposed at first and second ends of the first arm portion <b>334</b> by elbows <b>340</b>, <b>342</b>, respectively. The first elbow <b>340</b> and second elbow <b>342</b> are defined by obtuse angles as measured between the inside surface of the second arm portion <b>336</b> or third arm portion <b>338</b> and the inner surface of the first arm portion <b>334</b>. By forming the frame arm <b>332</b> in such a manner, the mounting brackets <b>60</b> are spaced apart at a pre-selected distance to receive an aperture ring of a size larger than the previously described embodiments. Since the second and third arm portions <b>336</b>,<b>338</b> are not parallel as in the previously described embodiments, clip elbows <b>349</b> are formed at distal ends of the second and third arm portions <b>336</b>,<b>338</b> so that the clip mechanisms <b>14</b> are parallel for proper connection of the aperture ring <b>16</b>. One of ordinary skill in the art should recognize that the fixture frame <b>330</b> is also formed from the blank (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) which is utilized to form the previously described embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The foregoing description of several methods and an embodiment of the invention has been presented for purposes of illustration. It is not intended to be exhaustive or to limit the invention to the precise steps and/or forms disclosed, and obviously many modifications and variations are possible in light of the above teaching. It is intended that the scope of the invention be defined by the claims appended hereto.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A fixture frame, comprising:
<claim-text>a frame arm having a first end and a second end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm further comprising a first elbow and a second elbow between said first end and said second end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a junction box integrally connected to said frame arm between said first elbow and said second elbow;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm having multiple bend positions defining said first and second elbows;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said fixture frame formed from a single blank;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm further extending from said elbows to mounting means for receiving aperture rings of multiple diameters at two opposed locations.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The fixture frame of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said frame arm being substantially U-shaped.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The fixture frame of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said frame arm being formed to receive multiple ring apertures sizes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The fixture frame of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said mounting means being a mounting bracket.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The fixture frame of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said frame arm having said multiple bend positions to allow mounting of various sizes of aperture ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A fixture frame, comprising:
<claim-text>a junction box integrally formed with a frame arm;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm having first and second ends, said junction box disposed between said first and second ends;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm having multiple bend positions defining first and second elbows;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said junction box and said arm formed from a single blank said ends capable of receiving multiple aperture ring sizes.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The fixture frame of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, said frame arm being substantially U-shaped to engage an aperture ring at two opposed positions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The fixture frame of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> further comprising a mounting bracket at each end of said frame arm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A fixture frame, comprising:
<claim-text>a junction box formed from a blank;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an integrally connected frame arm connected to said junction box and formed from said blank;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an elbow disposed along said frame arm, said frame arm extending beyond said elbow to an end for receiving an aperture ring.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A fixture frame for multiple ring aperture sizes, comprising:
<claim-text>a junction box and a substantially U-shaped frame arm integrally connected to said junction box;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm having a first arm portion with first and second opposed ends;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm having a second arm portion and a third arm portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first and second elbows disposed at said first and second ends, respectively, of said first arm portion connecting said second and third arm portions to said first arm portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said elbows being formable so that said frame arm can receive a plurality of ring aperture sizes.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A fixture frame, comprising:
<claim-text>a junction box and a frame arm formed from a single metal blank;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm having a first arm portion, a second arm portion and a third arm portion defining a substantially U-shape;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said junction box integrally connected to said first arm portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said frame arm having elbows disposed between said first arm portion and said second arm portion and said first arm portion and said third arm portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said elbows being formable in various positions to vary a preselected distance between said second arm portion and said third arm portion.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method of forming fixture frame, comprising:
<claim-text>a fixture frame having a junction box and an integral frame arm wherein said fixture frame is formable from a single blank of material to receive multiple aperture ring sizes:</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming one of said junction box and said frame arm from said single blank in a progressive die;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming the other of said junction box and said frame arm from said single blank in a progressive die;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming said frame arm to receive one of said multiple aperture ring sizes in a secondary tooling.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A fixture frame arm assembly, comprising:
<claim-text>a frame arm having a first end and a second end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a junction box integrally connected to said frame arm and disposed between said first end and said second end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first elbow disposed between said junction box and said first end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second elbow disposed between said junction box and said second end;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said junction box and said frame arm formed from a single blank;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said elbows capable of being formed at various locations along said frame arm such that said first and second ends may receive aperture rings of various diameters.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
