<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297015-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297015</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11687839</doc-number>
<date>20070319</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>64</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439377</main-classification>
<further-classification>361755</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Apparatus for docking a printed circuit board</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5115376</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Nakajima</name>
<date>19920500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5269698</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Singer</name>
<date>19931200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439157</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5790373</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kim et al.</name>
<date>19980800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5919055</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hattori</name>
<date>19990700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439310</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6093040</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kodama et al.</name>
<date>20000700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439157</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6195259</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Whitman et al.</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6267609</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Korsunsky et al.</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439160</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6406312</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Heitkamp</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6411517</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Babin</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6667890</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Barringer et al.</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6930892</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Barringer et al.</name>
<date>20050800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361801</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439 64</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439260</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439310</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439377</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361726</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361727</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361747</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361755</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361756</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Desrosiers</last-name>
<first-name>Norman Bruce</first-name>
<address>
<city>Oxford</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Herring</last-name>
<first-name>Dean Frederick</first-name>
<address>
<city>Youngsville</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Byrd</last-name>
<first-name>Cynthia S.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Streets &amp; Steele</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Streets</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey L.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>International Business Machines Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Armonk</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Le</last-name>
<first-name>Thanh-Tam</first-name>
<department>2839</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An apparatus comprising a guide plate selectively securable in a position adjacent a first electronic connector, wherein the guide plate includes a linear slot. A mounting plate is positioned generally parallel to the guide plate, wherein the mounting plate comprises two or more mounting pins, and is vertically slidably secured to the guide plate by the pins extending through the linear slot. Between the guide plate and the mounting plate, a rotatable plate is pivotally coupled, wherein the rotatable plate includes one or more cam slots slidably receiving a mounting pin. An electronic circuit board is coupled to the mounting plate, the electronic circuit board having a second electronic connector selectively mateable with the first electronic connector. The rotatable plate is actuated so that the cam slots cause the mounting plate and circuit board to move vertically to insert and remove the second connector relative to the first connector.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="162.73mm" wi="175.77mm" file="US07297015-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="186.94mm" wi="177.38mm" file="US07297015-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="186.35mm" wi="174.67mm" file="US07297015-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="203.88mm" wi="149.69mm" file="US07297015-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="203.37mm" wi="147.57mm" file="US07297015-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="206.25mm" wi="137.33mm" file="US07297015-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to printed circuit board installation in electronic devices. More specifically, the invention provides an apparatus for accurately docking a printed circuit board in a constrained space.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Swappable components have become commonplace in computer systems. Computer systems often use swappable memory, hard drives, and various pieces of hardware commonly referred to as daughter cards. Many maintenance, repair, or upgrade operations involve the removal of a piece of hardware, or the insertion of a piece of hardware, or both while the computer is on and functioning.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In a server rack, or chassis, many computer components are stored in close proximity. Often, these racks have numerous electronic circuit boards. The electronic circuit boards may be aligned in banks, both above or below, or beside each other. The electronic circuit boards may provide memory for the system, or perform specific other operations within the computer system.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Conventionally, the changing of an electronic circuit board may be accomplished by removing a cover, removing the prior electronic circuit board by lift it out of a header, and docking a new electronic circuit board by inserting it straight into the header. However, computer components are often installed in configurations making it difficult to achieve the mechanical advantage to accurately and carefully dock an electronic circuit board. If the docking or undocking of an electronic circuit board is needed where space is a concern, it may necessitate the removal of one or more electronic circuit boards from the neighboring slots. This procedure might then require the entire system to be shut down.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It is fairly common for computer systems to be continually operational. Therefore, installation, removal, or replacement of components is preferably accomplished via hot-swapping without disturbing the operation of adjacent circuit boards. This necessarily means that users are manipulating components of an electrically energized system. It would be desirable to have a means of inserting or removing an electronic circuit board without risk of damage to either the user or the component.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Printed circuit boards, such as daughter cards, can become damaged during insertion into a connector or header due to an uneven application of force or misalignment of the daughter card with the connector slot. It is ideal if the card is carefully position above and parallel to the connector, then pressed slowly and firmly straight toward the connector until a successful connection has been made. Haste and inaccessibility are just two of many factors that can prevent the ideal connection from ever occurring.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Therefore, there is a need for a device that facilitates safe, effective and simple insertion and removal of electronic circuit boards, even in very tight spaces. It would be desirable if such a device were durable and reliable in providing good connections.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention provides an apparatus comprising a guide plate selectively securable in a position adjacent a first electronic connector, wherein the guide plate includes at least one linear slot. A mounting plate is positioned generally parallel to the guide plate, wherein the mounting plate comprises two or more mounting pins, and is vertically slidably secured to the guide plate through the at least one linear slot. Between the guide plate and the mounting plate, a rotatable plate is pivotally coupled, wherein the rotatable plate includes two or more cam slots to slidably receive the mounting pins. An electronic circuit board is fixedly coupled to the mounting plate, the electronic circuit board having a second electronic connector selectively mateable with the first electronic connector. When the rotatable plate is actuated, the cam slots on the rotatable plate cause the mounting plate and circuit board to move vertically over a distance sufficient to insert and remove the second electronic connector relative to the first electronic connector.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The foregoing and other objects, features and advantages of the invention will be apparent from the following more particular description of a preferred embodiment of the invention, as illustrated in accompanying drawings wherein like reference numbers represent like parts of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of an apparatus including a guide plate and a rotary linkage in accordance with one embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of the guide plate and the rotary linkage with the guide plate shown as translucent for illustrative purposes.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-3C</figref> are a series of cross-sectional views showing the operation of the apparatus to insert a second connector into a first connector.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of a guide plate <b>10</b> and a rotary linkage in accordance with one embodiment of the invention. The guide plate <b>10</b> is a rigid structural member that supports and positions other components. The guide plate <b>10</b> has a pivot coupling <b>20</b> that pivotally secures a rotatable plate <b>12</b> to the guide plate and a generally vertical slot <b>22</b> to accommodate the vertical movement of a pin <b>24</b> secured to a mounting plate <b>30</b>. The pin <b>24</b> preferably terminates in a head (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) that prevents the pin <b>24</b> from pulling through the slot.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The rotary linkage allows for accurate and repeatable vertical movement of the mounting plate <b>30</b> relative to the guide plate <b>10</b> for insertion and removal from a connector where user access is constrained. Accordingly, the rotary linkage includes the rotatable plate <b>12</b> with a positioning handle <b>14</b> extending from one side for user access. The rotatable plate <b>12</b> is pivotally coupled to the guide plate <b>10</b> at the pivot coupling <b>20</b> and the positioning handle <b>14</b> may be actuated to rotate the rotatable plate <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the guide plate <b>10</b> has been slidingly inserted (preferably in the direction of arrow <b>56</b>) in a lower guide or guides <b>48</b> secured to a first electronic circuit board <b>70</b> and an upper guide or guides <b>50</b> secured to a chassis member (not shown). Alternatively, both upper and lower guides may be secured to a chassis member, so long as a second electronic circuit board <b>60</b> can be connected to and communicate with a first connector (not shown) positioned immediately adjacent the guide plate. In either instance, the leading edge of the guide plate <b>10</b> should engage a stop <b>58</b> at the point where the guide plate is properly aligned for inserting the second electronic circuit board <b>60</b> directly into the first connector. The stop <b>58</b> may be secured to the chassis (not shown) or could be positioned at the lower edge of the guide plate and be formed as part of the first connector (not shown) itself in order to further avoid alignment errors.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of the apparatus with the guide plate <b>10</b> shown as translucent in order to better illustrate the operation of the rotary linkage. The rotatable plate <b>12</b> comprises a cam slot <b>16</b> that receives the pin <b>24</b> attached to the mounting plate <b>30</b>. The cam slot <b>16</b> has a first end <b>15</b> and a second end <b>17</b>, wherein the first end <b>15</b> is a first distance to the pivot coupling <b>20</b> to allow for the lowering of the pin <b>24</b> and mounting plate <b>30</b> and the second end <b>17</b> is a second longer distance to the pivot coupling <b>20</b> to allow for the raising of the pin <b>24</b> and the mounting plate <b>30</b>. The rotatable plate <b>12</b> is made of a rigid material, such as metal, to maintain its shape during use, especially when actuated in either direction and encountering frictional resistance of the coupling or decoupling connectors.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">When more than one cam slot <b>16</b> exists on the rotatable plate <b>12</b> on opposite sides of the pivot coupling <b>20</b>, the distance from the pivot coupling <b>20</b> to one cam slot is related to the distance from the pivot coupling <b>20</b> to the other cam slot. Preferably, along any line intersecting the pivot coupling <b>20</b> and passing between the two cam slots in the plane of the rotatable plate <b>12</b>, the distance between the two cam slots <b>16</b> is a constant and should be the same as the distance between the two pins <b>24</b> received within the cam slots. If this relationship is not maintained, then the rotary linkage is likely to bind up.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The rotatable plate <b>12</b> supports a mounting plate <b>30</b>. While the mounting plate <b>30</b> is receiving vertical support from the cam slot <b>16</b> via the pins <b>24</b> attached to the mounting plate <b>30</b>, the movement of the mounting plate <b>30</b> is also laterally constrained by the pair of pins <b>24</b> that extend from the mounting plate <b>30</b> through a pair of vertical slots <b>22</b> in the guide plate <b>10</b>. While one slot and pin might be sufficient, the use of two or more parallel, vertical slots <b>22</b> and pins <b>24</b> is highly preferable. The slots <b>22</b> in the guide plate should run in a direction that a second electronic circuit board <b>60</b> should be moved for installation into a first connector (not shown). The pins <b>24</b> preferably have a head <b>25</b> to prevent the pins from pulling out of the slots <b>22</b>, as the pins <b>22</b> provide the only coupling of the mounting plate <b>30</b> to the guide plate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The positioning handle <b>14</b>, has been actuated upward along an arcuate path about pivot coupling <b>20</b>, toward the top of the guide plate <b>10</b> (in the direction of arrow <b>61</b>) causing the mounting plate <b>30</b> to be displaced upward (along the slot <b>22</b>). The rotation of the cam slots <b>16</b> have caused an upward displacement of the pins <b>24</b> attached to the mounting plate <b>30</b>. The displacement is accomplished by the action of the cam slots <b>16</b> increasing the distance from the pivotal coupling <b>20</b> to the upper pin <b>24</b> and decreasing the distance from the pivotal coupling <b>20</b> to the lower pin <b>24</b>. In this embodiment, when the positioning handle <b>14</b> is raised, the distal end <b>17</b> of the upper cam slot <b>16</b> is vertically aligned with the pivotal coupling <b>20</b> and the proximal end <b>15</b> of the lower cam slot <b>16</b> is vertically aligned with the pivotal coupling <b>20</b>. It should be noted that it is not necessary to utilize the entirety of either cam slot <b>16</b> in order to accomplish the motion of the mounting plate <b>30</b>. It should also be noted that the cam slots <b>16</b> can easily be designed to create a displacement of the pins <b>24</b> opposite to the direction of displacement of the positioning handle <b>14</b>. For example, raising the handle could be made to lower the mounting plate <b>30</b> by reversing the orientation of the cam slots <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">It should be recognized that movement of the positioning handle <b>14</b> in the direction of arrow <b>61</b> will cause the mounting plate to move to an “up” position and movement of the positioning handle <b>14</b> in the direction of arrow <b>57</b> will cause the mounting plate to move to a “down” position. Furthermore, this up and down movement occurs without any lateral movement of the guide plate or the mounting plate. In this manner, a second electronic circuit board mounted to the mounting plate may be carefully and accurately vertically downwardly inserted into and vertically upwardly removed from a connector (not shown) on a first electronic circuit board <b>70</b> by actuation of the positioning handle <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">One or more sliders <b>26</b> are optionally secured between the mounting plate and the guide plate to serve as low friction spacers that stabilize the motion of the mounting plate in a plane generally parallel to the plane of the guide plate. Any number of sliders may be secured to the mounting plate, the guide plate, or both. The sliders <b>26</b> may comprise a protrusion on the mounting plate or guide plate to contact the guide plate or mounting plate, respectively. The slider may be a small tab of plastic, or any other material that can maintain the uniform standoff between the guide plate and the mounting plate, without restricting or interfering with the motion of the mounting plate.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Still further, the guide plate <b>10</b> may also include a handle <b>46</b> to facilitate handling of the entire assembly without touching the second electronic circuit board <b>60</b>. The handle <b>46</b> may optionally be made of or protected by a non-conducting material, such as rubber, to protect the user from accidental electrical shock. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-3C</figref> are a series of cross-sectional views along the line A-A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, the guide plate <b>10</b> is shown fully inserted into a chassis (not shown) as described in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A first electronic circuit board <b>70</b> with a first connector <b>72</b> resides beneath the apparatus comprising the guide plate <b>10</b>, the rotatable plate <b>12</b>, and the mounting plate <b>30</b>. In this embodiment, the positioning handle (not shown) is in the “up” position, to position the mounting plate <b>30</b> in the up position in a manner consistent with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The guide plate <b>10</b> has been inserted into an upper and lower guide <b>50</b>, <b>48</b> respectively. A stop (not shown) has positioned the guide plate <b>10</b> to align the first connector <b>72</b> with a second connector <b>62</b>, as discussed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Further, the rotatable plate <b>12</b> is coupled at the pivot coupling <b>20</b> to the guide plate <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The mounting plate <b>30</b> comprises two pins <b>24</b> that pass through the cam slots <b>16</b> in the rotatable plate <b>12</b>, and the slots <b>22</b> in the guide plate <b>10</b>. The pins <b>24</b> may terminate in a head <b>25</b>, which prevents them from being pulled out of slots <b>22</b> in the guide plate <b>10</b>. The mounting plate is being vertically supported by the cam slots <b>16</b>, while being horizontally constrained by slots <b>22</b> in the guide plate <b>10</b>. Optionally the mounting plate <b>30</b> may comprise one or more sliders <b>26</b>, to maintain a parallel orientation between the mounting plate <b>30</b> and the guide plate <b>10</b>, as well as maintain an offset for the mounting plate <b>30</b> which helps align the first and second connectors <b>72</b>, <b>62</b>. As discussed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the optional sliders <b>26</b> may be on the mounting plate <b>30</b>, or the guide plate <b>10</b>. In this embodiment, the sliders <b>26</b> are shown attached to the mounting plate <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">A second electronic circuit board <b>60</b> with the second connector <b>62</b> is secured to the mounting plate <b>30</b>. The second electronic circuit board <b>60</b> may be secured with screws, clips, or any manner which ensures that the second electronic circuit board <b>60</b> is firmly secured, and will move in conjunction with the mounting plate <b>30</b>. Typically, the second electronic circuit board <b>62</b> is a daughter card, or some component which may be frequently inserted or removed from an operating computer system.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> shows the mounting plate <b>30</b> being displaced downward in the direction of arrow <b>74</b> as the positioning handle (not shown) is being actuated (partially lowered). The second connector <b>62</b> is shown about to be received in the first connector <b>72</b>. Actuating the positioning handle rotates the rotatable plate <b>12</b> as discussed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The pins <b>24</b> on the mounting plate <b>30</b> have been horizontally constrained by the slots <b>22</b> in the guide plate <b>10</b>, and the cam slots <b>16</b> in the rotatable plate are providing a vertical force to displace the mounting plate <b>30</b>, and therefore the second electronic circuit board <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref> shows the mounting plate <b>30</b> and second electronic circuit board <b>60</b> in the “down” position consistent with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, such that the second connector <b>62</b> has been properly received in the first connector <b>72</b>. In this figure, the positioning handle (not shown) has been fully actuated (downward), resulting in the complete connection of the second connector <b>62</b> into the first connector <b>72</b>. Removal of the second connector <b>62</b> can be accomplished by reversing the process.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Accordingly, the present invention further comprises a method of safely docking or undocking a first electronic circuit board with a first connector with a second electronic circuit board with a second connector to receive the first connector. Initially the first electronic circuit board, comprising a first connector is secured to a mounting plate linked to a guide plate. The first electronic circuit board may be screwed on, clipped on, or secured in any manner that ensures it will move in unison with the mounting plate. The first electronic circuit board may be removably secured, or permanently secured.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The guide plate is inserted into a chassis comprising guides. The guides may receive the guide plate on a rail, in a groove, in a bay, or any other means which allows the chassis to receive the guide plate. The first connector is aligned with a second connector on a second electronic circuit board within the chassis. This may be accomplished by the guides restricting the motion of the guide plate when inserted, manually, with a sensor, or any other method which indicates that the first connector and second connector are aligned.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">A force generally perpendicular to the direction of insertion of the guide plate into the chassis is applied. This force may be applied by a user with a handle, a motor, or any means which causes a force to be applied. The force is translated in a direction generally parallel to the direction of application. This translation may be accomplished by rotating an arcuately slotted plate to displace pins attached to the mounting plate, and slots on the guide plate to constrain the motion of the guide plate or mounting plate.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The translated force is applied to the mounting plate. The mounting plate is displaced in a direction generally perpendicular to the direction of insertion of the guide plate into the chassis. The first electronic circuit board secured to the mounting plate moves in unison with the mounting plate. The first connector is then received into the second connector or, alternatively, removed from the second connector.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The terms “comprising,” “including,” and “having,” as used in the claims and specification herein, shall be considered as indicating an open group that may include other elements not specified. The terms “a,” “an,” and the singular forms of words shall be taken to include the plural form of the same words, such that the terms mean that one or more of something is provided. The term “one” or “single” may be used to indicate that one and only one of something is intended. Similarly, other specific integer values, such as “two,” may be used when a specific number of things is intended. The terms “preferably,” “preferred,” “prefer,” “optionally,” “may,” and similar terms are used to indicate that an item, condition or step being referred to is an optional (not required) feature of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">While the invention has been described with respect to a limited number of embodiments, those skilled in the art, having benefit of this disclosure, will appreciate that other embodiments can be devised which do not depart from the scope of the invention as disclosed herein. Accordingly, the scope of the invention should be limited only by the attached claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An apparatus comprising:
<claim-text>a guide plate selectively securable in a position adjacent a first electronic connector, the guide plate including at least one linear slot;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a mounting plate positioned generally parallel to the guide plate, wherein the mounting plate has two or more spaced apart mounting pins slidably secured through the at least one linear slot of the guide plate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rotatable plate pivotally coupled to the guide plate, wherein the rotatable plate includes two or more opposing cam slots slidably receiving the mounting pins; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an electronic circuit board fixedly coupled to the mounting plate, the electronic circuit board having a second electronic connector selectively mateable with the first electronic connector, wherein rotation of the rotatable plate causes the mounting plate and circuit board to move vertically over a distance sufficient to insert and remove the second electronic connector relative to the first electronic connector;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the guide plate is slidably insertable in upper and lower guide channels secured in a position to transversely align the first and second connectors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the rotatable plate includes a handle extending to an edge of the guide plate for user access.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the guide plate includes a carrying handle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the cam slots have an upper edge arranged to bias the mounting pins downward during rotation of the rotatable plate in a first rotational direction and a lower edge arranged to bias the mounting pins upward during rotation of the rotatable plate in a second rotational direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>one or more stabilizing sliders disposed between the mounting plate and guide plate.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the one or more pins include a head to prevent accidental removal from the slots.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a stop member to limit the insertion of the guide plate and axially align the first and second connectors.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the rotatable plate vertically positions the first connector relative to the second connector after the first and second connectors are already axially and transversely aligned.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the rotatable plate is pivotally coupled to the guide plate by a rivet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one linear slot is a vertical slot.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the upper and lower guide channels are generally horizontal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one linear slot is a generally perpendicular to the guide channels.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The apparatus of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the mounting plate has offset mounting brackets for securing the electronic circuit board in a generally parallel spaced apart relationship.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
