<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298466-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298466</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11081926</doc-number>
<date>20050315</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>170</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>26</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356138</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">System and method for assembling optical components</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4850668</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hakimi</name>
<date>19890700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385134</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5666450</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fujimura et al.</name>
<date>19970900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385 93</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5859947</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kiryuscheva et al.</name>
<date>19990100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>385136</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0033941</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Seward</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>356153</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356138</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>356153</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060209297</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060921</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Biet</last-name>
<first-name>Michel</first-name>
<address>
<city>Antony</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ughetto</last-name>
<first-name>Gilles</first-name>
<address>
<city>Rambouillet</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lievre</last-name>
<first-name>Laurent</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lardy</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Felsemberg</last-name>
<first-name>Jerome</first-name>
<address>
<city>Boissy sous Saint Yon</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Patterson &amp; Sheridan, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Avanex Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Fremont</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chowdhury</last-name>
<first-name>Tarifur</first-name>
<department>2886</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Akanbi</last-name>
<first-name>Isiaka O</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The proposed solution to the problems associated with assembling optical components introduces an angular alignment step and the use of collimated optical beams to the assembly process. One embodiment of a method for aligning optical components includes the steps of angularly aligning a fiber subassembly and a laser subassembly to achieve a desired angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly, transversely aligning the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly to achieve a desired linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly, while maintaining the desired angular position, and installing an intermediate part configured to accommodate the desired angular position and the desired linear position. The method also includes the step of permanently assembling the fiber subassembly, the laser subassembly and the intermediate part, while maintaining the desired angular position and the desired linear position.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="83.31mm" wi="191.09mm" file="US07298466-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="192.62mm" wi="94.57mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298466-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="231.39mm" wi="151.13mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298466-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="207.60mm" wi="141.05mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298466-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="189.06mm" wi="113.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298466-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="183.05mm" wi="112.78mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298466-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="167.13mm" wi="109.39mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298466-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="173.40mm" wi="109.81mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298466-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="221.66mm" wi="129.20mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298466-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="109.81mm" wi="109.39mm" file="US07298466-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates generally to fiber optic systems and more particularly to a system and method for assembling optical components.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Background Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">An optical transmission system includes a number of optic components, such as a laser subassembly that contains the optical source (i.e., the laser) and a fiber subassembly that includes a portion of the fiber optic cable, that are coupled together to transmit the optical signal. Certain applications, such as pump modules, require high coupling efficiency between the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly. To optimize coupling efficiency between these components, five degrees of freedom ideally should be controlled during the assembly process. These five degrees of freedom include of the relative linear positions of the fiber and laser subassemblies in the x, y and z directions (where the z-axis is defined to be the optical axis) and the relative angular positions of the fiber and laser subassemblies in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Current assembly techniques do not control all five degrees of freedom. For example, direct coupling typically controls only three degrees of freedom, namely, the relative linear position of the fiber and laser subassemblies in the x, y and z directions. Such an approach results in a certain amount of angular misalignment between the fiber and laser subassemblies, leading to sub-optimal coupling efficiency. To increase coupling efficiency with current techniques, the transverse (i.e., linear) tolerances of the optic components must be very tight to reduce the amount of angular misalignment. Requiring tight tolerances substantially increases the complexity and cost of the assembly process.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Another drawback of current assembly techniques is that the distance between the fiber and laser subassemblies is purposefully kept short to reduce the amount of angular misalignment between the subassemblies. The short distance limits the usefulness of the resulting assembly because there is no free-space propagation path. Further, the short distance precludes inserting isolators, filters and the like between the fiber and laser subassemblies, further limiting the usefulness of the resulting assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Attempts have been made to use coupling lenses to solve the problems described above. However, using coupling lenses also results in complex and costly assembly.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The proposed solution to the problems associated with assembling optical components introduces an angular alignment step and the use of collimated optical beams to the assembly process. One embodiment of a method for aligning optical components includes the steps of angularly aligning a fiber subassembly and a laser subassembly to achieve a desired angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly, transversely aligning the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly to achieve a desired linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly, while maintaining the desired angular position, and installing an intermediate part configured to accommodate the desired angular position and the desired linear position. The method also includes the step of permanently assembling the fiber subassembly, the laser subassembly and the intermediate part, while maintaining the desired angular position and the desired linear position.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">One advantage of the disclosed system and method is that relative angular position between the laser subassembly and the fiber subassembly may be controlled in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions. This control along with using a collimated beam (produced by the laser subassembly) enables high coupling efficiency between the laser subassembly and the fiber subassembly without requiring tight transverse tolerances in the individual optical components or the use of bulk lenses for coupling. Allowing relaxed transverse tolerances reduces the complexity and cost of assembly. In addition, using a collimated beam enables the distance between the laser subassembly and the fiber subassembly to be increased, without impairing coupling efficiency, thereby creating space for a free-space propagation path and/or for inserting isolators, filters and the like.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a set of fiber optic components that may be assembled in accordance with the principles of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> illustrates a system for angularly aligning the laser subassembly and the fiber subassembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, according to one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> illustrates a system for angularly aligning the laser subassembly and the fiber subassembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, according to another embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> illustrate a system for transversely aligning the laser subassembly and the fiber subassembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, according to one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a system for coupling the laser subassembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> to the fiber subassembly of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> using an intermediate part, according to one embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates another set of fiber optic components that may be assembled in accordance with the principles of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref> illustrate how the brackets of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> accommodate the angular and linear positions of the fiber subassembly relative to laser subassembly resulting from the angular and transverse alignment steps.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flow diagram of method steps for assembling a set of fiber optic components, according to one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a set of fiber optic components <b>100</b> that may be assembled in accordance with the principles of the present invention. As shown, set of fiber optic components <b>100</b> includes, without limitation, a laser subassembly <b>110</b>, an intermediate piece <b>130</b> and a fiber subassembly <b>150</b>. Laser subassembly <b>110</b> includes, without limitation, an L-shaped base <b>112</b>, upon which an optical source <b>114</b> is mounted, and a collimating lens <b>120</b>. Optical source <b>114</b> includes a laser <b>115</b>, which is configured to emit a source beam that passes through collimating lens <b>120</b>. As described in further detail herein, collimating lens <b>120</b> enlarges the diameter of the source beam to produce a collimated beam that enlarges transverse tolerances while ensuring good optical coupling between laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b>. L-shaped base <b>112</b> contains an aperture <b>125</b> that allows the collimated beam to pass through L-shaped base <b>112</b> unimpeded.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Intermediate part <b>130</b> is a cylindrically-shaped piece having a substantially flat surface <b>132</b> at an end nearest laser subassembly <b>110</b> and a spherically-shaped concave surface <b>135</b> at an end nearest fiber subassembly <b>150</b>. As described in further detail herein, intermediate part <b>130</b> is configured to accommodate the angular position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to that of laser subassembly <b>110</b>. Intermediate part <b>130</b> also contains an aperture <b>140</b> that allows the collimated beam produced by laser subassembly <b>110</b> to pass through intermediate part <b>130</b> to fiber subassembly <b>150</b> unimpeded.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Fiber subassembly <b>150</b> includes an outer element <b>152</b> with a defined passageway <b>160</b>, a focusing lens <b>165</b>, a ferrule <b>170</b> and a fiber <b>175</b>. Focusing lens <b>165</b> is coupled to outer element <b>152</b> at an end of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> nearest intermediate part <b>130</b>, and ferrule <b>170</b> is partially disposed within passageway <b>160</b> at an opposite end of fiber subassembly <b>150</b>. Ferrule <b>170</b> supports fiber <b>175</b>, fixing the position of fiber <b>175</b> within fiber subassembly <b>150</b>. Focusing lens <b>165</b> is configured to focus the collimated beam produced by laser subassembly <b>110</b> onto a tip <b>180</b> of fiber <b>175</b>. Focusing lens <b>165</b> is further configured to fit within aperture <b>140</b> when fiber subassembly <b>150</b> is coupled to intermediate part <b>130</b>. In alternative embodiments, focusing lens <b>165</b> may be disposed farther within passageway <b>160</b> to reduce the risk of focusing lens <b>165</b> contacting concave surface <b>135</b> when fiber subassembly <b>150</b> is coupled to intermediate part <b>130</b>. In addition to the foregoing, outer element <b>152</b> has a spherically-shaped convex surface <b>155</b> at an end nearest intermediate part <b>130</b>. Importantly, convex surface <b>155</b> is configured to mate with concave surface <b>135</b> of intermediate part <b>130</b> to form a ball joint. As described in further detail herein, this ball joint configuration enables intermediate part <b>130</b> to accommodate the angular position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to that of laser subassembly <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A through 4</figref> describe steps for assembling laser subassembly <b>110</b>, intermediate part <b>130</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> in accordance with the principles of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> illustrates a system <b>200</b> for angularly aligning the laser subassembly <b>110</b> and the fiber subassembly <b>150</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, according to one embodiment of the present invention. Laser subassembly <b>110</b> is attached to a fixture <b>255</b> to fix the position of laser subassembly <b>110</b> during the assembly process. Laser source <b>114</b>, which is controlled by a laser controller <b>245</b>, directs a laser beam towards collimating lens <b>120</b> to produce a collimated beam <b>250</b>. Collimated beam <b>250</b> passes through aperture <b>125</b> to a camera <b>260</b>. Camera <b>260</b> detects collimated beam <b>250</b> and outputs a signal <b>265</b> to a channel <b>274</b> of beam analyzer <b>270</b> that corresponds to collimated beam <b>250</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Fiber subassembly <b>150</b> is coupled to a positioner <b>210</b> that is configured to adjust the angular and transverse positions of fiber subassembly <b>150</b>. A laser source <b>230</b>, which is optically coupled to an output end <b>235</b> of fiber <b>175</b>, directs a laser beam into output end <b>235</b>. Upon emerging from fiber <b>175</b>, the laser beam is collimated by focusing lens <b>165</b> to produce a collimated beam <b>240</b> that is directed to a camera <b>220</b>. Camera <b>220</b> detects collimated beam <b>240</b> and outputs a signal <b>225</b> to a channel <b>272</b> of beam analyzer <b>270</b> that corresponds to collimated beam <b>240</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Beam analyzer <b>270</b> is configured to measure the angular displacements of collimated beam <b>240</b> relative to collimated beam <b>250</b> in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions based on signals <b>225</b> and <b>265</b> received from cameras <b>220</b> and <b>260</b>, respectively. Positioner <b>210</b> is configured to adjust the angular position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions until collimated beam <b>240</b> and collimated <b>250</b> are substantially parallel to one another (i.e., until the angular displacements of collimated beam <b>240</b> relative to collimated beam <b>250</b> in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions are substantially zero).</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Beam analyzer <b>270</b> may be any type of well-known beam analyzing device, such as the Photon, Inc. PS <b>2315</b> optical analyzer, or other device configured with similar functionality. Likewise, positioner <b>210</b> may be any type of well-known positioning device, such as the Thorlabs, Inc. APT 600 family of 6-axis positioners, or other device configured with similar functionality.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In an alternate embodiment of the invention, the position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> may be fixed and angular alignment may be accomplished by adjusting the angular orientation of laser subassembly <b>110</b> relative to fiber subassembly <b>150</b> using positioner <b>210</b>. In yet another embodiment of the invention, each of laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> may be coupled to a positioner and angular alignment may achieved by adjusting the angular orientations of both subassemblies.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> illustrates a system <b>205</b> for angularly aligning the laser subassembly <b>110</b> and the fiber subassembly <b>150</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, according to an alternative embodiment of the present invention. As shown, a beam splitter <b>290</b> may be used to toggle the input to a camera <b>280</b> such that camera <b>280</b> receives either collimated beam <b>250</b> from laser subassembly <b>110</b> or collimated beam <b>240</b> from fiber subassembly <b>150</b>. Camera <b>280</b> detects collimated beam <b>250</b> and outputs a signal to beam analyzer <b>270</b> that corresponds to collimated beam <b>250</b> or detects collimated beam <b>240</b> and outputs signal <b>285</b> to beam analyzer <b>270</b> that corresponds to collimated beam <b>240</b>. Beam analyzer <b>270</b> is configured to measure the angular displacements of collimated beam <b>240</b> relative to collimated beam <b>250</b> in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions based on signals <b>285</b> received from camera <b>280</b>. Positioner <b>210</b>, which is coupled to fiber subassembly <b>150</b>, is configured to adjust the angular position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions until collimated beam <b>240</b> and collimated <b>250</b> are substantially parallel to one another (i.e., until the angular displacements of collimated beam <b>240</b> relative to collimated beam <b>250</b> in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions are substantially zero). As before, in alternative embodiments, a positioner may be used to adjust the angular orientation of laser subassembly <b>110</b>, as opposed to that of fiber subassembly <b>150</b>, or the angular orientations of both laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> may be adjusted with respective positioners.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> illustrate a system <b>300</b> for transversely aligning laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, according to one embodiment of the present invention. An “active alignment” technique is used for this step. As shown, laser source <b>114</b> of laser subsystem <b>110</b> emits a laser beam that is collimated by collimating lens <b>120</b> to increase the diameter of the laser beam. Increasing the diameter facilitates transverse alignment of laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> because a laser beam with a larger diameter can more easily intercept focusing lens <b>165</b> of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> than a laser beam with a smaller diameter. Resulting collimated beam <b>310</b> is incident on focusing lens <b>165</b>, which focuses collimated beam <b>310</b> on tip <b>180</b> of fiber <b>175</b>. A detector <b>320</b> is coupled to fiber <b>175</b> and is configured to measure optical signal power transmitted through fiber <b>175</b>. Positioner <b>210</b>, which is coupled to fiber subassembly <b>150</b>, is configured to adjust the position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> in the x and y directions to maximize the power measured by detector <b>320</b>. Importantly, when adjusting the position in the x and y directions, positioner <b>210</b> maintains the angular position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> resulting from the angular alignment step described above.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> is a side view showing the position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> being adjusted in the y-direction, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> is a top view showing the position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> being adjusted in the x-direction. In both <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref>, laser subassembly <b>110</b> is attached to fixture <b>255</b> and the position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> in the x and y directions is adjusted. In an alternative embodiment of the invention, the position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> may be fixed and transverse alignment may be accomplished by adjusting the position of laser subassembly <b>110</b> relative to fiber subassembly <b>150</b> in the x and y directions using positioner <b>210</b>. In yet another embodiment of the invention, each of laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> may be coupled to a positioner and transverse alignment may be achieved by adjusting the positions of both subassemblies in the x and y directions. Persons skilled in the art will recognize that these alternative embodiments also apply to the step described below in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> illustrate a system <b>300</b> for transversely aligning laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, according to one embodiment of the present invention. An “active alignment” technique is used for this step. As shown, laser source <b>114</b> of laser subsystem <b>110</b> emits a laser beam that is collimated by collimating lens <b>120</b> to increase the diameter of the laser beam. Increasing the diameter facilitates transverse alignment of laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> because a laser beam with a larger diameter can more easily intercept focusing lens <b>165</b> of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> than a laser beam with a smaller diameter. Resulting collimated beam <b>310</b> is incident on focusing lens <b>165</b>, which focuses collimated beam <b>310</b> on tip <b>180</b> of fiber <b>175</b>. A detector <b>320</b> is coupled to fiber <b>175</b> and is configured to measure optical signal power transmitted through fiber <b>175</b>. Positioner <b>210</b>, which is coupled to fiber subassembly <b>150</b>, is configured to adjust the position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> in the x and y directions to maximize the power measured by detector <b>320</b>. Importantly, when adjusting the position in the x and y directions, positioner <b>210</b> maintains the angular position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> resulting from the angular alignment step described above.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Positioner <b>210</b> continues adjusting the position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> in the z-direction until intermediate part <b>130</b> is in contact with both laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b>. When contact is made with laser subassembly <b>110</b>, surface <b>132</b> of intermediate part <b>130</b> mates with a surface <b>470</b> of laser subassembly <b>110</b> such that aperture <b>140</b> of intermediate part <b>130</b> aligns with aperture <b>125</b> of laser subassembly <b>110</b>. When contact is made with fiber subassembly <b>150</b>, concave surface <b>135</b> of intermediate part <b>130</b> mates with convex surface <b>155</b> of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> to form a ball socket. Importantly, intermediate part <b>130</b> is designed to accommodate the angular and linear positions of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> resulting from the angular and transverse alignment steps described above. More specifically, concave surface <b>135</b> and convex surface <b>155</b> are configured such that the resulting ball joint is able to accommodate the angular position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> resulting from the angular alignment step, and surfaces <b>132</b> and <b>470</b> are configured to accommodate the linear position of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> in the x and y directions resulting from the transverse alignment step.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In addition to the foregoing, intermediate part <b>130</b> is configured such that no external tooling is required to maintain the relative positions of laser subassembly <b>110</b>, intermediate part <b>130</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> once contact is made between intermediate part <b>130</b> and each of laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b>, as described above. YAG welding or some other technically feasible fastening technique is then used to permanently fix intermediate part <b>130</b> to each of laser subassembly <b>110</b> and intermediate part <b>130</b>, while maintaining the angular and linear positions of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> resulting from the angular and transverse alignment steps described above.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">One advantage of the disclosed system and method is that relative angular position between laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> may be controlled in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions. This control along with using a collimated beam (produced by laser subassembly <b>110</b>) enables high coupling efficiency between laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> without requiring tight transverse tolerances in the individual optical components or the use of bulk lenses for coupling. Allowing relaxed transverse tolerances reduces the complexity and cost of assembly. In addition, more controlled and precise alignment enables the distance between laser subassembly <b>110</b> and fiber subassembly <b>150</b> to be increased, without impairing coupling efficiency, thereby creating space for a free-space propagation path and/or for inserting isolators, filters and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The disclosed system and method may be used to assembly any set of optics components similar to set <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> so long as the set includes intermediate parts or some other means that are configured to accommodate the angular and linear positions of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> resulting from the angular and transverse alignment steps described above. For example, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates another set of fiber optic components <b>500</b> that may be assembled in accordance with the principles of the present invention. As described in further detail herein, the assembly process for set of fiber optic components <b>500</b> is similar to that described above in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Laser subassembly <b>510</b>, which is coupled to a base plate <b>505</b> is similar to laser subassembly <b>110</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Laser subassembly <b>510</b> includes a collimating lens <b>520</b> for producing a collimated beam, as previously described herein. Fiber subassembly <b>550</b> is similar to fiber subassembly <b>150</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and includes a focusing lens (not shown) that may be used to produce a collimated beam during the angular alignment step, as previously described herein.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The disclosed system and method may be used to assemble any set of optics components similar to set <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> so long as the set includes intermediate parts or some other means that are configured to accommodate the angular and linear positions of fiber subassembly <b>150</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>110</b> resulting from the angular and transverse alignment steps described above. For example, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> illustrates another set of fiber optic components <b>500</b> that may be assembled in accordance with the principles of the present invention. As described in further detail herein, the assembly process for set of fiber optic components <b>500</b> is similar to that described above in conjunction with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A and 6B</figref> illustrate how brackets <b>530</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> accommodate the angular and linear positions of fiber subassembly <b>550</b> relative to laser subassembly <b>530</b> resulting from the angular and transverse alignment steps described above. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> shows that fiber subassembly <b>550</b> may be rotated about the x-axis relative to brackets <b>530</b> to achieve the desired relative angular position of fiber subassembly <b>550</b> in the Θ<sub>x </sub>direction. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref> also shows that fiber subassembly <b>550</b> may be moved along the y-axis relative to brackets <b>530</b> to achieve the desired relative linear position of fiber subassembly <b>550</b> in the y-direction. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> shows that fiber subassembly <b>550</b> and brackets <b>530</b> may be rotated together about the y-axis on the top surface of base plate <b>505</b> to achieve the desired relative angular position of fiber subassembly <b>550</b> in the Θ<sub>y </sub>direction. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref> also shows that fiber subassembly <b>550</b> and brackets <b>530</b> may be moved together along the x-axis on the top surface of base plate <b>505</b> to achieve the desired relative linear position of fiber subassembly <b>550</b> in the x-direction.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flow diagram of method steps for assembling a set of fiber optic components, according to one embodiment of the present invention. Although the method steps are described in the context of the systems illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-6</figref>, any system configured to perform the method steps in any order is within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, the method of assembling starts in step <b>710</b> with the angular alignment of the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly. In one embodiment, a positioner adjusts the angular position of the fiber subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions while a beam analyzer measures the angular displacements of a collimated beam produced by the fiber subassembly relative to a collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions. The positioner adjusts the angular position of the fiber subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions the two collimated beams are substantially parallel to one another (i.e., until the angular displacements of the collimated beam produced by the fiber subassembly relative to the collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions are substantially zero).</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Next, in step <b>720</b>, the fiber subassembly and the fiber subassembly are transversely aligned. In one embodiment, a collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly is incident on a focusing lens included in the fiber subassembly. The focusing lens focuses the collimated beam on the tip of the fiber included in the fiber subassembly such that a detector that is coupled to the other end of the fiber is able to measure optical signal power transmitted through the fiber. The positioner adjusts the position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the x and y directions to maximize the power measured by the detector. Importantly, when adjusting the position in the x and y directions, the positioner maintains the angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly resulting from the angular alignment step.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In step <b>730</b>, an intermediate part is installed between the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly. The intermediate part is designed to accommodate the angular and linear positions of the fiber subassembly relative to laser subassembly resulting from the angular and transverse alignment steps. The positioner may be used to adjust the linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the z-direction before installing the intermediate part (e.g., when using brackets <b>530</b>) or after installing the intermediate part (e.g., when using intermediate part <b>130</b>). Also, to the extent necessary (as when using brackets <b>530</b>), springs or other means may be used to hold the intermediate part in place once the desired relative linear position of the fiber subassembly in the z-direction is achieved.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In step <b>740</b>, the optical components are permanently assembly using YAG welding or any other technically feasible fastening technique. Importantly, the angular and linear positions of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly resulting from the angular and transverse alignment steps are maintained during the permanent assembly step.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Although the invention has been described above with reference to specific embodiments, persons skilled in the art will understand that various modifications and changes may be made thereto without departing from the broader spirit and scope of the invention as set forth in the appended claims. The foregoing description and drawings are, accordingly, to be regarded in an illustrative rather than a restrictive sense.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for assembling optical components, the method comprising:
<claim-text>angularly aligning a fiber subassembly and a laser subassembly to achieve a desired angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transversely aligning the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly to achieve a desired linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly, while substantially maintaining the desired angular position;</claim-text>
<claim-text>installing an intermediate part between the laser subassembly and the fiber subassembly such that a shaped surface on the intermediate part mates with a corresponding shaped surface on the fiber subassembly, whereby the intermediate part is configured to accommodate the desired angular position and the desired linear position and the intermediate part includes an aperture that allows a collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly to pass therethrough; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>permanently assembling the fiber subassembly, the laser subassembly and the intermediate part, while substantially maintaining the desired angular position and the desired linear position.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of angularly aligning includes adjusting an angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of angularly aligning includes measuring angular displacements of a collimated beam produced by the fiber subassembly relative to a collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the step of angularly aligning includes adjusting an angular position of the fiber subassembly to the laser subassembly until the angular displacements of the collimated beam produced by the fiber subassembly relative to the collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions are substantially zero.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of transversely aligning includes adjusting a linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the x and y directions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of transversely aligning includes measuring optical signal power received by the fiber subassembly from a collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the step of transversely aligning includes adjusting a linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the x and y directions to maximize the optical signal power received by the fiber subassembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising the step of adjusting a linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the z-direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the intermediate part comprises brackets.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the step of installing an intermediate part includes using a means to hold the brackets in place.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the step of permanently assembling includes YAG welding.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A system for assembling optical components; the system comprising:
<claim-text>means for measuring angular displacements of a collimated beam produced by a fiber subassembly relative to a first collimated beam produced by a laser subassembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for angularly aligning the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly to achieve a desired angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for measuring optical signal power received by the fiber subassembly from a second collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly;</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for transversely aligning the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly to achieve a desired linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly, while substantially maintaining the desired angular position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means for accommodating the desired linear position and the desired angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly, wherein the means for accommodating the desired positions comprises an intermediate part disposable between the fiber subassembly and the laser subassembly, the intermediate part having a shaped surface capable of mating with a corresponding shaped surface on the fiber subassembly and the intermediate part having an aperture that allows a collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly to pass therethrough.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein means for measuring angular displacements comprises a beam analyzer.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein means for angularly aligning and means for transversely aligning comprise a positioner.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein means for measuring optical signal power comprises a detector coupled to the fiber subassembly.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein means for measuring angular displacements comprises a beam analyzer configured to measure angular displacements of the collimated beam produced by the fiber subassembly relative to the collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions, and means for angularly aligning comprises a positioner configured to adjust an angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the positioner is configured to adjust the angular position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions until the angular displacements of the collimated beam produced by the fiber subassembly relative to the collimated beam produced by the laser subassembly in the Θ<sub>x </sub>and Θ<sub>y </sub>directions are substantially zero.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein means for measuring optical signal power comprises a detector coupled to the fiber subassembly, and means for transversely aligning comprises a positioner configured to adjust a linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the x and y directions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, wherein the positioner is configured to adjust the linear position of the fiber subassembly relative to the laser subassembly in the x and y directions until the optical signal power received by the fiber subassembly is maximized.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the laser subassembly includes a collimating lens configured to produce the first collimated beam and the second collimated beam.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the shaped surface is a concave surface and the corresponding shaped surface is a convex surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
