<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296321-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296321</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10981774</doc-number>
<date>20041105</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>425</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>47</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>38</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 15304</main-classification>
<further-classification> 15314</further-classification>
<further-classification> 153161</further-classification>
<further-classification>108 5013</further-classification>
<further-classification>108 5018</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>1211325</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lilly</name>
<date>19170100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 34569</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2973790</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Huetter</name>
<date>19610300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>100 90</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3442230</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Polen</name>
<date>19690500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>108 24</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6101666</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cheng</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 15301</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6792878</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Cheng</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>108 5013</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6802266</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Cheng</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>108 5013</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7040239</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Shelton et al.</name>
<date>20060500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>108 5013</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0098006</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Jorgensen</name>
<date>20050500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 83100</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060096054</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060511</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cheng</last-name>
<first-name>Chieh-Yuan</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taichung</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chow</last-name>
<first-name>Ming</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sinorica, LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>San Ford Machinery Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taichung</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Redding</last-name>
<first-name>David</first-name>
<department>1744</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine includes a support frame, a machine base, a guide shade, a work faceplate and a dust-collecting unit. The machine base has its opposite upper side bored with plural transverse assistant guide grooves and its central portion bored with a longitudinal lower main guide groove communicating with a connecting opening in the front center. The guide shade covered on the lower main guide groove is formed with an upper guide groove. The work faceplate fixed on the topside of the machine base is bored with numerous wind-sucking vents. When the dust-collecting unit is started to operate, every wind-sucking vent of the work faceplate and the wind-sucking space in the machine base will receive a balanced suction force to let the wood waste produced completely sucked out.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="229.36mm" wi="123.27mm" file="US07296321-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="231.99mm" wi="174.67mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296321-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="189.06mm" wi="149.27mm" file="US07296321-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="230.63mm" wi="125.31mm" file="US07296321-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="228.01mm" wi="157.14mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296321-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="194.14mm" wi="148.17mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296321-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to a table-top wood-waste-collecting machine, particularly to one enabling, every wind-sucking vent of a work faceplate and every location of a wind-sucking space under the work faceplate to receive a suction force in a balanced condition to let wood waste dropping in the dust-sucking space completely and smoothly guided and sucked to a dust-collecting unit.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A conventional tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine <b>10</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, includes a support frame <b>11</b>, a machine base <b>12</b>, a work faceplate <b>13</b> and a dust-collecting unit <b>14</b> combined together. The machine base <b>12</b> positioned on the support frame <b>11</b> is provided with a base plate <b>121</b> having its peripheral side extending upward and forming a peripheral edge <b>122</b> and its central portion bored with a connecting opening <b>123</b> communicating with the dust-collecting unit <b>14</b>. The work faceplate <b>13</b> covered on the machine base <b>12</b> is provided with a top plate <b>131</b> for placing work pieces thereon, having an accommodating space <b>132</b> is formed between the top plate <b>131</b> of the work faceplate <b>13</b> and the machine base <b>12</b>. Further, the top plate <b>131</b> is bored with a plurality of wind-sucking vents <b>133</b>. Thus, when the dust-collecting unit <b>14</b> is started to operate, there will produce a vacuum suction force in the accommodating space <b>132</b> formed between the machine base <b>12</b> and the work faceplate <b>13</b> so that wood waste produced during wood processing can be sucked into the accommodating space <b>132</b> through the wind-sucking vents <b>133</b> of the work faceplate <b>13</b>. Simultaneously, the wood waste is sucked to the dust-collecting unit <b>14</b> to be collected and removed through the connecting opening <b>123</b> under the center of the accommodating space <b>132</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, the base plate <b>121</b> of the machine base <b>12</b> is a flat plate, and the connecting opening <b>123</b> of machine base <b>12</b> is located in the center; therefore, when the dust-collecting unit <b>14</b> is started to operate, a comparatively huge vacuum suction force will be produced around the base plate <b>121</b> of the machine base <b>12</b> and the wind-sucking vents <b>133</b> of the work faceplate <b>13</b>, which are near the connecting opening <b>123</b>, but the vacuum suction force produced at the locations that are far away from the connecting opening <b>123</b> will be comparatively small. Such unbalanced suction force may make some wood waste remain at or stick to the place where suction force is small, unable to exhaust out the wood waste completely, and it is necessary to have the tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine <b>10</b> disassembled for cleaning regularly.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The objective of the invention is to offer a tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine composed of a support frame, a machine base, a guide shade, a work faceplate and a dust-collecting unit. The machine base has its opposite upper sides respectively bored with a plurality of transverse assistant guide grooves and its central portion bored with a longitudinal lower main guide groove positioned between the left and the right transverse assistant guide grooves and communicating with a connecting opening at the front side. The guide shade with an upper guide groove is fixedly covered on a preset location of the lower main guide groove. The work faceplate is fixed on the topside of the machine base.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In this invention, every wind-sucking vent of the work faceplate and the wind-sucking space formed in the interior of the machine base are able to receive a balanced suction force, and the base surfaces of the upper guide groove of the guide shade and the transverse assistant guide grooves of the machine base are slope-shaped; therefore, the wood waste dropping in the upper guide groove and the transverse assistant guide grooves can be respectively guided into the lower main guide groove and then sucked to the dust-collecting unit, having excellent effect of dust removing.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">This invention will be better understood by referring to the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross-sectional view of a conventional tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a partial perspective view of a tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine in the present invention:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a partial exploded perspective view of the tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine in the present invention:</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine in the present invention: and</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a partial perspective view of the machine base of the tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine in the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A preferred embodiment of a table-top wood-waste-collecting machine in the present invention, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref>, <b>3</b> and <b>4</b>, includes a support frame <b>20</b>, a machine base <b>30</b>, a guide shade <b>40</b>, a work faceplate <b>50</b> and a dust-collecting unit <b>60</b> combined together.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The support frame <b>20</b> is collapsible and able to stand on the ground.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The machine base <b>30</b> to be fixed on the support frame <b>20</b> has a longitudinal connecting opening <b>31</b> bored in a front portion and having its outer side secured with a pipe adapter <b>32</b>. Further, the machine base <b>30</b> has a longitudinal lower main guide groove <b>33</b> bored in the topside near an intermediate portion and slanting downward toward the front end to communicate with the connecting opening <b>31</b>. The lower main guide groove <b>33</b> has its opposite upper sides respectively bored with a plurality of transverse assistant guide grooves <b>34</b> connected with the opposite edges of the lower main guide groove <b>33</b> and respectively having the base surface slanting downward toward the central portion of the machine base <b>30</b>. Furthermore, the machine base <b>30</b> has its upper peripheral side formed with a horizontal combining edge <b>35</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The guide shade <b>40</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 5</figref>, consists of a base plate <b>41</b> and two side plates <b>42</b> positioned at the opposite sides of the base plate <b>41</b>, having an upper guide groove <b>43</b> defined by the base plate <b>41</b> and the two side plates <b>42</b> and slanting downward toward the front end. Each side plate <b>42</b> has its front and rear end respectively provided with a combining member <b>421</b> to be combined on the corresponding inner wall of the machine base <b>30</b> so as to firmly cover the guide shade <b>40</b> on a proper portion of the lower main guide groove <b>33</b> of the machine base <b>30</b>, letting the front deep end of the upper guide groove <b>43</b> aligned to the connecting opening <b>31</b> of the machine base <b>30</b> and having an exhausting opening (a) with a preset size formed between the side plate <b>42</b> and the connecting place of each assistant guide groove <b>34</b> and the lower main guide groove <b>33</b>. Thus, wood waste dropping in each assistant guide groove <b>34</b> can respectively move into the lower main guide groove <b>33</b> along the slanting base surface and through the exhausting opening (a). In addition, an exhausting gap (b) with a preset size is formed between the lower end of the base plate <b>41</b> of the guide shade <b>40</b> facing the connecting opening <b>31</b>, and the corresponding inner wall of the machine base <b>30</b> so that the wood waste dropping in the upper guide groove <b>43</b> can move into the lower main guide groove <b>33</b> along the slanting base surface and through the exhausting gap (b) to be gathered therein and then sucked to the dust-collecting unit <b>60</b> through the connecting opening <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The work faceplate <b>50</b> is fixedly combined with the combining edge <b>35</b> of the machine base <b>30</b> and covered on the topside of the machine base <b>30</b> to form a wind-sucking space between them. The topside of the work faceplate <b>50</b> for placing work piece thereon is bored with numerous wind-sucking vents <b>51</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The dust-collecting unit <b>60</b> consists of a blower <b>61</b> having a wind-sucking pipe <b>62</b> connected with the pipe adapter <b>32</b> of the machine base <b>30</b> and a wind-exhausting pipe <b>63</b> connected with a wind-exhausting box <b>64</b>, which has its upper and lower side respectively fitted with a dust-collected bag <b>65</b>. Thus, when the blower <b>61</b> is started to operate, a vacuum suction force will be produced at the location of the connecting opening <b>31</b> of the machine base <b>30</b> through the wind-sucking pipe <b>62</b>, and the wind-sucking space between the machine base <b>30</b> and the work faceplate <b>50</b> will receive a comparatively balanced suction force that is able to completely suck wood waste on the work faceplate <b>50</b> and in the wind-sucking space into the dust-collecting bag <b>65</b>, in which wood waste stays.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Specifically, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b> and <b>5</b>, when the dust-collecting unit <b>60</b> is started to operate, a balanced suction force will be produced at the location of every wind-sucking vent <b>51</b> of the work faceplate <b>50</b>. Thus, wood waste produced on any part of the work faceplate <b>50</b> during wood processing can be completely sucked into both the upper guide groove <b>43</b> of the guide shade <b>40</b> and the assistant guide grooves <b>34</b> of the machine base <b>30</b> through the wind-sucking vents <b>51</b> of the work faceplate <b>50</b>. Simultaneously, the wood waste dropping in the upper guide groove <b>43</b> is actuated by the suction force and by its own gravity to drop in the lower main guide groove <b>33</b> of the machine base <b>30</b> along the slanting base surface of the upper guide groove <b>43</b> and through the exhausting gap (b) and instantly sucked to and collected to the dust-collecting unit <b>60</b> through the connecting opening <b>31</b>. On the other hand, the wood waste dropping in the assistant guide grooves <b>34</b> is actuated by the suction force and by its own gravity to drop in the lower main guide groove <b>33</b> along the slanting base surfaces of the assistant guide grooves <b>34</b> and through the exhausting opening (a) and instantly sucked to the dust-collecting unit <b>60</b> along the slanting base surface of the lower main guide groove <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">To sum up, the table-top wood-waste-collecting machine in the present invention has the machine base <b>30</b> bored with a plurality of transverse assistant guide grooves <b>34</b> in the left and the right topside and a longitudinal lower main guide groove <b>33</b> in the central portion and also has the guide shade <b>40</b> formed with an upper guide groove <b>43</b>, and the base surfaces of the guide grooves <b>34</b>, <b>33</b> and <b>43</b> are respectively slope-shaped. By so designing, every wind-sucking vent <b>51</b> of the work faceplate <b>50</b> can receive a balanced suction force, and the wood waste dropping in the wind-sucking space under the work faceplate <b>50</b> can be completely guided and moved to the connecting opening <b>31</b> in the front center of the machine base <b>30</b> and then sucked to and collected by the dust-collecting unit <b>60</b>. Thus the machine in the invention is able to produce a balanced suction force for completely sucking out wood waste, having an excellent effect of dust exhausting and lowering the cost for maintenance and repair of the dust-collecting machine.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">While the preferred embodiment of the invention has been described above, it will be recognized and understood that various modifications may be made therein and the appended claims are intended to cover all such modifications that may fall within the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A tabletop wood-waste-collecting machine comprising:
<claim-text>a support frame collapsible and able to stand on the ground;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a machine base fixed on said support frame, said machine base bored with a longitudinal connecting opening, said machine base bored with a longitudinal lower main guide groove, said lower main guide groove communicating with said connecting opening, said lower main guide groove slanting downward to said connecting opening, said machine base having its left and right upper side respectively bored with a plurality of transverse assistant guide grooves spaced apart, said transverse assistant guide grooves being located to be substantially transverse to the lower main guide groove, said transverse assistant guide grooves being respectively connected with the opposite edges of said lower main guide groove, each said assistant guide groove formed with a slope-shaped base surface slanting downward to the central portion of said machine base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a guide shade formed with a base plate and two side plates, an upper guide groove defined by said base plate and said two side plates, said upper guide groove having its base surface slanting downward towards the connecting opening of said machine base, said guide shade lengthwise covered on a preset portion of said lower main guide groove of said machine base, a plurality of exhausting opening with a preset size respectively formed between said two side plates of said guide shade and the connecting place of each said assistant guide groove and said lower main guide groove, wood waste dropping in each said assistant guide groove able to be sucked to said lower main guide groove along the slanting base surface of said assistant guide groove and through said exhausting opening, an exhausting gap with a preset size formed between the lower end of said base plate of said guide shade and the corresponding inner wall of said machine base, wood waste dropping in said upper guide groove of said guide shade sucked in said lower main guide groove along the slanting base surface of said upper guide groove and through said exhausting gap, said wood waste in said lower main guide groove then sucked out through said connecting opening of said machine base;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a work faceplate fixed on the topside of said machine base, a wind-sucking space formed between said topside of said machine base and said work faceplate, the topside of said work faceplate able to be used for placing work piece thereon, said topside of said work faceplate bored with numerous wind-sucking vents; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dust-collecting unit connected with said connecting opening of said machine base by a wind-sucking pipe, a vacuum suction force produced at the location of said connecting opening when said dust-collecting unit is started to operate, said wind-sucking space between said machine base and said work faceplate able to receive a balanced suction force.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The table-top wood-waste-collecting machine as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said connecting opening, said lower main guide groove and said assistant guide grooves of said machine base are formed integral.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The table-top wood-waste-collecting machine as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a pipe adapter is secured on the outer side of said connecting opening of said machine base for connecting said dust-collecting unit by said wind-sucking pipe.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The table-top wood-waste-collecting machine as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said machine base has its upper peripheral side formed with a horizontal combining edge for combining said work faceplate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The dust-top wood-waste-collecting machine as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said two side plates of said guide shade have their front and rear end respectively provided with a combining member extending outward vertically to be fastened on the inner wall of said machine base.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
